<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="halaven" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6    ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=25%) were neutropenia, anemia, asthenia/fatigue, alopecia, peripheral neuropathy, nausea, and constipation (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eisai Inc. at (1-877-873-4724) or contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

    6.1    Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The following adverse reactions are discussed in detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Neutropenia [ see Warnings and Precautions (    5.1    ) ]. 
 *  Peripheral neuropathy [ see Warnings and Precautions (    5.2    ) ]. 
 *  QT interval prolongation [ see Warnings and Precautions (    5.4    ) ]. 
    The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=25%) reported in patients receiving HALAVEN were neutropenia, anemia, asthenia/fatigue, alopecia, peripheral neuropathy, nausea, and constipation. The most common serious adverse reactions reported in patients receiving HALAVEN were febrile neutropenia (4%) and neutropenia (2%). The most common adverse reaction resulting in discontinuation of HALAVEN was peripheral neuropathy (5%).
 

 In clinical trials, HALAVEN has been administered to 1,222 patients with multiple tumor types, including 240 patients exposed to HALAVEN for 6 months or longer. The majority of the 1,222 patients were women (82%) with a median age of 58 years (range: 26 to 91 years). The racial and ethnic distribution was Caucasian (83%), Black (5%), Asian (2%), and other (5%).



 The adverse reactions described in Table 2 were identified in 750 patients treated in Study 1 [  see Clinical Studies (      14      )  ]. In Study 1, patients were randomized (2:1) to receive either HALAVEN (1.4 mg/m  2  on Days 1 and 8 of a 21-day cycle) or single agent treatment chosen by their physician (control group). A total of 503 patients received HALAVEN, and 247 patients in the control group received therapy consisting of chemotherapy [total 97% (anthracyclines 10%, capecitabine 18%, gemcitabine 19%, taxanes 15%, vinorelbine 25%, other chemotherapies 10%)] or hormonal therapy (3%). The median duration of exposure was 118 days for patients receiving HALAVEN and 63 days for patients receiving control therapy. Table 2 reports the most common adverse reactions occurring in at least 10% of patients in either group.



 Table 2       Adverse Reactions with a Per-Patient Incidence of at Least 10% in Study 1 
   MedDRA ver 10.0      HALAVEN    n=503      Control Group    n=247     
                    All Grades       &gt;= Grade 3       All Grades       &gt;= Grade 3      
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    a                                                                         
    Neutropenia   82%              57%              53%              23%               
    Anemia        58%              2%               55%              4%                
   Nervous system disorders                                                                         
    Peripheral neuropathy  b    35%              8%               16%              2%                
    Headache      19%              &lt;1%              12%              &lt;1%               
   General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                                         
    Asthenia/Fatigue  54%              10%              40%              11%               
    Mucosal inflammation  9%               1%               10%              2%                
    Pyrexia       21%              &lt;1%              13%              &lt;1%               
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                         
    Constipation  25%              1%               21%              1%                
    Diarrhea      18%              0                18%              0                 
    Nausea        35%              1%               28%              3%                
    Vomiting      18%              1%               18%              1%                
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                         
    Arthralgia/Myalgia  22%              &lt;1%              12%              1%                
    Back pain     16%              1%               7%               2%                
    Bone pain     12%              2%               9%               2%                
    Pain in extremity  11%              1%               10%              1%                
   Investigations                                                                         
    Weight decreased  21%              1%               14%              &lt;1%               
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                         
    Anorexia      20%              1%               13%              1%                
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                                         
    Cough         14%              0                9%               0                 
    Dyspnea       16%              4%               13%              4%                
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                         
    Alopecia      45%              NA  c            10%              NA  c             
   Infections and Infestations                                                                         
    Urinary Tract Infection  10%              1%               5%               0                 
   a.  based upon laboratory data.  b  includes neuropathy peripheral, neuropathy, peripheral motor neuropathy, polyneuropathy, peripheral sensoryneuropathy, and paraesthesia.  c        not applicable; (grading system does not specify &gt; Grade 2 for alopecia).   
             Cytopenias:  Grade 3 neutropenia occurred in 28% (143/503) of patients who received HALAVEN in Study 1, and 29% (144/503) of patients experienced Grade 4 neutropenia. Febrile neutropenia occurred in 5% (23/503) of patients; two patients (0.4%) died from complications of febrile neutropenia. Dose reduction due to neutropenia was required in 12% (62/503) of patients and discontinuation was required in &lt;1% of patients. The mean time to nadir was 13 days and the mean time to recovery from severe neutropenia (&lt;500/mm  3  ) was 8 days. Grade 3 or greater thrombocytopenia occurred in 1% (7/503) of patients. G-CSF (granulocyte colony-stimulating factor) or GM-CSF (granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor) was used in 19% of patients who received HALAVEN.  
 

   Peripheral Neuropathy:  In Study 1, 17 % of enrolled patients had Grade 1 peripheral neuropathy and 3% of patients had Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy at baseline. Dose reduction due to peripheral neuropathy was required by 3% (14/503) of patients who received HALAVEN. Four percent (20/503) of patients experienced peripheral motor neuropathy of any grade and 2% (8/503) of patients developed Grade 3 peripheral motor neuropathy.



   Liver Function Test Abnormalities:  Among patients with Grade 0 or 1 ALT levels at baseline, 18% of HALAVEN-treated patients experienced Grade 2 or greater ALT elevation. One HALAVEN-treated patient without documented liver metastases had concomitant Grade 2 elevations in bilirubin and ALT; these abnormalities resolved and did not recur with re-exposure to HALAVEN.



   Less Common Adverse Reactions  :     The following additional adverse reactions were reported in &gt;=5% to &lt;10% of the HALAVEN-treated group:



 *   Eye Disorders: increased lacrimation 
 *   Gastrointestinal Disorders: dyspepsia, abdominal pain, stomatitis, dry mouth 
 *   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions: peripheral edema 
 *   Infections and Infestations: upper respiratory tract infection 
 *   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders: hypokalemia 
 *   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:    muscle spasms, muscular weakness 
 *   Nervous System Disorders: dysgeusia, dizziness 
 *   Psychiatric Disorders: insomnia, depression 
 *   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders: rash 
        6. 2         Postmarketing Experience  
   The following adverse drug reactions have been identified during post-approval of HALAVEN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders: lymphopenia 
 *   Gastrointestinal Disorders: pancreatitis 
 *   Hepatobiliary Disorders: hepatotoxicity 
 *   Immune System Disorders: drug hypersensitivity 
 *   Infections and Infestations: pneumonia, sepsis/neutropenic sepsis 
 *   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders: hypomagnesemia, dehydration 
 *   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders: interstitial lung disease 
 *   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders: pruritus 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *   Neutropenia : Monitor peripheral blood cell counts and adjust dose as appropriate (  2.2  ,  5.1  ,  6  ) 
 *   Peripheral Neuropathy : Monitor for signs of neuropathy. Manage with dose delay and adjustment (  2.2  ,  5.2  ,  6  ) 
 *   Embryo-Fetal Toxicity : Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman (  5.3  ) (  8.1  ) 
 *   QT Prolongation : Monitor for prolonged QT intervals in patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, drugs known to prolong the QT interval, and electrolyte abnormalities. Avoid in patients with congenital long QT syndrome (  5.4  ) 
    
 

    5.1   Neutropenia  



  Severe neutropenia (ANC &lt; 500/mm  3  ) lasting more than one week occurred in 12% (62/503) of patients in Study 1, leading to discontinuation in &lt;1% of patients [ see Adverse Reactions (     6     )  ]. Patients with alanine aminotransferase or aspartate aminotransferase &gt; 3 * ULN (upper limit of normal) experienced a higher incidence of Grade 4 neutropenia and febrile neutropenia than patients with normal aminotransferase levels. Patients with bilirubin &gt; 1.5 * ULN also had a higher incidence of Grade 4 neutropenia and febrile neutropenia.



 Monitor complete blood counts prior to each dose; increase the frequency of monitoring in patients who develop Grade 3 or 4 cytopenias. Delay administration of HALAVEN and reduce subsequent doses in patients who experience febrile neutropenia or Grade 4 neutropenia lasting longer than 7 days [ see Dosage and Administration (     2.2     )  ]. Clinical studies of HALAVEN did not include patients with baseline neutrophil counts below 1,500/mm  3  .



     5.2   Peripheral Neuropathy  



  Grade 3 peripheral neuropathy occurred in 8% (40/503) of patients, and Grade 4 in 0.4% (2/503) of patients in Study 1. Peripheral neuropathy was the most common toxicity leading to discontinuation of HALAVEN (5% of patients; 24/503). Neuropathy lasting more than one year occurred in 5% (26/503) of patients. Twenty-two percent (109/503) of patients developed a new or worsening neuropathy that had not recovered within a median follow-up duration of 269 days (range 25-662 days). Monitor patients closely for signs of peripheral motor and sensory neuropathy. Withhold HALAVEN in patients who experience Grade 3 or 4 peripheral neuropathy until resolution to Grade 2 or less [ see    Dosage and Administration (     2.2     )  ].



     5.3   Embryo-Fetal Toxicity  



  There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of HALAVEN in pregnant women. HALAVEN is a microtubule inhibitor; therefore, it is expected to cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Embryo-fetal toxicity and teratogenicity occurred in rats that received eribulin mesylate at approximately half of the recommended human dose based on body surface area. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if a patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, she should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (     8.1     )]  .



     5.4   QT Prolongation  



  In an uncontrolled open-label ECG study in 26 patients, QT prolongation was observed on Day 8, independent of eribulin concentration, with no QT prolongation observed on Day 1. ECG monitoring is recommended if therapy is initiated in patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, drugs known to prolong the QT interval, including Class Ia and III antiarrhythmics, and electrolyte abnormalities. Correct hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia prior to initiating HALAVEN and monitor these electrolytes periodically during therapy. Avoid HALAVEN in patients with congenital long QT syndrome.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions>
    <Mention id="M1" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="102" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M2" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="115" len="6" str="anemia" />
    <Mention id="M3" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="123" len="8" str="asthenia" />
    <Mention id="M4" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="132" len="7" str="fatigue" />
    <Mention id="M5" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="141" len="8" str="alopecia" />
    <Mention id="M6" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="151" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M7" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="174" len="6" str="nausea" />
    <Mention id="M8" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="186" len="12" str="constipation" />
    <Mention id="M9" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="764" len="11" str="Neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M10" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="829" len="21" str="Peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M11" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="904" len="24" str="QT interval prolongation" />
    <Mention id="M12" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1068" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M13" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1081" len="6" str="anemia" />
    <Mention id="M14" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1089" len="8" str="asthenia" />
    <Mention id="M15" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1098" len="7" str="fatigue" />
    <Mention id="M16" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1107" len="8" str="alopecia" />
    <Mention id="M17" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1117" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M18" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1140" len="6" str="nausea" />
    <Mention id="M19" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1152" len="12" str="constipation" />
    <Mention id="M20" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1252" len="19" str="febrile neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M21" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1281" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M22" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="1376" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M23" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="2986" len="11" str="Neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M24" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3074" len="6" str="Anemia" />
    <Mention id="M25" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3263" len="21" str="Peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M26" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3365" len="8" str="Headache" />
    <Mention id="M27" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3582" len="8" str="Asthenia" />
    <Mention id="M28" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3591" len="7" str="Fatigue" />
    <Mention id="M29" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3674" len="20" str="Mucosal inflammation" />
    <Mention id="M30" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3770" len="7" str="Pyrexia" />
    <Mention id="M31" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3961" len="12" str="Constipation" />
    <Mention id="M32" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4049" len="8" str="Diarrhea" />
    <Mention id="M33" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4137" len="6" str="Nausea" />
    <Mention id="M34" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4225" len="8" str="Vomiting" />
    <Mention id="M35" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4437" len="10" str="Arthralgia" />
    <Mention id="M36" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4448" len="7" str="Myalgia" />
    <Mention id="M37" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4531" len="9" str="Back pain" />
    <Mention id="M38" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4619" len="9" str="Bone pain" />
    <Mention id="M39" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4707" len="17" str="Pain in extremity" />
    <Mention id="M40" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4891" len="16" str="Weight decreased" />
    <Mention id="M41" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5094" len="8" str="Anorexia" />
    <Mention id="M42" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5307" len="5" str="Cough" />
    <Mention id="M43" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5395" len="7" str="Dyspnea" />
    <Mention id="M44" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5598" len="8" str="Alopecia" />
    <Mention id="M45" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5790" len="23" str="Urinary Tract Infection" />
    <Mention id="M46" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5933" len="21" str="neuropathy peripheral" />
    <Mention id="M47" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5956" len="10" str="neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M48" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5968" len="27" str="peripheral motor neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M49" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5997" len="14" str="polyneuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M50" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6013" len="28" str="peripheral sensoryneuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M51" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6047" len="12" str="paraesthesia" />
    <Mention id="M52" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6134" len="8" str="alopecia" />
    <Mention id="M53" section="S1" type="Severity" start="6174" len="7" str="Grade 3" />
    <Mention id="M54" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6182" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M55" section="S1" type="Severity" start="6307" len="7" str="Grade 4" />
    <Mention id="M56" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6315" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M57" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6328" len="19" str="Febrile neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M58" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6405" len="4" str="died" />
    <Mention id="M59" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6432" len="19" str="febrile neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M60" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6475" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M61" section="S1" type="Severity" start="6651" len="6" str="severe" />
    <Mention id="M62" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6658" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M63" section="S1" type="Severity" start="6697" len="7" str="Grade 3" />
    <Mention id="M64" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="6716" len="16" str="thrombocytopenia" />
    <Mention id="M65" section="S1" type="Severity" start="7000" len="7" str="Grade 1" />
    <Mention id="M66" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7008" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M67" section="S1" type="Severity" start="7053" len="7" str="Grade 2" />
    <Mention id="M68" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7061" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M69" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7118" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M70" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7248" len="27" str="peripheral motor neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M71" section="S1" type="Severity" start="7326" len="7" str="Grade 3" />
    <Mention id="M72" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7334" len="27" str="peripheral motor neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M73" section="S1" type="Severity" start="7506" len="7" str="Grade 2" />
    <Mention id="M74" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7525" len="13" str="ALT elevation" />
    <Mention id="M75" section="S1" type="Severity" start="7620" len="7" str="Grade 2" />
    <Mention id="M76" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7628" len="23" str="elevations in bilirubin" />
    <Mention id="M77" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7628,7656" len="13,3" str="elevations in ALT" />
    <Mention id="M78" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7906" len="21" str="increased lacrimation" />
    <Mention id="M79" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7962" len="9" str="dyspepsia" />
    <Mention id="M80" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7973" len="14" str="abdominal pain" />
    <Mention id="M81" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="7989" len="10" str="stomatitis" />
    <Mention id="M82" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8001" len="9" str="dry mouth" />
    <Mention id="M83" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8071" len="16" str="peripheral edema" />
    <Mention id="M84" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8123" len="33" str="upper respiratory tract infection" />
    <Mention id="M85" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8199" len="11" str="hypokalemia" />
    <Mention id="M86" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8269" len="13" str="muscle spasms" />
    <Mention id="M87" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8284" len="17" str="muscular weakness" />
    <Mention id="M88" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8334" len="9" str="dysgeusia" />
    <Mention id="M89" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8345" len="9" str="dizziness" />
    <Mention id="M90" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8384" len="8" str="insomnia" />
    <Mention id="M91" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8394" len="10" str="depression" />
    <Mention id="M92" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8451" len="4" str="rash" />
    <Mention id="M93" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8847" len="11" str="lymphopenia" />
    <Mention id="M94" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8893" len="12" str="pancreatitis" />
    <Mention id="M95" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8937" len="14" str="hepatotoxicity" />
    <Mention id="M96" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8988" len="16" str="hypersensitivity" />
    <Mention id="M97" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9040" len="9" str="pneumonia" />
    <Mention id="M98" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9051" len="6" str="sepsis" />
    <Mention id="M99" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9058" len="18" str="neutropenic sepsis" />
    <Mention id="M100" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9119" len="14" str="hypomagnesemia" />
    <Mention id="M101" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9135" len="11" str="dehydration" />
    <Mention id="M102" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9202" len="25" str="interstitial lung disease" />
    <Mention id="M103" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9274" len="8" str="pruritus" />
    <Mention id="M104" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="58" len="11" str="Neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M105" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="170" len="21" str="Peripheral Neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M106" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="295" len="21" str="Embryo-Fetal Toxicity" />
    <Mention id="M107" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="319" len="10" str="Fetal harm" />
    <Mention id="M108" section="S2" type="Factor" start="330" len="3" str="can" />
    <Mention id="M109" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="404" len="15" str="QT Prolongation" />
    <Mention id="M110" section="S2" type="Severity" start="688" len="6" str="Severe" />
    <Mention id="M111" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="695" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M112" section="S2" type="Severity" start="1028" len="7" str="Grade 4" />
    <Mention id="M113" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1036" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M114" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1052" len="19" str="febrile neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M115" section="S2" type="Severity" start="1190" len="7" str="Grade 4" />
    <Mention id="M116" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1198" len="11" str="neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M117" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1214" len="19" str="febrile neutropenia" />
    <Mention id="M118" section="S2" type="Severity" start="1733" len="7" str="Grade 3" />
    <Mention id="M119" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1741" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M120" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1741" len="21" str="peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M121" section="S2" type="Severity" start="1804" len="7" str="Grade 4" />
    <Mention id="M122" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1852" len="21" str="Peripheral neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M123" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1967" len="10" str="Neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M124" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2112" len="10" str="neuropathy" />
    <Mention id="M125" section="S2" type="DrugClass" start="2599" len="21" str="microtubule inhibitor" />
    <Mention id="M126" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2657" len="10" str="fetal harm" />
    <Mention id="M127" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2707" len="21" str="Embryo-fetal toxicity" />
    <Mention id="M128" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2733" len="14" str="teratogenicity" />
    <Mention id="M129" section="S2" type="Animal" start="2760" len="4" str="rats" />
    <Mention id="M130" section="S2" type="Factor" start="2877" len="2" str="If" />
    <Mention id="M131" section="S2" type="Factor" start="3027" len="5" str="fetus" />
    <Mention id="M132" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="3179" len="15" str="QT prolongation" />
    <Mention id="M133" section="S2" type="Negation" start="3262" len="2" str="no" />
    <Mention id="M134" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="3265" len="15" str="QT prolongation" />
  </Mentions>
  <Relations>
    <Relation id="RL1" type="Effect" arg1="M54" arg2="M53" />
    <Relation id="RL2" type="Effect" arg1="M56" arg2="M55" />
    <Relation id="RL3" type="Effect" arg1="M62" arg2="M61" />
    <Relation id="RL4" type="Effect" arg1="M64" arg2="M63" />
    <Relation id="RL5" type="Effect" arg1="M66" arg2="M65" />
    <Relation id="RL6" type="Effect" arg1="M68" arg2="M67" />
    <Relation id="RL7" type="Effect" arg1="M72" arg2="M71" />
    <Relation id="RL8" type="Effect" arg1="M74" arg2="M73" />
    <Relation id="RL9" type="Effect" arg1="M76" arg2="M75" />
    <Relation id="RL10" type="Effect" arg1="M77" arg2="M75" />
    <Relation id="RL11" type="Hypothetical" arg1="M107" arg2="M108" />
    <Relation id="RL12" type="Effect" arg1="M111" arg2="M110" />
    <Relation id="RL13" type="Effect" arg1="M113" arg2="M112" />
    <Relation id="RL14" type="Effect" arg1="M116" arg2="M115" />
    <Relation id="RL15" type="Effect" arg1="M119" arg2="M118" />
    <Relation id="RL16" type="Effect" arg1="M120" arg2="M121" />
    <Relation id="RL17" type="Hypothetical" arg1="M126" arg2="M125" />
    <Relation id="RL18" type="Hypothetical" arg1="M127" arg2="M129" />
    <Relation id="RL19" type="Hypothetical" arg1="M128" arg2="M129" />
    <Relation id="RL20" type="Negated" arg1="M134" arg2="M133" />
  </Relations>
  <Reactions>
    <Reaction id="AR1" str="neutropenia">
      <Normalization id="AR1.N1" meddra_pt="Neutropenia" meddra_pt_id="10029354" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR2" str="anemia">
      <Normalization id="AR2.N1" meddra_pt="Anaemia" meddra_pt_id="10002034" meddra_llt="Anemia" meddra_llt_id="10002272" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR3" str="asthenia">
      <Normalization id="AR3.N1" meddra_pt="Asthenia" meddra_pt_id="10003549" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR4" str="fatigue">
      <Normalization id="AR4.N1" meddra_pt="Fatigue" meddra_pt_id="10016256" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR5" str="alopecia">
      <Normalization id="AR5.N1" meddra_pt="Alopecia" meddra_pt_id="10001760" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR6" str="peripheral neuropathy">
      <Normalization id="AR6.N1" meddra_pt="Neuropathy peripheral" meddra_pt_id="10029331" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR7" str="nausea">
      <Normalization id="AR7.N1" meddra_pt="Nausea" meddra_pt_id="10028813" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR8" str="constipation">
      <Normalization id="AR8.N1" meddra_pt="Constipation" meddra_pt_id="10010774" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR9" str="qt interval prolongation">
      <Normalization id="AR9.N1" meddra_pt="Electrocardiogram QT prolonged" meddra_pt_id="10014387" meddra_llt="QT interval prolonged" meddra_llt_id="10037703" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR10" str="febrile neutropenia">
      <Normalization id="AR10.N1" meddra_pt="Febrile neutropenia" meddra_pt_id="10016288" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR11" str="headache">
      <Normalization id="AR11.N1" meddra_pt="Headache" meddra_pt_id="10019211" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR12" str="mucosal inflammation">
      <Normalization id="AR12.N1" meddra_pt="Mucosal inflammation" meddra_pt_id="10028116" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR13" str="pyrexia">
      <Normalization id="AR13.N1" meddra_pt="Pyrexia" meddra_pt_id="10037660" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR14" str="diarrhea">
      <Normalization id="AR14.N1" meddra_pt="Diarrhoea" meddra_pt_id="10012735" meddra_llt="Diarrhea" meddra_llt_id="10012727" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR15" str="vomiting">
      <Normalization id="AR15.N1" meddra_pt="Vomiting" meddra_pt_id="10047700" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR16" str="arthralgia">
      <Normalization id="AR16.N1" meddra_pt="Arthralgia" meddra_pt_id="10003239" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR17" str="myalgia">
      <Normalization id="AR17.N1" meddra_pt="Myalgia" meddra_pt_id="10028411" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR18" str="back pain">
      <Normalization id="AR18.N1" meddra_pt="Back pain" meddra_pt_id="10003988" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR19" str="bone pain">
      <Normalization id="AR19.N1" meddra_pt="Bone pain" meddra_pt_id="10006002" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR20" str="pain in extremity">
      <Normalization id="AR20.N1" meddra_pt="Pain in extremity" meddra_pt_id="10033425" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR21" str="weight decreased">
      <Normalization id="AR21.N1" meddra_pt="Weight decreased" meddra_pt_id="10047895" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR22" str="anorexia">
      <Normalization id="AR22.N1" meddra_pt="Decreased appetite" meddra_pt_id="10061428" meddra_llt="Anorexia" meddra_llt_id="10002646" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR23" str="cough">
      <Normalization id="AR23.N1" meddra_pt="Cough" meddra_pt_id="10011224" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR24" str="dyspnea">
      <Normalization id="AR24.N1" meddra_pt="Dyspnoea" meddra_pt_id="10013968" meddra_llt="Dyspnea" meddra_llt_id="10013963" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR25" str="urinary tract infection">
      <Normalization id="AR25.N1" meddra_pt="Urinary tract infection" meddra_pt_id="10046571" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR26" str="neuropathy peripheral">
      <Normalization id="AR26.N1" meddra_pt="Neuropathy peripheral" meddra_pt_id="10029331" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR27" str="neuropathy">
      <Normalization id="AR27.N1" meddra_pt="Neuropathy peripheral" meddra_pt_id="10029331" meddra_llt="Neuropathy" meddra_llt_id="10029328" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR28" str="peripheral motor neuropathy">
      <Normalization id="AR28.N1" meddra_pt="Peripheral motor neuropathy" meddra_pt_id="10034580" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR29" str="polyneuropathy">
      <Normalization id="AR29.N1" meddra_pt="Polyneuropathy" meddra_pt_id="10036105" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR30" str="peripheral sensoryneuropathy">
      <Normalization id="AR30.N1" meddra_pt="Peripheral sensory neuropathy" meddra_pt_id="10034620" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR31" str="paraesthesia">
      <Normalization id="AR31.N1" meddra_pt="Paraesthesia" meddra_pt_id="10033775" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR32" str="died">
      <Normalization id="AR32.N1" meddra_pt="Death" meddra_pt_id="10011906" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR33" str="thrombocytopenia">
      <Normalization id="AR33.N1" meddra_pt="Thrombocytopenia" meddra_pt_id="10043554" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR34" str="alt elevation">
      <Normalization id="AR34.N1" meddra_pt="Alanine aminotransferase increased" meddra_pt_id="10001551" meddra_llt="ALT increased" meddra_llt_id="10001845" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR35" str="elevations in bilirubin">
      <Normalization id="AR35.N1" meddra_pt="Blood bilirubin increased" meddra_pt_id="10005364" meddra_llt="Bilirubin elevated" meddra_llt_id="10004688" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR36" str="elevations in alt">
      <Normalization id="AR36.N1" meddra_pt="Alanine aminotransferase increased" meddra_pt_id="10001551" meddra_llt="ALT increased" meddra_llt_id="10001845" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR37" str="increased lacrimation">
      <Normalization id="AR37.N1" meddra_pt="Lacrimation increased" meddra_pt_id="10023644" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR38" str="dyspepsia">
      <Normalization id="AR38.N1" meddra_pt="Dyspepsia" meddra_pt_id="10013946" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR39" str="abdominal pain">
      <Normalization id="AR39.N1" meddra_pt="Abdominal pain" meddra_pt_id="10000081" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR40" str="stomatitis">
      <Normalization id="AR40.N1" meddra_pt="Stomatitis" meddra_pt_id="10042128" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR41" str="dry mouth">
      <Normalization id="AR41.N1" meddra_pt="Dry mouth" meddra_pt_id="10013781" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR42" str="peripheral edema">
      <Normalization id="AR42.N1" meddra_pt="Oedema peripheral" meddra_pt_id="10030124" meddra_llt="Peripheral edema" meddra_llt_id="10034570" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR43" str="upper respiratory tract infection">
      <Normalization id="AR43.N1" meddra_pt="Upper respiratory tract infection" meddra_pt_id="10046306" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR44" str="hypokalemia">
      <Normalization id="AR44.N1" meddra_pt="Hypokalaemia" meddra_pt_id="10021015" meddra_llt="Hypokalemia" meddra_llt_id="10021018" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR45" str="muscle spasms">
      <Normalization id="AR45.N1" meddra_pt="Muscle spasms" meddra_pt_id="10028334" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR46" str="muscular weakness">
      <Normalization id="AR46.N1" meddra_pt="Muscular weakness" meddra_pt_id="10028372" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR47" str="dysgeusia">
      <Normalization id="AR47.N1" meddra_pt="Dysgeusia" meddra_pt_id="10013911" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR48" str="dizziness">
      <Normalization id="AR48.N1" meddra_pt="Dizziness" meddra_pt_id="10013573" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR49" str="insomnia">
      <Normalization id="AR49.N1" meddra_pt="Insomnia" meddra_pt_id="10022437" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR50" str="depression">
      <Normalization id="AR50.N1" meddra_pt="Depression" meddra_pt_id="10012378" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR51" str="rash">
      <Normalization id="AR51.N1" meddra_pt="Rash" meddra_pt_id="10037844" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR52" str="lymphopenia">
      <Normalization id="AR52.N1" meddra_pt="Lymphopenia" meddra_pt_id="10025327" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR53" str="pancreatitis">
      <Normalization id="AR53.N1" meddra_pt="Pancreatitis" meddra_pt_id="10033645" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR54" str="hepatotoxicity">
      <Normalization id="AR54.N1" meddra_pt="Hepatotoxicity" meddra_pt_id="10019851" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR55" str="hypersensitivity">
      <Normalization id="AR55.N1" meddra_pt="Hypersensitivity" meddra_pt_id="10020751" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR56" str="pneumonia">
      <Normalization id="AR56.N1" meddra_pt="Pneumonia" meddra_pt_id="10035664" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR57" str="sepsis">
      <Normalization id="AR57.N1" meddra_pt="Sepsis" meddra_pt_id="10040047" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR58" str="neutropenic sepsis">
      <Normalization id="AR58.N1" meddra_pt="Neutropenic sepsis" meddra_pt_id="10049151" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR59" str="hypomagnesemia">
      <Normalization id="AR59.N1" meddra_pt="Hypomagnesaemia" meddra_pt_id="10021027" meddra_llt="Hypomagnesemia" meddra_llt_id="10021028" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR60" str="dehydration">
      <Normalization id="AR60.N1" meddra_pt="Dehydration" meddra_pt_id="10012174" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR61" str="interstitial lung disease">
      <Normalization id="AR61.N1" meddra_pt="Interstitial lung disease" meddra_pt_id="10022611" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR62" str="pruritus">
      <Normalization id="AR62.N1" meddra_pt="Pruritus" meddra_pt_id="10037087" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR63" str="embryo-fetal toxicity">
      <Normalization id="AR63.N1" meddra_pt="Maternal drugs affecting foetus" meddra_pt_id="10026923" meddra_llt="Drug toxicity NEC affecting foetus" meddra_llt_id="10013750" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR64" str="fetal harm">
      <Normalization id="AR64.N1" meddra_pt="Foetal damage" meddra_pt_id="10016852" meddra_llt="Fetal damage" meddra_llt_id="10054743" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR65" str="qt prolongation">
      <Normalization id="AR65.N1" meddra_pt="Electrocardiogram QT prolonged" meddra_pt_id="10014387" meddra_llt="QT prolonged" meddra_llt_id="10037705" />
    </Reaction>
  </Reactions>
</Label>
