<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nesina" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions (reported in &gt;=4% of patients treated with NESINA 25 mg and more frequently than in patients who received placebo) are: nasopharyngitis, headache and upper respiratory tract infection. (6.1)



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Takeda Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-TAKEDA-7 (1-877-825-3327) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



      



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Approximately 8500 patients with type 2 diabetes have been treated with NESINA in 14 randomized, double-blind, controlled clinical trials with approximately 2900 subjects randomized to placebo and approximately 2200 to an active comparator. The mean exposure to NESINA was 40 weeks with more than 2400 subjects treated for more than one year. Among these patients, 63% had a history of hypertension, 51% had a history of dyslipidemia, 25% had a history of myocardial infarction, 8% had a history of unstable angina and 7% had a history of congestive heart failure. The mean duration of diabetes was seven years, the mean body mass index (BMI) was 31 kg/m  2  (51% of patients had a BMI &gt;=30 kg/m  2  ), and the mean age was 57 years (24% of patients &gt;=65 years of age).



 Two placebo-controlled monotherapy trials of 12 and 26 weeks of duration were conducted in patients treated with NESINA 12.5 mg daily, NESINA 25 mg daily and placebo. Four placebo-controlled add-on combination therapy trials of 26 weeks duration were also conducted: with metformin, with a sulfonylurea, with a thiazolidinedione and with insulin.



 Four placebo-controlled and one active-controlled trials of 16 weeks up through two years in duration were conducted in combination with metformin, in combination with pioglitazone and with pioglitazone added to a background of metformin therapy.



 Three active-controlled trials of 52 weeks in duration were conducted in patients treated with pioglitazone and metformin, in combination with metformin and as monotherapy compared to glipizide.



 In a pooled analysis of these 14 controlled clinical trials, the overall incidence of adverse events was 66% in patients treated with NESINA 25 mg compared to 62% with placebo and 70% with active comparator. Overall discontinuation of therapy due to adverse events was 4.7% with NESINA 25 mg compared to 4.5% with placebo or 6.2% with active comparator.



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=4% of patients treated with NESINA 25 mg and more frequently than in patients who received placebo are summarized in Table 1.




  Table 1. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=4% Patients Treated with NESINA 25 mg and More Frequently Than in Patients Given Placebo in Pooled Studies    
                                              Number of Patients (%)    
                                              NESINA25 mg          Placebo              Active  Comparator    
                                              N=5902               N=2926               N=2257               
  Nasopharyngitis                             257 (4.4)            89 (3.0)             113 (5.0)            
  Headache                                    247 (4.2)            72 (2.5)             121 (5.4)            
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection           247 (4.2)            61 (2.1)             113 (5.0)            
              Pancreatitis  
 

 In the clinical trial program, pancreatitis was reported in 11 of 5902 (0.2%) patients receiving NESINA 25 mg daily compared to five of 5183 (&lt;0.1%) patients receiving all comparators.



     Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 In a pooled analysis, the overall incidence of hypersensitivity reactions was 0.6% with NESINA 25 mg compared to 0.8% with all comparators. A single event of serum sickness was reported in a patient treated with NESINA 25 mg.



     Hypoglycemia  



 Hypoglycemic events were documented based upon a blood glucose value and/or clinical signs and symptoms of hypoglycemia.



 In the monotherapy study, the incidence of hypoglycemia was 1.5% in patients treated with NESINA compared to 1.6% with placebo. The use of NESINA as add-on therapy to glyburide or insulin did not increase the incidence of hypoglycemia compared to placebo. In a monotherapy study comparing NESINA to a sulfonylurea in elderly patients, the incidence of hypoglycemia was 5.4% with NESINA compared to 26% with glipizide  (Table 2)  .




  Table 2. Incidence and Rate of HypoglycemiaAdverse reactions of hypoglycemia were based on all reports of symptomatic and asymptomatic hypoglycemia; a concurrent glucose measurement was not required; intent-to-treat population. in Placebo and Active-Controlled Studies when NESINA Was Used as Add-On Therapy to Glyburide, Insulin, Metformin, Pioglitazone or Compared to Glipizide    
  Add-On to Glyburide(26 Weeks)                NESINA 25 mg+ Glyburide    Placebo+ Glyburide               
                                               N=198                      N=99                             
    Overall (%)                                19 (9.6)                   11 (11.1)                        
    Severe (%)Severe events of hypoglycemia were defined as those events requiring medical assistance or exhibiting depressed level or loss of consciousness or seizure.    0                          1 (1)                            
  Add-On to Insulin (+/- Metformin)(26 Weeks)    NESINA 25 mg+ Insulin  (+/- Metformin)    Placebo+ Insulin  (+/- Metformin)    
                                               N=129                      N=129                            
    Overall (%)                                35 (27)                    31 (24)                          
    Severe (%)                                 1 (0.8)                    2 (1.6)                          
  Add-On to Metformin(26 Weeks)                NESINA 25 mg+ Metformin    Placebo+ Metformin               
                                               N=207                      N=104                            
    Overall (%)                                0                          3 (2.9)                          
    Severe (%)                                 0                          0                                
  Add-On to Pioglitazone(+/- Metformin or Sulfonylurea)(26 Weeks)    NESINA 25 mg+ Pioglitazone    Placebo+ Pioglitazone            
                                               N=199                      N=97                             
    Overall (%)                                14 (7.0)                   5 (5.2)                          
    Severe (%)                                 0                          1 (1)                            
  Compared to Glipizide(52 Weeks)              NESINA 25 mg               Glipizide                        
                                               N=222                      N=219                            
    Overall (%)                                12 (5.4)                   57 (26)                          
    Severe (%)                                 0                          3 (1.4)                          
  Add-On to Metformin(26 Weeks)                NESINA 25 mg               Metformin 500 mg  twice daily    
                                               N=112                      N=109                            
    Overall (%)                                2 (1.8)                    2 (1.8)                          
    Severe (%)                                 0                          0                                
  Add-On to Metformin Compared to Glipizide(52 Weeks)    NESINA 25 mg+ Metformin    Glipizide  + Metformin           
                                               N=877                      N=869                            
    Overall (%)                                12 (1.4)                   207 (23.8)                       
    Severe (%)                                 0                          4 (0.5)                          
             Vital Signs  
 

 No clinically meaningful changes in vital signs or in electrocardiograms were observed in patients treated with NESINA.



     Laboratory Tests  



 No clinically meaningful changes in hematology, serum chemistry or urinalysis were observed in patients treated with NESINA.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during the postmarketing use of NESINA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, rash, urticaria and severe cutaneous adverse reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, hepatic enzyme elevations, fulminant hepatic failure, severe and disabling arthralgia and acute pancreatitis  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1,5.2,5.3,5.5)]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    Acute pancreatitis: There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue NESINA. (5.1) 
 *    Hypersensitivity: There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with NESINA such as anaphylaxis, angioedema and severe cutaneous adverse reactions. In such cases, promptly discontinue NESINA, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes. (5.2) 
 *    Hepatic effects: Postmarketing reports of hepatic failure, sometimes fatal. Causality cannot be excluded. If liver injury is detected, promptly interrupt NESINA and assess patient for probable cause, then treat cause if possible, to resolution or stabilization. Do not restart NESINA if liver injury is confirmed and no alternative etiology can be found. (5.3) 
 *    Hypoglycemia: When an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin is used in combination with NESINA, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia. (5.4) 
 *    Arthralgia: Severe and disabling arthralgia has been reported in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate. (5.5) 
 *    Macrovascular outcomes: There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with NESINA or any other antidiabetic drug. (5.6) 
    
   5.1 Pancreatitis

  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis in patients taking NESINA. After initiation of NESINA, patients should be observed carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, NESINA should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated. It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using NESINA.



   5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions

  There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with NESINA. These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema and severe cutaneous adverse reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome. If a serious hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue NESINA, assess for other potential causes for the event and institute alternative treatment for diabetes  [seeAdverse Reactions (6.2)]  . Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema with another DPP-4 inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with NESINA.



   5.3 Hepatic Effects

  There have been postmarketing reports of fatal and nonfatal hepatic failure in patients taking NESINA, although some of the reports contain insufficient information necessary to establish the probable cause  [seeAdverse Reactions (6.2)]  . In randomized controlled studies, serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) elevations greater than three times the upper limit of normal (ULN) were observed: 1.3% in alogliptin-treated patients and 1.5% in all comparator-treated patients.



 Patients with type 2 diabetes may have fatty liver disease, which may cause liver test abnormalities, and they may also have other forms of liver disease, many of which can be treated or managed. Therefore, obtaining a liver test panel and assessing the patient before initiating NESINA therapy is recommended. In patients with abnormal liver tests, NESINA should be initiated with caution.



 Measure liver tests promptly in patients who report symptoms that may indicate liver injury, including fatigue, anorexia, right upper abdominal discomfort, dark urine or jaundice. In this clinical context, if the patient is found to have clinically significant liver enzyme elevations and if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, NESINA should be interrupted and investigation done to establish the probable cause. NESINA should not be restarted in these patients without another explanation for the liver test abnormalities.



   5.4 Use with Medications Known to Cause Hypoglycemia

  Insulin and insulin secretagogues, such as sulfonylureas, are known to cause hypoglycemia. Therefore, a lower dose of insulin or insulin secretagogue may be required to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with NESINA.



     5.5 Severe and Disabling Arthralgia  

    There have been postmarketing reports of severe and disabling arthralgia in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. The time to onset of symptoms following initiation of drug therapy varied from one day to years. Patients experienced relief of symptoms upon discontinuation of the medication. A subset of patients experienced a recurrence of symptoms when restarting the same drug or a different DPP-4 inhibitor. Consider DPP-4 inhibitors as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate.  



   5.6 Macrovascular Outcomes

  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with NESINA or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions>
    <Mention id="M1" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="183" len="15" str="nasopharyngitis" />
    <Mention id="M2" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="200" len="8" str="headache" />
    <Mention id="M3" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="213" len="33" str="upper respiratory tract infection" />
    <Mention id="M4" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3298" len="15" str="Nasopharyngitis" />
    <Mention id="M5" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3408" len="8" str="Headache" />
    <Mention id="M6" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3518" len="33" str="Upper Respiratory Tract Infection" />
    <Mention id="M7" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3690" len="12" str="pancreatitis" />
    <Mention id="M8" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="3932" len="26" str="hypersensitivity reactions" />
    <Mention id="M9" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4043" len="14" str="serum sickness" />
    <Mention id="M10" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4138" len="19" str="Hypoglycemic events" />
    <Mention id="M11" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4245" len="12" str="hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M12" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4306" len="12" str="hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M13" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4485" len="12" str="hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M14" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4615" len="12" str="hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M15" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4731" len="12" str="Hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M16" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4764" len="12" str="hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M17" section="S1" type="Severity" start="4806" len="11" str="symptomatic" />
    <Mention id="M18" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="4835" len="12" str="hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M19" section="S1" type="Severity" start="5422" len="6" str="Severe" />
    <Mention id="M20" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="5439" len="12" str="hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M21" section="S1" type="Negation" start="8320" len="2" str="No" />
    <Mention id="M22" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8345" len="22" str="changes in vital signs" />
    <Mention id="M23" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8933" len="26" str="Hypersensitivity reactions" />
    <Mention id="M24" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8970" len="11" str="anaphylaxis" />
    <Mention id="M25" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8983" len="10" str="angioedema" />
    <Mention id="M26" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="8995" len="4" str="rash" />
    <Mention id="M27" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9001" len="9" str="urticaria" />
    <Mention id="M28" section="S1" type="Severity" start="9015" len="6" str="severe" />
    <Mention id="M29" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9022" len="27" str="cutaneous adverse reactions" />
    <Mention id="M30" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9061" len="24" str="Stevens-Johnson syndrome" />
    <Mention id="M31" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9087" len="25" str="hepatic enzyme elevations" />
    <Mention id="M32" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9114" len="25" str="fulminant hepatic failure" />
    <Mention id="M33" section="S1" type="Severity" start="9141" len="6" str="severe" />
    <Mention id="M34" section="S1" type="Severity" start="9152" len="9" str="disabling" />
    <Mention id="M35" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9162" len="10" str="arthralgia" />
    <Mention id="M36" section="S1" type="AdverseReaction" start="9177" len="18" str="acute pancreatitis" />
    <Mention id="M37" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="52" len="18" str="Acute pancreatitis" />
    <Mention id="M38" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="113" len="18" str="acute pancreatitis" />
    <Mention id="M39" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="205" len="16" str="Hypersensitivity" />
    <Mention id="M40" section="S2" type="Severity" start="264" len="7" str="serious" />
    <Mention id="M41" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="272" len="26" str="hypersensitivity reactions" />
    <Mention id="M42" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="339" len="11" str="anaphylaxis" />
    <Mention id="M43" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="352" len="10" str="angioedema" />
    <Mention id="M44" section="S2" type="Severity" start="367" len="6" str="severe" />
    <Mention id="M45" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="374" len="27" str="cutaneous adverse reactions" />
    <Mention id="M46" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="591" len="15" str="Hepatic effects" />
    <Mention id="M47" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="633" len="15" str="hepatic failure" />
    <Mention id="M48" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="660" len="5" str="fatal" />
    <Mention id="M49" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="959" len="12" str="Hypoglycemia" />
    <Mention id="M50" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1189" len="10" str="Arthralgia" />
    <Mention id="M51" section="S2" type="Severity" start="1201" len="6" str="Severe" />
    <Mention id="M52" section="S2" type="Severity" start="1212" len="9" str="disabling" />
    <Mention id="M53" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1222" len="10" str="arthralgia" />
    <Mention id="M54" section="S2" type="DrugClass" start="1270" len="16" str="DPP-4 inhibitors" />
    <Mention id="M55" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="1634" len="18" str="acute pancreatitis" />
    <Mention id="M56" section="S2" type="Severity" start="2124" len="7" str="serious" />
    <Mention id="M57" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2132" len="26" str="hypersensitivity reactions" />
    <Mention id="M58" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2216" len="11" str="anaphylaxis" />
    <Mention id="M59" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2229" len="10" str="angioedema" />
    <Mention id="M60" section="S2" type="Severity" start="2244" len="6" str="severe" />
    <Mention id="M61" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2251" len="27" str="cutaneous adverse reactions" />
    <Mention id="M62" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2290" len="24" str="Stevens-Johnson syndrome" />
    <Mention id="M63" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2763" len="5" str="fatal" />
    <Mention id="M64" section="S2" type="Severity" start="2773" len="8" str="nonfatal" />
    <Mention id="M65" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2782" len="15" str="hepatic failure" />
    <Mention id="M66" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2782" len="15" str="hepatic failure" />
    <Mention id="M67" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="2996,3033" len="30,10" str="serum alanine aminotransferase elevations" />
    <Mention id="M68" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="3028,3033" len="3,10" str="ALT elevations" />
    <Mention id="M69" section="S2" type="Severity" start="3057" len="43" str="three times the upper limit of normal (ULN)" />
    <Mention id="M70" section="S2" type="Severity" start="4519" len="6" str="severe" />
    <Mention id="M71" section="S2" type="Severity" start="4530" len="9" str="disabling" />
    <Mention id="M72" section="S2" type="AdverseReaction" start="4540" len="10" str="arthralgia" />
    <Mention id="M73" section="S2" type="DrugClass" start="4570" len="16" str="DPP-4 inhibitors" />
  </Mentions>
  <Relations>
    <Relation id="RL1" type="Effect" arg1="M18" arg2="M17" />
    <Relation id="RL2" type="Effect" arg1="M20" arg2="M19" />
    <Relation id="RL3" type="Negated" arg1="M22" arg2="M21" />
    <Relation id="RL4" type="Effect" arg1="M29" arg2="M28" />
    <Relation id="RL5" type="Effect" arg1="M35" arg2="M33" />
    <Relation id="RL6" type="Effect" arg1="M35" arg2="M34" />
    <Relation id="RL7" type="Effect" arg1="M41" arg2="M40" />
    <Relation id="RL8" type="Effect" arg1="M45" arg2="M44" />
    <Relation id="RL9" type="Effect" arg1="M53" arg2="M51" />
    <Relation id="RL10" type="Effect" arg1="M53" arg2="M52" />
    <Relation id="RL11" type="Hypothetical" arg1="M53" arg2="M54" />
    <Relation id="RL12" type="Effect" arg1="M57" arg2="M56" />
    <Relation id="RL13" type="Effect" arg1="M61" arg2="M60" />
    <Relation id="RL14" type="Effect" arg1="M66" arg2="M64" />
    <Relation id="RL15" type="Effect" arg1="M67" arg2="M69" />
    <Relation id="RL16" type="Effect" arg1="M68" arg2="M69" />
    <Relation id="RL17" type="Effect" arg1="M72" arg2="M70" />
    <Relation id="RL18" type="Hypothetical" arg1="M72" arg2="M73" />
    <Relation id="RL19" type="Effect" arg1="M72" arg2="M71" />
  </Relations>
  <Reactions>
    <Reaction id="AR1" str="nasopharyngitis">
      <Normalization id="AR1.N1" meddra_pt="Nasopharyngitis" meddra_pt_id="10028810" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR2" str="headache">
      <Normalization id="AR2.N1" meddra_pt="Headache" meddra_pt_id="10019211" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR3" str="upper respiratory tract infection">
      <Normalization id="AR3.N1" meddra_pt="Upper respiratory tract infection" meddra_pt_id="10046306" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR4" str="pancreatitis">
      <Normalization id="AR4.N1" meddra_pt="Pancreatitis" meddra_pt_id="10033645" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR5" str="hypersensitivity reactions">
      <Normalization id="AR5.N1" meddra_pt="Hypersensitivity" meddra_pt_id="10020751" meddra_llt="Hypersensitivity reaction" meddra_llt_id="10020756" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR6" str="serum sickness">
      <Normalization id="AR6.N1" meddra_pt="Serum sickness" meddra_pt_id="10040400" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR7" str="hypoglycemic events">
      <Normalization id="AR7.N1" meddra_pt="Hypoglycaemia" meddra_pt_id="10020993" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR8" str="hypoglycemia">
      <Normalization id="AR8.N1" meddra_pt="Hypoglycaemia" meddra_pt_id="10020993" meddra_llt="Hypoglycemia" meddra_llt_id="10021005" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR9" str="anaphylaxis">
      <Normalization id="AR9.N1" meddra_pt="Anaphylactic reaction" meddra_pt_id="10002198" meddra_llt="Anaphylaxis" meddra_llt_id="10002218" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR10" str="angioedema">
      <Normalization id="AR10.N1" meddra_pt="Angioedema" meddra_pt_id="10002424" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR11" str="rash">
      <Normalization id="AR11.N1" meddra_pt="Rash" meddra_pt_id="10037844" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR12" str="urticaria">
      <Normalization id="AR12.N1" meddra_pt="Urticaria" meddra_pt_id="10046735" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR13" str="cutaneous adverse reactions">
      <Normalization id="AR13.N1" meddra_pt="Skin reaction" meddra_pt_id="10040914" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR14" str="stevens-johnson syndrome">
      <Normalization id="AR14.N1" meddra_pt="Stevens-Johnson syndrome" meddra_pt_id="10042033" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR15" str="hepatic enzyme elevations">
      <Normalization id="AR15.N1" meddra_pt="Hepatic enzyme increased" meddra_pt_id="10060795" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR16" str="fulminant hepatic failure">
      <Normalization id="AR16.N1" meddra_pt="Acute hepatic failure" meddra_pt_id="10000804" meddra_llt="Fulminant hepatic failure" meddra_llt_id="10017469" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR17" str="arthralgia">
      <Normalization id="AR17.N1" meddra_pt="Arthralgia" meddra_pt_id="10003239" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR18" str="acute pancreatitis">
      <Normalization id="AR18.N1" meddra_pt="Pancreatitis acute" meddra_pt_id="10033647" meddra_llt="Acute pancreatitis" meddra_llt_id="10000971" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR19" str="hypersensitivity">
      <Normalization id="AR19.N1" meddra_pt="Hypersensitivity" meddra_pt_id="10020751" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR20" str="hepatic effects">
      <Normalization id="AR20.N1" meddra_pt="Hepatotoxicity" meddra_pt_id="10019851" meddra_llt="Hepatotoxic effect" meddra_llt_id="10019850" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR21" str="hepatic failure">
      <Normalization id="AR21.N1" meddra_pt="Hepatic failure" meddra_pt_id="10019663" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR22" str="fatal">
      <Normalization id="AR22.N1" meddra_pt="Death" meddra_pt_id="10011906" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR23" str="serum alanine aminotransferase elevations">
      <Normalization id="AR23.N1" meddra_pt="Alanine aminotransferase increased" meddra_pt_id="10001551" />
    </Reaction>
    <Reaction id="AR24" str="alt elevations">
      <Normalization id="AR24.N1" meddra_pt="Alanine aminotransferase increased" meddra_pt_id="10001551" meddra_llt="ALT increased" meddra_llt_id="10001845" />
    </Reaction>
  </Reactions>
</Label>
