<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="abelcet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The total safety data base is composed of 921 patients treated with ABELCET  (r)  (5 patients were enrolled twice and counted as separate patients), of whom 775 were treated with 5 mg/kg/day. Of these 775 patients, 194 patients were treated in four comparative studies; 25 were treated in open-label, non-comparative studies; and 556 patients were treated in an open-label, emergency-use program. Most had underlying hematologic neoplasms, and many were receiving multiple concomitant medications. Of the 556 patients treated with ABELCET  (r)  , 9% discontinued treatment due to adverse events regardless of presumed relationship to study drug.



 In general, the adverse events most commonly reported with ABELCET  (r)  were transient chills and/or fever during infusion of the drug.




  Adverse Eventsa with an Incidence of &gt;=3% (N=556)    
  Adverse Event                               Percentage (%) of Patients                                  
  Chills                                      18                                                          
  Fever                                       14                                                          
  Increased Serum Creatinine                  11                                                          
  Multiple Organ Failure                      11                                                          
  Nausea                                      9                                                           
  Hypotension                                 8                                                           
  Respiratory Failure                         8                                                           
  Vomiting                                    8                                                           
  Dyspnea                                     7                                                           
  Sepsis                                      7                                                           
  Diarrhea                                    6                                                           
  Headache                                    6                                                           
  Cardiac Arrest                              6                                                           
  Hypertension                                5                                                           
  Hypokalemia                                 5                                                           
  Infection                                   5                                                           
  Kidney Failure                              5                                                           
  Pain                                        5                                                           
  Thrombocytopenia                            5                                                           
  Anemia                                      4                                                           
  Hyperbilirubinemia                          4                                                           
  Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage                 4                                                           
  Leukopenia                                  4                                                           
  Rash                                        4                                                           
  Respiratory Disorder                        4                                                           
  Chest Pain                                  3                                                           
  Nausea and Vomiting                         3                                                           
           a  The causal association between these adverse events and ABELCET  (r)  is uncertain.
 

 The following adverse events have also been reported in patients using ABELCET  (r)  in open-label, uncontrolled clinical studies. The causal association between these adverse events and ABELCET  (r)  is uncertain.



   Body as a whole:  malaise, weight loss, deafness, injection site reaction including inflammation



   Allergic:  bronchospasm, wheezing, asthma, anaphylactoid and other allergic reactions



   Cardiopulmonary:  cardiac failure, pulmonary edema, shock, myocardial infarction, hemoptysis, tachypnea, thrombophlebitis, pulmonary embolus, cardiomyopathy, pleural effusion, arrhythmias including ventricular fibrillation.



   Dermatological:  maculopapular rash, pruritus, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme



   Gastrointestinal:  acute liver failure, hepatitis, jaundice, melena, anorexia, dyspepsia, cramping, epigastric pain, veno-occlusive liver disease, diarrhea, hepatomegaly, cholangitis, cholecystitis



   Hematologic:  coagulation defects, leukocytosis, blood dyscrasias including eosinophilia



   Musculoskeletal:  myasthenia, including bone, muscle, and joint pains



   Neurologic:  convulsions, tinnitus, visual impairment, hearing loss, peripheral neuropathy, transient vertigo, diplopia, encephalopathy, cerebral vascular accident, extrapyramidal syndrome and other neurologic symptoms



   Urogenital:  oliguria, decreased renal function, anuria, renal tubular acidosis, impotence, dysuria



   Serum electrolyte abnormalities:  hypomagnesemia, hyperkalemia, hypocalcemia, hypercalcemia



   Liver function test abnormalities:  increased AST, ALT, alkaline phosphatase, LDH



   Renal function test abnormalities:  increased BUN



   Other test abnormalities:  acidosis, hyperamylasemia, hypoglycemia, hyperglycemia, hyperuricemia, hypophosphatemia



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sigma-Tau Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-888-393-4584 or by email at drugsafety@sigmatau.com or contact the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/safety/medwatch.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
