<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="abilify2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia - Related Psychosis Use [see  BOXED WARNING  and    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)    ]  
 *    Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis [see  BOXED WARNING  and    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.2)    ]  
 *    Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.3)    ]  
 *    Tardive Dyskinesia [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.4)    ]  
 *    Metabolic Changes [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.5)    ]  
 *    Orthostatic Hypotension [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.6)    ]  
 *    Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.7)    ]  
 *    Seizures [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.8)    ]  
 *    Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.9)    ]  
 *    Body Temperature Regulation [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.10)    ]  
 *    Dysphagia [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.11)    ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most commonly observed adverse reactions with ABILIFY MAINTENA (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice that for placebo) were increased weight, akathisia, injection site pain, and sedation (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Otsuka America Pharmaceutical, Inc. at 1-800-438-9927 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 (  www.fda.gov/medwatch  ).  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Safety Database of ABILIFY MAINTENA and Oral Aripiprazole  



 Oral aripiprazole has been evaluated for safety in 16,114 adult patients who participated in multiple-dose, clinical trials in schizophrenia and other indications, and who had approximately 8,578 patient-years of exposure to oral aripiprazole. A total of 3,901 patients were treated with oral aripiprazole for at least 180 days, 2,259 patients were treated with oral aripiprazole for at least 360 days, and 933 patients continuing aripiprazole treatment for at least 720 days.



 ABILIFY MAINTENA has been evaluated for safety in 2,188 adult patients in clinical trials in schizophrenia, with approximately 2,646 patient-years of exposure to ABILIFY MAINTENA. A total of 1,230 patients were treated with ABILIFY MAINTENA for at least 180 days (at least 7 consecutive injections) and 935 patients treated with ABILIFY MAINTENA had at least 1 year of exposure (at least 13 consecutive injections).



 The conditions and duration of treatment with ABILIFY MAINTENA included double-blind and open-label studies. The safety data presented below are derived from the 12-week double-blind placebo-controlled study of ABILIFY MAINTENA in adult patients with schizophrenia.



     Adverse Reactions with ABILIFY MAINTENA  



     Most Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials in Schizophrenia  



 Based on the placebo-controlled trial of ABILIFY MAINTENA in schizophrenia, the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of ABILIFY MAINTENA in patients (incidence of 5% or greater and aripiprazole incidence at least twice that for placebo) were increased weight (16.8% vs 7.0%), akathisia (11.4% vs 3.5%), injection site pain (5.4% vs 0.6%) and sedation (5.4% vs 1.2%).



   Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials in Schizophrenia  



 The following findings are based on the double-blind, placebo-controlled trial that compared ABILIFY MAINTENA 400 mg or 300 mg to placebo in patients with schizophrenia. Table 7 lists the adverse reactions reported in 2% or more of ABILIFY MAINTENA-treated subjects and at a greater proportion than in the placebo group.



    
           Table 7: Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 2% of ABILIFY MAINTENA-Treated Adult Patients with Schizophrenia in a 12-Week Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial  a       
                                      Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction  a       
   System Organ Class                 ABILIFY MAINTENA           Placebo                           
   Preferred Term                     (n=167)                    (n=172)                           
  
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                       
  Constipation                       10                         7                                  
  Dry Mouth                          4                          2                                  
  Diarrhea                           3                          2                                  
  Vomiting                           3                          1                                  
  Abdominal Discomfort               2                          1                                  
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                  
  Injection Site Pain                5                          1                                  
  Infections and Infestations                                                                      
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection    4                          2                                  
  Investigations                                                                                   
  Increased Weight                   17                         7                                  
  Decreased Weight                   4                          2                                  
  Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                  
  Arthralgia                         4                          1                                  
  Back Pain                          4                          2                                  
  Myalgia                            4                          2                                  
  Musculoskeletal Pain               3                          1                                  
  Nervous System Disorders                                      
  Akathisia                          11                         4                                  
  Sedation                           5                          1                                  
  Dizziness                          4                          2                                  
  Tremor                             3                          1                                  
  Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal                                                                  
  Nasal Congestion                   2                          1                                  
  a This table does not include adverse reactions which had an incidence equal to or less than placebo.    
             Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Trial Evaluation of ABILIFY MAINTENA  
 

 The following listing does not include reactions: 1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, 2) for which a drug cause was remote, 3) which were so general as to be uninformative, 4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or 5) which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo.



 Reactions are categorized by body system according to the following definitions:  frequent  adverse reactions are those occurring in at least 1/100 patients;  infrequent  adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients;  rare  reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients:



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:    rare -  thrombocytopenia



   Cardiac Disorders:    infrequent  - tachycardia,  rare  - bradycardia, sinus tachycardia



   Endocrine Disorders:    rare -  hypoprolactinemia



   Eye Disorders:    infrequent -  vision blurred, oculogyric crisis



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:    infrequent  - abdominal pain upper, dyspepsia, nausea,  rare  -swollen tongue



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:    frequent -  fatigue, injection site reactions (including erythema, induration, pruritus, injection site reaction, swelling, rash, inflammation, hemorrhage),  infrequent -  chest discomfort, gait disturbance,  rare  -irritability, pyrexia



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:    rare  - drug induced liver injury



   Immune System Disorders:    rare  - drug hypersensitivity



   Infections and Infestations:    rare  - nasopharyngitis



   Investigations:    infrequent -  blood creatine phosphokinase increased, blood pressure decreased, hepatic enzyme increased, liver function test abnormal, electrocardiogram QT-prolonged,  rare -  blood triglycerides decreased, blood cholesterol decreased, electrocardiogram T-wave abnormal



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:    infrequent -  decreased appetite, obesity, hyperinsulinemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:    infrequent  - joint stiffness, muscle twitching,  rare -  rhabdomyolysis



   Nervous System Disorders:    infrequent  - cogwheel rigidity, extrapyramidal disorder, hypersomnia, lethargy,  rare  - bradykinesia, convulsion, dysgeusia, memory impairment, oromandibular dystonia



   Psychiatric Disorders:    frequent -  anxiety, insomnia restlessness,  infrequent  - agitation, bruxism, depression, psychotic disorder, suicidal ideation,  rare -  aggression, hypersexuality, panic attack



   Renal and Urinary Disorders  :  rare  - glycosuria, pollakiuria, urinary incontinence



   Vascular Disorders:    infrequent -  hypertension



   Demographic Differences  



 An examination of population subgroups was performed across demographic subgroup categories for adverse reactions experienced by at least 5% of ABILIFY MAINTENA subjects at least twice rate of the placebo (i.e., increased weight, akathisia, injection site pain, and sedation) in the double-blind placebo-controlled trial. This analysis did not reveal evidence of differences in safety differential adverse reaction incidence on the basis of age, gender, or race alone; however, there were few subjects &gt;= 65 years of age.



     Injection Site Reactions of ABILIFY MAINTENA  



 In the data from the short-term, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial with ABILIFY MAINTENA in patients with schizophrenia, the percent of patients reporting any injection site-related adverse reaction (all reported as injection site pain) was 5.4% for patients treated with gluteal administered ABILIFY MAINTENA and 0.6% for placebo. The mean intensity of injection pain reported by subjects using a visual analog scale (0=no pain to 100=unbearably painful) approximately one hour after injection was 7.1 (SD 14.5) for the first injection and 4.8 (SD 12.4) at the last visit in the double-blind, placebo-controlled phase.



 In an open-label study comparing bioavailability of ABILIFY MAINTENA administered in the deltoid or gluteal muscle, injection site pain was observed in both groups at approximately equal rates.



     Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS)  



 In the short-term, placebo-controlled trial of ABILIFY MAINTENA in adults with schizophrenia, the incidence of reported EPS-related events, excluding events related to akathisia, for ABILIFY MAINTENA-treated patients was 9.6% vs. 5.2% for placebo. The incidence of akathisia-related events for ABILIFY MAINTENA-treated patients was 11.5% vs. 3.5% for placebo.



     Dystonia  



 Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups. In the short-term, placebo-controlled trial of ABILIFY MAINTENA in adults with schizophrenia, the incidence of dystonia was 1.8% for ABILIFY MAINTENA vs. 0.6% for placebo.



     Neutropenia  



 In the short-term, placebo-controlled trial of ABILIFY MAINTENA in adults with schizophrenia, the incidence of neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;=1.5 thous/uL) for ABILIFY MAINTENA-treated patients was 5.7% vs. 2.1% for placebo. An absolute neutrophil count of &lt;1 thous/uL (i.e. 0.95 thous/uL) was observed in only one patient on ABILIFY MAINTENA and resolved spontaneously without any associated adverse events [see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.7)]



     Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with Oral Aripiprazole  



 The following is a list of additional adverse reactions that have been reported in clinical trials with oral aripiprazole and not reported above for ABILIFY MAINTENA:



   Cardiac Disorders:  palpitations, cardiopulmonary failure, myocardial infarction, cardio-respiratory arrest, atrioventricular block, extrasystoles, angina pectoris, myocardial ischemia, atrial flutter, supraventricular tachycardia, ventricular tachycardia



   Eye Disorders:  photophobia, diplopia, eyelid edema, photopsia



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  gastroesophageal reflux disease, swollen tongue, esophagitis, pancreatitis, stomach discomfort, toothache



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  asthenia, peripheral edema, chest pain, face edema, angioedema, hypothermia, pain



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  hepatitis, jaundice



   Immune System Disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications:  heat stroke



   Investigations:  blood prolactin increased, blood urea increased, blood creatinine increased, blood bilirubin increased, blood lactate dehydrogenase increased, glycosylated hemoglobin increased



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  anorexia, hyponatremia, hypoglycemia, polydipsia  ,  diabetic ketoacidosis



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  muscle rigidity, muscular weakness, muscle tightness, decreased mobility, rhabdomyolysis, musculoskeletal stiffness, pain in extremity, muscle spasms



   Nervous System Disorders:  coordination abnormal, speech disorder, hypokinesia, hypotonia, myoclonus, akinesia, bradykinesia, choreoathetosis



   Psychiatric Disorders:  loss of libido, suicide attempt, hostility, libido increased, anger, anorgasmia, delirium, intentional self injury, completed suicide, tic, homicidal ideation, catatonia, sleep walking



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  urinary retention, polyuria, nocturia



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  menstruation irregular, erectile dysfunction, amenorrhea, breast pain, gynecomastia, priapism



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  nasal congestion, dyspnea, pharyngolaryngeal pain, cough



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  rash (including erythematous, exfoliative, generalized, macular, maculopapular, papular rash; acneiform, allergic, contact, exfoliative, seborrheic dermatitis, neurodermatitis, and drug eruption), hyperhidrosis, pruritus, photosensitivity reaction, alopecia, urticaria



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of oral aripiprazole or ABILIFY MAINTENA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: occurrences of allergic reaction (anaphylactic reaction, angioedema, laryngospasm, pruritus/urticaria, or oropharyngeal spasm) and blood glucose fluctuation.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  

    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. ABILIFY MAINTENA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis   [see           WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)          ]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death (5.1) 
 *  ABILIFY MAINTENA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack, including fatalities) (  5.2  ) 
 *     Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring (  5.3  ) 
 *     Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue if clinically appropriate (  5.4  ) 
 *    *  -   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus: Monitor patients for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Monitor glucose regularly in patients with and at risk for diabetes (  5.5  ) 
 *  -   Dyslipidemia: Undesirable alterations have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics (  5.5  ) 
 *  -   Weight Gain: Gain in body weight has been observed; clinical monitoring of weight is recommended (  5.5  ) 
    Metabolic Changes: Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and weight gain (  5.5  ) 
 *     Orthostatic Hypotension: Use with caution in patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease (  5.6  ) 
 *     Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis: Perform complete blood counts in patients with a history of a clinically significant low white blood cell count (WBC)/absolute neutrophil count (ANC). Consider discontinuation if clinically significant decline in WBC/ANC in the absence of other causative factors (  5.7  ) 
 *     Seizures: Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold (  5.8  ) 
 *     Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment: Use caution when operating machinery (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia- Related Psychosis



  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group.



 Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. ABILIFY MAINTENA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis.



    5.2 Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  In placebo-controlled clinical studies (two flexible dose and one fixed dose study) of dementia-related psychosis, there was an increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack), including fatalities, in oral aripiprazole-treated patients (mean age: 84 years; range: 78-88 years). In the fixed-dose study, there was a statistically significant dose response relationship for cerebrovascular adverse reactions in patients treated with oral aripiprazole. ABILIFY MAINTENA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis .  



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) may occur with administration of antipsychotic drugs, including ABILIFY MAINTENA. Rare cases of NMS occurred during aripiprazole treatment in the worldwide clinical database.



 Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to exclude cases where the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: 1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; 2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and 3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for uncomplicated NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. The patient should be carefully monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4 Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses.



 There is no known treatment for established tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and, thereby, may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect of symptomatic suppression on the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, ABILIFY MAINTENA should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that 1) is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs and 2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient treated with ABILIFY MAINTENA drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with ABILIFY MAINTENA despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.5 Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that include hyperglycemia/diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, and weight gain. While all drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



     Hyperglycemia/Diabetes Mellitus    



  Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with diabetic ketoacidosis, hyperosmolar coma, or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. There have been reports of hyperglycemia in patients treated with aripiprazole [see     ADVERSE REACTIONS (6.1)     ]. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics.  



  Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes), who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the atypical antipsychotic drug.  



 In a short-term, placebo-controlled randomized trial in adults with schizophrenia, the mean change in fasting glucose was +9.8 mg/dL (N=88) in the ABILIFY MAINTENA- treated patients and +0.7 mg/dL (N=59) in the placebo-treated patients. Table 4 shows the proportion of ABILIFY MAINTENA-treated patients with normal and borderline fasting glucose at baseline and their changes in fasting glucose measurements.



   Table 4: Proportion of Patients with Potential Clinically Relevant Changes in Fasting Glucose from a 12-Week Placebo-Controlled Monotherapy Trial in Adult Patients with Schizophrenia    




                 Category Change (at least once) from Baseline        Treatment Arm                    n/N  a          %       
  
    a  N = the total number of subjects who had a measurement at baseline and at least one post-baseline result.n = the number of subjects with a potentially clinically relevant shift.     
  
  Fasting Glucose    Normal to High(&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA                 7/88         8.0      
  Placebo       0/75                                     0.0                              
  Borderline to High(&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;126 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA                         1/33                             3.0          
  Placebo       3/33                                     9.1                              
               Dyslipidemia    
 

  Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics.  



  Table 5 shows the proportion of adult patients from one short-term, placebo-controlled randomized trial in adults with schizophrenia taking ABILIFY MAINTENA, with changes in total cholesterol, fasting triglycerides, fasting LDL cholesterol and HDL cholesterol.  



   Table 5: Proportion of Patients with Potential Clinically Relevant Changes in Blood Lipid Parameters From a 12-Week Placebo-Controlled Monotherapy Trial in Adults with Schizophrenia    




                                      Treatment Arm                  n/N  a            %          
  
    a  N = the total number of subjects who had a measurement at baseline and at least one post-baseline result.n = the number of subjects with a potentially clinically relevant shift.     
  
  Total CholesterolNormal to High(&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA               3/83              3.6         
  Placebo                            2/73                           2.7               
  Borderline to High  (200~&lt;240 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA               6/27              22.2        
  Placebo                            2/19                           10.5              
  Any increase  (&gt;=40 mg/dL)         ABILIFY MAINTENA               15/122            12.3        
  Placebo                            6/110                          5.5               
  Fasting TriglyceridesNormal to High(&lt;150 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA               7/98              7.1         
  Placebo                            4/78                           5.1               
  Borderline to High  (150~&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA               3/11              27.3        
  Placebo                            4/15                           26.7              
  Any increase  ( &gt;= 50 mg/dL)       ABILIFY MAINTENA               24/122            19.7        
  Placebo                            20/110                         18.2              
  Fasting LDL CholesterolNormal to High(&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA               1/59              1.7         
  Placebo                            1/51                           2.0               
  Borderline to High  (100~&lt;160 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA               5/52              9.6         
  Placebo                            1/41                           2.4               
  Any increase  ( &gt;= 30 mg/dL)       ABILIFY MAINTENA               17/120            14.2        
  Placebo                            9/103                          8.7               
  HDL CholesterolNormal to Low(&gt;=40 mg/dL to &lt;40 mg/dL)    ABILIFY MAINTENA               14/104            13.5        
  Placebo                            11/87                          12.6              
  Any decrease  ( &gt;= 20 mg/dL)       ABILIFY MAINTENA               7/122             5.7         
  Placebo                            12/110                         10.9              
             Weight Gain  
 

 Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Clinical monitoring of weight is recommended.



  In one short-term, placebo-controlled trial with ABILIFY MAINTENA, the mean change in body weight at Week 12 was +3.5 kg (N=99) in the ABILIFY MAINTENA-treated patients and +0.8 kg (N=66) in the placebo-treated patients.  



  Table 6 shows the percentage of adult patients with weight gain &gt;=7% of body weight in a short-term, placebo-controlled trial with ABILIFY MAINTENA.  



   Table 6: Percentage of Patients From a 12-Week Placebo-Controlled Trial in Adult Patients with Schizophrenia with Weight Gain &gt;=7% of Body Weight    




                               Treatment Arm                        N  a          Patients n (%)              
  
    a  N = the total number of subjects who had a measurement at baseline and at least one post-baseline result.     
  
  Weight gain &gt;=7% of body weight    ABILIFY MAINTENA                     144           31 (21.5)                  
  Placebo                       141                                  12 (8.5)      
             5.6 Orthostatic Hypotension
 

   ABILIFY MAINTENA may cause orthostatic hypotension, perhaps due to its alpha1-adrenergic receptor antagonism. In the short-term, placebo-controlled trial in adults with schizophrenia, the adverse event of presyncope was reported in 1/167 (0.6%) of patients treated with ABILFY MAINTENA, while syncope and orthostatic hypotension were each reported in 1/172 (0.6%) of patients treated with placebo. During the stabilization phase of the randomized-withdrawal (maintenance) study, orthostasis-related adverse events were reported in 4/576 (0.7%) of patients treated with ABILIFY MAINTENA, including abnormal orthostatic blood pressure (1/576, 0.2%), postural dizziness (1/576, 0.2%), presyncope (1/576, 0.2%) and orthostatic hypotension (1/576, 0.2%).  



  In the short-term placebo-controlled trial, there were no patients in either treatment group with a significant orthostatic change in blood pressure (defined as a decrease in systolic blood pressure &gt;=20 mmHg accompanied by an increase in heart rate &gt;=25 when comparing standing to supine values). During the stabilization phase of the randomized-withdrawal (maintenance) study, the incidence of significant orthostatic change in blood pressure was 0.2% (1/575).  



    5.7 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



  In clinical trials and post-marketing experience, leukopenia and neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents, including ABILIFY MAINTENA. Agranulocytosis has also been reported [   see ADVERSE REACTIONS (6.1)    ].



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC)/absolute neutrophil count (ANC) and a history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. In patients with a history of a clinically significant low WBC /ANC or drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia, perform a complete blood count (CBC) frequently during the first few months of therapy. In such patients, consider discontinuation of ABILIFY MAINTENA at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Monitor patients with clinically significant neutropenia for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treat promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Discontinue ABILIFY MAINTENA in patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm3) and follow their WBC counts until recovery.



    5.8 Seizures



  As with other antipsychotic drugs, use ABILIFY MAINTENA cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in a population of 65 years or older.



    5.9 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  ABILIFY MAINTENA, like other antipsychotics, may impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills. Instruct patients to avoid operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that therapy with ABILIFY MAINTENA does not affect them adversely.



    5.10 Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing ABILIFY MAINTENA for patients who will be experiencing conditions which may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, (e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration).



    5.11 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use, including ABILIFY MAINTENA. ABILIFY MAINTENA and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia [see     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)     ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
