<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="accuretic" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  ACCURETIC has been evaluated for safety in 1571 patients in controlled and uncontrolled studies. Of these, 498 were given quinapril plus hydrochlorothiazide for at least 1 year, with 153 patients extending combination therapy for over 2 years. In clinical trials with ACCURETIC, no adverse experience specific to the combination has been observed. Adverse experiences that have occurred have been limited to those that have been previously reported with quinapril or hydrochlorothiazide.



 Adverse experiences were usually mild and transient, and there was no relationship between side effects and age, sex, race, or duration of therapy. Discontinuation of therapy because of adverse effects was required in 2.1% in patients in controlled studies. The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy with ACCURETIC were cough (1.0%; see    PRECAUTIONS    ) and headache (0.7%).



 Adverse experiences probably or possibly related to therapy or of unknown relationship to therapy occurring in 1% or more of the 943 patients treated with quinapril plus hydrochlorothiazide in controlled trials are shown below.




                                                     Percent of Patients in Controlled Trials   
                                                       Quinapril/HCTZN = 943         PlaceboN = 100         
  
 Headache                                                       6.7                       30.0              
 Dizziness                                                      4.8                        4.0              
 Coughing                                                       3.2                        2.0              
 Fatigue                                                        2.9                        3.0              
 Myalgia                                                        2.4                        5.0              
 Viral Infection                                                1.9                        4.0              
 Rhinitis                                                       2.0                        3.0              
 Nausea and/or Vomiting                                         1.8                        6.0              
 Abdominal Pain                                                 1.7                        4.0              
 Back Pain                                                      1.5                        2.0              
 Diarrhea                                                       1.4                        1.0              
 Upper Respiratory Infection                                    1.3                        4.0              
 Insomnia                                                       1.2                        2.0              
 Somnolence                                                     1.2                        0.0              
 Bronchitis                                                     1.2                        1.0              
 Dyspepsia                                                      1.2                        2.0              
 Asthenia                                                       1.1                        1.0              
 Pharyngitis                                                    1.1                        2.0              
 Vasodilatation                                                 1.0                        1.0              
 Vertigo                                                        1.0                        2.0              
 Chest Pain                                                     1.0                        2.0              
         Clinical adverse experiences probably, possibly, or definitely related or of uncertain relationship to therapy occurring in &gt;=0.5% to &lt;1.0% (except as noted) of the patients treated with quinapril/HCTZ in controlled and uncontrolled trials (N=1571) and less frequent, clinically significant events seen in clinical trials or postmarketing experience (the rarer events are in italics) include (listed by body system):
 


 BODY AS A WHOLE:                               Asthenia, Malaise                                         
 CARDIOVASCULAR:                                Palpitation, Tachycardia,  Heart Failure, Hyperkalemia, Myocardial Infarction, Cerebrovascular Accident, Hypertensive Crisis, Angina Pectoris, Orthostatic Hypotension, Cardiac Rhythm Disturbance     
 GASTROINTESTINAL:                              Mouth or Throat Dry,  Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage, Pancreatitis, Abnormal Liver Function Tests     
 NERVOUS/PSYCHIATRIC:                           Nervousness, Vertigo,  Paresthesia                        
 RESPIRATORY:                                   Sinusitis, Dyspnea                                        
 INTEGUMENTARY:                                 Pruritus, Sweating Increased,  Erythema Multiforme, Exfoliative Dermatitis, Photosensitivity Reaction, Alopecia, Pemphigus     
 UROGENITAL SYSTEM:                               Acute Renal Failure, Impotence                          
 OTHER:                                           Agranulocytosis, Thrombocytopenia, Arthralgia           
 Angioedema:                                    Angioedema has been reported in 0.1% of patients receiving quinapril (0.1%) (see    WARNINGS    ).   
          Postmarketing Experience
   The following serious nonfatal adverse events, regardless of their relationship to quinapril and HCTZ combination tablets, have been reported during extensive postmarketing experience:



 BODY AS A WHOLE: Shock, accidental injury, neoplasm, cellulitis, ascites, generalized edema, hernia and anaphylactoid reaction.



 CARDIOVASCULAR SYSTEM: Bradycardia, cor pulmonale, vasculitis, and deep thrombosis.



 DIGESTIVE SYSTEM: Gastrointestinal carcinoma, cholestatic jaundice, hepatitis, esophagitis, vomiting, and diarrhea.



 EYE DISORDERS: Acute myopia and acute angle closure glaucoma (see    WARNINGS    ).



 HEMIC SYSTEM: Anemia.



 METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL DISORDERS: Weight loss.



 MUSCULOSKELETAL SYSTEM: Myopathy, myositis, and arthritis.



 NERVOUS SYSTEM: Paralysis, hemiplegia, speech disorder, abnormal gait, meningism, and amnesia.



 RESPIRATORY SYSTEM: Pneumonia, asthma, respiratory infiltration, and lung disorder.



 SKIN AND APPENDAGES: Urticaria, macropapular rash, and petechiases.



 SPECIAL SENSES: Abnormal vision.



 UROGENITAL SYSTEM: Kidney function abnormal, albuminuria, pyuria, hematuria, and nephrosis.



 Quinapril monotherapy has been evaluated for safety in 4960 patients. In clinical trials adverse events which occurred with quinapril were also seen with ACCURETIC. In addition, the following were reported for quinapril at an incidence &gt;0.5%: depression, back pain, constipation, syncope, and amblyopia.



 Hydrochlorothiazide has been extensively prescribed for many years, but there has not been enough systematic collection of data to support an estimate of the frequency of the observed adverse reactions. Within organ-system groups, the reported reactions are listed here in decreasing order of severity, without regard to frequency.




 BODY AS A WHOLE:                               Weakness.                                                 
 CARDIOVASCULAR:                                Orthostatic hypotension (may be potentiated by alcohol, barbiturates, or narcotics).   
 DIGESTIVE:                                     Pancreatitis, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic), sialadenitis, vomiting, diarrhea, cramping, nausea, gastric irritation, constipation, and anorexia.   
 NEUROLOGIC:                                    Vertigo, lightheadedness, transient blurred vision, headache, paresthesia, xanthopsia, weakness, and restlessness.   
 MUSCULOSKELETAL:                               Muscle spasm.                                             
 HEMATOLOGIC:                                   Aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, and hemolytic anemia.   
 RENAL:                                         Renal failure, renal dysfunction, interstitial nephritis (see    WARNINGS    ).   
 METABOLIC:                                     Hyperglycemia, glycosuria, and hyperuricemia.             
 HYPERSENSITIVITY:                              Necrotizing angiitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, respiratory distress (including pneumonitis and pulmonary edema), purpura, urticaria, rash, and photosensitivity.   
          Clinical Laboratory Test Findings
     Serum Electrolytes

  See    PRECAUTIONS    .



   Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen

  Increases (&gt;1.25 times the upper limit of normal) in serum creatinine and blood urea nitrogen were observed in 3% and 4%, respectively, of patients treated with ACCURETIC. Most increases were minor and reversible, which can occur in patients with essential hypertension but most frequently in patients with renal artery stenosis (see    PRECAUTIONS    ).



   PBI and Tests of Parathyroid Function

  See    PRECAUTIONS    .



   Hematology

  See    WARNINGS    .



   Other (causal relationships unknown)

  Other clinically important changes in standard laboratory tests were rarely associated with ACCURETIC administration. Elevations in uric acid, glucose, magnesium, cholesterol, triglyceride, and calcium (see    PRECAUTIONS    ) have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

  WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ACCURETIC as soon as possible. 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. See Warnings: Fetal Toxicity 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
