<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="acetadote" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than 2%) are rash, urticaria/facial flushing and pruritus (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Cumberland Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-877-484-2700 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In the literature the most frequently reported adverse reactions attributed to intravenous acetylcysteine administration were rash, urticaria and pruritus. The frequency of adverse reactions has been reported to be between 0.2% and 20.8%, and they most commonly occur during the initial loading dose of acetylcysteine.



     Loading Dose/Infusion Rate Study  



 The incidence of drug-related adverse reactions occurring within the first 2 hours following acetylcysteine administration reported in a randomized study in patients with acetaminophen poisoning is presented in  Table 5  by preferred term. In this study patients were randomized to a 15-minute or a 60-minute loading dose regimen.



 Within the first 2 hours following intravenous acetylcysteine administration, 17% developed an anaphylactoid reaction (18% in the 15-minute treatment group; 14% in the 60-minute treatment group) in this randomized, open-label, multi-center clinical study conducted in Australia to compare the rates of anaphylactoid reactions between two rates of infusion for the intravenous acetylcysteine loading dose [  see Warnings (  Section 5  ) and Clinical Studies - Loading Dose/Infusion Rate Study (  Section 14  )  ].



 Table 5. Incidence of Drug-Related Adverse Reactions Occurring Within the First 2 Hours Following Study Drug Administration by Preferred Term: Loading Dose/Infusion Rate Study 
  Unkn=Unknown             
  
 Treatment Group          15-min    60-min     
 Number of Patients       n=109     n=71       
 Cardiac disorders        5 (5%)    2 (3%)     
   Severity:                Unkn      Mild      Moderate      Severe      Unkn      Mild      Moderate       Severe     
         Tachycardia NOS            4 (4%)    1 (1%)                          2 (3%)                              
 Gastrointestinal disorders  16 (15%)  7 (10%)    
   Severity:                Unkn      Mild      Moderate      Severe      Unkn      Mild      Moderate       Severe     
         Nausea           1 (1%)              6 (6%)                          1 (1%)    1 (1%)                    
         Vomiting NOS               2 (2%)    11 (10%)                        2 (3%)    4 (6%)                    
 Immune System Disorders  20 (18%)  10 (14%)   
   Severity:                Unkn      Mild      Moderate      Severe      Unkn      Mild      Moderate       Severe     
         Anaphylactoid reaction  2 (2%)    6 (6%)    11 (10%)    1 (1%)              4 (6%)    5 (7%)         1 (1%)     
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  2 (2%)    2 (3%)     
   Severity:                Unkn      Mild      Moderate      Severe      Unkn      Mild      Moderate       Severe     
         Pharyngitis                          1 (1%)                                                              
         Rhinorrhoea                1 (1%)                                                                        
         Rhonchi                                                              1 (1%)                              
         Throat tightness                                                      1 (1%)                              
 Skin &amp; subcutaneous tissue disorders  6 (6%)    5 (7%)     
   Severity:                Unkn      Mild      Moderate      Severe      Unkn      Mild      Moderate       Severe     
         Pruritus                   1 (1%)                                    2 (3%)                              
         Rash NOS                   3 (3%)    2 (2%)                          3 (4%)                              
 Vascular disorders       2 (2%)    3 (4%)     
   Severity:                Unkn      Mild      Moderate      Severe      Unkn      Mild      Moderate       Severe     
         Flushing                   1 (1%)    1 (1%)                          2 (3%)    1 (1%)                    
                   Postmarketing Safety Study  
 

 A large multi-center study was performed in Canada where data were collected from patients who were treated with intravenous acetylcysteine for acetaminophen overdose between 1980 and 2005. This study evaluated 4709 adult cases and 1905 pediatric cases. The incidence of anaphylactoid reactions in adult (overall incidence 7.9%) and pediatric (overall incidence 9.5%) patients is presented in  Tables 6  and  7  .



 Table 6. Distribution of reported reactions in adult patients receiving intravenous acetylcysteine 
                                                               Incidence (%)                             
   Reaction                                                  % of Patients (n=4709)                      
 Urticaria/Facial Flushing                                   6.1%                                        
 Pruritus                                                    4.3%                                        
 Respiratory Symptoms*                                       1.9%                                        
 Edema                                                       1.6%                                        
 Hypotension                                                 0.1%                                        
 Anaphylaxis                                                 0.1%                                        
       Table 7. Distribution of reported reactions in pediatric patients receiving intravenous acetylcysteine 
  *Respiratory symptoms are defined as presence of any of the following: cough, wheezing, stridor, shortness of breath, chest tightness, respiratory distress, or bronchospasm.    
  
                                                               Incidence (%)                             
   Reaction                                                  % of Patients (n=1905)                      
 Urticaria/Facial Flushing                                   7.6%                                        
 Pruritus                                                    4.1%                                        
 Respiratory Symptoms*                                       2.2%                                        
 Edema                                                       1.2%                                        
 Anaphylaxis                                                 0.2%                                        
 Hypotension                                                 0.1%                                        
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Monitor as acute flushing and erythema of the skin may occur; usually associated with the loading dose; often resolves spontaneously despite continued infusion (  5.1  ) 
 *  Monitor for serious anaphylactoid reactions; infusion may be interrupted until treatment of anaphylactoid symptoms has been initiated (  5.1  ) 
 *  Should be used with caution in patients with asthma, or where there is a history of bronchospasm (  5.2  ) 
 *  Total volume administered should be adjusted for patients less than 40 kg and for those requiring fluid restriction (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylactoid Reactions



  Serious anaphylactoid reactions, including death in a patient with asthma, have been reported in patients administered acetylcysteine intravenously.



 Acute flushing and erythema of the skin may occur in patients receiving acetylcysteine intravenously. These reactions usually occur 30 to 60 minutes after initiating the infusion and often resolve spontaneously despite continued infusion of acetylcysteine. Anaphylactoid reactions (defined as the occurrence of an acute hypersensitivity reaction during acetylcysteine administration including rash, hypotension, wheezing, and/or shortness of breath), have been observed in patients receiving intravenous acetylcysteine for acetaminophen overdose and occurred soon after initiation of the infusion [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. If a reaction to acetylcysteine involves more than simply flushing and erythema of the skin, it should be treated as an anaphylactoid reaction. This usually entails administering antihistaminic drugs and in severe cases may require administration of epinephrine. In addition, the acetylcysteine infusion may be interrupted until treatment of the anaphylactoid symptoms has been initiated and then carefully restarted. If the anaphylactoid reaction returns upon reinitiation of treatment or increases in severity, intravenous acetylcysteine should be discontinued and alternative patient management should be considered.



    5.2 Monitoring patients with asthma



  Acetadote should be used with caution in patients with asthma, or where there is a history of bronchospasm.



    5.3 Volume Adjustment: Patients less than 40 kg and Requiring Fluid Restriction



  The total volume administered should be adjusted for patients less than 40 kg and for those requiring fluid restriction. To avoid fluid overload, the volume of diluent should be reduced as needed [ see Dosage and Administration (  2  )  ]. If volume is not adjusted fluid overload can occur, potentially resulting in hyponatremia, seizure and death.



 For specific treatment information regarding the clinical management of acetaminophen overdose, please contact your regional poison center at 1-800-222-1222, or alternatively, a special health professional assistance line for acetaminophen overdose at 1-800-525-6115.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
