<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aciphex1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Worldwide, over 2900 patients have been treated with rabeprazole in Phase II-III clinical trials involving various dosages and durations of treatment.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



    EXCERPT:    *  In the adult studies (4 to 8 weeks), adverse reactions that occurred at a rate greater than 2% and greater than placebo included pain, pharyngitis, flatulence, infection and constipation ( ).  6.1   
 *  In studies of pediatric and adolescent patients (ages 1 to 16 years, and up to 36 weeks exposure) adverse reactions that occurred at a rate of &gt;=5% of patients included abdominal pain, diarrhea and headache ( ).  6.1   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eisai Inc. at 1-888-274-2378 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

    Adults  



 The data described below reflect exposure to ACIPHEX in 1064 adult patients exposed for up to 8 weeks. The studies were primarily placebo- and active-controlled trials in adult patients with Erosive or Ulcerative Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD), Duodenal Ulcers and Gastric Ulcers. The population had a mean age of 53 years (range 18-89 years) and had a ratio of approximately 60% male: 40% female. The racial distribution was 86% Caucasian, 8% African American, 2% Asian and 5% other. Most patients received either 10 mg, 20 mg or 40 mg/day of ACIPHEX.



 An analysis of adverse reactions appearing in &gt;=2% of ACIPHEX patients (n=1064) and with a greater frequency than placebo (n=89) in controlled North American and European acute treatment trials, revealed the following adverse reactions: pain (3% vs. 1%), pharyngitis (3% vs. 2%), flatulence (3% vs. 1%), infection (2% vs. 1%), and constipation (2% vs. 1%).



 Three long-term maintenance studies consisted of a total of 740 adult patients; at least 54% of adult patients were exposed to rabeprazole for 6 months while at least 33% were exposed for 12 months. Of the 740 adult patients, 247 (33%) and 241 (33%) patients received 10 mg and 20 mg of ACIPHEX, respectively, while 169 (23%) patients received placebo and 83 (11%) received omeprazole.



 The safety profile of rabeprazole in the maintenance studies in adults was consistent with what was observed in the acute studies.



 Other adverse reactions seen in controlled clinical trials, which do not meet the above criteria (&gt;=2% of ACIPHEX treated patients and greater than placebo) and for which there is a possibility of a causal relationship to rabeprazole, include the following: headache, abdominal pain, diarrhea, dry mouth, dizziness, peripheral edema, hepatic enzyme increase, hepatitis, hepatic encephalopathy, myalgia, and arthralgia.



 In clinical trials using combination therapy with rabeprazole plus amoxicillin and clarithromycin (RAC), no adverse reactions unique to this drug combination were observed. In the U.S. multicenter study, the most frequently reported drug related adverse reactions for patients who received RAC therapy for 7 or 10 days were diarrhea (8% and 7%) and taste perversion (6% and 10%), respectively.  Combination Treatment with Amoxicillin and Clarithromycin:  



 No clinically significant laboratory abnormalities particular to the drug combinations were observed.



 For more information on adverse reactions or laboratory changes with amoxicillin or clarithromycin, refer to their respective package prescribing information, section.  Adverse Reactions  



   Pediatric  



 In a multicenter, open-label study of adolescent patients 12 to 16 years of age with a clinical diagnosis of symptomatic GERD or endoscopically proven GERD, the adverse event profile was similar to that of adults. The adverse reactions reported without regard to relationship to ACIPHEX that occurred in &gt;=2% of 111 patients were headache (9.9%), diarrhea (4.5%), nausea (4.5%), vomiting (3.6%), and abdominal pain (3.6%). The related reported adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=2% of patients were headache (5.4%) and nausea (1.8%). There were no adverse reactions reported in this study that were not previously observed in adults.



 In a two-part, randomized, multicenter, double-blind, parallel-group study, 127 pediatric patients 1 to 11 years of age with endoscopically proven GERD received either 5 mg or 10 mg (&lt;15 kg body weight) or 10 mg or 20 mg (&gt;=15 kg body weight) rabeprazole. In this study, some patients were exposed to rabeprazole for 36 weeks. Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=5% of patients included abdominal pain (5%), diarrhea (5%), and headache (5%). There were no adverse reactions reported in this study that were not previously observed in trials of adolescents and adults.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of ACIPHEX. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: sudden death; coma, hyperammonemia; jaundice; rhabdomyolysis; disorientation and delirium; anaphylaxis; angioedema; bullous and other drug eruptions of the skin; severe dermatologic reactions, including toxic epidermal necrolysis (some fatal), Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and erythema multiforme; interstitial pneumonia; interstitial nephritis; TSH elevations; bone fractures; hypomagnesemia and associated diarrhea. In addition, agranulocytosis, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia have been reported. Increases in prothrombin time/INR in patients treated with concomitant warfarin have been reported.  Clostridium difficile  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Symptomatic response to therapy with rabeprazole does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy ( )  5.1   
 *  Use with warfarin: monitor for increases in INR and prothombin time ( )  5.2   
 *  PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of associated diarrhea ( ) Clostridium difficile   5.3   
 *  Bone fracture: Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine ( )  5.4   
 *  Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs ( )  5.5   
    
 

   5.1 Presence of Gastric Malignancy



  Symptomatic response to therapy with rabeprazole does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



 Patients with healed GERD were treated for up to 40 months with rabeprazole and monitored with serial gastric biopsies. Patients without infection (221 of 326 patients) had no clinically important pathologic changes in the gastric mucosa. Patients with infection at baseline (105 of 326 patients) had mild or moderate inflammation in the gastric body or mild inflammation in the gastric antrum. Patients with mild grades of infection or inflammation in the gastric body tended to change to moderate, whereas those graded moderate at baseline tended to remain stable. Patients with mild grades of infection or inflammation in the gastric antrum tended to remain stable. At baseline 8% of patients had atrophy of glands in the gastric body and 15% had atrophy in the gastric antrum. At endpoint, 15% of patients had atrophy of glands in the gastric body and 11% had atrophy in the gastric antrum. Approximately 4% of patients had intestinal metaplasia at some point during follow-up, but no consistent changes were seen. H. pylori   H. pylori  



    5.2 Concomitant Use with Warfarin



  Steady state interactions of rabeprazole and warfarin have not been adequately evaluated in patients. There have been reports of increased INR and prothrombin time in patients receiving a proton pump inhibitor and warfarin concomitantly. Increases in INR and prothrombin time may lead to abnormal bleeding and even death. Patients treated with a proton pump inhibitor and warfarin concomitantly may need to be monitored for increases in INR and prothrombin time.



     5.3 Associated Diarrhea Clostridium difficile    



   Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like ACIPHEX may be associated with an increased risk of associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [ ]. Clostridium difficile   see Adverse Reactions ( )  6.2      



  Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.  



  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents. For more information specific to antibacterial agents (clarithromycin and amoxicillin) indicated for use in combination with ACIPHEX, refer to and sections of those package inserts. Clostridium difficile   Warnings   Precautions    



    5.4 Bone Fracture



  Several published observational studies in adults suggest that PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines [ and ]. see Dosage and Administration ( )  2     Adverse Reactions ( )  6.2    



    5.5 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), healthcare professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically [ ]. see Adverse Reactions ( )  6.2    



     5.6 Concomitant Use of ACIPHEX with Methotrexate  



   Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients [ ]. see Drug Interactions ( )  7.7      
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
