<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="actoplus0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Congestive heart failure [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *    Lactic acidosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *    Edema [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *    Fractures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) are upper respiratory tract infection, edema, diarrhea, headache and weight gain. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Takeda Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-825-3327 and the ACTOPLUS MET website at: www.actoplusmet.com or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Pioglitazone  



 Over 8500 patients with type 2 diabetes have been treated with pioglitazone in randomized, double-blind, controlled clinical trials, including 2605 patients with type 2 diabetes and macrovascular disease treated with pioglitazone from the PROactive clinical trial. In these trials, over 6000 patients have been treated with pioglitazone for six months or longer, over 4500 patients have been treated with pioglitazone for one year or longer, and over 3000 patients have been treated with pioglitazone for at least two years.



 In six pooled 16- to 26-week placebo-controlled monotherapy and 16- to 24-week add-on combination therapy trials, the incidence of withdrawals due to adverse events was 4.5% for patients treated with pioglitazone and 5.8% for comparator-treated patients.



 The most common adverse events leading to withdrawal were related to inadequate glycemic control, although the incidence of these events was lower (1.5%) with pioglitazone than with placebo (3.0%).



 In the PROactive trial, the incidence of withdrawals due to adverse events was 9.0% for patients treated with pioglitazone and 7.7% for placebo-treated patients. Congestive heart failure was the most common serious adverse event leading to withdrawal occurring in 1.3% of patients treated with pioglitazone and 0.6% of patients treated with placebo.



     Common Adverse Events: 16- to 26-Week Monotherapy Trials    



 A summary of the incidence and type of common adverse events reported in three pooled 16- to 26-week placebo-controlled monotherapy trials of pioglitazone is provided in Table 1. Terms that are reported represent those that occurred at an incidence of &gt;5% and more commonly in patients treated with pioglitazone than in patients who received placebo. None of these adverse events were related to the pioglitazone dose.




  Table 1. Three Pooled 16- to 26-Week Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials of Pioglitazone Monotherapy: Adverse Events Reported at an Incidence &gt;5% and More Commonly in Patients Treated with Pioglitazone than in Patients Treated with Placebo    
  % of Patients                                          
                                                         PlaceboN=259         PioglitazoneN=606            
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                      8.5                  13.2                         
  Headache                                               6.9                  9.1                          
  Sinusitis                                              4.6                  6.3                          
  Myalgia                                                2.7                  5.4                          
  Pharyngitis                                            0.8                  5.1                          
             Common Adverse Events: 16- to 24-Week Add-on Combination Therapy Trials    
 

 A summary of the overall incidence and types of common adverse events reported in trials of pioglitazone add-on to metformin is provided in Table 2. Terms that are reported represent those that occurred at an incidence of &gt;5% and more commonly with the highest tested dose of pioglitazone.




  Table 2. 16- to 24-Week Clinical Trials of Pioglitazone Add-on to Metformin    
                       16-Week Placebo-Controlled TrialAdverse Events Reported in &gt;5% of Patients and More Commonly in Patients Treated with Pioglitazone + Metformin than in Patients Treated with Placebo + Metformin    
                       % of Patients                              
                       Placebo + MetforminN=160                   Pioglitazone 30 mg + MetforminN=168        
  Edema                2.5                                        6.0                                        
  Headache             1.9                                        6.0                                        
                       24-Week Non-Controlled Double-Blind Trial Adverse Events Reported in &gt;5% of Patients and More Commonly in Patients Treated with Pioglitazone 45 mg + Metformin than in Patients Treated with Pioglitazone 30 mg + Metformin    
  % of Patients        
  Pioglitazone 30 mg + MetforminN=411    Pioglitazone 45 mg + MetforminN=416        
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection    12.4                                       13.5                                       
  Edema                5.8                                        13.9                                       
  Headache             5.4                                        5.8                                        
  Weight Increased     2.9                                        6.7                                        
  Note: The preferred terms of edema peripheral, generalized edema, pitting edema, and fluid retention were combined to form the aggregate term of "edema."    
             Common Adverse Events: 24-Week ACTOPLUS MET Clinical Trial    
 

 Table 3 summarizes the incidence and types of adverse reactions reported in a controlled, 24-week double-blind clinical trial of ACTOPLUS MET dosed twice daily in patients with inadequate glycemic control on diet and exercise (N=600).




  Table 3. Adverse Events (&gt;=5% for ACTOPLUS MET) Reported by Patients with Inadequate Glycemic Control on Diet and Exercise in a 24-Week Double-Blind Clinical Trial of ACTOPLUS MET Administered Twice Daily    
  % of Patients         
                        ACTOPLUS MET15/850 mgTwice DailyN=201    Pioglitazone15 mgTwice DailyN=190    Metformin850 mgTwice DailyN=209    
  Diarrhea              9.0                               2.6                        15.3                      
  Headache              5.5                               2.6                        4.8                       
          In this 24-week trial, abdominal pain was reported in 2.0% of patients in the ACTOPLUS MET group, 1.6% in the pioglitazone monotherapy group and 3.3% in the metformin monotherapy group.
 

     Common Adverse Events: PROactive Trial    



 A summary of the overall incidence and types of common adverse events reported in the PROactive trial is provided in Table 4. Terms that are reported represent those that occurred at an incidence of &gt;5% and more commonly in patients treated with pioglitazone than in patients who received placebo.




  Table 4. PROactive Trial: Incidence and Types of Adverse Events Reported in &gt;5% of Patients Treated with Pioglitazone and More Commonly than Placebo    
                                               % of Patients            
  PlaceboN=2633                                PioglitazoneN=2605       
  Hypoglycemia                                 18.8                     27.3                                
  Edema                                        15.3                     26.7                                
  Cardiac Failure                              6.1                      8.1                                 
  Pain in Extremity                            5.7                      6.4                                 
  Back Pain                                    5.1                      5.5                                 
  Chest Pain                                   5.0                      5.1                                 
  Mean duration of patient follow-up was 34.5 months.    
             Congestive Heart Failure    
 

 A summary of the incidence of adverse events related to congestive heart failure is provided in Table 5 for the 16- to 24-week add-on to metformin trials. None of the events were fatal.




  Table 5. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events of Congestive Heart Failure (CHF) Patients Treated with Pioglitazone or Placebo Added on to Metformin    
                                 Number (%) of Patients    
  Placebo-Controlled Trial(16 weeks)    Non-Controlled Double-Blind Trial(24 weeks)    
  Placebo + MetforminN=160       Pioglitazone 30 mg + MetforminN=168    Pioglitazone 30 mg + MetforminN=411    Pioglitazone 45 mg + MetforminN=416    
  At least one congestive heart failure event    0                   1 (0.6%)            0                   1 (0.2%)            
  Hospitalized                   0                   1 (0.6%)            0                   1 (0.2%)            
         
  Table 6. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events of Congestive Heart Failure (CHF)    
  Patients Treated with Pioglitazone or Placebo Added on to a Sulfonylurea    
                         Number (%) of Patients    
  Placebo-Controlled Trial(16 weeks)    Non-Controlled Double-Blind Trial(24 weeks)    
                         Placebo + SulfonylureaN=187    Pioglitazone 15 mg + SulfonylureaN=184    Pioglitazone 30 mg + SulfonylureaN=189    Pioglitazone 30 mg + SulfonylureaN=351    Pioglitazone 45 mg + SulfonylureaN=351    
  At least one congestive heart failure event    2 (1.1%)          0                 0                 1 (0.3%)          6 (1.7%)          
  Hospitalized           2 (1.1%)          0                 0                 0                 2 (0.6%)          
  Patients Treated with Pioglitazone or Placebo Added on to Insulin    
                         Number (%) of Patients    
  Placebo-Controlled Trial(16 weeks)    Non-Controlled Double-Blind Trial(24 weeks)    
  Placebo + InsulinN=187    Pioglitazone15 mg + InsulinN=191    Pioglitazone30 mg + InsulinN=188    Pioglitazone30 mg + InsulinN=345    Pioglitazone45 mg + InsulinN=345    
  At least one congestive heart failure event    0                 2 (1.0%)          2 (1.1%)          3 (0.9%)          5 (1.4%)          
  Hospitalized           0                 2 (1.0%)          1 (0.5%)          1 (0.3%)          3 (0.9%)          
  Patients Treated with Pioglitazone or Placebo Added on to Metformin    
                         Number (%) of Patients    
  Placebo-Controlled Trial(16 weeks)    Non-Controlled Double-Blind Trial(24 weeks)    
  Placebo + MetforminN=160    Pioglitazone30 mg + MetforminN=168    Pioglitazone30 mg + MetforminN=411    Pioglitazone45 mg + MetforminN=416    
  At least one congestive heart failure event    0                 1 (0.6%)          0                 1 (0.2%)          
  Hospitalized           0                 1 (0.6%)          0                 1 (0.2%)          
          
  Table 7. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events of Congestive Heart Failure (CHF) in Patients with NYHA Class II or III Congestive Heart Failure Treated with Pioglitazone or Glyburide    
                                                                   Number (%) of Subjects    
  PioglitazoneN=262                                                GlyburideN=256        
  Death due to cardiovascular causes (adjudicated)                 5 (1.9%)              6 (2.3%)           
  Overnight hospitalization for worsening CHF (adjudicated)        26 (9.9%)             12 (4.7%)          
  Emergency room visit for CHF (adjudicated)                       4 (1.5%)              3 (1.2%)           
  Patients experiencing CHF progression during study               35 (13.4%)            21 (8.2%)          
         Congestive heart failure events leading to hospitalization that occurred during the PROactive trial are summarized in Table 8.
 


  Table 8. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events of Congestive Heart Failure (CHF) in PROactive Trial    
                                                                      Number (%) of Patients    
  PlaceboN=2633                                                       PioglitazoneN=2605    
  At least one hospitalized congestive heart failure event            108 (4.1%)        149 (5.7%)          
  Fatal                                                               22 (0.8%)         25 (1.0%)           
  Hospitalized, nonfatal                                              86 (3.3%)         124 (4.7%)          
             Cardiovascular Safety    
 

 In the PROactive trial, 5238 patients with type 2 diabetes and a history of macrovascular disease were randomized to pioglitazone (N=2605), force-titrated up to 45 mg daily or placebo (N=2633) in addition to standard of care. Almost all patients (95%) were receiving cardiovascular medications (beta blockers, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin II receptor blockers, calcium channel blockers, nitrates, diuretics, aspirin, statins, and fibrates). At baseline, patients had a mean age of 62 years, mean duration of diabetes of 9.5 years, and mean HbA1c of 8.1%. Mean duration of follow-up was 34.5 months.



 The primary objective of this trial was to examine the effect of pioglitazone on mortality and macrovascular morbidity in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus who were at high risk for macrovascular events. The primary efficacy variable was the time to the first occurrence of any event in a cardiovascular composite endpoint that included all-cause mortality, nonfatal myocardial infarction (MI) including silent MI, stroke, acute coronary syndrome, cardiac intervention including coronary artery bypass grafting or percutaneous intervention, major leg amputation above the ankle, and bypass surgery or revascularization in the leg. A total of 514 (19.7%) patients treated with pioglitazone and 572 (21.7%) placebo-treated patients experienced at least one event from the primary composite endpoint (HR 0.90; 95% CI: 0.80, 1.02; p=0.10).



 Although there was no statistically significant difference between pioglitazone and placebo for the three-year incidence of a first event within this composite, there was no increase in mortality or in total macrovascular events with pioglitazone. The number of first occurrences and total individual events contributing to the primary composite endpoint is shown in Table 9.




  Table 9. PROactive Trial: Number of First and Total Events for Each Component Within the Cardiovascular Composite Endpoint    
  Cardiovascular Events                    PlaceboN=2633    PioglitazoneN=2605    
  First Eventsn (%)                        Total eventsn    First Eventsn (%)    Total eventsn    
  Any event                                572 (21.7)       900              514 (19.7)       803              
    All-cause mortality                    122 (4.6)        186              110 (4.2)        177              
    Nonfatal myocardial infarction (MI)    118 (4.5)        157              105 (4.0)        131              
    Stroke                                 96 (3.6)         119              76 (2.9)         92               
    Acute coronary syndrome                63 (2.4)         78               42 (1.6)         65               
    Cardiac intervention (CABG/PCI)        101 (3.8)        240              101 (3.9)        195              
    Major leg amputation                   15 (0.6)         28               9 (0.3)          28               
    Leg revascularization                  57 (2.2)         92               71 (2.7)         115              
  CABG = coronary artery bypass grafting; PCI = percutaneous intervention    
               Weight Gain    
 

 Dose-related weight gain occurs when pioglitazone is used alone or in combination with other antidiabetic medications. The mechanism of weight gain is unclear but probably involves a combination of fluid retention and fat accumulation.



 Tables 10, 11, and 12 summarize the changes in body weight with pioglitazone and placebo in the 16- to 26-week randomized, double-blind monotherapy and 16- to 24-week combination add-on therapy trials, the PROactive trial, and the 24-week ACTOPLUS MET trial.




  Table 10. Weight Changes (kg) from Baseline During Randomized, Double-Blind Clinical Trials    
                       Control Group(Placebo)    Pioglitazone15 mg    Pioglitazone30 mg    Pioglitazone45 mg    
  Median(25th, 75th percentile)    Median(25th, 75th percentile)    Median(25th, 75th percentile)    Median(25th, 75th percentile)    
  Monotherapy(16 to 26 weeks)                  -1.4 (-2.7, 0.0)N=256    0.9 (-0.5, 3.4)N=79    1.0 (-0.9, 3.4)N=188    2.6 (0.2, 5.4)N=79    
  Combination Therapy(16 to 24 weeks)    Sulfonylurea    -0.5 (-1.8, 0.7)N=187    2.0 (0.2, 3.2)N=183    3.1 (1.1, 5.4)N=528    4.1 (1.8, 7.3)N=333    
  Metformin            -1.4 (-3.2, 0.3)N=160    N/A                0.9 (-1.3, 3.2)N=567    1.8 (-0.9, 5.0)N=407    
  Insulin              0.2 (-1.4, 1.4)N=182    2.3 (0.5, 4.3)N=190    3.3 (0.9, 6.3)N=522    4.1 (1.4, 6.8)N=338    
          
  Table 11. Median Change in Body Weight in Patients Treated with Pioglitazone Versus Patients Treated with Placebo During the Double-Blind Treatment Period in the PROactive Trial    
                                                 Placebo                      Pioglitazone                  
  Median(25th, 75th percentile)                  Median(25th, 75th percentile)    
  Change from baseline to final visit (kg)       -0.5 (-3.3, 2.0)N=2581       +3.6 (0.0, 7.5)N=2560         
  Note: Median exposure for both pioglitazone and placebo was 2.7 years.    
       
  Table 12. Weight Changes (kg) from Baseline During Double-Blind Clinical Trial with ACTOPLUS MET in Patients with Inadequate Glycemic Control on Diet and Exercise    
                                     ACTOPLUS MET15/850 mgTwice Daily    Pioglitazone15 mgTwice Daily    Metformin850 mgTwice Daily    
  Median(25th , 75th percentile)     Median(25th , 75th percentile)    Median(25th , 75th percentile)    
  Change from baseline to final visit (kg)    1.00 (-1.0, 3.0)N=198    1.35 (-0.7, 4.1)N=178    -1.00 (-2.6, 0.4)N=203    
  Note: Trial duration of 24 weeks.    
              Edema    
 

 Edema induced from taking pioglitazone is reversible when pioglitazone is discontinued. The edema usually does not require hospitalization unless there is coexisting congestive heart failure.



 In the 24-week ACTOPLUS MET trial, edema was reported in 3.0% of patients in the ACTOPLUS MET group, 4.2% in the pioglitazone monotherapy group, and 1.4% in the metformin monotherapy group.



 A summary of the frequency and types of edema adverse events occurring in clinical investigations of pioglitazone is provided in Table 13.




  Table 13. Adverse Events of Edema in Patients Treated with Pioglitazone    
                         Number (%) of Patients    
  Placebo                Pioglitazone15 mg    Pioglitazone30 mg    Pioglitazone45 mg    
  Monotherapy(16 to 26 weeks)    3 (1.2%)N=259     2 (2.5%)N= 81    13 (4.7%)N= 275    11 (6.5%)N=169     
  Combined Therapy(16 to 24 weeks)    Sulfonylurea      4 (2.1%)N=187    3 (1.6%)N=184      61 (11.3%)N=540    81 (23.1%)N=351    
  Metformin              4 (2.5%)N=160     N/A            34 (5.9%)N=579     58 (13.9%)N=416    
  Insulin                13 (7.0%)N=187    24 (12.6%)N=191    109 (20.5%)N=533    90 (26.1%)N=345    
  Note: The preferred terms of edema peripheral, generalized edema, pitting edema, and fluid retention were combined to form the aggregate term of "edema."    
          
  Table 14. Adverse Events of Edema in Patients in the PROactive Trial    
  Number (%) of Patients                             
  PlaceboN=2633                                      PioglitazoneN=2605                                   
  419 (15.9%)                                        712 (27.3%)                                          
  Note: The preferred terms of edema peripheral, generalized edema, pitting edema, and fluid retention were combined to form the aggregate term of "edema."    
            Hepatic Effects    
 

 There has been no evidence of pioglitazone-induced hepatotoxicity in the pioglitazone controlled clinical trial database to date. One randomized, double-blind, three-year trial comparing pioglitazone to glyburide as add-on to metformin and insulin therapy was specifically designed to evaluate the incidence of serum ALT elevation to greater than three times the upper limit of the reference range, measured every eight weeks for the first 48 weeks of the trial then every 12 weeks thereafter. A total of 3/1051 (0.3%) patients treated with pioglitazone and 9/1046 (0.9%) patients treated with glyburide developed ALT values greater than three times the upper limit of the reference range. None of the patients treated with pioglitazone in the pioglitazone controlled clinical trial database to date have had a serum ALT greater than three times the upper limit of the reference range and a corresponding total bilirubin greater than two times the upper limit of the reference range, a combination predictive of the potential for severe drug-induced liver injury.



     Hypoglycemia    



 In the pioglitazone clinical trials, adverse events of hypoglycemia were reported based on clinical judgment of the investigators and did not require confirmation with fingerstick glucose testing.



 In the 16-week add-on to sulfonylurea trial, the incidence of reported hypoglycemia was 3.7% with pioglitazone 30 mg and 0.5% with placebo. In the 16-week add-on to insulin trial, the incidence of reported hypoglycemia was 7.9% with pioglitazone 15 mg, 15.4% with pioglitazone 30 mg, and 4.8% with placebo.



 The incidence of reported hypoglycemia was higher with pioglitazone 45 mg compared to pioglitazone 30 mg in both the 24-week add-on to sulfonylurea trial (15.7% versus 13.4%) and in the 24-week add-on to insulin trial (47.8% versus 43.5%).



 Three patients in these four trials were hospitalized due to hypoglycemia. All three patients were receiving pioglitazone 30 mg (0.9%) in the 24-week add-on to insulin trial. An additional 14 patients reported severe hypoglycemia (defined as causing considerable interference with patient's usual activities) that did not require hospitalization. These patients were receiving pioglitazone 45 mg in combination with sulfonylurea (n=2) or pioglitazone 30 mg or 45 mg in combination with insulin (n=12).



     Urinary Bladder Tumors    



 Tumors were observed in the urinary bladder of male rats in the two-year carcinogenicity study  [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . In two 3-year trials in which pioglitazone was compared to placebo or glyburide, there were 16/3656 (0.44%) reports of bladder cancer in patients taking pioglitazone compared to 5/3679 (0.14%) in patients not taking pioglitazone. After excluding patients in whom exposure to study drug was less than one year at the time of diagnosis of bladder cancer, there were six (0.16%) cases on pioglitazone and two (0.05%) cases on placebo. There are too few events of bladder cancer to establish causality.



   Metformin hydrochloride  



 In a double-blind clinical study of metformin in patients with type 2 diabetes, a total of 141 patients received metformin therapy (up to 2550 mg per day) and 145 patients received placebo. Adverse reactions reported in greater than 5% of the metformin patients, and that were more common in metformin than placebo-treated patients, are listed in Table 15. In this trial, diarrhea led to discontinuation of study medication in 6% of patients treated with metformin.




  Table 15. Most Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;5.0%) in a Placebo-Controlled Clinical Study of Metformin MonotherapyReactions that were more common in metformin than placebo-treated patients.    
  Adverse Reaction                         Metformin Monotherapy(n=141)                  Placebo(n=145)     
  % of Patients                            
  Diarrhea                                 53.2                                          11.7               
  Nausea/Vomiting                          25.5                                          8.3                
  Flatulence                               12.1                                          5.5                
  Asthenia                                 9.2                                           5.5                
  Indigestion                              7.1                                           4.1                
  Abdominal Discomfort                     6.4                                           4.8                
  Headache                                 5.7                                           4.8                
           Laboratory Abnormalities  
 

   Hematologic Effects  



 Pioglitazone may cause decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit. In placebo-controlled monotherapy trials, mean hemoglobin values declined by 2% to 4% in patients treated with pioglitazone compared with a mean change in hemoglobin of -1% to +1% in placebo-treated patients. These changes primarily occurred within the first four to 12 weeks of therapy and remained relatively constant thereafter. These changes may be related to increased plasma volume associated with pioglitazone therapy and are not likely to be associated with any clinically significant hematologic effects.



   Vitamin B12Concentrations  



 Metformin may lower serum vitamin B12concentrations. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on ACTOPLUS MET and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)  ]  .



   Creatine Phosphokinase  



 During protocol-specified measurement of serum creatine phosphokinase (CPK) in pioglitazone clinical trials, an isolated elevation in CPK to greater than 10 times the upper limit of the reference range was noted in nine (0.2%) patients treated with pioglitazone (values of 2150 to 11400 IU/L) and in no comparator-treated patients. Six of these nine patients continued to receive pioglitazone, two patients were noted to have the CPK elevation on the last day of dosing, and one patient discontinued pioglitazone due to the elevation. These elevations resolved without any apparent clinical sequelae. The relationship of these events to pioglitazone therapy is unknown.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Pioglitazone  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of pioglitazone. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *    New onset or worsening diabetic macular edema with decreased visual acuity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ] . 
 *    Fatal and nonfatal hepatic failure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ] . 
    Postmarketing reports of congestive heart failure have been reported in patients treated with pioglitazone, both with and without previously known heart disease and both with and without concomitant insulin administration.
 

 In postmarketing experience, there have been reports of unusually rapid increases in weight and increases in excess of that generally observed in clinical trials. Patients who experience such increases should be assessed for fluid accumulation and volume-related events such as excessive edema and congestive heart failure  [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AND LACTIC ACIDOSIS

  WARNING: CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AND LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    Congestive Heart Failure  



 *  Thiazolidinediones, including pioglitazone, which is a component of ACTOPLUS MET, cause or exacerbate congestive heart failure in some patients [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  After initiation of ACTOPLUS MET, and after dose increases, monitor patients carefully for signs and symptoms of heart failure (e.g., excessive, rapid weight gain, dyspnea, and/or edema). If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care and discontinuation or dose reduction of ACTOPLUS MET must be considered [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  ACTOPLUS MET is not recommended in patients with symptomatic heart failure. 
 *  Initiation of ACTOPLUS MET in patients with established New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure is contraindicated [see Contraindications (4) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      Lactic Acidosis  
 

 *  Lactic acidosis is a rare but serious complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  The onset is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, ACTOPLUS MET should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AND LACTIC ACIDOSIS
 

 See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning



   Congestive Heart Failure  



 *  Thiazolidinediones, including pioglitazone, which is a component of ACTOPLUS MET, cause or exacerbate congestive heart failure in some patients. (5.1) 
 *  After initiation of ACTOPLUS MET, and after dose increases, monitor patients carefully for signs and symptoms of heart failure (e.g., excessive, rapid weight gain, dyspnea, and/or edema). If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care and discontinuation or dose reduction of ACTOPLUS MET must be considered. (5.1) 
 *  ACTOPLUS MET is not recommended in patients with symptomatic heart failure. 
 *  Initiation of ACTOPLUS MET in patients with established New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure is contraindicated. (4, 5.1) 
      Lactic Acidosis  
 

 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. (5.2) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate. (5.2) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue ACTOPLUS MET and hospitalize the patient immediately. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Congestive heart failure: Fluid retention may occur and can exacerbate or lead to congestive heart failure. Combination use with insulin and use in congestive heart failure NYHA Class I and II may increase risk. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Lactic acidosis: Warn against excessive alcohol intake. ACTOPLUS MET is not recommended in hepatic impairment and is contraindicated in renal impairment. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter. (  5.2  ,  5.10  ) 
 *    Edema: Dose-related edema may occur. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Hypoglycemia: When used with insulin or an insulin secretagogue, a lower dose of the insulin or insulin secretagogue may be needed to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Hepatic effects: Postmarketing reports of hepatic failure, sometimes fatal. Causality cannot be excluded. If liver injury is detected, promptly interrupt ACTOPLUS MET and assess patient for probable cause, then treat cause if possible, to resolution or stabilization. Do not restart ACTOPLUS MET if liver injury is confirmed and no alternate etiology can be found. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Bladder cancer: Preclinical and clinical trial data, and results from an observational study suggest an increased risk of bladder cancer in pioglitazone users. The observational data further suggest that the risk increases with duration of use. Do not use in patients with active bladder cancer. Use caution when using in patients with a prior history of bladder cancer. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Fractures: Increased incidence in female patients. Apply current standards of care for assessing and maintaining bone health. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Macular edema: Postmarketing reports. Recommend regular eye exams in all patients with diabetes according to current standards of care with prompt evaluation for acute visual changes. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Temporarily discontinue in patients undergoing radiologic studies with intravascular iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food and fluids. (  5.12  ) 
 *    Vitamin B12deficiency: Metformin may lower vitamin B12levels. Monitor hematologic parameters annually. (  5.14  ) 
 *    Macrovascular outcomes: There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with ACTOPLUS MET or any other antidiabetic drug. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Congestive Heart Failure



   Pioglitazone  



 Pioglitazone, like other thiazolidinediones, can cause dose-related fluid retention when used alone or in combination with other antidiabetic medications and is most common when pioglitazone is used in combination with insulin. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate congestive heart failure. Patients treated with ACTOPLUS MET should be observed for signs and symptoms of congestive heart failure. If congestive heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care and discontinuation or dose reduction of ACTOPLUS MET must be considered [see  Boxed Warning    ,   Contraindications (4)  , and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.2 Lactic Acidosis



   Metformin hydrochloride  



   Lactic Acidosis    



 Lactic acidosis is a serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with ACTOPLUS MET and it is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate concentrations (&gt;5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels &gt;5 mcg/mL are generally found.



 The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin hydrochloride is approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years. In more than 20,000 patient-years, exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal impairment, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, particularly when accompanied by hypoperfusion and hypoxemia, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking metformin. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. ACTOPLUS MET treatment should not be initiated in any patient unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced. In addition, metformin should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, metformin should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic impairment. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake when taking metformin, because alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin on lactate metabolism. In addition, metformin should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure necessitating restricted intake of food or fluids [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10  ,  5.11  ,  5.12  ,  5.13)  ]  . Use of topiramate, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, in epilepsy and migraine prophylaxis may frequently cause dose-dependent metabolic acidosis and may exacerbate the risk of metformin-induced lactic acidosis [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



 The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis. Patients should be educated to promptly report these symptoms should they occur. If present, ACTOPLUS MET should be withdrawn until lactic acidosis is ruled out. Serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, blood pH, lactate levels, and blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of metformin, gastrointestinal symptoms, which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to recur. Later occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease.



 Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking metformin do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explainable by other mechanisms, such as poorly controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  .



 Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia).



 Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking metformin, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin hydrochloride is dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  .



    5.3 Edema



  In controlled clinical trials with pioglitazone, edema was reported more frequently in patients treated with pioglitazone than in placebo-treated patients and is dose related [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . In postmarketing experience, reports of new onset or worsening of edema have been received.



 ACTOPLUS MET should be used with caution in patients with edema. Because thiazolidinediones, including pioglitazone, can cause fluid retention, which can exacerbate or lead to congestive heart failure, ACTOPLUS MET should be used with caution in patients at risk for congestive heart failure. Patients treated with ACTOPLUS MET should be monitored for signs and symptoms of congestive heart failure [see  Boxed Warning    ,   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    , and  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .



    5.4 Hypoglycemia



  Patients receiving ACTOPLUS MET in combination with insulin or other antidiabetic medications (particularly insulin secretagogues such as sulfonylureas) may be at risk for hypoglycemia. A reduction in the dose of the concomitant antidiabetic medication may be necessary to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  .



 Hypoglycemia can also occur when caloric intake is deficient or when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplement. Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.



    5.5 Hepatic Effects



  There have been postmarketing reports of fatal and nonfatal hepatic failure in patients taking pioglitazone, although the reports contain insufficient information necessary to establish the probable cause. There has been no evidence of drug-induced hepatotoxicity in the pioglitazone controlled clinical trial database to date [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Patients with type 2 diabetes may have fatty liver disease or cardiac disease with episodic congestive heart failure, both of which may cause liver test abnormalities, and they may also have other forms of liver disease, many of which can be treated or managed. Therefore, obtaining a liver test panel (serum alanine aminotransferase [ALT], aspartate aminotransferase [AST], alkaline phosphatase, and total bilirubin) and assessing the patient is recommended before initiating ACTOPLUS MET therapy.



 In patients with abnormal liver tests, ACTOPLUS MET should be initiated with caution.



 Measure liver tests promptly in patients who report symptoms that may indicate liver injury, including fatigue, anorexia, right upper abdominal discomfort, dark urine or jaundice. In this clinical context, if the patient is found to have abnormal liver tests (ALT greater than three times the upper limit of the reference range), ACTOPLUS MET treatment should be interrupted and investigation done to establish the probable cause. ACTOPLUS MET should not be restarted in these patients without another explanation for the liver test abnormalities.



 Patients who have serum ALT greater than three times the reference range with serum total bilirubin greater than two times the reference range without alternative etiologies are at risk for severe drug-induced liver injury, and should not be restarted on ACTOPLUS MET. For patients with lesser elevations of serum ALT or bilirubin and with an alternate probable cause, treatment with ACTOPLUS MET can be used with caution.



 Because impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis ACTOPLUS MET should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease.



    5.6 Urinary Bladder Tumors



  Tumors were observed in the urinary bladder of male rats in the two-year carcinogenicity study [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . In two 3-year trials in which pioglitazone was compared to placebo or glyburide, there were 16/3656 (0.44%) reports of bladder cancer in patients taking pioglitazone compared to 5/3679 (0.14%) in patients not taking pioglitazone. After excluding patients in whom exposure to study drug was less than one year at the time of diagnosis of bladder cancer, there were six (0.16%) cases on pioglitazone and two (0.05%) cases on placebo.



 A five-year interim report of an ongoing 10-year observational cohort study found a nonsignificant increase in the risk for bladder cancer in subjects ever exposed to pioglitazone, compared to subjects never exposed to pioglitazone (HR 1.2 [95% CI 0.9 - 1.5]). Compared to never exposure, a duration of pioglitazone therapy longer than 12 months was associated with an increase in risk (HR 1.4 [95% CI 0.9 - 2.1]), which reached statistical significance after more than 24 months of pioglitazone use (HR 1.4 [95% CI 1.03 - 2.0]). Interim results from this study suggested that taking pioglitazone longer than 12 months increased the relative risk of developing bladder cancer in any given year by 40%, which equates to an absolute increase of three cases in 10,000 (from approximately seven in 10,000 [without pioglitazone] to approximately 10 in 10,000 [with pioglitazone]).



 There are insufficient data to determine whether pioglitazone is a tumor promoter for urinary bladder tumors. Consequently, ACTOPLUS MET should not be used in patients with active bladder cancer and the benefits of glycemic control versus unknown risks for cancer recurrence with ACTOPLUS MET should be considered in patients with a prior history of bladder cancer.



    5.7 Fractures



  In PROactive (the Prospective Pioglitazone Clinical Trial in Macrovascular Events), 5238 patients with type 2 diabetes and a history of macrovascular disease were randomized to pioglitazone (N=2605), force-titrated up to 45 mg daily or placebo (N=2633) in addition to standard of care. During a mean follow-up of 34.5 months, the incidence of bone fracture in females was 5.1% (44/870) for pioglitazone versus 2.5% (23/905) for placebo. This difference was noted after the first year of treatment and persisted during the course of the study. The majority of fractures observed in female patients were nonvertebral fractures including lower limb and distal upper limb. No increase in the incidence of fracture was observed in men treated with pioglitazone (1.7%) versus placebo (2.1%). The risk of fracture should be considered in the care of patients, especially female patients, treated with ACTOPLUS MET and attention should be given to assessing and maintaining bone health according to current standards of care.



    5.8 Macular Edema



  Macular edema has been reported in postmarketing experience in diabetic patients who were taking pioglitazone or another thiazolidinedione. Some patients presented with blurred vision or decreased visual acuity, but others were diagnosed on routine ophthalmologic examination.



 Most patients had peripheral edema at the time macular edema was diagnosed. Some patients had improvement in their macular edema after discontinuation of the thiazolidinedione.



 Patients with diabetes should have regular eye exams by an ophthalmologist according to current standards of care. Patients with diabetes who report any visual symptoms should be promptly referred to an ophthalmologist, regardless of the patient's underlying medications or other physical findings [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.9 Ovulation



  Therapy with pioglitazone, like other thiazolidinediones, may result in ovulation in some premenopausal anovulatory women. As a result, these patients may be at an increased risk for pregnancy while taking ACTOPLUS MET [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  . This effect has not been investigated in clinical trials, so the frequency of this occurrence is not known. Adequate contraception in all premenopausal women treated with ACTOPLUS MET is recommended.



    5.10 Monitoring of Renal Function



  Metformin is substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of impairment of renal function. Therefore, ACTOPLUS MET is contraindicated in patients with renal impairment.



 Before initiation of therapy with ACTOPLUS MET and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal dysfunction is anticipated (e.g., elderly), renal function should be assessed more frequently and ACTOPLUS MET discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present.



  Use of Concomitant Medications That May Affect Renal Function or Metformin Disposition  



 Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or may interfere with the disposition of metformin, such as cationic drugs that are eliminated by renal tubular secretion, should be used with caution [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



  Radiological Studies and Surgical Procedures  



 Radiologic studies involving the use of intravascular iodinated contrast materials (for example, intravenous urogram, intravenous cholangiography, angiography, and computed tomography (CT) scans with intravascular contrast materials) can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, ACTOPLUS MET should be discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been re-evaluated and found to be normal.



    5.11 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause, acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients receiving ACTOPLUS MET therapy, the drug should be promptly discontinued.



    5.12 Surgical Procedures



  Use of ACTOPLUS MET should be temporarily suspended for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.13 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol is known to potentiate the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients, therefore, should be warned against excessive alcohol intake, acute or chronic, while receiving ACTOPLUS MET.



    5.14 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled clinical trials of metformin of 29 weeks' duration, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on ACTOPLUS MET and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. Certain individuals (those with inadequate vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum vitamin B12measurements at two- to three-year intervals may be useful.



    5.15 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with ACTOPLUS MET or any other oral antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
