<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aczone0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 10%) are oiliness/peeling, dryness and erythema at the application site (  6  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Allergan at 1-800-433-8871 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Serious adverse reactions reported in patients treated with  ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5%, during clinical trials included but were not limited to the following:



 *  Nervous system/Psychiatric - Suicide attempt, tonic clonic movements. 
 *  Gastrointestinal - Abdominal pain, severe vomiting, pancreatitis. 
 *  Other - Severe pharyngitis 
    In the clinical trials, a total of 12 out of 4032 patients were reported to have depression (3 of 1660 treated with vehicle and 9 of 2372 treated with  ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5%). Psychosis was reported in 2 of 2372 patients treated with  ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5%, and in 0 of 1660 patients treated with vehicle.
 

 Combined contact sensitization/irritation studies with  ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5%, in 253 healthy subjects resulted in at least 3 subjects with moderate erythema.  ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5%, did not induce phototoxicity or photoallergy in human dermal safety studies.



   ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5%, was evaluated for 12 weeks in four controlled studies for local cutaneous events in 1819 patients. The most common events reported from these studies include oiliness/peeling, dryness, and erythema. These data are shown by severity in  Table 1  below.



 Table 1 - Application Site Adverse Reactions by Maximum Severity 
                                  ACZONE    (r)  (N=1819)  Vehicle(N=1660)   
 Application Site Event         Mild         Moderate      Severe       Mild       Moderate       Severe        
 Erythema                       9%           5%            &lt;1%          9%         6%             &lt;1%           
 Dryness                        14%          3%            &lt;1%          14%        4%             &lt;1%           
 Oiliness/Peeling               13%          6%            &lt;1%          15%        6%             &lt;1%           
             The adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of patients in either arm in the four vehicle controlled studies are presented in  Table 2  .
 

 Table 2 - Adverse Reactions Occurring in at Least 1% of Patients 
  NOS = Not otherwise specified                                
  
                                                                ACZONE    (r)  N=1819  VehicleN=1660        
 Application Site Reaction NOS                                18%                    20%                  
 Application Site Dryness                                     16%                    17%                  
 Application Site Erythema                                    13%                    14%                  
 Application Site Burning                                     1%                     2%                   
 Application Site Pruritus                                    1%                     1%                   
 Pyrexia                                                      1%                     1%                   
 Nasopharyngitis                                              5%                     6%                   
 Upper Respiratory Tract Inf. NOS                             3%                     3%                   
 Sinusitis NOS                                                2%                     1%                   
 Influenza                                                    1%                     1%                   
 Pharyngitis                                                  2%                     2%                   
 Cough                                                        2%                     2%                   
 Joint Sprain                                                 1%                     1%                   
 Headache NOS                                                 4%                     4%                   
         One patient treated with  ACZONE    (r)  Gel in the clinical trials had facial swelling which led to discontinuation of medication.
 

 In addition, 486 patients were evaluated in a 12 month safety study. The adverse event profile in this study was consistent with that observed in the vehicle-controlled studies.



   6.2 Experience with Oral Use of Dapsone

  Although not observed in the clinical trials with  ACZONE    (r)  Gel (topical dapsone) serious adverse reactions have been reported with oral use of dapsone, including agranulocytosis, hemolytic anemia, peripheral neuropathy (motor loss and muscle weakness), and skin reactions (toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, morbilliform and scarlatiniform reactions, bullous and exfoliative dermatitis, erythema nodosum, and urticaria).



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of  ACZONE      (r)    Gel, 5%. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Methemoglobinemia has been identified during postmarketing use of  ACZONE      (r)    Gel, 5%  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Methemoglobinemia: Cases of methemoglobinemia have been reported. Discontinue ACZONE    (r)   gel if signs of methemoglobinemia occur (  5.1  ). 
 *  Hematologic Effects: Some subjects with G6PD deficiency using ACZONE    (r)   Gel developed laboratory changes suggestive of hemolysis. (  5.2  )(  8.6  ). 
    
 

      5.1 Methemoglobinemia



     Cases of methemoglobinemia, with resultant hospitalization, have been reported postmarketing in association with ACZONE     (r)    Gel, 5% treatment. Patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency or congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia are more susceptible to drug-induced methemoglobinemia. Avoid use of ACZONE     (r)    Gel, 5% in those patients with congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia.



    Signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia may be delayed some hours after exposure. Initial signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia are characterized by a slate grey cyanosis seen in, e.g., buccal mucous membranes, lips and nail beds. Advise patients to discontinue ACZONE     (r)    Gel, 5% and seek immediate medical attention in the event of cyanosis.



    Dapsone can cause elevated methemoglobin levels particularly in conjunction with methemoglobin-inducing agents.



    5.2 Hematologic Effects



  Oral dapsone treatment has produced dose-related hemolysis and hemolytic anemia. Individuals with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency are more prone to hemolysis with the use of certain drugs. G6PD deficiency is most prevalent in populations of African, South Asian, Middle Eastern, and Mediterranean ancestry.



 Some subjects with G6PD deficiency using ACZONE     (r)    Gel developed laboratory changes suggestive of hemolysis. There was no evidence of clinically relevant hemolysis or anemia in patients treated with ACZONE     (r)    Gel, 5%, including patients who were G6PD deficient.



 Discontinue ACZONE     (r)    Gel, 5%, if signs and symptoms suggestive of hemolytic anemia occur. Avoid use of ACZONE     (r)    Gel, 5% in patients who are taking oral dapsone or antimalarial medications because of the potential for hemolytic reactions. Combination of ACZONE     (r)    Gel, 5%, with trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole (TMP/SMX) may increase the likelihood of hemolysis in patients with G6PD deficiency.



    5.3 Peripheral Neuropathy



  Peripheral neuropathy (motor loss and muscle weakness) has been reported with oral dapsone treatment. No events of peripheral neuropathy were observed in clinical trials with topical ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5% treatment.



    5.4 Skin



  Skin reactions (toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, morbilliform and scarlatiniform reactions, bullous and exfoliative dermatitis, erythema nodosum, and urticaria) have been reported with oral dapsone treatment. These types of skin reactions were not observed in clinical trials with topical ACZONE    (r)  Gel, 5% treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
