<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aczone1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common (incidence &gt;= 0.9%) adverse reactions are application site dryness and pruritus (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Allergan at 1-800-433-8871 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 2161 subjects were treated with  ACZONE  Gel, 7.5%, for 12 weeks in 2 controlled clinical trials. The population ranged in age from 12 to 63 years, was 56% female, and 58% Caucasian. Adverse drug reactions that were reported in at least 0.9% of subjects treated with  ACZONE  Gel, 7.5% appear in  Table 1  below.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Occurring in at Least 0.9% of Subjects with Acne Vulgaris in 12-week Controlled Clinical Trials 
                                      ACZONE Gel, 7.5%    (N=2161)       Vehicle    (N=2175)               
 Application Site Dryness           24 (1.1%)                          21 (1.0%)                           
 Application Site Pruritus          20 (0.9%)                          11 (0.5%)                           
           6.2 Experience with Oral Use of Dapsone
   Although not observed in the clinical trials with topical dapsone, serious adverse reactions have been reported with oral use of dapsone, including agranulocytosis, hemolytic anemia, peripheral neuropathy (motor loss and muscle weakness), and skin reactions (toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, morbilliform and scarlatiniform reactions, bullous and exfoliative dermatitis, erythema nodosum, and urticaria).



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of topical dapsone. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Methemoglobinemia has been identified during postmarketing use of topical dapsone  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Methemoglobinemia: Cases of methemoglobinemia have been reported. Discontinue ACZONE Gel if signs of methemoglobinemia occur (  5.1  ). 
 *  Hemolysis: Some patients with Glucose-6-phosphate Dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency using topical dapsone developed laboratory changes suggestive of hemolysis (  5.1  )(  8.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hematological Effects



   Methemoglobinemia  



 Cases of methemoglobinemia, with resultant hospitalization, have been reported postmarketing in association with twice daily dapsone gel, 5%, treatment. Patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency or congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia are more susceptible to drug-induced methemoglobinemia. Avoid use of ACZONE  Gel, 7.5% in those patients with congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia.



 Signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia may be delayed some hours after exposure. Initial signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia are characterized by a slate grey cyanosis seen in e.g., buccal mucous membranes, lips, and nail beds. Advise patients to discontinue ACZONE  Gel, 7.5% and seek immediate medical attention in the event of cyanosis.



 Dapsone can cause elevated methemoglobin levels particularly in conjunction with methemoglobin-inducing agents [see Drug Interactions (  7.4  )]  .



    Hemolysis  



 Oral dapsone treatment has produced dose-related hemolysis and hemolytic anemia. Individuals with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency are more prone to hemolysis with the use of certain drugs. G6PD deficiency is most prevalent in populations of African, South Asian, Middle Eastern, and Mediterranean ancestry.



 In clinical trials, there was no evidence of clinically relevant hemolysis or hemolytic anemia in subjects treated with topical dapsone. Some subjects with G6PD deficiency using dapsone gel, 5 %, twice daily developed laboratory changes suggestive of hemolysis [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  )].  



 Discontinue ACZONE  Gel, 7.5%, if signs and symptoms suggestive of hemolytic anemia occur. Avoid use of ACZONE  Gel, 7.5% in patients who are taking oral dapsone or antimalarial medications because of the potential for hemolytic reactions. Combination of ACZONE  Gel, 7.5%, with trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole (TMP/SMX) may increase the likelihood of hemolysis in patients with G6PD deficiency [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



    5.2 Peripheral Neuropathy



  Peripheral neuropathy (motor loss and muscle weakness) has been reported with oral dapsone treatment. No events of peripheral neuropathy were observed in clinical trials with topical dapsone treatment.



    5.3 Skin Reactions



  Skin reactions (toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, morbilliform and scarlatiniform reactions, bullous and exfoliative dermatitis, erythema nodosum, and urticaria) have been reported with oral dapsone treatment. These types of skin reactions were not observed in clinical trials with topical dapsone treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
