<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="adcirca" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Visual Loss [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  
 *  Hearing loss [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Priapism [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reaction is headache. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-545 5979 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Tadalafil was administered to 398 patients with PAH during clinical trials worldwide. In trials of ADCIRCA, a total of 311 and 251 subjects have been treated for at least 182 days and 360 days, respectively. The overall rates of discontinuation because of an adverse event (AE) in the placebo-controlled trial were 9% for ADCIRCA 40 mg and 15% for placebo. The rates of discontinuation because of AEs, other than those related to worsening of PAH, in patients treated with ADCIRCA 40 mg was 4% compared to 5% in placebo-treated patients.



 In the placebo-controlled study, the most common AEs were generally transient and mild to moderate in intensity.  Table 1  presents treatment-emergent adverse events reported by &gt;=9% of patients in the ADCIRCA 40 mg group and occurring more frequently than with placebo.



 TABLE 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Reported by &gt;=9% of Patients in ADCIRCA and More Frequent than Placebo by 2% 
   EVENT                                      Placebo (%)    (N=82)      ADCIRCA 20 mg (%)    (N=82)      ADCIRCA 40 mg (%)    (N=79)     
 Headache                                   15                  32                    42                     
 Myalgia                                    4                   9                     14                     
 Nasopharyngitis                            7                   2                     13                     
 Flushing                                   2                   6                     13                     
 Respiratory Tract Infection (Upper and Lower)  6                   7                     13                     
 Pain in Extremity                          2                   5                     11                     
 Nausea                                     6                   10                    11                     
 Back Pain                                  6                   12                    10                     
 Dyspepsia                                  2                   13                    10                     
 Nasal Congestion (Including sinus congestion)  1                   0                     9                      
            6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of tadalafil. These events have been chosen for inclusion either because of their seriousness, reporting frequency, lack of clear alternative causation, or a combination of these factors. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate reliably their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The list does not include adverse events that are reported from clinical trials and that are listed elsewhere in this section.



   Cardiovascular and cerebrovascular  - Serious cardiovascular events, including myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death, stroke, chest pain, palpitations, and tachycardia, have been reported postmarketing in temporal association with the use of tadalafil. Most, but not all, of these patients had preexisting cardiovascular risk factors. Many of these events were reported to occur during or shortly after sexual activity, and a few were reported to occur shortly after the use of tadalafil without sexual activity. Others were reported to have occurred hours to days after the use of tadalafil and sexual activity. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to tadalafil, to sexual activity, to the patient's underlying cardiovascular disease, to a combination of these factors, or to other factors  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .



   Body as a whole  - Hypersensitivity reactions including urticaria, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and exfoliative dermatitis



   Nervous  - Migraine, seizure and seizure recurrence, and transient global amnesia



   Ophthalmologic  - Visual field defect, retinal vein occlusion, and retinal artery occlusion



   Otologic  - Cases of sudden decrease or loss of hearing have been reported postmarketing in temporal association with the use of PDE5 inhibitors, including tadalafil. In some of the cases, medical conditions and other factors were reported that may have also played a role in the otologic adverse events. In many cases, medical follow-up information was limited. It is not possible to determine whether these reported events are related directly to the use of tadalafil, to the patient's underlying risk factors for hearing loss, a combination of these factors, or to other factors  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



   Urogenital  - Priapism  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Cardiovascular effects: Carefully consider whether patients with certain underlying conditions (e.g., cardiovascular disease, impaired autonomic control of blood pressure, aortic stenosis) could be adversely affected by vasodilatory effects of ADCIRCA. Not recommended in patients with pulmonary veno-occlusive disease. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Concomitant alpha-blockers or alcohol: Note additive blood pressure-lowering effects. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Use with Ritonavir: Requires dosage adjustment. (  2.3  ,  5.2  ) 
 *  Other concomitant potent CYP3A inhibitors: Avoid use with ADCIRCA. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Potent Inducers of CYP3A: Avoid use of ADCIRCA in patients chronically taking potent inducers of CYP3A (e.g., rifampin). (  5.2  ,  7.2  ) 
 *  Effects on the eye: Patients should seek immediate medical attention if sudden loss of vision occurs, which could be a sign of non-arteritic ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION). (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hearing impairment: Advise patients to seek immediate medical attention if sudden decrease or loss of hearing occurs. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Concomitant PDE5 inhibitors: Avoid use with CIALIS or other PDE5 inhibitors. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Prolonged erection: Advise patients to seek emergency treatment if an erection lasts &gt;4 hours. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Effects



  Discuss with patients the appropriate action to take in the event that they experience anginal chest pain requiring nitroglycerin following intake of ADCIRCA. At least 48 hours should elapse after the last dose of ADCIRCA before taking nitrates. If a patient has taken ADCIRCA within 48 hours, administer nitrates under close medical supervision with appropriate hemodynamic monitoring. Patients who experience anginal chest pain after taking ADCIRCA should seek immediate medical attention.



 PDE5 inhibitors, including tadalafil, have mild systemic vasodilatory properties that may result in transient decreases in blood pressure. Prior to prescribing ADCIRCA, carefully consider whether patients with underlying cardiovascular disease could be affected adversely by such vasodilatory effects. Patients with severely impaired autonomic control of blood pressure or with left ventricular outflow obstruction, (e.g., aortic stenosis and idiopathic hypertrophic subaortic stenosis) may be particularly sensitive to the actions of vasodilators, including PDE5 inhibitors.



 Pulmonary vasodilators may significantly worsen the cardiovascular status of patients with pulmonary veno-occlusive disease (PVOD). Since there are no clinical data on administration of ADCIRCA to patients with veno-occlusive disease, administration of ADCIRCA to such patients is not recommended. Should signs of pulmonary edema occur when ADCIRCA is administered, the possibility of associated PVOD should be considered.



 There is a lack of data on safety and efficacy in the following groups who were specifically excluded from the PAH clinical trials:



 *  Patients with clinically significant aortic and mitral valve disease 
 *  Patients with pericardial constriction 
 *  Patients with restrictive or congestive cardiomyopathy 
 *  Patients with significant left ventricular dysfunction 
 *  Patients with life-threatening arrhythmias 
 *  Patients with symptomatic coronary artery disease 
 *  Patients with hypotension (&lt;90/50 mm Hg) or uncontrolled hypertension 
       Use with Alpha Blockers and Antihypertensives  
 

 PDE5 inhibitors, including ADCIRCA, and alpha-adrenergic blocking agents are vasodilators with blood pressure-lowering effects. When vasodilators are used in combination, an additive effect on blood pressure may be anticipated. In some patients, concomitant use of these two drug classes can lower blood pressure significantly [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  , which may lead to symptomatic hypotension (e.g., fainting). Safety of combined use of PDE5 inhibitors and alpha blockers may be affected by other variables, including intravascular volume depletion and use of other antihypertensive drugs [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



    Use with Alcohol  



 Both alcohol and tadalafil are mild vasodilators. When mild vasodilators are taken in combination, blood pressure-lowering effects are increased [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  .



    5.2 Use with Potent CYP3A Inhibitors or Inducers



   Co-administration of ADCIRCA in Patients on Ritonavir  



 In patients receiving ritonavir for at least one week, start ADCIRCA at 20 mg once daily. Increase to 40 mg once daily based upon individual tolerability [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ), Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    Co-administration of Ritonavir in Patients on ADCIRCA  



 Avoid use of ADCIRCA during the initiation of ritonavir. Stop ADCIRCA at least 24 hours prior to starting ritonavir. After at least one week following the initiation of ritonavir, resume ADCIRCA at 20 mg once daily. Increase to 40 mg once daily based upon individual tolerability [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ), Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    Other Potent Inhibitors of CYP3A  



 Tadalafil is metabolized predominantly by CYP3A in the liver. In patients taking potent inhibitors of CYP3A such as ketoconazole and itraconazole, avoid use of ADCIRCA [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    Potent Inducers of CYP3A  



 For patients chronically taking potent inducers of CYP3A, such as rifampin, avoid use of ADCIRCA [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    5.3 Use in Renal Impairment



   In patients with mild or moderate renal impairment  



 Start dosing at 20 mg once daily. Increase the dose to 40 mg once daily based upon individual tolerability [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    In patients with severe renal impairment  



 Avoid use of ADCIRCA because of increased tadalafil exposure (AUC), limited clinical experience, and the lack of ability to influence clearance by dialysis [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    5.4 Use in Hepatic Impairment



   In patients with mild to moderate hepatic cirrhosis (Child-Pugh Class A and B)  



 Because of limited clinical experience in patients with mild to moderate hepatic cirrhosis, consider a starting dose of 20 mg once daily ADCIRCA [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    In patients with severe hepatic cirrhosis (Child-Pugh Class C)  



 Patients with severe hepatic cirrhosis have not been studied. Avoid use of ADCIRCA [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    5.5 Visual Loss



  Physicians should advise patients to seek immediate medical attention in the event of a sudden loss of vision in one or both eyes. Such an event may be a sign of non-arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION), a cause of decreased vision, including permanent loss of vision, that has been reported postmarketing in temporal association with the use of all PDE5 inhibitors. Most, but not all, of these patients had underlying anatomic or vascular risk factors for development of NAION, including but not necessarily limited to: low cup to disc ratio ("crowded disc"), age over 50, diabetes, hypertension, coronary artery disease, hyperlipidemia, and smoking. Based on published literature, the annual incidence of NAION is 2.5-11.8 cases per 100,000 in males aged &gt;=50 in the general population. An observational study evaluated whether recent episodic use of PDE5 inhibitors, as a class, typical of erectile dysfunction treatment, was associated with acute onset of NAION. The results suggest an approximate 2-fold increase in the risk of NAION within 1 to 4 days of PDE5 inhibitor use.



 It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of PDE5 inhibitors or other factors. Physicians should also discuss with patients the increased risk of NAION in individuals who have already experienced NAION in one eye, including whether such individuals could be adversely affected by use of vasodilators such as PDE5 inhibitors.



 Patients with known hereditary degenerative retinal disorders, including retinitis pigmentosa, were not included in the clinical trials, and use in these patients is not recommended.



    5.6 Hearing Impairment



  Physicians should advise patients to seek immediate medical attention in the event of sudden decrease or loss of hearing. These events, which may be accompanied by tinnitus and dizziness, have been reported in temporal association to the intake of PDE5 inhibitors, including ADCIRCA. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of PDE5 inhibitors or to other factors [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )]  .



    5.7 Combination with Other PDE5 Inhibitors



  Tadalafil is also marketed as CIALIS. The safety and efficacy of taking ADCIRCA together with CIALIS or other PDE5 inhibitors have not been studied. Inform patients taking ADCIRCA not to take CIALIS or other PDE5 inhibitors.



    5.8 Prolonged Erection



  There have been rare reports of prolonged erections greater than 4 hours and priapism (painful erections greater than 6 hours in duration) for this class of compounds. Priapism, if not treated promptly, can result in irreversible damage to the erectile tissue. Patients who have an erection lasting greater than 4 hours, whether painful or not, should seek emergency medical attention.



 ADCIRCA should be used with caution in patients who have conditions that might predispose them to priapism (such as sickle cell anemia, multiple myeloma, or leukemia), or in patients with anatomical deformation of the penis (such as angulation, cavernosal fibrosis, or Peyronie's disease).



    5.9 Effects on Bleeding



  PDE5 is found in platelets. When administered in combination with aspirin, tadalafil 20 mg did not prolong bleeding time, relative to aspirin alone. ADCIRCA has not been administered to patients with bleeding disorders or significant active peptic ulceration. Although ADCIRCA has not been shown to increase bleeding times in healthy subjects, use in patients with bleeding disorders or significant active peptic ulceration should be based upon a careful risk-benefit assessment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
