<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="addyi" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Hypotension and Syncope [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1,     5.3  ,   5.5  ,   5.6)  ]  
 *    CNS Depression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
      EXCERPT:     Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2%) are dizziness, somnolence, nausea, fatigue, insomnia, and dry mouth.    (6.1)      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sprout Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-844-746-5745, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The approved 100 mg ADDYI dosage at bedtime was administered to 2,997 premenopausal women with acquired, generalized HSDD in clinical trials, of whom 1672 received treatment for at least 6 months, 850 received treatment for at least 12 months, and 88 received treatment for at least 18 months  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ].  



   Data from Five 24-Week, Randomized, Double-Blind Placebo-Controlled Trials in Premenopausal Women with HSDD  The data presented below are derived from five 24-week randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials in premenopausal women with acquired, generalized HSDD. In these five trials, the frequency and quantity of alcohol use was not recorded. Three of these trials (Studies 1 through 3) also provided efficacy data  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ].  One of these trials (Study 5) did not evaluate the 100 mg bedtime dose.



 In four trials, 100 mg ADDYI at bedtime was administered to 1543 premenopausal women with HSDD, of whom 1060 completed 24 weeks of treatment. The clinical trial population was generally healthy without significant comorbid medical conditions or concomitant medications. The age range was 18-56 years old with a mean age of 36 years old, and 88% were Caucasian and 9% were Black.



 Serious adverse reactions were reported in 0.9% and 0.5% of ADDYI-treated patients and placebo-treated patients, respectively.



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  The discontinuation rate due to adverse reactions was 13% among patients treated with 100 mg ADDYI at bedtime and 6% among patients treated with placebo.  Table 1  displays the most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in four trials of premenopausal women with HSDD.



 Table 1. Adverse ReactionsAdverse reactions leading to discontinuation of &gt;=1% of patients receiving 100 mg ADDYI at bedtime and at a higher incidence than placebo-treated patients. Leading to Discontinuation in Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Trials in Premenopausal Women with HSDD 
                                Placebo (N=1556)            ADDYI (N=1543)              
     Dizziness                  0.1%                        1.7%                        
     Nausea                     0.1%                        1.2%                        
     Insomnia                   0.2%                        1.1%                        
     Somnolence                  0.3%                       1.1%                        
     Anxiety                     0.3%                        1%                         
           Most Common Adverse Reactions    Table 2  summarizes the most common adverse reactions reported in four trials of premenopausal women with HSDD. This table shows adverse reactions reported in at least 2% of patients treated with ADDYI and at a higher incidence than with placebo  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].   The majority of these adverse reactions began within the first 14 days of treatment.
 

 Table 2. Common Adverse ReactionsAdverse reactions reported in &gt;=2% of patients receiving 100 mg ADDYI at bedtime and at a higher incidence than placebo-treated patients. in Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Trials in Premenopausal Women with HSDD 
                                Placebo(N=1556)             ADDYI(N=1543)               
     Dizziness                  2.2%                        11.4%                       
     Somnolence                 2.9%                        11.2%                       
     Nausea                     3.9%                        10.4%                       
     Fatigue                     5.5%                       9.2%                        
     Insomnia                    2.8%                       4.9%                        
     Dry mouth                   1.0%                       2.4%                        
           Less Common Adverse Reactions  In four trials in premenopausal women with HSDD treated with 100 mg ADDYI at bedtime, less common adverse reactions (reported in &gt;=1% but &lt;2% of ADDYI-treated patients and at a higher incidence than with placebo) included:
 

 *    Anxiety (ADDYI 1.8%; placebo 1.0%), 
 *    Constipation (ADDYI 1.6%; placebo 0.4%), 
 *    Abdominal pain (ADDYI 1.5%; placebo 0.9%), 
 *    Metrorrhagia (ADDYI 1.4%; placebo 1.4%), 
 *    Rash (ADDYI 1.3%; placebo 0.8%), 
 *    Sedation (ADDYI 1.3%; placebo 0.2%), and 
 *    Vertigo (ADDYI 1%; placebo 0.3%). 
      Appendicitis  In the five trials of premenopausal women with HSDD, appendicitis was reported in 6/3973 (0.2%) flibanserin-treated patients, while there were no reports of appendicitis in the 1905 placebo-treated patients.
 

   Accidental Injury  In five trials of premenopausal women with HSDD, accidental injury was reported in 42/1543 (2.7%) ADDYI-treated patients and 47/1905 (2.5%) placebo-treated patients. Among these 89 patients who experienced injuries, 9/42 (21%) ADDYI-treated patients and 3/47 (6%) placebo-treated patients reported adverse reactions consistent with CNS depression (e.g., somnolence, fatigue, or sedation) within the preceding 24 hours.



   Adverse Reactions in Patients Who Reported Hormonal Contraceptive Use  In four trials of premenopausal women with HSDD, 1466 patients (43%) reported concomitant use of hormonal contraceptives (HC) at study enrollment. These trials were not prospectively designed to assess an interaction between ADDYI and HC. ADDYI-treated patients who reported HC use had a greater incidence of dizziness, somnolence, and fatigue compared to ADDYI-treated patients who did not report HC use (dizziness 9.9% in HC non-users, 13.4% in HC users; somnolence 10.6% in HC non-users, 12.3% in HC users; fatigue 7.5% in HC non-users, 11.4% in HC users). There were no meaningful differences in the incidence of these adverse reactions in placebo-treated patients who reported or did not report HC use  [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  



   Data from Other Trials  



 One death occurred in a 54 year-old postmenopausal woman treated with 100 mg ADDYI taken at bedtime (ADDYI is not approved for the treatment of postmenopausal women with HSDD)  [see  Indications and Usage (1)  ]  . This patient had a history of hypertension and hypercholesterolemia and baseline alcohol consumption of 1-3 drinks daily. She died of acute alcohol intoxication 14 days after starting ADDYI. Blood alcohol concentration on autopsy was 0.289 g/dL. The autopsy report also noted coronary artery disease. A relationship between this patient's death and use of ADDYI is unknown  [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



   Hypotension, Syncope, and CNS Depression in Studies of Healthy Subjects  



   Hypotension, Syncope, and CNS Depression with Alcohol  In a cross-over alcohol interaction study of 100 mg ADDYI and alcohol in 25 healthy subjects dosed in the morning  [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ],   somnolence was reported in 67%, 74%, and 92% of subjects who received ADDYI alone, ADDYI in combination with 0.4 g/kg ethanol, and ADDYI in combination with 0.8 g/kg ethanol, respectively. In the group receiving ADDYI in combination with 0.4 g/kg ethanol, 4/23 (17%) subjects had substantial reductions in blood pressure, resulting in hypotension and/or syncope requiring medical intervention. In the group receiving ADDYI in combination with 0.8 g/kg ethanol, 6/24 (25%) subjects experienced orthostatic hypotension  [see  Boxed Warning,     Contraindications (4),     Warnings and Precautions (5.1,     5.3)  ].  



   Hypotension and Syncope with Fluconazole  In a pharmacokinetic drug interaction study of 100 mg ADDYI and 200 mg fluconazole (a moderate CYP3A4 inhibitor, moderate CYP2C9 inhibitor, and a strong CYP2C19 inhibitor) in healthy subjects, hypotension or syncope requiring placement supine with legs elevated occurred in 3/15 (20%) subjects treated with concomitant ADDYI and fluconazole compared to no such adverse reactions in subjects treated with ADDYI alone or fluconazole alone. One of these 3 subjects became unresponsive with a blood pressure of 64/41 mm Hg and required transportation to the hospital emergency department where she required intravenous saline. Due to these adverse reactions, the study was stopped. In this study, the concomitant use of ADDYI and fluconazole increased flibanserin exposure 7-fold  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ,  Drug Interactions (7)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



   Syncope with Ketoconazole  In a pharmacokinetic drug interaction study of 50 mg flibanserin and 400 mg ketoconazole, a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor, syncope occurred in 1/24 (4%) healthy subjects treated with concomitant flibanserin and ketoconazole, 1/24 (4%) receiving flibanserin alone, and no subjects receiving ketoconazole alone. In this study, the concomitant use of flibanserin and ketoconazole increased flibanserin exposure 4.5-fold  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ,  Drug Interactions (7)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



   Syncope in Poor CYP2C19 Metabolizers  In a pharmacogenomic study of 100 mg ADDYI in subjects who were poor or extensive CYP2C19 metabolizers, syncope occurred in 1/9 (11%) subjects who were CYP2C19 poor metabolizers (this subject had a 3.2 fold higher flibanserin exposure compared to CYP2C19 extensive metabolizers) compared to no such adverse reactions in subjects who were CYP2C19 extensive metabolizers  [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.5)  ].  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: HYPOTENSION AND SYNCOPE IN CERTAIN SETTINGS

  WARNING: HYPOTENSION AND SYNCOPE IN CERTAIN SETTINGS

      Contraindicated with Alcohol      The use of ADDYI and alcohol increases the risk of severe hypotension and syncope    [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . Therefore, alcohol use is contraindicated in patients taking ADDYI    [see   Contraindications (4)]  .   Before prescribing ADDY I, assess the likelihood of the patient abstaining from alcohol, taking into account the patient's current and past drinking behavior, and other pertinent social and medical history. Counsel patients who are prescribed ADDYI about the importance of abstaining from alcohol use  .   Because of the increased risk of hypotension and syncope due to an interaction with alcohol, ADDYI is available only through a restricted program under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) called the ADDYI REMS Program    [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .  



     Contraindicated with Strong or Moderate CYP3A4 Inhibitors      The concomitant use of ADDYI and moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitors increase s flibanserin concentrations, which can cause severe hypotension and syncope    [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  . Therefore, the use of moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitors is contraindicated in patients taking ADDYI   [see   Contraindications (4)  ].    



     Contraindicated in Patients with Hepatic Impairment      The use of ADDYI in patients with hepatic impairment increases flibanserin concentrations, which can cause severe hypotension and syncope    [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  . Therefore, ADDYI is contraindicated in patients with hepatic impairment    [see   Contraindications (4)  ]  .   



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: HYPOTENSION AND SYNCOPE IN CERTAIN SETTINGS  See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Use of ADDYI and alcohol increases the risk of severe hypotension and syncope; therefore alcohol use is contraindicated. Before prescribing ADDYI, assess the likelihood of the patient abstaining from alcohol. Counsel patients prescribed ADDYI about the importance of abstaining from alcohol. (4, 5.1) 
 *  ADDYI is available only through a restricted program called the ADDYI REMS Program. (5.2) 
 *  Severe hypotension and syncope can occur when ADDYI is used with moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitors or in patients with hepatic impairment; therefore, ADDYI use in these settings is contraindicated. (4, 5.3, 5.6) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Hypotension and Syncope with ADDYI Alone : Patients with pre-syncope should immediately lie supine and promptly seek medical help if symptoms do not resolve.  (5.5)   
 *     Central Nervous System (CNS) Depression (e.g., Somnolence, Sedation) : Can occur with ADDYI alone. Exacerbated by other CNS depressants, and in settings where flibanserin concentrations are increased. Patients should avoid activities requiring full alertness (e.g., operating machinery or driving) until at least 6 hours after each dose and until they know how ADDYI affects them. Can occur with ADDYI alone. Exacerbated by other CNS depressants, and in settings where flibanserin concentrations are increased. Patients should avoid activities requiring full alertness (e.g., operating machinery or driving) until at least 6 hours after each dose and until they know how ADDYI affects them.   (5.4)   
    
 

   5.1 Hypotension and Syncope due to an Interaction with Alcohol



   Alcohol use is contraindicated in patients taking ADDYI. Before prescribing ADDYI, the healthcare provider must assess the likelihood of the patient abstaining from alcohol use, taking into account the patient's current and past drinking behavior, and other pertinent social and medical history. Counsel patients who are prescribed ADDYI about the importance of abstaining from alcohol use [ see  Drug Interactions (7)  ].    



 The use of ADDYI and alcohol increases the risk of severe hypotension and syncope. In a dedicated alcohol interaction study conducted in 25 subjects (23 men and 2 premenopausal women), hypotension or syncope requiring therapeutic intervention (ammonia salts and/or placement in supine or Trendelenberg position) occurred in 4 (17%) of the 23 subjects co-administered ADDYI 100 mg and 0.4 g/kg alcohol (equivalent of two 12 ounce cans of beer containing 5% alcohol content, two 5 ounce glasses of wine containing 12% alcohol content, or two 1.5 ounce shots of 80-proof spirit in a 70 kg person, consumed over 10 minutes in the morning)   [see    Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)   ]  . In these four subjects, all of whom were men, the magnitude of the systolic blood pressure reductions ranged from about 28 to 54 mmHg and the magnitude of the diastolic blood pressure reductions ranged from about 24 to 46 mmHg. In addition, 6 (25%) of the 24 subjects co-administered ADDYI 100 mg and 0.8 g/kg alcohol experienced orthostatic hypotension when standing from a sitting position. The magnitude of the systolic blood pressure reductions in these 6 subjects ranged from 22 to 48 mmHg, and the diastolic blood pressure reductions ranged from 0 to 27 mmHg. One of these subjects required therapeutic intervention (ammonia salts and placement supine with the foot of the bed elevated). There were no events requiring therapeutic interventions when ADDYI or alcohol were administered alone.



 ADDYI is available only through a restricted program under a REMS [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  



    5.2 ADDYI REMS Program



  ADDYI is available only through a restricted program under a REMS called the ADDYI REMS Program, because of the increased risk of severe hypotension and syncope due to an interaction between ADDYI and alcohol [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



 Notable requirements of the ADDYI REMS Program include the following:



 *    Prescribers must be certified with the program by enrolling and completing training. 
 *    Pharmacies must be certified with the program and must only dispense to patients pursuant to a prescription from a certified prescriber. 
    Further information, including a list of qualified pharmacies, is available at www.AddyiREMS.com or 844-746-5745.
 

    5.3 Hypotension and Syncope with CYP3A4 Inhibitors



   Moderate or Strong CYP3A4 Inhibitors  



 The concomitant use of ADDYI with moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitors significantly increases flibanserin concentrations, which can lead to hypotension and syncope [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  The concomitant use of ADDYI with a moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitor is contraindicated. If the patient requires a moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitor, discontinue ADDYI at least 2 days prior to starting the moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitor. In cases where the benefit of initiating a moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitor within 2 days of stopping ADDYI clearly outweighs the risk of flibanserin exposure related hypotension and syncope, monitor the patient for signs of hypotension and syncope. Discontinue the moderate or strong CYP3A4 inhibitor for 2 weeks before restarting ADDYI [See  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  



   Multiple Concomitant Weak CYP3A4 Inhibitors    Concomitant use of multiple weak CYP3A4 inhibitors that may include herbal supplements (e.g., ginkgo, resveratrol) or non-prescription drugs (e.g., cimetidine) could also lead to clinically relevant increases in flibanserin concentrations that may increase the risk of hypotension and syncope [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .
 

    5.4 Central Nervous System Depression



  ADDYI can cause CNS depression (e.g., somnolence, sedation). In five 24-week, randomized, placebo controlled, double-blind trials of premenopausal women with HSDD, the incidence of somnolence, sedation or fatigue was 21% and 8% in patients treated with 100 mg ADDYI once daily at bedtime and placebo, respectively [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  and  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  . The risk of CNS depression is increased if ADDYI is taken during waking hours, or if ADDYI is taken with alcohol or other CNS depressants, or with medications that increase flibanserin concentrations, such as CYP3A4 inhibitors [see  Contraindications (4),     Warnings and Precautions (5.1,     5.3)  ,  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  , and  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  



 Patients should not drive or engage in other activities requiring full alertness until at least 6 hours after taking ADDYI and until they know how ADDYI affects them [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  



    5.5 Hypotension and Syncope with ADDYI Alone



  The use of ADDYI - without other concomitant medications known to cause hypotension or syncope - can cause hypotension and syncope. In five 24-week, randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind trials of premenopausal women with HSDD, hypotension was reported in 0.2% and &lt;0.1% of ADDYI-treated patients and placebo-treated patients, respectively; syncope was reported in 0.4% and 0.2% of ADDYI- treated patients and placebo-treated patients, respectively. The risk of hypotension and syncope is increased if ADDYI is taken during waking hours or if higher than the recommended dose is taken [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1,    5.3)  ,  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ,  Drug Interactions (7)  , and  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  ].  Consider the benefits of ADDYI and the risks of hypotension and syncope in patients with pre- existing conditions that predispose to hypotension. Patients who experience pre-syncope should immediately lie supine and promptly seek medical help if the symptoms do not resolve. Prompt medical attention should also be obtained for patients who experience syncope.



    5.6 Syncope and Hypotension in Patients with Hepatic Impairment



  The use of ADDYI in patients with any degree of hepatic impairment significantly increases flibanserin concentrations, which can lead to hypotension and syncope. Therefore, the use of ADDYI is contraindicated in patients with hepatic impairment [see  Contraindications (4),     Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.7 Mammary Tumors in Female Mice



  In a 2-year carcinogenicity study in mice, there was a statistically significant and dose-related increase in the incidence of malignant mammary tumors in female mice at exposures 3 and 10 times the recommended clinical dose. No such increases were seen in male mice or in male or female rats [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)]    . The clinical significance of these findings is unknown.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
