<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="adenocard" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    Adverse Reactions

  The following reactions were reported with intravenous Adenocard (adenosine injection) used in controlled U.S. clinical trials. The placebo group had less than 1% rate of all of these reactions.



   Cardiovascular

  Facial flushing (18%), headache (2%), sweating, palpitations, chest pain, hypotension (less than 1%).



   Respiratory

  Shortness of breath/dyspnea (12%), chest pressure (7%), hyperventilation, head pressure (less than 1%).



   Central Nervous System

  Lightheadedness (2%), dizziness, tingling in arms, numbness (1%), apprehension, blurred vision, burning sensation, heaviness in arms, neck and back pain (less than 1%).



   Gastrointestinal

  Nausea (3%), metallic taste, tightness in throat, pressure in groin (less than 1%).



   Post Marketing Experience (see Warnings)

  The following adverse events have been reported from marketing experience with Adenocard. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, are associated with concomitant diseases and multiple drug therapies and surgical procedures, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these events in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the event, (2) frequency of the reporting, (3) strength of causal connection to the drug, or a combination of these factors.



   Cardiovascular

  Prolonged asystole, ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, transient increase in blood pressure, bradycardia, atrial fibrillation, and Torsade de Pointes



   Respiratory

  Bronchospasm



   Central Nervous System

  Seizure activity, including tonic clonic (grand mal) seizures, and loss of consciousness.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
