<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="adenoscan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *    Fatal Cardiac Arrest, Ventricular Arrhythmias, and Myocardial Infarction [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.1  )]  
 *    Sinoatrial and Atrioventricular Nodal Block [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.2  )]  
 *    Bronchoconstriction [see     Warnings and Precautions     (  5.3  )]  
 *    Hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  )]  
 *    Cerebrovascular Accident [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.5  )]  
 *    Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.6  )]  
 *    Hypersensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.7  )]  
 *    Atrial Fibrillation [see  Warnings and Precautions   (  5.8  )]  
 *    Hypertension [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.9  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 10%) are: flushing; chest discomfort; shortness of breath; headache; throat, neck or jaw discomfort; gastrointestinal discomfort; and dizziness (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Astellas Pharma US, Inc. at 1-800-727-7003 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The following adverse reactions, with an incidence of at least 1%, were reported with Adenoscan among 1,421 patients in clinical trials. Eleven percent (11%) of the adverse reactions occurred several hours after Adenoscan administration. Eight percent (8%) of the adverse reactions began with Adenoscan infusion and persisted for up to 24 hours.



 The most common (incidence &gt;= 10%) adverse reactions to Adenoscan are flushing, chest discomfort, shortness of breath, headache, throat, neck or jaw discomfort, gastrointestinal discomfort, and dizziness (  Table 2  ).



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials (Frequency &gt;= 1%) 
   Adverse Reactions                       Adenoscan    N=1,421       
  
  Flushing                                44%                         
  Chest discomfort                        40%                         
  Dyspnea                                 28%                         
  Headache                                18%                         
  Throat, neck or jaw discomfort          15%                         
  Gastrointestinal discomfort             13%                         
  Lightheadedness/dizziness               12%                         
  Upper extremity discomfort              4%                          
  ST segment depression                   3%                          
  First-degree AV block                   3%                          
  Second-degree AV block                  3%                          
  Paresthesia                             2%                          
  Hypotension                             2%                          
  Nervousness                             2%                          
  Arrhythmias                             1%                          
        Adverse reactions to Adenoscan of any severity reported in less than 1% of patients include:
 

 Body as a Whole:                     back discomfort, lower extremity discomfort, weaknessCardiovascular System:           myocardial infarction, ventricular arrhythmia, third-degree AV block,                                                 bradycardia, palpitation, sinus exit block, sinus pause, T-wave changes,                                                 hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt; 200 mm Hg)Respiratory System:                 coughCentral Nervous System:         drowsiness, emotional instability, tremorsGenital/Urinary System:          vaginal pressure, urgencySpecial Senses:                         blurred vision, dry mouth, ear discomfort, metallic taste, nasal                                                 congestion, scotomas, tongue discomfort



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported from marketing experience with Adenoscan. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, are associated with concomitant diseases and multiple drug therapies and surgical procedures, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Cardiac Disorders:                                                              cardiac arrest, atrial fibrillation, cardiac failure,                                                                                            myocardial infarction, tachycardia, ventricular arrhythmiaGastrointestinal Disorders:                                                 nausea and vomitingGeneral Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:   chest pain, injection site reaction, infusion site painImmune System Disorders:                                                hypersensitivityNervous System Disorders:                                                cerebrovascular accident including intracranial hemorrhage,                                                                                            seizure activity including tonic-clonic (grand mal) seizures, loss                                                                                            of consciousnessRespiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:             bronchospasm, respiratory arrest, throat tightness
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Cardiac Arrest, Ventricular Arrhythmias, and Myocardial Infarction . Fatal cardiac events have occurred. Avoid use in patients with symptoms or signs of acute myocardial ischemia. Appropriate resuscitative measures should be available (  5.1  ) 
 *     Sinoatrial (SA) and Atrioventricular (AV) Nodal Block . First-, second- or third-degree AV block, or sinus bradycardia can occur. Discontinue Adenoscan if patient develops persistent or symptomatic high-grade AV block (  5.2  ) 
 *     Bronchoconstriction . Can induce dyspnea, bronchoconstriction, and respiratory compromise, especially in patients with obstructive pulmonary disease. Discontinue Adenoscan if patient develops severe respiratory difficulties (  5.3  ) 
 *     Hypotension . Significant hypotension can occur. Discontinue Adenoscan if patient develops persistent or symptomatic hypotension (  5.4  ) 
 *     Cerebrovascular Accidents . Hemorrhagic and ischemic cerebrovascular accidents have occurred (  5.5  ) 
 *     Seizures . New onset or recurrence of convulsive seizures have occurred. Use of methylxanthines (e.g., caffeine, aminophylline and theophylline) is not recommended in patients who experience seizures in association with Adenoscan (  5.6  ) 
 *     Hypersensitivity. Dyspnea, throat tightness, flushing, erythema, rash, and chest discomfort have occurred. Have personnel and resuscitative equipment immediately available (  5.7  ) 
 *     Atrial Fibrillation . Reported in patients with or without a history of atrial fibrillation (  5.8  ) 
 *     Hypertension . Clinically significant increases in systolic and diastolic pressure have been observed (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiac Arrest, Ventricular Arrhythmias, and Myocardial Infarction



   Fatal and nonfatal cardiac arrest, sustained ventricular tachycardia (requiring resuscitation), and myocardial infarction have occurred following Adenoscan infusion. Avoid use in patients with symptoms or signs of acute myocardial ischemia, for example, unstable angina or cardiovascular instability; these patients may be at greater risk of serious cardiovascular reactions to Adenoscan. Appropriate resuscitative measures should be available [see      Overdosage  (  10  )]  .  



    5.2 Sinoatrial and Atrioventricular Nodal Block



  Adenoscan exerts a direct depressant effect on the SA and AV nodes and may cause first-, second- or third-degree AV block, or sinus bradycardia. In clinical trials, approximately 6% of patients developed AV block following Adenoscan administration (first-degree heart block developed in 3%, second-degree in 3%, and third-degree in 0.8% of patients) [see  Clinical Trials Experience  (  6.1  )]  .



 Use Adenoscan with caution in patients with pre-existing first-degree AV block or bundle branch block. Do not use in patients with high-grade AV block or sinus node dysfunction (except in patients with a functioning artificial pacemaker). Discontinue Adenoscan in any patient who develops persistent or symptomatic high-grade AV block.



    5.3 Bronchoconstriction



  Adenoscan administration can cause dyspnea, bronchoconstriction, and respiratory compromise. Adenoscan should be used with caution in patients with obstructive lung disease not associated with bronchoconstriction (e.g., emphysema, bronchitis). Do not use in patients with bronchoconstriction or bronchospasm (e.g., asthma). Discontinue Adenoscan in any patient who develops severe respiratory difficulties. Resuscitative measures should be available prior to Adenoscan administration [see  Clinical Trials Experience  (  6.1  ),  Overdosage  (  10  ), and  Clinical Pharmacology  (  12.2  )].  



    5.4 Hypotension



  Adenoscan is a potent peripheral vasodilator and can induce significant hypotension. The risk of serious hypotension may be higher in patients with autonomic dysfunction, hypovolemia, stenotic valvular heart disease, pericarditis or pericardial effusions, or stenotic carotid artery disease with cerebrovascular insufficiency. Discontinue Adenoscan in any patient who develops persistent or symptomatic hypotension.



    5.5 Cerebrovascular Accident



   Hemorrhagic and ischemic cerebrovascular accidents have occurred. Hemodynamic effects of Adenoscan including hypotension or hypertension can be associated with these adverse reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  ) and (  5.9  )].    



    5.6 Seizures



   New-onset or recurrence of convulsive seizures has occurred following Adenoscan. Some seizures are prolonged and require emergent anticonvulsive management. Aminophylline may increase the risk of seizures associated with Adenoscan. Methylxanthine use is not recommended in patients who experience seizures in association with Adenoscan administration [see  Overdosage  (  10  )].    



    5.7 Hypersensitivity



   Dyspnea, throat tightness, flushing, erythema, rash, and chest discomfort have occurred. Symptomatic treatment may be required. Have personnel and appropriate treatment available. Resuscitative measures may be necessary if symptoms progress [see  Post-Marketing Experience  (  6.2  )].    



    5.8 Atrial Fibrillation



  Adenoscan can cause atrial fibrillation in patients with or without a history of atrial fibrillation. Atrial fibrillation typically began 1.5 to 3 minutes after initiation of Adenoscan, lasted for 15 seconds to 6 hours, and spontaneously converted to normal sinus rhythm [see  Post-Marketing Experience  (  6.2  )]  .



    5.9 Hypertension



  Adenoscan can induce clinically significant increases in systolic and diastolic blood pressure. Most increases resolved spontaneously within several minutes, but in some cases, hypertension lasted for several hours [see  Clinical Trials Experience  (  6.1  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
