<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="advate" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions seen with ADVATE are hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, and the development of high-titer inhibitors necessitating alternative treatments to factor VIII.



 The most common adverse reactions observed in clinical trials (frequency greater than 5% of subjects) were pyrexia, headache, cough, and nasopharyngitis, arthralgia, vomiting, upper respiratory tract infection, limb injury, nasal congestion, and diarrhea.



    EXCERPT:    *    Serious adverse drug reactions reported are hypersensitivity and factor VIII inhibitors. (6.1) 
 *    The most common adverse drug reactions observed in greater than 5% of patients are pyrexia, headache, cough, and nasopharyngitis, arthralgia, vomiting, upper respiratory tract infection, limb injury, nasal congestion and diarrhea. (6.1) 
    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare Corporation at 1-866-888-2472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 ADVATE has been evaluated in eleven clinical trials in previously treated patients (PTPs) and one trial in previously untreated patients (PUPs) with severe to moderately severe hemophilia A (factor VIII &lt;=2% of normal). A total of 418 subjects have been treated with ADVATE as of January 2012. Total exposure to ADVATE was 63,188 infusions. The median duration of participation per subject was 397 (min-max: 2 -1620) days and the median number of exposure days to ADVATE per subject was 97 (min-max: -709).



 The summary of adverse reactions with a frequency &gt;5% are shown in Table 3 below.



 No subject was withdrawn from a clinical trial due to an adverse reaction.



 Table 3 Summary of Adverse Reactions (ARs)1 with a Frequency Greater than 5% in 418 Subjects 
  MedDRAMedDRA version 8.1 was used. System Organ Class    MedDRA Preferred Term    Number of Adverse Reactions    Number of Subjects    Percent of Subjects    
  General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions    Pyrexia                 110           66             16            
  Nervous System Disorders               Headache                114           56             13            
  Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders    Cough                   86            54             13            
  Infections And Infestations            Nasopharyngitis         72            49             12            
  Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders    Arthralgia              49            32             8             
  Gastrointestinal Disorders             Vomiting                41            31             7             
  Infections And Infestations            Upper Respiratory Tract Infection    35            29             7             
  Injury, Poisoning And Procedural Complications    Limb Injury             56            25             6             
  Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders    Nasal Congestion        32            25             6             
  Gastrointestinal Disorders             Diarrhea                29            24             6             
  Injury, Poisoning And Procedural Complications    Procedural Pain         26            22             5             
  Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders    Oropharyngeal Pain      25            22             5             
  Infections And Infestations            Ear Infection           30            21             5             
             Immunogenicity  
 

 The development of factor VIII inhibitors with the use of ADVATE was evaluated in clinical trials with pediatric PTPs (&lt;6 years of age with &gt;=50 factor VIII exposures) and PTPs (  &gt;  10 years of age with &gt;=150 factor VIII exposures). Of 276 subjects who were treated with ADVATE for at least 10 exposure days or on study for a minimum of 120 days, 1 adult developed a low-titer inhibitor (2 BU in the Bethesda assay) after 26 exposure days. Eight weeks later, the inhibitor was no longer detectable, and  in vivo  recovery was normal at 1 and 3 hours after infusion of another marketed recombinant factor VIII concentrate. This event results in a factor VIII inhibitor frequency in PTPs of 0.4% (95% CI of 0.01 and 2% for the risk of any factor VIII inhibitor development).  3  No factor VIII inhibitors were detected in the 53 treated pediatric PTPs.



 In clinical trials that enrolled previously untreated subjects (defined as having had up to 3 exposures to a factor VIII product at the time of enrollment) , 16 (29.1%) of 55 subjects who received ADVATE developed inhibitors to factor VIII. Seven subjects developed high titer (&gt;5 BU) and nine subjects developed low-titer inhibitors. Inhibitors were detected at a median of 13 exposure days (min-max: 6 -26 exposure days) to the product.



 Immunogenicity also was evaluated by measuring the development of antibodies to heterologous proteins. When assessed for anti-Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cell protein antibodies, of 229 treated subjects, 3 showed an upward trend in antibody titer over time and 10 showed repeated but transient elevations of antibodies. When assessed for muIgG protein antibodies, of the 229 treated subjects, 10 showed an upward trend in anti-muIgG antibody titer over time and 2 showed repeated but transient elevations of antibodies. Four subjects who demonstrated antibody elevations to CHO cell or muIgG proteins, reported isolated events of urticaria, pruritus, rash, and slightly elevated eosinophil counts. All of these subjects had numerous repeat exposures to the product without recurrence of the events and a causal relationship between the antibody findings and these clinical events has not been established.



 When assessed for the presence of anti-human von Willebrand Factor (VWF) antibodies, of the 228 treated subjects, none displayed laboratory evidence indicative of a positive serologic response.



 The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to ADVATE with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ADVATE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Table 4 represents the most frequently reported post-marketing adverse reactions as MedDRA Preferred Terms.



 Table 4 Post-Marketing Experience 
  Organ System [MedDRA Primary SOC]                         Preferred Term                                
  Immune system disorders                                   Anaphylactic reactionThese reactions have been manifested by dizziness, paresthesias, rash, flushing, face swelling, urticaria, and/or pruritus.Hypersensitivity    
  Blood and lymphatic system disorders                      Factor VIII inhibition                        
  General disorders and administration site conditions      Injection site reaction  Chills  Fatigue/Malaise  Chest discomfort/pain  Decreased therapeutic effect    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis may occur. Patients may develop hypersensitivity to mouse or hamster protein, which is present in trace amounts in the product. Should symptoms occur, discontinue treatment with ADVATE and administer appropriate treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Development of activity-neutralizing antibodies may occur. If expected plasma factor VIII activity levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with an appropriate dose, perform an assay that measures factor VIII inhibitor concentration. (  5.2  ,  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Allergic-type hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have been reported with ADVATE. Symptoms include dizziness, paresthesia, rash, flushing, facial swelling, urticaria, dyspnea, pruritus, and vomiting.



 ADVATE contains trace amounts of mouse immunoglobulin G (MuIgG) &lt;=0.1 ng/IU ADVATE, and hamster proteins &lt;=1.5 ng/IU ADVATE. Patients treated with this product may develop hypersensitivity to these non-human mammalian proteins.



 Discontinue ADVATE if hypersensitivity symptoms occur and administer appropriate emergency treatment.



    5.2 Neutralizing Antibodies



  Neutralizing antibodies (inhibitors) have been reported following administration of ADVATE predominantly in previously untreated patients (PUPs) and previously minimally treated patients (MTPs). Monitor all patients for the development of factor VIII inhibitors by appropriate clinical observation and laboratory testing. If expected plasma factor VIII activity levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with an expected dose, perform an assay that measures factor VIII inhibitor concentration. [see Warnings and Precautions  (  5.3  )]



    5.3 Monitoring Laboratory Tests



    *    Monitor plasma factor VIII activity levels by the one-stage clotting assay to confirm the adequate factor VIII levels have been achieved and maintained when clinically indicated. [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )] 
 *    *  o  If the inhibitor titer is less than 10 BU per mL, the administration of additional antihemophilic factor concentrate may neutralize the inhibitor and may permit an appropriate hemostatic response. 
 *  o  If the inhibitor titer is above 10 BU per mL, adequate hemostasis may not be achieved. The inhibitor titer may rise following ADVATE infusion as a result of an anamnestic response to factor VIII. The treatment or prevention of bleeding in such patients requires the use of alternative therapeutic approaches and agents. 
   Monitor for development of factor VIII inhibitors. Perform the Bethesda assay to determine if factor VIII inhibitor is present. If expected factor VIII activity plasma levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with the expected dose of ADVATE, use Bethesda Units (BU) to titer inhibitors. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
