<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="adzenys" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Drug Dependence [see   Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  , and   Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2   ,   9.3)   ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity to amphetamine, or other components of ADZENYS XR-ODT [see   Contraindications (4)   ] 
 *  Hypertensive Crisis When Used Concomitantly with Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors [see   Contraindications (4)   and   Drug Interactions (7.1)   ] 
 *  Serious Cardiovascular Reactions [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Reactions [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Long-Term Suppression of Growth [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
   *  Pediatric patients ages 6 to 12 years: Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and with a higher incidence than on placebo) were loss of appetite, insomnia, abdominal pain, emotional lability, vomiting, nervousness, nausea, and fever. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Pediatric patients ages 13 to 17 years: Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and with a higher incidence than on placebo) were loss of appetite, insomnia, abdominal pain, weight loss, and nervousness. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adults: Most common adverse reactions &gt;=5% and with a higher incidence than on placebo were dry mouth, loss of appetite, insomnia, headache, weight loss, nausea, anxiety, agitation, dizziness, tachycardia, diarrhea, asthenia, and urinary tract infections. (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Neos Therapeutics, Inc. at 1-888-319-1789 or http://www.adzenysxrodt.com or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of ADZENYS XR-ODT has been established from adequate and well-controlled studies of single-entity amphetamine product extended-release (MAS ER) capsules [see    Clinical Studies (14)    ]. The adverse reactions of MAS ER capsules in these adequate and well-controlled studies are described below.



 The premarketing development program for MAS ER included exposures in a total of 1315 participants in clinical trials (635 pediatric patients, 350 adolescent patients, 248 adult patients, and 82 healthy adult subjects). Of these, 635 patients (ages 6 to 12 years) were evaluated in two controlled clinical studies, one open-label clinical study, and two single-dose clinical pharmacology studies (N= 40).



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment  



 The most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of MAS ER in controlled and uncontrolled, multiple-dose clinical trials of pediatric patients ages 6 to 12 years (N=595) were anorexia (loss of appetite) (2.9%), insomnia (1.5%), weight loss (1.2%), emotional lability (1%), and depression (0.7%).



 In a separate placebo-controlled 4-week study in pediatric patients ages 13 to 17 years with ADHD, five patients (2.1%) discontinued treatment due to adverse events among MAS ER-treated patients (N=233) compared to 0% who received placebo (N=54). The most frequent adverse event leading to discontinuation and considered to be drug-related (i.e., leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of MAS ER-treated patients and at a rate at least twice that of placebo) was insomnia (1.3%, n=3).



 In one placebo-controlled 4-week study among adults with ADHD with doses 20 mg to 60 mg, 23 patients (12.0% ) discontinued treatment due to adverse events among MAS ER-treated patients (N=191) compared to one patient (1.6%) who received placebo (N=64). The most frequent adverse events leading to discontinuation and considered to be drug-related (i.e., leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of MAS ER-treated patients and at a rate at least twice that of placebo) were insomnia (5.2%, n=10), anxiety (2.1%, n=4), nervousness (1.6%, n=3), dry mouth (1.6%, n=3), anorexia (1.6%, n=3), tachycardia (1.6%, n=3), headache (1.6%, n=3), and asthenia (1.0%, n=2).



     Adverse Reactions Occurring in Clinical Trials  



 Adverse reactions reported in a 3-week clinical trial of pediatric patients 6 to 12 years of age and a 4-week clinical trial in pediatric patients 13 to 17 years of age and adults, respectively, treated with MAS ER or placebo are presented in the tables below.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported by 2% or More of Pediatric Patients (6-12 years old) Receiving MAS ER with Higher Incidence than on Placebo in a 584-Patient Clinical Study 
 Body System                     Adverse Reaction                          MAS ER(n=374)     Placebo(n=210)   
  
   General                       Abdominal Pain (stomachache)              14%               10%              
                                 Fever                                     5%                2%               
                                 Infection                                 4%                2%               
                                 Accidental Injury                         3%                2%               
                                 Asthenia (fatigue)                        2%                0%               
   Digestive System              Loss of Appetite                          22%               2%               
                                 Vomiting                                  7%                4%               
                                 Nausea                                    5%                3%               
                                 Dyspepsia                                 2%                1%               
   Nervous System                Insomnia                                  17%               2%               
                                 Emotional Lability                        9%                2%               
                                 Nervousness                               6%                2%               
                                 Dizziness                                 2%                0%               
   Metabolic/Nutritional         Weight Loss                               4%                0%               
         Table 3: Adverse Reactions Reported by 5% or More of Pediatric Patients (13-17 Years Old) Weighing &lt;= 75kg Receiving MAS ER with Higher Incidence than Placebo in a 287 Patient Clinical Forced Weekly-Dose Titration StudyIncluded doses up to 40 mg 
 Body System                     Preferred Term                            MAS ER(n=233)     Placebo(n=54)    
  
 Note: The following reactions did not meet the criterion for inclusion in Table 3 but were reported by 2% to 4% of adolescent patients receiving MAS ER with a higher incidence than patients receiving placebo in this study: accidental injury, asthenia (fatigue), dry mouth, dyspepsia, emotional lability, nausea, somnolence, and vomiting.   
  
   General                       Abdominal Pain (stomachache)              11%               2%               
   Digestive System              Loss of Appetite                          36%               2%               
   Nervous System                Insomnia                                  12%               4%               
   Metabolic/Nutritional         Weight Loss                               9%                0%               
         Table 4: Adverse Reactions Reported by 5% or More of Adults Receiving MAS ER with Higher Incidence Than Placebo in a 255 Patient Clinical Forced Weekly-Dose Titration StudyIncluded doses up to 60 mg. 
 Body System                Preferred Term             MAS ER(n=191)              Placebo(n=64)               
  
 Note: The following reactions did not meet the criterion for inclusion in Table 4 but were reported by 2% to 4% of adult patients receiving MAS ER with a higher incidence than patients receiving placebo in this study: infection, photosensitivity reaction, constipation, tooth disorder (e.g., teeth clenching, tooth infection), emotional lability, libido decreased, somnolence, speech disorder (e.g., stuttering, excessive speech), palpitation, twitching, dyspnea, sweating, dysmenorrhea, and impotence.   
  
   General                  Headache                   26%                        13%                         
                            Asthenia                   6%                         5%                          
   Digestive System         Dry Mouth                  35%                        5%                          
                            Loss of Appetite           33%                        3%                          
                            Nausea                     8%                         3%                          
                            Diarrhea                   6%                         0%                          
   Nervous System           Insomnia                   27%                        13%                         
                            Agitation                  8%                         5%                          
                            Anxiety                    8%                         5%                          
                            Dizziness                  7%                         0%                          
   Cardiovascular System    Tachycardia                6%                         3%                          
   Metabolic/Nutritional    Weight Loss                10%                        0%                          
   Urogenital System        Urinary Tract Infection    5%                         0%                          
            6.2 Adverse Reactions from Clinical Trials and Spontaneous Postmarketing Reports of Other Amphetamine Products
   The following adverse reactions are from clinical trials and spontaneous postmarketing reports of other amphetamine products in pediatric patients and adults with ADHD. Because some of these reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate their frequency reliably or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Cardiovascular: Palpitations, sudden death, myocardial infarction. There have been isolated reports of cardiomyopathy associated with chronic amphetamine use.



 Central Nervous System: Restlessness, irritability, euphoria, dyskinesia, dysphoria, depression, tremor, aggression, anger, logorrhea, and paresthesia (including formication).



 Eye Disorders: Vision blurred, mydriasis.



 Gastrointestinal: Unpleasant taste, constipation, other gastrointestinal disturbances.



 Allergic: Urticaria, rash, hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema and anaphylaxis. Serious skin rashes, including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis have been reported.



 Endocrine: Impotence, change in libido, frequent or prolonged erections.



 Skin: Alopecia.



 Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue, and Bone Disorders: rhabdomyolysis.



 Psychiatric Disorders: dermatillomania, bruxism.



 Vascular Disorders: Raynaud's phenomenon.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE

    WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE  

    CNS stimulants, including ADZENYS XR-ODT, other amphetamine-containing products, and methylphenidate, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1    ,     9.3)    , and     Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2    ,     9.3)    ].   



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  CNS stimulants, including ADZENYS XR-ODT, other amphetamine-containing products, and methylphenidate, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. (5.1, 9.3) 
 *  Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy (9.2, 9.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Serious Cardiovascular Reactions: Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at recommended doses in pediatric patients with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. In adults, sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmia, or coronary artery disease. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases: Monitor blood pressure and pulse. Consider benefits and risks before use in patients for whom blood pressure increases may be problematic. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Psychiatric Adverse Reactions: May cause psychotic or manic symptoms in patients with no prior history, or exacerbation of symptoms in patients with pre-existing psychosis. Evaluate for bipolar disorder prior to stimulant use. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Long-Term Suppression of Growth: Monitor height and weight in pediatric patients during treatment. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon: Stimulants used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Potential for Abuse and Dependence



  CNS stimulants, including ADZENYS XR-ODT, other amphetamine-containing products, and methylphenidate, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy [see   Boxed Warning  ,  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2    ,   9.3)    ].



    5.2 Serious Cardiovascular Reactions



  Sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults with CNS stimulant treatment at recommended doses. Sudden death has been reported in pediatric patients with structural cardiac abnormalities and other serious heart problems taking CNS stimulants at recommended doses for ADHD. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmia, coronary artery disease, and other serious heart problems. Further evaluate patients who develop exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or arrhythmias during ADZENYS XR-ODT treatment.



    5.3 Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases



  CNS stimulants cause an increase in blood pressure (mean increase about 2-4 mm Hg) and heart rate (mean increase about 3-6 bpm). Monitor all patients for potential tachycardia and hypertension.



    5.4 Psychiatric Adverse Reactions



   Exacerbation Pre-Existing Psychosis  



 CNS stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with a pre-existing psychotic disorder.



    Induction of a Manic Episode in Patients with Bipolar Illness  



 CNS stimulants may induce a mixed or manic episode in patients with bipolar disorder. Prior to initiating treatment, screen patients for risk factors for developing a manic episode (e.g., comorbid or has a history of depressive symptoms or a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression).



    New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms  



 CNS stimulants, at recommended doses, may cause psychotic or manic symptoms, e.g., hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania in patients without prior history of psychotic illness or mania. If such symptoms occur, consider discontinuing ADZENYS XR-ODT. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies of CNS stimulants, psychotic or manic symptoms occurred in 0.1% of CNS stimulant-treated patients compared to 0% in placebo-treated patients.



    5.5 Long-Term Suppression of Growth



  CNS stimulants have been associated with weight loss and slowing of growth rate in pediatric patients. Closely monitor growth (weight and height) in pediatric patients treated with CNS stimulants, including ADZENYS XR-ODT.



    5.6 Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon



  Stimulants, including ADZENYS XR-ODT, used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Signs and symptoms are usually intermittent and mild; however, very rare sequelae include digital ulceration and/or soft tissue breakdown. Effects of peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon, were observed in post-marketing reports at different times and at therapeutic doses in all age groups throughout the course of treatment. Signs and symptoms generally improve after reduction in dose or discontinuation of drug. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. Further clinical evaluation (e.g., rheumatology referral) may be appropriate for certain patients.



    5.7 Potential for Overdose Due to Medication Errors



  Medication errors, including substitution and dispensing errors, between ADZENYS XR-ODT and other amphetamine products could occur, leading to possible overdosage. To avoid substitution errors and overdosage, do not substitute for other amphetamine products on a milligram-per-milligram basis because of different amphetamine base compositions and differing pharmacokinetic profiles [see   Dosage and Administration (2.5)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
