<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aerospan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic and local corticosteroid use may result in the following:



 *   Candida albicans infection [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Immunosuppression, increased risk of infections [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Reduction in bone mineral density [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Effects on growth [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure and cataracts [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Bronchospasm [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions are pharyngitis, rhinitis, headache, sinusitis, and increased cough. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Acton Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 855-653-6325 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The following table shows the adverse reactions that were reported in patients previously receiving bronchodilators and/or orally inhaled corticosteroids in two double-blind, placebo- controlled US clinical trials, in which 519 adult and pediatric patients age 4-78 years (279 males and 240 females) were treated with the AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol (80 mcg to 320 mcg twice daily for 12 weeks) or placebo. The mean duration of exposure was 76.7, 78.2, 80.5, and 69.4 days for AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol 80 mcg, 160 mcg, 320 mcg, and placebo, all dosed twice daily, respectively. The table includes all reactions that occurred at a rate of &gt;3% in any AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol group. In considering these data, the increased average duration of exposure for AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol patients should be taken into account, compared with placebo-treated patients.



 Adverse Reactions with &gt;3% incidence reported in controlled clinical studies with AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol (% of patients) 
         ADVERSE REACTION   PLACEBO(n = 220)    AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol   
          80 MCG(n = 189)   160 MCG(n = 217)     320 MCG(n = 113)     
  
          BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                       
                 Headache         12.7                  9.0                 13.8                  8.8           
        Allergic Reaction          2.3                  4.2                  4.6                  4.4           
                                                                                                                
     Infection, Bacterial          0.9                  3.7                  0.9                  0.9           
         DIGESTIVE SYSTEM                                                                                       
                 Vomiting          4.1                  4.2                  4.6                  0.0           
                Dyspepsia          1.4                  2.1                  3.2                  3.5           
       RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                                                                                       
              Pharyngitis         13.2                 17.5                 16.6                 16.8           
                 Rhinitis         10.0                  9.0                 15.7                  3.5           
          Cough Increased          7.7                  8.5                  5.5                  1.8           
                Sinusitis          5.5                  7.4                  4.1                  8.8           
                Epistaxis          0.9                  3.2                  0.9                  0.0           
        UROGENITAL SYSTEM                                                                                       
  Urinary Tract Infection          0.5                  1.1                  0.9                  3.5           
           The following other adverse reactions occurred in patients in these clinical trials using AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol with an incidence of 1 to 3% and were more common in AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol than in the placebo group.
 

   Body As A Whole  : abdominal pain, chest pain, infection, neck pain  Digestive System  : diarrhea, gastroenteritis, nausea, oral moniliasis  Metabolic And Nutritional Disorders  : edema  Musculoskeletal System  : myalgia  Nervous System  : dizziness, insomnia, migraine  Respiratory System  : bronchitis, laryngitis, voice alteration  Skin And Appendages  : erythema multiforme  Special Senses  : conjunctivitis, ear pain, taste perversion  Urogenital System  : dysmenorrhea, vaginitis



     Long-Term Clinical Trials  



 Two 52-week open label safety trials of AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol were conducted in 162 asthma patients 12 to 60 years of age and in 152 asthma patients 4 to 11 years of age. The adverse reaction profile exhibited in these trials was similar to that seen in the two 12-week studies.



   6.2 Adverse Reactions from Other Sources

  The following additional adverse reactions were derived from clinical trials conducted with flunisolide CFC inhalation aerosol with a frequency of &gt;=1% and not described above:



   Body as a Whole  : flu, decreased appetite, chills, increased appetite, weight gain, malaise, peripheral edema, sweating, weakness  Gastrointestinal System  : upset stomach, heartburn, constipation, gas, abdominal fullness  Cardiovascular System  : palpitations, hypertension, tachycardia  Nervous System  : headache, irritability, shakiness, anxiety, depression, faintness, fatigue, hyperactivity, hypoactivity, moodiness, numbness, vertigo  Respiratory System  : cold symptoms, nasal congestion, upper respiratory tract infection, chest congestion, hoarseness, runny nose, sinus congestion, sinus drainage, sinus infection, sneezing, sputum, wheezing, chest tightness, bronchospasm, dyspnea, head stuffiness, nasal irritation, pleurisy, pneumonia, sinus discomfort  Skin and Appendages  : eczema, pruritus, acne, urticaria  Special Senses  : loss of smell, loss of taste, ear infection, blurred vision, eye discomfort, eye infection  Hemic and Lymph  : capillary fragility, enlarged lymph nodes  Mouth and Throat  : sore throat, dry throat, glossitis, mouth irritation, phlegm, throat irritation
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Fungal infection of the mouth and pharynx. Monitor patients periodically for signs of adverse effects on the oral cavity. Advise patients to rinse mouth following inhalation. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Immunosuppression: Potential worsening of existing tuberculosis; fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infection; or ocular herpes simplex. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles in susceptible patients. Use caution in patients with above because of the potential for worsening of these infections. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Transferring patients from systemic corticosteroids: Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring from oral steroids. Taper patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to AEROSPAN. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: May occur with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals. If such changes occur, discontinue AEROSPAN slowly. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Decreases in bone mineral density: Assess bone mineral density initially and periodically thereafter in patients at risk. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Effect on growth: Monitor growth of children. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Glaucoma and cataracts: Close monitoring is warranted. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Paradoxical bronchospasm immediately after dosing: Treat bronchospasm immediately with a fast acting bronchodilator, and discontinue use of AEROSPAN. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Local Infections



  In clinical studies with flunisolide, localized infections with Candida albicans  or Aspergillus niger  have occurred in the mouth and pharynx and occasionally in the larynx. If oropharyngeal candidiasis develops, treat with appropriate local or systemic (i.e., oral) antifungal therapy while still continuing with AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol therapy, but at times therapy with AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol may need to be temporarily interrupted under close medical supervision. Rinsing the mouth after inhalation is advised. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.2 Acute Asthma Episodes



  AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol is not a bronchodilator and is not indicated for rapid relief of bronchospasm. Instruct patients to contact their physician immediately when episodes of asthma that are not responsive to bronchodilators occur during the course of treatment with AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol. During such episodes, patients may require therapy with systemic corticosteroids.



    5.3 Immunosuppression



  Patients who are using drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infections than healthy individuals. Chickenpox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in non-immune children or adults on corticosteroids. In such children or adults who have not had these diseases or been properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affects the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If a patient is exposed to chickenpox, prophylaxis with varicella-zoster immune globulin (VZIG) may be indicated. If a patient is exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See the respective package inserts for complete VZIG and IG prescribing information.) If chickenpox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.



 Because of the potential for worsening infections, use inhaled corticosteroids with caution, if at all, in patients with untreated active or quiescent tuberculosis infection of the respiratory tract; untreated systemic fungal, bacterial, parasitic or viral infections; or ocular herpes simplex.



    5.4 Transfer from Systemic Corticosteroids



  Particular care is needed in patients who are transferred from systemically active corticosteroids to AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol because deaths due to adrenal insufficiency have occurred in asthmatic patients during and after transfer from systemic corticosteroids to less systemically available inhaled corticosteroids. After withdrawal from systemic corticosteroids, a number of months are required for recovery of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) function.



 Patients who have been previously maintained on 20 mg or more per day of prednisone (or its equivalent) may be most susceptible, particularly when their systemic corticosteroids have been almost completely withdrawn. During this period of HPA suppression, patients may exhibit signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency when exposed to trauma, surgery or infections (particularly gastroenteritis) or other conditions associated with severe electrolyte loss. Although AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol may provide control of asthmatic symptoms during these episodes, in recommended doses it supplies less than the physiologic amounts of glucocorticoid (cortisol) systemically and does NOT provide the mineralocorticoid activity that is necessary for coping with these emergencies.



 During periods of stress or a severe asthmatic attack, patients who have been withdrawn from systemic corticosteroids should be instructed to resume systemic steroids immediately and to contact their physician for further instruction. Instruct these patients to carry a warning card indicating that they may need supplementary systemic steroids during periods of stress or a severe asthma attack.



 Wean patients requiring oral corticosteroids slowly from systemic corticosteroid use after transferring to AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol. Prednisone reduction can be accomplished by reducing the daily prednisone dose by 2.5 mg/day on a weekly basis [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  . Lung function (forced expiratory volume in one second [FEV1] or morning peak expiratory flow rate [AM PEF]), beta-agonist use, and asthma symptoms should be carefully monitored during withdrawal of oral corticosteroids. In addition to monitoring asthma signs and symptoms, observe patients for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency such as fatigue, lassitude, weakness, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension.



 Transfer of patients from systemic corticosteroid therapy to AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol may unmask allergic conditions previously suppressed by the systemic corticosteroid therapy, e.g. rhinitis, conjunctivitis, eczema, arthritis, and eosinophilic conditions.



 During withdrawal from oral corticosteroids, some patients may experience symptoms of systemically active corticosteroid withdrawal, e.g., joint or muscular pain, lassitude and depression, despite maintenance or even improvement of respiratory function.



    5.5 Hypercorticism and Adrenal Suppression



  In responsive patients, flunisolide may permit control of asthmatic symptoms with less suppression of HPA axis function than therapeutically equivalent oral doses of prednisone. Since flunisolide is absorbed into the circulation and can be systemically active, the beneficial effects of AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol in minimizing or preventing HPA axis dysfunction may be expected only when recommended dosages are not exceeded and individual patients are titrated to the lowest effective dose. Since individual sensitivity to effects on cortisol production exists, physicians should consider this information when prescribing AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol.



 Because of the possibility of systemic absorption of inhaled corticosteroids, observe patients treated with AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol carefully for any evidence of systemic corticosteroid effects. Particular care should be taken in observing patients post-operatively or during periods of stress for evidence of inadequate adrenal response.



 It is possible that systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression may appear in a small number of patients, particularly at higher doses. If such changes occur, reduce the AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol dose slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for management of asthma symptoms and for tapering of systemic corticosteroids.



    5.6 Reduction in Bone Mineral Density



  Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) have been observed with long-term administration of products containing inhaled corticosteroids, including flunisolide. The clinical significance of small changes in BMD with regard to long-term outcomes is unknown. Monitor patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content, such as prolonged immobilization, family history of osteoporosis, postmenopausal status, tobacco use, advanced age, poor nutrition, or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass (e.g., anticonvulsants and corticosteroids) and treat with established standards of care.



    5.7 Effects on Growth



  Orally inhaled corticosteroids, including flunisolide, may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to pediatric patients [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  . Monitor the growth of children and adolescents receiving AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol. To minimize the systemic effects of orally inhaled corticosteroids, including AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol, each titrate each patient to his/her lowest effective dose [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



    5.8 Glaucoma and Cataracts



  Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure, and cataracts have been reported in patients following the long-term administration of inhaled corticosteroids, including flunisolide. Monitor patients closely, especially patients with a change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, or cataracts.



    5.9 Paradoxical Bronchospasm



  As with other inhaled asthma medications, bronchospasm may occur with an immediate increase in wheezing after dosing. If bronchospasm occurs following dosing with AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol, treat immediately with a fast-acting inhaled bronchodilator. Discontinue treatment with AEROSPAN Inhalation Aerosol immediately and institute alternative therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
