<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="afluria" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In children 5 through 17 years of age, the most common injection-site reactions observed in clinical studies with AFLURIA administered by needle and syringe were pain (&gt;=60%), redness (&gt;=20%) and swelling (&gt;=10%). The most common systemic adverse events were headache, myalgia (&gt;=20%), irritability, malaise and fever (&gt;=10%).



 In adults 18 through 64 years of age, the most common injection-site adverse reactions observed in clinical studies with AFLURIA administered by needle and syringe were tenderness (&gt;=60%), pain (&gt;=40%), swelling (&gt;=20%), redness and itching (&gt;=10%). The most common systemic adverse events observed were muscle aches (&gt;=30%), headache and malaise (&gt;=20%).



 In adults 18 through 64 years of age, using the PharmaJet Stratis Needle-Free Injection System, the most common injection-site adverse reactions observed in a clinical study with AFLURIA up to 7 days post-vaccination were tenderness (&gt;=80%), swelling, pain, redness (&gt;=60%), itching (&gt;=20%) and bruising (&gt;=10%). The most common systemic adverse events within this period were myalgia, malaise (&gt;=30%) and headache (&gt;=20%).



 In adults 65 years of age and older, the most common injection-site adverse reactions observed in clinical studies with AFLURIA administered by needle and syringe were tenderness (&gt;=30%) and pain (&gt;=10%). No systemic adverse reactions occurred in &gt;=10% of subjects in this age group.



    EXCERPT:    *  In children 5 through 17 years of age, the most common injection-site adverse reactions when administered by needle and syringe were pain (&gt;=60%), redness (&gt;=20%) and swelling (&gt;=10%). The most common systemic adverse events were headache, myalgia (&gt;=20%), irritability, malaise and fever (&gt;=10%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In adults 18 through 64 years of age, the most common injection-site adverse reactions when administered by needle and syringe were tenderness (&gt;=60%), pain (&gt;=40%), swelling (&gt;=20%), and redness, itching (&gt;=10%). The most common systemic adverse events were muscle aches (&gt;=30%) and headache, malaise (&gt;=20%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In adults 18 through 64 years of age, the most common injection-site adverse reactions when administered by the PharmaJet Stratis Needle-Free Injection System up to 7 days post-vaccination were tenderness (&gt;=80%), swelling, pain, redness (&gt;=60%), itching (&gt;=20%) and bruising (&gt;=10%). The most common systemic adverse events within this period were myalgia, malaise (&gt;=30%), and headache (&gt;=20%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In adults 65 years of age and older, when administered by needle and syringe the most common injection-site adverse reactions were tenderness (&gt;=30%) and pain (&gt;=10%). No systemic adverse events occurred in &gt;=10% of subjects in this age group (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Seqirus USA Inc. at 1-844-275-2461 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Children  



 In clinical studies, AFLURIA has been administered to, and safety information collected for, 3,009 children ages 6 months through 17 years. The exposure in children includes 1,601 aged 6 months to less than 5 years, 756 children ages 5 years to less than 9 years and 652 children ages 9 years through 17 years. Clinical safety data for AFLURIA in children are presented from three clinical studies (Studies 1, 2 and 3). Data from a comparator-controlled trial (Study 1) are presented, followed by pooled data from two open label studies (Studies 2 and 3). Subjects 6 months through 8 years of age received one or two vaccinations, administered by needle and syringe, as determined by previous vaccination history (for further details on clinical study design, dosing and demographics  see  Clinical Studies [14]    ).



 Study 1 included 1,468 subjects for safety analysis, ages 6 months through 17 years, randomized to receive AFLURIA (735 subjects) or another U.S.-licensed trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine (manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur, Inc.) (733 subjects)  .  



 Study 2 included 1,976 subjects for safety analysis, ages 6 months through 17 years. All subjects received AFLURIA.



 Study 3 included 298 subjects for safety analysis, ages 6 months through 8 years. All subjects received AFLURIA.



 The safety assessment was similar for the three pediatric studies. Local (injection site) adverse reactions and systemic adverse events were solicited for 7 days post-vaccination (Tables 2 and 3). Unsolicited adverse events were collected for 30 days post-vaccination. All adverse events are presented regardless of any treatment causality assigned by study investigators.



 Among the pediatric studies, there were no vaccine-related deaths or vaccine-related serious adverse events reported in children 5 years of age and older.



 In this section, safety data from the pediatric studies are limited to children 5 years of age and older. AFLURIA is not approved for use in children less than 5 years of age. See  Warnings and Precautions [5.1]  and  Use in Specific Populations [8.4]  for risks of AFLURIA in children less than 5 years of age.



 In the comparator-controlled trial (Study 1), the rate of fever after the first dose of AFLURIA in subjects aged 5 through 8 years was 16% as compared to 8% in subjects who received the comparator. The rate of fever in subjects aged 9 through 17 years following a single dose of AFLURIA was 6% as compared to 4% in subjects who received the comparator. In all three pediatric studies, the rates of fever in subjects aged 5 through 8 years who received AFLURIA were lower after dose 2 than dose 1.



 Data in Tables 2 and 3 are presented for children 5 years and older.



 Table 2: Proportion of Subjects 5 through 17 Years of Age with Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or Systemic Adverse Events within 7 Days after Administration of First or Second Dose of AFLURIA, Irrespective of Causality (Study 1) 
                       Percentageof Subjects in each Age Group Reporting Event   
 Subjects 5 through 8 years  Subjects 9 through 17 years   
 AFLURIAN=161            ComparatorN=165         AFLURIAN=254        ComparatorN=250      
  
   After the First Dose     
   Local Adverse Reactions     
 Pain                           63                    60                    66                    60            
 Redness                        23                    27                    17                    17            
 Induration                     17                    17                    15                    16            
   Systemic Adverse Events     
 Myalgia                        34                    30                    40                    37            
 Malaise                        24                    13                    22                    20            
 Headache                       21                    19                    27                    26            
 Any Fever                      16                    8                     6                     4             
   Fever &gt;=102.2 degrees F           5                     1                     3                     1             
 Nausea/Vomiting                12                    8                     9                     10            
 Diarrhea                       7                     7                     8                     10            
                           AFLURIAN=39          ComparatorN=53                            
   After the Second Dose     
   Local Adverse Reactions     
 Pain                           36                    38                    -                     -             
 Redness                        10                    19                    -                     -             
 Induration                     8                     17                    -                     -             
   Systemic Adverse Events     
 Diarrhea                       13                    6                     -                     -             
 Headache                       13                    13                    -                     -             
 Myalgia                        13                    17                    -                     -             
 Malaise                        5                     8                     -                     -             
 Nausea/Vomiting                3                     8                     -                     -             
 Any Fever  Fever &gt;=102.2 degrees F           00                    20                    --                    --            
          Table 3: Proportion of Subjects 5 through 17 Years of Age with Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or Systemic Adverse Events Within 7 Days after Administration of AFLURIA, Irrespective of Causality (Studies 2 and 3) 
                                   Percentageof Subjects in each Age Group Reporting Event   
 Studies 2 and 3Subjects 5 through 8 years  Study 2Subjects 9 through 17 years   
 Dose 1N=82-595                     Dose 2N=82-426       Dose 1N=397      
  
   Local Adverse Reactions          
 Pain                                     61                 56                          68                   
 Erythema                                 24                 23                          17                   
 Swelling                                 17                 17                          13                   
   Systemic Adverse Events          
 Irritability                             18                 16                          -                    
 Headache                                 16                 10                          27                   
 Malaise or feeling generally unwell         16                  8                          17                   
 Any Fever                                13                  6                          5                    
   Fever &gt;= 102.2 degrees F                3                  2                          1                    
 General Muscle Ache (Myalgia)            12                  8                          20                   
 Nausea/Vomiting                           7                  3                          5                    
 Vomiting/Diarrhea                         5                  6                          -                    
 Loss of appetite                          5                  4                          -                    
 Diarrhea                                  4                  2                          5                    
          In Study 1, unsolicited adverse events that occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects who received AFLURIA in ages 5 years through 8 years following the first or second dose included cough (15%) and pyrexia (9%). Unsolicited adverse events that occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects who received AFLURIA in ages 9 years through 17 years following the first dose included cough (7%), oropharyngeal pain (7%), headache (7%) and nasal congestion (6%).
 

 In Studies 2 and 3, unsolicited adverse events that occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects ages 5 years through 8 years after the first or second dose included the following: upper respiratory tract infection (13%), cough (10%), rhinorrhea (7%), headache (5%), nasopharyngitis (5%) and pyrexia (5%). Unsolicited adverse events that occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects who received AFLURIA in ages 9 years through 17 years following the first dose included upper respiratory tract infection (9%) and headache (8%).



     Adults  



 In clinical studies comparing AFLURIA to placebo or a comparator trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine, a single dose of AFLURIA was administered to, and safety information collected for, 11,104 subjects ages 18 through 64 years and 836 subjects ages 65 years and older. Clinical safety data for AFLURIA in adults are presented from three clinical studies (Studies 4 through 6) conducted in the US and one clinical study (Study 7) conducted in the UK



 Study 4 included 1,357 subjects for safety analysis, ages 18 through 64 years, randomized to receive AFLURIA (1,089 subjects) or placebo (268 subjects) (  see  Clinical Studies [14]    ).



 Study 5 included 15,020 subjects for safety analysis, ages 18 through 64 years, randomized to receive AFLURIA (10,015 subjects) or placebo (5,005 subjects) (  see  Clinical Studies [14]    ).



 Study 6 included 1,266 subjects for safety analysis, ages 65 years and older, randomized to receive AFLURIA (630 subjects) or another U.S.-licensed trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine (manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur Inc.) as an active comparator (636 subjects) (  see  Clinical Studies [14]  )  . Study 7 included 275 subjects for safety analysis, ages 65 years and older, randomized to receive AFLURIA (206 subjects) or a UK-licensed trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine (manufactured by GSK) as an active comparator (69 subjects).



 The safety assessment was identical for the four adult studies. Local (injection-site) adverse reactions and systemic adverse events were solicited for 5 days post-vaccination (Table 4, studies 4 through 6). Unsolicited adverse events were collected for 21 days post-vaccination. All adverse events are presented regardless of any treatment causality assigned by study investigators.



 Among adult studies, there were no vaccine-related deaths or vaccine-related serious adverse events reported.



 Table 4: Proportion of Subjects 18 Years of Age and Older with Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or Systemic Adverse Events within 5 Days after Administration of AFLURIA or Placebo, Irrespective of Causality (Studies 4, 5 and 6) 
                            Percentageof Subjects in each Age Group Reporting Event   
 Study 4Subjects 18 through 64 years  Study 5Subjects 18 through 64 years  Study 6Subjects &gt;= 65 years   
 AFLURIAN=1087-1088         PlaceboN=266   AFLURIAN=10,015  PlaceboN=5005  AFLURIAN=630  ComparatorN=636   
  
   Local Adverse Reactions     
 Tenderness (Pain on touching)       60             18            69             17            36             31        
 Pain (without touching)         40             9             48             11            15             14        
 Redness                         16             8              4             &lt;1             3             1         
 Swelling                         9             1              4             &lt;1             7             8         
 Bruising                         5             1              1             1             &lt;1             1         
   Systemic Adverse Events     
 Headache                        26             26            25             23             9             11        
 Malaise                         19             19            29             26             7             6         
 Muscle aches                    13             9             21             12             9             8         
 Nausea                           6             9              7             6              2             1         
 Chills/Shivering                 3             2              5             4              2             2         
 Fever                            1             1              3             2             &lt;1             1         
             In Study 4, headache was the only unsolicited adverse event that occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects who received AFLURIA or placebo (8% versus 6%, respectively).
 

 In Study 5, unsolicited adverse events that occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects who received AFLURIA or placebo included headache (AFLURIA 12%, placebo 11%) and oropharyngeal pain (AFLURIA 5%, placebo 5%).



 In Study 6, headache was the only unsolicited adverse event that occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects who received AFLURIA (5%).



 Studies 1 to 7 were all conducted when AFLURIA was administered by needle and syringe.



 Additionally, safety information has been collected in a clinical study of AFLURIA administered using the PharmaJet Stratis Needle-Free Injection System (Study 8). Study 8 included 1,247 subjects for safety analysis, ages 18 through 64 years, randomized to receive AFLURIA by either the PharmaJet Stratis Needle-Free Injection System (624 subjects) or needle and syringe (623 subjects). No deaths or vaccine-related serious adverse events were reported in Study 8. Local (injection-site) adverse reactions and systemic adverse events were solicited for 7 days post-vaccination (Table 5).



 Table 5: Proportion of Subjects 18 through 64 Years of Age with Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or Systemic Adverse Events within 7 Days after Administration of AFLURIA by PharmaJet Stratis Needle-Free Injection System or Needle and Syringe Irrespective of Causality (Study 8). 
                                   Percentageof Subjects Reporting Event   
 Study 8Subjects 18 through 64 years   
 AFLURIA                            
 PharmaJet Stratis Needle-Free Injection SystemN=540-616     Needle and SyringeN=599-606       
  
   Local Adverse Reactions          
 Tenderness                                        89                                  78                   
 Swelling                                          65                                  20                   
 Pain                                              64                                  49                   
 Redness                                           60                                  19                   
 Itching                                           28                                  10                   
 Bruising                                          18                                  5                    
   Systemic Adverse Events          
 Myalgia                                           36                                  36                   
 Malaise                                           31                                  28                   
 Headache                                          25                                  22                   
 Chills                                            7                                   7                    
 Nausea                                            7                                   7                    
 Vomiting                                          1                                   2                    
 Fever                                             0                                   0                    
         In Study 8, no unsolicited adverse events occurred in &gt;= 5% of subjects who received AFLURIA administered via PharmaJet Stratis Needle-Free Injection System up to 28 days post-vaccination.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure. The adverse reactions described have been included in this section because they: 1) represent reactions that are known to occur following immunizations generally or influenza immunizations specifically; 2) are potentially serious; or 3) have been reported frequently. These adverse reactions reflect experience in both children and adults and include those identified during post-approval use of AFLURIA outside the US since 1985.



     Blood and lymphatic system disorders  



 Thrombocytopenia



     Immune system disorders  



 Allergic or immediate hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic shock and serum sickness



     Nervous system disorders  



 Neuralgia, paresthesia, convulsions (including febrile seizures), encephalomyelitis, encephalopathy, neuritis or neuropathy, transverse myelitis, and GBS



     Vascular disorders  



 Vasculitis which may be associated with transient renal involvement



     Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  



 Pruritus, urticaria, and rash



     General disorders and administration site conditions  



 Cellulitis and large injection site swellingInfluenza-like illness



   6.3 Adverse Reactions Associated With Influenza Vaccination

  Anaphylaxis has been reported after administration of AFLURIA. Egg protein can induce immediate hypersensitivity reactions among persons who have severe egg allergy. Allergic reactions include hives, angioedema, asthma, and systemic anaphylaxis (  see  Contraindications [4]    )  .  



 Neurological disorders temporally associated with influenza vaccination, such as encephalopathy, optic neuritis/neuropathy, partial facial paralysis, and brachial plexus neuropathy, have been reported.



 Microscopic polyangiitis (vasculitis) has been reported temporally associated with influenza vaccination.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Administration of CSL's 2010 Southern Hemisphere influenza vaccine was associated with increased rates of fever and febrile seizures in children predominantly below the age of 5 years as compared to previous years. Febrile events were also observed in children 5 through 8 years of age. (  5.1  ) 
 *  If Guillain-Barre Syndrome (GBS) has occurred within 6 weeks of previous influenza vaccination, the decision to give AFLURIA should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Immunocompromised persons may have a diminished immune response to AFLURIA. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Fever and Febrile Seizures



  Administration of CSL's 2010 Southern Hemisphere influenza vaccine was associated with postmarketing reports of increased rates of fever and febrile seizures in children predominantly below the age of 5 years as compared to previous years; these increased rates were confirmed by postmarketing studies. Febrile events were also observed in children 5 through 8 years of age.



    5.2 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre Syndrome (GBS) has occurred within 6 weeks of previous influenza vaccination, the decision to give AFLURIA should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks.



 The 1976 swine influenza vaccine was associated with an increased frequency of GBS. Evidence for a causal relation of GBS with subsequent vaccines prepared from other influenza viruses is unclear. If influenza vaccine does pose a risk, it is probably slightly more than one additional case per 1 million persons vaccinated.



    5.3 Preventing and Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine.



    5.4 Altered Immunocompetence



  If AFLURIA is administered to immunocompromised persons, including those receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the immune response may be diminished.



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with AFLURIA may not protect all individuals.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
