<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="agrylin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Bleeding Risk [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Pulmonary Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5%) are headache, palpitations, diarrhea, asthenia, edema, nausea, abdominal pain, dizziness, pain, dyspnea, cough, flatulence, vomiting, fever, peripheral edema, rash, chest pain, anorexia, tachycardia, malaise, paresthesia, back pain, pruritus, dyspepsia (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Shire US Inc. at 1-800-828-2088 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov./medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Clinical Studies in Adult Patients  



 In three single-arm clinical studies, 942 patients  [see  Clinical Trials (14)  ]  diagnosed with myeloproliferative neoplasms of varying etiology (ET: 551; PV: 117; OMPN: 274) were exposed to anagrelide with a mean duration of approximately 65 weeks. Serious adverse reactions reported in these patients included the following: congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction, cardiomyopathy, cardiomegaly, complete heart block, atrial fibrillation, cerebrovascular accident, pericardial effusion  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  , pleural effusion, pulmonary infiltrates, pulmonary fibrosis, pulmonary hypertension, and pancreatitis. Of the 942 patients treated with anagrelide, 161 (17%) were discontinued from the study because of adverse reactions or abnormal laboratory test results. The most common adverse reactions for treatment discontinuation were headache, diarrhea, edema, palpitations, and abdominal pain.



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions to anagrelide (in 5% or greater of 942 patients with myeloproliferative neoplasms) in clinical trials were listed in Table 1.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Studies in at least 5% of Patients 
 Adverse reactions                                                   AGRYLIN(N=942)(%)                    
  
   Cardiac disorders                                                                                      
 Palpitations                                                               26%                           
 Tachycardia                                                                 8%                           
 Chest pain                                                                  8%                           
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                         
 Asthenia                                                                   23%                           
 Edema                                                                      21%                           
 Pain                                                                       15%                           
 Fever                                                                       9%                           
 Peripheral edema                                                            9%                           
 Malaise                                                                     6%                           
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                             
 Diarrhea                                                                   26%                           
 Nausea                                                                     17%                           
 Abdominal pain                                                             16%                           
 Vomiting                                                                   10%                           
 Flatulence                                                                 10%                           
 Anorexia                                                                    8%                           
 Dyspepsia                                                                   5%                           
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                         
 Dyspnea                                                                    12%                           
 Cough                                                                       6%                           
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                 
 Rash                                                                        8%                           
 Pruritus                                                                    6%                           
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                         
 Back pain                                                                   6%                           
   Nervous system disorders                                                                               
 Headache                                                                   44%                           
 Dizziness                                                                  15%                           
 Paresthesia                                                                 6%                           
          Adverse Reactions (frequency 1% to &lt; 5%) included:  
 

   General disorders and administration site conditions:  Flu symptoms, chills.



   Cardiac disorders:  Arrhythmia, angina pectoris, heart failure, syncope.



   Vascular disorders  : Hemorrhage, hypertension, postural hypotension, vasodilatation.



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  Constipation, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastritis.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  Anemia, thrombocytopenia, ecchymosis.



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  Elevated liver enzymes.



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  Arthralgia, myalgia.



   Psychiatric disorders:  Depression, confusion, nervousness.



   Nervous system disorders:  Somnolence, insomnia, amnesia, migraine headache.



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  Epistaxis, pneumonia.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Alopecia.



   Eye disorders:  Abnormal vision, diplopia.



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  Tinnitus



   Renal and urinary disorders:  Hematuria, renal failure.



   Other less frequent adverse reactions (&lt;1%) were:  



   Cardiac disorders:  Ventricular tachycardia, supraventricular tachycardia.



   Nervous system disorders:  Hypoesthesia.



     Clinical Study in Pediatric Patients  



 The frequency of adverse events observed in pediatric patients was similar to adult patients. The most common adverse events observed in pediatric patients were fever, epistaxis, headache, and fatigue during the 3-month anagrelide treatment in the study. Episodes of increased pulse and decreased systolic or diastolic blood pressure beyond the normal ranges in the absence of clinical symptoms were observed. Adverse events that had been reported in these pediatric patients prior to the study and were considered to be related to anagrelide treatment based on retrospective review were; palpitations, headache, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, back pain, anorexia, fatigue, and muscle cramps.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-marketing use of AGRYLIN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Cases of torsades de pointes, interstitial lung diseases (including allergic alveolitis, eosinophilic pneumonia and interstitial pneumonitis)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5)  ]  , tubulointerstitial nephritis and clinically significant hepatotoxicity (including symptomatic ALT and AST elevations and elevations greater than three times the ULN) have been reported  .  



 Other adverse events in pediatric patients reported in spontaneous reports and literature reviews include anemia, cutaneous photosensitivity and elevated leukocyte count.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Cardiovascular Toxicity: QT prolongation and ventricular tachycardia have been reported with anagrelide. Obtain a pre-treatment cardiovascular examination including an ECG in all patients. Monitor patients for cardiovascular effects. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Bleeding Risk: Monitor patients for bleeding, including those receiving concomitant therapy with other drugs known to cause bleeding (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Toxicity



  Torsades de pointes and ventricular tachycardia have been reported with anagrelide. Obtain a pre-treatment cardiovascular examination including an ECG in all patients. During treatment with AGRYLIN monitor patients for cardiovascular effects and evaluate as necessary.



  Anagrelide increases the QTc interval of the electrocardiogram and increases the heart rate in healthy volunteers [  see   Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .  



  Do not use AGRYLIN in patients with known risk factors for QT interval prolongation, such as congenital long QT syndrome, a known history of acquired QTc prolongation, medicinal products that can prolong QTc interval and hypokalemia [  see   Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .  



  Hepatic impairment increases anagrelide exposure and could increase the risk of QTc prolongation. Monitor patients with hepatic impairment for QTc prolongation and other cardiovascular adverse reactions. The potential risks and benefits of anagrelide therapy in a patient with mild and moderate hepatic impairment should be assessed before treatment is commenced. Reduce AGRYLIN dose in patients with moderate hepatic impairment. Use of AGRYLIN in patients with severe hepatic impairment has not been studied [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2  ,  12.3)  ].    



  In patients with heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, or electrolyte abnormalities, consider periodic monitoring with electrocardiograms [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .  



 Anagrelide is a phosphodiesterase 3 (PDE3) inhibitor and may cause vasodilation, tachycardia, palpitations, and congestive heart failure. Other drugs that inhibit PDE3 have caused decreased survival when compared with placebo in patients with Class III-IV congestive heart failure [  see   Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



 In patients with cardiac disease, use AGRYLIN only when the benefits outweigh the risks.



    5.2 Bleeding Risk



  Use of concomitant anagrelide and aspirin increased major hemorrhagic events in a postmarketing study. Assess the potential risks and benefits for concomitant use of anagrelide with aspirin, since bleeding risks may be increased. Monitor patients for bleeding, including those receiving concomitant therapy with other drugs known to cause bleeding (e.g., anticoagulants, PDE3 inhibitors, NSAIDs, antiplatelet agents, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors) [see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.3 Pulmonary Toxicity



  Interstitial lung diseases (including allergic alveolitis, eosinophilic pneumonia and interstitial pneumonitis) have been reported to be associated with the use of anagrelide in post-marketing reports. Most cases presented with progressive dyspnea with lung infiltrations. The time of onset ranged from 1 week to several years after initiating anagrelide. If suspected, discontinue AGRYLIN and evaluate. Symptoms may improve after discontinuation [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
