<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="akovaz" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions associated with the use of ephedrine sulfate were identified in the literature. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate their frequency reliably or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  Nausea, vomiting



   Cardiac disorders:  Tachycardia, palpitations (thumping heart), reactive hypertension, bradycardia, ventricular ectopics, R-R variability



   Nervous system disorders:  Dizziness



   Psychiatric disorders:  Restlessness



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions during treatment: nausea, vomiting, and tachycardia. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eclat Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-622-2320 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Pressor Effect with Concomitant Oxytocic Drugs : Pressor effect of sympathomimetic pressor amines is potentiated (  5.1  ) 
 *   Tachyphylaxis and Tolerance : Repeated administration of ephedrine may cause tachyphylaxis (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Pressor Effect with Concomitant Oxytocic Drugs



  Serious postpartum hypertension has been described in patients who received both a vasopressor (i.e., methoxamine, phenylephrine, ephedrine) and an oxytocic (i.e., methylergonovine, ergonovine) [ see  Drug Interactions (7)    ]. Some of these patients experienced a stroke. Carefully monitor the blood pressure of individuals who have received both ephedrine and an oxytocic.



    5.2 Tolerance and Tachyphylaxis



  Data indicate that repeated administration of ephedrine can result in tachyphylaxis. Clinicians treating anesthesia-induced hypotension with AKOVAZ (ephedrine sulfate injection) should be aware of the possibility of tachyphylaxis and should be prepared with an alternative pressor to mitigate unacceptable responsiveness.



    5.3 Risk of Hypertension When Used Prophylactically



  When used to prevent hypotension, ephedrine has been associated with an increased incidence of hypertension compared with when ephedrine is used to treat hypotension.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
