<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="albenza" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Adverse reactions 1% or greater in hydatid disease: abnormal liver function tests, abdominal pain, nausea/vomiting, reversible alopecia, headache, dizziness/vertigo, fever. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adverse reactions 1% or greater in neurocysticercosis: headache, nausea/vomiting, raised intracranial pressure, meningeal signs. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Amedra Pharmaceuticals LLC at 1-888-894-6528 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The adverse reaction profile of ALBENZA differs between hydatid disease and neurocysticercosis. Adverse reactions occurring with a frequency of 1% or greater in either disease are described in Table 2 below.



 These symptoms were usually mild and resolved without treatment. Treatment discontinuations were predominantly due to leukopenia (0.7%) or hepatic abnormalities (3.8% in hydatid disease). The following incidence reflects adverse reactions that were reported to be at least possibly or probably related to ALBENZA.



 Table 2: Adverse Reaction Incidence 1% or Greater in Hydatid Disease and Neurocysticercosis 
    Adverse Reaction                    Hydatid Disease                    Neurocysticercosis               
    Gastrointestinal                  
  Abdominal Pain                      6                                  0                                  
  Nausea                              4                                  6                                  
  Vomiting                            4                                  6                                  
    General disorders and administration site conditions     
  Fever                               1                                  0                                  
    Investigations                    
  Elevated Hepatic Enzymes            16                                 less than 1                        
    Nervous system disorders          
  Dizziness                           1                                  less than 1                        
  Headache                            1                                  11                                 
  Meningeal Signs                     0                                  1                                  
  Raised Intracranial Pressure        0                                  2                                  
  Vertigo                             1                                  less than 1                        
    Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders     
  Reversible Alopecia                 2                                  less than 1                        
         The following adverse events were observed at an incidence of less than 1%:
 

   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  There have been reports of leukopenia, granulocytopenia, pancytopenia, agranulocytosis, or thrombocytopenia [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ].



   Immune System Disorders:  Hypersensitivity reactions, including rash and urticaria.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ALBENZA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Aplastic anemia, bone marrow suppression, neutropenia.



   Eye Disorders:  Vision blurred.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Diarrhea.



   General System Disorders:  Asthenia.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Elevations of hepatic enzymes, hepatitis, acute liver failure.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Rhabdomyolysis.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Somnolence, convulsion.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Acute renal failure.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Bone Marrow Suppression: Fatalities have been reported due to bone marrow suppression; monitor blood counts in all patients at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and every 2 weeks while on therapy. Discontinue ALBENZA if clinically significant changes in blood counts occur. (  5.1  ,  5.4  ) 
 *  Teratogenic Effects: Obtain pregnancy test in women of reproductive potential prior to therapy and avoid usage in pregnant women except in clinical circumstances where no alternative management is appropriate. Discontinue therapy if pregnancy occurs and apprise patient of potential hazard to the fetus. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Risk of Neurologic Symptoms: Neurocysticercosis patients may experience cerebral hypertensive episodes, seizures or focal neurologic deficits after initiation of therapy; begin appropriate steroid and anticonvulsant therapy. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Risk of Retinal Damage in Retinal Cysticercosis: Cases of retinal involvement have been reported; examine the patient for the presence of retinal lesions before initiating therapy for neurocysticercosis. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hepatic Effects. Elevations of liver enzymes may occur. Monitor liver enzymes before the start of each treatment cycle and at least every 2 weeks while on ALBENZA therapy and discontinue if clinically significant elevations occur. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Bone Marrow Suppression



  Fatalities associated with the use of ALBENZA have been reported due to granulocytopenia or pancytopenia ALBENZA may cause bone marrow suppression, aplastic anemia, and agranulocytosis. Monitor blood counts at the beginning of each 28-day cycle of therapy, and every 2 weeks while on therapy with ALBENZA in all patients. Patients with liver disease and patients with hepatic echinococcosis are at increased risk for bone marrow suppression and warrant more frequent monitoring of blood counts. Discontinue ALBENZA if clinically significant decreases in blood cell counts occur.



    5.2 Teratogenic Effects



  ALBENZA may cause fetal harm and should not be used in pregnant women except in clinical circumstances where no alternative management is appropriate. Obtain pregnancy test prior to prescribing ALBENZA to women of reproductive potential. Advise women of reproductive potential to use effective birth control for the duration of ALBENZA therapy and for one month after end of therapy. Immediately discontinue ALBENZA if a patient becomes pregnant and apprise the patient of the potential hazard to the fetus [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )  ].



    5.3 Risk of Neurologic Symptoms in Neurocysticercosis



  Patients being treated for neurocysticercosis should receive steroid and anticonvulsant therapy to prevent neurological symptoms (e.g. seizures, increased intracranial pressure and focal signs) as a result of an inflammatory reaction caused by death of the parasite within the brain.



    5.4 Risk of Retinal Damage in Patients with Retinal Neurocysticercosis



  Cysticercosis may involve the retina. Before initiating therapy for neurocysticercosis, examine the patient for the presence of retinal lesions. If such lesions are visualized, weigh the need for anticysticeral therapy against the possibility of retinal damage resulting from inflammatory damage caused by ALBENZA-induced death of the parasite.



    5.5 Hepatic Effects



  In clinical trials, treatment with ALBENZA has been associated with mild to moderate elevations of hepatic enzymes in approximately 16% of patients. These elevations have generally returned to normal upon discontinuation of therapy. There have also been case reports of acute liver failure of uncertain causality and hepatitis [ see Adverse Reactions (  6  )  ].



 Monitor liver enzymes (transaminases) before the start of each treatment cycle and at least every 2 weeks during treatment. If hepatic enzymes exceed twice the upper limit of normal, consideration should be given to discontinuing ALBENZA therapy based on individual patient circumstances. Restarting ALBENZA treatment in patients whose hepatic enzymes have normalized off treatment is an individual decision that should take into account the risk/benefit of further ALBENZA usage. Perform laboratory tests frequently if ALBENZA treatment is restarted.



 Patients with elevated liver enzyme test results are at increased risk for hepatotoxicity and bone marrow suppression [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ]. Discontinue therapy if liver enzymes are significantly increased or if clinically significant decreases in blood cell counts occur.



    5.6 Unmasking of Neurocysticercosis in Hydatid Patients



  Undiagnosed neurocysticercosis may be uncovered in patients treated with ALBENZA for other conditions. Patients with epidemiologic factors who are at risk for neurocysticercosis should be evaluated prior to initiation of therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
