<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="albumin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions seen in clinical trials (greater than or equal to 5% incidence) were anaphylactoid type reactions.



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Octapharma USA Inc. at phone # 866-766-4860 and/or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.



 

  6.1 General

  The most serious events are anaphylactic shock, circulatory failure, cardiac failure, and pulmonary edema.



 The most common adverse events are anaphylactoid type of reactions.



 Adverse reactions for ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25% normally resolve when the infusion rate is slowed down or the infusion is stopped. In case of severe reactions, the infusion should be stopped and appropriate treatment should be initiated.



   6.2 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trial of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 A prospective, double-blind parallel-group study was performed with ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25%. The trial compared the efficacy and safety of ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25% versus a licensed human albumin 25% solution in preventing central volume depletion after paracentesis due to cirrhotic ascites.



 In total, 17 subjects (12 males, 5 females; median age 53 years, range 35-75) received study infusions (10 subjects received ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25% infusions and 7 subjects received the comparator drug. The maximum exposure was 3 infusions (5 subjects in the ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25% treatment group and 4 subjects in the comparator group). The dose administered was 8 grams of study product for every 1000 mL of ascites removed.



 Table 1 lists all adverse events (AEs) that occurred in more than 5% of subjects, irrespective of causality.



   Table 1 Adverse Events in &gt;5% of Subjects, Irrespective of Causality  




                            ALBUMIN(HUMAN) 25%No. of Subjects Reporting [n=10]  Comparator (human albumin 25%)No. of Subjects Reporting [n=7]   
  
  Urinary tract infection    3                          3                          
  Nausea                     2                          1                          
  Abdominal discomfort       1                          1                          
        6.3 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ALBUMIN (HUMAN) (any strength). Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency.



   Table 2 Adverse reactions observed for ALBUMIN HUMAN (any strength) during post-marketing phase (in decreasing order of severity)  




 Observed Adverse Reactions   
  
  anaphylactic shock         
  cardiac failure            
  loss of consciousness      
  circulatory failure        
  hypersensitivity           
  congestive heart failure    
  pulmonary edema            
  dyspnea                    
  hypotension                
  hypertension               
  tachycardia                
  bradycardia                
  vomiting                   
  urticaria                  
  angioneurotic edema        
  rash erythematous          
  confusional state          
  headache                   
  chills                     
  pyrexia                    
  flushing                   
  nausea                     
  pruritus                   
  hyperhidrosis              
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    EXCERPT:   Hypersensitivity or allergic reactions have been observed, and may in some cases progress to severe anaphylaxis. Epinephrine should be available immediately to treat any acute hypersensitivity reaction. (5.1)



 Hypervolemia: Use with caution in patients who are at risk of hypervolemia or hemodilution. Stop infusion if signs of cardiovascular overload occur. (5.2)



 Electrolyte imbalances have been observed. Monitor electrolyte status. (5.3)



 Ensure adequate substitution of other blood constituents. Monitor coagulation status and hematocrit. (5.4)



 Hypotension has been observed. Monitor hemodynamic performance. (5.5)



 Do not dilute solution with sterile water for injection. (5.6)



 This product is made from human plasma and may contain infectious agents, e.g., viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent. (5.7)



 



   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Hypersensitivity or allergic reactions have been observed, and may in some cases progress to severe anaphylaxis. Epinephrine should be available immediately to treat any acute hypersensitivity reaction.



    5.2 Hypervolemia/Hemodilution



  Hypervolemia may occur if the dosage and rate of infusion are not adjusted to the patient's volume status. At the first clinical signs of possible cardiovascular overload, e.g., headache, dyspnea, increased blood pressure, jugular venous distention, elevated central venous pressure, pulmonary edema, the infusion should be stopped immediately and the patient reevaluated. Albumin should be used with caution in conditions where hypervolemia and its consequences or hemodilution could represent a special risk for the patient. Examples of such conditions are:



 *  Decompensated cardiac insufficiency 
 *  Hypertension 
 *  Esophageal varices 
 *  Pulmonary edema 
 *  Hemorrhagic diathesis 
 *  Severe anemia 
 *  Renal and post-renal anuria. 
       5.3 Electrolyte Imbalance
 

  20-25% Albumin (Human) is relatively low in electrolytes compared to the 4-5% Albumin (Human) solutions. When albumin is given, monitor the electrolyte status of the patient and take appropriate steps taken to restore or maintain the electrolyte balance.



    5.4 Coagulation Abnormalities



  If comparatively large volumes are to be replaced, monitoring of coagulation and hematocrit is necessary. Ensure adequate substitution of other blood constituents (coagulation factors, electrolytes, platelets and erythrocytes).



    5.5 Laboratory Monitoring



  If ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25% is to be administered, monitor hemodynamic performance regularly; this may include:



 *  Arterial blood pressure and pulse rate 
 *  Central venous pressure 
 *  Pulmonary artery occlusion pressure 
 *  Urine output 
 *  Electrolytes 
 *  Hematocrit/hemoglobin. 
       5.6 Application Precautions
 

  ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25% must not be diluted with sterile water for injection as this may cause hemolysis in recipients.



    5.7 Infection Risk from Human Plasma



  This product is a derivative of human plasma. Based on effective donor screening and product manufacturing processes it carries an extremely remote risk for transmission of viral diseases. A theoretical risk for transmission of Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease (CJD) also is considered extremely remote. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have been identified for ALBUMIN (HUMAN) 25%.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
