<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aldactone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions have been reported and, within each category (body system), are listed in order of decreasing severity.



   Digestive:  Gastric bleeding, ulceration, gastritis, diarrhea and cramping, nausea, vomiting.



   Reproductive:  Gynecomastia (see    Precautions    ), inability to achieve or maintain erection, irregular menses or amenorrhea, postmenopausal bleeding, breast pain. Carcinoma of the breast has been reported in patients taking ALDACTONE but a cause and effect relationship has not been established.



   Hematologic:  Leukopenia (including agranulocytosis), thrombocytopenia.



   Hypersensitivity:  Fever, urticaria, maculopapular or erythematous cutaneous eruptions, anaphylactic reactions, vasculitis.



   Metabolism:  Hyperkalemia, electrolyte disturbances (see    Warnings    and    Precautions  ).  



   Musculoskeletal:  Leg cramps.



   Nervous system /psychiatric:  Lethargy, mental confusion, ataxia, dizziness, headache, drowsiness.



   Liver / biliary:  A very few cases of mixed cholestatic/hepatocellular toxicity, with one reported fatality, have been reported with ALDACTONE administration.



   Renal:  Renal dysfunction (including renal failure).



   Skin:  Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), drug rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), alopecia, pruritis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

    WARNING  

  ALDACTONE has been shown to be a tumorigen in chronic toxicity studies in rats (see     Precautions    ). ALDACTONE should be used only in those conditions described under     Indications and Usage  .   Unnecessary use of this drug should be avoided.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
