<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aldara" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;28%) are application site reactions or local skin reactions: itching, burning, erythema, flaking/scaling/dryness, scabbing/crusting, edema, induration, excoriation, erosion, ulceration. Other reported reactions (&gt;= 1%) include fatigue, fever, and headache (  6.1  ,  6.2  ,  6.3  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Medicis, The Dermatology Company at 1-800-328-0255 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience: Actinic Keratosis

  The data described below reflect exposure to Aldara Cream or vehicle in 436 subjects enrolled in two double-blind, vehicle-controlled studies. Subjects applied Aldara Cream or vehicle to a 25 cm  2  contiguous treatment area on the face or scalp 2 times per week for 16 weeks.



 Table 2: Selected Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt; 1% of Aldara-Treated Subjects and at a Greater Frequency than with Vehicle in the Combined Studies (Actinic Keratosis) 
   Preferred Term                         Aldara Cream (n=215)          Vehicle (n=221)              
  
  Application Site Reaction              71 (33%)                      32 (14%)                      
  Upper Resp Tract Infection             33 (15%)                      27 (12%)                      
  Sinusitis                              16 (7%)                       14 (6%)                       
  Headache                               11 (5%)                       7 (3%)                        
  Carcinoma Squamous                     8 (4%)                        5 (2%)                        
  Diarrhea                               6 (3%)                        2 (1%)                        
  Eczema                                 4 (2%)                        3 (1%)                        
  Back Pain                              3 (1%)                        2 (1%)                        
  Fatigue                                3 (1%)                        2 (1%)                        
  Fibrillation Atrial                    3 (1%)                        2 (1%)                        
  Infection Viral                        3 (1%)                        2 (1%)                        
  Dizziness                              3 (1%)                        1 (&lt;1%)                       
  Vomiting                               3 (1%)                        1 (&lt;1%)                       
  Urinary Tract Infection                3 (1%)                        1 (&lt;1%)                       
  Fever                                  3 (1%)                        0 (0%)                        
  Rigors                                 3 (1%)                        0 (0%)                        
  Alopecia                               3 (1%)                        0 (0%)                        
        Table 3: Application Site Reactions Reported by &gt; 1% of Aldara-Treated Subjects and at a Greater Frequency than with Vehicle in the Combined Studies (Actinic Keratosis) 
   Included Term                          Aldara Cream (n=215)          Vehicle (n=221)              
  
  Itching                                44 (20%)                      17 (8%)                       
  Burning                                13 (6%)                       4 (2%)                        
  Bleeding                               7 (3%)                        1 (&lt;1%)                       
  Stinging                               6 (3%)                        2 (1%)                        
  Pain                                   6 (3%)                        2 (1%)                        
  Induration                             5 (2%)                        3 (1%)                        
  Tenderness                             4 (2%)                        3 (1%)                        
  Irritation                             4 (2%)                        0 (0%)                        
         Local skin reactions were collected independently of the adverse reaction "application site reaction" in an effort to provide a better picture of the specific types of local reactions that might be seen. The most frequently reported local skin reactions were erythema, flaking/scaling/dryness, and scabbing/crusting. The prevalence and severity of local skin reactions that occurred during controlled studies are shown in the following table.
 

 Table 4: Local Skin Reactions in the Treatment Area as Assessed by the Investigator (Actinic Keratosis) 
                                 Aldara Cream (n=215)      Vehicle (n=220)     
                                 All Grades          Severe              All Grades          Severe             
  
  Erythema                      209 (97%)           38 (18%)            206 (93%)           5 (2%)              
  Flaking/Scaling/Dryness       199 (93%)           16 (7%)             199 (91%)           7 (3%)              
  Scabbing/Crusting             169 (79%)           18 (8%)             92 (42%)            4 (2%)              
  Edema                         106 (49%)           0 (0%)              22 (10%)            0 (0%)              
  Erosion/Ulceration            103 (48%)           5 (2%)              20 (9%)             0 (0%)              
  Weeping/Exudate               45 (22%)            0 (0%)              3 (1%)              0 (0%)              
  Vesicles                      19 (9%)             0 (0%)              2 (1%)              0 (0%)              
           The adverse reactions that most frequently resulted in clinical intervention (e.g., rest periods, withdrawal from study) were local skin and application site reactions. Overall, in the clinical studies, 2% (5/215) of subjects discontinued for local skin/application site reactions. Of the 215 subjects treated, 35 subjects (16%) on Aldara Cream and 3 of 220 subjects (1%) on vehicle cream had at least one rest period. Of these Aldara Cream subjects, 32 (91%) resumed therapy after a rest period.
 

 In the AK studies, 22 of 678 (3.2%) of Aldara-treated subjects developed treatment site infections that required a rest period off Aldara Cream and were treated with antibiotics (19 with oral and 3 with topical).



 Of the 206 Aldara subjects with both baseline and 8-week post-treatment scarring assessments, 6 (2.9%) had a greater degree of scarring scores at 8-weeks post-treatment than at baseline.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience: Superficial Basal Cell Carcinoma

  The data described below reflect exposure to Aldara Cream or vehicle in 364 subjects enrolled in two double-blind, vehicle-controlled studies. Subjects applied Aldara Cream or vehicle 5 times per week for 6 weeks. The incidence of adverse reactions reported by &gt; 1% of subjects during the studies is summarized below.



 Table 5: Selected Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt; 1% of Aldara-Treated Subjects and at a Greater Frequency than with Vehicle in the Combined Studies (Superficial Basal Cell Carcinoma) 
   Preferred Term                          Aldara Cream (n=185)    N%      Vehicle (n=179)    N%       
  
  Application Site Reaction               52 (28%)                     5 (3%)                       
  Headache                                14 (8%)                      4 (2%)                       
  Back Pain                               7 (4%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Upper Resp Tract Infection              6 (3%)                       2 (1%)                       
  Rhinitis                                5 (3%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Lymphadenopathy                         5 (3%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Fatigue                                 4 (2%)                       2 (1%)                       
  Sinusitis                               4 (2%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Dyspepsia                               3 (2%)                       2 (1%)                       
  Coughing                                3 (2%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Fever                                   3 (2%)                       0 (0%)                       
  Dizziness                               2 (1%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Anxiety                                 2 (1%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Pharyngitis                             2 (1%)                       1 (&lt;1%)                      
  Chest Pain                              2 (1%)                       0 (0%)                       
  Nausea                                  2 (1%)                       0 (0%)                       
         The most frequently reported adverse reactions were local skin and application site reactions including erythema, edema, induration, erosion, flaking/scaling, scabbing/crusting, itching and burning at the application site. The incidence of application site reactions reported by &gt; 1% of the subjects during the 6 week treatment period is summarized in Table 6.
 

 Table 6: Application Site Reactions Reported by &gt; 1% of Aldara-Treated Subjects and at a Greater Frequency than with Vehicle in the Combined Studies (Superficial Basal Cell Carcinoma) 
   Included Term                          Aldara Cream (n=185)          Vehicle (n=179)              
  
  Itching                                30 (16%)                      1 (1%)                        
  Burning                                11 (6%)                       2 (1%)                        
  Pain                                   6 (3%)                        0 (0%)                        
  Bleeding                               4 (2%)                        0 (0%)                        
  Erythema                               3 (2%)                        0 (0%)                        
  Papule(s)                              3 (2%)                        0 (0%)                        
  Tenderness                             2 (1%)                        0 (0%)                        
  Infection                              2 (1%)                        0 (0%)                        
         Local skin reactions were collected independently of the adverse reaction "application site reaction" in an effort to provide a better picture of the specific types of local reactions that might be seen. The prevalence and severity of local skin reactions that occurred during controlled studies are shown in the following table.
 

 Table 7: Local Skin Reactions in the Treatment Area as Assessed by the Investigator (Superficial Basal Cell Carcinoma) 
                                 Aldara Cream (n=184)      Vehicle (n=178)     
                                 All Grades          Severe              All Grades          Severe             
  
  Erythema                      184 (100%)          57 (31%)            173 (97%)           4 (2%)              
  Flaking/Scaling               167 (91%)           7 (4%)              135 (76%)           0 (0%)              
  Induration                    154 (84%)           11 (6%)             94 (53%)            0 (0%)              
  Scabbing/Crusting             152 (83%)           35 (19%)            61 (34%)            0 (0%)              
  Edema                         143 (78%)           13 (7%)             64 (36%)            0 (0%)              
  Erosion                       122 (66%)           23 (13%)            25 (14%)            0 (0%)              
  Ulceration                    73 (40%)            11 (6%)             6 (3%)              0 (0%)              
  Vesicles                      57 (31%)            3 (2%)              4 (2%)              0 (0%)              
           The adverse reactions that most frequently resulted in clinical intervention (e.g., rest periods, withdrawal from study) were local skin and application site reactions; 10% (19/185) of subjects received rest periods. The average number of doses not received per subject due to rest periods was 7 doses with a range of 2 to 22 doses; 79% of subjects (15/19) resumed therapy after a rest period. Overall, in the clinical studies, 2% (4/185) of subjects discontinued for local skin/application site reactions.
 

 In the sBCC studies, 17 of 1266 (1.3%) Aldara-treated subjects developed treatment site infections that required a rest period and treatment with antibiotics.



   6.3 Clinical Trials Experience: External Genital Warts

  In controlled clinical trials for genital warts, the most frequently reported adverse reactions were local skin and application site reactions.



 Some subjects also reported systemic reactions. Overall, 1.2% (4/327) of the subjects discontinued due to local skin/application site reactions. The incidence and severity of local skin reactions during controlled clinical trials are shown in Table 8.



 Table 8: Local Skin Reactions in the Treatment Area as Assessed by the Investigator (External Genital Warts) 
                  Aldara Cream      Vehicle     
                  Females (n=114)      Males (n=156)      Females (n=99)      Males (n=157)     
                  All Grades      Severe       All Grades      Severe       All Grades      Severe       All Grades      Severe      
  
  Erythema       74 (65%)     4 (4%)       90 (58%)     6 (4%)       21 (21%)     0 (0%)       34 (22%)     0 (0%)       
  Erosion        35 (31%)     1 (1%)       47 (30%)     2 (1%)       8 (8%)       0 (0%)       10 (6%)      0 (0%)       
  Excoriation/Flaking    21 (18%)     0 (0%)       40 (26%)     1 (1%)       8 (8%)       0 (0%)       12 (8%)      0 (0%)       
  Edema          20 (18%)     1 (1%)       19 (12%)     0 (0%)       5 (5%)       0 (0%)       1 (1%)       0 (0%)       
  Scabbing       4 (4%)       0 (0%)       20 (13%)     0 (0%)       0 (0%)       0 (0%)       4 (3%)       0 (0%)       
  Induration     6 (5%)       0 (0%)       11 (7%)      0 (0%)       2 (2%)       0 (0%)       3 (2%)       0 (0%)       
  Ulceration     9 (8%)       3 (3%)       7 (4%)       0 (0%)       1 (1%)       0 (0%)       1 (1%)       0 (0%)       
  Vesicles       3 (3%)       0 (0%)       3 (2%)       0 (0%)       0 (0%)       0 (0%)       0 (0%)       0 (0%)       
               Remote site skin reactions were also reported. The severe remote site skin reactions reported for females were erythema (3%), ulceration (2%), and edema (1%); and for males, erosion (2%), and erythema, edema, induration, and excoriation/flaking (each 1%).
 

 Selected adverse reactions judged to be probably or possibly related to Aldara Cream are listed below.



 Table 9: Selected Treatment Related Reactions (External Genital Warts) 
                                   Females             Males             
                                   Aldara Cream    (n=117)      Vehicle    (n=103)      Aldara Cream    (n=156)      Vehicle    (n=158)     
  
  Application Site Disorders:                                                                                   
  Application Site Reactions                                                                                    
  Wart Site:                                                                                                    
  Itching                         38 (32%)            21 (20%)           34 (22%)            16 (10%)           
  Burning                         30 (26%)            12 (12%)           14 (9%)             8 (5%)             
  Pain                            9 (8%)              2 (2%)             3 (2%)              1 (1%)             
  Soreness                        3 (3%)              0 (0%)             0 (0%)              1 (1%)             
  Fungal InfectionIncidences reported without regard to causality with Aldara Cream.    13 (11%)            3 (3%)             3 (2%)              1 (1%)             
  Systemic Reactions:                                                                                           
  Headache                        5 (4%)              3 (3%)             8 (5%)              3 (2%)             
  Influenza-like symptoms         4 (3%)              2 (2%)             2 (1%)              0 (0%)             
  Myalgia                         1 (1%)              0 (0%)             2 (1%)              1 (1%)             
           Adverse reactions judged to be possibly or probably related to Aldara Cream and reported by more than 1% of subjects included:
 

   Application Site Disorders:  burning, hypopigmentation, irritation, itching, pain, rash, sensitivity, soreness, stinging, tenderness



   Remote Site Reactions:  bleeding, burning, itching, pain, tenderness, tinea cruris



   Body as a Whole:  fatigue, fever, influenza-like symptoms



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders:  headache



   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders:  diarrhea



   Musculo-Skeletal System Disorders:  myalgia



   6.4 Clinical Trials Experience: Dermal Safety Studies

  Provocative repeat insult patch test studies involving induction and challenge phases produced no evidence that Aldara Cream causes photoallergenicity or contact sensitization in healthy skin; however, cumulative irritancy testing revealed the potential for Aldara Cream to cause irritation, and application site reactions were reported in the clinical studies  [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  .



   6.5 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Aldara Cream. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Application Site Disorders:  tingling at the application site



   Body as a Whole:  angioedema



   Cardiovascular:  capillary leak syndrome, cardiac failure, cardiomyopathy, pulmonary edema, arrhythmias (tachycardia, atrial fibrillation, palpitations), chest pain, ischemia, myocardial infarction, syncope



   Endocrine:  thyroiditis



   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders:  abdominal pain



   Hematological:  decreases in red cell, white cell and platelet counts (including idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura), lymphoma



   Hepatic:  abnormal liver function



   Infections and Infestations:  herpes simplex



   Musculo-Skeletal System Disorders:  arthralgia



   Neuropsychiatric:  agitation, cerebrovascular accident, convulsions (including febrile convulsions), depression, insomnia, multiple sclerosis aggravation, paresis, suicide



   Respiratory:  dyspnea



   Urinary System Disorders:  proteinuria, dysuria, urinary retention



   Skin and Appendages:  exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme, hyperpigmentation, hypertrophic scar



   Vascular:  Henoch-Schonlein purpura syndrome
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Intense local inflammatory reactions can occur (e.g., skin weeping, erosion). Dosing interruption may be required (  2  ,  5.1  ,  6  ) 
 *    Severe local inflammatory reactions of the female external genitalia can lead to severe vulvar swelling. Severe vulvar swelling can lead to urinary retention; dosing should be interrupted or discontinued. 
 *    Flu-like systemic signs and symptoms including malaise, fever, nausea, myalgias and rigors may occur. Dosing interruption may be required (  2  ,  5.2  ,  6  ) 
 *    Avoid exposure to sunlight and sunlamps. Wear sunscreen daily (  5.3  ). 
 *    Safety and efficacy have not been established for repeat courses of treatment to the same area for AK. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Aldara Cream is not recommended for treatment of BCC subtypes other than the superficial variant, i.e., sBCC. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Treatment of urethral, intra-vaginal, cervical, rectal or intra-anal viral disease is not recommended. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Safety and efficacy in immunosuppressed patients have not been established (  1.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Local Inflammatory Reactions



  Intense local inflammatory reactions including skin weeping or erosion can occur after few applications of Aldara Cream and may require an interruption of dosing [see  Dosage and Administration (2)    and   Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  . Aldara Cream has the potential to exacerbate inflammatory conditions of the skin, including chronic graft versus host disease.



 Severe local inflammatory reactions of the female external genitalia can lead to severe vulvar swelling.



 Severe vulvar swelling can lead to urinary retention. Dosing should be interrupted or discontinued for severe vulvar swelling.



 Administration of Aldara Cream is not recommended until the skin is completely healed from any previous drug or surgical treatment.



    5.2 Systemic Reactions



  Flu-like signs and symptoms may accompany, or even precede, local inflammatory reactions and may include malaise, fever, nausea, myalgias and rigors. An interruption of dosing should be considered [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ].  



    5.3 Ultraviolet Light Exposure



  Exposure to sunlight (including sunlamps) should be avoided or minimized during use of Aldara Cream because of concern for heightened sunburn susceptibility. Patients should be warned to use protective clothing (e.g., a hat) when using Aldara Cream. Patients with sunburn should be advised not to use Aldara Cream until fully recovered. Patients who may have considerable sun exposure, e.g., due to their occupation, and those patients with inherent sensitivity to sunlight should exercise caution when using Aldara Cream.



 Aldara Cream shortened the time to skin tumor formation in an animal photoco-carcinogenicity study [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . The enhancement of ultraviolet carcinogenicity is not necessarily dependent on phototoxic mechanisms. Therefore, patients should minimize or avoid natural or artificial sunlight exposure.



    5.4 Unevaluated Uses: Actinic Keratosis



  Safety and efficacy have not been established for Aldara Cream in the treatment of actinic keratosis with repeated use, i.e. more than one treatment course, in the same area.



 The safety of Aldara Cream applied to areas of skin greater than 25 cm  2  (e.g., 5 cm * 5 cm) for the treatment of actinic keratosis has not been established [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.5 Unevaluated Uses: Superficial Basal Cell Carcinoma



  The safety and efficacy of Aldara Cream have not been established for other types of basal cell carcinomas (BCC), including nodular and morpheaform (fibrosing or sclerosing) types. Aldara Cream is not recommended for treatment of BCC subtypes other than the superficial variant (i.e., sBCC)  . Patients with sBCC treated with Aldara Cream should have regular follow-up of the treatment site [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 The safety and efficacy of treating sBCC lesions on the face, head and anogenital area have not been established.



    5.6 Unevaluated Uses: External Genital Warts



  Aldara Cream has not been evaluated for the treatment of urethral, intra-vaginal, cervical, rectal, or intra-anal human papilloma viral disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
