<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="alecensa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Hepatotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Interstitial Lung Disease (ILD)/Pneumonitis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Bradycardia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Severe Myalgia and Creatine Phosphokinase (CPK) Elevation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Embryo-Fetal Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=20%) were fatigue, constipation, edema and myalgia. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genentech at 1-888-835-2555 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of ALECENSA was evaluated in 253 patients with ALK-positive non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) treated with ALECENSA 600 mg orally twice daily in two clinical trials, Studies 1 and 2. The median duration of exposure to ALECENSA was 9.3 months. One hundred sixty-nine patients (67%) were exposed to ALECENSA for more than 6 months, and 100 patients (40%) for more than one year. The population characteristics were: median age 53 years, age less than 65 (86%), female (55%), White (74%), Asian (18%), NSCLC adenocarcinoma histology (96%), never or former smoker (98%), ECOG Performance Status (PS) 0 or 1 (91%), and prior chemotherapy treatment (78%).



 Serious adverse reactions occurred in 19% of patients; the most frequently reported serious adverse reactions were pulmonary embolism (1.2%), dyspnea (1.2%), and hyperbilirubinemia (1.2%). Fatal adverse reactions occurred in 2.8% of patients and included hemorrhage (0.8%), intestinal perforation (0.4%), dyspnea (0.4%), pulmonary embolism (0.4%), and endocarditis (0.4%). Permanent discontinuation of ALECENSA for adverse reactions occurred in 6% of patients. The most frequent adverse reactions that led to permanent discontinuation were hyperbilirubinemia (1.6%), increased ALT levels (1.6%), and increased AST levels (1.2%). Overall, 23% of patients initiating treatment at the recommended dose required at least one dose reduction. The median time to first dose reduction was 48 days. The most frequent adverse reactions that led to dose reductions or interruptions were elevations in bilirubin (6%), CPK (4.3%), ALT (4.0%), and AST (2.8%), and vomiting (2.8%).



   Table 3  summarizes adverse reactions in Studies 1 and 2.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 10% (All Grades) or &gt;= 2% (Grade 3-4) of Patients in Studies 1 and 2 
 Adverse Reactions                             ALECENSAN=253             
 All Grades (%)                               Grades 3-4 (%)             
  
 Fatigue                                            41                                 1.2                  
 Constipation                                       34                                  0                   
 Edema                                              30                                 0.8                  
 Myalgia                                            29                                 1.2                  
 Cough                                              19                                  0                   
 Rash                                               18                                 0.4                  
 Nausea                                             18                                  0                   
 Headache                                           17                                 0.8                  
 Diarrhea                                           16                                 1.2                  
 Dyspnea                                            16                                 3.6                  
 Back pain                                          12                                  0                   
 Vomiting                                           12                                 0.4                  
 Increased weight                                   11                                 0.4                  
 Vision disorder                                    10                                  0                   
             Additional safety information from clinical trial experience  
 

 Photosensitivity occurred in 9.9% of patients exposed to ALECENSA in Studies 1 and 2. Patients were advised to avoid sun exposure and to use broad-spectrum sunscreen. The incidence of Grade 2 photosensitivity was 0.4%; the remaining events were Grade 1 in severity.



   Table 4  summarizes laboratory abnormalities of ALECENSA in Studies 1 and 2. 



 Table 4. Laboratory Abnormalities Occurring in &gt;20% of Patients in Studies 1 and 2 
 Parameter                                        Alectinib N=250           
 All Grades (%)                                    Grades 3-4 (%)           
  
   Chemistry                                
   Increased AST                                         51                             3.6                 
   Increased Alkaline Phosphatase                        47                             1.2                 
   Increased CPK                                         43                             4.6                 
   Hyperbilirubinemia                                    39                             2.4                 
   Hyperglycemia                                         36                             2.0                 
   Increased ALT                                         34                             4.8                 
   Hypocalcemia                                          32                             0.4                 
   Hypokalemia                                           29                             4.0                 
   Increased Creatinine                                  28                              0                  
   Hypophosphatemia                                      21                             2.8                 
   Hyponatremia                                          20                             2.0                 
   Hematology                               
   Anemia                                                56                             2.0                 
   Lymphopenia                                           22                             4.6                 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hepatotoxicity: Monitor liver laboratory tests every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of treatment, and then periodically during treatment. In case of severe ALT, AST, or bilirubin elevations, withhold, then reduce dose, or permanently discontinue ALECENSA. (  2.2  ,  5.1  ) 
 *  Interstitial Lung Disease (ILD)/Pneumonitis: Occurred in 0.4% of patients. Immediately withhold ALECENSA in patients diagnosed with ILD/pneumonitis and permanently discontinue if no other potential causes of ILD/pneumonitis have been identified. (  2.2  ,  5.2  ) 
 *  Bradycardia: Monitor heart rate and blood pressure regularly. If symptomatic, withhold ALECENSA then reduce dose, or permanently discontinue. (  2.2  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  Severe Myalgia and Creatine Phosphokinase (CPK) Elevation: Occurred in 1.2% and 4.6% of patients, respectively. Assess CPK every 2 weeks during the first month of treatment and in patients reporting unexplained muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness. In case of severe CPK elevations, withhold, then resume or reduce dose. (  2.2  ,  5.4  ) 
 *  Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: ALECENSA can cause fetal harm. Advise females of reproductive potential of the potential risk to a fetus and to use effective contraception. (  5.5  ,  8.1    8.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatotoxicity



  Elevations of AST greater than 5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) occurred in 3.6% of patients, and elevations of ALT greater than 5 times the ULN occurred in 4.8% of patients. Elevations of bilirubin greater than 3 times the ULN occurred in 2.8% of patients. The majority (73% of the patients with hepatic transaminase elevations and 49% of the patients with bilirubin elevations) of these events occurred during the first 2 months of treatment. Four patients discontinued ALECENSA for Grade 3-4 AST and/or ALT elevations, and 3 patients discontinued ALECENSA for Grade 3 bilirubin elevations. Two patients with Grade 3-4 AST/ALT elevations had documented drug induced liver injury by liver biopsy.



 Monitor liver function tests including ALT, AST, and total bilirubin every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of treatment, then periodically during treatment, with more frequent testing in patients who develop transaminase and bilirubin elevations. Based on the severity of the adverse drug reaction, withhold ALECENSA and resume at a reduced dose, or permanently discontinue ALECENSA as described in  Table 2   [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ].  



    5.2 Interstitial Lung Disease (ILD)/Pneumonitis



  Severe ILD (Grade 3) occurred in one (0.4%) of 253 patients exposed to ALECENSA in clinical trials.



 Promptly investigate for ILD/pneumonitis in any patient who presents with worsening of respiratory symptoms indicative of ILD/pneumonitis (e.g., dyspnea, cough and fever).



 Immediately withhold ALECENSA treatment in patients diagnosed with ILD/pneumonitis and permanently discontinue ALECENSA if no other potential causes of ILD/pneumonitis have been identified [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  .



    5.3 Bradycardia



  Symptomatic bradycardia can occur with ALECENSA. Cases of bradycardia (7.5%) have been reported in patients treated with ALECENSA. Twenty percent of 221 patients treated with ALECENSA for whom serial ECGs were available had heart rates of less than 50 beats per minute (bpm).



 Monitor heart rate and blood pressure regularly. Dose modification is not required in cases of asymptomatic bradycardia. In cases of symptomatic bradycardia that is not life-threatening, withhold ALECENSA until recovery to asymptomatic bradycardia or to a heart rate of 60 bpm or above and evaluate concomitant medications known to cause bradycardia, as well as anti-hypertensive medications. If attributable to a concomitant medication, resume ALECENSA at a reduced dose (see  Table 1  ) upon recovery to asymptomatic bradycardia or to a heart rate of 60 bpm or above, with frequent monitoring as clinically indicated. Permanently discontinue ALECENSA in case of recurrence. Permanently discontinue ALECENSA in cases of life-threatening bradycardia if no contributing concomitant medication is identified [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ].  



    5.4 Severe Myalgia and Creatine Phosphokinase (CPK) Elevation



  Myalgia or musculoskeletal pain occurred in 29% of patients in Study 1 and Study 2. The incidence of Grade 3 myalgia/musculoskeletal pain was 1.2%. Dose modifications for myalgia/musculoskeletal pain were required in 0.8% of patients.



 Elevations of CPK occurred in 43% of 218 patients with CPK laboratory data available in Study 1 and Study 2. The incidence of Grade 3 elevations of CPK was 4.6%. Median time to Grade 3 CPK elevation was 14 days (interquartile range 13-14 days). Dose modifications for elevation of CPK occurred in 5.0% of patients.



 Advise patients to report any unexplained muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness. Assess CPK levels every two weeks for the first month of treatment and as clinically indicated in patients reporting symptoms. Based on the severity of the CPK elevation, withhold ALECENSA, then resume or reduce dose [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ].  



    5.5 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  Based on findings from animal studies and its mechanism of action, ALECENSA can cause fetal harm when administered to pregnant women. Administration of alectinib to pregnant rats and rabbits during the period of organogenesis resulted in embryo-fetal toxicity and abortion at maternally toxic doses with exposures approximately 2.7-times those observed in humans with alectinib 600 mg twice daily. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus.



 Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with ALECENSA and for 1 week following the final dose [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  and  8.3)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.1  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
