<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="alimta" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=20%) with single-agent use are fatigue, nausea, and anorexia. Additional common adverse reactions when used in combination with cisplatin include vomiting, neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, stomatitis/pharyngitis, thrombocytopenia, and constipation. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In clinical trials, the most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=20%) during therapy with ALIMTA as a single-agent were fatigue, nausea, and anorexia. Additional common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=20%) during therapy with ALIMTA when used in combination with cisplatin included vomiting, neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, stomatitis/pharyngitis, thrombocytopenia, and constipation.



     Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) - ALIMTA in Combination with Cisplatin  



   Table 4  provides the frequency and severity of adverse reactions that have been reported in &gt;5% of 839 patients with NSCLC who were randomized to study and received ALIMTA plus cisplatin and 830 patients with NSCLC who were randomized to study and received gemcitabine plus cisplatin. All patients received study therapy as initial treatment for locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC and patients in both treatment groups were fully supplemented with folic acid and vitamin B12.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions in Fully Supplemented Patients Receiving ALIMTA plus Cisplatin in NSCLCa 
  a For the purpose of this table a cut off of 5% was used for inclusion of all events where the reporter considered a possible relationship to ALIMTA.    
  b Refer to NCI CTC Criteria version 2.0 for each Grade of toxicity.    
  c According to NCI CTC Criteria version 2.0, this adverse event term should only be reported as Grade 1 or 2.    
  
   Reaction  b                             ALIMTA/cisplatin    (N=839)      Gemcitabine/cisplatin    (N=830)     
   All GradesToxicity (%)                  Grade 3-4Toxicity (%)      All GradesToxicity (%)      Grade 3-4Toxicity (%)     
   All Adverse Reactions                 90               37               91               53                
    Laboratory                                                                                                
     Hematologic                                                                                              
    Anemia                               33               6                46               10                
    Neutropenia                          29               15               38               27                
    Leukopenia                           18               5                21               8                 
    Thrombocytopenia                     10               4                27               13                
     Renal                                                                                                    
    Creatinine elevation                 10               1                7                1                 
    Clinical                                                                                                  
     Constitutional Symptoms                                                                                  
    Fatigue                              43               7                45               5                 
     Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
    Nausea                               56               7                53               4                 
    Vomiting                             40               6                36               6                 
    Anorexia                             27               2                24               1                 
    Constipation                         21               1                20               0                 
    Stomatitis/Pharyngitis               14               1                12               0                 
    Diarrhea                             12               1                13               2                 
    Dyspepsia/Heartburn                  5                0                6                0                 
     Neurology                                                                                                
    Neuropathy-sensory                   9                0                12               1                 
    Taste disturbance                    8                0  c             9                0  c              
     Dermatology/Skin                                                                                         
    Alopecia                             12               0  c             21               1  c              
    Rash/Desquamation                    7                0                8                1                 
           No clinically relevant differences in adverse reactions were seen in patients based on histology.
 

 In addition to the lower incidence of hematologic toxicity on the ALIMTA and cisplatin arm, use of transfusions (RBC and platelet) and hematopoietic growth factors was lower in the ALIMTA and cisplatin arm compared to the gemcitabine and cisplatin arm.



 The following additional adverse reactions were observed in patients with non-small cell lung cancer randomly assigned to receive ALIMTA plus cisplatin.



   Incidence 1% to 5%  



 *      Body as a Whole - febrile neutropenia, infection, pyrexia 
 *      General Disorders - dehydration 
 *      Metabolism and Nutrition - increased AST, increased ALT 
 *      Renal - creatinine clearance decrease, renal failure 
 *      Special Senses - conjunctivitis 
      Incidence Less than 1%  
 

 *      Cardiovascular - arrhythmia 
 *      General Disorders - chest pain 
 *      Metabolism and Nutrition - increased GGT 
 *      Neurology - motor neuropathy 
        Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) - Maintenance  
 

   ALIMTA Maintenance Following Non-ALIMTA Containing, Platinum-Based Induction Therapy  



   Table 5  provides the frequency and severity of adverse reactions reported in &gt;5% of the 438 patients with NSCLC who received ALIMTA maintenance and the 218 patients with NSCLC who received placebo following a platinum-based induction therapy.



 All patients received study therapy immediately following 4 cycles of platinum-based treatment for locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC. Patients in both study arms were fully supplemented with folic acid and vitamin B12.



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions in Patients Receiving ALIMTA versus Placebo in NSCLCa Following Platinum-Based Induction Therapy 
  a For the purpose of this table a cut off of 5% was used for inclusion of all events where the reporter considered a possible relationship to ALIMTA.    
  b Refer to NCI CTCAE Criteria version 3.0 for each Grade of toxicity.    
  
                                                   ALIMTA(N=438)      Placebo(N=218)     
   Reaction  b                                     All GradesToxicity (%)      Grade 3-4Toxicity (%)      All GradesToxicity (%)      Grade 3-4Toxicity (%)     
   All Adverse Reactions                         66            16             37            4               
    Laboratory                                    
     Hematologic                                  
   Anemia                                        15            3              6             1               
   Neutropenia                                   6             3              0             0               
   Leukopenia                                    6             2              1             1               
    Hepatic                                       
   Increased ALT                                 10            0              4             0               
   Increased AST                                 8             0              4             0               
    Clinical                                      
    Constitutional Symptoms                       
   Fatigue                                       25            5              11            1               
    Gastrointestinal                              
   Nausea                                        19            1              6             1               
   Anorexia                                      19            2              5             0               
   Vomiting                                      9             0              1             0               
   Mucositis/stomatitis                          7             1              2             0               
   Diarrhea                                      5             1              3             0               
    Infection                                    5             2              2             0               
    Neurology                                     
   Neuropathy-sensory                            9             1              4             0               
    Dermatology/Skin                              
   Rash/Desquamation                             10            0              3             0               
           No clinically relevant differences in Grade 3/4 adverse reactions were seen in patients based on age, gender, ethnic origin, or histology except a higher incidence of Grade 3/4 fatigue for Caucasian patients compared to non-Caucasian patients (6.5% versus 0.6%).
 

 Safety was assessed by exposure for patients who received at least one dose of ALIMTA (N=438). The incidence of adverse reactions was evaluated for patients who received &lt;=6 cycles of ALIMTA, and compared to patients who received &gt;6 cycles of ALIMTA. Increases in adverse reactions (all grades) were observed with longer exposure; however no clinically relevant differences in Grade 3/4 adverse reactions were seen.



 Consistent with the higher incidence of anemia (all grades) on the ALIMTA arm, use of transfusions (mainly RBC) and erythropoiesis stimulating agents (ESAs; erythropoietin and darbepoetin) were higher in the ALIMTA arm compared to the placebo arm (transfusions 9.5% versus 3.2%, ESAs 5.9% versus 1.8%).



 The following additional adverse reactions were observed in patients with non-small cell lung cancer who received ALIMTA.



   Incidence 1% to 5%  



 *      Dermatology/Skin - alopecia, pruritis/itching 
 *      Gastrointestinal - constipation 
 *      General Disorders - edema, fever (in the absence of neutropenia) 
 *      Hematologic - thrombocytopenia 
 *      Renal - decreased creatinine clearance, increased creatinine, decreased glomerular filtration rate 
 *      Special Senses - ocular surface disease (including conjunctivitis), increased lacrimation 
      Incidence Less than 1%  
 

 *      Cardiovascular - supraventricular arrhythmia 
 *      Dermatology/Skin - erythema multiforme 
 *      General Disorders - febrile neutropenia, allergic reaction/hypersensitivity 
 *      Neurology - motor neuropathy 
 *      Renal - renal failure 
        Continuation of ALIMTA as Maintenance Following ALIMTA Plus Platinum Induction Therapy  
 

   Table 6  provides the frequency and severity of adverse reactions reported in &gt;5% of the 500 patients with non-squamous NSCLC who received at least one cycle of ALIMTA maintenance (n=333) or placebo (n=167) on the continuation maintenance trial.



 The median of maintenance cycles administered to patients receiving one or more doses of maintenance therapy was 4 on both the pemetrexed and placebo arms. Dose reductions for adverse events occurred in 3.3% of patients in the ALIMTA arm and 0.6% in the placebo arm. Dose delays for adverse events occurred in 22% of patients in the ALIMTA arm and 16% in the placebo arm. Patients in both study arms were supplemented with folic acid and vitamin B12.



 Table 6: Selecteda Adverse Reactionsb Occurring in &gt;=5% of Patients Receiving ALIMTA in Nonsquamous NSCLC Following ALIMTA Plus Cisplatin Induction Therapy 
  a Adverse reactions of any severity (all grades) occurring more frequently (&gt;=5%) or Grade 3-4 adverse reactions occurring more frequently (&gt;=2%) in ALIMTA-treated patients compared to those receiving placebo.    
  b NCI CTCAE Criteria version 3.0            
  
   Adverse Reaction Organ System and Term      ALIMTA    (N=333)      Placebo    (N=167)     
   All Grades  a  Toxicity (%)                 Grade 3-4  a  Toxicity (%)      All Grades  a  Toxicity (%)      Grades 3-4  a  Toxicity (%)     
   All Adverse Reactions                     53              17             34               4.8              
    Laboratory                                
     Hematologic                              
    Anemia                                   15              4.8            4.8              0.6              
    Neutropenia                              9               3.9            0.6              0                
    Clinical                                  
     Constitutional Symptoms                  
    Fatigue                                  18              4.5            11               0.6              
     Gastrointestinal                         
    Nausea                                   12              0.3            2.4              0                
    Vomiting                                 6               0              1.8              0                
    Mucositis/stomatitis                     5               0.3            2.4              0                
     General Disorders                        
    Edema                                    5               0              3.6              0                
           Administration of RBC (13% versus 4.8%) and platelet (1.5% versus 0.6%) transfusions, erythropoiesis stimulating agents (12% versus 7%), and granulocyte colony stimulating factors (6% versus 0) were higher in the ALIMTA arm compared to the placebo arm.
 

 The following additional Grade 3 or 4 adverse reactions were observed more frequently in the ALIMTA arm.



   Incidence 1% to 5%  



 *      
 *   Blood/Bone Marrow - thrombocytopenia 
 *      
 *   General Disorders - febrile neutropenia 
      Incidence Less than 1%  
 

 *      
 *   Cardiovascular - ventricular tachycardia, syncope 
 *      
 *   General Disorders - pain 
 *      
 *   Gastrointestinal - gastrointestinal obstruction 
 *      
 *   Neurologic - depression 
 *      
 *      
 *   Renal - renal failure 
 *      
 *   Vascular - pulmonary embolism 
        Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) - After Prior Chemotherapy  
 

   Table 7  provides the frequency and severity of adverse reactions that have been reported in &gt;5% of 265 patients randomly assigned to receive single-agent ALIMTA with folic acid and vitamin B12supplementation and 276 patients randomly assigned to receive single-agent docetaxel. All patients were diagnosed with locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC and received prior chemotherapy.



 Table 7: Adverse Reactions in Fully Supplemented Patients Receiving ALIMTA versus Docetaxel in NSCLCa 
  a For the purpose of this table a cut off of 5% was used for inclusion of all events where the reporter considered a possible relationship to ALIMTA.    
  b Refer to NCI CTC Criteria for lab values for each Grade of toxicity (version 2.0).    
  c According to NCI CTC Criteria version 2.0, this adverse event term should only be reported as Grade 1 or 2.    
  
                                           ALIMTA(N=265)      Docetaxel(N=276)     
   Reaction  b                             All GradesToxicity (%)      Grades 3-4Toxicity (%)      All GradesToxicity (%)      Grades 3-4Toxicity (%)     
    Laboratory                                                                                                
     Hematologic                                                                                              
    Anemia                               19               4                22               4                 
    Leukopenia                           12               4                34               27                
    Neutropenia                          11               5                45               40                
    Thrombocytopenia                     8                2                1                0                 
     Hepatic                                                                                                  
    Increased ALT                        8                2                1                0                 
    Increased AST                        7                1                1                0                 
    Clinical                                                                                                  
     Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
    Nausea                               31               3                17               2                 
    Anorexia                             22               2                24               3                 
    Vomiting                             16               2                12               1                 
    Stomatitis/Pharyngitis               15               1                17               1                 
    Diarrhea                             13               0                24               3                 
    Constipation                         6                0                4                0                 
     Constitutional Symptoms                                                                                  
    Fatigue                              34               5                36               5                 
    Fever                                8                0                8                0                 
     Dermatology/Skin                                                                                         
    Rash/Desquamation                    14               0                6                0                 
    Pruritis                             7                0                2                0                 
    Alopecia                             6                1  c             38               2  c              
           No clinically relevant differences in adverse reactions were seen in patients based on histology.
 

 Clinically relevant adverse reactions occurring in &lt;5% of patients that received ALIMTA treatment but &gt;5% of patients that received docetaxel include CTC Grade 3/4 febrile neutropenia (1.9% ALIMTA, 12.7% docetaxel).



 The following additional adverse reactions were observed in patients with non-small cell lung cancer randomly assigned to receive ALIMTA.



   Incidence 1% to 5%  



 *      Body as a Whole - abdominal pain, allergic reaction/hypersensitivity, febrile neutropenia, infection 
 *      Dermatology/Skin - erythema multiforme 
 *      Neurology - motor neuropathy, sensory neuropathy 
 *      Renal - increased creatinine 
      Incidence Less than 1%  
 

 *      Cardiovascular - supraventricular arrhythmias 
        Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma (MPM)  
 

   Table 8  provides the frequency and severity of adverse reactions that have been reported in &gt;5% of 168 patients with mesothelioma who were randomly assigned to receive cisplatin and ALIMTA and 163 patients with mesothelioma randomly assigned to receive single-agent cisplatin. In both treatment arms, these chemonaive patients were fully supplemented with folic acid and vitamin B12.



 Table 8: Adverse Reactions in Fully Supplemented Patients Receiving ALIMTA plus Cisplatin in MPMa 
  a For the purpose of this table a cut off of 5% was used for inclusion of all events where the reporter considered a possible relationship to ALIMTA.    
  b Refer to NCI CTC Criteria version 2.0 for each Grade of toxicity except the term "creatinine clearance decreased" which is derived from the CTC term "renal/genitourinary-other".    
  c According to NCI CTC Criteria version 2.0, this adverse event term should only be reported as Grade 1 or 2.    
  
                                                         ALIMTA/cisplatin    (N=168)      Cisplatin    (N=163)     
   Reaction  b                                           All Grades Toxicity (%)      Grade 3-4 Toxicity (%)      All Grades Toxicity (%)      Grade 3-4 Toxicity (%)     
    Laboratory                                                                                              
     Hematologic                                                                                            
    Neutropenia                                        56           23           13           3             
    Leukopenia                                         53           15           17           1             
    Anemia                                             26           4            10           0             
    Thrombocytopenia                                   23           5            9            0             
     Renal                                                                                                  
    Creatinine elevation                               11           1            10           1             
    Creatinine clearance decreased                     16           1            18           2             
    Clinical                                                                                                
     Eye Disorder                                                                                           
    Conjunctivitis                                     5            0            1            0             
     Gastrointestinal                                                                                       
    Nausea                                             82           12           77           6             
    Vomiting                                           57           11           50           4             
    Stomatitis/Pharyngitis                             23           3            6            0             
    Anorexia                                           20           1            14           1             
    Diarrhea                                           17           4            8            0             
    Constipation                                       12           1            7            1             
    Dyspepsia                                          5            1            1            0             
     Constitutional Symptoms                                                                                
    Fatigue                                            48           10           42           9             
     Metabolism and Nutrition                                                                               
    Dehydration                                        7            4            1            1             
     Neurology                                                                                              
    Neuropathy-sensory                                 10           0            10           1             
    Taste Disturbance                                  8            0  c         6            0  c          
     Dermatology/Skin                                                                                       
    Rash                                               16           1            5            0             
    Alopecia                                           11           0  c         6            0  c          
           The following additional adverse reactions were observed in patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma randomly assigned to receive ALIMTA plus cisplatin.
 

   Incidence 1% to 5%  



 *      Body as a Whole - febrile neutropenia, infection, pyrexia 
 *      Dermatology/Skin - urticaria 
 *      General Disorders - chest pain 
 *      Metabolism and Nutrition - increased AST, increased ALT, increased GGT 
 *      Renal - renal failure 
      Incidence Less than 1%  
 

 *      Cardiovascular - arrhythmia 
 *      Neurology - motor neuropathy 
        Effects of Vitamin Supplementations on Toxicity  
 

   Table 9  compares the incidence (percentage of patients) of CTC Grade 3/4 toxicities in patients who received vitamin supplementation with daily folic acid and vitamin B12from the time of enrollment in the study (fully supplemented) with the incidence in patients who never received vitamin supplementation (never supplemented) during the study in the ALIMTA plus cisplatin arm.



 Table 9: Selected Grade 3/4 Adverse Events Comparing Fully Supplemented versus Never Supplemented Patients in the ALIMTA plus Cisplatin arm (% incidence) 
  a Refer to NCI CTC criteria for lab and non-laboratory values for each grade of toxicity (Version 2.0).    
  
 Adverse Event  a   (%)                                Fully Supplemented Patients  (N=168)    Never Supplemented Patients  (N=32)   
 Neutropenia/granulocytopenia                        23                        38                         
 Thrombocytopenia                                    5                         9                          
 Vomiting                                            11                        31                         
 Febrile neutropenia                                 1                         9                          
 Infection with Grade 3/4 neutropenia                0                         6                          
 Diarrhea                                            4                         9                          
         The following adverse events were greater in the fully supplemented group compared to the never supplemented group: hypertension (11%, 3%), chest pain (8%, 6%), and thrombosis/embolism (6%, 3%).
 

 No relevant effect for ALIMTA safety due to gender or race was identified, except an increased incidence of rash in men (24%) compared to women (16%).



     Additional Experience Across Clinical Trials  



 Sepsis, which in some cases was fatal, occurred in approximately 1% of patients.



 Esophagitis occurred in less than 1% of patients.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ALIMTA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 These reactions occurred with ALIMTA when used as a single-agent and in combination therapies.



   Blood and Lymphatic System  - immune-mediated hemolytic anemia



   Gastrointestinal  - colitis, pancreatitis



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  - edema



   Injury, poisoning, and procedural complications  - Radiation recall has been reported in patients who have previously received radiotherapy.



   Respiratory  - interstitial pneumonitis



   Skin  - Bullous conditions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis. Some cases were fatal.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Premedication regimen: Prior to treatment with ALIMTA, initiate supplementation with oral folic acid and intramuscular vitamin B12to reduce the severity of hematologic and gastrointestinal toxicity of ALIMTA. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Bone marrow suppression: Reduce doses for subsequent cycles based on hematologic and nonhematologic toxicities. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Renal function: Do not administer when CrCl &lt;45 mL/min. (  2.4  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  NSAIDs with renal insufficiency: Use caution in patients with mild to moderate renal insufficiency (CrCl 45-79 mL/min). (  5.4  ) 
 *  Lab monitoring: Do not initiate a cycle unless ANC &gt;=1500 cells/mm  3  , platelets &gt;=100,000 cells/mm  3  , and CrCl &gt;=45 mL/min. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Pregnancy: Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised to use effective contraception measures to prevent pregnancy during treatment with ALIMTA. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Requirement for Premedication and Concomitant Medication to Reduce Toxicity



      Vitamin Supplementation  



    Prior to treatment with ALIMTA, initiate supplementation with oral folic acid and intramuscular vitamin B12to reduce the severity of hematologic and gastrointestinal toxicity of ALIMTA [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )]  . Do not substitute oral vitamin B12for intramuscular vitamin B12. In clinical studies, the incidence of the following Grade 3-4 toxicities were higher in patients with mesothelioma who were never supplemented as compared to patients who were fully supplemented with folic acid and vitamin B12prior to and throughout ALIMTA treatment: neutropenia [38% versus 23%], thrombocytopenia [9% versus 5%], febrile neutropenia [9% versus 0.6%], and infection with neutropenia [6% versus. 0].



       Corticosteroids  



    Administer dexamethasone the day before, the day of, and the day after ALIMTA administration [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )]  .



    5.2 Bone Marrow Suppression



  ALIMTA can suppress bone marrow function, as manifested by neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and anemia (or pancytopenia) [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  ; myelosuppression is usually the dose-limiting toxicity. Dose reductions for subsequent cycles are based on nadir ANC, platelet count, and maximum nonhematologic toxicity seen in the previous cycle [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .



    5.3 Decreased Renal Function



  ALIMTA is primarily eliminated unchanged by renal excretion. No dosage adjustment is needed in patients with creatinine clearance &gt;=45 mL/min. Insufficient numbers of patients have been studied with creatinine clearance &lt;45 mL/min to give a dose recommendation. Therefore, ALIMTA should not be administered to patients whose creatinine clearance is &lt;45 mL/min [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .



 One patient with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance 19 mL/min) who did not receive folic acid and vitamin B12died of drug-related toxicity following administration of ALIMTA alone.



    5.4 Use with Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) with Mild to Moderate Renal Insufficiency



  Caution should be used when administering NSAIDs concurrently with ALIMTA to patients with mild to moderate renal insufficiency (creatinine clearance from 45 to 79 mL/min) [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



    5.5 Required Laboratory Monitoring



     Obtain a complete blood count and renal function tests at the beginning of each cycle and as needed. Do not initiate a cycle of treatment unless the ANC is &gt;=1500 cells/mm  3  , the platelet count is &gt;=100,000 cells/mm  3  , and creatinine clearance is &gt;=45 mL/min [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .



    5.6 Pregnancy Category D



  Based on its mechanism of action, ALIMTA can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Pemetrexed administered intraperitoneally to mice during organogenesis was embryotoxic, fetotoxic and teratogenic in mice at greater than 1/833rd the recommended human dose. If ALIMTA is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant. Women should be advised to use effective contraceptive measures to prevent pregnancy during treatment with ALIMTA [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
