<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="allegra" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  ALLEGRA-D 12 HOUR

  In one clinical trial (n=651) in which 215 subjects with seasonal allergic rhinitis received the 60 mg fexofenadine hydrochloride/120 mg pseudoephedrine hydrochloride combination tablet twice daily for up to 2 weeks, adverse events were similar to those reported either in subjects receiving fexofenadine hydrochloride 60 mg alone (n=218 subjects) or in subjects receiving pseudoephedrine hydrochloride 120 mg alone (n=218). A placebo group was not included in this study.



 The percent of subjects who withdrew prematurely because of adverse events was 3.7% for the fexofenadine hydrochloride/pseudoephedrine hydrochloride combination group, 0.5% for the fexofenadine hydrochloride group, and 4.1% for the pseudoephedrine hydrochloride group. All adverse events that were reported by greater than 1% of subjects who received the recommended daily dose of the fexofenadine hydrochloride/pseudoephedrine hydrochloride combination are listed in the following table.



 Adverse Experiences Reported in One Active-Controlled Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis Clinical Trial at Rates of Greater than 1% 
 Adverse Experience         60 mg FexofenadineHydrochloride/120 mgPseudoephedrineHydrochlorideCombination TabletTwice Daily(n=215)  FexofenadineHydrochloride60 mg Twice Daily(n=218)  PseudoephedrineHydrochloride120 mg Twice Daily(n=218)   
  
 Headache                   13.0%                        11.5%                    17.4%                       
 Insomnia                   12.6%                        3.2%                     13.3%                       
 Nausea                     7.4%                         0.5%                     5.0%                        
 Dry Mouth                  2.8%                         0.5%                     5.5%                        
 Dyspepsia                  2.8%                         0.5%                     0.9%                        
 Throat Irritation          2.3%                         1.8%                     0.5%                        
 Dizziness                  1.9%                         0.0%                     3.2%                        
 Agitation                  1.9%                         0.0%                     1.4%                        
 Back Pain                  1.9%                         0.5%                     0.5%                        
 Palpitation                1.9%                         0.0%                     0.9%                        
 Nervousness                1.4%                         0.5%                     1.8%                        
 Anxiety                    1.4%                         0.0%                     1.4%                        
 Upper Respiratory Infection  1.4%                         0.9%                     0.9%                        
 Abdominal Pain             1.4%                         0.5%                     0.5%                        
          Many of the adverse events occurring in the fexofenadine hydrochloride/pseudoephedrine hydrochloride combination group were adverse events also reported predominately in the pseudoephedrine hydrochloride group, such as insomnia, headache, nausea, dry mouth, dizziness, agitation, nervousness, anxiety, and palpitation.
 

   Fexofenadine Hydrochloride

  In placebo-controlled clinical trials, which included 2461 subjects receiving fexofenadine hydrochloride at doses of 20 mg to 240 mg twice daily, adverse events were similar in fexofenadine hydrochloride and placebo-treated subjects. The incidence of adverse events, including drowsiness, was not dose related and was similar across subgroups defined by age, gender, and race. The percent of subjects who withdrew prematurely because of adverse events was 2.2% with fexofenadine hydrochloride vs 3.3% with placebo.



 Events that have been reported during controlled clinical trials involving subjects with seasonal allergic rhinitis and chronic idiopathic urticaria at incidences less than 1% and similar to placebo and have been rarely reported during postmarketing surveillance include: insomnia, nervousness, and sleep disorders or paroniria. In rare cases, rash, urticaria, pruritus and hypersensitivity reactions with manifestations such as angioedema, chest tightness, dyspnea, flushing and systemic anaphylaxis have been reported.



   Pseudoephedrine Hydrochloride

  Pseudoephedrine hydrochloride may cause mild CNS stimulation in hypersensitive patients. Nervousness, excitability, restlessness, dizziness, weakness, or insomnia may occur. Headache, drowsiness, tachycardia, palpitation, pressor activity, cardiac arrhythmias and ischemic colitis have been reported. Sympathomimetic drugs have also been associated with other untoward effects such as fear, anxiety, tenseness, tremor, hallucinations, seizures, pallor, respiratory difficulty, dysuria, and cardiovascular collapse.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
