<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="alogliptin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions reported in &gt;=4% of patients treated with coadministration of alogliptin with metformin were: upper respiratory tract infection, nasopharyngitis, diarrhea, hypertension, headache, back pain and urinary tract infection. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Takeda Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-TAKEDA-7 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Alogliptin and Metformin Hydrochloride  



 Over 2700 patients with type 2 diabetes have received alogliptin coadministered with metformin in four large, randomized, double-blind controlled clinical trials. The mean exposure to alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets was 58 weeks, with more than 1400 subjects treated for more than one year. These included two 26-week placebo-controlled studies, one 52-week active control study and an interim analysis of a 104-week active-controlled study. In the alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets arm, the mean duration of diabetes was approximately six years, the mean body mass index (BMI) was 31 kg/m  2  (56% of patients had a BMI &gt;=30 kg/m  2  ) and the mean age was 55 years (18% of patients &gt;=65 years of age).



 In a pooled analysis of these four controlled clinical studies, the overall incidence of adverse reactions was 74% in patients treated with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets compared to 75% treated with placebo. Overall discontinuation of therapy due to adverse events was 6.2% with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets compared to 1.9% in placebo, 6.4% in metformin and 5.0% in alogliptin.



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=4% of patients treated with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets and more frequently than in patients who received alogliptin, metformin or placebo are summarized in Table 1.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=4% of Patients Treated with Alogliptin and Metformin HCl Tablets and More Frequently than in Patients Receiving Either Alogliptin, Metformin or Placebo 
   Number of Patients (%)                                        
                                Alogliptin and Metformin HCl Tablets      Alogliptin      Metformin       Placebo     
                                N=2794                            N=222          N=1592          N=106      
  
  Upper respiratory tract infection    224 (8.0)                         6 (2.7)        105 (6.6)       3 (2.8)     
  Nasopharyngitis              191 (6.8)                         7 (3.2)        93 (5.8)        2 (1.9)     
  Diarrhea                     155 (5.5)                         4 (1.8)        105 (6.6)       3 (2.8)     
  Hypertension                 154 (5.5)                         5 (2.3)        96 (6.0)        6 (5.7)     
  Headache                     149 (5.3)                         11 (5.0)       74 (4.6)        3 (2.8)     
  Back pain                    119 (4.3)                         1 (0.5)        72 (4.5)        1 (0.9)     
  Urinary tract infection      116 (4.2)                         4 (1.8)        59 (3.7)        2 (1.9)     
                Hypoglycemia  
 

 In a 26-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of alogliptin in combination with metformin, the number of patients reporting hypoglycemia was 1.9% in the alogliptin 12.5 mg with metformin HCl 500 mg, 5.3% in the alogliptin 12.5 mg with metformin HCl 1000 mg, 1.8% in the metformin HCl 500 mg and 6.3% in the metformin HCl 1000 mg treatment groups.



 In a 26-week placebo-controlled study of alogliptin 25 mg administered once daily as add-on to metformin regimen, the number of patients reporting hypoglycemic events was 0% in the alogliptin with metformin and 2.9% in the placebo treatment groups.



 In a 52-week, active-controlled, double-blind study of alogliptin once daily as add-on therapy to the combination of pioglitazone 30 mg and metformin compared to the titration of pioglitazone 30 mg to 45 mg and metformin, the number of patients reporting hypoglycemia was 4.5% in the alogliptin 25 mg with pioglitazone 30 mg and metformin group versus 1.5% in the pioglitazone 45 mg with metformin group.



 In an interim analysis conducted in a 104-week, double-blind, active-controlled study of alogliptin 25 mg in combination with metformin, the number of patients reporting hypoglycemia was 1.4% in the alogliptin 25 mg with metformin group versus 23.8% in the glipizide with metformin group.



     Alogliptin  



 Approximately 8500 patients with type 2 diabetes have been treated with alogliptin in 14 randomized, double-blind, controlled clinical trials with approximately 2900 subjects randomized to placebo and approximately 2200 to an active comparator. The mean exposure to alogliptin was 40 weeks, with more than 2400 subjects treated for more than one year. Among these patients, 63% had a history of hypertension, 51% had a history of dyslipidemia, 25% had a history of myocardial infarction, 8% had a history of unstable angina and 7% had a history of congestive heart failure. The mean duration of diabetes was seven years, the mean BMI was 31 kg/m  2  (51% of patients had a BMI &gt;=30 kg/m  2  ) and the mean age was 57 years (24% of patients &gt;=65 years of age).



 Two placebo-controlled monotherapy trials of 12 and 26 weeks of duration were conducted in patients treated with alogliptin 12.5 mg daily, alogliptin 25 mg daily and placebo. Four placebo-controlled add-on combination therapy trials of 26 weeks' duration were also conducted: with metformin, with a sulfonylurea, with a thiazolidinedione and with insulin.



 Four placebo-controlled and one active-controlled trials of 16 weeks up through two years in duration were conducted in combination with metformin, in combination with pioglitazone and with pioglitazone added to a background of metformin therapy.



 Three active-controlled trials of 52 weeks in duration were conducted in patients treated with pioglitazone and metformin, in combination with metformin and as monotherapy compared to glipizide.



 In a pooled analysis of these 14 controlled clinical trials, the overall incidence of adverse events was 66% in patients treated with alogliptin 25 mg compared to 62% with placebo and 70% with active comparator. Overall discontinuation of therapy due to adverse events was 4.7% with alogliptin 25 mg compared to 4.5% with placebo or 6.2% with active comparator.



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=4% of patients treated with alogliptin 25 mg and more frequently than in patients who received placebo are summarized in Table 2.



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=4% Patients Treated with Alogliptin 25 mg and More Frequently than in Patients Given Placebo in Pooled Studies 
                                               Number of Patients (%)     
                                               Alogliptin    25 mg      Placebo        Active Comparator            
                                               N=5902            N=2926         N=2257                       
  
  Nasopharyngitis                             257 (4.4)         89 (3.0)       113 (5.0)                     
  Headache                                    247 (4.2)         72 (2.5)       121 (5.4)                     
  Upper respiratory tract infection           247 (4.2)         61 (2.1)       113 (5.0)                     
              Pancreatitis  
 

 In the clinical trial program, pancreatitis was reported in 11 of 5902 (0.2%) patients receiving alogliptin 25 mg daily compared to five of 5183 (?0.1%) patients receiving all comparators.



     Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 In a pooled analysis, the overall incidence of hypersensitivity reactions was 0.6% with alogliptin 25 mg compared to 0.8% with all comparators. A single event of serum sickness was reported in a patient treated with alogliptin 25 mg.



     Hypoglycemia  



 Hypoglycemic events were documented based upon a blood glucose value and/or clinical signs and symptoms of hypoglycemia.



 In the monotherapy study, the incidence of hypoglycemia was 1.5% in patients treated with alogliptin compared to 1.6% with placebo. The use of alogliptin as add-on therapy to glyburide or insulin did not increase the incidence of hypoglycemia compared to placebo. In a monotherapy study comparing alogliptin to a sulfonylurea in elderly patients, the incidence of hypoglycemia was 5.4% with alogliptin compared to 26% with glipizide.



     Metformin Hydrochloride  



 Table 3. Most Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;=5%) in a Placebo-Controlled Clinical Study of Metformin MonotherapyReactions that were more common in metformin than placebo-treated patients 
   Adverse Reaction                   Metformin Monotherapy    (n=141)         Placebo    (n=145)     
   % of Patients                     
  
  Diarrhea                           53.2                                     11.7            
  Nausea/vomiting                    25.5                                     8.3             
  Flatulence                         12.1                                     5.5             
  Asthenia                           9.2                                      5.5             
  Indigestion                        7.1                                      4.1             
  Abdominal discomfort               6.4                                      4.8             
  Headache                           5.7                                      4.8             
           6.2 Laboratory Abnormalities
     Alogliptin and Metformin Hydrochloride  



 No clinically meaningful differences were observed among treatment groups regarding hematology, serum chemistry or urinalysis results.



     Alogliptin  



 No clinically meaningful changes in hematology, serum chemistry or urinalysis were observed in patients treated with alogliptin.



     Metformin Hydrochloride  



 Metformin may lower serum vitamin B12concentrations. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets, and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ].  



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

    Alogliptin  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during the postmarketing use of alogliptin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Hypersensitivity reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema, rash, urticaria, and severe cutaneous adverse reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, hepatic enzyme elevations, fulminant hepatic failure, severe and disabling arthralgia and acute pancreatitis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.10  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS  

    *  Lactic acidosis is a rare but serious complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment and acute congestive heart failure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  The onset is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap and elevated blood lactate [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment and acute congestive heart failure. (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap and elevated blood lactate. (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets and hospitalize the patient immediately. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Lactic acidosis: Warn against excessive alcohol intake. Alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets are not recommended in hepatic impairment and are contraindicated in renal impairment. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Acute pancreatitis: There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Hypersensitivity: There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with alogliptin such as anaphylaxis, angioedema and severe cutaneous adverse reactions. In such cases, promptly discontinue alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Hepatic effects: Postmarketing reports of hepatic failure, sometimes fatal. Causality cannot be excluded. If liver injury is detected, promptly interrupt alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets and assess patient for probable cause, then treat cause if possible, to resolution or stabilization. Do not restart alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets if liver injury is confirmed and no alternative etiology can be found. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Temporarily discontinue in patients undergoing radiologic studies with intravascular administration of iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food and fluids. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Vitamin B12deficiency: Metformin may lower vitamin B12levels. Monitor hematologic parameters annually. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Hypoglycemia: When used with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or with insulin, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. (  5.9  ) 
 *    Arthralgia: Severe and disabling arthralgia has been reported in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate. (  5.10  ) 
 *    Macrovascular outcomes: There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets or any other antidiabetic drug. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



  Lactic acidosis is a rare but serious metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets and is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate levels (more than 5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels of more than 5 mcg/mL are generally found.



 The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin HCl is very low (approximately 0.03 cases per 1000 patient-years, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases per 1000 patient-years). In more than 20,000 patient-years' exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal impairment, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, particularly when accompanied by hypoperfusion and hypoxemia due to unstable or acute failure, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking metformin. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. Metformin treatment should not be initiated in any patients unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced, as these patients are more susceptible to developing lactic acidosis. In addition, metformin should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, metformin should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic impairment. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake when taking metformin, because alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin on lactate metabolism. In addition, metformin should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure necessitating restricted intake of food or fluids. Use of topiramate, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, in epilepsy and migraine prophylaxis may frequently cause dose-dependent metabolic acidosis (in controlled trials, 32% and 67% for adjunctive treatment in adult and pediatric patients, respectively, and 15% to 25% for monotherapy of epilepsy, with decrease in serum bicarbonate to less than 20 mEq/L; 3% and 11% for adjunctive treatment in adult and pediatric patients, respectively, and 1% to 7% for monotherapy of epilepsy, with decrease in serum bicarbonate to less than 17 mEq/L) and may exacerbate the risk of metformin-induced lactic acidosis [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



 The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia, hypotension and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis.



 Patients should be educated to promptly report these symptoms should they occur. If present, alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets should be withdrawn until lactic acidosis is ruled out. Serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, blood pH, lactate levels and blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of metformin, GI symptoms, which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to recur. Later occurrence of GI symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease.



 Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking metformin do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explainable by other mechanisms such as poorly controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity or technical problems in sample handling .  



 Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia).



 Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking metformin, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin is dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery [see  Contraindications (4)  ].  



    5.2 Pancreatitis



  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis in patients taking alogliptin. After initiation of alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets, patients should be observed carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, alogliptin should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated. It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with alogliptin. These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema and severe cutaneous adverse reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome. If a serious hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets, assess for other potential causes for the event and institute alternative treatment for diabetes [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  . Use caution in patients with a history of angioedema to another DPP-4 inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets.



    5.4 Hepatic Effects



  There have been postmarketing reports of fatal and nonfatal hepatic failure in patients taking alogliptin, although the reports contain insufficient information necessary to establish the probable cause [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ].  In randomized controlled studies, serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) elevations greater than three times the upper limit of normal (ULN) were observed: 1.3% in alogliptin-treated patients and 1.5% in all comparator-treated patients.



 Patients with type 2 diabetes may have fatty liver disease, which may cause liver test abnormalities, and they may also have other forms of liver disease, many of which can be treated or managed. Therefore, obtaining a liver test panel and assessing the patient before initiating alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets therapy is recommended. Because impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis with use of metformin, alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease.



 Measure liver tests promptly in patients who report symptoms that may indicate liver injury, including fatigue, anorexia, right upper abdominal discomfort, dark urine or jaundice. In this clinical context, if the patient is found to have clinically significant liver enzyme elevations and if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets should be interrupted and investigation done to establish the probable cause. Alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets should not be restarted in these patients without another explanation for the liver test abnormalities.



    5.5 Monitoring of Renal Function



  Metformin is substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of impairment. Therefore, alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets are contraindicated in patients with renal impairment .  



 Before initiation of alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets therapy and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal dysfunction is anticipated, renal function should be assessed more frequently and alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present. Metformin treatment should not be initiated in patients &gt;=80 years of age unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced, as these patients are more susceptible to developing lactic acidosis.



    Use of Concomitant Medications that May Affect Renal Function or Metformin Disposition  



 Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or may interfere with the disposition of metformin, such as cationic drugs that are eliminated by renal tubular secretion [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  , should be used with caution.



    Radiological Studies and Surgical Procedures  



 Radiological studies involving the use of intravascular iodinated contrast materials (for example, intravenous urogram, intravenous cholangiography, angiography and computed tomography) can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin. Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets should be temporarily discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been re-evaluated and found to be normal.



 Alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets therapy should be temporarily suspended for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.6 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause, acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients on alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets therapy, the drug should be promptly discontinued.



    5.7 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol is known to potentiate the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients, therefore, should be warned against excessive alcohol intake while receiving alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets.



    5.8 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled, 29-week clinical trials of immediate-release metformin, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets, and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. Certain individuals (those with inadequate vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum vitamin B12measurements at two- to three-year intervals may be useful.



    5.9 Use with Medications Known to Cause Hypoglycemia



   Alogliptin  



 Insulin and insulin secretagogues, such as sulfonylureas, are known to cause hypoglycemia. Therefore, a lower dose of insulin or insulin secretagogue may be required to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets.



    Metformin Hydrochloride  



 Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as sulfonylureas and insulin) or ethanol. Elderly, debilitated or malnourished patients and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.



    5.10 Severe and Disabling Arthralgia



   There have been postmarketing reports of severe and disabling arthralgia in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. The time to onset of symptoms following initiation of drug therapy varied from one day to years. Patients experienced a relief of symptoms upon discontinuation of the medication. A subset of patients experienced a recurrence of symptoms when restarting the same drug or a different DPP-4 inhibitor. Consider DPP-4 inhibitors as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate.  



    5.11 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with alogliptin and metformin HCl tablets or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
