<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aloxi" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in adults (incidence &gt;=5%) are headache and constipation (  6.1  ).   



 The most common adverse reactions in postoperative nausea and vomiting (incidence &gt;= 2%) are QT prolongation, bradycardia, headache, and constipation (  6.2  ).   



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    EISAI at 1-888-422-4743    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.      



 

  6.1 Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting

      Adults    



 In clinical trials for the prevention of nausea and vomiting induced by moderately or highly emetogenic chemotherapy, 1374 adult patients received palonosetron.  Adverse reactions were similar in frequency and severity with ALOXI and ondansetron or dolasetron.  Following is a listing of all adverse reactions reported by &gt;= 2% of patients in these trials (Table 1).



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions from Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting Studies &gt;= 2% in any Treatment Group 
    Event                      ALOXI 0.25 mg    (N=633)       Ondansetron    32 mg I.V.    (N=410)       Dolasetron    100 mg I.V.    (N=194)     
   Headache                   60 (9%)                    34 (8%)                    32 (16%)                  
   Constipation               29 (5%)                    8 (2%)                     12 (6%)                   
   Diarrhea                   8 (1%)                     7 (2%)                     4 (2%)                    
   Dizziness                  8 (1%)                     9 (2%)                     4 (2%)                    
   Fatigue                    3 (&lt; 1%)                   4 (1%)                     4 (2%)                    
   Abdominal Pain             1 (&lt; 1%)                   2 (&lt; 1%)                   3 (2%)                    
   Insomnia                   1 (&lt; 1%)                   3 (1%)                     3 (2%)                    
          In other studies, 2 subjects experienced severe constipation following a single palonosetron dose of approximately 0.75 mg, three times the recommended dose. One patient received a 10 mcg/kg oral dose in a post-operative nausea and vomiting study and one healthy subject received a 0.75 mg I.V. dose in a pharmacokinetic study.
 

 In clinical trials, the following infrequently reported adverse reactions, assessed by investigators as treatment-related or causality unknown, occurred following administration of ALOXI to adult patients receiving concomitant cancer chemotherapy:



 Cardiovascular  :  1%: non-sustained tachycardia, bradycardia, hypotension, &lt; 1%: hypertension, myocardial ischemia, extrasystoles, sinus tachycardia, sinus arrhythmia, supraventricular extrasystoles and QT prolongation.  In many cases, the relationship to ALOXI was unclear.



 Dermatological: &lt; 1%: allergic dermatitis, rash.



 Hearing and Vision: &lt; 1%: motion sickness, tinnitus, eye irritation and amblyopia.



 Gastrointestinal System: 1%: diarrhea, &lt; 1%: dyspepsia, abdominal pain, dry mouth, hiccups and flatulence.



 General: 1%: weakness, &lt; 1%: fatigue, fever, hot flash, flu-like syndrome.



 Liver: &lt; 1%: transient, asymptomatic increases in AST and/or ALT and bilirubin.  These changes occurred predominantly in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy.



 Metabolic: 1%: hyperkalemia, &lt; 1%: electrolyte fluctuations, hyperglycemia, metabolic acidosis, glycosuria, appetite decrease, anorexia.



 Musculoskeletal: &lt; 1%: arthralgia.



 Nervous System: 1%: dizziness, &lt; 1%: somnolence, insomnia, hypersomnia, paresthesia.



 Psychiatric: 1%: anxiety, &lt; 1%: euphoric mood.



 Urinary System: &lt; 1%: urinary retention.



 Vascular: &lt; 1%: vein discoloration, vein distention.



     Pediatrics    



 In a pediatric clinical trial for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting 163 cancer patients received a single 20 mcg/kg (maximum 1.5 mg) intravenous infusion of palonosetron 30 minutes before beginning the first cycle of emetogenic chemotherapy. Patients had a mean age of 8.4 years (range 2 months to 16.9 years) and were 46% male; and 93% white.



 The following adverse reactions were reported for palonosetron:



 Nervous System: &lt;1%: headache, dizziness, dyskinesia.



 General: &lt;1%: infusion site pain.



 Dermatological: &lt;1%: allergic dermatitis, skin disorder.



 In the trial, adverse reactions were evaluated in pediatric patients receiving palonosetron for up to 4 chemotherapy cycles.



   6.2 Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting

  The adverse reactions cited in Table 2 were reported in &gt;= 2% of adults receiving I.V. ALOXI 0.075 mg immediately before induction of anesthesia in one phase 2 and two phase 3 randomized placebo-controlled trials. Rates of events between palonosetron and placebo groups were similar. Some events are known to be associated with, or may be exacerbated by concomitant perioperative and intraoperative medications administered in this surgical population.  Please refer to Section 12.2, thorough QT/QTc study results, for data demonstrating the lack of palonosetron effect on QT/QTc.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions from Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting Studies &gt;= 2% in any Treatment Group 
    Event                               ALOXI 0.075 mg    (N=336)          Placebo    (N=369)               
 ElectrocardiogramQT prolongation      16 (5%)                            11 (3%)                           
 Bradycardia                           13 (4%)                            16 (4%)                           
 Headache                              11 (3%)                            14 (4%)                           
 Constipation                          8 (2%)                             11 (3%)                           
         In these clinical trials, the following infrequently reported adverse reactions, assessed by investigators as treatment-related or causality unknown, occurred following administration of ALOXI to adult patients receiving concomitant perioperative and intraoperative medications including those associated with anesthesia:
 

 Cardiovascular: 1%: electrocardiogram QTc prolongation, sinus bradycardia, tachycardia, &lt; 1%: blood pressure decreased, hypotension, hypertension, arrhythmia, ventricular extrasystoles, generalized edema, ECG T wave amplitude decreased, platelet count decreased. The frequency of these adverse effects did not appear to be different from placebo.



 Dermatological: 1%: pruritus.



 Gastrointestinal System: 1%: flatulence, &lt; 1%: dry mouth, upper abdominal pain, salivary hypersecretion, dyspepsia, diarrhea, intestinal hypomotility, anorexia.



 General: &lt; 1%: chills.



 Liver: 1%: increases in AST and/or ALT, &lt; 1%: hepatic enzyme increased.



 Metabolic: &lt; 1%: hypokalemia, anorexia.



 Nervous System: &lt; 1%: dizziness.



 Respiratory: &lt; 1%: hypoventilation, laryngospasm.



 Urinary System: 1%: urinary retention.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of ALOXI.  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Very rare cases (&lt;1/10,000) of hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis and anaphylactic shock and injection site reactions (burning, induration, discomfort and pain) were reported from postmarketing experience of ALOXI 0.25 mg in the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have been reported with or without known hypersensitivity to other selective 5-HT3receptor antagonists (  5.1  ) 
 *  Serotonin syndrome has been reported with 5-HT3receptor antagonists alone but particularly with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have been reported with or without known hypersensitivity to other 5-HT3receptor antagonists.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of serotonin syndrome has been reported with 5-HT3receptor antagonists.  Most reports have been associated with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (e.g., selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), monoamine oxidase inhibitors, mirtazapine, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, and intravenous methylene blue).  Some of the reported cases were fatal. Serotonin syndrome occurring with overdose of another 5-HT3receptor antagonist alone has also been reported. The majority of reports of serotonin syndrome related to 5-HT3receptor antagonist use occurred in a post-anesthesia care unit or an infusion center.



 Symptoms associated with serotonin syndrome may include the following combination of signs and symptoms: mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, with or without gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome, especially with concomitant use of ALOXIand other serotonergic drugs. If symptoms of serotonin syndrome occur, discontinue ALOXI and initiate supportive treatment.  Patients should be informed of the increased risk of serotonin syndrome, especially if ALOXI is used concomitantly with other serotonergic drugs [ see Drug Interactions (  7  ), Patient Counseling   Information (  17  )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
