<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="alphanine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The administration of plasma preparations may cause allergic reactions, mild chills, nausea or stinging at the infusion site. For most reactive individuals, slowing the infusion rate relieves the symptoms. For those highly reactive individuals, a different lot may be satisfactory.



 Adverse reactions, characterized by either thrombosis or disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), have been reported following administration of Factor IX Complex concentrates. Patients who receive Coagulation Factor IX (Human), AlphaNine SD, following operation, or those with known liver disease, should be kept under close observation for potential signs or symptoms of intravascular coagulation. Continued administration should be left to the discretion of the physician.



 In the clinical study that compared the  in vivo  half-life and recovery of AlphaNine SD and HT products, no adverse events were associated with 18 infusions of AlphaNine SD administered to 18 individuals with severe to moderate hemophilia B.  2  Short term safety of the earlier version of this product, AlphaNine, was demonstrated by an absence of adverse events after 225 infusions of this product were received by 31 patients participating in three clinical trials. In the clinical trial to evaluate efficacy of AlphaNine in providing hemostatic protection during and after surgery, 13 patients received a total of 370,655 IU of AlphaNine. In 208 total infusions, each patient received approximately 15,000 IU (range 3,295 to 52,200 IU Factor IX) in an average of 16 infusions (range 2 to 26 infusions). Results from this study showed no bleeding episodes during the course of postsurgery therapy. There was no hematological evidence (measured by hematocrit, partial thromboplastin time, prothrombin time, fibrinogen/fibrin degradation products, fibrin monomers, D-dimers and platelet counts) of thrombogenicity.  12  



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Grifols at 1-888-GRIFOLS (1-888-474-3657) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
