<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="alphanate" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions observed in patients receiving Alphanate are anaphylaxis/hypersensitivity reactions. Thromboembolic events have also been observed in patients receiving Alphanate for VWD. See also  Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ).  



 The most frequent adverse events reported with Alphanate in &gt; 5% of patients are respiratory distress, pruritus, rash, urticaria, face edema, paresthesia, pain, fever, chills, joint pain and fatigue.



   EXCERPT:   The most frequent adverse events reported with Alphanate in &gt; 5% of patients are respiratory distress, pruritus, rash, urticaria, face edema, paresthesia, pain, fever, chills, joint pain and fatigue (  6  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Grifols Biologicals Inc. at 1-888-GRIFOLS (1-888-474-3657) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.  



     Hemophilia A  



 In a clinical study with Alphanate, regardless of causality, 14 of 23 (60.9%) patients experienced a total of 47 adverse events. Twenty-three (48.9%) of the AEs were mild, 19 (40.4%) were moderate and 5 (10.6%) were severe.



 Two of 23 (8.7%) patients experienced 10 serious AEs during the study. None of the SAEs were considered to be related to study drug.



 The most common AEs were pain (combined terms), with 14 episodes occurring in 7 patients, and headache, with 3 episodes occurring in 2 patients. None of the symptoms were judged to be related to treatment (see    Table 3    ).



 Table 3: Most Commonly Reported AEs irrespective of relationship to study drug 
   Adverse Event                  Number of Episodes       Number of Subjects with signs/symptoms      %                   
   Body as a whole                23                       11                            47.8%               
      Pain (combined terms)     14                                                                           
      Headache                  3                                                                            
      Accidental injury         2                                                                            
      Asthenia                  1                                                                            
      Cellulitis                1                                                                            
      Chest pain                1                                                                            
      Flu syndrome              1                                                                            
   Digestive system               6                        4                             17.4%               
      Dyspepsia                 1                                                                            
      GI disorder               1                                                                            
      Hepatitis                 1                                                                            
      Nausea                    1                                                                            
      Tooth disorder            1                                                                            
      Vomiting                  1                                                                            
   Respiratory system             5                        4                             17.4%               
      Cough increased           1                                                                            
      Lung disorder             1                                                                            
      Pharyngitis               1                                                                            
      Respiratory disorder      1                                                                            
      Rhinitis                  1                                                                            
   Musculoskeletal system         3                        3                             13.0%               
      Bone disorder             2                                                                            
      Bone necrosis             1                                                                            
   Skin and appendages            3                        3                             13.0%               
      Acne                      1                                                                            
      Dry skin                  1                                                                            
      Sweating                  1                                                                            
   Nervous system                 2                        2                             8.7%                
      Insomnia                  1                                                                            
      Somnolence                1                                                                            
   Hemic and lymphatic system      2                        2                             8.7%                
      Anemia                    1                                                                            
      Ecchymosis                1                                                                            
   Urogenital system              2                        2                             8.7%                
      Abnormal ejaculation      1                                                                            
      Cutaneous moniliasis      1                                                                            
   Special senses                 1                        1                             4.3%                
      Eye disorder              1                                                                            
              VWD  
 

 In the prospective clinical study of Alphanate (A-SD/HT)** in patients with von Willebrand Disease, adverse events occurred in 18 of 36 (50.0%) subjects (irrespective of causality) and 53 of 204 (26.0%) infusions. Most of the AEs were unrelated to study drug, however, and the proportion of subjects experiencing an AE possibly, probably, or definitely related to study drug was 5 of 36 subjects (13.9%) treated with Alphanate.



 The proportion of subjects with at least one serious AE, regardless of causality was 3 of 36 subjects (8.3%). There were no subjects who reported at least one serious AE possibly, probably, or definitely related to study drug.



 Overall, AEs, regardless of causality, were observed in association with 53 of 204 (26.0%) infusions of Alphanate across all parts of these studies. Most AEs were unrelated to study drug, however, and the proportion of infusions associated with AEs possibly, probably, or definitely related to study drug was 14 of 204 infusions (6.9%).



 The proportion of infusions associated with serious AEs, regardless of causality, was 5 of 204 (2.5%) infusions of Alphanate. There were no observed serious AEs possibly, probably or definitely related to study drug.



 **Alphanate, Solvent Detergent, non heat-treated (A-SD), is the previous formulation and Alphanate, Solvent Detergent/Heat Treated (A-SD/HT), is the current formulation. Both products are biochemically equivalent and demonstrate similar  in vivo  pharmacokinetic profiles. Both products are also similarly effective for the treatment of bleeding episodes and provide adequate hemostasis for surgical and invasive procedures, even the absence of bleeding time correction, in subjects with moderate and severe VWD.



 The most common AEs regardless of causality are listed in    Table 4    .



 Table 4: Most Commonly Reported AEs irrespective of relationship to study drug 
   Adverse Event                  Number of Episodes       Number of Subjects with signs/symptoms      % of Subjects       
   Body as a whole                42                       14                            33.3%               
      Pain (combined terms)     31                                                                           
      Headache                  4                                                                            
      Edema face                3                                                                            
      Fever                     2                                                                            
   Digestive system               16                       10                            27.8%               
      Nausea                    12                                                                           
      Constipation              2                                                                            
      Vomiting                  2                                                                            
   Skin and appendages            10                       7                             19.4%               
      Pruritis                  6                                                                            
      Rash                      4                                                                            
   Respiratory system             4                        2                             5.6%                
      Respiratory disorder      4                                                                            
   Nervous system                 6                        2                             5.6%                
      Paresthesia               3                                                                            
      Anxiety                   3                                                                            
   Hemic and Lymphic system       3                        1                             2.8%                
      Anemia                    3                                                                            
          One incident of pulmonary embolus was reported that was considered to have a possible relationship to the product. This subject received the dose of 60 IU VWF:RCo/kg body weight and the FVIII:C level achieved was 290%.
 

 In the retrospective study conducted to determine the efficacy and safety of Alphanate (A-SD/HT) in a surgical or invasive procedure setting as peri-operative prophylaxis against excessive bleeding, see  Clinical Studies (  14    ), 3 out of 39 subjects (7.7%) experienced 6 adverse drug reactions. Four were considered mild and 2 were considered moderate. No subject discontinued their treatment due to an adverse reaction. The adverse drug reactions were pruritus, paresthesia (2 events) and hemorrhage (all considered mild), and one event each of moderate hematocrit decrease and orthostatic hypotension.



 One adverse event (pain) related to the treatment with heat-treated Alphanate (A-SD/HT) was reported on the four pediatric patients with von Willebrand Disease during the course of the prospective study and none of the five pediatric subjects in the retrospective clinical study.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

    The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Alphanate (A-SD/HT). Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.  



 Among patients treated with Alphanate (A-SD/HT), cases of allergic/hypersensitivity reactions (including urticaria, rash, pruritus, chest tightness shortness of breath, wheezing, flushing, palpitations, nausea, and vomiting) have been reported.



 The following represents the most frequently reported adverse reactions: fever, chills, headache, joint pain, and fatigue. In addition, one case was reported for swelling of the parotid gland, pulmonary embolus, femoral venous thrombosis, seizure, and brief cardiorespiratory arrest.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Anaphylaxis and severe hypersensitivity reactions are possible. Should symptoms occur, treatment with Alphanate should be discontinued, and emergency treatment should be sought (  5.1  ). 
 *  Development of activity-neutralizing antibodies has been detected in patients receiving FVIII containing products. Development of alloantibodies to VWF in Type 3 VWD patients has been occasionally reported in the literature (  5.2  ). 
 *  Thromboembolic events may be associated with AHF/VWF Complex (Human) in VWD patients, especially in the setting of known risk factors (  5.3  ). 
 *  Intravascular hemolysis may be associated with infusion of massive doses of AHF/VWF Complex (Human) (  5.4  ). 
 *  Rapid administration of a FVIII concentrate may result in vasomotor reactions (  5.5  ). 
 *  Plasma products carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, such as viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent, despite steps designed to reduce this risk (  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylaxis and Severe Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Anaphylaxis and severe hypersensitivity reactions are possible. Should symptoms occur, treatment with Alphanate should be discontinued, and emergency treatment should be administered.



    5.2 Neutralizing Antibodies



  Development of procoagulant activity-neutralizing antibodies (inhibitors) has been detected in patients receiving FVIII-containing products. Carefully monitor patients treated with AHF products for the development of FVIII inhibitors by appropriate clinical observations and laboratory tests. No studies have been conducted with Alphanate to evaluate inhibitor formation. Therefore, it is not known whether there are greater, lesser or the same risks of developing inhibitors due to the use of this product than there are with other FVIII preparations. If expected plasma FVIII activity levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with an appropriate dose, an assay that measures FVIII inhibitor concentration should be performed. Patients with these inhibitors may not respond to treatment with Antihemophilic Factor/von Willebrand Factor Complex (Human), or the response may be much less than would otherwise be expected; therefore, larger doses of Antihemophilic Factor/von Willebrand Factor Complex (Human) are often required. The management of bleeding in patients with inhibitors requires careful monitoring, especially if surgical procedures are indicated.  4-6  Depending on the level of the inhibitor and/or clinical response, it may be appropriate to use an alternative 'bypass' therapeutic agent.



 Reports in the literature suggest that patients with Type 3, severe von Willebrand Disease, may develop alloantibodies to von Willebrand factor (VWF) after replacement therapy.  13  The risk of developing alloantibodies in patients with von Willebrand disease due to the use of this product is not known.



    5.3 Thromboembolic Events



  Thromboembolic events have been reported in von Willebrand Disease patients receiving AHF/VWF Complex (Human) replacement therapy, especially in the setting of known risk factors for thrombosis.  14-16  In addition, endogenous high levels of FVIII have also been associated with thrombosis but no causal relationship has been established. In all VWD patients in situations of high thrombotic risk receiving coagulation factor replacement therapy, caution should be exercised and antithrombotic measures should be considered. See also Adverse Reactions (  6  ).  



    5.4 Intravascular Hemolysis



  Massive doses of AHF/VWF Complex (Human) have resulted in a few cases of acute hemolytic anemia, increased bleeding tendency or hyperfibrinogenemia as reported in the literature, which subside after cessation of the commercial factor infusion.  17  Alphanate contains blood group specific isoagglutinins and, when large and/or frequent doses are required in patients of blood groups A, B, or AB, the patient should be monitored for signs of intravascular hemolysis and falling hematocrit. Should this condition occur, thus leading to progressive hemolytic anemia, the administration of serologically compatible Type O red blood cells should be considered, the administration of Alphanate should be discontinued, and alternative therapy should be considered.



    5.5 Vasomotor Reactions



  Rapid administration of a FVIII concentrate may result in vasomotor reactions. Alphanate should not be administered at a rate exceeding 10 mL/minute.



    5.6 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because Alphanate is made from pooled human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease (CJD) agent. Stringent procedures designed to reduce the risk of adventitious agent transmission have been employed in the manufacture of this product, from the screening of plasma donors and the collection and testing of plasma, through the application of viral elimination/reduction steps such as solvent detergent and heat treatment in the manufacturing process.  18,19  Despite these measures, such products can still potentially transmit disease; therefore, the risk of infectious agents cannot be totally eliminated. See also Description (  11  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
