<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="alprazolam0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The information included in the subsection on Adverse Events Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials with Alprazolam XR tablets is based on pooled data of five 6- and 8-week placebo-controlled clinical studies in panic disorder.



 Adverse event reports were elicited either by general inquiry or by checklist, and were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. The stated frequencies of adverse events represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened during therapy following baseline evaluation. In the tables and tabulations that follow, standard MedDRA terminology (version 4.0) was used to classify reported adverse events.



   Adverse Events Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials of Alprazolam XR

  Adverse Events Reported as Reasons for Discontinuation of Treatment in Placebo-Controlled Trials

  Approximately 17% of the 531 patients who received Alprazolam XR in placebo-controlled clinical trials for panic disorder had at least one adverse event that led to discontinuation compared to 8% of 349 placebo-treated patients. The most common events leading to discontinuation and considered to be drug-related (ie, leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of the patients treated with Alprazolam XR at a rate at least twice that of placebo) are shown in the following table.



 Common Adverse Events Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment in Placebo-Controlled Trials 
 System Organ Class/Adverse Event          Percentage of Patients Discontinuing Due to Adverse Events   
                                                Alprazolam XR(n=531)               Placebo(n=349)           
  
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
   Sedation                                             7.5                             0.6                 
   Somnolence                                           3.2                             0.3                 
   Dysarthria                                           2.1                              0                  
   Coordination abnormal                                1.9                             0.3                 
   Memory impairment                                    1.5                             0.3                 
   General disorders/administration site conditions                                                                     
   Fatigue                                              1.7                             0.6                 
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Depression                                           2.5                             1.2                 
           Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among Patients Treated with Alprazolam XR
   The prescriber should be aware that adverse event incidence cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with event incidence obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited values, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidence rate in the population studied.



 The following table shows the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events that occurred during 6- to 8-week placebo-controlled trials in 1% or more of patients treated with Alprazolam XR where the incidence in patients treated with Alprazolam XR was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients. The most commonly observed adverse events in panic disorder patients treated with Alprazolam XR (incidence of 5% or greater and at least twice the incidence in placebo patients) were: sedation, somnolence, memory impairment, dysarthria, coordination abnormal, ataxia, libido decreased (see  table  ).



 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events: Incidence in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials with Alprazolam XR 
 System Organ Class/Adverse Event          Percentage of Patients Reporting Adverse Event   
                                                Alprazolam XR(n=531)               Placebo(n=349)           
  
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
   Sedation                                             45.2                            22.6                
   Somnolence                                           23.0                            6.0                 
   Memory impairment                                    15.4                            6.9                 
   Dysarthria                                           10.9                            2.6                 
   Coordination abnormal                                9.4                             0.9                 
   Mental impairment                                    7.2                             5.7                 
   Ataxia                                               7.2                             3.2                 
   Disturbance in attention                             3.2                             0.6                 
   Balance impaired                                     3.2                             0.6                 
   Paresthesia                                          2.4                             1.7                 
   Dyskinesia                                           1.7                             1.4                 
   Hypoesthesia                                         1.3                             0.3                 
   Hypersomnia                                          1.3                              0                  
   General disorders/administration site conditions                                                                     
   Fatigue                                              13.9                            9.2                 
   Lethargy                                             1.7                             0.6                 
   Infections and infestations                                                                              
   Influenza                                            2.4                             2.3                 
   Upper respiratory tract infections                   1.9                             1.7                 
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Depression                                           12.1                            9.2                 
   Libido decreased                                     6.0                             2.3                 
   Disorientation                                       1.5                              0                  
   Confusion                                            1.5                             0.9                 
   Depressed mood                                       1.3                             0.3                 
   Anxiety                                              1.1                             0.6                 
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                       
   Appetite decreased                                   7.3                             7.2                 
   Appetite increased                                   7.0                             6.0                 
   Anorexia                                             1.5                              0                  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
   Dry mouth                                            10.2                            9.7                 
   Constipation                                         8.1                             4.3                 
   Nausea                                               6.0                             3.2                 
   Pharyngolaryngeal pain                               3.2                             2.6                 
   Investigations                                                                                           
   Weight increased                                     5.1                             4.3                 
   Weight decreased                                     4.3                             3.7                 
   Injury, poisoning, and procedural complications                                                                     
   Road traffic accident                                1.5                              0                  
   Reproductive system and breast disorders                                                                     
   Dysmenorrhea                                         3.6                             2.9                 
   Sexual dysfunction                                   2.4                             1.1                 
   Premenstrual syndrome                                1.7                             0.6                 
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                     
   Arthralgia                                           2.4                             0.6                 
   Myalgia                                              1.5                             1.1                 
   Pain in limb                                         1.1                             0.3                 
   Vascular disorders                                                                                       
   Hot flushes                                          1.5                             1.4                 
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                                     
   Dyspnea                                              1.5                             0.3                 
   Rhinitis allergic                                    1.1                             0.6                 
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                     
   Pruritis                                             1.1                             0.9                 
           Other Adverse Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Alprazolam XR tablets
   Following is a list of MedDRA terms that reflect treatment-emergent adverse events reported by 531 patients with panic disorder treated with Alprazolam XR. All potentially important reported events are included except those already listed in the above table or elsewhere in labeling, those events for which a drug cause was remote, those event terms that were so general as to be uninformative, and those events that occurred at rates similar to background rates in the general population. It is important to emphasize that, although the events reported occurred during treatment with Alprazolam XR, they were not necessarily caused by the drug. Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: frequent adverse events are those occurring on 1 or more occasions in at least l/l00 patients; infrequent adverse events are those occurring in less than l/100 patients but at least l/1000 patients; rare events are those occurring in fewer than l/1000 patients.



   Cardiac disorders:    Frequent:  palpitation;  Infrequent:  sinus tachycardia



   Ear and Labyrinth disorders:    Frequent:  Vertigo;  Infrequent:  tinnitus, ear pain



   Eye disorders:    Frequent:  blurred vision;  Infrequent:  tmydriasis, photophobia



   Gastrointestinal disorders:    Frequent:  diarrhea, vomiting, dyspepsia, abdominal pain;  Infrequent:  dysphagia, salivary hypersecretion



   General disorders and administration site conditions:    Frequent:  malaise, weakness, chest pains;  Infrequent:  fall, pyrexia, thirst, feeling hot and cold, edema, feeling jittery, sluggishness, asthenia, feeling drunk, chest tightness, increased energy, feeling of relaxation, hangover, loss of control of legs, rigors



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:    Frequent:  back pain, muscle cramps, muscle twitching



   Nervous system disorders:    Frequent:  headache, dizziness, tremor;  Infrequent:  amnesia, clumsiness, syncope, hypotonia, seizures, depressed level of consciousness, sleep apnea syndrome, sleep talking, stupor



   Psychiatric system disorders:    Frequent:  irritability, insomnia, nervousness, derealization, libido increased, restlessness, agitation, depersonalization, nightmare;  Infrequent:  abnormal dreams, apathy, aggression, anger, bradyphrenia, euphoric mood, logorrhea, mood swings, dysphonia, hallucination, homicidal ideation, mania, hypomania, impulse control, psychomotor retardation, suicidal ideation



   Renal and urinary disorders:    Frequent:  difficulty in micturition;  Infrequent:  urinary frequency, urinary incontinence



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:    Frequent:  nasal congestion, hyperventilation;  Infrequent:  choking sensation, epistaxis, rhinorrhea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:    Frequent:  sweating increased;  Infrequent:  clamminess, rash, urticaria



   Vascular disorders:    Infrequent:  hypotension



 The categories of adverse events reported in the clinical development program for Alprazolam tablets in the treatment of panic disorder differ somewhat from those reported for Alprazolam XR tablets because the clinical trials with Alprazolam tablets and Alprazolam XR tablets used different standard medical nomenclature for reporting the adverse events. Nevertheless, the types of adverse events reported in the clinical trials with Alprazolam tablets were generally the same as those reported in the clinical trials with Alprazolam XR tablets.



   Discontinuation-Emergent Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 5% or More Among Patients Treated with Alprazolam XR

  The following table shows the incidence of discontinuation-emergent adverse events that occurred during short-term, placebo-controlled trials in 5% or more of patients treated with Alprazolam XR where the incidence in patients treated with Alprazolam XR was two times greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 Discontinuation-Emergent Symptoms: Incidence in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials with Alprazolam XR 
 System Organ Class/Adverse Event          Percentage of Patients Reporting Adverse Event   
                                                Alprazolam XR(n=422)               Placebo(n=261)           
  
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
   Tremor                                               28.2                            10.7                
   Headache                                             26.5                            12.6                
   Hypoesthesia                                         7.8                             2.3                 
   Paraesthesia                                         7.1                             2.7                 
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                             24.2                            9.6                 
   Nervousness                                          21.8                            8.8                 
   Depression                                           10.9                            5.0                 
   Derealization                                        8.0                             3.8                 
   Anxiety                                              7.8                             2.7                 
   Depersonalization                                    5.7                             1.9                 
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
   Diarrhea                                             12.1                            3.1                 
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                     
   Hyperventilation                                     8.5                             2.7                 
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                       
   Appetite decreased                                   9.5                             3.8                 
   Musculosketal and connective tissue disorders                                                                     
   Muscle twitching                                     7.4                             2.7                 
   Vascular disorders                                                                                       
   Hot flushes                                          5.9                             2.7                 
         There have also been reports of withdrawal seizures upon rapid decrease or abrupt discontinuation of alprazolam (see  WARNINGS  ).
 

 To discontinue treatment in patients taking Alprazolam XR tablets, the dosage should be reduced slowly in keeping with good medical practice. It is suggested that the daily dosage of Alprazolam XR tablets be decreased by no more than 0.5 mg every three days (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ). Some patients may benefit from an even slower dosage reduction. In a controlled postmarketing discontinuation study of panic disorder patients which compared this recommended taper schedule with a slower taper schedule, no difference was observed between the groups in the proportion of patients who tapered to zero dose; however, the slower schedule was associated with a reduction in symptoms associated with a withdrawal syndrome.



 As with all benzodiazepines, paradoxical reactions such as stimulation, increased muscle spasticity, sleep disturbances, hallucinations, and other adverse behavioral effects such as agitation, rage, irritability, and aggressive or hostile behavior have been reported rarely. In many of the spontaneous case reports of adverse behavioral effects, patients were receiving other CNS drugs concomitantly and/or were described as having underlying psychiatric conditions. Should any of the above events occur, alprazolam should be discontinued. Isolated published reports involving small numbers of patients have suggested that patients who have borderline personality disorder, a prior history of violent or aggressive behavior, or alcohol or substance abuse may be at risk for such events. Instances of irritability, hostility, and intrusive thoughts have been reported during discontinuation of alprazolam in patients with posttraumatic stress disorder.



   Post Introduction Reports

  Various adverse drug reactions have been reported in association with the use of Alprazolam tablets since market introduction. The majority of these reactions were reported through the medical event voluntary reporting system. Because of the spontaneous nature of the reporting of medical events and the lack of controls, a causal relationship to the use of Alprazolam tablets cannot be readily determined. Reported events include: gastrointestinal disorder, hypomania, mania, liver enzyme elevations, hepatitis, jaundice, hepatic failure, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, photosensitivity reaction, angioedema, peripheral edema, menstruation irregular, hyperprolactinemia, gynecomastia, and galactorrhea. (see  PRECAUTIONS  ).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
