<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="altace" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in patients with hypertension included headache, dizziness, fatigue, and cough (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer at 1-800-438-1985 or the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Hypertension  



 ALTACE has been evaluated for safety in over 4000 patients with hypertension; of these, 1230 patients were studied in U.S. controlled trials, and 1107 were studied in foreign controlled trials. Almost 700 of these patients were treated for at least one year. The overall incidence of reported adverse events was similar in ALTACE and placebo patients. The most frequent clinical side effects (possibly or probably related to study drug) reported by patients receiving ALTACE in placebo-controlled trials were: headache (5.4%), dizziness (2.2%), and fatigue or asthenia (2.0%), but only the last one was more common in ALTACE patients than in patients given placebo. Generally the side effects were mild and transient, and there was no relation to total dosage within the range of 1.25 mg-20 mg. Discontinuation of therapy because of a side effect was required in approximately 3% of U.S. patients treated with ALTACE. The most common reasons for discontinuation were: cough (1.0%), dizziness (0.5%), and impotence (0.4%).



 Of observed side effects considered possibly or probably related to study drug that occurred in U.S. placebo-controlled trials in more than 1% of patients treated with ALTACE, only asthenia (fatigue) was more common on ALTACE than placebo (2% [n=13/651] vs. 1% [n=2/286], respectively).



 In placebo-controlled trials, there was also an excess of upper respiratory infection and flu syndrome in the ALTACE group, not attributed at that time to ramipril. As these studies were carried out before the relationship of cough to ACE inhibitors was recognized, some of these events may represent ramipril-induced cough. In a later 1-year study, increased cough was seen in almost 12% of ALTACE patients, with about 4% of patients requiring discontinuation of treatment.



     Reduction in the Risk of Myocardial Infarction, Stroke, and Death from Cardiovascular Causes  



     HOPE Study  



 Safety data in the Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation (HOPE) study were collected as reasons for discontinuation or temporary interruption of treatment. The incidence of cough was similar to that seen in the Acute Infarction Ramipril Efficacy (AIRE) trial. The rate of angioedema was the same as in previous clinical trials  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



 Table 1. Reasons for Discontinuation or Temporary Interruption of Treatment-HOPE Study 
                                                Placebo(N=4652)                    ALTACE(N=4645)           
  
 Discontinuation at any time                          32%                               34%                 
 Permanent discontinuation                            28%                               29%                 
 Reasons for stopping                                                                                       
   Cough                                              2%                                 7%                 
   Hypotension or dizziness                          1.5%                               1.9%                
   Angioedema                                        0.1%                               0.3%                
             Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction  
 

     AIRE Study  



 Adverse reactions (except laboratory abnormalities) considered possibly/probably related to study drug that occurred in more than 1% of patients and more frequently on ALTACE are shown below. The incidences are from the AIRE study. The follow-up time was between 6 and 46 months for this study.



 Table 2. Percentage of Patients with Adverse Events Possibly/ Probably Related to Study Drug-Placebo-Controlled (AIRE) Mortality Study 
 Adverse Event                                  Placebo(N=982)                     ALTACE(N=1004)           
  
 Hypotension                                          5%                                11%                 
 Cough increased                                      4%                                 8%                 
 Dizziness                                            3%                                 4%                 
 Angina pectoris                                      2%                                 3%                 
 Nausea                                               1%                                 2%                 
 Postural hypotension                                 1%                                 2%                 
 Syncope                                              1%                                 2%                 
 Vomiting                                            0.5%                                2%                 
 Vertigo                                             0.7%                                2%                 
 Abnormal kidney function                            0.5%                                1%                 
 Diarrhea                                            0.4%                                1%                 
             Other Adverse Reactions  
 

 Other adverse reactions reported in controlled clinical trials (in less than 1% of ALTACE patients), or rarer events seen in post-marketing experience, include the following (in some, a causal relationship to drug is uncertain):



   Body as a whole:  Anaphylactoid reactions  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



   Cardiovascular:  Symptomatic hypotension (reported in 0.5% of patients in U.S. trials)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ],  syncope, and palpitations.



   Hematologic:  Pancytopenia, hemolytic anemia, and thrombocytopenia.



 Decreases in hemoglobin or hematocrit (a low value and a decrease of 5 g/dL or 5%, respectively) were rare, occurring in 0.4% of patients receiving ALTACE alone and in 1.5% of patients receiving ALTACE plus a diuretic.



   Renal:  Acute renal failure. Some hypertensive patients with no apparent pre-existing renal disease have developed minor, usually transient, increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine when taking ALTACE, particularly when ALTACE was given concomitantly with a diuretic  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



   Angioneurotic edema:  Angioneurotic edema has been reported in 0.3% of patients in U.S. clinical trials of ALTACE  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



   Gastrointestinal:  Hepatic failure, hepatitis, jaundice, pancreatitis, abdominal pain (sometimes with enzyme changes suggesting pancreatitis), anorexia, constipation, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, dysphagia, gastroenteritis, increased salivation, and taste disturbance.



   Dermatologic:  Apparent hypersensitivity reactions (manifested by urticaria, pruritus, or rash, with or without fever), photosensitivity, purpura, onycholysis, pemphigus, pemphigoid, erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and Stevens-Johnson syndrome.



   Neurologic and Psychiatric:  Anxiety, amnesia, convulsions, depression, hearing loss, insomnia, nervousness, neuralgia, neuropathy, paresthesia, somnolence, tinnitus, tremor, vertigo, and vision disturbances.



   Miscellaneous:  As with other ACE inhibitors, a symptom complex has been reported which may include a positive ANA, an elevated erythrocyte sedimentation rate, arthralgia/arthritis, myalgia, fever, vasculitis, eosinophilia, photosensitivity, rash and other dermatologic manifestations. Additionally, as with other ACE inhibitors, eosinophilic pneumonitis has been reported.



   Other:  Arthralgia, arthritis, dyspnea, edema, epistaxis, impotence, increased sweating, malaise, myalgia, and weight gain.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, there have been rare reports of hypoglycemia reported during ALTACE therapy when given to patients concomitantly taking oral hypoglycemic agents or insulin. The causal relationship is unknown.



   6.3 Clinical Laboratory Test Findings

    Creatinine and Blood Urea Nitrogen:  Increases in creatinine levels occurred in 1.2% of patients receiving ALTACE alone, and in 1.5% of patients receiving ALTACE and a diuretic. Increases in blood urea nitrogen levels occurred in 0.5% of patients receiving ALTACE alone and in 3% of patients receiving ALTACE with a diuretic. None of these increases required discontinuation of treatment. Increases in these laboratory values are more likely to occur in patients with renal insufficiency or those pretreated with a diuretic and, based on experience with other ACE inhibitors, would be expected to be especially likely in patients with renal artery stenosis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  . As ramipril decreases aldosterone secretion, elevation of serum potassium can occur. Use potassium supplements and potassium sparing diuretics with caution, and monitor the patient's serum potassium frequently  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ].  



     Hemoglobin and Hematocrit:  Decreases in hemoglobin or hematocrit (a low value and a decrease of 5 g/dL or 5%, respectively) were rare, occurring in 0.4% of patients receiving ALTACE alone and in 1.5% of patients receiving ALTACE plus a diuretic. No US patients discontinued treatment because of decreases in hemoglobin or hematocrit.



     Other (causal relationships unknown):  Clinically important changes in standard laboratory tests were rarely associated with ALTACE administration. Elevations of liver enzymes, serum bilirubin, uric acid, and blood glucose have been reported, as have cases of hyponatremia and scattered incidents of leucopenia, eosinophilia, and proteinuria. In US trials, less than 0.2% of patients discontinued treatment for laboratory abnormalities; all of these were cases of proteinuria or abnormal liver-function tests.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible (5.6). 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.6). 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible (5.6). 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.6). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Angioedema, increased risk in patients with a prior history (  5.1  )



 Hypotension and hyperkalemia (  5.5  ,  5.8  )



 Renal impairment: monitor renal function during therapy (  5.3  )



 Avoid concomitant use of an ACE inhibitor and angiotensin blocker (  5.7  )



 Rare cholestatic jaundice and hepatic failure (  5.2  )



 Rare neutropenia and agranulocytosis (  5.4  )



 



   5.1 Anaphylactoid and Possibly Related Reactions



  Presumably because drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., ACE inhibitors) affect the metabolism of eicosanoids and polypeptides, including endogenous bradykinin, patients receiving these drugs (including ALTACE) may be subject to a variety of adverse reactions, some of them serious.



    Angioedema  



    Head and Neck Angioedema  



 Patients with a history of angioedema unrelated to ACE inhibitor therapy may be at increased risk of angioedema while receiving an ACE inhibitor.



 Angioedema of the face, extremities, lips, tongue, glottis, and larynx has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors. Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema can be fatal. If laryngeal stridor or angioedema of the face, tongue, or glottis occurs, discontinue treatment with ALTACE and institute appropriate therapy immediately. Where there is involvement of the tongue, glottis, or larynx likely to cause airway obstruction, administer appropriate therapy (e.g., subcutaneous epinephrine solution 1:1000 [0.3 mL to 0.5 mL]) promptly [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ].  



 In considering the use of ALTACE, note that in controlled clinical trials ACE inhibitors cause a higher rate of angioedema in Black patients than in non-Black patients.



 In a large U.S. post-marketing study, angioedema (defined as reports of angio, face, larynx, tongue, or throat edema) was reported in 3/1523 (0.20%) Black patients and in 8/8680 (0.09%) non-Black patients. These rates were not different statistically.



  Patients taking concomitant mTOR inhibitor (e.g. temsirolimus) therapy may be at increased risk for angioedema [see  Drug Interactions (7.7)  ].    



    Intestinal Angioedema  



 Intestinal angioedema has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors. These patients presented with abdominal pain (with or without nausea or vomiting); in some cases there was no prior history of facial angioedema and C-1 esterase levels were normal. The angioedema was diagnosed by procedures including abdominal CT scan or ultrasound, or at surgery, and symptoms resolved after stopping the ACE inhibitor. Include intestinal angioedema in the differential diagnosis of patients on ACE inhibitors presenting with abdominal pain.



    Anaphylactoid Reactions During Desensitization  



 Two patients undergoing desensitizing treatment with hymenoptera venom while receiving ACE inhibitors sustained life-threatening anaphylactoid reactions. In the same patients, these reactions were avoided when ACE inhibitors were temporarily withheld, but they reappeared upon inadvertent rechallenge.



    Anaphylactoid Reactions During Membrane Exposure  



 Anaphylactoid reactions have been reported in patients dialyzed with high-flux membranes and treated concomitantly with an ACE inhibitor. Anaphylactoid reactions have also been reported in patients undergoing low-density lipoprotein apheresis with dextran sulfate absorption.



    5.2 Hepatic Failure and Impaired Liver Function



  Rarely, ACE inhibitors, including ALTACE, have been associated with a syndrome that starts with cholestatic jaundice and progresses to fulminant hepatic necrosis and sometimes death. The mechanism of this syndrome is not understood. Discontinue ALTACE if patient develops jaundice or marked elevations of hepatic enzymes.



 As ramipril is primarily metabolized by hepatic esterases to its active moiety, ramiprilat, patients with impaired liver function could develop markedly elevated plasma levels of ramipril. No formal pharmacokinetic studies have been carried out in hypertensive patients with impaired liver function.



    5.3 Renal Impairment



  As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals. In patients with severe congestive heart failure whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, treatment with ACE inhibitors, including ALTACE, may be associated with oliguria or progressive azotemia and rarely with acute renal failure or death.



 In hypertensive patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine may occur. Experience with another ACE inhibitor suggests that these increases would be reversible upon discontinuation of ALTACE and/or diuretic therapy. In such patients, monitor renal function during the first few weeks of therapy. Some hypertensive patients with no apparent pre-existing renal vascular disease have developed increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine, usually minor and transient, especially when ALTACE has been given concomitantly with a diuretic. This is more likely to occur in patients with pre-existing renal impairment. Dosage reduction of ALTACE and/or discontinuation of the diuretic may be required.



    5.4 Neutropenia and Agranulocytosis



  In rare instances, treatment with ACE inhibitors may be associated with mild reductions in red blood cell count and hemoglobin content, blood cell or platelet counts. In isolated cases, agranulocytosis, pancytopenia, and bone marrow depression may occur. Hematological reactions to ACE inhibitors are more likely to occur in patients with collagen-vascular disease (e.g., systemic lupus erythematosus, scleroderma) and renal impairment. Consider monitoring white blood cell counts in patients with collagen-vascular disease, especially if the disease is associated with impaired renal function.



    5.5 Hypotension



   General Considerations  



 ALTACE can cause symptomatic hypotension, after either the initial dose or a later dose when the dosage has been increased. Like other ACE inhibitors, ALTACE, has been only rarely associated with hypotension in uncomplicated hypertensive patients. Symptomatic hypotension is most likely to occur in patients who have been volume- and/or salt-depleted as a result of prolonged diuretic therapy, dietary salt restriction, dialysis, diarrhea, or vomiting. Correct volume- and salt-depletion before initiating therapy with ALTACE.



 If excessive hypotension occurs, place the patient in a supine position and, if necessary, treat with intravenous infusion of physiological saline. ALTACE treatment usually can be continued following restoration of blood pressure and volume.



    Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction  



 In patients with heart failure post-myocardial infarction who are currently being treated with a diuretic, symptomatic hypotension occasionally can occur following the initial dose of ALTACE. If the initial dose of 2.5 mg ALTACE cannot be tolerated, use an initial dose of 1.25 mg ALTACE to avoid excessive hypotension .  Consider reducing the dose of concomitant diuretic to decrease the incidence of hypotension.



    Congestive Heart Failure  



 In patients with congestive heart failure, with or without associated renal insufficiency, ACE inhibitor therapy may cause excessive hypotension, which may be associated with oliguria or azotemia and rarely, with acute renal failure and death. In such patients, initiate ALTACE therapy under close medical supervision and follow patients closely for the first 2 weeks of treatment and whenever the dose of ALTACE or diuretic is increased.



    Surgery and Anesthesia  



 In patients undergoing surgery or during anesthesia with agents that produce hypotension, ramipril may block angiotensin II formation that would otherwise occur secondary to compensatory renin release. Hypotension that occurs as a result of this mechanism can be corrected by volume expansion.



    5.6 Fetal Toxicity



   Pregnancy Category D  



 Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ALTACE as soon as possible [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



    5.7 Dual Blockade of the Renin-Angiotensin System



   Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy. Most patients receiving the combination of two RAS inhibitors do not obtain any additional benefit compared to monotherapy. In general, avoid combined use of RAS inhibitors. Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function and electrolytes in patients on ALTACE and other agents that affect the RAS.  



    Telmisartan  



 The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients &gt;55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomized them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months. Patients receiving the combination of telmisartan and ramipril did not obtain any benefit in the composite endpoint of cardiovascular death, MI, stroke and heart failure hospitalization compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of clinically important renal dysfunction (death, doubling of serum creatinine, or dialysis) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone. Concomitant use of telmisartan and ramipril is not recommended.



     Aliskiren    



  Do not co-administer aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with diabetes. Avoid concomitant use of aliskiren with ALTACE in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ) .    



    5.8 Hyperkalemia



  In clinical trials with ALTACE, hyperkalemia (serum potassium &gt;5.7 mEq/L) occurred in approximately 1% of hypertensive patients receiving ALTACE. In most cases, these were isolated values, which resolved despite continued therapy. None of these patients were discontinued from the trials because of hyperkalemia. Risk factors for the development of hyperkalemia include renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, and the concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium supplements, and/or potassium-containing salt substitutes, which should be used cautiously, if at all, with ALTACE [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .



    5.9 Cough



  Presumably caused by inhibition of the degradation of endogenous bradykinin, persistent nonproductive cough has been reported with all ACE inhibitors, always resolving after discontinuation of therapy. Consider the possibility of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor induced-cough in the differential diagnosis of cough.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
