<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="amaryl" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in more detail below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Hypoglycemia [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Hemolytic anemia [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
    In clinical trials, the most common adverse reactions with AMARYL were hypoglycemia, dizziness, asthenia, headache, and nausea.
 

   EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions in clinical trials (&gt;=5% and more common than with placebo) include hypoglycemia, headache, nausea, and dizziness (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi-aventis U.S. LLC at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Approximately 2,800 patients with type 2 diabetes have been treated with AMARYL in the controlled clinical trials. In these trials, approximately 1,700 patients were treated with AMARYL for at least 1 year.



 Table 1 summarizes adverse events, other than hypoglycemia, that were reported in 11 pooled placebo-controlled trials, whether or not considered to be possibly or probably related to study medication. Treatment duration ranged from 13 weeks to 12 months. Terms that are reported represent those that occurred at an incidence of &gt;=5% among AMARYL-treated patients and more commonly than in patients who received placebo.



 Table 1. Eleven Pooled Placebo-Controlled Trials ranging from 13 weeks to 12 months: Adverse Events (Excluding Hypoglycemia) Occurring in &gt;=5% of AMARYL-treated Patients and at a Greater Incidence than with PlaceboAMARYL doses ranged from 1-16 mg administered daily 
                                               AMARYLN=745%                       PlaceboN=294%             
  
 Headache                                          8.2                                 7.8                  
 Accidental Injury                                 5.8                                 3.4                  
 Flu Syndrome                                      5.4                                 4.4                  
 Nausea                                            5.0                                 3.4                  
 Dizziness                                         5.0                                 2.4                  
             Hypoglycemia:  
 

 In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled monotherapy trial of 14 weeks duration, patients already on sulfonylurea therapy underwent a 3-week washout period then were randomized to AMARYL 1 mg, 4 mg, 8 mg or placebo. Patients randomized to AMARYL 4 mg or 8 mg underwent forced-titration from an initial dose of 1 mg to these final doses, as tolerated  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ].  The overall incidence of possible hypoglycemia (defined by the presence of at least one symptom that the investigator believed might be related to hypoglycemia; a concurrent glucose measurement was not required) was 4% for AMARYL 1 mg, 17% for AMARYL 4 mg, 16% for AMARYL 8 mg and 0% for placebo. All of these events were self-treated.



 In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled monotherapy trial of 22 weeks duration, patients received a starting dose of either 1 mg AMARYL or placebo daily. The dose of AMARYL was titrated to a target fasting plasma glucose of 90-150 mg/dL. Final daily doses of AMARYL were 1, 2, 3, 4, 6 or 8 mg  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  . The overall incidence of possible hypoglycemia (as defined above for the 14-week trial) for AMARYL vs. placebo was 19.7% vs. 3.2%. All of these events were self-treated.



     Weight gain:  AMARYL, like all sulfonylureas, can cause weight gain [see    Clinical Studies (14.1)    ].



     Allergic Reactions:  In clinical trials, allergic reactions, such as pruritus, erythema, urticaria, and morbilliform or maculopapular eruptions, occurred in less than 1% of AMARYL-treated patients. These may resolve despite continued treatment with AMARYL. There are postmarketing reports of more serious allergic reactions (e.g., dyspnea, hypotension, shock) [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].



     Laboratory Tests:  



   Elevated Serum Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT):  In 11 pooled placebo-controlled trials of AMARYL, 1.9% of AMARYL-treated patients and 0.8% of placebo-treated patients developed serum ALT greater than 2 times the upper limit of the reference range.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of AMARYL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  Serious hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, angioedema, and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Hemolytic anemia in patients with and without G6PD deficiency [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Impairment of liver function (e.g. with cholestasis and jaundice), as well as hepatitis, which may progress to liver failure. 
 *  Porphyria cutanea tarda, photosensitivity reactions and allergic vasculitis 
 *  Leukopenia, agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia, and pancytopenia 
 *  Thrombocytopenia (including severe cases with platelet count less than 10,000/uL) and thrombocytopenic purpura 
 *  Hepatic porphyria reactions and disulfiram-like reactions 
 *  Hyponatremia and syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH), most often in patients who are on other medications or who have medical conditions known to cause hyponatremia or increase release of antidiuretic hormone 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypoglycemia: May be severe. Ensure proper patient selection, dosing, and instructions, particularly in at-risk populations (e.g., elderly, renally impaired) and when used with other anti-diabetic medications (  5.1  ). 
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions: Postmarketing reports include anaphylaxis, angioedema and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome. Promptly discontinue AMARYL, assess for other causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment, and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes (  5.2  ). 
 *  Hemolytic Anemia: Can occur if glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficient. Consider a non-sulfonylurea alternative. (  5.3  ). 
 *  Potential Increased Risk of Cardiovascular Mortality with Sulfonylureas: Inform patient of risks, benefits and treatment alternatives (  5.4  ). 
 *  Macrovascular Outcomes: No clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with AMARYL or any other anti-diabetic drug (  5.5  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypoglycemia



  All sulfonylureas, including AMARYL, can cause severe hypoglycemia [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]. The patient's ability to concentrate and react may be impaired as a result of hypoglycemia. These impairments may present a risk in situations where these abilities are especially important, such as driving or operating other machinery. Severe hypoglycemia can lead to unconsciousness or convulsions and may result in temporary or permanent impairment of brain function or death.



 Patients must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Use caution when initiating and increasing AMARYL doses in patients who may be predisposed to hypoglycemia (e.g., the elderly, patients with renal impairment, patients on other anti-diabetic medications). Debilitated or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal, pituitary, or hepatic impairment are particularly susceptible to the hypoglycemic action of glucose-lowering medications. Hypoglycemia is also more likely to occur when caloric intake is deficient, after severe or prolonged exercise, or when alcohol is ingested.



 Early warning symptoms of hypoglycemia may be different or less pronounced in patients with autonomic neuropathy, the elderly, and in patients who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking medications or other sympatholytic agents. These situations may result in severe hypoglycemia before the patient is aware of the hypoglycemia.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with AMARYL, including serious reactions such as anaphylaxis, angioedema, and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome. If a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, promptly discontinue AMARYL, assess for other potential causes for the reaction, and institute alternative treatment for diabetes.



    5.3 Hemolytic Anemia



  Sulfonylureas can cause hemolytic anemia in patients with glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency. Because AMARYL is a sulfonylurea, use caution in patients with G6PD deficiency and consider the use of a non-sulfonylurea alternative. There are also postmarketing reports of hemolytic anemia in patients receiving AMARYL who did not have known G6PD deficiency [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



    5.4 Increased Risk of Cardiovascular Mortality with Sulfonylureas



  The administration of oral hypoglycemic drugs has been reported to be associated with increased cardiovascular mortality as compared to treatment with diet alone or diet plus insulin. This warning is based on the study conducted by the University Group Diabetes Program (UGDP), a long-term, prospective clinical trial designed to evaluate the effectiveness of glucose-lowering drugs in preventing or delaying vascular complications in patients with non-insulin-dependent diabetes. The study involved 823 patients who were randomly assigned to one of four treatment groups



 UGDP reported that patients treated for 5 to 8 years with diet plus a fixed dose of tolbutamide (1.5 grams per day) had a rate of cardiovascular mortality approximately 2-1/2 times that of patients treated with diet alone. A significant increase in total mortality was not observed, but the use of tolbutamide was discontinued based on the increase in cardiovascular mortality, thus limiting the opportunity for the study to show an increase in overall mortality. Despite controversy regarding the interpretation of these results, the findings of the UGDP study provide an adequate basis for this warning. The patient should be informed of the potential risks and advantages of AMARYL and of alternative modes of therapy.



 Although only one drug in the sulfonylurea class (tolbutamide) was included in this study, it is prudent from a safety standpoint to consider that this warning may also apply to other oral hypoglycemic drugs in this class, in view of their close similarities in mode of action and chemical structure.



    5.5 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with AMARYL or any other anti-diabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
