<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ambisome" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse events are based on the experience of 592 adult patients (295 treated with Am  B  isome and 297 treated with amphotericin B deoxycholate) and 95 pediatric patients (48 treated with Am  B  isome and 47 treated with amphotericin B deoxycholate) in Study 94-0-002, a randomized double-blind, multi-center study in febrile, neutropenic patients. Am  B  isome and amphotericin B were infused over two hours.



 The incidence of common adverse events (incidence of 10% or greater) occurring with Am  B  isome compared to amphotericin B deoxycholate, regardless of relationship to study drug, is shown in the following table:



 Empirical Therapy Study 94-0-002 Common Adverse Events 
   Adverse Event by Body System              AmBisome  n=343   %          Amphotericin B  n=344   %        
   Body as a Whole                           
  Abdominal pain  Asthenia  Back pain  Blood product transfusion react.  Chills  Infection  Pain Sepsis   19.8  13.1  12  18.4  47.5  11.1  14 14   21.8  10.8  7.3  18.6  75.9  9.3  12.8 11.3   
   Cardiovascular System                     
  Chest pain  Hypertension  Hypotension Tachycardia   12  7.9  14.3 13.4           11.6  16.3  21.5 20.9            
   Digestive System                          
  Diarrhea  Gastrointestinal hemorrhage  Nausea Vomiting   30.3  9.9  39.7 31.8         27.3  11.3  38.7 43.9            
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders       
  Alkaline phosphatase increased  ALT (SGPT) increased  AST (SGOT) increased  Bilirubinemia  BUN increased  Creatinine increased  Edema  Hyperglycemia  Hypernatremia  Hypervolemia  Hypocalcemia  Hypokalemia  Hypomagnesemia Peripheral edema   22.2  14.6  12.8  18.1  21  22.4  14.3  23  4.1  12.2  18.4  42.9  20.4 14.6   19.2  14  12.8  19.2  31.1  42.2  14.8  27.9  11  15.4  20.9  50.6  25.6 17.2   
   Nervous System                            
  Anxiety  Confusion  Headache Insomnia      13.7  11.4  19.8 17.2        11  13.4  20.9 14.2              
   Respiratory System                        
  Cough increased  Dyspnea  Epistaxis  Hypoxia  Lung disorder  Pleural effusion Rhinitis   17.8  23  14.9  7.6  17.8  12.5 11.1   21.8  29.1  20.1  14.8  17.4  9.6 11   
                                                                                                           
   Skin and Appendages                       
  Pruritus  Rash Sweating                    10.8  24.8 7                 10.2  24.4 10.8                  
   Urogenital System                         
 Hematuria                                  14                           14                                
          
 

 Am  B  isome was well tolerated. Am  B  isome had a lower incidence of chills, hypertension, hypotension, tachycardia, hypoxia, hypokalemia, and various events related to decreased kidney function as compared to amphotericin B deoxycholate.



 In pediatric patients (16 years of age or less) in this double-blind study, Am  B  isome compared to amphotericin B deoxycholate had a lower incidence of hypokalemia (37% versus 55%), chills (29% versus 68%), vomiting (27% versus 55%), and hypertension (10% versus 21%). Similar trends, although with a somewhat lower incidence, were observed in open-label, randomized Study 104-14 involving 205 febrile neutropenic pediatric patients (141 treated with Am  B  isome and 64 treated with amphotericin B deoxycholate). Pediatric patients appear to have more tolerance than older individuals for the nephrotoxic effects of amphotericin B deoxycholate.



 The following adverse events are based on the experience of 244 patients (202 adult and 42 pediatric patients) of whom 85 patients were treated with Am  B  isome 3 mg/kg, 81 patients were treated with Am  B  isome 5 mg/kg and 78 patients treated with amphotericin B lipid complex 5 mg/kg in Study 97-0-034, a randomized double-blind, multi-center study in febrile, neutropenic patients. Am  B  isome and amphotericin B lipid complex were infused over two hours. The incidence of adverse events occurring in more than 10% of subjects in one or more arms regardless of relationship to study drug are summarized in the following table:



 Empirical Therapy Study 97-0-034 Common Adverse Events 
   Adverse Event by Body System        AmBisome  3 mg/kg/day  n=85   %     AmBisome  5 mg/kg/day  n=81   %     Amphotericin B Lipid Complex  5 mg/kg/day  n=78   %     
   Body as a Whole                     
  Abdominal pain  Asthenia  Chills/rigors  Sepsis Transfusion reaction   12.9  8.2  40  12.9 10.6   9.9  6.2  48.1  7.4 8.6   11.5  11.5  89.7  11.5 5.1   
   Cardiovascular System               
  Chest pain  Hypertension  Hypotension Tachycardia   8.2  10.6  10.6 9.4   11.1  19.8  7.4 18.5   6.4  23.1  19.2 23.1      
   Digestive System                    
  Diarrhea  Nausea Vomiting            15.3  25.9 22.4      17.3  29.6 25.9       14.1  37.2 30.8           
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders     
  Alkaline phosphatase increased  Bilirubinemia  BUN increased  Creatinine increased  Edema  Hyperglycemia  Hypervolemia  Hypocalcemia  Hypokalemia  Hypomagnesemia Liver function tests abnormal   7.1  16.5  20  20  12.9  8.2  8.2  10.6  37.6  15.3 10.6   8.6  11.1  18.5  18.5  12.3  8.6  11.1  4.9  43.2  25.9 7.4   12.8  11.5  28.2  48.7  12.8  14.1  14.1  5.1  39.7  15.4 11.5   
   Nervous System                      
  Anxiety  Confusion Headache          10.6  12.9 9.4       7.4  8.6 17.3         9  3.8 10.3               
   Respiratory System                  
  Dyspnea  Epistaxis  Hypoxia Lung disorder   17.6  10.6  7.1 14.1   22.2  8.6  6.2 13.6   23.1  14.1  20.5 15.4     
   Skin and Appendages                 
 Rash                                 23.5                 22.2                  14.1                       
           
 

 The following adverse events are based on the experience of 267 patients (266 adult patients and 1 pediatric patient) of whom 86 patients were treated with Am  B  isome 3 mg/kg, 94 patients were treated with Am  B  isome 6 mg/kg and 87 patients treated with amphotericin B deoxycholate 0.7 mg/kg in Study 94-0-013 a randomized, double-blind, comparative multi-center trial, in the treatment of cryptococcal meningitis in HIV positive patients. The incidence of adverse events occurring in more than 10% of subjects in one or more arms regardless of relationship to study drug are summarized in the following table:



 Cryptococcal Meningitis Therapy Study 94-0-013 Common Adverse Events 
   Adverse Event by Body System          AmBisome  3 mg/kg/day  n=86   %     AmBisome  6 mg/kg/day  n=94   %     Amphotericin B  0.7 mg/kg/day  n=87   %     
   Body as a Whole                       
  Abdominal pain  Infection Procedural Complication   7  12.8 8.1      7.4  11.7 9.6      10.3  6.9 10.3                  
   Cardiovascular System                 
 Phlebitis                              9.3              10.6               25.3                             
   Digestive System                      
  Anorexia  Constipation  Diarrhea  Nausea Vomiting   14  15.1  10.5  16.3 10.5   9.6  14.9  16  21.3 21.3   11.5  20.7  10.3  25.3 20.7     
   Hemic and Lymphatic System            
  Anemia  Leukopenia Thrombocytopenia    26.7  15.1 5.8   47.9  17 12.8      43.7  17.2 6.9                  
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders     
  Bilirubinemia  BUN increased  Creatinine increased  Hyperglycemia  Hypocalcemia  Hypokalemia  Hypomagnesemia  Hyponatremia Liver Function Tests Abnormal   0  9.3  18.6  9.3  12.8  31.4  29.1  11.6 12.8   8.5  7.4  39.4  12.8  17  51.1  48.9  8.5 4.3   12.6  10.3  43.7  17.2  13.8  48.3  40.2  9.2 9.2   
   Nervous System                        
  Dizziness Insomnia                     7 22.1           8.5 17             10.3 20.7                       
   Respiratory System                    
 Cough Increased                        8.1              2.1                10.3                             
   Skin and Appendages                   
 Rash                                   4.7              11.7               4.6                              
            Infusion Related Reactions
   In Study 94-0-002, the large, double-blind study of pediatric and adult febrile neutropenic patients, no premedication to prevent infusion related reaction was administered prior to the first dose of study drug (Day 1). Am  B  isome-treated patients had a lower incidence of infusion related fever (17% versus 44%), chills/rigors (18% versus 54%) and vomiting (6% versus 8%) on Day 1 as compared to amphotericin B deoxycholate-treated patients.



 The incidence of infusion related reactions on Day 1 in pediatric and adult patients is summarized in the following table:



 Incidence of Day 1 Infusion Related Reactions (IRR) By Patient Age 
                   Pediatric Patients   (&lt;=16 years of age)     Adult Patients   (&gt; 16 years of age)     
                    AmBisome         Amphotericin B          AmBisome          Amphotericin B                
  
   Total number of patients receiving at least one dose of study drug    48               47                      295               297                             
   Patients with fever    Increase  &gt;=1.0  o  C  6 (13%)          22 (47%)                52 (18%)          128 (43%)                       
   Patients with chills/rigors    4 (8%)           22 (47%)                59 (20%)          165 (56%)                       
   Patients with nausea    4 (8%)           4 (9%)                  38 (13%)          31 (10%)                        
   Patients with vomiting    2 (4%)           7 (15%)                 19 (6%)           21 (7%)                         
   Patients with other reactions    10 (21%)         13 (28%)                47 (16%)          69 (23%)                        
           Cardiorespiratory events, except for vasodilatation (flushing), during all study drug infusions were more frequent in amphotericin B-treated patients as summarized in the following table:
 

 Incidence of Infusion Related Cardiorespiratory Events 
   Event                       AmBisome  n=343                   Amphotericin B   n=344                   
  
 Hypotension                  12 (3.5%)                         28 (8.1%)                                 
 Tachycardia                  8 (2.3%)                          43 (12.5%)                                
 Hypertension                 8 (2.3%)                          39 (11.3%)                                
 Vasodilatation               18 (5.2%)                         2 (0.6%)                                  
 Dyspnea                      16 (4.7%)                         25 (7.3%)                                 
 Hyperventilation             4 (1.2%)                          17 (4.9%)                                 
 Hypoxia                      1 (0.3%)                          22 (6.4%)                                 
         The percentage of patients who received drugs either for the treatment or prevention of infusion related reactions (e.g., acetaminophen, diphenhydramine, meperidine and hydrocortisone) was lower in Am  B  isome-treated patients compared with amphotericin B deoxycholate-treated patients.
 

 In the empirical therapy study 97-0-034, on Day 1, where no premedication was administered, the overall incidence of infusion related events of chills/rigors was significantly lower for patients administered Am  B  isome compared with amphotericin B lipid complex. Fever, chills/rigors and hypoxia were significantly lower for each Am  B  isome group compared with the amphotericin B lipid complex group. The infusion related event hypoxia was reported for 11.5% of amphotericin B lipid complex-treated patients compared with 0% of patients administered 3 mg/kg per day Am  B  isome and 1.2% of patients treated with 5 mg/kg per day Am  B  isome.



 Incidence of Day 1 Infusion Related Reactions (IRR) Chills/Rigors Empirical Therapy Study 97-0-034 
                                 AmBisome          Amphotericin B lipid complex   5 mg/kg/day     
                                 3 mg/kg/day        5 mg/kg/day      BOTH                                    
 Total number of patients      85                 81               166             78                        
 Patients with Chills/Rigors (Day1)  16 (18.8%)         19 (23.5%)       35 (21.1%)      62 (79.5%)                
  Patients with other notable reactions:                                                                                 
  Fever(&gt;=1oC increase in temperature)    20 (23.5%)         16 (19.8%)       36 (21.7%)      45 (57.7%)               
  Nausea  Vomiting  Hypertension  Tachycardia  Dyspnea Hypoxia   9 (10.6%)  5 (5.9%)  4 (4.7%)  2 (2.4%)  4 (4.7%) 0   7 (8.6%)  5 (6.2%)  7 (8.6%)  8 (9.9%)  8 (9.9%) 1 (1.2%)   16 (9.6%)  10 (6%)  11 (6.6%)  10 (6%)  12 (7.2%) 1 (&lt;1%)   9 (11.5%)  11 (14.1%)  12 (15.4%)  14 (17.9%)  8 (10.3%) 9 (11.5%)   
           Day 1 body temperature increased above the temperature taken within 1 hour prior to infusion (preinfusion temperature) or above the lowest infusion value (no preinfusion temperature recorded).
 

 Patients were not administered premedications to prevent infusion related reactions prior to the Day 1 study drug infusion.



 In Study 94-0-013, a randomized double-blind multicenter trial comparing Am  B  isome and amphotericin B deoxycholate as initial therapy for cryptococcal meningitis, premedications to prevent infusion related reactions were permitted. Am  B  isome treated patients had a lower incidence of fever, chill/rigors and respiratory adverse events as summarized in the following table:



 Incidence of Infusion-Related Reactions Study 94-0-013 
                                    Am  B  isome 3 mg/kg  Am  B  isome 6 mg/kg  Amphotericin B                    
  
 Total number of patients receiving at least one dose of study drug  86                 94                 87                                
 Patients with fever increase of &gt;1oC  6 (7%)             8 (9%)             24 (28%)                          
 Patients with chills/rigors        5 (6%)             8 (9%)             42 (48%)                          
 Patients with nausea               11 (13%)           13 (14%)           18 (20%)                          
 Patients with vomiting             14 (16%)           13 (14%)           16 (18%)                          
 Respiratory adverse events         0                  1 (1%)             8 (9%)                            
           
 

 There have been a few reports of flushing, back pain with or without chest tightness, and chest pain associated with Am  B  isome administration; on occasion this has been severe. Where these symptoms were noted, the reaction developed within a few minutes after the start of infusion and disappeared rapidly when the infusion was stopped. The symptoms do not occur with every dose and usually do not recur on subsequent administrations when the infusion rate is slowed.



   Toxicity and Discontinuation of Dosing

  In Study 94-0-002, a significantly lower incidence of grade 3 or 4 toxicity was observed in the Am  B  isome group compared with the amphotericin B group. In addition, nearly three times as many patients administered amphotericin B required a reduction in dose due to toxicity or discontinuation of study drug due to an infusion related reaction compared with those administered Am  B  isome.



 In empirical therapy study 97-0-034, a greater proportion of patients in the amphotericin B lipid complex group discontinued the study drug due to an adverse event than in the Am  B  isome groups.



   Less Common Adverse Events

  The following adverse events also have been reported in 2% to 10% of Am  B  isome-treated patients receiving chemotherapy or bone marrow transplantation, or had HIV disease in six comparative, clinical trials:



     Body as a Whole    



 Abdomen enlarged, allergic reaction, cellulitis, cell mediated immunological reaction, face edema, graft versus host disease, malaise, neck pain, and procedural complication  .  



     Cardiovascular        System    



 Arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, cardiac arrest, cardiomegaly, hemorrhage, postural hypotension, valvular heart disease, vascular disorder, and vasodilatation (flushing).



     Digestive System    



 Anorexia, constipation, dry mouth/nose, dyspepsia, dysphagia, eructation, fecal incontinence, flatulence, hemorrhoids, gum/oral hemorrhage, hematemesis, hepatocellular damage, hepatomegaly, liver function test abnormal, ileus, mucositis, rectal disorder, stomatitis, ulcerative stomatitis, and veno-occlusive liver disease  .  



     Hemic &amp; Lymphatic System    



 Anemia, coagulation disorder, ecchymosis, fluid overload, petechia, prothrombin decreased, prothrombin increased, and thrombocytopenia.



     Metabolic &amp; Nutritional Disorders    



 Acidosis, amylase increased, hyperchloremia, hyperkalemia, hypermagnesemia, hyperphosphatemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, hypoproteinemia, lactate dehydrogenase increased, nonprotein nitrogen (NPN) increased, and respiratory alkalosis.



     Musculoskeletal System    



 Arthralgia, bone pain, dystonia, myalgia, and rigors.



     Nervous System    



 Agitation, coma, convulsion, cough, depression, dysesthesia, dizziness, hallucinations, nervousness, paresthesia, somnolence, thinking abnormality, and tremor.



     Respiratory System    



 Asthma, atelectasis, hemoptysis, hiccup, hyperventilation, influenza-like symptoms, lung edema, pharyngitis, pneumonia, respiratory insufficiency, respiratory failure, and sinusitis.



     Skin &amp; Appendages    



 Alopecia, dry skin, herpes simplex, injection site inflammation, maculopapular rash, purpura, skin discoloration, skin disorder, skin ulcer, urticaria, and vesiculobullous rash.



     Special Senses    



 Conjunctivitis, dry eyes, and eye hemorrhage.



     Urogenital System    



 Abnormal renal function, acute kidney failure, acute renal failure, dysuria, kidney failure, toxic nephropathy, urinary incontinence, and vaginal hemorrhage.



   Post-marketing Experience

  The following infrequent adverse experiences have been reported in post-marketing surveillance, in addition to those mentioned above: angioedema, erythema, urticaria, bronchospasm, cyanosis/hypoventilation, pulmonary edema, agranulocytosis, hemorrhagic cystitis, and rhabdomyolysis.



   Clinical Laboratory Values

  The effect of Am  B  isome on renal and hepatic function and on serum electrolytes was assessed from laboratory values measured repeatedly in Study 94-0-002. The frequency and magnitude of hepatic test abnormalities were similar in the Am  B  isome and amphotericin B groups. Nephrotoxicity was defined as creatinine values increasing 100% or more over pretreatment levels in pediatric patients, and creatinine values increasing 100% or more over pretreatment levels in adult patients provided the peak creatinine concentration was &gt;1.2 mg/dL. Hypokalemia was defined as potassium levels &lt;=2.5 mmol/L any time during treatment.



 Incidence of nephrotoxicity, mean peak serum creatinine concentration, mean change from baseline in serum creatinine, and, incidence of hypokalemia in the double-blind randomized study were lower in the Am  B  isome group as summarized in the following table:



 Study 94-0-002 Laboratory Evidence of Nephrotoxicity 
                                               AmBisome                   Amphotericin B                    
  
 Total number of patients receiving at least one dose of study drug  343                        344                                 
 Nephrotoxicity                              64 (18.7%)                 116 (33.7%)                         
 Mean peak creatinine                        1.24 mg/dL                 1.52 mg/dL                          
 Mean change from baseline in creatinine     0.48 mg/dL                 0.77 mg/dL                          
 Hypokalemia                                 23 (6.7%)                  40 (11.6%)                          
          
 

 The effect of Am  B  isome (3 mg/kg/day) vs. amphotericin B (0.6 mg/kg/day) on renal function in adult patients enrolled in this study is illustrated in the following figure:



 In empirical therapy study 97-0-034, the incidence of nephrotoxicity as measured by increases of serum creatinine from baseline was significantly lower for patients administered Am  B  isome (individual dose groups and combined) compared with amphotericin B lipid complex.



   Incidence of Nephrotoxicity  



 Empirical Therapy Study 97-0-034 
                                AmBisome         Amphotericin B lipid complex   5 mg/kg/day     
                                3 mg/kg/day       5 mg/kg/day      BOTH                                       
   Total number of patients    85                81              166             78                           
   Number with nephrotoxicity     
   1.5X baseline serum creatinine value    25 (29.4%)        21 (25.9%)      46 (27.7%)      49 (62.8%)                   
   2X baseline serum creatinine value    12 (14.1%)        12 (14.8%)      24 (14.5%)      33 (42.3%)                   
           The following graph shows the average serum creatinine concentrations in the compassionate use study and shows that there is a drop from pretreatment concentrations for all patients, especially those with elevated (greater than 1.7 mg/dL) pretreatment creatinine concentrations.
 

 The incidence of nephrotoxicity in Study 94-0-013, comparative trial in cryptococcal meningitis was lower in the Am  B  isome groups as shown in the following table:



 Laboratory Evidence of Nephrotoxicity Study 94-0-013 
                             AmBisome  3 mg/kg      AmBisome  6 mg/kg     Amphotericin B                    
  
 Total number of patients receiving at least one dose of study drug  86                     94                     87                                
  Number with Nephrotoxicity (%)   
 1.5X baseline serum creatinine  30 (35%)               44 (47%)               52 (60%)                          
 2 X baseline serum creatinine  12 (14%)               20 (21%)               29 (33%)                          
           graph1  graph2 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
