<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ameluz" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Risk of BF-RhodoLED Lamp Induced Eye Injury [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ] . 
 *  Increased Photosensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] . 
 *  Risk of Bleeding in Patients with Coagulation Disorders [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] . 
 *  Ophthalmic Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ] . 
 *  Risk of Mucous Membrane Irritation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ] . 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) were application site erythema, pain/burning, irritation, edema, pruritus, exfoliation, scab, induration, and vesicles (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Biofrontera Inc. at 1-844-829-7434 or FDA at 1-800-332-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The clinical program for AMELUZ included three double-blind and placebo-controlled trials (Trials 1, 2, and 3), enrolling a total of 299 subjects that were treated with narrow band light. Trial subjects were adults greater than or equal to 49 years of age, and the majority had Fitzpatrick skin type I, II, or III. No subjects had Fitzpatrick skin type V or VI. Approximately 86% of subjects were male, and all subjects were Caucasian.



 For all trials, the enrolled subjects had mild to moderate AKs (Olsen grade 1 and 2) with 4 to 8 lesions on the face and scalp. Overall, 87 placebo-treated subjects (n=16, n=32, n=39) and 212 AMELUZ-treated subjects (n=32, n=55, and n=125) were illuminated with BF-RhodoLED or similar narrow spectrum lamps.



 Local skin reactions at the application site were observed in about 99.5% of subjects treated with AMELUZ and narrow spectrum lamps. The most frequent adverse reactions during and after PDT were application site erythema, pain, burning, irritation, edema, pruritus, exfoliation, scab, induration, and vesicles.



 Most adverse reactions occurred during illumination or shortly afterwards, were generally of mild or moderate intensity, and lasted for 1 to 4 days in most cases; in some cases, however, they persisted for 1 to 2 weeks or even longer. Severe pain/burning occurred in up to 30% of subjects. In one case, the adverse reactions required interruption or discontinuation of the illumination.



 The incidence of common (&gt;=1%, &lt;10%) and very common (&gt;=10%) adverse reactions in randomized, multicenter trials at the application site are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1: Incidence of Adverse Reactions Occurring at &gt;=1% of the AMELUZ Group and More Frequently than the Vehicle Group in the Actinic Keratosis Trials at the Application Site 
  Adverse reaction                   Vehiclen=87                        AMELUZn=212                        
  Adverse reactions at theapplication site                                                                          
  Erythema  Pain/Burning  Irritation  Edema  Pruritus  Exfoliation  Scab  Induration  Vesicles  Paresthesia  Hyperalgesia  Reaction  Discomfort  Erosion  Discharge  Bleeding  Pustules    34 (39%)  26 (30%)  17 (20%)  3 (3%)  14 (16%)  4 (5%)  2 (2%)  0 (0%)  1 (1%)  2 (2%)  0 (0%)  2 (2%)  0 (0%)  0 (0%)  0 (0%)  0 (0%)  0 (0%)    195 (92%)  195 (92%)  153 (72%)  75 (35%)  72 (34%)  41 (19%)  41 (19%)  26 (12%)  25 (12%)  18 (9%)  10 (5%)  8 (4%)  7 (3%)  6 (3%)  4 (2%)  3 (1%)  3 (1%)    
      Common (&gt;=1%, &lt;10%) adverse reactions not limited to the application site were chills, headache, and skin exfoliation.
 

 Uncommon (&gt;=0.1%, &lt;1%) adverse reactions at the application site for AMELUZ were hemorrhage and swelling. The adverse reactions not limited to the application site were eyelid edema, feeling hot, pain, pyrexia, ulcer, hyperalgesia, rash pustular, nervousness, blister, petechiae, pruritus, scab and skin erosion.



 In a clinical trial designed to investigate the sensitization potential of aminolevulinic acid with 216 healthy subjects, 13 subjects (6%) developed allergic contact dermatitis after continuous exposure for 21 days with doses of aminolevulinic acid that were higher than doses normally used in the treatment of AK.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of AMELUZ outside the United States. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  erythema, swelling, application site inflammation and skin discoloration.



   Eye disorders:  eye irritation, diplopia, ocular hyperemia, photophobia, and blurred vision.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Risk of Eye Injury: Patients and healthcare providers must wear protective eyewear before operating BF-RhodoLED lamp (  5.1  ). 
 *   Photosensitivity: Protect treated lesions from sunlight exposure for 48 hours post treatment (  5.2  ). 
 *   Risk of Bleeding: Special care should be taken to avoid bleeding during lesion preparation in patients with inherited or acquired coagulation disorders (  5.3  ). 
 *   Ophthalmic Adverse Reactions: Avoid direct contact of AMELUZ with the eyes (  5.4  ). 
 *   Mucous Membrane Irritation: Avoid direct contact of AMELUZ with the mucous membranes (  5.5  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of BF-RhodoLED Lamp Induced Eye Injury



  BF-RhodoLED lamp may cause eye irritation, glare, or injury. Before operating the lamp, personnel must refer to the user manual for specific warnings, cautions, and instructions. Eye exposure to the BF-RhodoLED light must be prevented. Protective eye equipment must be used by patient, healthcare providers and any person present during the illumination period. Avoid staring directly into the light source [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



    5.2 Increased Photosensitivity



  AMELUZ increases photosensitivity. Avoid sunlight, prolonged or intense light (e.g., tanning beds, sun lamps) on lesions and surrounding skin treated with AMELUZ for approximately 48 hours following treatment whether exposed to illumination or not. Concomitant use of AMELUZ with other known photosensitizing agents may increase the risk of phototoxic reaction to PDT [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .



    5.3 Risk of Bleeding in Patients with Coagulation Disorders



  AMELUZ has not been tested on patients with inherited or acquired coagulation disorders.



 Special care should be taken to avoid bleeding during lesion preparation in such patients [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  . Any bleeding must be stopped before application of the gel.



    5.4 Ophthalmic Adverse Reactions



  Eyelid edema has occurred with AMELUZ application. AMELUZ can cause ophthalmic adverse reactions. AMELUZ is intended for topical use only. Do not apply AMELUZ into the eyes. Rinse eyes with water in case of accidental contact.



    5.5 Risk of Mucous Membrane Irritation



  AMELUZ can cause mucous membrane irritation. AMELUZ is intended for topical use only. Do not apply AMELUZ to the mucous membranes. Rinse with water in case of accidental contact.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
