<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="amerge" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *    Myocardial ischemia, myocardial infarction, and Prinzmetal's angina [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Arrhythmias [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Chest, throat, neck, and/or jaw pain/tightness/pressure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *    Cerebrovascular events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *    Other vasospasm reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
 *    Medication overuse headache [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]  
 *    Serotonin syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)]  
 *    Increase in blood pressure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  
 *    Hypersensitivity reactions [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.9)]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2 % and &gt; placebo) were paresthesias, nausea, dizziness, drowsiness, malaise/fatigue, and throat/neck symptoms. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a long-term open-label trial where patients were allowed to treat multiple migraine attacks for up to 1 year, 15 patients (3.6%) discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions.



 In controlled clinical trials, the most common adverse reactions were paresthesias, dizziness, drowsiness, malaise/fatigue, and throat/neck symptoms, which occurred at a rate of 2% and at least 2 times placebo rate.



 Table 1 lists the adverse reactions that occurred in 5 placebo-controlled clinical trials of approximately 1,752 exposures to placebo and AMERGE in adult patients with migraine. Only reactions that occurred at a frequency of 2% or more in groups treated with AMERGE 2.5 mg and that occurred at a frequency greater than the placebo group in the 5 pooled trials are included in Table 1.



   Table 1. Adverse Reactions Reported by at Least 2% of Patients Treated with AMERGE and at a Frequency Greater than Placebo  




  Adverse Reaction                         Percent of Patients Reporting    
  AMERGE 1 mg  (n = 627)                   AMERGE 2.5 mg  (n = 627)    Placebo  (n = 498)         
  Atypical sensation                       2                        4                          1               
                                          Paresthesias (all types)                
                                                                                    1                        2                          &lt;1              
  Gastrointestinal                         6                        7                          5               
                                          Nausea                                  
                                                                                    4                        5                          4               
  Neurological                             4                        7                          3               
                                          Dizziness                               
                                                                                    1                        2                          1               
                                          Drowsiness                              
                                                                                    1                        2                          &lt;1              
                                          Malaise/fatigue                         
                                                                                    2                        2                          1               
  Pain and pressure sensation              2                        4                          2               
                                          Throat/neck symptoms                    
                                                                                    1                        2                          1               
          The incidence of adverse reactions in controlled clinical trials was not affected by age or weight of the patients, duration of headache prior to treatment, presence of aura, use of prophylactic medications, or tobacco use. There were insufficient data to assess the impact of race on the incidence of adverse reactions.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Myocardial ischemia/infarction and Prinzmetal's angina: Perform cardiac evaluation in patients with multiple cardiovascular risk factors. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Arrhythmias: Discontinue AMERGE if occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Chest/throat/neck/jaw pain, tightness, pressure, or heaviness: Generally not associated with myocardial ischemia; evaluate for CAD in patients at high risk. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Cerebral hemorrhage, subarachnoid hemorrhage, and stroke: Discontinue AMERGE if occurs. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Gastrointestinal ischemic reactions and peripheral vasospastic reactions: Discontinue AMERGE if occurs. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Medication overuse headache: Detoxification may be necessary. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Serotonin syndrome: Discontinue AMERGE if occurs. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myocardial Ischemia, Myocardial Infarction, and Prinzmetal's Angina



  AMERGE is contraindicated in patients with ischemic or vasospastic CAD. There have been rare reports of serious cardiac adverse reactions, including acute myocardial infarction, occurring within a few hours following administration of AMERGE. Some of these reactions occurred in patients without known CAD. AMERGE may cause coronary artery vasospasm (Prinzmetal's angina) even in patients without a history of CAD.



 Perform a cardiovascular evaluation in triptan-naive patients who have multiple cardiovascular risk factors (e.g., increased age, diabetes, hypertension, smoking, obesity, strong family history of CAD) prior to receiving AMERGE. If there is evidence of CAD or coronary artery vasospasm, AMERGE is contraindicated. For patients with multiple cardiovascular risk factors who have a negative cardiovascular evaluation, consider administering the first dose of AMERGE in a medically supervised setting and performing an electrocardiogram (ECG) immediately following administration of AMERGE. For such patients, consider periodic cardiovascular evaluation in intermittent long-term users of AMERGE.



    5.2 Arrhythmias



  Life-threatening disturbances of cardiac rhythm, including ventricular tachycardia and ventricular fibrillation leading to death, have been reported within a few hours following the administration of 5-HT1agonists. Discontinue AMERGE if these disturbances occur. AMERGE is contraindicated in patients with Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome or arrhythmias associated with other cardiac accessory conduction pathway disorders.



    5.3 Chest, Throat, Neck, and/or Jaw Pain/Tightness/Pressure



  Sensations of tightness, pain, and pressure in the chest, throat, neck, and jaw commonly occur after treatment with AMERGE and are usually non-cardiac in origin. However, perform a cardiac evaluation if these patients are at high cardiac risk. 5-HT1agonists, including AMERGE, are contraindicated in patients with CAD and those with Prinzmetal's variant angina.



    5.4 Cerebrovascular Events



  Cerebral hemorrhage, subarachnoid hemorrhage, and stroke have occurred in patients treated with 5-HT1agonists, and some have resulted in fatalities. In a number of cases, it appears possible that the cerebrovascular events were primary, the 5-HT1agonist having been administered in the incorrect belief that the symptoms experienced were a consequence of migraine when they were not. Also, patients with migraine may be at increased risk of certain cerebrovascular events (e.g., stroke, hemorrhage, TIA). Discontinue AMERGE if a cerebrovascular event occurs.



 Before treating headaches in patients not previously diagnosed as migraineurs, and in migraineurs who present with symptoms atypical for migraine, exclude other potentially serious neurological conditions. AMERGE is contraindicated in patients with a history of stroke or TIA.



    5.5 Other Vasospasm Reactions



  AMERGE may cause non-coronary vasospastic reactions, such as peripheral vascular ischemia, gastrointestinal vascular ischemia and infarction (presenting with abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea), splenic infarction, and Raynaud's syndrome. In patients who experience symptoms or signs suggestive of non-coronary vasospasm reaction following the use of any 5-HT1agonist, rule out a vasospastic reaction before receiving additional doses of AMERGE.



 Reports of transient and permanent blindness and significant partial vision loss have been reported with the use of 5-HT1agonists. Since visual disorders may be part of a migraine attack, a causal relationship between these events and the use of 5-HT1agonists have not been clearly established.



    5.6 Medication Overuse Headache



  Overuse of acute migraine drugs (e.g., ergotamine, triptans, opioids, or combination of these drugs for 10 or more days per month) may lead to exacerbation of headache (medication overuse headache). Medication overuse headache may present as migraine-like daily headaches or as a marked increase in frequency of migraine attacks. Detoxification of patients, including withdrawal of the overused drugs, and treatment of withdrawal symptoms (which often includes a transient worsening of headache) may be necessary.



    5.7 Serotonin Syndrome



  Serotonin syndrome may occur with AMERGE, particularly during co-administration with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), and monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors [see Drug Interactions (7.3)]  . Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination), and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). The onset of symptoms usually occurs within minutes to hours of receiving a new or a greater dose of a serotonergic medication. Discontinue AMERGE if serotonin syndrome is suspected.



    5.8 Increase in Blood Pressure



  Significant elevation in blood pressure, including hypertensive crisis with acute impairment of organ systems, has been reported on rare occasions in patients treated with 5-HT1agonists, including patients without a history of hypertension. Monitor blood pressure in patients treated with AMERGE. AMERGE is contraindicated in patients with uncontrolled hypertension.



    5.9 Anaphylactic/Anaphylactoid Reactions



  There have been reports of anaphylaxis and anaphylactoid and hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema, in patients receiving AMERGE. Such reactions can be life threatening or fatal. In general, anaphylactic reactions to drugs are more likely to occur in individuals with a history of sensitivity to multiple allergens. AMERGE is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity reaction to AMERGE.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
