<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="amlodipine2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=3%) edema (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Daiichi Sankyo, Inc. at 1-877-437-7763 or FDA at 1-800-332-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets  The data described below reflect exposure to amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets in more than 1600 patients including more than 1000 exposed for at least 6 months and more than 700 exposed for 1 year. Amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets were studied in one placebo-controlled factorial trial (See Section  14.1  ). The population had a mean age of 54 years and included approximately 55% males. Seventy-one percent were Caucasian and 25% were Black. Patients received doses ranging from 5/20 mg to 10/40 mg orally once daily.



 The overall incidence of adverse reactions on therapy with amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets was similar to that seen with corresponding doses of the individual components of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets, and to placebo. The reported adverse reactions were generally mild and seldom led to discontinuation of treatment (2.6% for amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets and 6.8% for placebo).



   Edema  Edema is a known, dose-dependent adverse effect of amlodipine but not of olmesartan medoxomil.



 The placebo-subtracted incidence of edema during the 8-week, randomized, double-blind treatment period was highest with amlodipine 10 mg monotherapy. The incidence was significantly reduced when 20 mg or 40 mg of olmesartan medoxomil was added to the 10 mg amlodipine dose.



   Placebo-Subtracted Incidence of Edema During the Double-Blind Treatment Period  




                         Olmesartan Medoxomil     
       Placebo                20 mg                 40 mg           
      Amlodipine             Placebo                  -*                  -2.4%                  6.2%           
         5 mg                  0.7%                  5.7%                  6.2%           
        10 mg                 24.5%                 13.3%                 11.2%           
 *12.3% = actual placebo incidence   
           Across all treatment groups, the frequency of edema was generally higher in women than men, as has been observed in previous studies of amlodipine.
 

 Adverse reactions seen at lower rates during the double-blind period also occurred in the patients treated with amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets at about the same or greater incidence as in patients receiving placebo. These included hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, rash, pruritus, palpitation, urinary frequency, and nocturia.



 The adverse event profile obtained from 44 weeks of open-label combination therapy with amlodipine plus olmesartan medoxomil was similar to that observed during the 8-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled period.



   Initial Therapy  Analyzing the data described above specifically for initial therapy, it was observed that higher doses of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets caused slightly more hypotension and orthostatic symptoms, but not at the recommended starting dose of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets 5/20 mg. No increase in the incidence of syncope or near syncope was observed. The incidences of discontinuation because of any treatment emergent adverse events in the double blind phase are summarized in the table below.



   Discontinuation for any Treatment Emergent Adverse Event  1    




                              Olmesartan Medoxomil      
   Placebo                    10 mg                      20 mg                      40 mg                     
   Amlodipine                 Placebo                  4.9%                       4.3%                       5.6%                       3.1%                        
   5 mg                     3.7%                       0.0%                       1.2%                       3.7%                        
   10 mg                    5.5%                       6.8%                       2.5%                       5.6%                        
   1  Hypertension is counted as treatment failure and not as treatment emergent adverse event.N=160-163 subjects per treatment group.   
        Amlodipine  Amlodipine has been evaluated for safety in more than 11,000 patients in U.S. and foreign clinical trials. Most adverse reactions reported during therapy with amlodipine were of mild or moderate severity. In controlled clinical trials directly comparing amlodipine (N=1730) in doses up to 10 mg to placebo (N=1250), discontinuation of amlodipine due to adverse reactions was required in only about 1.5% of amlodipine-treated patients and about 1% of placebo-treated patients. The most common side effects were headache and edema. The incidence (%) of dose-related side effects was as follows:
 


 Adverse Event              PlaceboN=520               2.5 mgN=275                5.0 mgN=296                10.0 mgN=268                
 Edema                      0.6                        1.8                        3.0                        10.8                        
 Dizziness                  1.5                        1.1                        3.4                        3.4                         
 Flushing                   0.0                        0.7                        1.4                        2.6                         
 Palpitation                0.6                        0.7                        1.4                        4.5                         
      For several adverse experiences that appear to be drug- and dose-related, there was a greater incidence in women than men associated with amlodipine treatment as shown in the following table:
 


 Adverse Event              Placebo                    Amlodipine                  
                            Male=%(N=914)              Female=%(N=336)            Male=%(N=1218)             Female=%(N=512)             
 Edema                      1.4                        5.1                        5.6                        14.6                        
 Flushing                   0.3                        0.9                        1.5                        4.5                         
 Palpitation                0.9                        0.9                        1.4                        3.3                         
 Somnolence                 0.8                        0.3                        1.3                        1.6                         
        Olmesartan medoxomil.  Olmesartan medoxomil has been evaluated for safety in more than 3825 patients/subjects, including more than 3275 patients treated for hypertension in controlled trials. This experience included about 900 patients treated for at least 6 months and more than 525 treated for at least 1 year. Treatment with olmesartan medoxomil was well tolerated, with an incidence of adverse events similar to that seen with placebo. Events were generally mild, transient, and without relationship to the dose of olmesartan medoxomil.
 

 The overall frequency of adverse events was not dose-related. Analysis of gender, age, and race groups demonstrated no differences between olmesartan medoxomil- and placebo-treated patients. The rate of withdrawals due to adverse events in all trials of hypertensive patients was 2.4% (i.e., 79/3278) of patients treated with olmesartan medoxomil and 2.7% (i.e., 32/1179) of control patients. In placebo-controlled trials, the only adverse event that occurred in more than 1% of patients treated with olmesartan medoxomil and at a higher incidence in olmesartan medoxomil treated patients vs. placebo was dizziness (3% vs 1%).



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of the individual components of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Amlodipine.  The following post-marketing event has been reported infrequently where a causal relationship is uncertain: gynecomastia. In post-marketing experience, jaundice and hepatic enzyme elevations (mostly consistent with cholestasis or hepatitis), in some cases severe enough to require hospitalization, have been reported in association with use of amlodipine.



   Olmesartan medoxomil.  The following adverse reactions have been reported in post-marketing experience:



        Body as a Whole:  asthenia, angioedema, anaphylactic reactions, peripheral edema



        Gastrointestinal:  vomiting, diarrhea, sprue-like enteropathy [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )  ]



        Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  hyperkalemia



        Musculoskeletal:  rhabdomyolysis



        Urogenital System:  acute renal failure



        Skin and Appendages:  alopecia, pruritus, urticaria



 Data from one controlled trial and an epidemiologic study have suggested that high-dose olmesartan may increase cardiovascular (CV) risk in diabetic patients, but the overall data are not conclusive. The randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind ROADMAP trial (Randomized Olmesartan And Diabetes MicroAlbuminuria Prevention trial, n=4447) examined the use of olmesartan, 40 mg daily, vs. placebo in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, normoalbuminuria, and at least one additional risk factor for CV disease. The trial met its primary endpoint, delayed onset of microalbuminuria, but olmesartan had no beneficial effect on decline in glomerular filtration rate (GFR). There was a finding of increased CV mortality (adjudicated sudden cardiac death, fatal myocardial infarction, fatal stroke, revascularization death) in the olmesartan group compared to the placebo group (15 olmesartan vs. 3 placebo, HR 4.9, 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.4, 17), but the risk of non-fatal myocardial infarction was lower with olmesartan (HR 0.64, 95% CI 0.35, 1.18).



 The epidemiologic study included patients 65 years and older with overall exposure of &gt; 300,000 patient-years. In the sub-group of diabetic patients receiving high-dose olmesartan (40 mg/d) for &gt; 6 months, there appeared to be an increased risk of death (HR 2.0, 95% CI 1.1, 3.8) compared to similar patients taking other angiotensin receptor blockers. In contrast, high-dose olmesartan use in non-diabetic patients appeared to be associated with a decreased risk of death (HR 0.46, 95% CI 0.24, 0.86) compared to similar patients taking other angiotensin receptor blockers. No differences were observed between the groups receiving lower doses of olmesartan compared to other angiotensin blockers or those receiving therapy for &lt; 6 months.



 Overall, these data raise a concern of a possible increased CV risk associated with the use of high-dose olmesartan in diabetic patients. There are, however, concerns with the credibility of the finding of increased CV risk, notably the observation in the large epidemiologic study for a survival benefit in non-diabetics of a magnitude similar to the adverse finding in diabetics.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

  WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets as soon as possible (5.1). 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1). 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY    See full prescribing information for   complete boxed warning  .  
 

 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets as soon as possible (5.1). 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Avoid fetal (in utero) exposure (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypotension in volume- or salt-depleted patients with treatment initiation may be anticipated. Start treatment under close supervision (  5.2  ). 
 *  Increased angina or myocardial infarction with calcium channel blockers may occur upon dosage initiation or increase (  5.4  ). 
 *  Impaired renal function: changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individual  5.6  ). 
 *  Sprue-like enteropathy has been reported. Consider discontinuation of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets in cases where no other etiology is found (  5.8  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Fetal toxicity



   Pregnancy Category D  



 Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets as soon as possible possible [See Use in specific Populations (  8.1  ]  .



    5.2 Hypotension in Volume- or Salt-Depleted Patients



   Olmesartan medoxomil.  Symptomatic hypotension may be anticipated after initiation of treatment with olmesartan medoxomil. Patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- and/or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics) may be particularly vulnerable. Initiate treatment with amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets under close medical supervision. If hypotension does occur, place the patient in the supine position and, if necessary, give an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.



    5.3 Vasodilation



   Amlodipine.  Since the vasodilation attributable to amlodipine in amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets is gradual in onset, acute hypotension has rarely been reported after oral administration. Nonetheless, exercise caution, as with any other peripheral vasodilator, when administering amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tabltes, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis.



    5.4 Patients with Severe Obstructive Coronary Artery Disease



  Patients, particularly those with severe obstructive coronary artery disease, may develop increased frequency, duration, or severity of angina or acute myocardial infarction on starting calcium channel blocker therapy or at the time of dosage increase. The mechanism of this effect has not been elucidated.



    5.5 Patients with Congestive Heart Failure



   Amlodipine.  Amlodipine (5-10 mg per day) has been studied in a placebo-controlled trial of 1153 patients with NYHA Class III or IV heart failure on stable doses of ACE inhibitor, digoxin, and diuretics. Follow-up was at least 6 months, with a mean of about 14 months. There was no overall adverse effect on survival or cardiac morbidity (as defined by life-threatening arrhythmia, acute myocardial infarction, or hospitalization for worsened heart failure). Amlodipine has been compared to placebo in four 8-12 week studies of patients with NYHA class II/III heart failure, involving a total of 697 patients. In these studies, there was no evidence of worsening of heart failure based on measures of exercise tolerance, NYHA classification, symptoms, or LVEF.



    5.6 Patients with Impaired Renal Function



   Amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets.  There are no studies of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets in patients with renal impairment.



  Olmesartan medoxomil.  Changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals treated with olmesartan medoxomil as a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system. In patients whose renal function may depend upon the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar effects may occur in patients treated with amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets because of the olmesartan medoxomil component [See Drug Interactions (  7  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )  ].



 In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen (BUN) have been reported. There has been no long-term use of olmesartan medoxomil in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but similar effects would be expected with olmesartan medoxomil and amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets.



    5.7 Patients with Hepatic Impairment



   Amlodipine.  Since amlodipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and the plasma elimination half-life (t1/2) is 56 hours in patients with severely impaired hepatic function, exercise caution when administering amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets to patients with severe hepatic impairment.



 Patients with hepatic impairment have decreased clearance of amlodipine. Starting amlodipine or adding amlodipine at 2.5 mg in hepatically impaired patients is recommended. The lowest dose of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil is 5/20 mg; therefore, initial therapy with amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets is not recommended in hepatically impaired patients [See Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  )  ].



    5.8 Sprue-like Enteropathy



  Severe, chronic diarrhea with substantial weight loss has been reported in patients taking olmesartan months to years after drug initiation. Intestinal biopsies of patients often demonstrated villous atrophy. If a patient develops these symptoms during treatment with olmesartan, exclude other etiologies. Consider discontinuation of amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets in cases where no other etiology is identified.



       5.9 Electrolyte and Metabolic Imbalances



     Amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets contain olmesartan, a drug that inhibits the renin-angiotensin system (RAS). Drugs that inhibit the RAS can cause hyperkalemia. Monitor serum electrolytes periodically.



    5.10 Laboratory Tests



   Amlodipine and olmesartan medoxomil tablets.  There was a greater decrease in hemoglobin and hematocrit in the combination product compared to either component. Other laboratory changes can usually be attributed to either monotherapy component.



  Amlodipine.  In post-marketing experience, hepatic enzyme elevations have been reported (  6.2  ).



  Olmesartan medoxomil.  In post-marketing experience, increased blood creatinine levels have been reported.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
