<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="amlodipine0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6        ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   Discontinuation because of adverse reactions occurred in 4% of Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules -treated patients and 3% of placebo-treated patients. The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy with Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules were cough and edema. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sandoz Inc at 1-800-525-8747 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

    6.1    Clinical    Trials    Experience      

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates. 



 Amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride has been evaluated for safety in over 2,991 patients with hypertension; over 500 of these patients were treated for at least 6 months, and over 400 were treated for more than 1 year.



 In a pooled analysis of 5 placebo-controlled trials involving amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride doses up to 5/20, the reported side effects were generally mild and transient, and there was no relationship between side effects and age, sex, race, or duration of therapy. Discontinuation of therapy due to side effects was required in approximately 4% of patients treated with amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride and in 3% of patients treated with placebo.



 The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy with amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride in these studies were cough and edema (including angioedema). 



 The peripheral edema associated with amlodipine use is dose-dependent. When benazepril is added to a regimen of amlodipine, the incidence of edema is substantially reduced.



 The addition of benazepril to a regimen of amlodipine should not be expected to provide additional antihypertensive effect in African-Americans. However, all patient groups benefit from the reduction in amlodipine-induced edema.



 The side effects considered possibly or probably related to study drug that occurred in these trials in more than 1% of patients treated with amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride are shown in the table below. Cough was the only adverse event with at least possible relationship to treatment that was more common on amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride (3.3%) than on placebo (0.2%).



 PERCENT INCIDENCE IN U.S. PLACEBO-CONTROLLED TRIALS 
                  Benazepril/Amlodipine  Benazepril       Amlodipine       Placebo           
                    N=760            N=554            N=475            N=408           
 Cough            3.3              1.8              0.4              0.2               
 Headache         2.2              3.8              2.9              5.6               
 Dizziness        1.3              1.6              2.3              1.5               
 Edema*           2.1              0.9              5.1              2.2               
           *Edema refers to all edema, such as dependent edema, angioedema, facial edema.
 

 The incidence of edema was greater in patients treated with amlodipine monotherapy (5.1%) than in patients treated with amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride (2.1%) or placebo (2.2%).



 Other side effects considered possibly or probably related to study drug that occurred in U.S. placebo-controlled trials of patients treated with amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride or in postmarketing experience were the following:



   Body as a Whole:  Asthenia and fatigue.



   CNS:  Insomnia, nervousness, anxiety, tremor, and decreased libido.



   Dermatologic:  Flushing, hot flashes, rash, skin nodule, and dermatitis.



   Digestive:  Dry mouth, nausea, abdominal pain, constipation, diarrhea, dyspepsia, and esophagitis.



   Hematologic:      Neutropenia



   Metabolic and Nutritional:   Hypokalemia.



   Musculoskeletal:  Back pain, musculoskeletal pain, cramps, and muscle cramps.



   Respiratory:   Pharyngitis.



   Urogenital    :  Sexual problems such as impotence, and polyuria.



 Monotherapies of benazepril and amlodipine have been evaluated for safety in clinical trials in over 6,000 and 11,000 patients, respectively. The observed adverse reactions to the monotherapies in these trials were similar to those seen in trials of amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride.



     6.2 Post-marketing Experience  

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 In postmarketing experience with benazepril, there have been rare reports of Stevens-Johnson syndrome, pancreatitis, hemolytic anemia, pemphigus, and thrombocytopenia. Gingival hyperplasia, tachycardia, jaundice, and hepatic enzyme elevations (mostly consistent with cholestasis severe enough to require hospitalization) have been reported in association with use of amlodipine. Other potentially important adverse experiences attributed to other ACE inhibitors and calcium channel blockers include: eosinophilic pneumonitis (ACE inhibitors) and gynecomastia (CCBs). Other infrequently reported events included chest pain, ventricular extrasystole, gout, neuritis, tinnitus, alopecia, upper respiratory tract infection, palpitations and somnolence.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:FETAL TOXICITY 

    WARNING:        FETAL TOXICITY   

    When pregnancy is detected, discontinue     Amlodipine        Besylate     and     Benazepril     Hydrochloride Capsules        as soon as possible (5.4).        Drugs that act directly on the     renin-angiotensin     system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.4)  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:        FETAL TOXICITY   



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   When pregnancy is detected, discontinue     Amlodipine        Besylate     and     Benazepril     Hydrochloride Capsules     as soon as possible (  5.4  ).     Drugs that act directly on the     renin-angiotensin     system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (  5.4  ).  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5      WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Watch for anaphylactoid reactions, including angioedema (head, neck or intestinal). 
 *  Warn patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease about the risk of myocardial infarction or increased angina (  5.2  ) 
 *  Assess for hypotension and hyperkalemia (  5.3  and  5.7  ) 
 *  Titrate slowly in patients with impaired hepatic (  5.5  ) or severely impaired renal (  5.6  ) function.  
    
 

    5.1   Anaphylact   o   i   d   and Possibly Related Reactions  



  Presumably because angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors affect the metabolism of eicosanoids and polypeptides, including endogenous bradykinin, patients receiving ACE inhibitors (including Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules) may be subject to a variety of adverse reactions, some of them serious. These reactions usually occur after one of the first few doses of the ACE inhibitor, but they sometimes do not appear until after months of therapy. Black patients receiving ACE inhibitors have a higher incidence of angioedema compared to nonblacks.



  Head and Neck   Angioedema   :   Angioedema of the face, extremities, lips, tongue, glottis, and larynx has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors. In U.S. clinical trials, symptoms consistent with angioedema were seen in none of the subjects who received placebo and in about 0.5% of the subjects who received benazepril. Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema can be fatal. If laryngeal stridor or angioedema of the face, tongue, or glottis occurs, discontinue treatment with Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules and treat immediately. When involvement of the tongue, glottis, or larynx appears likely to cause airway obstruction, appropriate therapy, e.g.,   administer   subcutaneous epinephrine injection 1:1000 (0.3-0.5   mL   ),   promptly  [see Adverse Reactions (6)  ].



  Intestinal   Angioedema   :  Intestinal angioedema has been reported in patients treated with ACE inhibitors. These patients presented with abdominal pain (with or without nausea or vomiting); in some cases there was no prior history of facial angioedema and C-1 esterase levels were normal. The angioedema was diagnosed by procedures including abdominal CT scan or ultrasound, or at surgery, and symptoms resolved after stopping the ACE inhibitor. Intestinal angioedema should be included in the differential diagnosis of patients on ACE inhibitors presenting with abdominal pain.



  Anaphylactoid   Reactions During Desensitization:  Two patients undergoing desensitizing treatment with hymenoptera venom while receiving ACE inhibitors sustained life-threatening anaphylactoid reactions. In the same patients, these reactions were avoided when ACE inhibitors were temporarily withheld, but they reappeared upon inadvertent rechallenge.



  Anaphylactoid   Reactions During Membrane Exposure:   Anaphylactoid reactions have been reported in patients dialyzed with high-flux membranes and treated concomitantly with an ACE inhibitor. Anaphylactoid reactions have also been reported in patients undergoing low-density lipoprotein apheresis with dextran sulfate absorption.



     5.2   Increased Angina and/or Myocardial Infarction  



  Rarely, patients, particularly those with severe obstructive coronary artery disease, have developed documented increased frequency, duration or severity of angina or acute myocardial infarction on starting calcium channel blocker therapy or at the time of dosage increase. The mechanism of this effect has not been elucidated.



     5.   3   Hypotension  



  Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules can cause symptomatic hypotension. Symptomatic hypotension is most likely to occur in patients who have been volume or salt depleted as a result of prolonged diuretic therapy, dietary salt restriction, dialysis, diarrhea, or vomiting.



 In patients with congestive heart failure, with or without associated renal insufficiency, ACE inhibitor therapy may cause excessive hypotension, which may be associated with oliguria, azotemia, and (rarely) with acute renal failure and death. In such patients, start amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride therapy under close medical supervision; follow closely for the first 2 weeks of treatment and whenever the dose of the benazepril component is increased or a diuretic is added or its dose increased.



 Symptomatic hypotension is also possible in patients with severe aortic stenosis.



 If hypotension occurs, place the patient in a supine position, and if necessary, treat with intravenous infusion of physiologic saline. Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules treatment usually can be continued following restoration of blood pressure and volume.



     5.4 Fetal Toxicity  



    Pregnancy Category D    



  Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules as soon as possible [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)].  



     5.5 Hepatic Failure     



  Rarely, ACE inhibitors have been associated with a syndrome that starts with cholestatic jaundice and progresses to fulminant hepatic necrosis and, sometimes, death. The mechanism of this syndrome is not understood. Patients receiving ACE inhibitors who develop jaundice or marked elevations of hepatic enzymes should discontinue the ACE inhibitor and receive appropriate medical follow-up.



 In patients with hepatic dysfunction due to cirrhosis, levels of benazeprilat are essentially unaltered.



 However, since amlodipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and the plasma elimination half-life (t1/2) is 56 hours in patients with impaired hepatic function, titrate amlodipine besylate and benazepril hydrochloride slowly in patients with severe hepatic impairment.



     5.6 Impaired Renal Function  



  Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules should not be used in patients with severe renal disease (Clearance creatinine &lt; 30 mL/min) [see Dosage and Administration  (2)] 



 In patients with severe heart failure, whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin aldosterone system, treatment with benazepril may be associated with oliguria or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death.



 In a small study of hypertensive patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, treatment with benazepril was associated with increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine; these increases were reversible upon discontinuation of benazepril therapy, concomitant diuretic therapy, or both. When such patients are treated with Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules, monitor renal function during the first few weeks of therapy.



 Some benazepril-treated hypertensive patients with no apparent preexisting renal vascular disease have developed increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine, usually minor and transient, especially when benazepril has been given concomitantly with a diuretic. Dosage reduction of Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules may be required.



 Renal function should be monitored periodically in patients receiving benazepril.



     5.7   Hyperkalemia  



  In U.S. placebo-controlled trials of Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules, hyperkalemia (serum potassium at least 0.5 mEq/L greater than the upper limit of normal) not present at baseline occurred in approximately 1.5% of hypertensive patients receiving Amlodipine Besylate and Benazepril Hydrochloride Capsules. Increases in serum potassium were generally reversible. Risk factors for the development of hyperkalemia include renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, and the concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium supplements, and/or potassium-containing salt substitutes. Serum potassium should be monitored periodically in patients receiving benazepril.



     5.   8   Cough  



  Presumably due to the inhibition of the degradation of endogenous bradykinin, persistent nonproductive cough has been reported with all ACE inhibitors, generally resolving after discontinuation of therapy. Consider ACE inhibitor-induced cough in the differential diagnosis of cough.



     5.   9   Surgery/Ane   s   thesia  



  In patients undergoing surgery or during anesthesia with agents that produce hypotension, benazepril will block the angiotensin II formation that could otherwise occur secondary to compensatory renin release. Hypotension that occurs as a result of this mechanism can be corrected by volume expansion.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
