<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="anafranil" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Commonly Observed

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of Anafranil and not seen at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients were gastrointestinal complaints, including dry mouth, constipation, nausea, dyspepsia, and anorexia; nervous system complaints, including somnolence, tremor, dizziness, nervousness, and myoclonus; genitourinary complaints, including changed libido, ejaculatory failure, impotence, and micturition disorder; and other miscellaneous complaints, including fatigue, sweating, increased appetite, weight gain, and visual changes.



   Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment

  Approximately 20% of 3616 patients who received Anafranil in U.S. premarketing clinical trials discontinued treatment because of an adverse event. Approximately one-half of the patients who discontinued (9% of the total) had multiple complaints, none of which could be classified as primary. Where a primary reason for discontinuation could be identified, most patients discontinued because of nervous system complaints (5.4%), primarily somnolence. The second-most-frequent reason for discontinuation was digestive system complaints (1.3%), primarily vomiting and nausea.



 There was no apparent relationship between the adverse events and elevated plasma drug concentrations.



   Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials

  The following table enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 1% or greater among patients with OCD who received Anafranil in adult or pediatric placebo-controlled clinical trials. The frequencies were obtained from pooled data of clinical trials involving either adults receiving Anafranil (N=322) or placebo (N=319) or children treated with Anafranil (N=46) or placebo (N=44). The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice, in which patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, provide the physician with a basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the incidence of side effects in the populations studied.



 Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials (Percentage of Patients Reporting Event) 
   *Events reported by at least 1% of Anafranil patients are included.    
  
                     Adults                            Children and Adolescents     
    Body System/Adverse Event*       Anafranil(N=322)       Placebo(N=319)                        Anafranil(N=46)       Placebo(N=44)     
                                                                                       
    Nervous System                                                                         
  Somnolence       54               16               46               11               
  Tremor           54               2                33               2                
  Dizziness        54               14               41               14               
  Headache         52               41               28               34               
  Insomnia         25               15               11               7                
  Libido change    21               3                -                -                
  Nervousness      18               2                4                2                
  Myoclonus        13               -                2                -                
  Increased appetite   11               2                -                2                
  Paresthesia      9                3                2                2                
  Memory impairment   9                1                7                2                
  Anxiety          9                4                2                -                
  Twitching        7                1                4                5                
  Impaired concentration   5                2                -                -                
  Depression       5                1                -                -                
  Hypertonia       4                1                2                -                
  Sleep disorder   4                -                9                5                
  Psychosomatic disorder   3                -                -                -                
  Yawning          3                -                -                -                
  Confusion        3                -                2                -                
  Speech disorder   3                -                -                -                
  Abnormal dreaming   3                -                -                2                
  Agitation        3                -                -                -                
  Migraine         3                -                -                -                
  Depersonalization   2                -                2                -                
  Irritability     2                2                2                -                
  Emotional lability   2                -                -                2                
  Panic reaction   1                -                2                -                
  Aggressive reaction   -                -                2                -                
  Paresis          -                -                2                -                
                                                                                       
    Skin and Appendages                                                                         
  Increased sweating   29               3                9                -                
  Rash             8                1                4                2                
  Pruritus         6                -                2                2                
  Dermatitis       2                -                -                2                
  Acne             2                2                -                5                
  Dry skin         2                -                -                5                
  Urticaria        1                -                -                -                
  Abnormal skin odor   -                -                2                -                
                                                                                       
    Digestive System                                                                         
  Dry mouth        84               17               63               16               
  Constipation     47               11               22               9                
  Nausea           33               14               9                11               
  Dyspepsia        22               10               13               2                
  Diarrhea         13               9                7                5                
  Anorexia         12               -                22               2                
  Abdominal pain   11               9                13               16               
  Vomiting         7                2                7                -                
  Flatulence       6                3                -                2                
  Tooth disorder   5                -                -                -                
  Gastrointestinal disorder   2                -                -                2                
  Dysphagia        2                -                -                -                
  Esophagitis      1                -                -                -                
  Eructation       -                -                2                2                
  Ulcerative stomatitis   -                -                2                -                
                                                                                       
    Body as a Whole                                                                         
  Fatigue          39               18               35               9                
  Weight increase   18               1                2                -                
  Flushing         8                -                7                -                
  Hot flushes      5                -                2                -                
  Chest pain       4                4                7                -                
  Fever            4                -                2                7                
  Allergy          3                3                7                5                
  Pain             3                2                4                2                
  Local edema      2                4                -                -                
  Chills           2                1                -                -                
  Weight decrease   -                -                7                -                
  Otitis media     -                -                4                5                
  Asthenia         -                -                2                -                
  Halitosis        -                -                2                -                
                                                                                       
    Cardiovascular System                                                                         
  Postural hypotension   6                -                4                -                
  Palpitation      4                2                4                -                
  Tachycardia      4                -                2                -                
  Syncope          -                -                2                -                
                                                                                       
    Respiratory System                                                                         
  Pharyngitis      14               9                -                5                
  Rhinitis         12               10               7                9                
  Sinusitis        6                4                2                5                
  Coughing         6                6                4                5                
  Bronchospasm     2                -                7                2                
  Epistaxis        2                -                -                2                
  Dyspnea          -                -                2                -                
  Laryngitis       -                1                2                -                
                                                                                       
    Urogenital System                                                                         
      Male and Female Patients Combined                                                          
  Micturition disorder   14               2                4                2                
  Urinary tract infection   6                1                -                -                
  Micturition frequency   5                3                -                -                
  Urinary retention   2                -                7                -                
  Dysuria          2                2                -                -                
  Cystitis         2                -                -                -                
      Female Patients Only         (N=182)          (N=167)          (N=10)           (N=21)         
  Dysmenorrhea     12               14               10               10               
  Lactation (nonpuerperal)   4                -                -                -                
  Menstrual disorder   4                2                -                -                
  Vaginitis        2                -                -                -                
  Leukorrhea       2                -                -                -                
  Breast enlargement   2                -                -                -                
  Breast pain      1                -                -                -                
  Amenorrhea       1                -                -                -                
      Male Patients Only         (N=140)          (N=152)          (N=36)           (N=23)         
  Ejaculation failure   42               2                6                -                
  Impotence        20               3                -                -                
                                                                                       
    Special Senses                                                                         
  Abnormal vision   18               4                7                2                
  Taste perversion   8                -                4                -                
  Tinnitus         6                -                4                -                
  Abnormal lacrimation   3                2                -                -                
  Mydriasis        2                -                -                -                
  Conjunctivitis   1                -                -                -                
  Anisocoria       -                -                2                -                
  Blepharospasm    -                -                2                -                
  Ocular allergy   -                -                2                -                
  Vestibular disorder   -                -                2                2                
                                                                                       
    Musculoskeletal                                                                         
  Myalgia          13               9                -                -                
  Back pain        6                6                -                -                
  Arthralgia       3                5                -                -                
  Muscle weakness   1                -                2                -                
                                                                                       
    Hemic and Lymphatic                                                                         
  Purpura          3                -                -                -                
  Anemia           -                -                2                2                
                                                                                       
    Metabolic and Nutritional                                                                         
  Thirst           2                2                -                2                
                                                                                       
              Other Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Anafranil
   During clinical testing in the U.S., multiple doses of Anafranil were administered to approximately 3600 subjects. Untoward events associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized event categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, a modified World Health Organization dictionary of terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the 3525 individuals exposed to Anafranil who experienced an event of the type cited on at least one occasion while receiving Anafranil. All events are included except those already listed in the previous table, those reported in terms so general as to be uninformative, and those in which an association with the drug was remote. It is important to emphasize that although the events reported occurred during treatment with Anafranil, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: frequent adverse events are those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare events are those occurring in less than 1/1000 patients.



   

    Body as a Whole      -  Infrequent -  general edema, increased susceptibility to infection, malaise.  Rare -  dependent edema, withdrawal syndrome.



   

    Cardiovascular System      -  Infrequent -  abnormal ECG, arrhythmia, bradycardia, cardiac arrest, extrasystoles, pallor.  Rare -  aneurysm, atrial flutter, bundle branch block, cardiac failure, cerebral hemorrhage, heart block, myocardial infarction, myocardial ischemia, peripheral ischemia, thrombophlebitis, vasospasm, ventricular tachycardia.



   

    Digestive System      -  Infrequent -  abnormal hepatic function, blood in stool, colitis, duodenitis, gastric ulcer, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux, gingivitis, glossitis, hemorrhoids, hepatitis, increased saliva, irritable bowel syndrome, peptic ulcer, rectal hemorrhage, tongue ulceration, tooth caries.  Rare -  cheilitis, chronic enteritis, discolored feces, gastric dilatation, gingival bleeding, hiccup, intestinal obstruction, oral/pharyngeal edema, paralytic ileus, salivary gland enlargement.



   

    Endocrine System      -  Infrequent  - hypothyroidism.  Rare -  goiter, gynecomastia, hyperthyroidism.



   

    Hemic and Lymphatic System      -  Infrequent -  lymphadenopathy.  Rare -  leukemoid reaction, lymphoma-like disorder, marrow depression.



   

    Metabolic and Nutritional Disorder      -  Infrequent -  dehydration, diabetes mellitus, gout, hypercholesterolemia, hyperglycemia, hyperuricemia, hypokalemia.  Rare -  fat intolerance, glycosuria.



   

    Musculoskeletal System      -  Infrequent -  arthrosis.  Rare -  dystonia, exostosis, lupus erythematosus rash, bruising, myopathy, myositis, polyarteritis nodosa, torticollis.



   

    Nervous System      -  Frequent -  abnormal thinking, vertigo.  Infrequent -  abnormal coordination, abnormal EEG, abnormal gait, apathy, ataxia, coma, convulsions, delirium, delusion, dyskinesia, dysphonia, encephalopathy, euphoria, extrapyramidal disorder, hallucinations, hostility, hyperkinesia, hypnagogic hallucinations, hypokinesia, leg cramps, manic reaction, neuralgia, paranoia, phobic disorder, psychosis, sensory disturbance, somnambulism, stimulation, suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, teeth-grinding.  Rare -  anticholinergic syndrome, aphasia, apraxia, catalepsy, cholinergic syndrome, choreoathetosis, generalized spasm, hemiparesis, hyperesthesia, hyperreflexia, hypoesthesia, illusion, impaired impulse control, indecisiveness, mutism, neuropathy, nystagmus, oculogyric crisis, oculomotor nerve paralysis, schizophrenic reaction, stupor, suicide.



   

    Respiratory System      -  Infrequent -  bronchitis, hyperventilation, increased sputum, pneumonia.  Rare -  cyanosis, hemoptysis, hypoventilation, laryngismus.



   

    Skin and Appendages      -  Infrequent -  alopecia, cellulitis, cyst, eczema, erythematous rash, genital pruritus, maculopapular rash, photosensitivity reaction, psoriasis, pustular rash, skin discoloration.  Rare -  chloasma, folliculitis, hypertrichosis, piloerection, seborrhea, skin hypertrophy, skin ulceration.



   

    Special Senses      -  Infrequent -  abnormal accommodation, deafness, diplopia, earache, eye pain, foreign body sensation, hyperacusis, parosmia, photophobia, scleritis, taste loss.  Rare -  blepharitis, chromatopsia, conjunctival hemorrhage, exophthalmos, glaucoma, keratitis, labyrinth disorder, night blindness, retinal disorder, strabismus, visual field defect.



   

    Urogenital System      -  Infrequent -  endometriosis, epididymitis, hematuria, nocturia, oliguria, ovarian cyst, perineal pain, polyuria, prostatic disorder, renal calculus, renal pain, urethral disorder, urinary incontinence, uterine hemorrhage, vaginal hemorrhage.  Rare -  albuminuria, anorgasmy, breast engorgement, breast fibroadenosis, cervical dysplasia, endometrial hyperplasia, premature ejaculation, pyelonephritis, pyuria, renal cyst, uterine inflammation, vulvar disorder.



     Postmarketing Experience  

  The following adverse drug reaction has been reported during post-approval use of Anafranil. Because this reaction is reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate frequency.



   

    Eye Disorders -  angle-closure glaucoma. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

  Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of clomipramine hydrochloride or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. Clomipramine hydrochloride is not approved for use in pediatric patients except for patients with obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD) (  see     WARNINGS, Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk  ;   PRECAUTIONS, Information for Patients  ;   and     PRECAUTIONS, Pediatric Use  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
