<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="androgel1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience



   Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  



 Clinical Trials in Hypogonadal Men



 Table 2 shows the incidence of all adverse events judged by the investigator to be at least possibly related to treatment with AndroGel and reported by &gt;1% of patients in a 180 Day, Phase 3 study.



 Table 2: Adverse Events Possibly, Probably or Definitely Related to Use of AndroGel in the 180-Day Controlled Clinical Trial 
                                                      ___________         Dose of AndroGel          ___                                 
                  Adverse Event                                                        
   ____________________      _    __________  _    _________5 g________      _____     ______7.5 g________________      ________  10 g____________     
                                     _______N = 77                  _______     ____ N = 40                                 ________N = 78___________     
 Acne                              1%               3%               8%                
 Alopecia                          1%               0%               1%                
 Application Site Reaction                   5%               3%               4%                
 Asthenia                          0%               3%               1%                
 Depression                        1%               0%               1%                
 Emotional Lability                   0%               3%               3%                
 Gynecomastia                      1%               0%               3%                
 Headache                          4%               3%               0%                
 Hypertension                      3%               0%               3%                
 Lab Test Abnormal *                   6%               5%               3%                
 Libido Decreased                   0%               3%               1%                
 Nervousness                       0%               3%               1%                
 Pain Breast                       1%               3%               1%                
 Prostate Disorder **                   3%               3%               5%                
 Testis Disorder ***                   3%               0%               0%                
           *     
 

   Lab test abnormal  



 occurred in nine patients with one or more of the following events reported: elevated hemoglobin or hematocrit, hyperlipidemia, elevated triglycerides, hypokalemia, decreased HDL, elevated glucose, elevated creatinine, elevated total bilirubin.



 **   



   Prostate disorders  



 included five patients with enlarged prostate, one with BPH, and one with elevated PSA results.



 *** 



   Testis disorders  



 were reported in two patients: one with left varicocele and one with slight sensitivity of left testis.



 Other less common adverse reactions, reported in fewer than 1% of patients included: amnesia, anxiety, discolored hair, dizziness, dry skin, hirsutism, hostility, impaired urination, paresthesia, penis disorder, peripheral edema, sweating, and vasodilation.



 In this 180 day clinical trial, skin reactions at the site of application were reported with AndroGel, but none was severe enough to require treatment or discontinuation of drug.



 Six patients (4%) in this trial had adverse events that led to discontinuation of AndroGel. These events included: cerebral hemorrhage, convulsion (neither of which were considered related to AndroGel administration), depression, sadness, memory loss, elevated prostate specific antigen, and hypertension No AndroGel patient discontinued due to skin reactions.



 In a separate uncontrolled pharmacokinetic study of 10 patients, two had adverse events associated with AndroGel; these were asthenia and depression in one patient and increased libido and hyperkinesia in the other.



 In a 3 year, flexible dose, extension study, the incidence of all adverse events judged by the investigator to be at least possibly related to treatment with AndroGel and reported by greater than 1% of patients is shown in Table 3.



 Table 3: Adverse Events Possibly, Probably or Definitely Related to Use of AndroGel in the 3 Year, Flexible Dose, Extension Study 
 Adverse Event      Percent of Subjects   (N = 162)   
 Lab Test Abnormal+  9.3               
 Skin dry         1.9               
 Application Site Reaction  5.6               
 Acne             3.1               
 Pruritus         1.9               
 Enlarged Prostate  11.7              
 Carcinoma of Prostate  1.2               
 Urinary Symptoms*  3.7               
 Testis Disorder**  1.9               
 Gynecomastia     2.5               
 Anemia           2.5               
        +    
 

   Lab test abnormal  



 occurred in 15 patients with one or more of the following events reported: elevated AST, elevated ALT, elevated testosterone, elevated hemoglobin or hematocrit, elevated cholesterol, elevated cholesterol/LDL ratio, elevated triglycerides, elevated HDL, elevated serum creatinine.*    



   Urinary symptoms  



 included nocturia, urinary hesitancy, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urinary urgency and weak urinary stream.



 **  



   Testis disorders  



 included three patients. There were two with a non-palpable testis and one with slight right testicular tenderness.



 Two patients reported serious adverse events considered possibly related to treatment: deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and prostate disorder requiring a transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP).



 Discontinuation for adverse events in this study included: two patients with application site reactions, one with kidney failure, and five with prostate disorders (including increase in serum PSA in 4 patients, and increase in PSA with prostate enlargement in a fifth patient).



 Increases in Serum PSA Observed in Clinical Trials of Hypogonadal Men



 During the initial 6-month study, the mean change in PSA values had a statistically significant increase of 0.26 ng/mL. Serum PSA was measured every 6 months thereafter in the 162 hypogonadal men on AndroGel in the 3-year extension study. There was no additional statistically significant increase observed in mean PSA from 6 months through 36 months. However, there were increases in serum PSA observed in approximately 18% of individual patients. The overall mean change from baseline in serum PSA values for the entire group from month 6 to 36 was 0.11 ng/mL.



 Twenty-nine patients (18%) met the per-protocol criterion for increase in serum PSA, defined as greater than 2X the baseline or any single serum PSA greater than 6 ng/mL. Most of these (25/29) met this criterion by at least doubling of their PSA from baseline. In most cases where PSA at least doubled (22/25), the maximum serum PSA value was still less than 2 ng/mL. The first occurrence of a pre-specified, post-baseline increase in serum PSA was seen at or prior to Month 12 in most of the patients who met this criterion (23 of 29; 79%).



 Four patients met this criterion by having a serum PSA greater than 6 ng/mL and in these, maximum serum PSA values were 6.2 ng/mL, 6.6 ng/mL, 6.7 ng/mL, and 10.7 ng/mL. In two of these patients, prostate cancer was detected on biopsy. The first patient's PSA levels were 4.7 ng/mL and 6.2 ng/mL at baseline and at Month 6/Final, respectively. The second patient's PSA levels were 4.2 ng/mL, 5.2 ng/mL, 5.8 ng/mL, and 6.6 ng/mL at baseline, Month 6, Month 12, and Final, respectively.



 6.2 Postmarketing Experience



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of AndroGel. Because the reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Hypogonadal Men



 Table 4 includes adverse reactions that have been identified postmarketing.



 Table 4: Adverse Drug Reactions from Postmarketing Experience of AndroGel by MedDRA System Organ Class 
 Blood and the lymphatic system disorders:  Elevated Hgb, Hct (polycythemia)   
 Endocrine disorders:  Hirsutism         
 Gastrointestinal disorders:  Nausea            
 General disorders and administration site reactions:  Asthenia, edema, malaise   
 Genitourinary disorders:  Impaired urination   
 Hepatobiliary disorders:  Abnormal liver function tests (e.g. transaminases, elevated GCTP,bilirubin)   
 Investigations:  Elevated PSA, electrolyte changes (nitrogen, calcium, potassium,phosphorus, sodium), changes in serum lipids (hyperlipidemia, elevatedtriglycerides, decreased HDL), impaired glucose tolerance, fluctuatingtestosterone levels, weight increase   
 Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (cysts and polyps):  Prostate cancer   
 Nervous system:  Headache, dizziness, sleep apnea, insomnia   
 Psychiatric disorders:  Depression, emotional lability, decreased libido, nervousness, hostility,amnesia, anxiety   
 Reproductive system and breast disorders:  Gynecomastia, mastodynia, prostatic enlargement, testicular atrophy,oligospermia, priapism (frequent or prolonged erections)   
 Respiratory disorders:  Dyspnea           
 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Acne, alopecia, application site reaction (pruritus, dry skin, erythema,rash, discolored hair, paresthesia), sweating   
 Vascular disorders:  Hypertension, vasodilation (hot flushes)   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  5.1 Worsening of BPH and Potential Risk of Prostate Cancer



 *  Patients with BPH treated with androgens are at an increased risk for worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH. 
 *  Patients treated with androgens may be at increased risk for prostate cancer. Evaluation of the patient for prostate cancer prior to initiating and during treatment with androgens is appropriate [see Warnings and Precaution (5.9), Adverse Reactions (6.1), and Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)].  
 *  Increases in serum PSA from baseline values were seen in approximately 18% of individuals in an open label study of 162 hypogonadal men treated with AndroGel for up to 42 months. Most of these increases were seen within the first year of therapy [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.9), Adverse Reactions (6), and Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)].  
    5.2 Potential for Testosterone Transfer to Others
 

 Transfer of testosterone to others (including women and children) can occur when vigorous skin-to-skin contact is made with the application site [see Clinical Studies (14.3)]  . The following precautions are recommended to minimize potential transfer of testosterone from AndroGel-treated skin to another person:



 *  Patients should wash their hands immediately with soap and water after application of AndroGel. 
 *  Patients should cover the application site(s) with clothing after the gel has dried (e.g., a shirt). 
 *  In the event that unwashed or unclothed skin to which AndroGel has been applied does come in direct contact with the skin of another person, the general area of contact on the other person should be washed with soap and water as soon as possible. In vitro studies show that residual testosterone is removed from the skin surface by washing with soap and water. 
 *  Women and children should avoid skin contact with AndroGel application sites in males. Changes in body hair distribution, significant increase in acne, or other signs of virilization should be brought to the attention of a physician. AndroGel may cause fetal harm in a pregnant woman due to virilization of a female fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)].  
    5.3 Use in Women
 

 Due to lack of controlled evaluations in women and potential virilizing effects, AndroGel is not indicated for use in women [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1, 8.3)].  



 5.4 Potential for Adverse Effects on Spermatogenesis



 At large doses of exogenous androgens, spermatogenesis may be suppressed through feedback inhibition of pituitary follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) which could possibly lead to adverse effects on semen parameters including sperm count.



 5.5 Hepatic Adverse Effects



 Prolonged use of high doses of orally active 17-alpha-alkyl androgens (e.g., methyltestosterone) has been associated with serious hepatic adverse effects (peliosis hepatis, hepatic neoplasms, cholestatic hepatitis, and jaundice). Peliosis hepatis can be a life-threatening or fatal complication. Long-term therapy with intramuscular testosterone enanthate has produced multiple hepatic adenomas. AndroGel is not known to produce these adverse effects.



 There are rare reports of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients receiving long-term oral therapy with androgens in high doses. Withdrawal of the drugs did not lead to regression of the tumors in all cases.



 5.6 Edema



 Drugs in the androgen class may promote retention of sodium and water. Edema with or without congestive heart failure may be a serious complication in patients with preexisting cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)].  



 5.7 Gynecomastia



 Gynecomastia may develop and may persist in patients being treated with androgens, including AndroGel, for hypogonadism.



 5.8 Sleep Apnea



 The treatment of hypogonadal men with testosterone products may potentiate sleep apnea in some patients, especially those with risk factors such as obesity or chronic lung diseases [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .



 5.9 Laboratory Tests



 *  Increases in hematocrit, reflective of increases in red blood cell mass, may require lowering or discontinuation of testosterone. Increase in red blood cell mass may increase the risk for a thromboembolic event. 
 *  Changes in serum lipid profile may require dose adjustment or discontinuation of testosterone therapy. 
 *  Androgens may decrease levels of thyroxin-binding globulin, resulting in decreased total T4 serum levels and increased resin uptake of T3 and T4. Free thyroid hormone levels remain unchanged, however, and there is no clinical evidence of thyroid dysfunction. 
 *  Androgens should be used with caution in cancer patients at risk of hypercalcemia (and associated hypercalciuria). Regular monitoring of serum calcium concentrations is recommended in these patients. 
    5.10 Flammable until Dry
 

 *   Alcohol Based Products including AndroGel are flammable; therefore avoid fire, flame or smoking until the gel has dried.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
