<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="androgel0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reaction (incidence &gt;= 5%) is an increase in prostate specific antigen (PSA). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Abbott Laboratories at 1-800-241-1643 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 AndroGel 1.62% was evaluated in a two-phase, 364-day, controlled clinical study. The first phase was a multi-center, randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, placebo-controlled period of 182 days, in which 234 hypogonadal men were treated with AndroGel 1.62% and 40 received placebo. Patients could continue in an open-label, non-comparative, maintenance period for an additional 182 days  [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  .



 The most common adverse reaction reported in the double-blind period was increased prostate specific antigen (PSA) reported in 26 AndroGel 1.62%-treated patients (11.1%). In 17 patients, increased PSA was considered an adverse event by meeting one of the two pre-specified criteria for abnormal PSA values, defined as (1) average serum PSA &gt;4 ng/mL based on two separate determinations, or (2) an average change from baseline in serum PSA of greater than 0.75 ng/mL on two determinations.



 During the 182-day, double-blind period of the clinical trial, the mean change in serum PSA value was 0.14 ng/mL for patients receiving AndroGel 1.62% and -0.12 ng/mL for the patients in the placebo group. During the double-blind period, seven patients had a PSA value &gt;4.0 ng/mL, four of these seven patients had PSA less than or equal to 4.0 ng/mL upon repeat testing. The other three patients did not undergo repeat PSA testing.



 During the 182-day, open-label period of the study, the mean change in serum PSA values was 0.10 ng/mL for both patients continuing on active therapy and patients transitioning onto active from placebo. During the open-label period, three patients had a serum PSA value &gt; 4.0 ng/mL, two of whom had a serum PSA less than or equal to 4.0 ng/mL upon repeated testing. The other patient did not undergo repeat PSA testing. Among previous placebo patients, 3 of 28 (10.7%), had increased PSA as an adverse event in the open-label period.



   Table 4  shows adverse reactions reported by &gt;2% of patients in the 182-day, double-blind period of the AndroGel 1.62% clinical trial and more frequent in the AndroGel 1.62% treated group versus placebo.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;2% of Patients in the 182-Day, Double-Blind Period of AndroGel 1.62% Clinical Trial 
  *PSA increased includes: PSA values that met pre-specified criteria for abnormal PSA values (an average change from baseline &gt; 0.75 ng/mL and/or an average PSA value &gt;4.0 ng/mL based on two measurements) as well as those reported as adverse events.    
  **Emotional lability includes: mood swings, affective disorder, impatience, anger, and aggression.    
  ***Contact dermatitis includes: 4 patients with dermatitis at non-application sites.    
  
                                           Number (%) of Patients        
   Adverse Reaction                        AndroGel 1.62%    N=234        Placebo    N= 40                 
 PSA increased*                          26 (11.1%)                     0%                                 
 Emotional lability**                    6 (2.6%)                       0%                                 
 Hypertension                            5 (2.1%)                       0%                                 
 Hematocrit or hemoglobin increased      5 (2.1%)                       0%                                 
 Contact dermatitis***                   5 (2.1%)                       0%                                 
         Other adverse reactions occurring in less than or equal to 2% of AndroGel 1.62%-treated patients and more frequently than placebo included: frequent urination, and hyperlipidemia.
 

 In the open-label period of the study (N=191), the most commonly reported adverse reaction (experienced by greater than 2% of patients) was increased PSA (n=13; 6.2%) and sinusitis. Other adverse reactions reported by less than or equal to 2% of patients included increased hemoglobin or hematocrit, hypertension, acne, libido decreased, insomnia, and benign prostatic hypertrophy.



 During the 182-day, double-blind period of the clinical trial, 25 AndroGel 1.62%-treated patients (10.7%) discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions. These adverse reactions included 17 patients with PSA increased and 1 report each of: hematocrit increased, blood pressure increased, frequent urination, diarrhea, fatigue, pituitary tumor, dizziness, skin erythema and skin nodule (same patient - neither at application site), vasovagal syncope, and diabetes mellitus. During the 182-day, open-label period, 9 patients discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions. These adverse reactions included 6 reports of PSA increased, 2 of hematocrit increased, and 1 each of triglycerides increased and prostate cancer.



     Application Site Reactions  



 In the 182-day double-blind period of the study, application site reactions were reported in two (2/234; 0.9%) patients receiving AndroGel 1.62%, both of which resolved. Neither of these patients discontinued the study due to application site adverse reactions. In the open-label period of the study, application site reactions were reported in three (3/219; 1.4%) additional patients that were treated with AndroGel 1.62%. None of these subjects were discontinued from the study due to application site reactions.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of AndroGel 1%. Because the reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure (  Table 5  ).



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions from Post Approval Experience of AndroGel 1% by System Organ Class 
  * Impaired urination includes nocturia, urinary hesitancy, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urinary urgency and weak urinary stream    
  **Lab test abnormal includes elevated AST, elevated ALT, elevated testosterone, elevated hemoglobin or hematocrit, elevated cholesterol, elevated cholesterol/LDL ratio, elevated triglycerides, or elevated serum creatinine    
  ***Testis disorder includes atrophy or non-palpable testis, varicocele, testis sensitivity or tenderness    
  
   System Organ Class                           Adverse Reaction                                         
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:      Elevated hemoglobin or hematocrit, polycythemia, anemia    
   Endocrine disorders:                       Hirsutism                                                  
   Gastrointestinal disorders:                Nausea                                                     
   General disorders:                         Asthenia, edema, malaise                                   
   Genitourinary disorders:                   Impaired urination*                                        
   Hepatobiliary disorders:                   Abnormal liver function tests                              
   Investigations:                            Lab test abnormal**, elevated PSA, electrolyte changes (nitrogen, calcium, potassium [includes hypokalemia]  ,  phosphorus, sodium), impaired glucose tolerance, hyperlipidemia, HDL, fluctuating testosterone levels, weight increase   
   Neoplasms:                                 Prostate cancer                                            
   Nervous system disorders:                  Dizziness, headache, insomnia, sleep apnea                 
   Psychiatric disorders:                     Amnesia, anxiety, depression, hostility, emotional lability, decreased libido, nervousness   
   Reproductive system and breast disorders:    Gynecomastia, mastodynia, oligospermia, priapism (frequent or prolonged erections), prostate enlargement, BPH, testis disorder***   
   Respiratory disorders:                     Dyspnea                                                    
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:    Acne, alopecia, application site reaction (discolored hair, dry skin, erythema, paresthesia, pruritus, rash), skin dry, pruritus, sweating   
   Vascular disorders:                        Hypertension, vasodilation (hot flushes)                   
              Secondary Exposure to Testosterone in Children    
 

 Cases of secondary exposure to testosterone resulting in virilization of children have been reported in postmarketing surveillance of testosterone gel products. Signs and symptoms of these reported cases have included enlargement of the clitoris (with surgical intervention) or the penis, development of pubic hair, increased erections and libido, aggressive behavior, and advanced bone age. In most cases with a reported outcome, these signs and symptoms were reported to have regressed with removal of the testosterone gel exposure. In a few cases, however, enlarged genitalia did not fully return to age appropriate normal size, and bone age remained modestly greater than chronological age. In some of the cases, direct contact with the sites of application on the skin of men using testosterone gel was reported. In at least one reported case, the reporter considered the possibility of secondary exposure from items such as the testosterone gel user's shirts and/or other fabric, such as towels and sheets  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE

  WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE

    *  Virilization has been reported in children who were secondarily exposed to testosterone gel [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) and Adverse Reactions (6.2)]. 
 *  Children should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using testosterone gel [see Dosage and Administration (2.2) and Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  Healthcare providers should advise patients to strictly adhere to recommended instructions for use [see Dosage and Administration (2.2), Warnings and Precautions (5.2) and Patient Counseling Information (17)]. 
      EXCERPT:   
 

   WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE  



 *  Virilization has been reported in children who were secondarily exposed to testosterone gel (5.2, 6.2). 
 *  Children should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using testosterone gel (2.2, 5.2). 
 *  Healthcare providers should advise patients to strictly adhere to recommended instructions for use (2.2, 5.2, 17). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Monitor patients with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) for worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH (  5.1  ) 
 *  Avoid unintentional exposure of women or children to AndroGel 1.62%. Secondary exposure to testosterone can produce signs of virilization. AndroGel 1.62% should be discontinued until the cause of virilization is identified (  5.2  ) 
 *  Exogenous administration of androgens may lead to azoospermia (  5.5  ) 
 *  Edema with or without congestive heart failure (CHF) may be a complication in patients with preexisting cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease (  5.7  ) 
 *  Sleep apnea may occur in those with risk factors (  5.9  ) 
 *  Monitor serum testosterone, prostate specific antigen (PSA), hemoglobin, hematocrit, liver function tests and lipid concentrations periodically (  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.6  ,  5.10  ) 
 *  AndroGel 1.62% is flammable until dry (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Worsening of Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia (BPH) and Potential Risk of Prostate Cancer



    *  Patients with BPH treated with androgens are at an increased risk for worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH. Monitor patients with BPH for worsening signs and symptoms. 
 *  Patients treated with androgens may be at increased risk for prostate cancer. Evaluation of patients for prostate cancer prior to initiating and during treatment with androgens is appropriate [see Contraindications (  4  )].  
       5.2 Potential for Secondary Exposure to Testosterone
 

  Cases of secondary exposure resulting in virilization of children have been reported in postmarketing surveillance of testosterone gel products. Signs and symptoms have included enlargement of the penis or clitoris, development of pubic hair, increased erections and libido, aggressive behavior, and advanced bone age. In most cases, these signs and symptoms regressed with removal of the exposure to testosterone gel. In a few cases, however, enlarged genitalia did not fully return to age-appropriate normal size, and bone age remained modestly greater than chronological age. The risk of transfer was increased in some of these cases by not adhering to precautions for the appropriate use of the topical testosterone product. Children and women should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using AndroGel 1.62% [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



 Inappropriate changes in genital size or development of pubic hair or libido in children, or changes in body hair distribution, significant increase in acne, or other signs of virilization in adult women should be brought to the attention of a physician and the possibility of secondary exposure to testosterone gel should also be brought to the attention of a physician. Testosterone gel should be promptly discontinued until the cause of virilization has been identified.



    5.3 Polycythemia



  Increases in hematocrit, reflective of increases in red blood cell mass, may require lowering or discontinuation of testosterone. Check hematocrit prior to initiating treatment. It would also be appropriate to re-evaluate the hematocrit 3 to 6 months after starting treatment, and then annually. If hematocrit becomes elevated, stop therapy until hematocrit decreases to an acceptable concentration. An increase in red blood cell mass may increase the risk of thromboembolic events.



    5.4 Use in Women



  Due to the lack of controlled evaluations in women and potential virilizing effects, AndroGel 1.62% is not indicated for use in women [see Contraindications (  4  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ,  8.3  )].  



    5.5 Potential for Adverse Effects on Spermatogenesis



  With large doses of exogenous androgens, including AndroGel 1.62%, spermatogenesis may be suppressed through feedback inhibition of pituitary FSH possibly leading to adverse effects on semen parameters including sperm count.



    5.6 Hepatic Adverse Effects



  Prolonged use of high doses of orally active 17-alpha-alkyl androgens (e.g., methyltestosterone) has been associated with serious hepatic adverse effects (peliosis hepatis, hepatic neoplasms, cholestatic hepatitis, and jaundice). Peliosis hepatis can be a life-threatening or fatal complication. Long-term therapy with intramuscular testosterone enanthate has produced multiple hepatic adenomas. AndroGel 1.62% is not known to cause these adverse effects.



    5.7 Edema



  Androgens, including AndroGel 1.62%, may promote retention of sodium and water. Edema, with or without congestive heart failure, may be a serious complication in patients with preexisting cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )]  .



    5.8 Gynecomastia



  Gynecomastia may develop and persist in patients being treated with androgens, including AndroGel 1.62%, for hypogonadism.



    5.9 Sleep Apnea



  The treatment of hypogonadal men with testosterone may potentiate sleep apnea in some patients, especially those with risk factors such as obesity or chronic lung diseases.



    5.10 Lipids



  Changes in serum lipid profile may require dose adjustment or discontinuation of testosterone therapy.



    5.11 Hypercalcemia



  Androgens, including AndroGel 1.62 %, should be used with caution in cancer patients at risk of hypercalcemia (and associated hypercalciuria). Regular monitoring of serum calcium concentrations is recommended in these patients.



    5.12 Decreased Thyroxine-binding Globulin



  Androgens, including AndroGel 1.62%, may decrease concentrations of thyroxin-binding globulins, resulting in decreased total T4 serum concentrations and increased resin uptake of T3 and T4. Free thyroid hormone concentrations remain unchanged, however, and there is no clinical evidence of thyroid dysfunction.



    5.13 Flammability



   Alcohol based products, including AndroGel 1.62%, are flammable; therefore, patients should be advised to avoid fire, flame or smoking until the AndroGel 1.62% has dried.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
