<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="anzemet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Postoperative Patients

  In controlled clinical trials with 2550 adult patients, headache and dizziness were reported more frequently with 12.5 mg ANZEMET Injection than with placebo. Rates of other adverse events were similar. Following is a listing of all adverse events reported in &gt;=2% of patients receiving either placebo or 12.5 mg ANZEMET Injection for the prevention or treatment of postoperative nausea and vomiting in controlled clinical trials (Table 2).



 Table 2. Adverse Events &gt;=2% from Placebo-Controlled Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting Studies 
 Event            ANZEMET Injection12.5 mg(n=615)  Placebo (n=739)   
  
 Headache           58   (9.4%)      51   (6.9%)     
 Dizziness          34   (5.5%)      23   (3.1%)     
 Drowsiness         15   (2.4%)      18   (2.4%)     
 Pain               15   (2.4%)      21   (2.8%)     
 Urinary Retention    12   (2.0%)      16   (2.2%)     
         In clinical trials, the following reported adverse events, assessed by investigators as treatment-related or causality unknown, occurred following oral or intravenous administration of ANZEMET in &lt; 2% of adult patients undergoing surgery:
 

   Body as a Whole:  Chills/shivering.



   Cardiovascular:  Sinus arrhythmia, hypotension, orthostatic hypotension. The following events also occurred and with a similar frequency as placebo and/or active comparator: Mobitz I AV block, chest pain, syncope, severe bradycardia, and palpitations. See  PRECAUTIONS  section for information on potential effects on ECG.



 In addition, the following asymptomatic treatment-emergent ECG changes were seen at rates less than or equal to those for active or placebo controls: bradycardia, tachycardia, T wave change, ST-T wave change, extrasystole (APCs or VPCs), bundle branch block (left and right).



 Furthermore, severe hypotension, bradycardia and syncope have been reported immediately or closely following IV administration.



   Dermatologic:  Rash.



   Gastrointestinal System:  Constipation, dyspepsia, abdominal pain.



   Hearing, Taste and Vision:  Taste perversion, abnormal vision.



   Hypersensitivity:  Anaphylactic reaction, urticaria.



   Liver and Biliary System:  Transient increases in AST (SGOT) and/or ALT (SGPT). The increases did not appear to be related to dose or duration of therapy and were not associated with symptomatic hepatic disease. Similar increases were seen with patients receiving active comparator.



   Musculoskeletal:  Myalgia, arthralgia.



   Nervous System:  Vertigo; flushing, paraesthesia.



   Psychiatric:  Agitation, anxiety, abnormal dreaming.



   Respiratory System:  Bronchospasm.



   Vascular (Extracardiac):  Local pain or burning on IV administration.



   Postmarketing Experience

  There are reports of wide complex tachycardia or ventricular tachycardia and of ventricular fibrillation cardiac arrest following intravenous administration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
