<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aplenzin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following risks are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Clinical worsening and suicide risk [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk (5.1)   ]  
 *  Activation of Psychosis and/or Mania [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Activation of Psychosis and/or Mania (5.2)   and   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder (5.3)   ]  
 *  Hepatotoxicity [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Potential for Hepatotoxicity (5.6)   ]  
 *  Agitation and Insomnia [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Agitation and Insomnia (5.7)   ]  
 *  Psychosis, confusion and other neuropsychiatric phenomena [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Psychosis, Confusion, and Other Neuropsychiatric Phenomena (5.8)   ]  
 *  Altered appetite [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Altered Appetite and Weight (5.9)   ]  
 *  Allergic reactions, including anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Allergic Reactions (5.10)   ]  
 *  Hypertension [see   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Cardiovascular Effects (5.11)   ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are (incidence &gt;= 5%; &gt;= 2* placebo rate): Dry mouth, nausea, insomnia, dizziness, pharyngitis, abdominal pain, agitation, anxiety, tremor, palpitation, sweating, tinnitus, myalgia, anorexia, urinary frequency, rash (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Biovail Pharmaceuticals at (866-246-8245 (opt.3) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Controlled Clinical Trials

  Adverse reactions from Table 4 occurring in at least 5% of patients treated with the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed below for the 300- and 400-mg/day dose groups.



   300 mg/day of WELLBUTRIN SR (  equivalent  to 348 mg/day bupropion HBr)  : Anorexia, dry mouth, rash, sweating, tinnitus, and tremor.



   400 mg/day of WELLBUTRIN SR (  equivalent  to 464 mg/day bupropion HBr)  : Abdominal pain, agitation, anxiety, dizziness, dry mouth, insomnia, myalgia, nausea, palpitation, pharyngitis, sweating, tinnitus, and urinary frequency.



 Aplenzin is bioequivalent to WELLBUTRIN XL  (r)  , which has been demonstrated to have similar bioavailability both to the immediate-release formulation of bupropion and to the sustained-release formulation of bupropion. The information included under this subsection and under subsections 6.2 and 6.3 is based primarily on data from controlled clinical trials with WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  Tablets, the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride.



   6.2 Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment With WELLBUTRIN or WELLBUTRIN SR

  In placebo-controlled clinical trials, 9% and 11% of patients treated with 300 and 400 mg/day, respectively, of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride and 4% of patients treated with placebo discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions. The specific adverse reactions in these trials that led to discontinuation in at least 1% of patients treated with either 300 mg/day or 400 mg/day of WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  , the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed in Table 4.



 Table 4. Treatment Discontinuations Due to Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Trials for Major Depressive Disorder 
 Adverse Reaction Term      WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)300 mg/day(n = 376)  WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)400 mg/day(n = 114)      Placebo(n = 385)        
  
 Rash                                 2.4%                       0.9%                       0.0%              
 Nausea                               0.8%                       1.8%                       0.3%              
 Agitation                            0.3%                       1.8%                       0.3%              
 Migraine                             0.0%                       1.8%                       0.3%              
          In clinical trials with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion, 10% of patients and volunteers discontinued due to an adverse reaction. Reactions resulting in discontinuation, in addition to those listed above for the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, include vomiting, seizures, and sleep disturbances.
 

   6.3 Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among Patients Treated With WELLBUTRIN or WELLBUTRIN SR

  Table 5 enumerates treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred among patients treated with 300 and 400 mg/day of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride and with placebo in controlled trials. Reactions that occurred in either the 300- or 400-mg/day group at an incidence of 1% or more and were more frequent than in the placebo group are included. Reported adverse reactions were classified using a COSTART-based Dictionary.



 Accurate estimates of the incidence of adverse reactions associated with the use of any drug are difficult to obtain. Estimates are influenced by drug dose, detection technique, setting, physician judgments, etc. The figures cited cannot be used to predict precisely the incidence of untoward reactions in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. These incidence figures also cannot be compared with those obtained from other clinical studies involving related drug products as each group of drug trials is conducted under a different set of conditions.



 Finally, it is important to emphasize that the tabulation does not reflect the relative severity and/or clinical importance of the reactions. A better perspective on the serious adverse reactions associated with the use of bupropion is provided in the  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS section (5)  .



 Table 5. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled TrialsAdverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of patients treated with either 300 or 400 mg/day of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, but equally or more frequently in the placebo group, were: abnormal dreams, accidental injury, acne, appetite increased, back pain, bronchitis, dysmenorrhea, dyspepsia, flatulence, flu syndrome, hypertension, neck pain, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, and tooth disorder. for Major Depressive Disorder 
 Body System/Adverse Reaction         WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)300 mg/day(n = 376)  WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)400 mg/day(n = 114)    Placebo(n = 385)      
  
 - Hyphen denotes adverse reactions occurring in greater than 0 but less than 0.5% of patients.   
  
 Body (General)                                                                                               
   Headache                                    26%                     25%                     23%            
   Infection                                    8%                      9%                     6%             
   Abdominal pain                               3%                      9%                     2%             
   Asthenia                                     2%                      4%                     2%             
   Chest pain                                   3%                      4%                     1%             
   Pain                                         2%                      3%                     2%             
   Fever                                        1%                      2%                      -             
 Cardiovascular                                                                                               
   Palpitation                                  2%                      6%                     2%             
   Flushing                                     1%                      4%                      -             
   Migraine                                     1%                      4%                     1%             
   Hot flashes                                  1%                      3%                     1%             
 Digestive                                                                                                    
   Dry mouth                                   17%                     24%                     7%             
   Nausea                                      13%                     18%                     8%             
   Constipation                                10%                      5%                     7%             
   Diarrhea                                     5%                      7%                     6%             
   Anorexia                                     5%                      3%                     2%             
   Vomiting                                     4%                      2%                     2%             
   Dysphagia                                    0%                      2%                     0%             
 Musculoskeletal                                                                                              
   Myalgia                                      2%                      6%                     3%             
   Arthralgia                                   1%                      4%                     1%             
   Arthritis                                    0%                      2%                     0%             
   Twitch                                       1%                      2%                      -             
 Nervous system                                                                                               
   Insomnia                                    11%                     16%                     6%             
   Dizziness                                    7%                     11%                     5%             
   Agitation                                    3%                      9%                     2%             
   Anxiety                                      5%                      6%                     3%             
   Tremor                                       6%                      3%                     1%             
   Nervousness                                  5%                      3%                     3%             
   Somnolence                                   2%                      3%                     2%             
   Irritability                                 3%                      2%                     2%             
   Memory decreased                             -                       3%                     1%             
   Paresthesia                                  1%                      2%                     1%             
   Central nervous system stimulation            2%                      1%                     1%             
 Respiratory                                                                                                  
   Pharyngitis                                  3%                     11%                     2%             
   Sinusitis                                    3%                      1%                     2%             
   Increased cough                              1%                      2%                     1%             
 Skin                                                                                                         
   Sweating                                     6%                      5%                     2%             
   Rash                                         5%                      4%                     1%             
   Pruritus                                     2%                      4%                     2%             
   Urticaria                                    2%                      1%                     0%             
 Special senses                                                                                               
   Tinnitus                                     6%                      6%                     2%             
   Taste perversion                             2%                      4%                      -             
   Blurred vision or diplopia                   3%                      2%                     2%             
 Urogenital                                                                                                   
   Urinary frequency                            2%                      5%                     2%             
   Urinary urgency                              -                       2%                     0%             
   Vaginal hemorrhage                           0%                      2%                      -             
   Urinary tract infection                      1%                      0%                      -             
          Additional reactions to those listed in Table 5 that occurred at an incidence of at least 1% in controlled clinical trials of the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride (300 to 600 mg/day) and that were numerically more frequent than placebo were: cardiac arrhythmias (5% vs 4%), hypertension (4% vs 2%), hypotension (3% vs 2%), tachycardia (11% vs 9%), appetite increase (4% vs 2%), dyspepsia (3% vs 2%), menstrual complaints (5% vs 1%), akathisia (2% vs 1%), impaired sleep quality (4% vs 2%), sensory disturbance (4% vs 3%), confusion (8% vs 5%), decreased libido (3% vs 2%), hostility (6% vs 4%), auditory disturbance (5% vs 3%), and gustatory disturbance (3% vs 1%).
 

   6.4 Other Events Observed During the Clinical Development and Postmarketing Experience of Bupropion

  In addition to the adverse events noted above, the following events have been reported in clinical trials and postmarketing experience with the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride in depressed patients and in nondepressed smokers, as well as in clinical trials and postmarketing clinical experience with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride.



 Adverse events for which frequencies are provided below occurred in clinical trials with the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride. The frequencies represent the proportion of patients who experienced a treatment-emergent adverse event on at least one occasion in placebo-controlled studies for depression (n = 987) or smoking cessation (n = 1,013), or patients who experienced an adverse event requiring discontinuation of treatment in an open-label surveillance study with the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride (n = 3,100). All treatment-emergent adverse events are included except those listed in Tables 2 through 5, those events listed in other safety-related sections, those adverse events subsumed under COSTART terms that are either overly general or excessively specific so as to be uninformative, those events not reasonably associated with the use of the drug, and those events that were not serious and occurred in fewer than 2 patients. Events of major clinical importance are described in the  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS section (5)  .



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions of frequency: Frequent adverse events are defined as those occurring in at least 1/100 patients. Infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients, while rare events are those occurring in less than 1/1,000 patients.



 Adverse events for which frequencies are not provided occurred in clinical trials or postmarketing experience with bupropion. Only those adverse events not previously listed for sustained-release bupropion are included. The extent to which these events may be associated with Aplenzin is unknown.



   

    Body (General)  



 Infrequent were chills, facial edema, musculoskeletal chest pain, and photosensitivity. Rare was malaise. Also observed were arthralgia, myalgia, and fever with rash and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity. These symptoms may resemble serum sickness  [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Allergic Reactions (5.10)    ]  .



   

    Cardiovascular  



 Infrequent were postural hypotension, stroke, tachycardia, and vasodilation. Rare was syncope. Also observed were complete atrioventricular block, extrasystoles, hypotension, hypertension (in some cases severe;  [see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Cardiovascular Effects (5.11)    ]  , myocardial infarction, phlebitis, and pulmonary embolism.



   

    Digestive  



 Infrequent were abnormal liver function, bruxism, gastric reflux, gingivitis, glossitis, increased salivation, jaundice, mouth ulcers, stomatitis, and thirst. Rare was edema of tongue. Also observed were colitis, esophagitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gum hemorrhage, hepatitis, intestinal perforation, liver damage, pancreatitis, and stomach ulcer.



   

    Endocrine  



 Also observed were hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia, and syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone.



   

    Hemic and Lymphatic  



 Infrequent was ecchymosis. Also observed were anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia. Altered PT and/or INR, infrequently associated with hemorrhagic or thrombotic complications, were observed when bupropion was coadministered with warfarin.



   

    Metabolic and Nutritional  



 Infrequent were edema and peripheral edema. Also observed was glycosuria.



   

    Musculoskeletal  



 Infrequent were leg cramps. Also observed were muscle rigidity/fever/rhabdomyolysis and muscle weakness.



   

    Nervous System  



 Infrequent were abnormal coordination, decreased libido, depersonalization, dysphoria, emotional lability, hostility, hyperkinesia, hypertonia, hypesthesia, suicidal ideation, and vertigo. Rare were amnesia, ataxia, derealization, and hypomania. Also observed were abnormal electroencephalogram (EEG), aggression, akinesia, aphasia, coma, delirium, delusions, dysarthria, dyskinesia, dystonia, euphoria, extrapyramidal syndrome, hallucinations, hypokinesia, increased libido, manic reaction, neuralgia, neuropathy, paranoid ideation, restlessness, and unmasking tardive dyskinesia.



   

    Respiratory  



 Rare was bronchospasm. Also observed was pneumonia.



   

    Skin  



 Rare was maculopapular rash. Also observed were alopecia, angioedema, exfoliative dermatitis, and hirsutism.



   

    Special Senses  



 Infrequent were accommodation abnormality and dry eye. Also observed were deafness, diplopia, increased intraocular pressure, and mydriasis.



   

    Urogenital  



 Infrequent were impotence, polyuria, and prostate disorder. Also observed were abnormal ejaculation, cystitis, dyspareunia, dysuria, gynecomastia, menopause, painful erection, salpingitis, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, and vaginitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS

    SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS  

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of AplenzinTM or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. Aplenzin is not approved for use in pediatric patients. [See     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk (5.1)   and   USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS: Pediatric Use (8.4)    ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders (5.1) (8.4) 
 *  Anyone considering the use of Aplenzin or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. (8.4) 
 *  Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. (5.1) 
 *  Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. (5.1) 
 *  Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. (5.1) 
 *  Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. (17) 
 *  Aplenzin is not approved for use in pediatric patients. [See WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk (5.1) and Use In Specific Populations: Pediatric Use (8.4)] 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Suicide risk: Closely monitor high risk patients and all other patients (   BOXED WARNING   ,  5.1  ,  8.4  ) 
 *  Risk of activation of psychosis and/or mixed/manic episodes (  5.2  )Screen patients for bipolar disorder. Aplenzin is not approved for bipolar depression (  5.3  ) 
 *  Seizure risk: Can be minimized by limiting daily dose to 522 mg and slow dose increase. Extreme caution with high risk patients (  5.4  ,  4  ,  7.4  ) 
 *  Hepatic impairment: Use with caution; reduce dose and/or frequency. Severe hepatic cirrhosis: Extreme caution; max. 174 mg/48 hours (  5.5  ) 
 *  Potential for hepatotoxicity (  5.6  ) 
 *  Risk of restlessness, agitation, anxiety, insomnia (  5.7  ); risk of neuropsychiatric events, incl. delusions, hallucinations, psychosis, concentration disturbance, paranoia, confusion (  5.8  ) 
 *  Loss of appetite should be considered if weight loss is a concern (  5.9  ) 
 *  Risk of anaphylactic/oid reactions; erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome; risk of arthralgia, myalgia, and fever with rash and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity (  5.10  ) 
 *  Risk of severe hypertension; may require acute treatment. Caution in patients with recent history of MI or unstable heart disease (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment.



 Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) show that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4,400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1,000 patients treated) are provided in Table 1.



 Table 1 
 Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1,000 Patients Treated   
           Age Range                                                                                      
  
                                                     Increases Compared to Placebo                        
              &lt;18                                         14 additional cases                             
             18-24                                         5 additional cases                             
                                                     Decreases Compared to Placebo                        
             25-64                                            1 fewer case                                
              &gt;=65                                           6 fewer cases                                
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases. [See   BOXED WARNING    and   USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS: Pediatric Use (8.4)    ]  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. [See also   PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION (17)    ]  Prescriptions for Aplenzin should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose. Families and caregivers of adults being treated for depression should be similarly advised.



    5.2 Activation of Psychosis and/or Mania



  Antidepressants can precipitate manic episodes in bipolar disorder patients during the depressed phase of their illness and may activate latent psychosis in other susceptible patients. Aplenzin is expected to pose similar risks.



    5.3 Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder



  A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described above represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It should be noted that Aplenzin is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



  Patients should be made aware that Aplenzin contains bupropion, the same active ingredient found in ZYBAN, used as an aid to smoking cessation treatment, and that Aplenzin should not be used in combination with ZYBAN, or any other medications that contain bupropion, such as WELLBUTRIN XL  (r)  (bupropion hydrochloride extended-release formulation), WELLBUTRIN SR (bupropion hydrochloride sustained-release formulation), or WELLBUTRIN (bupropion hydrochloride immediate-release formulation). [See also   PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION (17)    ]  



    5.4 Seizures



   Bupropion is associated with a dose-related risk of seizures. The risk of seizures is also related to patient factors, clinical situations, and concomitant medications, which must be considered in selection of patients for therapy with Aplenzin. Aplenzin should be discontinued and not restarted in patients who experience a seizure while on treatment.  



  The seizure incidence with Aplenzin has not been formally evaluated in clinical trials. Studies in mice suggest the potential for a significant reduction in the risk of seizure with bupropion HBr as compared to bupropion HCl. The seizure incidence is not expected to be worse than presented below for comparable doses of the immediate-release and sustained release formulations of bupropion HCl.  



 *   Dose  
     At doses up to 300 mg/day (equivalent to 348 mg/day of bupropion HBr) of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride (WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  ), the incidence of seizure is approximately 0.1% (1/1,000).  
 

  Data for the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride revealed a seizure incidence of approximately 0.4% (i.e., 13 of 3,200 patients followed prospectively) in patients treated at doses in a range of 300 to 450 mg/day (equivalent to a range of 348 to 522 mg/day of bupropion HBr). This seizure incidence (0.4%) may exceed that of some other marketed antidepressants.  



  Additional data accumulated for the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride suggested that the estimated seizure incidence increases almost tenfold between 450 and 600 mg/day (equivalent to 522 and 696 mg/day bupropion HBr). The 600 mg dose is twice the usual adult dose and one and one-third the maximum recommended daily dose (450 mg) of WELLBUTRIN XL (equivalent to 522 mg Aplenzin) Tablets. This disproportionate increase in seizure incidence with dose incrementation calls for caution in dosing.  



 *   Patient Factors  
     Predisposing factors that may increase the risk of seizure with bupropion use include history of head trauma or prior seizure, central nervous system (CNS) tumor, the presence of severe hepatic cirrhosis, and concomitant medications that lower seizure threshold.  
 

 *   Clinical Situations  
     Circumstances associated with an increased seizure risk include, among others, excessive use of alcohol or sedatives (including benzodiazepines); addiction to opiates, cocaine, or stimulants; use of over-the-counter stimulants and anorectics; and diabetes treated with oral hypoglycemics or insulin.  
 

 *   Concomitant Medications  
     Many medications (e.g., antipsychotics, antidepressants, theophylline, systemic steroids) are known to lower seizure threshold.  
 

    



   Recommendations for Reducing the Risk of Seizure;  



  Retrospective analysis of clinical experience gained during the development of bupropion suggests that the risk of seizure may be minimized if  



 *   the total daily dose of Aplenzin Tablets does not exceed 522 mg,  
 *   the rate of incrementation of dose is gradual.  
     Aplenzin should be administered with extreme caution to patients with a history of seizure, cranial trauma, or other predisposition(s) toward seizure, or patients treated with other agents (e.g., antipsychotics, other antidepressants, theophylline, systemic steroids, etc.) that lower seizure threshold.  
 

    5.5 Hepatic Impairment



   Aplenzin should be used with extreme caution in patients with severe hepatic cirrhosis. In these patients a reduced frequency and/or dose is required, as peak bupropion, as well as AUC, levels are substantially increased and accumulation is likely to occur in such patients to a greater extent than usual. The dose should not exceed 174 mg every other day in these patients.  



 Aplenzin should be used with caution in patients with hepatic impairment (including mild to moderate hepatic cirrhosis) and reduced frequency and/or dose should be considered in patients with mild to moderate hepatic cirrhosis.



 All patients with hepatic impairment should be closely monitored for possible adverse effects that could indicate high drug and metabolite levels.



  See   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION: Dosage Adjustment for Patients With Impaired Hepatic Function (2.5)  ,  USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS: Hepatic Impairment (8.7)    and   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY: Pharmacokinetics (12.3)      



    5.6 Potential for Hepatotoxicity



  In rats receiving large doses of bupropion chronically, there was an increase in incidence of hepatic hyperplastic nodules and hepatocellular hypertrophy. In dogs receiving large doses of bupropion chronically, various histologic changes were seen in the liver, and laboratory tests suggesting mild hepatocellular injury were noted.



    5.7 Agitation and Insomnia



  Increased restlessness, agitation, anxiety, and insomnia, especially shortly after initiation of treatment, have been associated with treatment with bupropion.



 Patients in placebo-controlled trials of major depressive disorder with WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  , the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, experienced agitation, anxiety, and insomnia as shown in Table 2.



 Table 2. Incidence of Agitation, Anxiety, and Insomnia in Placebo-Controlled Trials of WELLBUTRIN SR (Bupropion HCl Sustained-release Tablets) for Major Depressive Disorder 
 Adverse Reaction Term      WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)300 mg/day(n = 376)  WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)400 mg/day(n = 114)      Placebo(n = 385)        
  
 Agitation                             3%                         9%                         2%               
 Anxiety                               5%                         6%                         3%               
 Insomnia                              11%                        16%                        6%               
          In clinical studies of major depressive disorder, these symptoms were sometimes of sufficient magnitude to require treatment with sedative/hypnotic drugs.
 

 Symptoms in these studies were sufficiently severe to require discontinuation of treatment in 1% and 2.6% of patients treated with 300 and 400 mg/day, respectively, of bupropion hydrochloride sustained-release tablets and 0.8% of patients treated with placebo.



    5.8 Psychosis, Confusion, and Other Neuropsychiatric Phenomena



  Depressed patients treated with bupropion have been reported to show a variety of neuropsychiatric signs and symptoms, including delusions, hallucinations, psychosis, concentration disturbance, paranoia, and confusion. In some cases, these symptoms abated upon dose reduction and/or withdrawal of treatment.



    5.9 Altered Appetite and Weight



  In placebo-controlled studies of major depressive disorder using WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  , the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, patients experienced weight gain or weight loss as shown in Table 3.



 Table 3. Incidence of Weight Gain and Weight Loss in Placebo-Controlled Trials of WELLBUTRIN SR(r) (Bupropion Hydrochloride Sustained-Release Tablets) for Major Depressive Disorder 
 Weight Change              WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)300 mg/day(n = 339)  WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  (Bupropion HCl)400 mg/day(n = 112)      Placebo(n = 347)        
  
 Gained &gt;5 lbs                         3%                         2%                         4%               
 Lost &gt;5 lbs                           14%                        19%                        6%               
          In studies conducted with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, 35% of patients receiving tricyclic antidepressants gained weight, compared to 9% of patients treated with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride. If weight loss is a major presenting sign of a patient's depressive illness, the anorectic and/or weight-reducing potential of Aplenzin Tablets should be considered.
 

    5.10 Allergic Reactions



  Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions characterized by symptoms such as pruritus, urticaria, angioedema, and dyspnea requiring medical treatment have been reported in clinical trials with bupropion. In addition, there have been rare spontaneous postmarketing reports of erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and anaphylactic shock associated with bupropion. A patient should stop taking Aplenzin and consult a doctor if experiencing allergic or anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions (e.g., skin rash, pruritus, hives, chest pain, edema, and shortness of breath) during treatment.



 Arthralgia, myalgia, and fever with rash and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity have been reported in association with bupropion. These symptoms may resemble serum sickness.



    5.11 Cardiovascular Effects



  In clinical practice, hypertension, in some cases severe, requiring acute treatment, has been reported in patients receiving bupropion alone and in combination with nicotine replacement therapy. These reactions have been observed in both patients with and without evidence of preexisting hypertension.



 Data from a comparative study of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride (ZYBAN  (r)  Sustained-Release Tablets), nicotine transdermal system (NTS), the combination of sustained-release bupropion hydrochloride plus NTS, and placebo as an aid to smoking cessation suggest a higher incidence of treatment-emergent hypertension in patients treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion hydrochloride and NTS. In this study, 6.1% of patients treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion hydrochloride and NTS had treatment-emergent hypertension compared to 2.5%, 1.6%, and 3.1% of patients treated with sustained-release bupropion hydrochloride, NTS, and placebo, respectively. The majority of these patients had evidence of preexisting hypertension. Three patients (1.2%) treated with the combination of ZYBAN and NTS and 1 patient (0.4%) treated with NTS had study medication discontinued due to hypertension compared to none of the patients treated with ZYBAN or placebo. Monitoring of blood pressure is recommended in patients who receive the combination of bupropion and nicotine replacement.



 There is no clinical experience establishing the safety of Aplenzin Tablets in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Therefore, care should be exercised if it is used in these groups. Bupropion was well tolerated in depressed patients who had previously developed orthostatic hypotension while receiving tricyclic antidepressants, and was also generally well tolerated in a group of 36 depressed inpatients with stable congestive heart failure (CHF). However, bupropion was associated with a rise in supine blood pressure in the study of patients with CHF, resulting in discontinuation of treatment in 2 patients for exacerbation of baseline hypertension.



    5.12 Laboratory Tests



  There are no specific laboratory tests recommended.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
