<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aptensio" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Drug Dependence  [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.2  ,  9.3  )]  
 *  Hypersensitivity to Methylphenidate [see Contraindications (  4  )]  
 *  Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors [see Contraindications (  4  ) and Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  
 *  Serious Cardiovascular Events [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Reactions  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Priapism  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Long-Term Suppression of Growth [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in double-blind clinical trials (&gt; 5% and twice the rate of placebo) in pediatric patients 6 to 17 years were abdominal pain, decreased appetite, headache and insomnia. (  6.1  )
 

 



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Rhodes Pharmaceuticals L.P. at (1-888-827-0616); or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Clinical Trials Experience with Other Methylphenidate Products in Children, Adolescents, and Adults with ADHD  



 Commonly reported (&gt;=2% of the methylphenidate group and at least twice the rate of the placebo group) adverse reactions from placebo-controlled trials of methylphenidate products include: decreased appetite, decreased weight, nausea, abdominal pain, dyspepsia, dry mouth, vomiting, insomnia, anxiety, nervousness, restlessness, affect lability, agitation, irritability, dizziness, vertigo, tremor, blurred vision, increased blood pressure, increased heart rate, tachycardia, palpitations, hyperhidrosis, and pyrexia.



   Clinical Trials Experience with APTENSIO XR in Pediatric Patients with ADHD  



 The safety data in this section is based on data from two one-week controlled clinical studies of APTENSIO XR in pediatric patients with ADHD, one in children ages 6 to 12 years (RP-BP-EF001, hereafter "Study 1"), and one in children and adolescents ages 6 to 17 years (RP-BP-EF002, hereafter "Study 2").



 Two APTENSIO XR clinical studies evaluated a total of 256 patients with ADHD. Two hundred and forty-three (243) patients participated in the double-blind phase of these two clinical studies.



 Study 1 was a randomized, double-blind, single center, placebo-controlled, flexible-dose, cross-over study to evaluate the time of onset, duration of efficacy, tolerability and safety of APTENSIO XR 15 mg, 20 mg, 30 mg, or 40 mg administered for one week in 26 pediatric patients aged 6 to 12 years who met DSM-IV criteria for ADHD  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )].  



   Most Common Adverse Reactions  (incidence of  &gt;= 5% and at a rate at least twice placebo): abdominal pain, pyrexia and headache.



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation:  No subjects discontinued due to adverse reactions during the double-blind phase of this study.



 Study 2 was a randomized, double-blind, multicenter, placebo-controlled, parallel group, fixed-dose study of 10 mg, 15 mg, 20 mg, and 40 mg of APTENSIO XR administered for one week in 221 pediatric patients (6 to 17 years of age) who met DSM-IV criteria for ADHD  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )].  



   Most Common Adverse Reactions  (incidence of  &gt;= 5% and at a rate of at least twice placebo): abdominal pain, decreased appetite, headache and insomnia.



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation:  Two patients (4.4%) in the APTENSIO XR 40 mg group discontinued due to insomnia, nausea and rapid heart rate, respectively during the double-blind phase of the study.



   Table 1: Common Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 2% of Pediatric Patients (6 to 17 years of age) with ADHD Taking APTENSIO XR and at a Rate Greater than Placebo (Study 2)  



 



  
  System Organ Class  Adverse Reaction     Aptensio   (n = 183)       Placebo   (n = 47)        
   Nervous System Disorders                                                           
    Headache                  10.9%                      8.5%                      
    Insomnia                    9.8%                     2.1%                      
    Dizziness                   2.2%                     2.1%                      
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                           
    Abdominal pain upper        8.2%                       0%                      
    Nausea                      3.8%                    2.1%                       
    Vomiting                    3.8%                       0%                      
   Metabolism and Nutritional                                                           
    Decreased Appetite          4.9%                       0%                      
      
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of methylphenidate products. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These adverse reactions are as follows:



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Pancytopenia, Thrombocytopenia, Thrombocytopenic purpura  Cardiac Disorders:  Angina pectoris, Bradycardia, Extrasystole, Supraventricular tachycardia, Ventricular extrasystole  Eye Disorders:  Diplopia, Mydriasis, Visual impairment  General Disorders:  Chest pain, Chest discomfort, Hyperpyrexia  Immune System Disorders:  Hypersensitivity reactions such as Angioedema, Anaphylactic reactions, Auricular swelling, Bullous conditions, Exfoliative conditions, Urticarias, Pruritus NEC, Rashes, Eruptions, and Exanthemas NEC  Investigations:  Alkaline phosphatase increased, Bilirubin increased, Hepatic enzyme increased, Platelet count decreased, White blood cell count abnormal  Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders:  Arthralgia, Myalgia, Muscle twitching, Rhabdomyolysis  Nervous System Disorders:  Convulsion, Grand mal convulsion, Dyskinesia  Psychiatric Disorders:  Disorientation, Libido changes  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Alopecia, Erythema 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE

  WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE

    CNS stimulants, including APTENSIO XR, other methylphenidate-containing products, and amphetamines, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy    [see Warning and Precautions (  5.1  ), Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.2,     9.3  )]  .



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE



   See full prescribing information for complete   boxed warning  .  



 *  CNS stimulants, including APTENSIO XR, other methylphenidate-containing products, and amphetamines, have a high potential for abuse and dependence (5.1, 9.2, 9.3) 
 *  Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy (5.1, 9.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Serious Cardiovascular Events: Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at recommended doses in pediatric patients with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. In adults, sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmias, or coronary artery disease. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases: Monitor blood pressure and pulse. Consider the benefits and risks in patients for whom an increase in blood pressure or heart rate would be problematic. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Psychiatric Adverse Reactions: Use of stimulants may cause psychotic or manic symptoms in patients with no prior history, or exacerbation of symptoms in patients with pre-existing psychiatric illness. Evaluate for bipolar disorder prior to APTENSIO XR use.  (  5.4  ) 
 *   Priapism: Cases of painful and prolonged penile erections and priapism have been reported with methylphenidate products. Immediate medical attention should be sought if signs or symptoms of prolonged penile erections or priapism are observed. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon: Stimulants used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Long-Term Suppression of Growth: Monitor height and weight at appropriate intervals in pediatric patients.  (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Potential for Abuse and Dependence



  CNS stimulants, including APTENSIO XR, other methylphenidate-containing products, and amphetamines, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy [see Boxed Warning and Drug Abuse and Dependence    (  9.2  ,  9.3  )]  .



    5.2 Serious Cardiovascular Events



  Sudden death, stroke and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults with CNS stimulant treatment at recommended doses. Sudden death has been reported in pediatric patients with structural cardiac abnormalities and other serious heart problems taking CNS stimulants at recommended doses for ADHD. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmia, coronary artery disease, and other serious heart problems. Further evaluate patients who develop exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or arrhythmias during APTENSIO XR treatment. 



    5.3 Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases



  CNS stimulants cause an increase in blood pressure (mean increase approximately 2 to 4 mmHg) and heart rate (mean increase approximately 3 to 6 bpm). Individuals may have larger increases. Monitor all patients for hypertension and tachycardia.



    5.4 Psychiatric Adverse Reactions



    Exacerbation of Pre-Existing Psychosis    CNS stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with a pre-existing psychotic disorder.
 

   Induction of a Manic Episode in Patients with Bipolar Disorder    CNS stimulants may induce a manic or mixed episode in patients. Prior to initiating treatment, screen patients for risk factors for developing a manic episode (e.g., comorbid or history of depressive symptoms or a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, or depression).
 

   New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms    CNS stimulants, at recommended doses, may cause psychotic or manic symptoms (e.g., hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania) in patients without a prior history of psychotic illness or mania. If such symptoms occur, consider discontinuing APTENSIO XR. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies of CNS stimulants, psychotic or manic symptoms occurred in approximately 0.1% of CNS stimulant-treated patients, compared to 0 in placebo-treated patients.
 

    5.5 Priapism



  Prolonged and painful erections, sometimes requiring surgical intervention, have been reported with methylphenidate products, in both pediatric and adult patients. Priapism was not reported with drug initiation but developed after some time on the drug, often subsequent to an increase in dose. Priapism has also appeared during a period of drug withdrawal (drug holidays or during discontinuation). Patients who develop abnormally sustained or frequent and painful erections should seek immediate medical attention.



    5.6 Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon



  Stimulants, including APTENSIO XR, used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Signs and symptoms are usually intermittent and mild; however, very rare sequelae include digital ulceration and/or soft tissue breakdown. Effects of peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon, were observed in post-marketing reports at different times and at therapeutic doses in all age groups throughout the course of treatment. Signs and symptoms generally improve after reduction in dose or discontinuation of drug. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. Further clinical evaluation (e.g., rheumatology referral) may be appropriate for certain patients.



    5.7 Long-Term Suppression of Growth



  CNS stimulants have been associated with weight loss and slowing of growth rate in pediatric patients. Closely monitor growth (weight and height) in pediatric patients treated with CNS stimulants, including APTENSIO XR.



 Careful follow-up of weight and height in pediatric patients ages 7 to 10 years who were randomized to either methylphenidate or non-medication treatment groups over 14 months, as well as in naturalistic subgroups of newly methylphenidate-treated and non-medication treated pediatric patients over 36 months (to the ages of 10 to 13 years), suggests that consistently medicated pediatric patients (i.e., treatment for 7 days per week throughout the year) have a temporary slowing in growth rate (on average, a total of about 2 cm less growth in height and 2.7 kg less growth in weight over 3 years), without evidence of growth rebound during this period of development.



 Published data are inadequate to determine whether chronic use of amphetamines may cause a similar suppression of growth, however, it is anticipated that they likely have this effect as well. Therefore, growth should be monitored during treatment with stimulants, and patients who are not growing or gaining height or weight as expected may need to have their treatment interrupted.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
