<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aptivus" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described, in greater detail, in other sections:



 *  Hepatic Impairment and Toxicity [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)    ] 
 *  Intracranial Hemorrhage [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)    ] 
 *  Rash [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)    ] 
    Due to the need for co-administration of APTIVUS with ritonavir, please refer to ritonavir prescribing information for ritonavir-associated adverse reactions.
 

 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



    EXCERPT:    *  In adults the most frequent adverse reactions (incidence &gt;4%) were diarrhea, nausea, pyrexia, vomiting, fatigue, headache, and abdominal pain  (6.1)   
 *  In pediatric patients (age 2 to 18 years) the most frequent adverse reactions were generally similar to those seen in adults. However, rash was more frequent in pediatric patients than in adults.  (6.2)   
        To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    
 

 

  6.1  Clinical Trials in Adults

  APTIVUS, co-administered with ritonavir, has been studied in a total of 6308 HIV-1 positive adults as combination therapy in clinical studies. Of these, 1299 treatment-experienced patients received the dose of 500/200 mg BID. Nine hundred nine (909) adults, including 541 in the 1182.12 and 1182.48 controlled clinical trials, have been treated for at least 48 weeks [    see Clinical Studies  (14)      ].



 In 1182.12 and 1182.48 in the APTIVUS/ritonavir arm, the most frequent adverse reactions were diarrhea, nausea, pyrexia, vomiting, fatigue, headache, and abdominal pain. The 48-Week Kaplan-Meier rates of adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were 13.3% for APTIVUS/ritonavir-treated patients and 10.8% for the comparator arm patients.



 Adverse reactions reported in the controlled clinical trials 1182.12 and 1182.48, based on treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions of moderate to severe intensity (Grades 2 - 4) in at least 2% of treatment-experienced subjects in either treatment group are summarized in Table 2 below.



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions Reported in Randomized, Controlled Clinical Trials (1182.12 and 1182.48) Based on Treatment-Emergent Clinical Adverse Reactions of Moderate to Severe Intensity (Grades 2 - 4) in at least 2% of Treatment-Experienced Subjects in either Treatment Groupa (48-week Analyses) 
                                                     Percentage of patients (rate per 100 patient-exposure years)   
                                                     APTIVUS/ritonavir (500/200 mgBID) + OBR  c  (n=749; 757.4 patient-exposure years)  Comparator PI/ritonavir  b  + OBR(n=737; 503.9 patient-exposure years)   
  
   a  Excludes laboratory abnormalities that were Adverse Events   
   b  Comparator PI/ritonavir: lopinavir/ritonavir 400/100 mg BID, indinavir/ritonavir 800/100 mg BID, saquinavir/ritonavir 1000/100 mg BID, amprenavir/ritonavir 600/100 mg BID   
   c  Optimized Background Regimen                    
  
     Blood and Lymphatic Disorders                    
          Anemia                                     3.3% (3.4)                 2.3% (3.4)                  
          Neutropenia                                2.0% (2.0)                 1.0% (1.4)                  
     Gastrointestinal Disorders                       
          Diarrhea                                   15.0% (16.5)               13.4% (21.6)                
          Nausea                                     8.5% (9.0)                 6.4% (9.7)                  
          Vomiting                                   5.9% (6.0)                 4.1% (6.1)                  
          Abdominal pain                             4.4% (4.5)                 3.4% (5.1)                  
          Abdominal pain upper                       1.5% (1.5)                 2.3% (3.4)                  
     General Disorders                                
          Pyrexia                                    7.5% (7.7)                 5.4% (8.2)                  
          Fatigue                                    5.7% (5.9)                 5.6% (8.4)                  
     Investigations                                   
          Weight decreased                           3.1% (3.1)                 2.2% (3.2)                  
          ALT increased                              2.0% (2.0)                 0.5% (0.8)                  
          GGT increased                              2.0% (2.0)                 0.4% (0.6)                  
     Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders               
          Hypertriglyceridemia                       3.9% (4.0)                 2.0% (3.0)                  
          Hyperlipidemia                             2.5% (2.6)                 0.8% (1.2)                  
          Dehydration                                2.1% (2.1)                 1.1% (1.6)                  
     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders       
          Myalgia                                    2.3% (2.3)                 1.8% (2.6)                  
     Nervous System Disorders                         
          Headache                                   5.2% (5.3)                 4.2% (6.3)                  
          Peripheral neuropathy                      1.5% (1.5)                 2.0% (3.0)                  
     Psychiatric Disorders                            
          Insomnia                                   1.7% (1.7)                 3.7% (5.5)                  
     Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders       
          Dyspnea                                    2.1% (2.1)                 1.0% (1.4)                  
     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders           
          Rash                                       3.1% (3.1)                 3.8% (5.7)                  
          Less Common Adverse Reactions    Other adverse reactions reported in &lt;2% of adult patients (n=1474) treated with APTIVUS/ritonavir 500/200 mg in Phase 2 and 3 clinical trials are listed below by body system:
 

     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    : thrombocytopenia



     Gastrointestinal Disorders    : abdominal distension, dyspepsia, flatulence, gastroesophageal reflux disease, pancreatitis



     General Disorders    : influenza-like illness, malaise



     Hepatobiliary Disorders    : hepatitis, hepatic failure, hyperbilirubinemia, cytolytic hepatitis, toxic hepatitis, hepatic steatosis



     Immune System Disorders    : hypersensitivity



     Investigations    : hepatic enzymes increased, liver function test abnormal, lipase increased



     Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders    : anorexia, decreased appetite, diabetes mellitus, facial wasting, hyperamylasemia, hypercholesterolemia, hyperglycemia, mitochondrial toxicity



     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    : muscle cramp



     Nervous System Disorders    : dizziness, intracranial hemorrhage, somnolence



     Psychiatric Disorders    : sleep disorder



     Renal and Urinary Disorders    : renal insufficiency



     Skin and Subcutaneous System Disorders    : exanthem, lipoatrophy, lipodystrophy acquired, lipohypertrophy, pruritus



     Laboratory Abnormalities    Treatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities reported at 48 weeks in the controlled clinical trials 1182.12 and 1182.48 in adults are summarized in Table 3 below.



 Table 3 Treatment-Emergent Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Patients (48-week Analyses) 
                              Randomized, Controlled Clinical Trials 1182.12 and 1182.48   
                              Percentage of Patients (rate per 100 patient-exposure years)   
        Limit                 APTIVUS/ritonavir (500/200 mg BID) + OBR(n=738)  Comparator PI/ritonavir + OBR*(n=724)   
  
 *Comparator PI/ritonavir: lopinavir/ritonavir 400/100 mg BID, indinavir/ritonavir 800/100 mg BID, saquinavir/ritonavir 1000/100 mg BID, amprenavir/ritonavir 600/100 mg BID   
  
     Hematology       
        WBC count decreaseGrade 3     &lt;2.0 x 10  3  /muL             5.4% (5.6)               4.8% (7.7)        
        Grade 4                  &lt;1.0 x 10  3  /muL             0.3% (0.3)               1.1% (1.7)        
     Chemistry       
        AmylaseGrade 3               &gt;2.5 x ULN                 5.7% (5.9)              6.4% (10.4)        
        Grade 4                       &gt;5 x ULN                  0.3% (0.3)               0.7% (1.1)        
         
        ALTGrade 2                  &gt;2.5-5 x ULN               14.9% (16.5)             7.5% (12.4)        
        Grade 3                      &gt;5-10 x ULN                5.6% (5.7)               1.7% (2.6)        
        Grade 4                       &gt;10 x ULN                 4.1% (4.1)               0.4% (0.7)        
         
        ASTGrade 2                  &gt;2.5-5 x ULN                9.9% (10.5)             8.0% (13.3)        
        Grade 3                      &gt;5-10 x ULN                4.5% (4.6)               1.4% (2.2)        
        Grade 4                       &gt;10 x ULN                 1.6% (1.6)               0.4% (0.6)        
         
        ALT and/or ASTGrade 2-4         &gt;2.5 x ULN                26.0% (31.5)             13.7% (23.8)       
         
        CholesterolGrade 2        &gt;300 - 400 mg/dL             15.6% (17.7)             6.4% (10.5)        
        Grade 3                   &gt;400 - 500 mg/dL              3.3% (3.3)               0.3% (0.4)        
        Grade 4                      &gt;500 mg/dL                 0.9% (1.0)               0.1% (0.2)        
         
        TriglyceridesGrade 2       400 - 750 mg/dL             35.9% (49.9)             26.8% (51.0)       
        Grade 3                   &gt;750 - 1200 mg/dL            16.9% (19.4)             8.7% (14.6)        
        Grade 4                      &gt;1200 mg/dL                8.0% (8.4)               4.3% (7.0)        
      In controlled clinical trials 1182.12 and 1182.48 extending up to 96 weeks, the proportion of patients who developed Grade 2-4 ALT and/or AST elevations increased from 26% at week 48 to 32.1% at week 96 with APTIVUS/ritonavir. The risk of developing transaminase elevations is greater during the first year of therapy.
 

   6.2  Clinical Trials in Pediatric Patients

  APTIVUS, co-administered with ritonavir, has been studied in a total of 135 HIV-1 infected pediatric patients age 2 through 18 years as combination therapy. This study enrolled HIV-1 infected, treatment-experienced pediatric patients (with the exception of 3 treatment-naive patients), with baseline HIV-1 RNA of at least 1500 copies/mL. One hundred and ten (110) patients were enrolled in a randomized, open-label 48-week clinical trial (Study 1182.14) and 25 patients were enrolled in other clinical studies including Expanded Access and Emergency Use Programs.



 The adverse reactions profile seen in Study 1182.14 was similar to adults. Pyrexia (6.4%), vomiting (5.5%), cough (5.5%), rash (5.5%), nausea (4.5%), and diarrhea (3.6%) were the most frequently reported adverse reactions (Grade 2-4, all causes) in pediatric patients. Rash was reported more frequently in pediatric patients than in adults.



 The most common Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities were increases in CPK (11%), ALT (6.5%), and amylase (7.5%).



 Due to previous reports of both fatal and non-fatal intracranial hemorrhage (ICH), an analysis of bleeding events was performed. At 48 weeks of treatment, the frequency of pediatric patients with any bleeding adverse reactions was 7.5%. No drug related serious bleeding adverse reaction was reported. The most frequent bleeding adverse reaction was epistaxis (3.7%). No other bleeding adverse reaction was reported in frequency of &gt;1%. Additional trial follow-up through 100 weeks showed a cumulative 12% frequency of any bleeding adverse reaction.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY and INTRACRANIAL HEMORRHAGE

  WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY and INTRACRANIAL HEMORRHAGE

      Hepatotoxicity:    



     Clinical

hepatitis and hepatic decompensation, including some fatalities, have

been reported. Extra vigilance is warranted in patients with chronic

hepatitis B or hepatitis C co-infection, as these patients have an

increased risk of hepatotoxicity     [    see Warnings and Precautions   (5.1)      ].



     Intracranial Hemorrhage:    



     Both fatal and non-fatal intracranial

hemorrhage have been reported     [    see Warnings and Precautions   (5.2)      ].



   EXCERPT:       WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY and

INTRACRANIAL HEMORRHAGE    



 



       See full prescribing

information for complete boxed warning.      



 *  Clinical hepatitis and hepatic decompensation including some fatalities. Extra vigilance is warranted in patients with chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C co-infection. (5.1) 
 *  Fatal and non-fatal intracranial hemorrhage (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  Please refer to the ritonavir prescribing information for additional information on precautionary measures.



    EXCERPT:    *  Hepatic Impairment: Discontinue for signs and symptoms of clinical hepatitis or asymptomatic increases in ALT/AST &gt;10 times ULN or asymptomatic increases in ALT/AST 5-10 times ULN with concomitant increases in total bilirubin. Monitor liver function tests prior to therapy and frequently thereafter.  (5.1)   
 *  Intracranial Hemorrhage/Platelet Aggregation and Coagulation: Use with caution in patients at risk for increased bleeding or who are receiving medications that increase the risk of bleeding  (5.2  ,  5.4)   
 *  The concomitant use of APTIVUS/ritonavir and certain other drugs may result in known or potentially significant drug interactions. Consult the full prescribing information prior to and during treatment for potential drug interactions.  (5.3,    7.2)   
 *  Rash: Discontinue and initiate appropriate treatment if severe skin reaction occurs or is suspected.  (5.6)  Use with caution in patients with a known sulfonamide allergy.  (5.7)   
 *  Patients may develop new onset or exacerbations of diabetes mellitus, hyperglycemia  (5.8)  , immune reconstitution syndrome  (5.9)  , redistribution/accumulation of body fat  (5.10)  , and elevated lipids.  (5.11)  Monitor cholesterol and triglycerides prior to therapy and periodically thereafter. 
 *  Hemophilia: Spontaneous bleeding may occur, and additional factor VIII may be required  (5.12)   
    
 

   5.1  Hepatic Impairment and Toxicity



  Clinical hepatitis and hepatic decompensation, including some fatalities, were reported with APTIVUS co-administered with 200 mg of ritonavir. These have generally occurred in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease taking multiple concomitant medications. A causal relationship to APTIVUS/ritonavir could not be established. Physicians and patients should be vigilant for the appearance of signs or symptoms of hepatitis, such as fatigue, malaise, anorexia, nausea, jaundice, bilirubinuria, acholic stools, liver tenderness or hepatomegaly. Patients with signs or symptoms of clinical hepatitis should discontinue APTIVUS/ritonavir treatment and seek medical evaluation.



 All patients should be followed closely with clinical and laboratory monitoring, especially those with chronic hepatitis B or C co-infection, as these patients have an increased risk of hepatotoxicity. Liver function tests should be performed prior to initiating therapy with APTIVUS/ritonavir, and frequently throughout the duration of treatment.



 If asymptomatic elevations in AST or ALT greater than 10 times the upper limit of normal occur, APTIVUS/ritonavir therapy should be discontinued. If asymptomatic elevations in AST or ALT between 5 - 10 times the upper limit of normal and increases in total bilirubin greater than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal occur, APTIVUS/ritonavir therapy should be discontinued.



 Treatment-experienced patients with chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C co-infection or elevated transaminases are at approximately 2-fold risk for developing Grade 3 or 4 transaminase elevations or hepatic decompensation. In two large, randomized, open-label, controlled clinical trials with an active comparator (1182.12 and 1182.48) of treatment-experienced patients, Grade 3 and 4 increases in hepatic transaminases were observed in 10.3% (10.9/100 PEY) receiving APTIVUS/ritonavir through week 48. In a study of treatment-naive patients, 20.3% (21/100 PEY) experienced Grade 3 or 4 hepatic transaminase elevations while receiving APTIVUS/ritonavir 500 mg/200 mg through week 48.



 Tipranavir is principally metabolized by the liver. Caution should be exercised when administering APTIVUS/ritonavir to patients with mild hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class A) because tipranavir concentrations may be increased [  see Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].



    5.2  Intracranial Hemorrhage



  APTIVUS, co-administered with 200 mg of ritonavir, has been associated with reports of both fatal and non-fatal intracranial hemorrhage (ICH). Many of these patients had other medical conditions or were receiving concomitant medications that may have caused or contributed to these events. No pattern of abnormal coagulation parameters has been observed in patients in general, or preceding the development of ICH. Therefore, routine measurement of coagulation parameters is not currently indicated in the management of patients on APTIVUS.



    5.3  Risk of Serious Adverse Reactions Due to Drug Interactions



   Initiation of APTIVUS/ritonavir, a CYP3A inhibitor, in patients receiving medications metabolized by CYP3A or initiation of medications metabolized by CYP3A in patients already receiving APTIVUS/ritonavir, may increase plasma concentrations of medications metabolized by CYP3A. Initiation of medications that inhibit or induce CYP3A may increase or decrease concentrations of APTIVUS/ritonavir, respectively. These interactions may lead to:  



 *   Clinically significant adverse reactions, potentially leading to severe, life-threatening, or fatal events from greater exposures of concomitant medications.  
 *   Clinically significant adverse reactions from greater exposures of APTIVUS/ritonavir.  
 *   Loss of therapeutic effect of APTIVUS/ritonavir and possible development of resistance.  
     See Table 4 for steps to prevent or manage these possible and known significant drug interactions, including dosing recommendations [see Drug Interactions  (7)  ]  . Consider the potential for drug interactions prior to and during APTIVUS/ritonavir therapy; review concomitant medications during APTIVUS/ritonavir therapy; and monitor for the adverse reactions associated with the concomitant medications [see Contraindications  (4)  and Drug Interactions  (7)  ]  .  
 

    5.4  Effects on Platelet Aggregation and Coagulation



  APTIVUS/ritonavir should be used with caution in patients who may be at risk of increased bleeding from trauma, surgery or other medical conditions, or who are receiving medications known to increase the risk of bleeding such as antiplatelet agents and anticoagulants, or who are taking supplemental high doses of vitamin E.



 In rats, tipranavir treatment alone induced dose-dependent changes in coagulation parameters, bleeding events and death. Co-administration with vitamin E significantly increased these effects [  see Nonclinical Toxicology  (13.2)      ]. However, analyses of stored plasma from adult patients treated with APTIVUS capsules and pediatric patients treated with APTIVUS oral solution (which contains a vitamin E derivative) showed no effect of APTIVUS/ritonavir on vitamin K-dependent coagulation factors (Factor II and Factor VII), Factor V, or on prothrombin or activated partial thromboplastin times.



 In  in vitro    experiments, tipranavir was observed to inhibit human platelet aggregation at levels consistent with exposures observed in patients receiving APTIVUS/ritonavir.



    5.5  Vitamin E Intake



  Patients taking APTIVUS oral solution should be advised not to take supplemental vitamin E greater than a standard multivitamin as APTIVUS oral solution contains 116 IU/mL of vitamin E which is higher than the Reference Daily Intake (adults 30 IU, pediatrics approximately 10 IU).



    5.6  Rash



  Rash, including urticarial rash, maculopapular rash, and possible photosensitivity, has been reported in subjects receiving APTIVUS/ritonavir. In some cases rash was accompanied by joint pain or stiffness, throat tightness, or generalized pruritus. In controlled adult clinical trials, rash (all grades, all causality) was observed in 10% of females and in 8% of males receiving APTIVUS/ritonavir through 48 weeks of treatment. The median time to onset of rash was 53 days and the median duration of rash was 22 days. The discontinuation rate for rash in clinical trials was 0.5%. In an uncontrolled compassionate use program (n=3920), cases of rash, some of which were severe, accompanied by myalgia, fever, erythema, desquamation, and mucosal erosions were reported. In the pediatric clinical trial, the frequency of rash (all grades, all causality) through 48 weeks of treatment was 21%. Overall, most of the pediatric patients had mild rash and 5 (5%) had moderate rash. Overall 3% of pediatric patients interrupted APTIVUS treatment due to rash and the discontinuation rate for rash in pediatric patients was 0.9%. Discontinue and initiate appropriate treatment if severe skin rash develops.



    5.7  Sulfa Allergy



  APTIVUS should be used with caution in patients with a known sulfonamide allergy. Tipranavir contains a sulfonamide moiety. The potential for cross-sensitivity between drugs in the sulfonamide class and APTIVUS is unknown.



    5.8  Diabetes Mellitus/Hyperglycemia



  New onset diabetes mellitus, exacerbation of pre-existing diabetes mellitus and hyperglycemia have been reported during post-marketing surveillance in HIV-1 infected patients receiving protease inhibitor therapy. Some patients required either initiation or dose adjustments of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents for treatment of these events. In some cases, diabetic ketoacidosis has occurred. In those patients who discontinued protease inhibitor therapy, hyperglycemia persisted in some cases. Because these events have been reported voluntarily during clinical practice, estimates of frequency cannot be made and a causal relationship between protease inhibitor therapy and these events has not been established.



    5.9  Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including APTIVUS. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as  Mycobacterium avium    infection, cytomegalovirus,  Pneumocystis jiroveci    pneumonia, tuberculosis, or reactivation of herpes simplex and herpes zoster), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.10  Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.11  Elevated Lipids



  Treatment with APTIVUS co-administered with 200 mg of ritonavir has resulted in large increases in the concentration of total cholesterol and triglycerides [  see Adverse Reactions  (6)      ]. Triglyceride and cholesterol testing should be performed prior to initiating APTIVUS/ritonavir therapy and at periodic intervals during therapy. Lipid disorders should be managed as clinically appropriate; taking into account any potential drug-drug interactions [  see Drug Interactions  (7.2)      ].



    5.12  Patients with Hemophilia



  There have been reports of increased bleeding, including spontaneous skin hematomas and hemarthrosis in patients with hemophilia type A and B treated with protease inhibitors. In some patients additional Factor VIII was given. In more than half of the reported cases, treatment with protease inhibitors was continued or reintroduced if treatment had been discontinued. A causal relationship between protease inhibitors and these events has not been established.



    5.13  Resistance/Cross Resistance



  Because the potential for HIV-1 cross-resistance among protease inhibitors has not been fully explored in APTIVUS/ritonavir treated patients, it is unknown what effect therapy with APTIVUS will have on the activity of subsequently administered protease inhibitors.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
