<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aralast" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Hypersensitivity reactions have been reported in patients following administration of ARALAST/ARALAST NP [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ].



 No serious adverse reactions related to the use of ARALAST NP were reported in clinical trials.The most common adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of infusions in clinical trials were headache, musculoskeletal discomfort, vessel puncture site bruise, nausea, and rhinorrhea.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of infusions in clinical studies were headache, musculoskeletal discomfort, vessel puncture site bruise, nausea, and rhinorrhea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare Corporation at 1-800-423-2862 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of ARALAST NP was evaluated in a total of 38 subjects with severe congenital Alpha1-PI deficiency (pre-augmentation therapy serum levels of Alpha1-PI of less than 11 microM) in two clinical trials. The crossover trial was a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, single-dose pharmacokinetic (PK) comparability trial conducted in 25 subjects with severe congenital Alpha1-PI deficiency to evaluate the pharmacokinetics of ARALAST NP (test drug, 60 mg/kg body weight) as compared to ARALAST (reference drug, 60 mg/kg body weight), each infused at a rate of 0.2 mL/kg body weight/minute. The BAL trial was a multicenter, open-label, non-randomized trial in 13 subjects with severe congenital Alpha1-PI deficiency to determine the safety and effects of weekly augmentation therapy with ARALAST NP (60 mg/kg body weight/week) administered at a rate of 0.2 mL/kg body weight/minute in elevating Alpha1-PI levels in serum and epithelial lining fluid (ELF).



 In both trials, there were no deaths and no serious adverse reactions associated with ARALAST NP or ARALAST administration. None of the subjects withdrew from the trial due to an adverse reaction. There was no reduction in infusion rate at 0.2 mL/kg body weight/min or infusion discontinuation/interruption due to an adverse reaction, except for one subject in the crossover trial who experienced pain at infusion site during ARALAST administration.



   Table 1  summarizes the number of subjects, the total number of infusions, and the rate of adverse reactions (ARs) associated with ARALAST NP or ARALAST treatment for each clinical trial.



 Table 1 Number of Subjects/Infusions/Adverse Reactions (ARs)An adverse reaction (AR) is any adverse event which met any of the following criteria: (a) an adverse event that began during infusion or within 72 hours following the end of product infusion, or (b) an adverse event considered by the investigator to be at least possibly related to product administration, or (c) an adverse event for which causality assessment was missing or indeterminate. Occurring during ARALAST NP or ARALAST Treatment 
                                             Crossover Trial      BAL Trial            
                                             ARALAST NP           ARALAST               ARALAST NP          
 No. of subjects treated                   25                   25                    13                    
 No. of infusions                          25                   25                    104                   
 No. (%) of subjects with serious ARs      0 (0%)               0 (0%)                0 (0%)                
 No. of serious ARs                        0                    0                     0                     
 No. (%) of subjects with non-serious ARs  12 (48%)             13 (52%)              4 (31%)               
 No. of non-serious ARs                    26                   21                    14                    
 No. (%) of MildARs                        21 (81%)             16 (76%)              8 (57%)               
 No. (%) of ModerateARs                    5 (19%)              5 (24%)               5 (36%)               
 No. (%) of Severe ARs                     0 (0%)               0 (0%)                1 (7%)                
          The most common ARs (defined as adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of infusions) in each clinical trial are shown in  Table 2  .
 

 Table 2 Adverse Reactions (ARs) An adverse reaction (AR) is any adverse event which met any of the following criteria: (a) an adverse event that began during infusion or within 72 hours following the end of product infusion, or (b) an adverse event considered by the investigator to be at least possibly related to product administration, or (c) an adverse event for which causality assessment was missing or indeterminate. Occurring in &gt;=5% of Infusions 
                                    Crossover Trial(Number of Subjects = 25;Number of infusions per product = 25)      BAL Trial(Number of Subjects = 13; Number of infusions = 104)     
   Reaction                         ARALAST NPN (%)         ARALASTN (%)           ARALAST NPN (%)          
 Headache                         4 (16%)                 3 (12%)                0 (0%)                     
 Musculoskeletal discomfort       4 (16%)                 2 (8%)                 0 (0%)                     
 Vessel puncture site bruise      2 (8%)                  4 (16%)                0 (0%)                     
 Lethargy                         0 (0%)                  2 (8%)                 0 (0%)                     
 Nausea                           2 (8%)                  2 (8%)                 0 (0%)                     
 Rhinorrhea                       1 (4%)                  0 (0%)                 6 (6%)                     
              ARALAST versus PROLASTIN Trial    
 

 ARALAST was evaluated for up to 96 weeks in 27 subjects with a congenital deficiency of Alpha1-PI and clinically evident emphysema. During the initial 10 weeks of the trial, subjects were randomized to receive either ARALAST or a commercially available preparation of Alpha1-PI (PROLASTIN).



 During the entire period of administration of ARALAST, the most common adverse reactions occurring at a rate of &gt;0.5% of infusions included pharyngitis (1.2%), headache (0.8%), and cough increased (0.5%). Adverse reactions that occurred at rates &lt; 0.5% included somnolence, rash, tinnitus, back pain, chest pain, peripheral edema, dizziness, insomnia, bronchitis, abdomen enlarged, abdominal pain, allergic reaction, pruritus, chills, fever, vasodilation, nausea, hypertonia, hypesthesia, nervousness, asthma, dyspnea, lung disorder, abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, and dysmenorrhea.



 Twenty-six (26) of 27 (96.3%) subjects experienced a total of 94 upper and lower respiratory-tract infections during the 96-week trial (median: 3.0; range: 1 to 8; mean +/- SD: 3.6 +/- 2.3 infections). Twenty-eight (29.8%) of the respiratory infections occurred in 19 (70.4%) subjects during the first 24 weeks of the 96-week trial suggesting that the risk of infection did not change with time on ARALAST. In a post-hoc analysis, subjects experienced a range of 0 to 8 exacerbations of COPD over the 96-week trial with a median of less than one exacerbation per year (median: 0.61; mean +/- SD: 0.83 +/- 0.87 exacerbations per year).



 Treatment-emergent elevations (&gt; two times the upper limit of normal) in aminotransferases (ALT or AST), up to 3.7 times the upper limit of normal, were noted in 3 of 27 (11.1%) subjects. Elevations were transient lasting three months or less. No subject developed any evidence of viral hepatitis or hepatitis seroconversion while being treated with ARALAST, including 13 evaluable subjects who were not vaccinated against hepatitis B.



 No clinically relevant alterations in blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, or body temperature occurred during infusion of ARALAST. Mean hematology and routine clinical chemistry (other than ALT) laboratory parameters were little changed over the duration of the trial, with individual variations not clinically meaningful.



 There were no serious adverse reactions or seroconversions reported for the ARALAST group during the 96 week trial period. No subject developed antibodies to Alpha1-PI.



     Immunogenicity    



 a. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to ARALAST NP with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.



 b. Immunogenicity of ARALAST NP was evaluated in the BAL trial. None of the treated subjects developed antibodies against ARALAST NP.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ARALAST NP. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Vascular Disorders  : Flushing



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : Vomiting, Diarrhea



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  : Urticaria



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  : Myalgia



   General and Administration Site Conditions  : Injection site reaction, Fatigue, Malaise, Asthenia, Feeling abnormal
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions may occur in IgA deficient patients with antibodies against IgA. (  5.1  ) 
 *  May carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents such as viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent, despite manufacturing steps designed to minimize the risk of viral transmission. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  ARALAST NP may contain trace amounts of IgA. Patients with known antibodies to IgA, which can be present in patients with selective or severe IgA deficiency, have a greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. Closely follow the recommended infusion rate [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )  ]. Monitor vital signs continuously and observe the patient carefully throughout the infusion. . Discontinue the infusion if hypersensitivity symptoms occur and administer appropriate emergency treatment. Have epinephrine and other appropriate supportive therapy available for the treatment of any acute anaphylactic or anaphylactoid reaction.



    5.2 Transmission of Infectious Agents



  Because this product is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, such as viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. This also applies to unknown or emerging viruses and other pathogens. The risk of transmitting an infectious agent has been minimized by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, by testing for the presence of certain virus infections and by inactivating and removing certain viruses during the manufacturing process. Despite these measures, such products may still potentially transmit human pathogenic agents.



 No seroconversions for hepatitis B or C (HBV or HCV) or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or any other known infectious agent were reported with the use of ARALAST NP during clinical studies.



 All infections thought by a physician to possibly have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Baxter Healthcare Corporation, at 1-800-423-2862 (in the U.S.).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
