<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aricept" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6         ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular Conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.2    )]  
 *  Nausea and Vomiting [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.3    )]  
 *  Peptic Ulcer Disease and GI Bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.4    )]  
 *  Weight Loss [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.5    )]  
 *  Genitourinary Conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.6    )]  
 *  Neurological Conditions: Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.7    )]  
 *  Pulmonary Conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.8    )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions in clinical studies of ARICEPT are nausea, diarrhea, insomnia, vomiting, muscle cramps, fatigue, and anorexia (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eisai Inc. at 1-888-274-2378 (fax 1-201-746-3207) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 ARICEPT has been administered to over 1,700 individuals during clinical trials worldwide. Approximately 1200 of these patients have been treated for at least 3 months and more than 1,000 patients have been treated for at least 6 months. Controlled and uncontrolled trials in the United States included approximately 900 patients. In regards to the highest dose of 10 mg/day, this population includes 650 patients treated for 3 months, 475 patients treated for 6 months, and 116 patients treated for over 1 year. The range of patient exposure is from 1 to 1,214 days.



   Mild    t    o Moderate    Alzheimer    '    s D    isease       



   Adverse    Reactions    Leading to Discontinuation  The rates of discontinuation from controlled clinical trials of ARICEPT due to adverse reactions for the ARICEPT 5 mg/day treatment groups were comparable to those of placebo treatment groups at approximately 5%. The rate of discontinuation of patients who received 7-day escalations from 5 mg/day to 10 mg/day was higher at 13%.



 The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation, defined as those occurring in at least 2% of patients and at twice or more the incidence seen in placebo patients, are shown in Table 1.




   Table 1. Most    Common    Adverse    Reactions    Leading to        Discontinuation    in    Patients with Mild to Moderate        Alzhe    i    mer's Disease     
   Adverse Reaction      Placebo    (n=355)    %      5 mg/day    ARICEPT    (n=350)    %      10 mg/day    ARICEPT    (n=315)    %     
 Nausea           1                1                3                 
 Diarrhea         0                &lt;1               3                 
 Vomiting         &lt;1               &lt;1               2                 
            Most    Common    Adverse         Reactions  
 

 The most common adverse reactions, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in patients receiving 10 mg/day and twice the placebo rate, are largely predicted by ARICEPT's cholinomimetic effects. These include nausea, diarrhea, insomnia, vomiting, muscle cramp, fatigue, and anorexia. These adverse reactions were often transient, resolving during continued ARICEPT treatment without the need for dose modification.



 There is evidence to suggest that the frequency of these common adverse reactions may be affected by the rate of titration. An open-label study was conducted with 269 patients who received placebo in the 15- and 30-week studies. These patients were titrated to a dose of 10 mg/day over a 6-week period. The rates of common adverse reactions were lower than those seen in patients titrated to 10 mg/day over one week in the controlled clinical trials and were comparable to those seen in patients on 5 mg/day.



 See Table 2 for a comparison of the most common adverse reactions following one and six week titration regimens.




   Table 2. Comparison of    R    ates of    A    dverse    Reactions         in    M    ild to    M    oderate    P    atients    Titrated    to 10 mg/day over 1 and 6    W    eeks     
                    No titration      One week    titration      Six week    titration     
   Adverse    Reaction      Placebo    (n=315)    %      5 mg/day    (n=311)    %      10 mg/day    (n=315)    %      10 mg/day    (n=269)    %     
 Nausea           6                5                19               6                 
 Diarrhea         5                8                15               9                 
 Insomnia         6                6                14               6                 
 Fatigue          3                4                8                3                 
 Vomiting         3                3                8                5                 
 Muscle cramps    2                6                8                3                 
 Anorexia         2                3                7                3                 
           Table 3 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients in pooled placebo-controlled trials who received either ARICEPT 5 mg or 10 mg and for which the rate of occurrence was greater for patients treated with ARICEPT than with placebo. In general, adverse reactions occurred more frequently in female patients and with advancing age.
 


   Table 3. Adverse    Reactions    in    Pooled    Placebo-    Controlled Clinical Trials in Mild to Moderate    Alzheimer's D    isease          
   Adverse    Reaction      Placebo    (n=355)    %      ARICEPT    (n=747)    %     
   Percent of Pa    tients with any Adverse    Reaction      72               74              
       Nausea     6                11                
       Diarrhea   5                10                
       Headache   9                10                
       Insomnia   6                9                 
       Pain, various locations  8                9                 
       Dizziness  6                8                 
       Accident   6                7                 
       Muscle Cramps  2                6                 
       Fatigue    3                5                 
       Vomiting   3                5                 
       Anorexia   2                4                 
       Ecchymosis  3                4                 
       Abnormal Dreams  0                3                 
       Depression  &lt;1               3                 
       Weight Loss  1                3                 
       Arthritis  1                2                 
       Frequent Urination  1                2                 
       Somnolence  &lt;1               2                 
       Syncope    1                2                 
           Severe    Alzheimer's D    isease         (ARICEPT 5 mg/day and 10 mg/day)  
 

 ARICEPT has been administered to over 600 patients with severe Alzheimer's disease during clinical trials of at least 6 months duration, including three double-blind, placebo-controlled trials, two of which had an open label extension.



   Adverse    Reactions    Leading to Discontinuation  



 The rates of discontinuation from controlled clinical trials of ARICEPT due to adverse reactions for the ARICEPT patients were approximately 12% compared to 7% for placebo patients. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation, defined as those occurring in at least 2% of ARICEPT     patients and at twice or more the incidence seen in placebo, were anorexia (2% vs. 1% placebo), nausea (2% vs. &lt;1% placebo), diarrhea (2% vs. 0% placebo), and urinary tract infection (2% vs. 1% placebo).



   Most    Common    Adverse         Reactions  



 The most common adverse reactions, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in patients receiving ARICEPT and at twice or more the placebo rate, are largely predicted by ARICEPT's cholinomimetic effects. These include diarrhea, anorexia, vomiting, nausea, and ecchymosis. These adverse reactions were often transient, resolving during continued ARICEPT treatment without the need for dose modification.



 Table 4 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients in pooled placebo-controlled trials who received ARICEPT 5 mg or 10 mg and for which the rate of occurrence was greater for patients treated with ARICEPT than with placebo.




   Table 4. Adverse    Reactions    in    Pooled    Controlled Clinical Trials in Severe    Alzheimer's D    isease          
   Body System/Adverse    Reaction      Placebo    (n=392)    %      ARICEPT    (n=501)    %     
   Percent of Patients with any Adverse    Reaction      73               81              
 Accident         12               13                
 Infection        9                11                
 Diarrhea         4                10                
 Anorexia         4                8                 
 Vomiting         4                8                 
 Nausea           2                6                 
 Insomnia         4                5                 
 Ecchymosis       2                5                 
 Headache         3                4                 
 Hypertension     2                3                 
 Pain             2                3                 
 Back Pain        2                3                 
 Eczema           2                3                 
 Hallucinations   1                3                 
 Hostility        2                3                 
 Increase in Creatine Phosphokinase  1                3                 
 Nervousness      2                3                 
 Fever            1                2                 
 Chest Pain       &lt;1               2                 
 Confusion        1                2                 
 Dehydration      1                2                 
 Depression       1                2                 
 Dizziness        1                2                 
 Emotional Lability  1                2                 
 Hemorrhage       1                2                 
 Hyperlipemia     &lt;1               2                 
 Personality Disorder  1                2                 
 Somnolence       1                2                 
 Syncope          1                2                 
 Urinary Incontinence  1                2                 
           Moderate to Severe Alzheimer's Disease    (ARICEPT 23 mg/day)  
 

 ARICEPT 23 mg/day has been administered to over 1300 individuals globally in clinical trials. Approximately 1050 of these patients have been treated for at least three months and more than 950 patients have been treated for at least six months. The range of patient exposure was from 1 to over 500 days.



   Adverse    Reactions         Leading to Discontinuation  



 The rate of discontinuation from a controlled clinical trial of ARICEPT 23 mg/day due to adverse reactions was higher (19%) than for the 10 mg/day treatment group (8%). The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation, defined as those occurring in at least 1% of patients and greater than those occurring with 10 mg/day are shown in Table 5.




   Table 5. Most    Common    Adverse    Reactions    Leading to    Discontinuat    i    on    in P    atients with Moderate to Severe    Alzheimer's Disease     
   Adverse Reaction      23 mg/day    ARICEPT    (n=963)    %      10 mg/day    ARICEPT    (n=471)    %     
       Vomiting   3                0                 
       Diarrhea   2                0                 
       Nausea     2                0                 
       Dizziness  1                0                 
         The majority of discontinuations due to adverse reactions in the 23 mg group occurred during the first month of treatment.
 

   Most    Common    Adverse    Reactions    with    ARICEPT    23 mg    /day  



 The most common adverse reactions, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5%, include nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, and anorexia.



 Table 6 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients who received 23 mg/day of ARICEPT and at a higher frequency than those receiving 10 mg/day of ARICEPT in a controlled clinical trial that compared the two doses. In this study, there were no important differences in the type of adverse reactions in patients taking ARICEPT with or without memantine.




   Table 6. Adverse    Reactions    in a Controlled Clinical Trial in Moderate to Severe Alzheimer's Disease     
   Adverse    Reaction      23 mg/day    ARICEPT    (n=963)    %      10 mg/day    ARICEPT    (n=471)    %     
   Percent of Patie    nts with any Adverse    Reaction    74               64                
          Nausea  12               3                 
          Vomiting  9                3                 
          Diarrhea  8                5                 
          Anorexia  5                2                 
          Dizziness  5                3                 
          Weight Loss  5                3                 
          Headache  4                3                 
          Insomnia  3                2                 
          Urinary incontinence  3                1                 
          Asthenia  2                1                 
          Contusion  2                0                 
          Fatigue  2                1                 
          Somnolence  2                1                 
             6.2    Postmarketing Experience  
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use ARICEPT. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Abdominal pain, agitation, aggression, cholecystitis, confusion, convulsions, hallucinations, heart block (all types), hemolytic anemia, hepatitis, hyponatremia, neuroleptic malignant syndrome, pancreatitis, rash, rhabdomyolysis, QTc prolongation, and torsade de pointes.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5        WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Cholinesterase inhibitors are likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia (  5.1  ) 
 *  Cholinesterase inhibitors may have vagotonic effects on the sinoatrial and atrioventricular nodes manifesting as bradycardia or heart block (  5.2  ) 
 *  ARICEPT can cause vomiting. Patients should be observed closely at initiation of treatment and after dose increases (  5.3  ) 
 *  Patients should be monitored closely for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers (  5.4  ) 
 *  The use of ARICEPT in a dose of 23 mg once daily is associated with weight loss (  5.5  ) 
 *  Cholinomimetics may cause bladder outflow obstructions (  5.6  ) 
 *  Cholinomimetics are believed to have some potential to cause generalized convulsions (  5.7  ) 
 *  Cholinesterase inhibitors should be prescribed with care to patients with a history of asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease (  5.8  ) 
    
 

    5.1   Anesthesia      



  ARICEPT, as a cholinesterase inhibitor, is likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia.



     5.2   Cardiovascular Conditions  



  Because of their pharmacological action, cholinesterase inhibitors may have vagotonic effects on the sinoatrial and atrioventricular nodes. This effect may manifest as bradycardia or heart block in patients both with and without known underlying cardiac conduction abnormalities. Syncopal episodes have been reported in association with the use of ARICEPT.



     5.3   Nausea and Vomiting  



  ARICEPT, as a predictable consequence of its pharmacological properties, has been shown to produce diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting. These effects, when they occur, appear more frequently with the 10 mg/day dose than with the 5 mg/day dose, and more frequently with the 23 mg dose than with the 10 mg dose. Specifically, in a controlled trial that compared a dose of 23 mg/day to 10 mg/day in patients who had been treated with donepezil 10 mg/day for at least three months, the incidence of nausea in the 23 mg group was markedly greater than in the patients who continued on 10 mg/day (11.8% vs. 3.4%, respectively), and the incidence of vomiting in the 23 mg group was markedly greater than in the 10 mg group (9.2% vs. 2.5%, respectively). The percent of patients who discontinued treatment due to vomiting in the 23 mg group was markedly higher than in the 10 mg group (2.9% vs. 0.4%, respectively).



 Although in most cases, these effects have been transient, sometimes lasting one to three weeks, and have resolved during continued use of ARICEPT,     patients should be observed closely at the initiation of treatment and after dose increases.



     5.4   Peptic Ulcer Disease and GI Bleeding  



  Through their primary action, cholinesterase inhibitors may be expected to increase gastric acid secretion due to increased cholinergic activity. Therefore, patients should be monitored closely for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers, e.g., those with a history of ulcer disease or those receiving concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). Clinical studies of ARICEPT in a dose of 5 mg/day to 10 mg/day have shown no increase, relative to placebo, in the incidence of either peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding. Results of a controlled clinical study with 23 mg/day showed an increase, relative to 10 mg/day, in the incidence of peptic ulcer disease (0.4% vs. 0.2%) and gastrointestinal bleeding from any site (1.1% vs. 0.6%).



     5.5   Weight Loss  



  Weight loss was reported as an adverse reaction in 4.7% of patients assigned to ARICEPT in a dose of 23 mg/day compared to 2.5% of patients assigned to 10 mg/day. Compared to their baseline weights, 8.4% of patients taking 23 mg/day were found to have a weight decrease of &gt;= 7% by the end of the study, while 4.9% of patients taking 10 mg/day were found to have weight loss of &gt;= 7% at the end of the study.



     5.6 Genitourinary Conditions  



  Although not observed in clinical trials of ARICEPT, cholinomimetics may cause bladder outflow obstruction.



     5.7 Neurological Con   d   itions: Seizures  



  Cholinomimetics are believed to have some potential to cause generalized convulsions. However, seizure activity also may be a manifestation of Alzheimer's disease.



     5.8 Pulmonary Con   d   itions  



  Because of their cholinomimetic actions, cholinesterase inhibitors should be prescribed with care to patients with a history of asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
