<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="arimidex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions with ARIMIDEX occurring in less than 1 in 10,000 patients, are: 1) skin reactions such as lesions, ulcers, or blisters; 2) allergic reactions with swelling of the face, lips, tongue, and/or throat. This may cause difficulty in swallowing and/or breathing; and 3) changes in blood tests of the liver function, including inflammation of the liver with symptoms that may include a general feeling of not being well, with or without jaundice, liver pain or liver swelling [see    Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



 Common adverse reactions (occurring with an incidence of &gt;=10%) in women taking ARIMIDEX included: hot flashes, asthenia, arthritis, pain, arthralgia, hypertension, depression, nausea and vomiting, rash, osteoporosis, fractures, back pain, insomnia, headache, bone pain, peripheral edema, increased cough, dyspnea, pharyngitis and lymphedema.



 In the ATAC trial, the most common reported adverse reaction (&gt;0.1%) leading to discontinuation of therapy for both treatment groups was hot flashes, although there were fewer patients who discontinued therapy as a result of hot flashes in the ARIMIDEX group.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   In the early breast cancer (ATAC) study, the most common (occurring with an incidence of &gt;=10%) side effects occurring in women taking ARIMIDEX included: hot flashes, asthenia, arthritis, pain, arthralgia, pharyngitis, hypertension, depression, nausea and vomiting, rash, osteoporosis, fractures, back pain, insomnia, headache, peripheral edema and lymphedema, regardless of causality. (  6.1  )



 In the advanced breast cancer studies, the most common (occurring with an incidence of &gt;10%) side effects occurring in women taking ARIMIDEX included: hot flashes, nausea, asthenia, pain, headache, back pain, bone pain, increased cough, dyspnea, pharyngitis and peripheral edema. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals LP at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Adjuvant Therapy

  Adverse reaction data for adjuvant therapy are based on the ATAC trial [see    Clinical Studies (14.1)    ]. The median duration of adjuvant treatment for safety evaluation was 59.8 months and 59.6 months for patients receiving ARIMIDEX 1 mg and tamoxifen 20 mg, respectively.



 Adverse reactions occurring with an incidence of at least 5% in either treatment group during treatment or within 14 days of the end of treatment are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1 - Adverse reactions occurring with an incidence of at least 5% in either treatment group during treatment, or within 14 days of the end of treatment in the ATAC trial The combination arm was discontinued due to lack of efficacy benefit at 33 months of follow-up. 
   Body system and adverse reactions by    COSTART    preferred term      ARIMIDEX 1 mg    (N    = 3092)      Tamoxifen 20 mg    (N    = 3094)     
  
  Body as a whole                                                                          
  Asthenia                                                          575 (19)                
                                                                         544 (18)             
                                              
  Pain                                                              533 (17)                
                                                                         485 (16)             
                                              
  Back pain                                                         321 (10)                
                                                                         309 (10)             
                                              
  Headache                                                          314 (10)                
                                                                         249    (8)           
                                              
  Abdominal pain                                                    271    (9)              
                                                                         276    (9)           
                                              
  Infection                                                         285    (9)              
                                                                         276    (9)           
                                              
  Accidental injury                                                 311 (10)                
                                                                         303 (10)             
                                              
  Flu syndrome                                                      175    (6)              
                                                                         195    (6)           
                                              
  Chest pain                                                        200    (7)              
                                                                         150    (5)           
                                              
  Neoplasm                                                          162    (5)              
                                                                         144    (5)           
                                              
  Cyst                                                              138    (5)              
                                                                         162    (5)           
                                              
  Cardiovascular                                                                           
  Vasodilatation                                                    1104 (36)               
                                                                         1264 (41)            
                                              
  Hypertension                                                      402 (13)                
                                                                         349 (11)             
                                              
  Digestive                                                                                
  Nausea                                                            343 (11)                
                                                                         335 (11)             
                                              
  Constipation                                                      249 (8)                 
                                                                         252 (8)              
                                              
  Diarrhea                                                          265    (9)              
                                                                         216    (7)           
                                              
  Dyspepsia                                                         206    (7)              
                                                                         169    (6)           
                                              
  Gastrointestinal disorder                                         210    (7)              
                                                                         158    (5)           
                                              
  Hemic and lymphatic                                                                      
  Lymphedema                                                        304 (10)                
                                                                         341 (11)             
                                              
  Anemia                                                            113    (4)              
                                                                         159    (5)           
                                              
  Metabolic and nutritional                                                                
  Peripheral edema                                                  311 (10)                
                                                                         343 (11)             
                                              
  Weight gain                                                       285    (9)              
                                                                         274    (9)           
                                              
  Hypercholesterolemia                                              278    (9)              
                                                                         108 (3.5)            
                                              
  Musculoskeletal                                                                          
  Arthritis                                                         512 (17)                
                                                                         445 (14)             
                                              
  Arthralgia                                                        467 (15)                
                                                                         344 (11)             
                                              
  Osteoporosis                                                      325 (11)                
                                                                         226    (7)           
                                              
  Fracture                                                          315 (10)                
                                                                         209    (7)           
                                              
  Bone pain                                                         201    (7)              
                                                                         185    (6)           
                                              
  Arthrosis                                                         207    (7)              
                                                                         156    (5)           
                                              
  Joint Disorder                                                    184    (6)              
                                                                         160    (5)           
                                              
  Myalgia                                                           179    (6)              
                                                                         160    (5)           
                                              
  Nervous system                                                                           
  Depression                                                        413 (13)                
                                                                         382 (12)             
                                              
  Insomnia                                                          309 (10)                
                                                                         281    (9)           
                                              
  Dizziness                                                         236    (8)              
                                                                         234    (8)           
                                              
  Anxiety                                                           195    (6)              
                                                                         180    (6)           
                                              
  Paresthesia                                                       215    (7)              
                                                                         145    (5)           
                                              
  Respiratory                                                                              
  Pharyngitis                                                       443 (14)                
                                                                         422 (14)             
                                              
  Cough increased                                                   261    (8)              
                                                                         287    (9)           
                                              
  Dyspnea                                                           234    (8)              
                                                                         237    (8)           
                                              
  Sinusitis                                                         184    (6)              
                                                                         159    (5)           
                                              
  Bronchitis                                                        167    (5)              
                                                                         153    (5)           
                                              
  Skin and appendages                                                                      
  Rash                                                              333 (11)                
                                                                         387 (13)             
                                              
  Sweating                                                          145    (5)              
                                                                         177    (6)           
                                              
  Special Senses                                                                           
  Cataract Specified                                                182    (6)              
                                                                         213    (7)           
                                              
  Urogenital                                                                               
  Leukorrhea                                                        86    (3)               
                                                                         286   (9)            
                                              
  Urinary tract infection                                           244   (8)               
                                                                         313 (10)             
                                              
  Breast pain                                                       251    (8)              
                                                                         169    (6)           
                                              
  Breast Neoplasm                                                   164    (5)              
                                                                         139    (5)           
                                              
  Vulvovaginitis                                                    194   (6)               
                                                                         150    (5)           
                                              
  Vaginal HemorrhageVaginal Hemorrhage without further diagnosis.                            122    (4)              
                                                                         180    (6)           
                                              
  Vaginitis                                                         125    (4)              
                                                                         158    (5)           
                                              
         Certain adverse reactions and combinations of adverse reactions were prospectively specified for analysis, based on the known pharmacologic properties and side effect profiles of the two drugs (see Table 2).
 

 Table 2 - Number of Patients with Pre-specified Adverse Reactions in ATAC TrialPatients with multiple events in the same category are counted only once in that category. 
                                           ARIMIDEX    N=3092    (%)      Tamoxifen    N=3094    (%)      Odds-ratio      95% CI        
  
  Hot Flashes                                              1104 (36)        
                                                       1264 (41)        
                                      0.80           0.73 - 0.89    
  Musculoskeletal EventsRefers to joint symptoms, including joint disorder, arthritis, arthrosis and arthralgia.                     1100 (36)        
                                                       911 (29)         
                                      1.32           1.19 - 1.47    
  Fatigue/Asthenia                                         575 (19)         
                                                       544 (18)         
                                      1.07           0.94 - 1.22    
  Mood Disturbances                                        597 (19)         
                                                       554 (18)         
                                      1.10           0.97 - 1.25    
  Nausea and Vomiting                                      393 (13)         
                                                       384 (12)         
                                      1.03           0.88 - 1.19    
  All Fractures                                            315 (10)         
                                                       209   (7)        
                                      1.57           1.30 - 1.88    
  Fractures of Spine, Hip, or Wrist                        133   (4)        
                                                       91   (3)         
                                      1.48           1.13 - 1.95    
                                         Wrist/Colles' fractures                
                                                                                                   67   (2)         
                                                       50   (2)         
                                                                    
                                         Spine fractures                        
                                                                                                   43   (1)         
                                                       22   (1)         
                                                                    
                                         Hip fractures                          
                                                                                                   28   (1)         
                                                       26   (1)         
                                                                    
  Cataracts                                                182   (6)        
                                                       213   (7)        
                                      0.85           0.69 - 1.04    
  Vaginal Bleeding                                         167   (5)        
                                                       317 (10)         
                                      0.50           0.41 - 0.61    
  Ischemic Cardiovascular Disease                          127   (4)        
                                                       104   (3)        
                                      1.23           0.95 - 1.60    
  Vaginal Discharge                                        109   (4)        
                                                       408 (13)         
                                      0.24           0.19 - 0.30    
  Venous Thromboembolic events                             87   (3)         
                                                       140   (5)        
                                      0.61           0.47 - 0.80    
  Deep Venous Thromboembolic Events                        48   (2)         
                                                       74   (2)         
                                      0.64           0.45 - 0.93    
  Ischemic Cerebrovascular Event                           62   (2)         
                                                       88   (3)         
                                      0.70           0.50 - 0.97    
  Endometrial CancerPercentages calculated based upon the numbers of patients with an intact uterus at baseline                     4 (0.2)          
                                                       13 (0.6)         
                                      0.31           0.10 - 0.94    
             Ischemic Cardiovascular Events  
 

 Between treatment arms in the overall population of 6186 patients, there was no statistical difference in ischemic cardiovascular events (4% ARIMIDEX vs. 3% tamoxifen). In the overall population, angina pectoris was reported in 71/3092 (2.3%) patients in the ARIMIDEX arm and 51/3094 (1.6%) patients in the tamoxifen arm; myocardial infarction was reported in 37/3092 (1.2%) patients in the ARIMIDEX arm and 34/3094 (1.1%) patients in the tamoxifen arm.



 In women with pre-existing ischemic heart disease 465/6186 (7.5%), the incidence of ischemic cardiovascular events was 17% in patients on ARIMIDEX and 10% in patients on tamoxifen. In this patient population, angina pectoris was reported in 25/216 (11.6%) patients receiving ARIMIDEX and 13/249 (5.2%) patients receiving tamoxifen; myocardial infarction was reported in 2/216 (0.9%) patients receiving ARIMIDEX and 8/249 (3.2%) patients receiving tamoxifen.



   Bone Mineral Density Findings  



 Results from the ATAC trial bone substudy at 12 and 24 months demonstrated that patients receiving ARIMIDEX had a mean decrease in both lumbar spine and total hip bone mineral density (BMD) compared to baseline. Patients receiving tamoxifen had a mean increase in both lumbar spine and total hip BMD compared to baseline.



 Because ARIMIDEX lowers circulating estrogen levels it may cause a reduction in bone mineral density.



 A post-marketing trial assessed the combined effects of ARIMIDEX and the bisphosphonate risedronate on changes from baseline in BMD and markers of bone resorption and formation in postmenopausal women with hormone receptor-positive early breast cancer. All patients received calcium and vitamin D supplementation. At 12 months, small reductions in lumbar spine bone mineral density were noted in patients not receiving bisphosphonates. Bisphosphonate treatment preserved bone density in most patients at risk of fracture.



 Postmenopausal women with early breast cancer scheduled to be treated with ARIMIDEX should have their bone status managed according to treatment guidelines already available for postmenopausal women at similar risk of fragility fracture.



   Cholesterol  



 During the ATAC trial, more patients receiving ARIMIDEX were reported to have an elevated serum cholesterol compared to patients receiving tamoxifen (9% versus 3.5%, respectively).



 A post-marketing trial also evaluated any potential effects of ARIMIDEX on lipid profile. In the primary analysis population for lipids (ARIMIDEX alone), there was no clinically significant change in LDL-C from baseline to 12 months and HDL-C from baseline to 12 months.



 In secondary population for lipids (ARIMIDEX+risedronate), there also was no clinically significant change in LDL-C and HDL-C from baseline to 12 months.



 In both populations for lipids, there was no clinically significant difference in total cholesterol (TC) or serum triglycerides (TG) at 12 months compared with baseline.



 In this trial, treatment for 12 months with ARIMIDEX alone had a neutral effect on lipid profile. Combination treatment with ARIMIDEX and risedronate also had a neutral effect on lipid profile.



 The trial provides evidence that postmenopausal women with early breast cancer scheduled to be treated with ARIMIDEX should be managed using the current National Cholesterol Education Program guidelines for cardiovascular risk-based management of individual patients with LDL elevations.



   Other Adverse Reactions  



 Patients receiving ARIMIDEX had an increase in joint disorders (including arthritis, arthrosis and arthralgia) compared with patients receiving tamoxifen. Patients receiving ARIMIDEX had an increase in the incidence of all fractures (specifically fractures of spine, hip and wrist) [315 (10%)] compared with patients receiving tamoxifen [209 (7%)].



 Patients receiving ARIMIDEX had a higher incidence of carpal tunnel syndrome [78 (2.5%)] compared with patients receiving tamoxifen [22 (0.7%)].



 Vaginal bleeding occurred more frequently in the tamoxifen-treated patients versus the ARIMIDEX-treated patients 317 (10%) versus 167 (5%), respectively.



 Patients receiving ARIMIDEX had a lower incidence of hot flashes, vaginal bleeding, vaginal discharge, endometrial cancer, venous thromboembolic events and ischemic cerebrovascular events compared with patients receiving tamoxifen.



   10-year median follow-up Safety Results from the ATAC Trial  



 Results are consistent with the previous analyses.



 Serious adverse reactions were similar between ARIMIDEX (50%) and tamoxifen (51%).



 *    Cardiovascular events were consistent with the known safety profiles of ARIMIDEX and tamoxifen. 
 *    The cumulative incidences of all first fractures (both serious and non-serious, occurring either during or after treatment) was higher in the ARIMIDEX group (15%) compared to the tamoxifen group (11%). This increased first fracture rate during treatment did not continue in the post-treatment follow-up period. 
 *    The cumulative incidence of new primary cancers was similar in the ARIMIDEX group (13.7%) compared to the tamoxifen group (13.9%). Consistent with the previous analyses, endometrial cancer was higher in the tamoxifen group (0.8%) compared to the ARIMIDEX group (0.2%). 
 *    The overall number of deaths (during or off-trial treatment) was similar between the treatment groups. There were more deaths related to breast cancer in the tamoxifen than in the ARIMIDEX treatment group. 
      First-Line Therapy
   Adverse reactions occurring with an incidence of at least 5% in either treatment group of trials 0030 and 0027 during or within 2 weeks of the end of treatment are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3 - Adverse Reactions Occurring with an Incidence of at Least 5% in Trials 0030 and 0027 
   Body system    Adverse Reaction      Number (%) of subjects     
                                 ARIMIDEX    (N=506)      Tamoxifen    (N=511)     
  
  Whole body                                                      
  Asthenia                                      83 (16)         
                                                    81 (16)         
                                    
  Pain                                          70 (14)         
                                                    73 (14)         
                                    
  Back pain                                     60 (12)         
                                                    68 (13)         
                                    
  Headache                                      47   (9)        
                                                    40   (8)        
                                    
  Abdominal pain                                40   (8)        
                                                    38   (7)        
                                    
  Chest pain                                    37   (7)        
                                                    37   (7)        
                                    
  Flu syndrome                                  35   (7)        
                                                    30   (6)        
                                    
  Pelvic pain                                   23   (5)        
                                                    30   (6)        
                                    
  Cardiovascular                                                  
  Vasodilation                                  128 (25)        
                                                    106 (21)        
                                    
  Hypertension                                  25   (5)        
                                                    36   (7)        
                                    
  Digestive                                                       
  Nausea                                        94 (19)         
                                                    106 (21)        
                                    
  Constipation                                  47   (9)        
                                                    66 (13)         
                                    
  Diarrhea                                      40   (8)        
                                                    33   (6)        
                                    
  Vomiting                                      38   (8)        
                                                    36   (7)        
                                    
  Anorexia                                      26   (5)        
                                                    46   (9)        
                                    
  Metabolic and Nutritional                                       
  Peripheral edema                              51 (10)         
                                                    41   (8)        
                                    
  Musculoskeletal                                                 
  Bone pain                                     54  (11)        
                                                    52 (10)         
                                    
  Nervous                                                         
  Dizziness                                     30   (6)        
                                                    22   (4)        
                                    
  Insomnia                                      30   (6)        
                                                    38   (7)        
                                    
  Depression                                    23   (5)        
                                                    32   (6)        
                                    
  Hypertonia                                    16   (3)        
                                                    26   (5)        
                                    
  Respiratory                                                     
  Cough increased                               55 (11)         
                                                    52 (10)         
                                    
  Dyspnea                                       51 (10)         
                                                    47   (9)        
                                    
  Pharyngitis                                   49 (10)         
                                                    68 (13)         
                                    
  Skin and appendages                                             
  Rash                                          38   (8)        
                                                    34   (8)        
                                    
  Urogenital                                                      
  Leukorrhea                                    9   (2)         
                                                    31   (6)        
                                    
         Less frequent adverse experiences reported in patients receiving ARIMIDEX 1 mg in either Trial 0030 or Trial 0027 were similar to those reported for second-line therapy.
 

 Based on results from second-line therapy and the established safety profile of tamoxifen, the incidences of 9 pre-specified adverse event categories potentially causally related to one or both of the therapies because of their pharmacology were statistically analyzed. No significant differences were seen between treatment groups.



 Table 4 - Number of Patients with Pre-specified Adverse Reactions in Trials 0030 and 0027 
                                  Number (n) and Percentage of Patients     
   Adverse Reaction               ARIMIDEX    1 mg    (N=506)    n (%)      NOLVADEX    20 mg    (N=511)    n (%)     
  
  Depression                                          23   (5)             
                                                                      32   (6)                
                                                    
  Tumor Flare                                         15   (3)             
                                                                      18   (4)                
                                                    
  Thromboembolic DiseaseIncludes pulmonary embolus, thrombophlebitis, retinal vein thrombosis.                         18   (4)             
                                                                      33   (6)                
                                                    
  Venous                                              5                    
                                                                      15                      
                                                    
  Coronary and CerebralIncludes myocardial infarction, myocardial ischemia, angina pectoris, cerebrovascular accident, cerebral ischemia and cerebral infarct.                         13                   
                                                                      19                      
                                                    
  Gastrointestinal Disturbance                         170 (34)             
                                                                      196 (38)                
                                                    
  Hot Flushes                                         134 (26)             
                                                                      118 (23)                
                                                    
  Vaginal Dryness                                     9   (2)              
                                                                      3   (1)                 
                                                    
  Lethargy                                            6   (1)              
                                                                      15   (3)                
                                                    
  Vaginal Bleeding                                    5   (1)              
                                                                      11   (2)                
                                                    
  Weight Gain                                         11   (2)             
                                                                      8   (2)                 
                                                    
           Second-Line Therapy
   ARIMIDEX was tolerated in two controlled clinical trials (i.e., Trials 0004 and 0005), with less than 3.3% of the ARIMIDEX-treated patients and 4.0% of the megestrol acetate-treated patients withdrawing due to an adverse reaction.



 The principal adverse reaction more common with ARIMIDEX than megestrol acetate was diarrhea. Adverse reactions reported in greater than 5% of the patients in any of the treatment groups in these two controlled clinical trials, regardless of causality, are presented below:



 Table 5 - Number (N) and Percentage of Patients with Adverse Reactions in Trials 0004 and 0005 
   Adverse Reaction        ARIMIDEX      ARIMIDEX      Megestrol Acetate     
   1 mg                    10 mg      160 mg     
   (N=262)                 (N=246)      (N=253)     
   n                       %       n          %       n          %         
  
  Asthenia                42      (16)       33      (13)       47         (19)       
  Nausea                  41      (16)       48      (20)       28         (11)       
  Headache                34      (13)       44      (18)       24         (9)        
  Hot Flashes             32      (12)       29      (11)       21         (8)        
  Pain                    28      (11)       38      (15)       29         (11)       
  Back Pain               28      (11)       26      (11)       19         (8)        
  Dyspnea                 24      (9)        27      (11)       53         (21)       
  Vomiting                24      (9)        26      (11)       16         (6)        
  Cough Increased         22      (8)        18      (7)        19         (8)        
  Diarrhea                22      (8)        18      (7)        7          (3)        
  Constipation            18      (7)        18      (7)        21         (8)        
  Abdominal Pain          18      (7)        14      (6)        18         (7)        
  Anorexia                18      (7)        19      (8)        11         (4)        
  Bone Pain               17      (6)        26      (12)       19         (8)        
  Pharyngitis             16      (6)        23      (9)        15         (6)        
  Dizziness               16      (6)        12      (5)        15         (6)        
  Rash                    15      (6)        15      (6)        19         (8)        
  Dry Mouth               15      (6)        11      (4)        13         (5)        
  Peripheral Edema        14      (5)        21      (9)        28         (11)       
  Pelvic Pain             14      (5)        17      (7)        13         (5)        
  Depression              14      (5)        6       (2)        5          (2)        
  Chest Pain              13      (5)        18      (7)        13         (5)        
  Paresthesia             12      (5)        15      (6)        9          (4)        
  Vaginal Hemorrhage      6       (2)        4       (2)        13         (5)        
  Weight Gain             4       (2)        9       (4)        30         (12)       
  Sweating                4       (2)        3       (1)        16         (6)        
  Increased Appetite      0       (0)        1       (0)        13         (5)        
             Other less frequent (2% to 5%) adverse reactions reported in patients receiving ARIMIDEX 1 mg in either Trial 0004 or Trial 0005 are listed below. These adverse experiences are listed by body system and are in order of decreasing frequency within each body system regardless of assessed causality.
 

   Body as a Whole:  Flu syndrome; fever; neck pain; malaise; accidental injury; infection



   Cardiovascular:  Hypertension; thrombophlebitis



   Hepatic:  Gamma GT increased; SGOT increased; SGPT increased



   Hematologic:  Anemia; leukopenia



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Alkaline phosphatase increased; weight loss



 Mean serum total cholesterol levels increased by 0.5 mmol/L among patients receiving ARIMIDEX. Increases in LDL cholesterol have been shown to contribute to these changes.



   Musculoskeletal:  Myalgia; arthralgia; pathological fracture



   Nervous:  Somnolence; confusion; insomnia; anxiety; nervousness



   Respiratory:  Sinusitis; bronchitis; rhinitis



   Skin and Appendages:   Hair thinning (alopecia); pruritus



   Urogenital:  Urinary tract infection; breast pain



 The incidences of the following adverse reaction groups potentially causally related to one or both of the therapies because of their pharmacology, were statistically analyzed: weight gain, edema, thromboembolic disease, gastrointestinal disturbance, hot flushes, and vaginal dryness. These six groups, and the adverse reactions captured in the groups, were prospectively defined. The results are shown in the table below.



 Table 6 - Number (n) and Percentage of Patients with Pre-specified Adverse Reactions in Trials 0004 and 0005 
                                  ARIMIDEX      ARIMIDEX      Megestrol Acetate     
   1 mg                           10 mg      160 mg     
   (N=262)                        (N=246)      (N=253)     
   Adverse Reaction Group         n       (%)       n       (%)       n          (%)          
  
  Gastrointestinal Disturbance    77      (29)      81      (33)      54         (21)          
  Hot Flushes                    33      (13)      29      (12)      35         (14)          
  Edema                          19      (7)       28      (11)      35         (14)          
  Thromboembolic Disease         9       (3)       4       (2)       12         (5)           
  Vaginal Dryness                5       (2)       3       (1)       2          (1)           
  Weight Gain                    4       (2)       10      (4)       30         (12)          
               6.2 Post-Marketing Experience
   These adverse reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size. Therefore, it is not always possible to estimate reliably their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The following have been reported in post-approval use of Arimidex:



 *    Hepatobiliary events including increases in alkaline phosphatase, alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, gamma-GT, and bilirubin; hepatitis 
 *    Rash including cases of mucocutaneous disorders such as erythema multiforme and Stevens-Johnson syndrome 
 *    *    Myalgia, trigger finger and hypercalcemia (with or without an increase in parathyroid hormone) 
   Cases of allergic reactions including angioedema, urticaria and anaphylaxis [see   Contraindications (4.2)   ] 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    In women with pre-existing ischemic heart disease, an increased incidence of ischemic cardiovascular events occurred with ARIMIDEX use compared to tamoxifen use. Consider risks and benefits. (  5.1  ,  6.1  ) 
 *    Decreases in bone mineral density may occur. Consider bone mineral density monitoring. (  5.2  ,  6.1  ) 
 *    Increases in total cholesterol may occur. Consider cholesterol monitoring. (  5.3  ,  6.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Ischemic Cardiovascular Events



  In women with pre-existing ischemic heart disease, an increased incidence of ischemic cardiovascular events was observed with ARIMIDEX in the ATAC trial (17% of patients on ARIMIDEX and 10% of patients on tamoxifen). Consider risk and benefits of ARIMIDEX therapy in patients with pre-existing ischemic heart disease [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.2 Bone Effects



  Results from the ATAC trial bone substudy at 12 and 24 months demonstrated that patients receiving ARIMIDEX had a mean decrease in both lumbar spine and total hip bone mineral density (BMD) compared to baseline. Patients receiving tamoxifen had a mean increase in both lumbar spine and total hip BMD compared to baseline. Consider bone mineral density monitoring in patients treated with ARIMIDEX [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.3 Cholesterol



  During the ATAC trial, more patients receiving ARIMIDEX were reported to have elevated serum cholesterol compared to patients receiving tamoxifen (9% versus 3.5%, respectively) [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
