<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aristada" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more details in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-related Psychosis [see   Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke [see   Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Tardive Dyskinesia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Metabolic Changes [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Body Temperature Regulation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Dysphagia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most commonly observed adverse reaction with ARISTADA (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice that for placebo) was akathisia (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Alkermes, Inc. at 1-866-274-7823 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1. Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     ARISTADA  



     Patient Exposure  



 ARISTADA has been evaluated for safety in 880 adult patients in clinical trials in schizophrenia.



     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions  



 The most common adverse reaction (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice the rate of placebo in patients treated with ARISTADA) was akathisia.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More in ARISTADA-Treated Patients  



 Adverse reactions associated with the use of ARISTADA (incidence of 2% or greater, rounded to the nearest percent and ARISTADA incidence greater than placebo) that occurred are shown in  Table 8  .



 Table 8: Adverse Reaction in 2% or More of ARISTADA-Treated Patients and That Occurred at Greater Incidence than in the Placebo-Treated Patients in the 12-Week, Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose Schizophrenia Trial 
   Adverse Reaction System Organ Class           Preferred Term      PlaceboN=207(%)      Aripiprazole Lauroxil     
   441 mgN=207(%)                                         882 mgN=208(%)     
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
        Injection site pain                             2                3                4                 
   Investigations                                        
        Increased weight                                1                2                2                 
        Increased blood creatine phosphokinase          0                2                1                 
   Nervous system disorders                              
        Akathisia                                       4                11               11                
        Headache                                        3                3                5                 
   Psychiatric disorders                                 
        Insomnia                                        2                3                4                 
        Restlessness                                    1                3                1                 
              Injection Site Reactions  
 

 Injection site reactions were reported by 4% of patients treated with 441 mg ARISTADA and 5% of patients treated with 882 mg ARISTADA compared to 2% of patients treated with placebo. Most of these were injection site pain (3%, 4% and 2% in the 441 mg ARISTADA, 882 mg ARISTADA and placebo groups, respectively) and most were associated with the first injection, and decreased with each subsequent injection to less than or equal to 1% for both doses of ARISTADA and placebo. Other injection site reactions (induration, swelling and redness) occurred at less than 1%.



     Extrapyramidal Symptoms  



 In the 12-week schizophrenia efficacy study  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  , for ARISTADA-treated patients, the incidence of other EPS-related events, excluding akathisia and restlessness, was 5% and 7% for patients on 441 mg and 882 mg, respectively, versus 4% for placebo-treated patient (  Table 9  ).



 Table 9: Incidence of EPS Compared to Placebo 
                                                               ARISTADA               
  
   Adverse Reaction Term                   Placebo    N=207    (%)      441 mg    N=207    (%)      882 mg    N=208    (%)     
   Akathisia                             4                     11                    11                     
   Restlessness                          1                     3                     1                      
   Other EPS                             4                     5                     7                      
        Dystonia                         1                     2                     2                      
        Parkinsonism                     3                     3                     4                      
              Dystonia  
 

 Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed in Clinical Studies  



 The following listing does not include reactions: 1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, 2) for which a drug cause was remote, 3) which were so general as to be uninformative, 4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or 5) which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo.



   Cardiac  - angina pectoris, tachycardia, palpitations



   Gastrointestinal disorders -  constipation, dry mouth



   General disorders  - asthenia



   Musculoskeletal  - muscular weakness



   Nervous system disorders -  dizziness



   Psychiatric disorders -  anxiety, suicide



     Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with Oral Aripiprazole  



 The following is a list of additional adverse reactions that have been reported in clinical trials with oral aripiprazole and not reported above for ARISTADA.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  thrombocytopenia



   Cardiac Disorders:  bradycardia, atrial flutter, cardiorespiratory arrest, atrioventricular block, atrial fibrillation, myocardial ischemia, myocardial infarction, cardiopulmonary failure



   Eye Disorders:  photophobia, diplopia



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  gastroesophageal reflux disease



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  peripheral edema, chest pain, face edema



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  hepatitis, jaundice



   Immune System Disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications:  fall, heat stroke



   Investigations:  weight decreased, hepatic enzyme increased, blood glucose increased, blood lactate dehydrogenase increased, gamma glutamyl transferase increased, blood prolactin increased, blood urea increased, blood creatinine increased, blood bilirubin increased, electrocardiogram QT prolonged, glycosylated hemoglobin increased



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  anorexia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypoglycemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  muscle tightness, rhabdomyolysis, mobility decreased



   Nervous System Disorders:  memory impairment, cogwheel rigidity, hypokinesia, myoclonus, bradykinesia, akinesia, myoclonus, coordination abnormal, speech disorder, choreoathetosis



   Psychiatric Disorders:  aggression, loss of libido, delirium, libido increased, anorgasmia, tic, homicidal ideation, catatonia, sleep walking



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  urinary retention, nocturia



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  erectile dysfunction, gynaecomastia, menstruation irregular, amenorrhea, breast pain, priapism



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  nasal congestion, dyspnea



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  rash, hyperhidrosis, pruritus, photosensitivity reaction, alopecia, urticaria



   Vascular Disorders:  hypotension, hypertension



   6.2. Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of oral aripiprazole. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: occurrences of allergic reaction (anaphylactic reaction, angioedema, laryngospasm, pruritus/urticaria, or oropharyngeal spasm), and blood glucose fluctuation.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



  WARNING:  INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. ARISTADA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [    see Warnings and Precautions

    (  5.1  )].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:  INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. (5.1) 
 *  ARISTADA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (e.g., stroke, transient ischemia attack, including fatalities) (  5.2  ). 
 *   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome : Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring (  5.3  ). 
 *   Tardive Dyskinesia : Discontinue if clinically appropriate (  5.4  ). 
 *   Metabolic Changes : Monitor for hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and weight gain (  5.5  ). 
 *   Orthostatic Hypotension : Monitor heart rate and blood pressure and warn patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease, and risk of dehydration or syncope (  5.6  ). 
 *   Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis : Perform complete blood counts in patients with a history of a clinically significant low white blood cell (WBC) count. Consider discontinuation if clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors (  5.7  ). 
 *   Seizures : Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold (  5.8  ). 
 *   Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment : Use caution when operating machinery (  5.9  ). 
    
 

   5.1. Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-related Psychosis



  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group.



 Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. ARISTADA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].  



    5.2. Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke



  In placebo-controlled trials with risperidone, aripiprazole, and olanzapine in elderly patients with dementia, there was a higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (cerebrovascular accidents and transient ischemic attacks) including fatalities compared to placebo-treated patients. ARISTADA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see   Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



    5.3. Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) may occur in association with antipsychotic drugs, including ARISTADA. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to identify cases in which the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: (1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and (3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for uncomplicated NMS.



 If a patient appears to require antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, reintroduction of drug therapy should be closely monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4. Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to predict which patients will develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible appear to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase, but the syndrome can develop after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses, although this is uncommon.



 There is no known treatment for established tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment itself may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and may thus mask the underlying process. The effect of symptomatic suppression on the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, ARISTADA should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient treated with ARISTADA drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with ARISTADA despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.5. Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that include hyperglycemia/diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, and weight gain. While all drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



    Hyperglycemia/ Diabetes Mellitus  



 Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. There have been reports of hyperglycemia in patients treated with oral aripiprazole. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse events is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients require continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



 In the long-term, open-label schizophrenia study with ARISTADA, 14% of patients with normal hemoglobin A1c (&lt;5.7%) at baseline developed elevated levels (&gt;=5.7%) post-baseline.



    Dyslipidemia  



 Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics.



 In the long-term, open-label schizophrenia study with ARISTADA, shifts in baseline fasting total cholesterol from normal (&lt;200 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=240 mg/dL) were reported in 1% of patients; shifts in baseline fasting LDL cholesterol from normal (&lt;100 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=160 mg/dL) were reported in 1% of patients; and shifts in baseline fasting triglycerides from normal (&lt;150 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=200 mg/dL) were reported in 8% of patients. In the same study, shifts in baseline fasting total cholesterol from borderline (&gt;= 200 mg/dL and &lt;240 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=240 mg/dL) were reported in 15% of patients; shifts in baseline fasting LDL cholesterol from borderline (&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;160 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=160 mg/dL) were reported in 8% of patients; and shifts in baseline fasting triglycerides from borderline (&gt;=150 mg/dL and &lt;200 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=200 mg/dL) were reported in 35% of patients. In addition, the proportion of patients with shifts in fasting HDL cholesterol from normal (&gt;=40 mg/dL) to low (&lt;40 mg/dL) was reported in 15% of patients.



    Weight Gain  



 Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Clinical monitoring of weight is recommended.



 The proportion of adult patients with weight gain &gt;=7% of body weight is presented in  Table 7  .



 Table 7: Proportion of Adult Patients with Shifts in Weight in the 12-Week, Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose Schizophrenia Trial 
                                              PlaceboN = 207(%)   ARISTADA             
 441 mgN = 207(%)                             882 mgN = 208(%)     
  
  Weight Gain                                                                                              
 &gt;=7% increase from baseline                  6                   10                  9                    
             5.6. Orthostatic Hypotension
 

  Aripiprazole may cause orthostatic hypotension, perhaps due to its alpha1-adrenergic receptor antagonism. Associated adverse reactions related to orthostatic hypotension can include dizziness, lightheadedness and tachycardia. Generally, these risks are greatest at the beginning of treatment and during dose escalation. Patients at increased risk of these adverse reactions or at increased risk of developing complications from hypotension include those with dehydration, hypovolemia, treatment with antihypertensive medication, history of cardiovascular disease (e.g., heart failure, myocardial infarction, ischemia, or conduction abnormalities), history of cerebrovascular disease, as well as patients who are antipsychotic-naive. In such patients, consider using a lower starting dose, and monitor orthostatic vital signs.



 Orthostatic hypotension was reported for one patient in the ARISTADA 882 mg group (0.5%) and no patients in the ARISTADA 441 mg and placebo groups in the 12-week schizophrenia efficacy study [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  . In the long-term open-label schizophrenia study, orthostatic hypotension was reported for 1 (0.2%) patient treated with ARISTADA. Orthostatic hypotension was defined as a decrease in systolic blood pressure &gt;=20 mmHg accompanied by an increase in heart rate &gt;=25 bpm when comparing standing to supine values.



    5.7. Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



  In clinical trials and/or postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia and neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents. Agranulocytosis has also been reported.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC)/absolute neutrophil count (ANC) and history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. In patients with a history of a clinically significant low WBC/ANC or drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia, perform a complete blood count (CBC) frequently during the first few months of therapy. In such patients, consider discontinuation of ARISTADA at the first sign of a clinical significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Monitor patients with clinically significant neutropenia for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treat promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Discontinue ARISTADA in patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm  3  ) and follow their WBC until recovery.



    5.8. Seizures



  As with other antipsychotic drugs, use ARISTADA cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in a population of 65 years or older.



    5.9. Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  ARISTADA, like other antipsychotics, has the potential to impair judgment, thinking or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that therapy with ARISTADA does not affect them adversely.



    5.10. Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing ARISTADA for patients who will be experiencing conditions which may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, (e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration).



    5.11. Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. ARISTADA and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
