<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="arnuity" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic and local corticosteroid use may result in the following:



 *     Candida albicans infection [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Immunosuppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *    Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
 *    Reduction in BMD [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)]  
 *    Growth effects in pediatrics [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)]  
 *    Glaucoma and cataracts [see Warnings and Precautions (5.11)]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (reported in greater than or equal to 5% of subjects) are:
 

 *    upper respiratory tract infection, nasopharyngitis, headache, and bronchitis. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of ARNUITY ELLIPTA was evaluated in 10 double-blind, parallel-group, controlled trials (7 with placebo) of 8 to 76 weeks' duration, which enrolled 6,219 subjects with asthma. Doses of fluticasone furoate studied ranged from 25 to 800 mcg.



 ARNUITY ELLIPTA 100 mcg was studied in 1,663 subjects, and ARNUITY ELLIPTA 200 mcg was studied in 608 subjects. Subject ages ranged from 12 to 84 years, 65% were female, and 75% were Caucasian.



 In these trials, the proportion of subjects who discontinued study treatment early due to adverse reactions was 2% for subjects treated with both ARNUITY ELLIPTA 100 mcg and ARNUITY ELLIPTA 200 mcg and less than or equal to 1% for placebo-treated subjects. Serious adverse events, whether considered drug-related or not by the investigators, that occurred in more than 1 subject and in a greater percentage of subjects treated with ARNUITY ELLIPTA than placebo included hypertension, abscess, breast cancer, traumatic limb amputation, subarachnoid hemorrhage, and intervertebral disc protrusion; all events occurred at rates less than or equal to 1%.



 The incidence of adverse reactions associated with ARNUITY ELLIPTA 100 mcg is shown in Table 1 and is based on one 24-week trial (Trial 1) in adolescent and adult subjects with asthma.



   Table 1. Adverse Reactions with ARNUITY ELLIPTA 100 mcg with Greater than or Equal to 3% Incidence and More Common than Placebo (Trial 1, Intent-to-Treat Population)  




                                                     Adverse Reaction                                 
                                                                                                        ARNUITY ELLIPTA 100 mcg  n = 114  %    Placebo  n = 115  %    
  Nasopharyngitis                                    8                                     5                
  Bronchitis                                         7                                     6                
  Upper respiratory tract infection                  6                                     5                
  Headache                                           6                                     4                
  Pharyngitis                                        4                                     3                
  Sinusitis                                          4                                     &lt;1               
  Toothache                                          3                                     &lt;1               
  Gastroenteritis viral                              3                                     0                
  Oral candidiasis                                   3                                     0                
  Oropharyngeal candidiasis                          3                                     0                
  Oropharyngeal pain                                 3                                     0                
         The incidence of adverse reactions associated with ARNUITY ELLIPTA 200 mcg is shown in Table 2 and is based on one 24-week trial (Trial 3) in adolescent and adult subjects with asthma. This trial did not have a placebo arm.
 

   Table 2. Adverse Reactions with ARNUITY ELLIPTA 200 mcg with Greater than or Equal to 3% Incidence (Trial 3, Safety Population)  




  Adverse Reaction                         ARNUITY ELLIPTA 200 mcg  n = 119  %    ARNUITY ELLIPTA 100 mcg  n = 119  %    
  Nasopharyngitis                          13                              12                              
  Headache                                 13                              10                              
  Bronchitis                               7                               12                              
  Influenza                                7                               4                               
  Upper respiratory tract infection        6                               2                               
  Sinusitis                                4                               7                               
  Oropharyngeal pain                       4                               3                               
  Pharyngitis                              3                               6                               
  Back pain                                3                               3                               
  Dysphonia                                3                               2                               
  Oral candidiasis                         3                               &lt;1                              
  Procedural pain                          3                               &lt;1                              
  Rhinitis                                 3                               &lt;1                              
  Throat irritation                        3                               &lt;1                              
  Abdominal pain                           3                               0                               
  Cough                                    3                               0                               
         Adverse reactions observed in the other trials were consistent with those described in Tables 1 and 2.
 

   Long-Term Safety:  Long-term safety data are based on 2 trials in adolescent and adult subjects with asthma. In one 52-week trial, subjects received fluticasone furoate 100 mcg (n = 201) or fluticasone furoate 200 mcg (n = 202) in combination with a LABA. Subjects had a mean age of 39 years (adolescents made up 16% of the population), 63% were female, and 67% were Caucasian. In addition to the events shown in Table 1 and Table 2, adverse events occurring in greater than or equal to 3% of the subjects treated with fluticasone furoate 100 mcg or fluticasone furoate 200 mcg, in combination with a LABA, included pyrexia, extrasystoles, upper abdominal pain, respiratory tract infection, diarrhea, and allergic rhinitis.



 In a second 24- to 76-week trial, subjects received fluticasone furoate 100 mcg (n = 1,010). Subjects participating in this trial had a history of one or more asthma exacerbations that required treatment with oral/systemic corticosteroids or emergency department visit or in-patient hospitalization for the treatment of asthma within the previous 12 months. Subjects had a mean age of 42 years (adolescents made up 14% of the population), 67% were female, and 73% were Caucasian. In addition to the events shown in Table 1 and Table 2, adverse events occurring in greater than or equal to 3% of subjects treated with fluticasone furoate 100 mcg for up to 76 weeks included allergic rhinitis, nasal congestion, and arthralgia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Localized infections: Candida albicans infection of the mouth and throat may occur. Monitor patients periodically. Advise the patient to rinse his/her mouth with water without swallowing after inhalation.  (5.1)   
 *    Deterioration of asthma and acute episodes: Do not use for relief of acute symptoms. Patients require immediate re-evaluation during rapidly deteriorating asthma.  (5.2)   
 *    Immunosuppression: Potential worsening of existing tuberculosis, fungal, bacterial, viral, parasitic infections or ocular herpes simplex. Use with caution in patients with these infections. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles can occur in susceptible patients.  (5.3)   
 *    Transferring patients from systemic corticosteroids: Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring from systemic corticosteroids. Wean patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to ARNUITY ELLIPTA.  (5.4)   
 *    Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: May occur with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals. If such changes occur, discontinue ARNUITY ELLIPTA slowly.  (5.5)   
 *    Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue ARNUITY ELLIPTA and institute alternative therapy if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs.  (5.7)   
 *    Decreases in bone mineral density: Monitor patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content.  (5.9)   
 *    Monitor growth of adolescent patients.  (5.10)   
 *    Close monitoring for glaucoma and cataracts is warranted.  (5.11)   
    
 

   5.1 Local Effects of Inhaled Corticosteroids



  In clinical trials, the development of localized infections of the mouth and pharynx with Candida albicans  has occurred in subjects treated with ARNUITY ELLIPTA. When such an infection develops, it should be treated with appropriate local or systemic (i.e., oral) antifungal therapy while treatment with ARNUITY ELLIPTA continues, but at times therapy with ARNUITY ELLIPTA may need to be interrupted. Advise the patient to rinse his/her mouth with water without swallowing following inhalation to help reduce the risk of oropharyngeal candidiasis.



    5.2 Acute Asthma Episodes



  ARNUITY ELLIPTA is not indicated for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm. An inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist, not ARNUITY ELLIPTA, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath. When prescribing ARNUITY ELLIPTA, the physician must provide the patient with an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist (e.g., albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms, despite regular once-daily use of ARNUITY ELLIPTA. Instruct patients to contact their physicians immediately if episodes of asthma not responsive to bronchodilators occur during the course of treatment with ARNUITY ELLIPTA. During such episodes, patients may require therapy with oral corticosteroids.



    5.3 Immunosuppression



  Persons using drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infections than healthy individuals.



 Chickenpox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible children or adults using corticosteroids. In such patients who have not had these diseases or who have not been properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If a patient is exposed to chickenpox, prophylaxis with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) may be indicated. If a patient is exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See the respective package inserts for complete VZIG and IG prescribing information.) If chickenpox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.



 Inhaled corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infections of the respiratory tract; untreated systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infections; or ocular herpes simplex.



    5.4 Transferring Patients from Systemic Corticosteroid Therapy



  Particular care is needed for patients who are transferred from systemically active corticosteroids to inhaled corticosteroids because deaths due to adrenal insufficiency have occurred in patients with asthma during and after transfer from systemic corticosteroids to less systemically available inhaled corticosteroids. After withdrawal from systemic corticosteroids, a number of months are required for recovery of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) function.



 Patients who have been previously maintained on 20 mg or more of prednisone (or its equivalent) may be most susceptible, particularly when their systemic corticosteroids have been almost completely withdrawn. During this period of HPA suppression, patients may exhibit signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency when exposed to trauma, surgery, or infection (particularly gastroenteritis) or other conditions associated with severe electrolyte loss. Although ARNUITY ELLIPTA may improve control of asthma symptoms during these episodes, in recommended doses it supplies less than normal physiological amounts of corticosteroid systemically and does NOT provide the mineralocorticoid activity that is necessary for coping with these emergencies.



 During periods of stress or a severe asthma attack, patients who have been withdrawn from systemic corticosteroids should be instructed to resume oral corticosteroids (in large doses) immediately and to contact their physicians for further instruction. These patients should also be instructed to carry a medical identification warning card indicating that they may need supplementary systemic corticosteroids during periods of stress or a severe asthma attack.



 Patients requiring systemic corticosteroids should be weaned slowly from systemic corticosteroid use after transferring to ARNUITY ELLIPTA. Lung function (forced expiratory volume in 1 second [FEV1] or morning peak expiratory flow [AM PEF]), beta-agonist use, and asthma symptoms should be carefully monitored during withdrawal of systemic corticosteroids. In addition to monitoring asthma signs and symptoms, patients should be observed for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency, such as fatigue, lassitude, weakness, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension.



 Transfer of patients from systemic corticosteroid therapy to ARNUITY ELLIPTA may unmask allergic conditions previously suppressed by the systemic corticosteroid therapy (e.g., rhinitis, conjunctivitis, eczema, arthritis, eosinophilic conditions).



 During withdrawal from oral corticosteroids, some patients may experience symptoms of systemically active corticosteroid withdrawal (e.g., joint and/or muscular pain, lassitude, depression), despite maintenance or even improvement of respiratory function.



    5.5 Hypercorticism and Adrenal Suppression



  ARNUITY ELLIPTA will often help control asthma symptoms with less suppression of HPA function than therapeutically equivalent oral doses of prednisone. Since ARNUITY ELLIPTA is absorbed into the circulation and can be systemically active at higher doses, the beneficial effects of ARNUITY ELLIPTA in minimizing HPA dysfunction may be expected only when recommended dosages are not exceeded and individual patients are titrated to the lowest effective dose.



 Because of the possibility of significant systemic absorption of inhaled corticosteroids, patients treated with ARNUITY ELLIPTA should be observed carefully for any evidence of systemic corticosteroid effects. Particular care should be taken in observing patients postoperatively or during periods of stress for evidence of inadequate adrenal response.



 It is possible that systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression (including adrenal crisis) may appear in a small number of patients, particularly when fluticasone furoate is administered at higher than recommended doses over prolonged periods of time. If such effects occur, the dosage of ARNUITY ELLIPTA should be reduced slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for reducing systemic corticosteroids and for management of asthma symptoms.



    5.6 Drug Interactions with Strong Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors



  Caution should be exercised when considering the coadministration of ARNUITY ELLIPTA with long-term ketoconazole and other known strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, clarithromycin, conivaptan, indinavir, itraconazole, lopinavir, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin, troleandomycin, voriconazole) because increased systemic corticosteroid adverse effects may occur [see Drug Interactions (7.1), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  .



    5.7 Paradoxical Bronchospasm and Upper Airway Symptoms



  As with other inhaled medicines, bronchospasm may occur with an immediate increase in wheezing after dosing. If bronchospasm occurs following dosing with ARNUITY ELLIPTA, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator; ARNUITY ELLIPTA should be discontinued immediately; and alternative therapy should be instituted.



    5.8 Hypersensitivity Reactions, Including Anaphylaxis



  Hypersensitivity reactions such as urticaria, flushing, allergic dermatitis, and bronchospasm may occur after administration of ARNUITY ELLIPTA. Discontinue ARNUITY ELLIPTA if such reactions occur. There have been reports of anaphylactic reactions in patients with severe milk protein allergy after inhalation of other powder products containing lactose; therefore, patients with severe milk protein allergy should not use ARNUITY ELLIPTA [see Contraindications (4.2)]  .



    5.9 Reduction in Bone Mineral Density



  Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) have been observed with long-term administration of products containing inhaled corticosteroids. The clinical significance of small changes in BMD with regard to long-term outcomes, such as fracture, is unknown. Patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content, such as prolonged immobilization, family history of osteoporosis, or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass (e.g., anticonvulsants, oral corticosteroids), should be monitored and treated with established standards of care.



    5.10 Effect on Growth



  Orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ARNUITY ELLIPTA, may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to children and adolescents. Monitor the growth of children and adolescents receiving ARNUITY ELLIPTA routinely (e.g., via stadiometry). To minimize the systemic effects of orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ARNUITY ELLIPTA, titrate each patient's dose to the lowest dosage that effectively controls his/her symptoms [see Use in Specific Populations (8.4)]  .



    5.11 Glaucoma and Cataracts



  Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure, and cataracts have been reported in patients following the long-term administration of inhaled corticosteroids. Therefore, close monitoring is warranted in patients with a change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and/or cataracts.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
