<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="arranon" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *    Neurologic [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Hematologic [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Hyperuricemia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common (&gt;= 20%) adverse reactions were:
 

 *    Adult: anemia, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, constipation, fatigue, pyrexia, cough, and dyspnea (  6.1  ) 
 *    Pediatric: anemia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and leukopenia (  6.1  ) 
    The most common (&gt;10%) neurological adverse reactions were:
 

 *    Adult: somnolence, dizziness, peripheral neurologic disorders, hypoesthesia, headache, and paresthesia (  6.1  ) 
 *    Pediatric: headache and peripheral neurologic disorders (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 ARRANON was studied in 459 patients in Phase I and Phase II clinical trials.



   Adults:  The safety profile of ARRANON is based on data from 103 adult patients treated with the recommended dose and schedule in 2 studies: an adult T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL)/T-cell lymphoblastic lymphoma (T-LBL) trial and an adult chronic lymphocytic leukemia trial.



 The most common adverse reactions in adults, regardless of causality, were fatigue; gastrointestinal (GI) disorders (nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, and constipation); hematologic disorders (anemia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia); respiratory disorders (cough and dyspnea); nervous system disorders (somnolence and dizziness); and pyrexia.



 The most common adverse reactions in adults, by System Organ Class, regardless of causality, including severe or life-threatening adverse reactions (NCI Common Toxicity Criteria Grade 3 or Grade 4) and fatal adverse reactions (Grade 5) are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1. Most Commonly Reported (&gt;=5% Overall) Adverse Reactions Regardless of Causality in Adult Patients Treated with 1,500 mg/m2 of ARRANON Administered Intravenously over 2 Hours on Days 1, 3, and 5 Repeated Every 21 Days 
  System Organ Class     Preferred Term    Percentage of Patients (N = 103)    
  Toxicity Grade                           
  Grade 3  %                               Grade 4 and 5a  %    All Grades  %               
  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders     
     Anemia                                20                14                          99                    
     Thrombocytopenia                      37                22                          86                    
     Neutropenia                           14                49                          81                    
     Febrile neutropenia                   9                 1                           12                    
  Cardiac Disorders                        
     Sinus tachycardia                     1                 0                           8                     
  Gastrointestinal Disorders               
     Nausea                                0                 0                           41                    
     Diarrhea                              1                 0                           22                    
     Vomiting                              1                 0                           22                    
     Constipation                          1                 0                           21                    
     Abdominal pain                        1                 0                           9                     
     Stomatitis                            1                 0                           8                     
     Abdominal distension                  0                 0                           6                     
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    
     Fatigue                               10                2                           50                    
     Pyrexia                               5                 0                           23                    
     Asthenia                              0                 1                           17                    
     Edema, peripheral                     0                 0                           15                    
     Edema                                 0                 0                           11                    
     Pain                                  3                 0                           11                    
     Rigors                                0                 0                           8                     
     Gait, abnormal                        0                 0                           6                     
     Chest pain                            0                 0                           5                     
     Non-cardiac chest pain                0                 1                           5                     
  Infections                               
     Infection                             2                 1                           9                     
     Pneumonia                             4                 1                           8                     
     Sinusitis                             1                 0                           7                     
  Hepatobiliary Disorders                  
     AST increased                         1                 1                           6                     
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders       
     Anorexia                              0                 0                           9                     
     Dehydration                           3                 1                           7                     
     Hyperglycemia                         1                 0                           6                     
  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    
     Myalgia                               1                 0                           13                    
     Arthralgia                            1                 0                           9                     
     Back pain                             0                 0                           8                     
     Muscular weakness                     5                 0                           8                     
     Pain in extremity                     1                 0                           7                     
  Nervous System Disorders (see Table 2)    
  Psychiatric Disorders                    
     Confusional state                     2                 0                           8                     
     Insomnia                              0                 0                           7                     
     Depression                            1                 0                           6                     
  Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders    
     Cough                                 0                 0                           25                    
     Dyspnea                               4                 2                           20                    
     Pleural effusion                      5                 1                           10                    
     Epistaxis                             0                 0                           8                     
     Dyspnea, exertional                   0                 0                           7                     
     Wheezing                              0                 0                           5                     
  Vascular Disorders                       
     Petechiae                             2                 0                           12                    
     Hypotension                           1                 1                           8                     
            a  Five patients had a fatal adverse reaction. Fatal adverse reactions included hypotension (n = 1), respiratory arrest (n = 1), pleural effusion/pneumothorax (n = 1), pneumonia (n = 1), and cerebral hemorrhage/coma/leukoencephalopathy (n = 1).
 

   Other Adverse Events:  Blurred vision was also reported in 4% of adult patients.



 There was a single report of biopsy-confirmed progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy in the adult patient population.



   Neurologic Adverse Reactions:  Nervous system adverse reactions, regardless of drug relationship, were reported for 76% of adult patients across the Phase I and Phase II trials. The most common neurologic adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) in adult patients, regardless of causality, including all grades (NCI Common Toxicity Criteria) are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2. Neurologic Adverse Reactions (&gt;=2%) Regardless of Causality in Adult Patients Treated with 1,500 mg/m2 of ARRANON Administered Intravenously over 2 Hours on Days 1, 3, and 5 Repeated Every 21 Days 
  Nervous System Disorders     Preferred Term        Percentage of Patients (N =103)    
  Grade 1  %                                         Grade 2  %    Grade 3  %    Grade 4  %    All Grades  %    
  Somnolence                                         20          3           0           0           23            
  Dizziness                                          14          8           0           0           21            
  Peripheral neurologic disorders, any adverse reaction    8           12          2           0           21            
     Neuropathy                                      0           4           0           0           4             
     Peripheral neuropathy                           2           2           1           0           5             
     Peripheral motor neuropathy                     3           3           1           0           7             
     Peripheral sensory neuropathy                   7           6           0           0           13            
  Hypoesthesia                                       5           10          2           0           17            
  Headache                                           11          3           1           0           15            
  Paresthesia                                        11          4           0           0           15            
  Ataxia                                             1           6           2           0           9             
  Depressed level of consciousness                   4           1           0           1           6             
  Tremor                                             2           3           0           0           5             
  Amnesia                                            2           1           0           0           3             
  Dysgeusia                                          2           1           0           0           3             
  Balance disorder                                   1           1           0           0           2             
  Sensory loss                                       0           2           0           0           2             
            One patient had a fatal neurologic adverse reaction, cerebral hemorrhage/coma/leukoencephalopathy.
 

 Most nervous system adverse reactions in the adult patients were evaluated as Grade 1 or 2. The additional Grade 3 adverse reactions in adult patients, regardless of causality, were aphasia, convulsion, hemiparesis, and loss of consciousness, each reported in 1 patient (1%). The additional Grade 4 adverse reactions, regardless of causality, were cerebral hemorrhage, coma, intracranial hemorrhage, leukoencephalopathy, and metabolic encephalopathy, each reported in one patient (1%).



 The other neurologic adverse reactions, regardless of causality, reported as Grade 1, 2, or unknown in adult patients were abnormal coordination, burning sensation, disturbance in attention, dysarthria, hyporeflexia, neuropathic pain, nystagmus, peroneal nerve palsy, sciatica, sensory disturbance, sinus headache, and speech disorder, each reported in one patient (1%).



   Pediatrics:  The safety profile for children is based on data from 84 pediatric patients treated with the recommended dose and schedule in a T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL)/T-cell lymphoblastic lymphoma (T-LBL) treatment trial.



 The most common adverse reactions in pediatric patients, regardless of causality, were hematologic disorders (anemia, leukopenia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia). Of the non-hematologic adverse reactions in pediatric patients, the most frequent adverse reactions reported were headache, increased transaminase levels, decreased blood potassium, decreased blood albumin, increased blood bilirubin, and vomiting.



 The most common adverse reactions in pediatric patients, by System Organ Class, regardless of causality, including severe or life threatening adverse reactions (NCI Common Toxicity Criteria Grade 3 or Grade 4) and fatal adverse reactions (Grade 5) are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3. Most Commonly Reported (&gt;=5% Overall) Adverse Reactions Regardless of Causality in Pediatric Patients Treated with 650 mg/m2 of ARRANON Administered Intravenously over 1 Hour Daily for 5 Consecutive Days Repeated Every 21 Days 
  System Organ Class     Preferred Term        Percentage of Patients (N = 84)    
  Toxicity Grade                               
  Grade 3  %                                   Grade 4 and 5a  %    All Grades  %             
  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders         
     Anemia                                    45               10                        95                  
     Neutropenia                               17               62                        94                  
     Thrombocytopenia                          27               32                        88                  
     Leukopenia                                14               7                         38                  
  Hepatobiliary Disorders                      
     Transaminases increased                   4                0                         12                  
     Blood albumin decreased                   5                1                         10                  
     Blood bilirubin increased                 7                2                         10                  
  Metabolic/Laboratory                                                                                        
     Blood potassium decreased                 4                2                         11                  
     Blood calcium decreased                   1                1                         8                   
     Blood creatinine increased                0                0                         6                   
     Blood glucose decreased                   4                0                         6                   
     Blood magnesium decreased                 2                0                         6                   
  Nervous System Disorders (see Table 4)       
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                   
     Vomiting                                  0                0                         10                  
  General Disorders &amp; Administration Site Conditions    
     Asthenia                                  1                0                         6                   
  Infections &amp; Infestations                    
     Infection                                 2                1                         5                   
            a  Three patients had a fatal adverse reaction. Fatal adverse reactions included neutropenia and pyrexia (n = 1), status epilepticus/seizure (n = 1), and fungal pneumonia (n = 1).
 

   Neurologic Adverse Reactions:  Nervous system adverse reactions, regardless of drug relationship, were reported for 42% of pediatric patients across the Phase I and Phase II trials. The most common neurologic adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) in pediatric patients, regardless of causality, including all grades (NCI Common Toxicity Criteria) are shown in Table 4.



 Table 4. Neurologic Adverse Reactions (&gt;=2%) Regardless of Causality in Pediatric Patients Treated with 650 mg/m2 of ARRANON Administered Intravenously over 1 Hour Daily for 5 Consecutive Days Repeated Every 21 Days 
  Nervous System Disorders     Preferred Term     Percentage of Patients (N = 84)    
  Grade 1  %                                      Grade 2  %    Grade 3  %    Grade 4 and 5a  %    All Grades  %    
  Headache                                        8          2          4          2                17            
  Peripheral neurologic disorders, any adverse reaction    1          4          7          0                12            
     Peripheral neuropathy                        0          4          2          0                6             
     Peripheral motor neuropathy                  1          0          2          0                4             
     Peripheral sensory neuropathy                0          0          6          0                6             
  Somnolence                                      1          4          1          1                7             
  Hypoesthesia                                    1          1          4          0                6             
  Seizures                                        0          0          0          6                6             
     Convulsions                                  0          0          0          3                4             
     Grand mal convulsions                        0          0          0          1                1             
     Status epilepticus                           0          0          0          1                1             
  Motor dysfunction                               1          1          1          0                4             
  Nervous system disorder                         1          2          0          0                4             
  Paresthesia                                     0          2          1          0                4             
  Tremor                                          1          2          0          0                4             
  Ataxia                                          1          0          1          0                2             
              a  One (1) patient had a fatal neurologic adverse reaction, status epilepticus.
 

 The other Grade 3 neurologic adverse reaction in pediatric patients, regardless of causality, was hypertonia reported in 1 patient (1%). The additional Grade 4 neurologic adverse reactions, regardless of causality, were 3  rd  nerve paralysis, and 6  th  nerve paralysis, each reported in 1 patient (1%).



 The other neurologic adverse reactions, regardless of causality, reported as Grade 1, 2, or unknown in pediatric patients were dysarthria, encephalopathy, hydrocephalus, hyporeflexia, lethargy, mental impairment, paralysis, and sensory loss, each reported in 1 patient (1%).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ARRANON. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Infections and Infestations:  Fatal opportunistic infections.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Tumor lysis syndrome.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Demyelination and ascending peripheral neuropathies similar in appearance to Guillain-Barre syndrome.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Disorders:  Rhabdomyolysis, blood creatine phosphokinase increased.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: NEUROLOGIC ADVERSE REACTIONS

  WARNING: NEUROLOGIC ADVERSE REACTIONS

     Severe neurologic adverse reactions have been reported with the use of ARRANON  (r)  . These adverse reactions have included altered mental states including severe somnolence, central nervous system effects including convulsions, and peripheral neuropathy ranging from numbness and paresthesias to motor weakness and paralysis. There have also been reports of adverse reactions associated with demyelination, and ascending peripheral neuropathies similar in appearance to Guillain-Barre syndrome   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .  



    Full recovery from these adverse reactions has not always occurred with cessation of therapy with ARRANON. Close monitoring for neurologic adverse reactions is strongly recommended, and ARRANON should be discontinued for neurologic adverse reactions of NCI Common Toxicity Criteria Grade 2 or greater   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: NEUROLOGIC ADVERSE REACTIONS



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



    Severe neurologic adverse reactions have been reported with the use of ARRANON. These adverse reactions have included altered mental states including severe somnolence, central nervous system effects including convulsions, and peripheral neuropathy ranging from numbness and paresthesias to motor weakness and paralysis. There have also been reports of adverse reactions associated with demyelination, and ascending peripheral neuropathies similar in appearance to Guillain-Barre syndrome. (  5.1  )  



    Full recovery from these adverse reactions has not always occurred with cessation of therapy with ARRANON. Close monitoring for neurologic adverse reactions is strongly recommended, and ARRANON should be discontinued for neurologic adverse reactions of NCI Common Toxicity Criteria Grade 2 or greater. (  5.1  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Severe neurologic reactions have been reported. Monitor for signs and symptoms of neurologic toxicity. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Hematologic Reactions: Complete blood counts including platelets should be monitored regularly. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Fetal harm can occur if administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised not to become pregnant when taking ARRANON. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Neurologic Adverse Reactions



  Neurotoxicity is the dose-limiting toxicity of nelarabine. Patients undergoing therapy with ARRANON should be closely observed for signs and symptoms of neurologic toxicity [see Boxed Warning, Dosage and Administration (2.2)]  . Common signs and symptoms of nelarabine-related neurotoxicity include somnolence, confusion, convulsions, ataxia, paresthesias, and hypoesthesia. Severe neurologic toxicity can manifest as coma, status epilepticus, craniospinal demyelination, or ascending neuropathy similar in presentation to Guillain-Barre syndrome.



 Patients treated previously or concurrently with intrathecal chemotherapy or previously with craniospinal irradiation may be at increased risk for neurologic adverse events.



    5.2 Hematologic Adverse Reactions



  Leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, and neutropenia, including febrile neutropenia, have been associated with nelarabine therapy. Complete blood counts including platelets should be monitored regularly [see Dosage and Administration (2.2), Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  .



    5.3 Pregnancy



  Pregnancy Category D



 ARRANON can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.



 Nelarabine administered during the period of organogenesis caused increased incidences of fetal malformations, anomalies, and variations in rabbits (see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  .



 There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of ARRANON in pregnant women. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Women of child-bearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving treatment with ARRANON.



    5.4 Hyperuricemia



  Patients receiving ARRANON should receive intravenous hydration according to standard medical practice for the management of hyperuricemia in patients at risk for tumor lysis syndrome. Consideration should be given to the use of allopurinol in patients at risk of hyperuricemia [see Dosage and Administration (2.4)]  .



    5.5 Vaccinations



  Administration of live vaccines to immunocompromised patients should be avoided.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
