<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="arthrotec" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions associated with ARTHROTEC

  Adverse reaction information for ARTHROTEC is derived from Phase III multinational controlled clinical trials in over 2,000 patients, receiving ARTHROTEC 50 or ARTHROTEC 75, as well as from blinded, controlled trials of Voltaren  (r)  Delayed-Release Tablets (diclofenac) and Cytotec  (r)  Tablets (misoprostol).



   Gastrointestinal

  GI disorders had the highest reported incidence of adverse events for patients receiving ARTHROTEC. These events were generally minor, but led to discontinuation of therapy in 9% of patients on ARTHROTEC and 5% of patients on diclofenac. For GI ulcer rates, see    CLINICAL STUDIES-Upper gastrointestinal safety    .




 GI disorder                                    ARTHROTEC                          Diclofenac               
  
 Abdominal pain                                    21%                                15%                   
 Diarrhea                                          19%                                11%                   
 Dyspepsia                                         14%                                11%                   
 Nausea                                            11%                                 6%                   
 Flatulence                                        9%                                  4%                   
         ARTHROTEC can cause more abdominal pain, diarrhea and other GI symptoms than diclofenac alone.
 

 Diarrhea and abdominal pain developed early in the course of therapy, and were usually self-limited (resolved after 2 to 7 days). Rare instances of profound diarrhea leading to severe dehydration have been reported in patients receiving misoprostol. Patients with an underlying condition such as inflammatory bowel disease, or those in whom dehydration, were it to occur, would be dangerous, should be monitored carefully if ARTHROTEC is prescribed. The incidence of diarrhea can be minimized by administering ARTHROTEC with food and by avoiding coadministration with magnesium-containing antacids.



   Gynecological

  Gynecological disorders previously reported with misoprostol use have also been reported for women receiving ARTHROTEC (see below). Postmenopausal vaginal bleeding may be related to administration of ARTHROTEC. If it occurs, diagnostic workup should be undertaken to rule out gynecological pathology (see boxed    CONTRAINDICATIONS AND WARNINGS    ).



   Elderly

  Overall, there were no significant differences in the safety profile of ARTHROTEC in over 500 patients 65 years of age or older compared with younger patients.



 Other adverse experiences reported occasionally or rarely with ARTHROTEC, diclofenac or other NSAIDs, or misoprostol are:



   Body as a whole:  Asthenia, death, fatigue, fever, infection, malaise, sepsis, chills.



   Cardiovascular system:  Arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, congestive heart failure, hypertension, hypotension, increased CPK, increased LDH, myocardial infarction, palpitations, phlebitis, premature ventricular contractions, syncope, tachycardia, vasculitis.



   Central and peripheral nervous system:  Coma, convulsions, dizziness, drowsiness, headache, hyperesthesia, hypertonia, hypoesthesia, insomnia, meningitis, migraine, neuralgia, paresthesia, somnolence, tremor, vertigo.



   Digestive:  Anorexia, appetite changes, constipation, dry mouth, dysphagia, enteritis, esophageal ulceration, esophagitis, eructation, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux, GI bleeding, GI neoplasm benign, glossitis, heartburn, hematemesis, hemorrhoids, intestinal perforation, peptic ulcer, stomatitis and ulcerative stomatitis, tenesmus, vomiting.



   Female reproductive disorders:  Breast pain, dysmenorrhea, intermenstrual bleeding, leukorrhea, menstrual disorder, menorrhagia, vaginal hemorrhage.



   Hemic and lymphatic system:  Agranulocytosis, anemia, aplastic anemia, coagulation time increased, ecchymosis, eosinophilia, epistaxis, hemolytic anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, melena, pancytopenia, pulmonary embolism, purpura, rectal bleeding, thrombocythemia, thrombocytopenia.



   Hypersensitivity:  Angioedema, laryngeal/pharyngeal edema, urticaria.



   Liver and biliary system:  Abnormal hepatic function, bilirubinemia, hepatitis, jaundice, liver failure, pancreatitis.



   Male reproductive disorders:  Impotence, perineal pain.



   Metabolic and nutritional:  Alkaline phosphatase increased, BUN increased, dehydration, glycosuria, gout, hypercholesterolemia, hyperglycemia, hyperuricemia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, periorbital edema, porphyria, weight changes.



   Musculoskeletal system:  Arthralgia, myalgia.



   Psychiatric:  Anxiety, concentration impaired, confusion, depression, disorientation, dream abnormalities, hallucinations, irritability, nervousness, paranoia, psychotic reaction.



   Respiratory system:  Asthma, coughing, dyspnea, hyperventilation, pneumonia, respiratory depression.



   Skin and appendages:  Acne, alopecia, bruising, eczema, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, pemphigoid reaction, photosensitivity, pruritus, pruritus ani, rash, skin ulceration, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, sweating increased, toxic epidermal necrolysis.



   Special senses:  Hearing impairment, taste loss, taste perversion, tinnitus.



   Urinary system:  Cystitis, dysuria, hematuria, interstitial nephritis, micturition frequency, nocturia, nephrotic syndrome, oliguria/polyuria, papillary necrosis, proteinuria, renal failure, urinary tract infection.



   Vision:  Amblyopia, blurred vision, conjunctivitis, diplopia, glaucoma, iritis, lacrimation abnormal, night blindness, vision abnormal.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: CONTRAINDICATIONS AND WARNINGS

  CONTRAINDICATIONS AND WARNINGS

  ARTHROTEC  (r)   CONTAINS DICLOFENAC SODIUM AND MISOPROSTOL. ADMINISTRATION OF MISOPROSTOL TO WOMEN WHO ARE PREGNANT CAN CAUSE ABORTION, PREMATURE BIRTH, OR BIRTH DEFECTS. UTERINE RUPTURE HAS BEEN REPORTED WHEN MISOPROSTOL WAS ADMINISTERED IN PREGNANT WOMEN TO INDUCE LABOR OR TO INDUCE ABORTION BEYOND THE EIGHTH WEEK OF PREGNANCY (see also     PRECAUTIONS    ). ARTHROTEC SHOULD NOT BE TAKEN BY PREGNANT WOMEN (see     CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,   WARNINGS     and     PRECAUTIONS    ).



 PATIENTS MUST BE ADVISED OF THE ABORTIFACIENT PROPERTY AND WARNED NOT TO GIVE THE DRUG TO OTHERS.ARTHROTEC should not be used in women of childbearing potential unless the patient requires nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) therapy and is at high risk of developing gastric or duodenal ulceration or for developing complications from gastric or duodenal ulcers associated with the use of the NSAID (see     WARNINGS    ). In such patients, ARTHROTEC may be prescribed if the patient:



 *  has had a negative serum pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to beginning therapy. 
 *  is capable of complying with effective contraceptive measures. 
 *  has received both oral and written warnings of the hazards of misoprostol, the risk of possible contraception failure, and the danger to other women of childbearing potential should the drug be taken by mistake. 
 *  will begin ARTHROTEC only on the second or third day of the next normal menstrual period. 
      Cardiovascular Risk
     *  NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk (see WARNINGS). 
 *  ARTHROTEC is contraindicated for treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery (see WARNINGS). 
      Gastrointestinal Risk
   NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events (see     WARNINGS    ).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
