<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="articaine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Reactions to articaine are characteristic of those associated with other amide local anesthetics. Adverse reactions to this group of drugs may also result from excessive plasma levels (which may be due to overdosage, unintentional intravascular injection, or slow metabolic degradation), injection technique, volume of injection, or hypersensitivity or they may be idiosyncratic.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;2%) are headache and pain (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pierrel S.p.A. at 610-989-4213 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The reported adverse events are derived from clinical trials in the United States and the United Kingdom with a similar product containing articaine and epinephrine. Table 2 displays the adverse events reported in clinical trials where 882 individuals were exposed to articaine containing epinephrine 1:100,000. Table 3 displays the adverse events reported in clinical trials where 182 individuals were exposed to articaine containing epinephrine 1:100,000 and 179 individuals were exposed to articaine containing epinephrine 1:200,000.



   Adverse reactions observed in at least 1% of patients:  



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions in Controlled Trials with an Incidence of 1% or Greater in Patients Administered Articaine HCl and Epinephrine containing Epinephrine 1:100,000 
   Body System/Reaction       articaine containing epinephrine 1:100,000 (N=882) Incidence     
   Body as a whole                                      
 Face edema                 13 (1%)                     
 Headache                   31 (4%)                     
 Infection                  10 (1%)                     
 Pain                       114 (13%)                   
   Digestive system          
 Gingivitis                 13 (1%)                     
   Nervous system            
 Paresthesia                11 (1%)                     
     Table 3: Adverse Reactions in Controlled Trials with an Incidence of 1% or Greater in Patients Administered Articaine HCl and Epinephrine containing Epinephrine 1:200,000 and Articaine HCl and Epinephrine containing Epinephrine 1:100,000 
 Reaction                   articaine with epinephrine 1:200,000 (N=179) Incidence  articaine with epinephrine 1:100,000 (N=182) Incidence   
 Any adverse event          33 (18%)                   35 (19%)                    
 Pain                       11 (6.1%)                  14 (7.6%)                   
 Headache                   9 (5%)                     6 (3.2%)                    
 Positive blood aspiration into syringe  3 (1.6%)                   6 (3.2%)                    
 Swelling                   3 (1.6%)                   5 (2.7%)                    
 Trismus                    1 (0.3%)                   3 (1.6%)                    
 Nausea and emesis          3 (1.6%)                   0 (0%)                      
 Sleepiness                 2 (1.1%)                   1 (0.5%)                    
 Numbness and tingling      1 (0.5%)                   2 (1.%)                     
 Palpitation                0 (0%)                     2 (1.%)                     
 Ear symptoms (earache, otitis media)  1 (0.5%)                   2 (1.%)                     
 Cough, persistent cough    0 (0%)                     2 (1.%)                     
        Adverse reactions observed in less than 1% of patients:  
 

 Table 4: Adverse Reactions in Controlled Trials with an Incidence of Less than 1% but Considered Clinically Relevant 
   Body System                Events                    
 Body as a Whole            Asthenia; back pain; injection site pain; burning sensation above injection site; malaise; neck pain   
 Cardiovascular System      Hemorrhage; migraine; syncope; tachycardia; elevated blood pressure   
 Digestive System           Dyspepsia; glossitis; gum hemorrhage; mouth ulceration; nausea; stomatitis; tongue edemas; tooth disorder; vomiting   
 Hemic and Lymphatic System  Ecchymosis; lymphadenopathy   
 Metabolic and Nutritional System  Edema; thirst               
 Musculoskeletal System     Arthralgia; myalgia; osteomyelitis   
 Nervous System             Dizziness; dry mouth; facial paralysis; hyperesthesia; increased salivation; nervousness; neuropathy; paresthesia; somnolence; exacerbation of Kearns-Sayre Syndrome   
 Respiratory System         Pharyngitis; rhinitis; sinus pain; sinus congestion   
 Skin and Appendages        Pruritus; skin disorder     
 Special Senses             Ear pain; taste perversion   
      
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of articaine hydrochloride with epinephrine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a casual relationship to drug exposure.



 Persistent paresthesias of the lips, tongue, and oral tissues have been reported with use of articaine hydrochloride, with slow, incomplete, or no recovery. These postmarketing events have been reported chiefly following nerve blocks in the mandible and have involved the trigeminal nerve and its branches.



 Hypoesthesia has been reported with use of articaine, especially in pediatric age groups, which is usually reversible. Prolonged numbness can result in soft tissue injuries such as that of the lips and tongue in these age groups.



 Ischemic injury and necrosis has been described following use of articaine with epinephrine and has been postulated to be due to vascular spasm of terminal arterial branches.



 Paralysis of ocular muscles has been reported, especially after posterior, superior alveolar injections of articaine during dental anesthesia. Symptoms include diplopia, mydriasis, ptosis and difficulty in abduction of the affected eye. These symptoms have been described as developing immediately after injection of the anesthetic solution and persisting one minute to several hours, with generally complete recovery.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Accidental Intravascular Injection: May be associated with convulsions followed by coma and respiratory arrest. Resuscitative equipment, oxygen and other resuscitative drugs should be available. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Systemic Toxicity (  5.2  ) 
 *   Vasoconstrictor Toxicity: Local anesthetic solutions like Articaine HCl and Epinephrine that contain a vasoconstrictor should be used cautiously, especially in patients with impaired cardiovascular function or vascular disease. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Methemoglobinemia (  5.4  ) 
 *   Anaphylaxis and Allergic-Type Reactions (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Accidental Intravascular Injection



  Accidental intravascular injection of Articaine HCl and Epinephrine may be associated with convulsions, followed by central nervous system or cardiorespiratory depression and coma, progressing ultimately to respiratory arrest. Dental practitioners who employ local anesthetic agents including Articaine HCl and Epinephrine should be well versed in diagnosis and management of emergencies that may arise from their use. Resuscitative equipment, oxygen, and other resuscitative drugs should be available for immediate use. To avoid intravascular injection, aspiration should be performed before Articaine HCl and Epinephrine is injected. The needle must be repositioned until no return of blood can be elicited by aspiration. Note, however, that the absence of blood in the syringe does not guarantee that intravascular injection has been avoided.



 Small doses of local anesthetics injected in dental blocks may produce adverse reactions similar to systemic toxicity seen with unintentional intravascular injections of larger doses. Confusion, convulsions, respiratory depression and/or respiratory arrest, and cardiovascular stimulation or depression have been reported. These reactions may be due to intra-arterial injection of the local anesthetic with retrograde flow to the cerebral circulation. Patients receiving these blocks should be observed constantly. Resuscitative equipment and personnel for treating adverse reactions should be immediately available. Dosage recommendations should not be exceeded [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )]  .



    5.2 Systemic Toxicity



  This includes toxicity arising from accidental intravascular injection of Articaine HCl and Epinephrine discussed in Section 5.1, as well as that related to higher systemic concentrations of local anesthetics or epinephrine [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )].  Systemic absorption of local anesthetics including Articaine HCl and Epinephrine can produce effects on the central nervous and cardiovascular systems.



 At blood concentrations achieved with therapeutic doses of Articaine HCl and Epinephrine, changes in cardiac conduction, excitability, refractoriness, contractility, and peripheral vascular resistance are minimal. However, toxic blood concentrations of Articaine HCl and Epinephrine can depress cardiac conduction and excitability, which may lead to atrioventricular block, ventricular arrhythmias, and cardiac arrest, possibly resulting in fatalities. In addition, myocardial contractility is depressed and peripheral vasodilatation occurs, leading to decreased cardiac output and arterial blood pressure. Articaine HCl and Epinephrine should also be used with caution in patients with heart block as well as those with impaired cardiovascular function since they may be less able to compensate for functional changes associated with the prolongation of A-V conduction produced by these drugs.



 Restlessness, anxiety, tinnitus, dizziness, blurred vision, tremors, depression, or drowsiness may be early warning signs of central nervous system toxicity.



 Careful and constant monitoring of cardiovascular and respiratory (adequacy of ventilation) vital signs and the patient's state of consciousness should be performed after each local anesthetic injection of Articaine HCl and Epinephrine. Repeated doses of Articaine HCl and Epinephrine may cause significant increases in blood levels because of possible accumulation of the drug or its metabolites. The lowest dosage that results in effective anesthesia should be used to decrease the risk of high plasma levels and serious adverse effects. Tolerance to elevated blood levels varies with the status of the patient. Resuscitative equipment, oxygen, and other resuscitative drugs should be available for immediate use. Precautions for epinephrine administration, discussed in Section 5.3 should be observed.



 Debilitated patients, elderly patients, acutely ill patients, and pediatric patients should be given reduced doses commensurate with their age and physical condition [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  ,  2.3  )]  . No studies have been performed in patients with liver dysfunction, and caution should be used in patients with severe hepatic disease.



    5.3 Vasoconstrictor Toxicity



  Articaine HCl and Epinephrine contains epinephrine, a vasoconstrictor that can cause local or systemic toxicity and should be used cautiously. Local toxicity may include ischemic injury or necrosis, which may be related to vascular spasm. Articaine HCl and Epinephrine should be used with caution in patients during or following the administration of potent general anesthetic agents, since cardiac arrhythmias may occur under such conditions. Patients with peripheral vascular disease and those with hypertensive vascular disease may exhibit exaggerated vasoconstrictor response.



 The American Heart Association has made the following recommendation regarding the use of local anesthetics with vasoconstrictors in patients with ischemic heart disease: "Vasoconstrictor agents should be used in local anesthesia solutions during dental practice only when it is clear that the procedure will be shortened or the analgesia rendered more profound. When a vasoconstrictor is indicated, extreme care should be taken to avoid intravascular injection. The minimum possible amount of vasoconstrictor should be used."  (Kaplan, 1986)  .



 It is essential to aspirate before any injection to avoid administration of the drug into the blood stream.



    5.4 Methemoglobinemia



  Articaine HCl and Epinephrine, like other local anesthetic solutions containing a vasoconstrictor, can cause methemoglobinemia, particularly in conjunction with methemoglobin-inducing agents. Articaine HCl and Epinephrine should not be used in patients with congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia, and in patients who are receiving treatment with methemoglobin-inducing agents since they are more susceptible to drug-induced methemoglobinemia.



 Signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia may be delayed some hours after exposure. Initial signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia include slate grey cyanosis seen in buccal mucous membranes, lips and nail beds. In severe cases, symptoms may include central cyanosis, headache, lethargy, dizziness, fatigue, syncope, dyspnea, CNS depression, seizures, dysrythmia and shock. Methemoglobinemia should be considered if central cyanosis unresponsive to oxygen therapy occurs, especially if methemoglobin-inducing agents have been used. Calculated oxygen saturation and pulse oximetry are inaccurate in the setting of methemoglobinemia. The diagnosis can be confirmed by an elevated methemoglobin level of at least 10% is present. The development of methemoglobinemia is dose-related.



  Management of methemoglobinemia   :  If methemoglobinemia does not respond to administration of oxygen, clinically significant symptoms of methemoglobinemia should be treated with administration of a slow intravenous injection (over 5 minutes) of methylene blue at a dosage of 1-2 mg/kg body weight.



    5.5 Anaphylaxis and Allergic-Type Reactions



  Articaine HCl and Epinephrine contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfite that may cause allergic-type reactions including anaphylactic symptoms and life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in certain susceptible people. The overall prevalence of sulfite sensitivity in the general population is unknown. Sulfite sensitivity is seen more frequently in asthmatic than in non-asthmatic people.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
