<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="artiss" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions occurring in greater than 1% of patients treated with ARTISS were skin graft failure and pruritus (  6.1  ,  6.2  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare Corporation at 1-866-888-2472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Overall Adverse Reactions

  Adverse reactions occurring in greater than 1% of patients treated with ARTISS were skin graft failure and pruritus.



   Hypersensitivity/Allergic/Anaphylactic Reactions:  Hypersensitivity or allergic/anaphylactoid reactions may occur  (see  WARNINGS/PRECAUTIONS, Hypersensitivity/Allergic/Anaphylactic Reactions (5.1)    ). No adverse events of this type were reported during clinical trials.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The following adverse reactions have been reported from a clinical trial where ARTISS was used to affix split thickness sheet skin grafts to excised burn wounds  (see  CLINICAL STUDIES (14)  )  . A total of 8 non-serious adverse reactions were deemed related to the use of ARTISS by the investigator. Of the 8 related non-serious adverse reactions, 5 were incidences of skin graft failure: 4 were graft detachment/non-adherence and 1 was graft necrosis. The graft detachment in 2 patients may have been related to the maximum thawing temperature (40 degrees C) being exceeded during study product preparation. The 3 other non-serious adverse reactions considered related to ARTISS were 2 incidences of pruritus and 1 incidence of dermal cyst. The graft necrosis and the 2 cases of pruritus considered related to ARTISS each had an equivalent adverse reaction with the exact start date and severity reported at a control wound where skin grafts were affixed with staples. Therefore, these events are most likely not related to ARTISS, but instead are expected outcomes for any grafted wound regardless of the method of attachment.



 Overall, the data collected and analyzed during this study demonstrated that ARTISS is safe for the attachment of sheet skin grafts in subjects with deep partial thickness or full thickness burn wounds.



 The adverse reactions and their frequencies are summarized in Table 2:



 Table 2. 
         Adverse reactions (Preferred Term)             Number of events/Number of patients treated       
  
                    Dermal cyst                                            1/138                          
                      Pruritus                                             2/138                          
                 Skin graft failure                                        5/138                          
          6.3 Post Marketing
   The following adverse reactions reflect what has been reported in post marketing experience with Baxter's fibrin sealant that could reasonably be expected to occur with ARTISS:



   Immune system disorders  : anaphylactic responses, hypersensitivity  Cardiac disorders  : bradycardia, tachycardia  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  : dyspnea  Gastrointestinal disorders  : nausea  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : urticaria  General disorders and administration site conditions  : flushing, impaired healing, edema, pyrexia  Injury, poisoning and procedural complication  : seroma



 Air embolism associated with misapplication of fibrin sealant using the spray device, Class Effect: A postmarketing fatality was reported in association with the use of another fibrin sealant when applied using a spray device. The case involved an attempt to stop active bleeding by applying the fibrin sealant using a spray device attached to a wall unit at a higher than recommended pressure for the spray device. In addition, the spray head was placed at a distance from the bleeding site that was closer than the recommended distance guidelines for the application of the sealant. The patient suffered a fatal air embolism.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Apply only as thin layer (  2.3  ,  5.2  ) 
 *  Air or gas embolism has occurred with the use of spray devices employing pressure regulator to administer fibrin sealants. This event appears to be related to the use of the spray device at higher than recommended pressures and in close proximity to the surface of the tissue (  5.2  ) 
 *  Exposure to solutions containing alcohol, iodine or heavy metals may cause ARTISS to be denatured (  5.2  ) 
 *  This product is made from pooled human plasma which may, theoretically, contain infectious agents (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity/Allergic/Anaphylactic Reactions



  Hypersensitivity or allergic/anaphylactoid reactions may occur with the use of ARTISS. Cases (&lt;1/10,000) have been reported in post marketing experience with Baxter's fibrin sealant (see  ADVERSE REACTIONS, Post Marketing (6.3)  )  . In specific cases, these reactions have progressed to severe anaphylaxis. Such reactions may especially be seen if ARTISS is applied repeatedly over time or in the same setting, or if systemic aprotinin has been administered previously. Even if the first treatment was well tolerated, a subsequent administration of ARTISS or systemic aprotinin may not exclude the occurrence of an allergic reaction. Symptoms associated with allergic anaphylactic reactions include: flush, urticaria, pruritus, nausea, drop in blood pressure, tachycardia or bradycardia, dyspnea, severe hypotension and anaphylactic shock. Such reactions may also occur in patients receiving ARTISS for the first time.



 Discontinue administration of ARTISS in the event of hypersensitivity reactions. Remove the already applied, polymerized product from the surgical field. Mild reactions can be managed with antihistamines. Severe hypotensive reactions require immediate intervention using current principles of shock therapy.



    5.2 Application Precautions



  Apply ARTISS as a thin layer. Excessive clot thickness may negatively interfere with the product's efficacy and the wound healing process.



 Air or gas embolism has occurred with the use of spray devices employing pressure regulator to administer fibrin sealants. This event appears to be related to the use of the spray device at higher than recommended pressures and in close proximity to the tissue surface.



 When applying ARTISS using a spray device, be sure to use the pressure within the pressure range recommended by the spray device manufacturer. In the absence of a specific recommendation avoid using pressure above 20-25 psi. Do not spray closer than the distance recommended by the spray device manufacturer. In the absence of a specific recommendation avoid spraying closer than 10-15 cm from the surface of the tissue. When spraying ARTISS, changes in blood pressure, pulse, oxygen saturation and end tidal CO2should be monitored because of the possibility of occurrence of air or gas embolism.



 The sealer protein and thrombin solutions can be denatured by alcohol, iodine or heavy metal ions (e.g. antiseptic solutions). If any of these substances have been used to clean the wound area, the area must be thoroughly rinsed before application of ARTISS and made as dry as possible.



    5.3 Infection Risk from Human Plasma



  ARTISS is made from human plasma. Products made from human plasma may contain infectious agents, such as viruses, that can cause disease. The risk that such products will transmit an infectious agent has been reduced by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, by testing for the presence of certain current virus infections, and by inactivating and removing certain viruses (see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Other Clinical Pharmacology Information (12.4)  ).  Despite these measures, such products can still potentially transmit disease. Because this product is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. This also applies to unknown or emerging viruses or other pathogens. All infections thought by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Baxter Healthcare Corporation, telephone # 1-866-888-2472.



 Some viruses, such as parvovirus B19, are particularly difficult to remove or inactivate at this time. Parvovirus B19 most seriously affects pregnant women (fetal infection), immune-compromised individuals or individuals with an increased erythropoiesis (e.g., hemolytic anemia) (see   USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS, Pregnancy (8.1)    and   PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION (17)  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
