<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="asacol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6          ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The most serious adverse reactions seen in Asacol HD clinical trials or with other products that contain mesalamine or are metabolized to mesalamine were:



 *  Renal impairment, including renal failure (rare)  [  see     Warnings     and     Precautions     (    5.1    )]  
 *  Acute intolerance syndrome  [  see     Warnings     and     Precautions     (    5.2    )]  
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions  [  see     Warnings     and     Precautions     (    5.3    )]  
 *  Hepatic failure  [  see     Warnings     and     Precautions     (    5.4    )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (observed in greater than 2 percent of patients) were headache, nausea, nasopharyngitis, abdominal pain, and worsening of ulcerative colitis (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Warner Chilcott at 1-800-521-8813 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

    6.1          Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Asacol HD has been evaluated in 896 patients with ulcerative colitis in controlled studies. Three six- week, active-controlled studies were conducted comparing Asacol HD 4.8 grams/day with Asacol (mesalamine) 2.4 grams/day in patients with mildly to moderately active ulcerative colitis. In these studies, 727 patients were dosed with the Asacol HD tablet and 732 patients were dosed with the Asacol 400 mg tablet. (One Asacol HD 800 mg tablet cannot be substituted for two Asacol 400 mg tablets   [    see         Clinical         Pharmacology         (      12.3      )    ]  .)



 The most common reactions reported in the Asacol HD group were headache (4.7 percent), nausea (2.8 percent), nasopharyngitis (2.5 percent), abdominal pain (2.3 percent), exacerbation of ulcerative colitis (2.3 percent), diarrhea (1.7 percent), and dyspepsia (1.7 percent);  Table 1  enumerates adverse reactions that occurred in the three studies. The most common reactions in patients with moderately active ulcerative colitis (602 patients dosed with Asacol HD and 618 patients dosed with the Asacol 400 mg) were the same as all treated patients.



 Discontinuations due to adverse reactions occurred in 3.9 percent of patients in the Asacol HD group and in 4.2 percent of patients in the Asacol 400 mg tablet comparator group. The most common cause for discontinuation was gastrointestinal symptoms associated with ulcerative colitis.



 Severe adverse reactions occurred in 7.6 percent of patients in the Asacol HD group and in 7.6 percent of patients in the Asacol 400 mg tablet comparator group. Most of these reactions were gastrointestinal symptoms related to ulcerative colitis. Serious adverse reactions occurred in 0.8 percent of patients in the Asacol HD group and in 1.8 percent of patients in the Asacol 400 mg tablet comparator group. The majority involved the gastrointestinal system.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in 1 Percent or More of All Treated Patients (Three studies combined) 
                  Asacol*2.4 g/day  Asacol HD*4.8 g/day   
                  (400 mg Tablet)  (800 mg Tablet)   
 Adverse Reaction  (N = 732)        (N = 727)         
 Headache         4.9 %            4.7 %             
 Nausea           2.9 %            2.8 %             
 Nasopharyngitis  1.4 %            2.5 %             
 Abdominal pain   2.3 %            2.3 %             
 Ulcerative Colitis  2.7 %            2.3 %             
 Diarrhea         1.9 %            1.7 %             
 Dyspepsia        0.8 %            1.7 %             
 Vomiting         1.6 %            1.4 %             
 Flatulence       0.7 %            1.2 %             
 Influenza        1.2 %            1.0 %             
 Pyrexia          1.2 %            0.7 %             
 Cough            1.4 %            0.3 %             
 N = number of patients within specified treatment group   
 Percent = percentage of patients in category and treatment group   
 *One Asacol HD 800 mg tablet cannot be substituted for two Asacol 400 mg tablets   [    see         Clinical    Pharmacology         (      12.3      )    ]    .     
             6.2          Postmarketing Experience  
   In addition to the adverse reactions reported above in clinical trials involving the Asacol HD tablet, the adverse events listed below have been reported in controlled clinical trials, open label studies, literature reports, or foreign and domestic marketing experience with Asacol 400 mg tablets or other products that contain mesalamine or are metabolized to mesalamine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body         as         a         Whole  : Facial edema, edema, peripheral edema, asthenia, chills, infection, malaise, pain, neck pain, chest pain, back pain, abdominal enlargement, lupus-like syndrome, drug fever (rare).



   Cardiovascular  : Pericarditis (rare) and myocarditis (rare) [  see         Warnings         and         Precautions         (      5.3      )  ], pericardial effusion, vasodilation, migraine.



   Gastrointestinal  : Dry mouth, stomatitis, oral ulcers, anorexia, increased appetite, eructation, pancreatitis, cholecystitis, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal bleeding, perforated peptic ulcer (rare), constipation, hemorrhoids, rectal hemorrhage, bloody diarrhea, tenesmus, stool abnormality.



   Hepatic  : There have been rare reports of hepatotoxicity, including jaundice, cholestatic jaundice, hepatitis, and possible hepatocellular damage including liver necrosis and liver failure. Some of these cases were fatal. Asymptomatic elevations of liver enzymes which usually resolve during continued use or with discontinuation of the drug have also been reported. One case of Kawasaki-like syndrome, that included changes in liver enzymes, was also reported   [see Warnings and Precautions (      5.4      )]  .



   He    m    atologi    c  : Agranulocytosis (rare), aplastic anemia (rare), anemia, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, eosinophilia, lymphadenopathy.



   Musculoskeleta    l  : Gout, rheumatoid arthritis, arthritis, arthralgia, joint disorder, myalgia, hypertonia.



   Neurological/Psychiatric  : Anxiety, depression, somnolence, insomnia, nervousness, confusion, emotional lability, dizziness, vertigo, tremor, paresthesia, hyperesthesia, peripheral neuropathy (rare), Guillain-Barre syndrome (rare), and transverse myelitis (rare).



   Respirator    y    /Pul    m    onar    y  : Sinusitis, rhinitis, pharyngitis, asthma exacerbation, pleuritis, bronchitis, eosinophilic pneumonia, interstitial pneumonitis.



   Ski    n  : Alopecia, psoriasis (rare), pyoderma gangrenosum (rare), erythema nodosum, acne, dry skin, sweating, pruritus, urticaria, rash.



   Special         Senses  : Ear pain, tinnitus, ear congestion, ear disorder, conjunctivitis, eye pain, blurred vision, vision abnormality, taste perversion.



   Renal/Urogenital  : Renal failure (rare), interstitial nephritis, minimal change nephropathy   [    see         W    a    rnings and         Precautions         (      5.1      )    ]  , dysuria, urinary frequency and urgency, hematuria, epididymitis, decreased libido, dysmenorrhea, menorrhagia.



   Laboratory         Abnor    m    alitie    s  : Elevated AST (SGOT) or ALT (SGPT), elevated alkaline phosphatase, elevated GGT, elevated LDH, elevated bilirubin, elevated serum creatinine and BUN.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5         WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *   Development     of     Renal     Impairment     (  for     example,     minimal     change  nephropathy,     acute     and     chronic     interstitial     nephritis     renal     failure):    Assess renal function at beginning of treatment and periodically during therapy (  5.1  ) 
 *   Mesalamine-induced     Acute     I  n  tolerance     Syndrome:    Has been reported. Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment (  5.2  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity     Reactions : Use caution when treating patients who are hypersensitive to sulfasalazine. Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hepatic     Failure:    Has been reported in patients with pre-existing liver disease. Use caution when treating patients with liver disease (  5.4  ) 
 *   Prolonged     Gastric     Retention     in     P  a  ti  e  nts     with     Upper     Gastrointestinal   Obstruction:    May lead to a delay in onset of action (  5.5  ) 
    
 

    5.1         Renal Impairment  



  Renal impairment, including minimal change nephropathy, acute and chronic interstitial nephritis, and, rarely, renal failure, has been reported in patients taking products such as Asacol HD that contain or are converted to mesalamine.



 It is recommended that all patients have an evaluation of renal function prior to initiation of Asacol HD and periodically while on therapy. Prescribers should carefully evaluate the risks and benefits when using Asacol HD in patients with known renal impairment or history of renal disease  [   see       Drug   Interactions       (     7.1     )       and       Nonclinical       Toxicology       (     13.2     )   ]  .



     5.   2         Mesalamine-Induced Acute Intolerance Syndrome  



  Mesalamine has been associated with an acute intolerance syndrome that may be difficult to distinguish from an exacerbation of ulcerative colitis. Exacerbation of the symptoms of colitis has been reported in 2.3 percent of Asacol HD-treated patients in controlled clinical trials. This acute reaction, characterized by cramping, abdominal pain, bloody diarrhea, and occasionally by fever, headache, malaise, pruritus, rash, and conjunctivitis, has been reported after the initiation of Asacol HD tablets as well as other mesalamine products. Symptoms usually abate when Asacol HD tablets are discontinued.



     5.   3         Hypersensitivity Reactions  



  Some patients who have experienced a hypersensitivity reaction to sulfasalazine may have a similar reaction to Asacol HD tablets or to other compounds that contain or are converted to mesalamine.



 Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported with Asacol HD and other mesalamine medications. Caution should be taken in prescribing this medicine to patients with conditions predisposing them to the development of myocarditis or pericarditis.



     5.   4         Hepatic Failure  



  There have been reports of hepatic failure in patients with pre-existing liver disease who have been administered mesalamine. Caution should be exercised when administering Asacol HD to patients with liver disease.



     5.   5         Prolonged Gastric Retention in Patients       w   ith Upper Gastrointestinal Obstruction  



  Organic or functional obstruction in the upper gastrointestinal tract may cause prolonged gastric retention of Asacol HD which would delay release of mesalamine in the colon.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
