<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="asmanex0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic and local corticosteroid use may result in the following:



 *   Candida albicans infection [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Immunosuppression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Growth effects in pediatrics [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Glaucoma and cataracts [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (reported in greater than or equal to 3% of patients) included:
 

 *  nasopharyngitis, headache, sinusitis, bronchitis, and influenza. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The safety of ASMANEX HFA was evaluated in 2 randomized placebo and active-controlled trials of 12 and 26 weeks' duration, conducted as part of a mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate combination product asthma program, which enrolled 1509 patients with persistent asthma. Patient ages ranged from 12 to 84 years of age, 41% were male and 59% female, 73% were Caucasian and 27% non-Caucasian. Of the total population enrolled in the 2 trials, 432 patients received two inhalations twice daily of either ASMANEX HFA, 100 mcg or 200 mcg/actuation. In the 26-week trial (Trial 1) 192 patients received two inhalations twice daily of ASMANEX HFA 100 mcg/actuation and 196 patients received placebo. In the 12 week trial (Trial 2) 240 patients received two inhalations twice daily of ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg/actuation and 233 and 255 patients received mometasone furoate and formoterol fumarate 100 mcg/5 mcg and 200 mcg/5 mcg/actuation combination products, respectively, as comparators.



 In these trials, the proportion of patients who discontinued study treatment early due to adverse reactions was 3% and 2% for ASMANEX HFA 100 and 200 mcg treated patients, respectively, and 4% for placebo-treated patients. Serious adverse reactions, whether considered drug-related or not by the investigators, which occurred more frequently in ASMANEX HFA-treated patients included colitis ulcerative, colonic polyp, chest pain, gastroenteritis, endometriosis, asthma, and hemoptysis; all events occurred at rates less than 1%.



 The incidence of treatment emergent adverse reactions associated with ASMANEX HFA are shown in Tables 2 and 3. These are based upon data from each of the 2 clinical trials of 12 or 26 weeks in duration in patients 12 years and older treated with two inhalations twice daily of ASMANEX HFA (100 mcg or 200 mcg), mometasone furoate/formoterol fumarate (100 mcg/5 mcg or 200 mcg/5 mcg), or placebo.



 TABLE 2: Trial 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of &gt;=3% and More Commonly than Placebo Over 26 Weeks 
                                       ASMANEX HFA 100 mcgN=192n (%)            PlaceboN=196n (%)           
  
 Nasopharyngitis                                  15 (8)                              7 (4)                 
 Headache                                         10 (5)                              7 (4)                 
 Influenza                                         7 (4)                              5 (3)                 
 Sinusitis                                         6 (3)                              2 (1)                 
        TABLE 3: Trial 2: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of &gt;=3% Over 12 Weeks 
                            ASMANEX HFA200 mcgN=240n (%)   MF/F100/5 mcgN=233n (%)    MF/F200/5 mcgN=255n (%)    
  
 Nasopharyngitis                     13 (5)                      8 (3)                     12 (5)             
 Headache                             8 (3)                     10 (4)                      5 (2)             
 Bronchitis                           6 (3)                      2 (1)                      7 (3)             
          Oral candidiasis has been reported in clinical trials at an incidence of 0.5% in patients using ASMANEX HFA 100 mcg, 0.8% in patients using ASMANEX HFA 200 mcg and 0.5% in the placebo group.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  There are no postmarketing adverse experiences reported to date with ASMANEX HFA. However, the postmarketing safety experience with mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler is relevant to ASMANEX HFA since they contain the same active ingredient. The following adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Immune System Disorders:  Immediate and delayed hypersensitivity reactions including rash, pruritus, angioedema and anaphylactic reaction  [see  Contraindications (4.2)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  .



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Asthma aggravation, which may include cough, dyspnea, wheezing and bronchospasm.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Deterioration of asthma and acute episodes: ASMANEX HFA should not be used for relief of acute symptoms. Patients require immediate re-evaluation during rapidly deteriorating asthma. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Localized infections: Candida albicans infection of the mouth and throat may occur. Monitor patients periodically for signs of adverse effects on the oral cavity. Advise patients to rinse the mouth following inhalation. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Immunosuppression: Potential worsening of existing tuberculosis, fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infection; or ocular herpes simplex infections. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles can occur in susceptible patients. Use with caution in patients with these infections because of the potential for worsening of these infections. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Transferring patients from systemic corticosteroids: Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring from oral steroids. Wean patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to ASMANEX HFA. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: May occur with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals. If such changes occur, discontinue ASMANEX HFA slowly. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Strong cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir): Risk of increased systemic corticosteroid effects. Exercise caution when used with ASMANEX HFA. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue ASMANEX HFA and institute alternative therapy if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis: Hypersensitivity reactions, such as urticaria, flushing, allergic dermatitis, bronchospasm, rash, pruritus, angioedema, and anaphylactic reaction may occur. Discontinue ASMANEX HFA if such reactions occur. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Decreases in bone mineral density: Monitor patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Effects on growth: Monitor growth of pediatric patients. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Glaucoma and cataracts: Monitor patients with change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and/or cataracts closely. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Deterioration of Asthma and Acute Episodes



  ASMANEX HFA is not indicated for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm. An inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist, not ASMANEX HFA, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath. When prescribing ASMANEX HFA, the physician must also provide the patient with an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist (e.g., albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms, despite regular twice-daily (morning and evening) use of ASMANEX HFA. Instruct patients to contact their physician immediately if episodes of asthma that are not responsive to bronchodilators occur during the course of treatment with ASMANEX HFA. During such episodes, patients may require therapy with oral corticosteroids.



    5.2 Local Effects



  In clinical trials, the development of localized infections of the mouth and pharynx with Candida albicans  have occurred in patients treated with ASMANEX HFA. If oropharyngeal candidiasis develops, it should be treated with appropriate local or systemic (i.e., oral) antifungal therapy while remaining on treatment with ASMANEX HFA therapy, but at times therapy with ASMANEX HFA may need to be interrupted. Advise patients to rinse the mouth after inhalation of ASMANEX HFA.



    5.3 Immunosuppression



  Persons who are using drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infections than healthy individuals.



 Chickenpox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible children or adults using corticosteroids. In such children or adults who have not had these diseases or who are not properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If exposed to chickenpox, prophylaxis with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) may be indicated. If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See the respective package inserts for complete VZIG and IG prescribing information.) If chickenpox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.



 Inhaled corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection of the respiratory tract, untreated systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infections; or ocular herpes simplex.



    5.4 Transferring Patients from Systemic Corticosteroid Therapy



  Particular care is needed for patients who are transferred from systemically active corticosteroids to ASMANEX HFA because deaths due to adrenal insufficiency have occurred in asthmatic patients during and after transfer from systemic corticosteroids to less systemically available inhaled corticosteroids. After withdrawal from systemic corticosteroids, a number of months are required for recovery of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) function.



 Patients who have been previously maintained on 20 mg or more per day of prednisone (or its equivalent) may be most susceptible, particularly when their systemic corticosteroids have been almost completely withdrawn. During this period of HPA suppression, patients may exhibit signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency when exposed to trauma, surgery, or infection (particularly gastroenteritis) or other conditions associated with severe electrolyte loss. Although ASMANEX HFA may improve control of asthma symptoms during these episodes, in recommended doses it supplies less than normal physiological amounts of corticosteroid systemically and does NOT provide the mineralocorticoid activity necessary for coping with these emergencies.



 During periods of stress or severe asthma attack, patients who have been withdrawn from systemic corticosteroids should be instructed to resume oral corticosteroids (in large doses) immediately and to contact their physicians for further instruction. These patients should also be instructed to carry a medical identification card indicating that they may need supplementary systemic corticosteroids during periods of stress or severe asthma attack.



 Patients requiring oral or other systemic corticosteroids should be weaned slowly from oral or other systemic corticosteroid use after transferring to ASMANEX HFA. Lung function (FEV1or PEF), beta-agonist use, and asthma symptoms should be carefully monitored during withdrawal of oral or other systemic corticosteroids. In addition to monitoring asthma signs and symptoms, patients should be observed for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency such as fatigue, lassitude, weakness, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension.



 Transfer of patients from systemic corticosteroid therapy to ASMANEX HFA may unmask allergic conditions previously suppressed by the systemic corticosteroid therapy, e.g., rhinitis, conjunctivitis, eczema, arthritis, and eosinophilic conditions.



 During withdrawal from oral corticosteroids, some patients may experience symptoms of systemically active corticosteroid withdrawal, e.g., joint and/or muscular pain, lassitude, and depression, despite maintenance or even improvement of respiratory function.



    5.5 Hypercorticism and Adrenal Suppression



  ASMANEX HFA will often help control asthma symptoms with less suppression of HPA function than therapeutically equivalent oral doses of prednisone. Since mometasone furoate is absorbed into the circulation and can be systemically active at higher doses, the beneficial effects of ASMANEX HFA in minimizing HPA dysfunction may be expected only when recommended dosages are not exceeded and individual patients are titrated to the lowest effective dose.



 Because of the possibility of systemic absorption of inhaled corticosteroids, patients treated with ASMANEX HFA should be observed carefully for any evidence of systemic corticosteroid effects. Particular care should be taken in observing patients postoperatively or during periods of stress for evidence of inadequate adrenal response.



 It is possible that systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression (including adrenal crisis) may appear in a small number of patients, particularly when mometasone furoate is administered at higher than recommended doses over prolonged periods of time. If such effects occur, the dosage of ASMANEX HFA should be reduced slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for reducing systemic corticosteroids and for management of asthma symptoms.



    5.6 Drug Interactions with Strong Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors



  Caution should be exercised when considering the coadministration of ASMANEX HFA with ketoconazole, and other known strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) isoenzyme 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin) because adverse effects related to increased systemic exposure to mometasone furoate may occur [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.7 Paradoxical Bronchospasm and Upper Airway Symptoms



  ASMANEX HFA may produce inhalation induced bronchospasm with an immediate increase in wheezing after dosing that may be life-threatening. If inhalation induced bronchospasm occurs, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator. ASMANEX HFA should be discontinued immediately and alternative therapy instituted.



    5.8 Hypersensitivity Reactions Including Anaphylaxis



  Hypersensitivity reactions such as urticaria, flushing, allergic dermatitis, and bronchospasm, may occur after administration of ASMANEX HFA. Discontinue ASMANEX HFA if such reactions occur [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ].  



 The following additional hypersensitivity reactions, such as rash, pruritus, angioedema, and anaphylactic reaction, have been reported after administration of mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.9 Reduction in Bone Mineral Density



  Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) have been observed with long-term administration of products containing inhaled corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate. The clinical significance of small changes in BMD with regard to long-term outcomes, such as fracture, is unknown. Patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content, such as prolonged immobilization, family history of osteoporosis, or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass (e.g., anticonvulsants and corticosteroids) should be monitored and treated with established standards of care.



 In a 2-year double-blind study in 103 male and female asthma patients 18 to 50 years of age previously maintained on bronchodilator therapy (Baseline FEV185%-88% predicted), treatment with mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler 200 mcg twice daily resulted in significant reductions in lumbar spine (LS) BMD at the end of the treatment period compared to placebo. The mean change from Baseline to Endpoint in the lumbar spine BMD was -0.015 (-1.43%) for the mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler group compared to 0.002 (0.25%) for the placebo group. In another 2-year double-blind study in 87 male and female asthma patients 18 to 50 years of age previously maintained on bronchodilator therapy (Baseline FEV182%-83% predicted), treatment with mometasone furoate dry powder inhaler 400 mcg twice daily demonstrated no statistically significant changes in lumbar spine BMD at the end of the treatment period compared to placebo. The mean change from Baseline to Endpoint in the lumbar spine BMD was -0.018 (-1.57%) for the mometasone furoate group compared to -0.006 (-0.43%) for the placebo group.



    5.10 Effect on Growth



  Orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ASMANEX HFA, may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to pediatric patients. Monitor the growth of pediatric patients receiving ASMANEX HFA routinely (e.g., via stadiometry). To minimize the systemic effects of orally inhaled corticosteroids, including ASMANEX HFA, titrate each patient's dose to the lowest dosage that effectively controls his/her symptoms [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



    5.11 Glaucoma and Cataracts



  Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure, and cataracts have been reported following the use of long-term administration of inhaled corticosteroids, including mometasone furoate. Therefore, close monitoring is warranted in patients with a change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and/or cataracts [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
