<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aspirin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Hypersensitivity [ see Contraindications    (4.1)   ]. 
 *    Allergy [ see Contraindications    (4.2)   ]. 
 *    Risk of Bleeding [ see Warnings and Precautions    (5.1)   ]. 
   *    The most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;10% and greater than placebo) were headache, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, nausea, and diarrhea  (6)   
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1  Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The efficacy and safety of aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules was established in the European Stroke Prevention Study-2 (ESPS2). ESPS2 was a double-blind, placebo controlled study that evaluated 6602 patients over the age of 18 years who had a previous ischemic stroke or transient ischemic attack within ninety days prior to entry. Patients were randomized to either aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules, aspirin, ER-DP, or placebo [  see Clinical Studies      (14)    ]; primary endpoints included stroke (fatal or nonfatal) and death from all causes.



 This 24-month, multicenter, double-blind, randomized study (ESPS2) was conducted to compare the efficacy and safety of aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules with placebo, extended-release dipyridamole alone and aspirin alone. The study was conducted in a total of 6602 male and female patients who had experienced a previous ischemic stroke or transient ischemia of the brain within three months prior to randomization.



 Table 1 presents the incidence of adverse events that occurred in 1% or more of patients treated with aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules where the incidence was also greater than in those patients treated with placebo. There is no clear benefit of the dipyridamole/aspirin combination over aspirin with respect to safety.



 Table 1   Incidence of Adverse Events in ESPS2* 
                                                 Individual Treatment Group     
   Body System/Preferred Term                    ASA/ER-DP      ER-DP Alone      ASA Alone      Placebo     
  
 * Reported by &gt;=1% of patients during aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules treatment where the incidence was greater than in those treated with placebo.   
 Note:              ASA/ER-DP = aspirin 25 mg/extended release dipyridamole 200 mg; ER-DP = extended-release dipyridamole 200 mg; ASA = aspirin 25 mg. The dosage regimen for all treatment groups is BID                           NOS = not otherwise specified.   
                                                
  
  Total Number of Patients                      1650       1654      1649      1649    
  Total Number (%) of Patients With atLeast One On-Treatment AdverseEvent    1319       (80%)     1305      (79%)    1323    (80%)    1304    (79%)    
  Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders    
  Headache                                      647        (39%)     634       (38%)    558     (34%)    543     (33%)    
  Convulsions                                   28         (2%)      15        (1%)    28      (2%)    26      (2%)     
  Gastrointestinal System Disorders             
  Dyspepsia                                     303        (18%)     288       (17%)    299     (18%)    275     (17%)    
  Abdominal Pain                                289        (18%)     255       (15%)    262     (16%)    239     (14%)    
  Nausea                                        264        (16%)     254       (15%)    210     (13%)    232     (14%)    
  Diarrhea                                      210        (13%)     257       (16%)    112     (7%)    161     (10%)    
  Vomiting                                      138        (8%)      129       (8%)    101     (6%)    118     (7%)     
  Hemorrhage Rectum                             26         (2%)      22        (1%)    16      (1%)    13      (1%)     
  Melena                                        31         (2%)      10        (1%)    20      (1%)    13      (1%)     
  Hemorrhoids                                   16         (1%)      13        (1%)    10      (1%)    10      (1%)     
  GI Hemorrhage                                 20         (1%)      5         (0%)    15      (1%)    7       (0%)     
  Body as a Whole - General Disorders           
  Pain                                          105        (6%)      88        (5%)    103     (6%)    99      (6%)     
  Fatigue                                       95         (6%)      93        (6%)    97      (6%)    90      (5%)     
  Back Pain                                     76         (5%)      77        (5%)    74      (4%)    65      (4%)     
  Accidental Injury                             42         (3%)      24        (1%)    51      (3%)    37      (2%)     
  Malaise                                       27         (2%)      23        (1%)    26      (2%)    22      (1%)     
  Asthenia                                      29         (2%)      19        (1%)    17      (1%)    18      (1%)     
  Syncope                                       17         (1%)      13        (1%)    16      (1%)    8       (0%)     
  Psychiatric Disorders                         
  Amnesia                                       39         (2%)      40        (2%)    57      (3%)    34      (2%)     
  Confusion                                     18         (1%)      9         (1%)    22      (1%)    15      (1%)     
  Anorexia                                      19         (1%)      17        (1%)    10      (1%)    15      (1%)     
  Somnolence                                    20         (1%)      13        (1%)    18      (1%)    9       (1%)     
  Musculoskeletal System Disorders              
  Arthralgia                                    91         (6%)      75        (5%)    91      (6%)    76      (5%)     
  Arthritis                                     34         (2%)      25        (2%)    17      (1%)    19      (1%)     
  Arthrosis                                     18         (1%)      22        (1%)    13      (1%)    14      (1%)     
  Myalgia                                       20         (1%)      16        (1%)    11      (1%)    11      (1%)     
  Respiratory System Disorders                  
  Coughing                                      25         (2%)      18        (1%)    32      (2%)    21      (1%)     
  Upper Respiratory TractInfection              16         (1%)      9         (1%)    16      (1%)    14      (1%)     
  Cardiovascular Disorders, General             
  Cardiac Failure                               26         (2%)      17        (1%)    30      (2%)    25      (2%)     
  Platelet, Bleeding and Clotting Disorders     
  Hemorrhage NOS                                52         (3%)      24        (1%)    46      (3%)    24      (1%)     
  Epistaxis                                     39         (2%)      16        (1%)    45      (3%)    25      (2%)     
  Purpura                                       23         (1%)      8         (0%)    9       (1%)    7       (0%)     
  Neoplasm                                      
  Neoplasm NOS                                  28         (2%)      16        (1%)    23      (1%)    20      (1%)     
  Red Blood Cell Disorders                      
  Anemia                                        27         (2%)      16        (1%)    19      (1%)    9       (1%)     
               Discontinuation due to adverse events in ESPS2 was 25% for aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules, 25% for extended-release dipyridamole, 19% for aspirin, and 21% for placebo (refer to Table 2)
 

 Table 2 Incidence of Adverse Events that Led to the Discontinuation of Treatment: Adverse Events with an Incidence of &gt;=1% in the Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules Group 
                                              Treatment Groups              
                                              ASA/ER-DP      ER-DP      ASA      Placebo     
  
 Note: ASA/ER-DP = aspirin 25 mg/extended release dipyridamole 200 mg; ER-DP = extended-release dipyridamole 200 mg; ASA = aspirin 25 mg. The dosage regimen for all treatment groups is BID   
                                             
  
  Total Number of Patients                   1650     1654     1649     1649     
  Patients with at least one Adverse Eventthat led to treatment discontinuation    417      (25%)    419      (25%)    318       (19%)    352        (21%)      
  Headache                                   165      (10%)    166      (10%)    57        (3%)     69         (4%)       
  Dizziness                                  85       (5%)     97       (6%)     69        (4%)     68         (4%)       
  Nausea                                     91       (6%)     95       (6%)     51        (3%)     53         (3%)       
  Abdominal Pain                             74       (4%)     64       (4%)     56        (3%)     52         (3%)       
  Dyspepsia                                  59       (4%)     61       (4%)     49        (3%)     46         (3%)       
  Vomiting                                   53       (3%)     52       (3%)     28        (2%)     24         (1%)       
  Diarrhea                                   35       (2%)     41       (2%)     9         (&lt;1%)    16         (&lt;1%)      
  Stroke                                     39       (2%)     48       (3%)     57        (3%)     73         (4%)       
  Transient Ischemic Attack                  35       (2%)     40       (2%)     26        (2%)     48         (3%)       
  Angina Pectoris                            23       (1%)     20       (1%)     16        (&lt;1%)    26         (2%)       
               Headache was most notable in the first month of treatment.
 

   Other Adverse Events  Adverse reactions that occurred in less than 1% of patients treated with aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules in the ESPS2 study and that were medically judged to be possibly related to either dipyridamole or aspirin are listed below.



   Body as a Whole  : Allergic reaction, fever



   Cardiovascular  : Hypotension



   Central Nervous System  : Coma, dizziness, paresthesia, cerebral hemorrhage, intracranial hemorrhage, subarachnoid hemorrhage



   Gastrointestinal  : Gastritis, ulceration and perforation



   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders  : Tinnitus, and deafness. Patients with high frequency hearing loss may have difficulty perceiving tinnitus. In these patients, tinnitus cannot be used as a clinical indicator of salicylism



   Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders  : Tachycardia, palpitation, arrhythmia, supraventricular tachycardia



   Liver and Biliary System Disorders  : Cholelithiasis, jaundice, hepatic function abnormal



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  : Hyperglycemia, thirst



   Platelet, Bleeding and Clotting Disorders  : Hematoma, gingival bleeding



   Psychiatric Disorders  : Agitation



   Reproductive  : Uterine hemorrhage



   Respiratory  : Hyperpnea, asthma, bronchospasm, hemoptysis, pulmonary edema



   Special Senses Other Disorders  : Taste loss



   Skin and Appendages Disorders  : Pruritus, urticaria



   Urogenital  : Renal insufficiency and failure, hematuria



   Vascular (Extracardiac) Disorders  : Flushing



   Laboratory Changes  Over the course of the 24-month study (ESPS2), patients treated with aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules showed a decline (mean change from baseline) in hemoglobin of 0.25 g/dL, hematocrit of 0.75%, and erythrocyte count of 0.13x10  6  /mm  3  .



   6.2  Post-Marketing Experience

  The following is a list of additional adverse reactions that have been reported either in the literature or are from post-marketing spontaneous reports for either dipyridamole or aspirin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate reliably their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to aspirin and extended release dipyridamole capsules.



   Body as a Whole  : Hypothermia, chest pain



   Cardiovascular  : Angina pectoris



   Central Nervous System  : Cerebral edema



   Fluid and Electrolyte  : Hyperkalemia, metabolic acidosis, respiratory alkalosis, hypokalemia



   Gastrointestinal  : Pancreatitis, Reye syndrome, hematemesis



   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders  : Hearing loss



   Immune System Disorders  : Hypersensitivity, acute anaphylaxis, laryngeal edema



   Liver and Biliary System Disorders  : Hepatitis, hepatic failure



   Musculoskeletal  : Rhabdomyolysis



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  : Hypoglycemia, dehydration



   Platelet, Bleeding and Clotting Disorders  : Prolongation of the prothrombin time, disseminated intravascular coagulation, coagulopathy, thrombocytopenia



   Reproductive  : Prolonged pregnancy and labor, stillbirths, lower birth weight infants, antepartum and postpartum bleeding



   Respiratory  : Tachypnea, dyspnea



   Skin and Appendages Disorders  : Rash, alopecia, angioedema, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, skin hemorrhages such as bruising, ecchymosis, and hematoma



   Urogenital  : Interstitial nephritis, papillary necrosis, proteinuria



   Vascular (Extracardiac Disorders)  : Allergic vasculitis



   Other Adverse Events  : anorexia, aplastic anemia, migraine, pancytopenia, thrombocytosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules increases the risk of bleeding  (5.1)   
 *    Avoid use in patients with severe hepatic or renal insufficiency  (5.2  ,  5.3)   
 *    Can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman, especially in the third trimester  (5.4)   
    
 

   5.1  Risk of Bleeding



  Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules increases the risk of bleeding. Risk factors for bleeding include the use of other drugs that increase the risk of bleeding (e.g., anticoagulants, antiplatelet agents, heparin, fibrinolytic therapy, and chronic use of NSAIDs) [ see Drug Interactions  (7.1)    ].



   Intracranial Hemorrhage    In ESPS2 the incidence of intracranial hemorrhage was 0.6% in the Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules group, 0.5% in the extended-release dipyridamole (ER-DP) group, 0.4% in the aspirin (ASA) group and 0.4% in the placebo groups.
 

   Gastrointestinal (GI) Side Effects    GI side effects include stomach pain, heartburn, nausea, vomiting, and gross GI bleeding. Although minor upper GI symptoms, such as dyspepsia, are common and can occur anytime during therapy, physicians should remain alert for signs of ulceration and bleeding, even in the absence of previous GI symptoms. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of GI side effects and what steps to take if they occur.
 

 In ESPS2 the incidence of gastrointestinal bleeding was 4.1% in the Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules group, 2.2% in the extended-release dipyridamole group, 3.2% in the aspirin group, and 2.1% in the placebo groups.



   Peptic Ulcer Disease    Avoid using aspirin in patients with a history of active peptic ulcer disease, which can cause gastric mucosal irritation and bleeding.
 

   Alcohol Warning    Because Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules contains aspirin, counsel patients who consume three or more alcoholic drinks every day about the bleeding risks involved with chronic, heavy alcohol use while taking aspirin.
 

    5.2  Renal Failure



  Avoid aspirin in patients with severe renal failure (glomerular filtration rate less than 10 mL/minute) [ see Use in Specific Populations     (8.6)     and Clinical Pharmacology     (12.3)    ].



    5.3  Hepatic Insufficiency



  Elevations of hepatic enzymes and hepatic failure have been reported in association with dipyridamole administration [ see Use in Specific Populations     (8.6)     and Clinical Pharmacology     (12.3)    ].



    5.4  Pregnancy



  Because Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules contains aspirin, Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Maternal aspirin use during later stages of pregnancy may cause low birth weight, increased incidence for intracranial hemorrhage in premature infants, stillbirths and neonatal death. Because of the above and because of the known effects of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) on the fetal cardiovascular system (closure of the ductus arteriosus), avoid Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules in the third trimester of pregnancy [ see Use in Specific Populations     (8.1)    ].



 Aspirin has been shown to be teratogenic in rats (spina bifida, exencephaly, microphthalmia and coelosomia) and rabbits (congested fetuses, agenesis of skull and upper jaw, generalized edema with malformation of the head, and diaphanous skin) at oral doses of 330 mg/kg/day and 110 mg/kg/day, respectively. These doses, which also resulted in a high resorption rate in rats (63% of implantations versus 5% in controls), are, on a mg/m  2  basis, about 66 and 44 times, respectively, the dose of aspirin contained in the maximum recommended daily human dose of Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules. Reproduction studies with dipyridamole have been performed in mice, rabbits and rats at oral doses of up to 125 mg/kg, 40 mg/kg and 1000 mg/kg, respectively (about 11/2, 2 and 25 times the maximum recommended daily human oral dose, respectively, on a mg/m  2  basis) and have revealed no evidence of harm to the fetus due to dipyridamole. When 330 mg aspirin/kg/day was combined with 75 mg dipyridamole/kg/day in the rat, the resorption rate approached 100%, indicating potentiation of aspirin-related fetal toxicity. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of the use of Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules in pregnant women. If Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules, inform the patient of the potential hazard to the fetus.



    5.5  Coronary Artery Disease



  Dipyridamole has a vasodilatory effect. Chest pain may be precipitated or aggravated in patients with underlying coronary artery disease who are receiving dipyridamole.



 For stroke or TIA patients for whom aspirin is indicated to prevent recurrent myocardial infarction (MI) or angina pectoris, the aspirin in this product may not provide adequate treatment for the cardiac indications.



    5.6  Hypotension



  Dipyridamole produces peripheral vasodilation, which can exacerbate pre-existing hypotension.



    5.7  General



  Aspirin and Extended Release Dipyridamole Capsules are not interchangeable with the individual components of aspirin and dipyridamole tablets.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
