<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="astagraf" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse drug reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of labeling:



 *    Lymphoma and Other Malignancies [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.2  ) ] 
 *    Serious Infections [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.3  ) ] 
 *    Polyoma Virus Infections [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.6  ) ] 
 *    Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infections [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.7  ) ] 
 *    New Onset Diabetes after Transplant [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.8  ) ] 
 *    Nephrotoxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.9  ) ] 
 *    Neurotoxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.10  ) ] 
 *    Hyperkalemia [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.11  ) ] 
 *    Hypertension [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.12  ) ] 
 *    Pure Red Cell Aplasia [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.17  ) ] 
 *    Gastrointestinal Perforation [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.18  ) ] 
   *    The most common adverse reactions ( &gt;= 30%) are: diarrhea, constipation, nausea, peripheral edema, tremor and anemia (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Astellas Pharma US, Inc. at 1-800-727-7003 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. In addition, the clinical trials were not designed to establish comparative differences across study arms with regards to the adverse reactions discussed below.



 The data described below reflect exposure to ASTAGRAF XL in 545 renal transplant recipients exposed to ASTAGRAF XL for periods up to two years [  see  Clinical Studies  (  14  )  ].



 The most frequent diseases leading to transplantation were glomerulonephritis, polycystic kidney disease, nephrosclerosis/hypertensive nephropathy, and diabetic nephropathy in both studies.  Study 1: With Basiliximab Induction  



 The proportion of patients who discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions was 9% in the ASTAGRAF XL arm and 11% in the Prograf control arm through 12 months of treatment. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in ASTAGRAF XL-treated patients were related to infections or renal/urinary disorders. The most common (&gt;= 30%) adverse reactions observed in the ASTAGRAF XL group were: diarrhea, constipation, nausea, peripheral edema, tremor and anemia.  Study 2: Without Induction  



 The proportion of patients who discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions was 13% in the ASTAGRAF XL arm and 11% in the Prograf control arm through 12 months of treatment. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in ASTAGRAF XL-treated patients were related to infections, graft dysfunction, renal vascular/ischemic conditions and diabetes. The most common (&gt;=30%) adverse reaction observed in the ASTAGRAF XL group was anemia.



 Information on selected significant adverse reactions observed during Studies 1 and 2 are summarized below.  New Onset Diabetes After Transplant (NODAT)  



 New onset diabetes after transplantation (defined by the composite occurrence of &gt;= 2 fasting plasma glucose values that were &gt; 126 mg/dL at &gt;= 30 days apart, insulin use for &gt;= 30 consecutive days, oral hypoglycemic use for &gt;= 30 consecutive days, and/or HbA1C&gt;= 6.5%) is summarized in  Table 2  below for Study 1 and Study 2 through one year post-transplant.



 Table 2. Composite NODAT Through 1 Year Post-Transplant in Studies 1 and 2 
                                               Study 1             Study 2      
  ASTAGRAF XL  n (%)  (N=162)                  Prograf  n (%)  (N=151)    ASTAGRAF XL  n (%)  (N=288)    Prograf  n (%)  (N=299)    
  Composite NODAT                              58 (36)             53 (35)      105 (37)          90 (30)      
        &gt;= 2 Fasting Plasma Glucose Values       &gt;= 126 mg/dL &gt;= 30 days apart    42 (26)             35 (23)      51 (18)           47 (16)      
        Insulin use &gt;= 30 consecutive days     10 (6)              12 (8)       29 (10)           29 (10)      
        Oral hypoglycemic use &gt;= 30       consecutive days    22 (14)             13 (9)       20 (7)            23 (8)       
        HbA1C &gt;= 6.5%                          31 (19)             33 (22)      48 (17)           39 (13)      
             Infections  
 

 Adverse reactions of infectious etiology were reported based on clinical assessment by physicians. The causative organisms for these reactions are identified when provided by the physician. The overall number of infections, serious infections, and select infections with identified etiology reported in patients treated with ASTAGRAF XL or the control in Studies 1 and 2 are shown in  Table 3  .



 Table 3. Overall Infections and Select Infections by Treatment Group in Studies 1 and 2 Through One Year Post-Transplant 
                                           Study 1             Study 2        
  ASTAGRAF XL  n (%)  (N=214)              Prograf  n (%)  (N=212)    ASTAGRAF XL  n (%)  (N=331)    Prograf  n (%)  (N=336)    
  All Infections                           148 (69)            146 (69)       228 (69)           216 (64)      
     Serious Infections                    48 (22)             49 (23)        79 (24)            64 (19)       
     Bacterial Infections                  18 (8)              25 (12)        125 (38)           137 (41)      
     Respiratory Infections                73 (34)             65 (31)        75 (23)            74 (22)       
     Cytomegalovirus Infections            21 (10)             24 (11)        38 (12)            21 (6)        
     Polyomavirus Infections               6 (3)               10 (5)         7 (2)              1 (0)         
     Gastroenteritis                       16 (7)              6 (3)          16 (5)             8 (2)         
  Studies 1 and 2 were not designed to support comparative claims for ASTAGRAF XL for the adverse reactions reported in this table.    
             Glomerular Filtration Rate  
 

 The estimated mean glomerular filtration rates, using the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) formula, by treatment group at Month 12 in the ITT population in Studies 1 and 2 are shown in  Table 4  .



 Table 4. Estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (mL/min/1.73m2) by MDRD Formula at 12 Months Post-Transplant 
                                           Study 1             Study 2        
  ASTAGRAF XL  (n=201)                     Prograf  (n=202)    ASTAGRAF XL  (n=287)    Prograf  (n=300)    
  Month 1 Baseline Mean (SD)               56 (20)             56 (21)        51 (19)            52 (20)       
  Month 12 LOCFSubject's last observation carried forward (LOCF) for missing data at Month 1; patients who died, lost the graft or were lost to follow-up are imputed as zeroes                                                                        
     Mean (Standard deviation)             58 (21)             56 (23)        52 (20)            55 (19)       
     Median (Min-Max)                      56 (0, 177)         57 (0, 120)    54 (0, 116)        54 (0, 134)    
     Mean Difference XL-PrografTacrolimus XL-Prograf treatment mean difference results of analysis of covariance model with Month 1 Baseline as a covariate.    +2.3 (-1.2, +5.8)                   -1.8 (-4.6, +0.8)                  
           The incidence of adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 15% of ASTAGRAF XL-treated patients compared to control through one year of treatment in Studies 1 and 2 are shown in  Table 5  .
 

 Table 5. Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;= 15% of ASTAGRAF XL-Treated Kidney Transplant Patients Through One Year Post Transplant in Studies 1 or 2Studies 1 and 2 were not designed to support comparative claims for ASTAGRAF XL for the adverse reactions reported in this table. 
                                        Study 1               Study 2         
  Adverse Reactions                     ASTAGRAF XL  n (%)(N=214)    Prograf  n (%)(N=212)    ASTAGRAF XL  n (%)(N=331)    Prografn (%)  (N=336)    
  Anemia                                70 (33)               61 (29)         103 (31)          87 (26)          
  Constipation                          85 (40)               68 (32)         45 (14)           60 (18)          
  Diarrhea                              96 (45)               94 (44)         88 (27)           103 (31)         
  Fatigue                               34 (16)               22 (10)         7 (2)             6 (2)            
  Graft Dysfunction                     29 (14)               45 (21)         57 (17)           56 (17)          
  Headache                              46 (22)               50 (24)         39 (12)           33 (10)          
  Hyperglycemia                         34 (16)               39 (18)         61 (18)           65 (19)          
  Hyperkalemia                          43 (20)               49 (23)         50 (15)           49 (15)          
  Hyperlipidemia                        35 (16)               36 (17)         23 (7)            28 (8)           
  Hypertension                          59 (28)               63 (30)         80 (24)           76 (23)          
  Hypomagnesemia                        52 (24)               57 (27)         9 (3)             12 (4)           
  Hypophosphatemia                      50 (23)               59 (28)         15 (5)            22 (7)           
  Increased Blood Creatinine            40 (19)               49 (23)         54 (16)           63 (19)          
  Insomnia                              52 (24)               60 (28)         29 (9)            34 (10)          
  Leukopenia                            35 (16)               33 (16)         51 (15)           37 (11)          
  Nausea                                76 (36)               75 (35)         51 (15)           42 (13)          
  Peripheral Edema                      76 (36)               73 (34)         38 (12)           49 (15)          
  Tremor                                75 (35)               73 (34)         58 (18)           58 (17)          
  Urinary Tract Infection               34 (16)               53 (25)         7 (2)             10 (3)           
  Urinary Tract Infection (bacterial)    1 (1)                 6 (3)           86 (26)           102 (30)         
  Vomiting                              53 (25)               53 (25)         42 (13)           43 (13)          
             Less Frequently Reported Adverse Reactions (  &lt;  15%) by System Organ Class  
 

 The following adverse reactions were also reported in clinical studies of kidney transplant recipients who were treated with ASTAGRAF XL.  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Coagulopathy, hemolytic anemia, leukocytosis, neutropenia, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenia, thrombotic microangiopathy  Cardiac Disorders  



 Angina pectoris, atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, bradycardia, cardiac arrest, congestive cardiac failure, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, myocardial ischemia, myocardial infarction, pericardial effusion, tachycardia, ventricular extrasystoles  Ear Disorders  



 Hearing loss, otitis (media and externa), tinnitus  Eye Disorders  



 Vision blurred, conjunctivitis  Gastrointestinal Disorders  



 Abdominal distension, abdominal pain, aphthous stomatitis, ascites, colitis, dyspepsia, esophagitis, flatulence, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux disease, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, ileus, impaired gastric emptying, pancreatitis, stomach ulcer  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  



 Anasarca, asthenia, edema  Hepatobiliary Disorders  



 Abnormal hepatic function, cholestasis, hepatitis (acute and chronic), hepatotoxicity  Infections and Infestations  



 Condyloma acuminatum, Epstein-Barr virus infection, tinea versicolor  Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications  



 Fall  Investigations  



 Abnormal electrocardiogram T wave, increased blood lactate dehydrogenase, increased blood urea, increased hematocrit, increased hepatic enzyme, increased international normalized ratio, weight fluctuation  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  



 Anorexia, dehydration, fluid overload, hypercalcemia, hyperphosphatemia, hyperuricemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypoproteinemia, metabolic acidosis  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  



 Arthralgia, osteopenia, osteoporosis  Neoplasms  



 Bladder cancer, Kaposi's sarcoma, non-melanoma skin cancer, papillary thyroid cancer  Nervous System Disorders  



 Aphasia, carpal tunnel syndrome, cerebral infarction, cerebral ischemia, convulsion, dizziness, hypoesthesia, neurotoxicity, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, somnolence, syncope  Psychiatric Disorders  



 Agitation, anxiety, confusional state, depression, hallucination, mental status changes, mood swings, nightmare  Renal and Urinary Disorders  



 Anuria, hematuria, oliguria, proteinuria, renal failure, renal graft dysfunction, renal tubular necrosis, toxic nephropathy, urinary incontinence, urinary retention  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  



 Acute respiratory distress syndrome, allergic rhinitis, dyspnea, emphysema, hiccups, lung infiltration, pulmonary edema, productive cough, respiratory failure  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Acne, alopecia, dermatitis, hyperhidrosis, hypotrichosis, pruritus, rash  Vascular Disorders  



 Deep vein thrombosis, flushing, hemorrhage, hypotension, orthostatic hypotension



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported from worldwide marketing experience with tacrolimus. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Agranulocytosis, decreased blood fibrinogen, disseminated intravascular coagulation, hemolytic uremic syndrome, prolonged activated partial thromboplastin time, pure red cell aplasia [  see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.17  )  ], thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura  Cardiac Disorders  



 QT prolongation, supraventricular extrasystoles, supraventricular tachycardia, Torsade de Pointes, ventricular fibrillation  Eye Disorders  



 Blindness, photophobia, optic atrophy  Gastrointestinal Disorders  



 Dysphagia, gastrointestinal perforation [  see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.18  )  ], intestinal obstruction, peritonitis  General Disorders  



 Multi-organ failure  Hepatobiliary Disorders  



 Bile duct stenosis, cholangitis, cirrhosis, hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatic steatosis, jaundice, venoocclusive liver disease  Immune disorders  



 Graft versus host disease (acute and chronic)  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  



 Myalgia, polyarthritis, rhabdomyolysis  Neoplasms  



 Lymphoma including EBV-associated lymphoproliferative disorder, hepatosplenic T-cell lymphoma, PTLD [  see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.2  )  ]; leukemia, melanoma  Nervous System Disorders  



 Coma, dysarthria, flaccid paralysis, hemiparesis, mutism, nerve compression, posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES) [  see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.10  )  ], progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML) sometimes fatal [  see       Warnings and Precautions  (  5.6  )  ], quadriplegia, status epilepticus  Renal and Urinary Disorders  



 Hemorrhagic cystitis  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  



 Interstitial lung disease, pulmonary hypertension  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Hyperpigmentation, photosensitivity, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, urticaria
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: MALIGNANCIES;  SERIOUS INFECTIONS;  AND MORTALITY IN FEMALE LIVER TRANSPLANT RECIPIENTS

  WARNING: MALIGNANCIES;  SERIOUS INFECTIONS;  AND MORTALITY IN FEMALE LIVER TRANSPLANT RECIPIENTS

    *  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe ASTAGRAF XL. Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physician responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      Malignancies and Serious Infections  
 

 *  Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of malignancies such as lymphoma and skin cancer may result from immunosuppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2, 5.3, 5.6, 5.7)]. 
      Mortality in Liver Transplantation  
 

 *  Increased mortality in female transplant recipients was observed in a clinical trial of liver transplantation. Use in liver transplantation is not recommended [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: MALIGNANCIES;   SERIOUS INFECTIONS;   AND MORTALITY IN FEMALE LIVER TRANSPLANT RECIPIENTS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe ASTAGRAF XL (5.1) 
 *  Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of malignancies may result from immunosuppression (5.2, 5.3, 5.6, 5.7) 
 *  Use in liver transplantation is not recommended due to increased mortality rate in female liver transplant recipients (5.4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Medication errors have been reported including unintentional substitution between immediate-release tacrolimus and ASTAGRAF XL (extended-release) tacrolimus formulations (  5.5  ) 
 *    New Onset Diabetes After Transplant: Monitor blood glucose (  5.8  ) 
 *    Nephrotoxicity (acute and/or chronic): Monitor renal function; reduce the dose; use caution with other nephrotoxic drugs (  5.9  ) 
 *    Neurotoxicity, Risk of Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome (PRES): Monitor for neurologic abnormalities; reduce or discontinue immunosuppression (  5.10  ) 
 *    Hyperkalemia: Monitor serum potassium levels; use caution with other agents that increase potassium (  5.11  ) 
 *    Hypertension: May require antihypertensive therapy; monitor relevant drug-drug interactions (  5.12  ) 
 *    Use with Sirolimus: Not recommended; increased risk of serious adverse reactions in liver and heart transplant recipients (  5.13  ) 
 *    Use with Strong CYP3A Inhibitors and Inducers: Adjust tacrolimus dose and monitor trough concentrations and for occurrence of adverse reactions, including QT prolongation (  5.14  ,  5.15  ,  7  ) 
 *    Immunizations: Avoid use of live vaccines (  5.16  ) 
 *    Pure Red Cell Aplasia: Consider discontinuation (  5.17  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Immunosuppression



  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe ASTAGRAF XL. Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physicians responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patients [ see  Boxed Warning    ] .  



    5.2 Lymphoma and Other Malignancies



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including ASTAGRAF XL, are at increased risk of developing lymphomas and other malignancies, particularly of the skin [ see  Boxed Warning    ]. The risk appears to be related to the intensity and duration of immunosuppression rather than to the use of any specific agent.



 As usual for patients with increased risk for skin cancer, exposure to sunlight and UV light should be limited by wearing protective clothing and using a sunscreen with a high protection factor.



 Post-transplant lymphoproliferative disorder (PTLD) has been reported in immunosuppressed organ transplant recipients. The majority of PTLD events appear related to Epstein-Barr Virus (EBV) infection. The risk of PTLD appears greatest in those individuals who are EBV seronegative, a population which includes many young children.



    5.3 Serious Infections



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including ASTAGRAF XL, are at increased risk of developing bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections [ see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.6    ,   5.7  )  ]. These infections may lead to serious, including fatal, outcomes. Because of the danger of oversuppression of the immune system which can increase susceptibility to infection, combination immunosuppressant therapy should be used with caution.



    5.4 Liver Transplant Recipients



  In a clinical trial of 471 liver transplant recipients randomized to ASTAGRAF XL or Prograf, mortality at 12 months was 10% higher among the 76 female patients (18%) treated with ASTAGRAF XL compared to the 64 female patients (8%) treated with Prograf. Use of ASTAGRAF XL in liver transplantation is not recommended [ see  Boxed Warning    ].



    5.5 Medication Errors



  ASTAGRAF XL extended-release capsules are not interchangeable or substitutable with tacrolimus immediate-release capsules. Medication and dispensing errors, including inadvertent or unintentional substitution between twice daily immediate-release and ASTAGRAF XL (once daily extended-release) tacrolimus formulations have been observed in postmarketing surveillance of ASTAGRAF XL in countries where it is approved and marketed. This has led to serious adverse events, including graft rejection, or other adverse reactions, which could be a consequence of either under- or over-exposure to tacrolimus [ see  How Supplied  (  16  )  ].



 Note that ASTAGRAF XL is supplied in short, square bottles as well as in blister cartons containing 5 blister cards of 10 capsules on each card, and contains the statement "ONCE DAILY" on its label.



    5.6 Polyoma Virus Infections



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including ASTAGRAF XL, are at increased risk for opportunistic infections, including polyoma virus infections. Polyoma virus infections in transplant patients may have serious, and sometimes fatal, outcomes. These include polyoma virus-associated nephropathy (PVAN), mostly due to BK virus infection, and JC virus-associated progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), which have been observed in patients receiving ASTAGRAF XL [ see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.2  )  ]. PVAN is associated with serious outcomes, including deteriorating renal function and kidney graft loss. Patient monitoring may help detect patients at risk for PVAN.



 Cases of PML have been reported in patients treated with ASTAGRAF XL. PML, which is sometimes fatal, commonly presents with hemiparesis, apathy, confusion, cognitive deficiencies and ataxia. Risk factors for PML include treatment with immunosuppressant therapies and impairment of immune function. In immunosuppressed patients, physicians should consider PML in the differential diagnosis in patients reporting neurological symptoms and consultation with a neurologist should be considered as clinically indicated.



 Reductions in immunosuppression should be considered for patients who develop evidence of PVAN or PML. Physicians should also consider the risk that reduced immunosuppression represents to the functioning allograft.



    5.7 Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infections



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including ASTAGRAF XL, are at increased risk of developing CMV viremia and CMV disease. The risk of CMV disease is highest among transplant recipients seronegative for CMV at the time of transplant who receive a graft from a CMV seropositive donor. Therapeutic approaches to limiting CMV disease exist and should be routinely provided. Patient monitoring may help detect patients at risk for CMV disease. Consideration should be given to reducing the amount of immunosuppression in patients who develop CMV viremia and/or CMV disease.



    5.8 New Onset Diabetes after Transplant



  ASTAGRAF XL was shown to cause new onset diabetes mellitus in clinical trials of kidney transplant patients [ see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )  ]. New onset diabetes after transplantation may be reversible in some patients. Black and Hispanic kidney transplant patients are at an increased risk [ see  Use in Specific Populations  (  8.8  )  ]. Blood glucose concentrations should be monitored frequently in patients using ASTAGRAF XL.



    5.9 Nephrotoxicity



  ASTAGRAF XL, like other calcineurin-inhibitors, can cause acute or chronic nephrotoxicity, particularly when used in high doses. Acute nephrotoxicity is most often related to vasoconstriction of the afferent renal arteriole, is characterized by increasing serum creatinine, hyperkalemia, and/or a decrease in urine output, and is typically reversible. Chronic calcineurin-inhibitor nephrotoxicity is associated with increased serum creatinine, decreased kidney graft life, and characteristic histologic changes observed on renal biopsy; the changes associated with chronic calcineurin-inhibitor nephrotoxicity are typically progressive. Patients with impaired renal function should be monitored closely, as the dosage of ASTAGRAF XL may need to be reduced. In patients with persistent elevations of serum creatinine who are unresponsive to dosage adjustments, consideration should be given to changing to another immunosuppressive therapy.



 Due to the potential for additive or synergistic impairment of renal function, care should be taken when administering ASTAGRAF XL with drugs that may be associated with renal dysfunction. These include, but are not limited to, aminoglycosides, ganciclovir, amphotericin B, cisplatin, nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors (e.g., tenofovir) and protease inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, indinavir). Similarly, care should be exercised when administering with CYP3A inhibitors such as antifungal drugs (e.g., ketoconazole), calcium channel blockers (e.g., diltiazem, verapamil), and macrolide antibiotics (e.g., clarithromycin, erythromycin, troleandomycin), which will result in increased tacrolimus whole blood concentrations due to inhibition of tacrolimus metabolism [ see  Drug Interactions  (  7.4  ,  7.5  ,  7.6  ,  7.7  )  ].



    5.10 Neurotoxicity



  ASTAGRAF XL may cause a spectrum of neurotoxicities, particularly when used in high doses. The most severe neurotoxicities include posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES), delirium, and coma. Patients treated with tacrolimus have been reported to develop PRES. Symptoms indicating PRES include headache, altered mental status, seizures, visual disturbances and hypertension. Diagnosis may be confirmed by radiological procedure. If PRES is suspected or diagnosed, blood pressure control should be maintained and immediate reduction of immunosuppression is advised. This syndrome is characterized by reversal of symptoms upon reduction or discontinuation of immunosuppression.



 Coma and delirium, in the absence of PRES, have also been associated with high plasma concentrations of tacrolimus. Seizures have occurred in patients receiving tacrolimus    [ see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.2  )  ]. Other less severe neurotoxicities, include tremors, paresthesias, headache, and other changes in motor function, mental status, and sensory function have also been reported [ see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )  ] .  Tremor and headache have been associated with high whole-blood concentrations of tacrolimus and may respond to dosage adjustment.



    5.11 Hyperkalemia



  Hyperkalemia has been reported with ASTAGRAF XL use. Serum potassium levels should be monitored. Careful consideration should be given prior to use of other agents also associated with hyperkalemia (e.g., potassium-sparing diuretics, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers) during ASTAGRAF XL therapy [ see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )  ] .  



    5.12 Hypertension



  Hypertension is a common adverse effect of ASTAGRAF XL therapy and may require antihypertensive therapy [ see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )  ] .  The control of blood pressure can be accomplished with any of the common antihypertensive agents, though careful consideration should be given prior to use of antihypertensive agents associated with hyperkalemia (e.g., potassium-sparing diuretics, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers) [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.11  )  ]. Calcium-channel blocking agents may increase tacrolimus blood concentrations and therefore require dosage reduction of ASTAGRAF XL [ see  Drug Interactions  (  7.6  )  ]. 



    5.13 Use with Sirolimus



  The use of ASTAGRAF XL with sirolimus is not recommended in kidney transplant patients. Use of sirolimus with tacrolimus in studies of de novo  liver transplant recipients was associated with an excess mortality, graft loss and hepatic artery thrombosis (HAT). Use of sirolimus with tacrolimus in heart transplant patients was associated with an increased risk of renal function impairment, wound healing complications, and insulin-dependent post-transplant diabetes mellitus.



    5.14 Use with CYP3A Inhibitors and Inducers



  When coadministering ASTAGRAF XL with strong CYP3A-inhibitors (e.g., telaprevir, boceprevir, ritonavir, ketoconazole, itraconazole, voriconazole, clarithromycin) and strong CYP3A inducers (e.g., rifampin, rifabutin), adjustments in the dosing regimen of ASTAGRAF XL and subsequent frequent monitoring of tacrolimus whole blood trough concentrations and tacrolimus-associated adverse reactions are recommended [ see  Drug Interactions  (  7  )  ].



    5.15 QT Prolongation



  ASTAGRAF XL may prolong the QT/QTc interval and may cause Torsade de Pointes. Avoid ASTAGRAF XL in patients with congenital long QT syndrome. In patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, those taking certain antiarrhythmic medications or other medicinal products that lead to QT prolongation, and those with electrolyte disturbances such as hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, or hypomagnesemia, consider obtaining electrocardiograms and monitoring electrolytes (magnesium, potassium, calcium) periodically during treatment.



 When coadministering ASTAGRAF XL with other substrates and/or inhibitors of CYP3A that also have the potential to prolong the QT interval, a reduction in ASTAGRAF XL dose, frequent monitoring of tacrolimus whole blood concentrations, and monitoring for QT prolongation is recommended. Use of tacrolimus with amiodarone has been reported to result in increased tacrolimus whole blood concentrations with or without concurrent QT prolongation [ see  Drug Interactions  (  7  )  ].



    5.16 Immunizations



  The use of live vaccines should be avoided during treatment with ASTAGRAF XL; examples include (not limited to) the following: intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, BCG, yellow fever, varicella, and TY21a typhoid vaccines.



    5.17 Pure Red Cell Aplasia



  Cases of pure red cell aplasia (PRCA) have been reported in patients treated with tacrolimus. A mechanism for tacrolimus-induced PRCA has not been elucidated. All patients reported risk factors for PRCA such as parvovirus B19 infection, underlying disease, or concomitant medications associated with PRCA. If PRCA is diagnosed, discontinuation of ASTAGRAF XL should be considered.



    5.18 Gastrointestinal Perforation



  Gastrointestinal perforation has been reported in patients treated with tacrolimus; all reported cases were considered to be a complication of transplant surgery or accompanied by infection, diverticulum, or malignant neoplasm. As gastrointestinal perforation may be serious or life-threatening, appropriate medical/surgical management should be instituted promptly [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.2  )]  . 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
