<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="atacand0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  



   EXCERPT:   . Most common adverse reactions which caused adult patients to discontinue therapy for:



 . Hypertension were headache (0.6%) and dizziness (0.3%) (6.1).



 . Heart Failure were hypotension (4.1%) (5.3), abnormal renal function (6.3%) (5.5), and hyperkalemia (2.4%) (5.6).



 . Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 2% and greater than placebo) are back pain, dizziness, upper respiratory tract infection, pharyngitis and rhinitis (6.1).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adult Hypertension  



 ATACAND has been evaluated for safety in more than 3600 patients/subjects, including more than 3200 patients treated for hypertension. About 600 of these patients were studied for at least 6 months and about 200 for at least 1 year. In general, treatment with ATACAND was well tolerated. The overall incidence of adverse events reported with ATACAND was similar to placebo.



 The rate of withdrawals due to adverse events in all trials in patients (7510 total) was 3.3% (ie, 108 of 3260) of patients treated with ATACAND as monotherapy and 3.5% (ie, 39 of 1106) of patients treated with placebo. In placebo-controlled trials, discontinuation of therapy due to clinical adverse events occurred in 2.4% (ie, 57 of 2350) of patients treated with ATACAND and 3.4% (ie, 35 of 1027) of patients treated with placebo.



 The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy with ATACAND were headache (0.6%) and dizziness (0.3%).



 The adverse events that occurred in placebo-controlled clinical trials in at least 1% of patients treated with ATACAND and at a higher incidence in candesartan cilexetil (n = 2350) than placebo (n = 1027) patients included back pain (3% vs. 2%), dizziness (4% vs. 3%), upper respiratory tract infection (6% vs. 4%), pharyngitis (2% vs. 1%), and rhinitis (2% vs. 1%).



 The following adverse events occurred in placebo-controlled clinical trials at a more than 1% rate but at about the same or greater incidence in patients receiving placebo compared to ATACAND: fatigue, peripheral edema, chest pain, headache, bronchitis, coughing, sinusitis, nausea, abdominal pain, diarrhea, vomiting, arthralgia, albuminuria.



 Other potentially important adverse events that have been reported, whether or not attributed to treatment, with an incidence of 0.5% or greater from the 3260 patients worldwide treated in clinical trials with ATACAND are listed below. It cannot be determined whether these events were causally related to ATACAND.  Body as a Whole:  asthenia, fever;  Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  paresthesia, vertigo;  Gastrointestinal System Disorder:  dyspepsia, gastroenteritis;  Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders:  tachycardia, palpitation;  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  creatine phosphokinase increased, hyperglycemia, hypertriglyceridemia, hyperuricemia;  Musculoskeletal System Disorders:  myalgia;  Platelet/Bleeding-Clotting Disorders:  epistaxis;  Psychiatric Disorders:  anxiety, depression, somnolence;  Respiratory System Disorders:  dyspnea;  Skin and Appendages Disorders:  rash, sweating increased;  Urinary System Disorders:  hematuria.



 Other reported events seen less frequently included angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, and angioedema.



 Adverse events occurred at about the same rates in men and women, older and younger patients, and black and non-black patients.



   Pediatric Hypertension  



 Among children in clinical studies, 1 in 93 children age 1 to &lt; 6 and 3 in 240 age 6 to &lt; 17 experienced worsening renal disease. The association between candesartan and exacerbation of the underlying condition could not be excluded.



   Heart Failure  



 The adverse event profile of ATACAND in adult heart failure patients was consistent with the pharmacology of the drug and the health status of the patients. In the CHARM program, comparing ATACAND in total daily doses up to 32 mg once daily (n=3803) with placebo (n=3796), 21.0% of patients discontinued ATACAND for adverse events vs. 16.1% of placebo patients.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions were identified during post-approval use of ATACAND. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following have been very rarely reported in post-marketing experience:



   Digestive:  Abnormal hepatic function and hepatitis.



   Hematologic:  Neutropenia, leukopenia, and agranulocytosis.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  hyperkalemia, hyponatremia.



   Renal:  renal impairment, renal failure.



   Skin and Appendages Disorders:  Pruritus and urticaria.



 Rare reports of rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers.



   6.3 Laboratory Test Findings

    Hypertension  



 In controlled clinical trials, clinically important changes in standard laboratory parameters were rarely associated with the administration of ATACAND.



   Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen  



 Minor increases in blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine were observed infrequently.



   Hyperuricemia  



 Hyperuricemia was rarely found (19 or 0.6% of 3260 patients treated with ATACAND and 5 or 0.5% of 1106 patients treated with placebo).



   Hemoglobin and Hematocrit  



 Small decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit (mean decreases of approximately 0.2 grams/dL and 0.5 volume percent, respectively) were observed in patients treated with ATACAND alone but were rarely of clinical importance. Anemia, leukopenia, and thrombocytopenia were associated with withdrawal of one patient each from clinical trials.



   Potassium  



 A small increase (mean increase of 0.1 mEq/L) was observed in patients treated with ATACAND alone but was rarely of clinical importance. One patient from a congestive heart failure trial was withdrawn for hyperkalemia (serum potassium = 7.5 mEq/L). This patient was also receiving spironolactone  [see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  (5.6)].  



   Liver Function Tests  



 Elevations of liver enzymes and/or serum bilirubin were observed infrequently. Five patients assigned to ATACAND in clinical trials were withdrawn because of abnormal liver chemistries. All had elevated transaminases. Two had mildly elevated total bilirubin, but one of these patients was diagnosed with Hepatitis A.



   Heart Failure  



 In the CHARM program, small increases in serum creatinine (mean increase 0.2 mg/dL in candesartan-treated patients and 0.1 mg/dL in placebo-treated patients) and serum potassium (mean increase 0.15 mEq/L in ATACAND-treated patients and 0.02 mEq/L in placebo-treated patients), and small decreases in hemoglobin (mean decrease 0.5 gm/dL in ATACAND-treated patients and 0.3 gm/dL in placebo-treated patients) and hematocrit (mean decrease 1.6% in ATACAND-treated patients and 0.9% in placebo-treated patients) were observed.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Warning Use in Pregnancy

  Warning Use in Pregnancy

    When used in pregnancy during the second and third trimesters, drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus.    When pregnancy is detected, ATACAND should  be discontinued as soon as possible    [see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS, Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality (5.1)].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: USE IN PREGNANCY:   See Full Prescribing Information for complete boxed warning.    



   When used in pregnancy during the second and third trimesters, drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus.    When pregnancy is detected, ATACAND should  be discontinued as soon as possible.  See WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS, Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality (5.1).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  



   EXCERPT:   . Avoid fetal (in utero) and neonatal exposure (5.1).



 . Children &lt; 1 year of age must not receive ATACAND for hypertension (5.2).



 . Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension (5.3).



 . Use with caution in patients with impaired hepatic (5.4) or renal (5.5) function.



 . Hyperkalemia may occur in heart failure patients treated with ATACAND (5.6).



 



   5.1 Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality



  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause fetal and neonatal morbidity and death when administered to pregnant women. Several dozen cases have been reported in the world literature in patients who were taking angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors. Post-marketing experience has identified reports of fetal and neonatal toxicity in babies born to women treated with ATACAND during pregnancy. When pregnancy is detected, ATACAND should be discontinued as soon as possible.



 The use of drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy has been associated with fetal and neonatal injury, including hypotension, neonatal skull hypoplasia, anuria, reversible or irreversible renal failure, and death. Oligohydramnios has also been reported, presumably resulting from decreased fetal renal function; oligohydramnios in this setting has been associated with fetal limb contractures, craniofacial deformation, and hypoplastic lung development. Prematurity, intrauterine growth retardation, and patent ductus arteriosus have also been reported, although it is not clear whether these occurrences were due to exposure to the drug.



 These adverse effects do not appear to have resulted from intrauterine drug exposure that has been limited to the first trimester. Mothers whose embryos and fetuses are exposed to an angiotensin II receptor antagonist only during the first trimester should be so informed. Nonetheless, when patients become pregnant, physicians should have the patient discontinue the use of ATACAND as soon as possible.



 Rarely (probably less often than once in every thousand pregnancies), no alternative to a drug acting on the renin-angiotensin system will be found. In these rare cases, the mothers should be apprised of the potential hazards to their fetuses, and serial ultrasound examinations should be performed to assess the intra-amniotic environment.



 If oligohydramnios is observed, ATACAND should be discontinued unless it is considered life saving for the mother. Contraction stress testing (CST), a nonstress test (NST), or biophysical profiling (BPP) may be appropriate, depending upon the week of pregnancy. Patients and physicians should be aware, however, that oligohydramnios may not appear until after the fetus has sustained irreversible injury.



 Infants with histories of in utero  exposure to an angiotensin II receptor antagonist should be closely observed for hypotension, oliguria, and hyperkalemia. If oliguria occurs, attention should be directed toward support of blood pressure and renal perfusion. Exchange transfusion or dialysis may be required as means of reversing hypotension and/or substituting for disordered renal function.



 Oral doses &gt;=10 mg of candesartan cilexetil/kg/day administered to pregnant rats during late gestation and continued through lactation were associated with reduced survival and an increased incidence of hydronephrosis in the offspring. The 10-mg/kg/day dose in rats is approximately 2.8 times the maximum recommended daily human dose (MRHD) of 32 mg on a mg/m  2  basis (comparison assumes human body weight of 50 kg). Candesartan cilexetil given to pregnant rabbits at an oral dose of 3 mg/kg/day (approximately 1.7 times the MRHD on a mg/m  2  basis) caused maternal toxicity (decreased body weight and death) but, in surviving dams, had no adverse effects on fetal survival, fetal weight, or external, visceral, or skeletal development. No maternal toxicity or adverse effects on fetal development were observed when oral doses up to 1000 mg of candesartan cilexetil/kg/day (approximately 138 times the MRHD on a mg/m  2  basis) were administered to pregnant mice.



    5.2 Morbidity in Infants



  Children &lt; 1 year of age must not receive ATACAND for hypertension. The consequences of administering drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) can have effects on the development of immature kidneys.



    5.3 Hypotension



  In adult or children patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- and/or salt-depleted patients (eg, those being treated with diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur. These conditions should be corrected prior to administration of ATACAND, or the treatment should start under close medical supervision [see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  (2.1)].  



 If hypotension occurs, the patients should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.



 Caution should be observed when initiating therapy in patients with heart failure. Patients with heart failure given ATACAND commonly have some reduction in blood pressure. In patients with symptomatic hypotension this may require temporarily reducing the dose of ATACAND, or diuretic, or both, and volume repletion. In the CHARM program, hypotension was reported in 18.8% of patients on ATACAND versus 9.8% of patients on placebo. The incidence of hypotension leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 4.1% compared with 2.0% in placebo-treated patients.



 Monitoring of blood pressure is recommended during dose escalation and periodically thereafter.



  Major Surgery/Anesthesia  



 Hypotension may occur during major surgery and anesthesia in patients treated with angiotensin II receptor antagonists, including ATACAND, due to blockade of the renin-angiotensin system. Very rarely, hypotension may be severe such that it may warrant the use of intravenous fluids and/or vasopressors.



    5.4 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Based on pharmacokinetic data which demonstrate significant increases in candesartan AUC and Cmaxin patients with moderate hepatic impairment, a lower initiating dose should be considered for patients with moderate hepatic impairment [see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY  (12.3)].  



    5.5 Renal Function Deterioration



  As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may be anticipated in some individuals treated with ATACAND. In patients whose renal function may depend upon the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (eg, patients with severe heart failure), treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar results may be anticipated in patients treated with ATACAND [see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY  (12.3)].  



 In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen (BUN) have been reported. There has been no long-term use of ATACAND in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but similar results may be expected.



 In heart failure patients treated with ATACAND, increases in serum creatinine may occur. Dosage reduction or discontinuation of the diuretic or ATACAND, and volume repletion may be required. In the CHARM program, the incidence of abnormal renal function (e.g., creatinine increase) was 12.5% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 6.3% in patients treated with placebo. The incidence of abnormal renal function (eg, creatinine increase) leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 6.3% compared with 2.9% in placebo-treated patients. Evaluation of patients with heart failure should always include assessment of renal function and volume status. Monitoring of serum creatinine is recommended during dose escalation and periodically thereafter.



 Pediatrics - ATACAND has not been studied in children with estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m  2  .



    5.6 Hyperkalemia



  In heart failure patients treated with ATACAND, hyperkalemia may occur, especially when taken concomitantly with ACE inhibitors and potassium-sparing diuretics such as spironolactone. In the CHARM program, the incidence of hyperkalemia was 6.3% in patients treated with ATACAND versus 2.1% in patients treated with placebo. The incidence of hyperkalemia leading to drug discontinuation in ATACAND-treated patients was 2.4% compared with 0.6% in placebo-treated patients. During treatment with ATACAND in patients with heart failure, monitoring of serum potassium is recommended during dose escalation and periodically thereafter.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
