<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="atovaquone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because many patients who participated in clinical trials with Atovaquone had complications of advanced HIV disease, it was often difficult to distinguish adverse events caused by Atovaquone from those caused by underlying medical conditions. There were no life-threatening or fatal adverse experiences caused by Atovaquone.



   PCP Prevention Studies

  In the dapsone comparative study of Atovaquone Suspension, adverse experience data were collected only for treatment-limiting events. Among the entire population (n = 1,057), treatment-limiting events occurred at similar frequencies in patients treated with Atovaquone Suspension or dapsone (Table 6). Among patients who were taking neither dapsone nor atovaquone at enrollment (n = 487), treatment-limiting events occurred in 43% of patients treated with dapsone and 20% of patients treated with Atovaquone Suspension (  P   &lt;0.001). In both populations, the type of treatment-limiting events differed between the 2 treatment arms. Hypersensitivity reactions (rash, fever, allergic reaction) and anemia were more common in patients treated with dapsone, while gastrointestinal events (nausea, diarrhea, and vomiting) were more common in patients treated with Atovaquone Suspension.



 Table 6. Treatment-Limiting Adverse Experiences in the Dapsone Comparative PCP Prevention Study 
  Treatment-Limiting  Adverse Experience    Percentage of Patients with Treatment-Limiting Adverse Experience    
  All Patients           Patients Not Taking Either Drug at Enrollment    
  Atovaquone  1,500 mg/day  (n = 536)    Dapsone  100 mg/day  (n = 521)    Atovaquone  1,500 mg/day  (n = 238)    Dapsone  100 mg/day  (n = 249)    
  Any event              24.4                25.9              20.2                      43.4                   
  Rash                   6.3                 8.8               7.6                       16.1                   
  Nausea                 4.1                 0.6               2.5                       0.8                    
  Diarrhea               3.2                 0.2               2.1                       0.4                    
  Vomiting               2.2                 0.6               1.3                       0.8                    
  Allergic reaction      1.1                 2.9               0.8                       4.8                    
  Fever                  0.6                 2.9               0                         5.6                    
  Anemia                 0                   1.5               0                         2.0                    
           Table 7 summarizes the clinical adverse experiences reported by &gt;=20% of patients in any group in the aerosolized pentamidine comparative study of Atovaquone Suspension (n = 549), regardless of attribution. The incidence of adverse experiences at the recommended dose was similar to that seen with aerosolized pentamidine. Rash was the only individual adverse experience that occurred significantly more commonly in patients treated with both dosages of Atovaquone Suspension (39% to 46%) than in patients treated with aerosolized pentamidine (28%). Among patients treated with Atovaquone Suspension, there was no evidence of a dose-related increase in the incidence of adverse experiences. Treatment-limiting adverse experiences occurred less often in patients treated with aerosolized pentamidine (7%) than in patients treated with 1,500 mg Atovaquone Suspension once daily (25%,  P  &lt;=0.001) or 750 mg Atovaquone Suspension once daily (16%,  P   = 0.004). The most common adverse experiences requiring discontinuation of dosing in the group receiving 1,500 mg Atovaquone Suspension once daily were rash (6%), diarrhea (4%), and nausea (3%). The most common adverse experience requiring discontinuation of dosing in the group receiving aerosolized pentamidine was bronchospasm (2%).
 

 Table 7. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experiences in the Aerosolized Pentamidine Comparative PCP Prevention Study 
  Treatment-Emergent  Adverse Experience    Percentage of Patients with Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience    
  Atovaquone  1,500 mg/day  (n = 175)       Atovaquone  750 mg/day  (n = 188)    Aerosolized  Pentamidine  (n = 186)    
  Diarrhea                                  42                     42                   35                    
  Rash                                      39                     46                   28                    
  Headache                                  28                     31                   22                    
  Nausea                                    26                     32                   23                    
  Cough increased                           25                     25                   31                    
  Fever                                     25                     31                   18                    
  Rhinitis                                  24                     18                   17                    
  Asthenia                                  22                     31                   31                    
  Infection                                 22                     18                   19                    
  Abdominal pain                            20                     21                   20                    
  Dyspnea                                   15                     21                   16                    
  Vomiting                                  15                     22                   11                    
  Patients discontinuing therapy due to an adverse experience    25                     16                   7                     
  Patients reporting at least 1 adverse experience    98                     96                   89                    
          Other events occurring in &gt;=10% of the patients receiving the recommended dose of Atovaquone included sweating, flu syndrome, pain, sinusitis, pruritus, insomnia, depression, and myalgia. Bronchospasm occurred more frequently in patients receiving aerosolized pentamidine (11%) than in patients receiving Atovaquone 1,500 mg/day (4%) and Atovaquone 750 mg/day (2%).
 

 Neither Atovaquone nor aerosolized pentamidine was associated with a substantial change from baseline values in any measured laboratory parameter, nor were there any significant differences in any measured laboratory parameter between Atovaquone and aerosolized pentamidine. Some patients had laboratory abnormalities considered serious by the investigator or that contributed to discontinuation of therapy.



   PCP Treatment Studies

  Table 8 summarizes all the clinical adverse experiences reported by &gt;=5% of the study population during the TMP-SMX comparative study of Atovaquone (n = 408), regardless of attribution. The incidence of adverse experiences with Atovaquone Suspension at the recommended dose was similar to that seen with the tablet formulation of atovaquone.



 Table 8. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experiences in the TMP-SMX Comparative PCP Treatment Study 
                                                Percentage of Patients with Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience    
  Treatment-Emergent  Adverse Experience        Atovaquone  (n = 203)          TMP-SMX  (n = 205)           
  Rash (including maculopapular)                23                             34                           
  Nausea                                        21                             44                           
  Diarrhea                                      19                             7                            
  Headache                                      16                             22                           
  Vomiting                                      14                             35                           
  Fever                                         14                             25                           
  Insomnia                                      10                             9                            
  Asthenia                                      8                              8                            
  Pruritus                                      5                              9                            
  Monilia, oral                                 5                              10                           
  Abdominal pain                                4                              7                            
  Constipation                                  3                              17                           
  Dizziness                                     3                              8                            
  Patients discontinuing therapy due to an adverse experience    9                              24                           
  Patients reporting at least 1 adverse experience    63                             65                           
         Although an equal percentage of patients receiving Atovaquone and TMP-SMX reported at least 1 adverse experience, more patients receiving TMP-SMX required discontinuation of therapy due to an adverse event. Twenty-four percent of patients receiving TMP-SMX were prematurely discontinued from therapy due to an adverse experience versus 9% of patients receiving Atovaquone. Four percent of patients receiving Atovaquone had therapy discontinued due to development of rash. The majority of cases of rash among patients receiving Atovaquone were mild and did not require the discontinuation of dosing. The only other clinical adverse experience that led to premature discontinuation of dosing of Atovaquone by more than 1 patient was vomiting (&lt;1%). The most common adverse experience requiring discontinuation of dosing in the TMP-SMX group was rash (8%).
 

 Laboratory test abnormalities reported for &gt;=5% of the study population during the treatment period are summarized in Table 9. Two percent of patients treated with Atovaquone and 7% of patients treated with TMP-SMX had therapy prematurely discontinued due to elevations in ALT/AST. In general, patients treated with Atovaquone developed fewer abnormalities in measures of hepatocellular function (ALT, AST, alkaline phosphatase) or amylase values than patients treated with TMP-SMX.



 Table 9. Treatment-Emergent Laboratory Test Abnormalities in the TMP-SMX Comparative PCP Treatment Study 
  Laboratory Test Abnormality              Percentage of Patients Developing a Laboratory Test Abnormality    
  Atovaquone                               TMP-SMX                           
  Anemia (Hgb&lt;8.0 g/dL)                    6                                 7                              
  Neutropenia (ANC&lt;750 cells/mm3)          3                                 9                              
  Elevated ALT (&gt;5 x ULN)                  6                                 16                             
  Elevated AST (&gt;5 x ULN)                  4                                 14                             
  Elevated alkaline phosphatase (&gt;2.5 x ULN)    8                                 6                              
  Elevated amylase (&gt;1.5 x ULN)            7                                 12                             
  Hyponatremia (&lt;0.96 x LLN)               7                                 26                             
         ULN = upper limit of normal range.
 

 LLN = lower limit of normal range.



 Table 10 summarizes the clinical adverse experiences reported by &gt;=5% of the primary therapy study population (n = 144) during the comparative trial of Atovaquone and intravenous pentamidine, regardless of attribution. A slightly lower percentage of patients who received Atovaquone reported occurrence of adverse events than did those who received pentamidine (63% vs 72%). However, only 7% of patients discontinued treatment with Atovaquone due to adverse events, while 41% of patients who received pentamidine discontinued treatment for this reason (  P  &lt;0.001). Of the 5 patients who discontinued therapy with Atovaquone, 3 reported rash (4%). Rash was not severe in any patient. No other reason for discontinuation of Atovaquone was cited more than once. The most frequently cited reasons for discontinuation of pentamidine therapy were hypoglycemia (11%) and vomiting (9%).



 Table 10. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experiences in the Pentamidine Comparative PCP Treatment Study (Primary Therapy Group) 
  Treatment-Emergent  Adverse Experience       Percentage of Patients with Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience    
  Atovaquone  (n = 73)                         Pentamidine  (n = 71)         
  Fever                                        40                            25                             
  Nausea                                       22                            37                             
  Rash                                         22                            13                             
  Diarrhea                                     21                            31                             
  Insomnia                                     19                            14                             
  Headache                                     18                            28                             
  Vomiting                                     14                            17                             
  Cough                                        14                            1                              
  Abdominal pain                               10                            11                             
  Pain                                         10                            10                             
  Sweat                                        10                            3                              
  Monilia, oral                                10                            3                              
  Asthenia                                     8                             14                             
  Dizziness                                    8                             14                             
  Anxiety                                      7                             10                             
  Anorexia                                     7                             10                             
  Sinusitis                                    7                             6                              
  Dyspepsia                                    5                             10                             
  Rhinitis                                     5                             7                              
  Taste perversion                             3                             13                             
  Hypoglycemia                                 1                             15                             
  Hypotension                                  1                             10                             
  Patients discontinuing therapy due to an adverse experience    7                             41                             
  Patients reporting at least 1 adverse experience    63                            72                             
         Laboratory test abnormalities reported in &gt;=5% of patients in the pentamidine comparative study are presented in Table 11. Laboratory abnormality was reported as the reason for discontinuation of treatment in 2 of 73 patients who received Atovaquone. One patient (1%) had elevated creatinine and BUN levels and 1 patient (1%) had elevated amylase levels. Laboratory abnormalities were the sole or contributing factor in 14 patients who prematurely discontinued pentamidine therapy. In the 71 patients who received pentamidine, laboratory parameters most frequently reported as reasons for discontinuation were hypoglycemia (11%), elevated creatinine levels (6%), and leukopenia (4%).
 

 Table 11. Treatment-Emergent Laboratory Test Abnormalities in the Pentamidine Comparative PCP Treatment Study 
  Laboratory Test Abnormality         Percentage of Patients Developing a Laboratory Test Abnormality    
  Atovaquone                          Pentamidine                       
  Anemia (Hgb&lt;8.0 g/dL)               4                                 9                                  
  Neutropenia (ANC&lt;750 cells/mm3)     5                                 9                                  
  Hyponatremia (&lt;0.96 x LLN)          10                                10                                 
  Hyperkalemia (&gt;1.18 x ULN)          0                                 5                                  
  Alkaline phosphatase (&gt;2.5 x ULN)    5                                 2                                  
  Hyperglycemia (&gt;1.8 x ULN)          9                                 13                                 
  Elevated AST (&gt;5 x ULN)             0                                 5                                  
  Elevated amylase (&gt;1.5 x ULN)       8                                 4                                  
  Elevated creatinine (&gt;1.5 x ULN)    0                                 7                                  
         ULN = upper limit of normal range.
 

 LLN = lower limit of normal range.



   Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse events reported from clinical trials, the following events have been identified during post-approval use of Atovaquone. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to Atovaquone.



     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  

  Methemoglobinemia, thrombocytopenia.



     Immune System Disorders  

  Hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema, bronchospasm, throat tightness, and urticaria.



     Eye Disorders  

  Vortex keratopathy.



     Gastrointestinal Disorders  

  Pancreatitis.



     Hepatobiliary Disorders  

  Rare cases of hepatitis, and one case of fatal liver failure have been reported with atovaquone usage.



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  

  Erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and skin desquamation have been reported in patients receiving multiple drug therapy including atovaquone.



     Renal and Urinary Disorders  

  Acute renal impairment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
