<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="atrovent1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described, or described in greater detail, in other sections:



 *  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis [  see Contraindications  (4)  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)    ] 
 *  Paradoxical bronchospasm [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.3)    ] 
 *  Ocular effects [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)    ] 
 *  Urinary retention [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.5)    ] 
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in patients.
 

   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt; 5% incidence in the 12-week placebo-controlled trials) were bronchitis, COPD exacerbation, dyspnea, and headache  (6.1)  



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  .



 

  6.1  Clinical Trials Experience

  The adverse reaction information concerning ATROVENT HFA is derived from two 12-week, double-blind, parallel group studies and one 1-year open-label, parallel group study. These studies compared ATROVENT HFA Inhalation Aerosol, ATROVENT CFC Inhalation Aerosol, and placebo (in one study only) in 1010 COPD patients. The following table lists the incidence of adverse reactions that occurred at a rate of greater than or equal to 3% in any ipratropium bromide group and greater than placebo in the 12-week study. The frequency of corresponding reactions in the 1-year open label study is included for comparison.



 TABLE 1 Adverse Reactions (% Patients) in ATROVENT HFA Clinical Trials 
                      Placebo-controlled 12 week Study 244.1405 andActive-controlled 12 week Study 244.1408          Active-controlled 1-year Study 244.2453       
                      Atrovent HFA(N=243)%          Atrovent CFC(N=183)%          Placebo(N=128)%          Atrovent HFA(N=305)%          Atrovent CFC(N=151)%       
  
     BODY AS A WHOLE - GENERAL DISORDERS       
    Back pain            2                3                2                7                3          
    Headache             6                9                8                7                5          
    Influenza-like symptoms         4                2                2                8                5          
     CENTRAL &amp; PERIPHERAL NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS       
    Dizziness            3                3                2                3                1          
     GASTROINTESTINAL SYSTEM DISORDERS       
    Dyspepsia            1                3                1                5                3          
    Mouth dry            4                2                2                2                3          
    Nausea               4                1                2                4                4          
     RESPIRATORY SYSTEM DISORDERS       
    Bronchitis          10               11                6               23               19          
    COPD exacerbation         8               14               13               23               23          
    Dyspnea              8                8                4                7                4          
    Sinusitis            1                4                3               11               14          
     URINARY SYSTEM DISORDERS       
    Urinary tract infection         2                3                1               10                8          
      Cough, rhinitis, and upper respiratory infection occurred in greater than or equal to 3% of patients in either ipratropium treatment group but not greater than placebo in the 12-week study.
 

 In the one open label controlled study in 456 COPD patients, the overall incidence of adverse events was also similar between ATROVENT HFA and ATROVENT CFC formulations.



 Overall, in the above mentioned studies, 9.3% of the patients taking 42 mcg ATROVENT HFA and 8.7% of the patients taking 42 mcg ATROVENT CFC reported at least one adverse event that was considered by the investigator to be related to the study drug. The most common drug-related adverse events were dry mouth (1.6% of ATROVENT HFA and 0.9% of ATROVENT CFC patients), and taste perversion (bitter taste) (0.9% of ATROVENT HFA and 0.3% of ATROVENT CFC patients).



 As an anticholinergic drug, cases of precipitation or worsening of narrow-angle glaucoma, glaucoma, halo vision, conjunctival hyperaemia, corneal edema, mydriasis, acute eye pain, dry throat, hypotension, palpitations, urinary retention, tachycardia, constipation, bronchospasm, including paradoxical bronchospasm have been reported with the use of ATROVENT. Additional adverse reactions identified for ATROVENT seen in clinical trials include throat irritation, stomatitis, mouth edema, and vision blurred.



 Allergic-type reactions such as skin rash, pruritus, angioedema including that of tongue, lips and face, urticaria (including giant urticaria), laryngospasm and anaphylactic reactions have been reported [    see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)      ].



   6.2  Post-Marketing Experience

  In a 5-year placebo-controlled trial, hospitalizations for supraventricular tachycardia and/or atrial fibrillation occurred with an incidence rate of 0.5% in COPD patients receiving ATROVENT CFC.



 In addition to the adverse reactions reported in the controlled clinical trials, adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of ATROVENT. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Allergic-type reactions such as skin rash, angioedema including that of tongue, lips and face, urticaria (including giant urticaria), laryngospasm and anaphylactic reactions have been reported, with positive rechallenge in some cases.



 Additionally, urinary retention, mydriasis, gastrointestinal distress (diarrhea, nausea, vomiting), cough and bronchospasm, including paradoxical bronchospasm, hypersensitivity reactions, intraocular pressure increased, accommodation disorder, heart rate increased, pharyngeal edema, and gastrointestinal motility disorders have been reported during the post-marketing period with use of ATROVENT.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Not indicated for the initial treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm where rescue therapy is required for rapid response  (5.1)   
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis: Discontinue ATROVENT HFA at once and consider alternative treatments  (5.2)   
 *  Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue ATROVENT HFA and consider other treatments if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs  (5.3)   
 *  Ocular effects: Use with caution in patients with narrow-angle glaucoma and instruct patients to consult a physician immediately if signs or symptoms of narrow-angle glaucoma develop  (5.4)   
 *  Urinary retention: Use with caution in patients with prostatic hyperplasia or bladder-neck obstruction and instruct patients to consult a physician immediately if signs or symptoms of urinary retention develop  (5.5)   
    
 

   5.1  Use for Maintenance Treatment Only



  ATROVENT HFA is a bronchodilator for the maintenance treatment of bronchospasm associated with COPD and is not indicated for the initial treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm where rescue therapy is required for rapid response.



    5.2  Hypersensitivity Reactions, Including Anaphylaxis



  Hypersensitivity reactions including urticaria, angioedema, rash, bronchospasm, anaphylaxis, and oropharyngeal edema may occur after the administration of ATROVENT HFA. In clinical trials and post marketing experience with ipratropium containing products, hypersensitivity reactions such as skin rash, pruritus, angioedema of tongue, lips and face, urticaria (including giant urticaria), laryngospasm and anaphylactic reactions have been reported [  see Adverse Reactions  (6.1  ,  6.2)      ]. If such a reaction occurs, therapy with ATROVENT HFA should be stopped at once and alternative treatment should be considered [  see Contraindications  (4)      ].



    5.3  Paradoxical Bronchospasm



  ATROVENT HFA can produce paradoxical bronchospasm that can be life threatening. If this occurs, treatment with ATROVENT HFA should be stopped and other treatments considered.



    5.4  Ocular Effects



  ATROVENT HFA is an anticholinergic and its use may increase intraocular pressure. This may result in precipitation or worsening of narrow-angle glaucoma. Therefore, ATROVENT HFA should be used with caution in patients with narrow-angle glaucoma.



 Patients should avoid spraying ATROVENT HFA into their eyes. If a patient sprays ATROVENT HFA into their eyes, they may cause eye pain or discomfort, temporary blurring of vision, mydriasis, visual halos or colored images in association with red eyes from conjunctival and corneal congestion. Advise patients to consult their physician immediately if any of these symptoms develop while using ATROVENT HFA Inhalation Aerosol.



    5.5  Urinary Retention



  ATROVENT HFA is an anticholinergic and may cause urinary retention. Therefore caution is advised when administering ATROVENT HFA Inhalation Aerosol to patients with prostatic hyperplasia, or bladder-neck obstruction [  see Drug Interactions  (7.1)      ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
