<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="avage" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In human dermal safety studies, tazarotene 0.05% and 0.1% creams did not induce allergic contact sensitization, phototoxicity, or photoallergy.



 The most frequent treatment-related adverse reactions (greater than or equal to 5%) reported during the clinical trials with  AVAGE  (r)    (tazarotene) Cream 0.1% in the treatment of facial fine wrinkling, mottled hypo- and hyperpigmentation, and benign facial lentigines were limited to the skin. Those occurring in greater than 10%, in descending order, included: desquamation, erythema, burning sensation, and dry skin. Events occurring in greater than or equal to 1% to less than or equal to 10% of patients, in descending order included: skin irritation, pruritus, irritant contact dermatitis, stinging, acne, rash, or cheilitis. Common adverse events observed in the clinical trials are presented in the following table:



 TABLE OF ADVERSE EVENTS SEEN IN CLINICAL TRIALS WITH AVAGE(r) (TAZAROTENE) CREAM 0.1% 
   Adverse Event                AVAGE  (r)      N=567                 Vehicle    N=564                     
  
 Desquamation                 40%                                   3%                                     
 Erythema                     34%                                   3%                                     
 Burning Sensation            26%                                   &lt;1%                                    
 Dry Skin                     16%                                   3%                                     
 Irritation Skin              10%                                   1%                                     
 Pruritus                     10%                                   1%                                     
 Irritant Contact Dermatitis  8%                                    1%                                     
 Stinging                     3%                                    &lt;1%                                    
 Acne                         3%                                    3%                                     
 Rash                         3%                                    1%                                     
 Cheilitis                    1%                                    0%                                     
         A few patients reported adverse events at Week 0; however, for patients who were treated with  AVAGE  (r)    the highest number of new reports for each adverse event was at Week 2.
 

 When combining data from the two pivotal studies, 5.3% of patients in the tazarotene cream group and 0.9% of patients in the vehicle group discontinued due to adverse events.



 Overall, 20/567 (3.5%) patients in the  AVAGE  (r)    (tazarotene) Cream 0.1% group and 16/564 (2.8%) patients in the vehicle group reported adverse events (including edema, irritation, and inflammation) directly related to the eye or eyelid. The majority of these conditions were mild.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
