<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="avalide" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse events (&gt;=5% on AVALIDE and more often than on placebo) are dizziness, fatigue, and musculoskeletal pain. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact -sanofi-aventis U.S. LLC at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



     Irbesartan-Hydrochlorothiazide  



 AVALIDE Tablets have been evaluated for safety in 1694 patients treated for essential hypertension in 6 clinical trials. In Studies I through IV with AVALIDE, no adverse events peculiar to this combination drug product have been observed. Adverse events have been limited to those that were reported previously with irbesartan or hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ). The overall incidence of adverse events was similar with the combination and placebo. In general, treatment with AVALIDE was well tolerated. For the most part, adverse events have been mild and transient in nature and have not required discontinuation of therapy. In controlled clinical trials, discontinuation of AVALIDE therapy due to clinical adverse events was required in only 3.6%. This incidence was significantly less (p=0.023) than the 6.8% of patients treated with placebo who discontinued therapy.



 In these double-blind controlled clinical trials, the following adverse events reported with AVALIDE occurred in &gt;=1% of patients, and more often on the irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide combination than on placebo, regardless of drug relationship:




                             Irbesartan/HCTZ(n=898)(%)  Placebo(n=236)(%)   Irbesartan(n=400)(%)    HCTZ(n=380)(%)     
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                              
   Chest Pain                         2                    1                   2                   2            
   Fatigue                            6                    3                   4                   3            
   Influenza                          3                    1                   2                   2            
   Cardiovascular                                                                                               
   Edema                              3                    3                   2                   2            
   Tachycardia                        1                    0                   1                   1            
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                             
   Abdominal Pain                     2                    1                   2                   2            
   Dyspepsia/heartburn                2                    1                   0                   2            
   Nausea/vomiting                    3                    0                   2                   2            
   Immunology                                                                                                   
   Allergy                            1                    0                   1                   1            
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                              
   Musculoskeletal Pain               6                    5                   6                   10           
   Nervous System                                                                                               
   Dizziness                          8                    4                   6                   5            
   Dizziness Orthostatic              1                    0                   1                   1            
   Renal/Genitourinary                                                                                          
   Abnormality Urination              2                    1                   1                   2            
           The following adverse events were also reported at a rate of 1% or greater, but were as, or more, common in the placebo group: headache, sinus abnormality, cough, URI, pharyngitis, diarrhea, rhinitis, urinary tract infection, rash, anxiety/nervousness, and muscle cramp.
 

 Adverse events occurred at about the same rates in men and women, older and younger patients, and black and non-black patients.



 Adverse events in Studies V and VI were similar to those described above in Studies I through IV.



     Irbesartan  



 Other adverse events that have been reported with irbesartan, without regard to causality, are listed below:



   Body as a Whole:  fever, chills, orthostatic effects, facial edema, upper extremity edema



   Cardiovascular:  flushing, hypertension, cardiac murmur, myocardial infarction, angina pectoris, hypotension, syncope, arrhythmic/conduction disorder, cardiorespiratory arrest, heart failure, hypertensive crisis



   Dermatologic:  pruritus, dermatitis, ecchymosis, erythema face, urticaria



   Endocrine/Metabolic/Electrolyte Imbalances:  sexual dysfunction, libido change, gout



   Gastrointestinal:  diarrhea, constipation, gastroenteritis, flatulence, abdominal distention



   Musculoskeletal/Connective Tissue:  musculoskeletal trauma, extremity swelling, muscle cramp, arthritis, muscle ache, musculoskeletal chest pain, joint stiffness, bursitis, muscle weakness



   Nervous System:  anxiety/nervousness, sleep disturbance, numbness, somnolence, vertigo, emotional disturbance, depression, paresthesia, tremor, transient ischemic attack, cerebrovascular accident



   Renal/Genitourinary:  prostate disorder



   Respiratory:  cough, upper respiratory infection, epistaxis, tracheobronchitis, congestion, pulmonary congestion, dyspnea, wheezing



   Special Senses:  vision disturbance, hearing abnormality, ear infection, ear pain, conjunctivitis



   Hydrochlorothiazide  



 Other adverse events that have been reported with hydrochlorothiazide, without regard to causality, are listed below:



   Body as a Whole:  weakness



   Digestive:  pancreatitis, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice), sialadenitis, cramping, gastric irritation



   Hematologic:  aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia



   Hypersensitivity:  purpura, photosensitivity, urticaria, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis and cutaneous vasculitis), fever, respiratory distress including pneumonitis and pulmonary edema, anaphylactic reactions



   Metabolic:  hyperglycemia, glycosuria, hyperuricemia



   Musculoskeletal:  muscle spasm



   Nervous System/Psychiatric:  restlessness



   Renal:  renal failure, renal dysfunction, interstitial nephritis



   Skin:  erythema multiforme including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis including toxic epidermal necrolysis



   Special Senses:  transient blurred vision, xanthopsia



     Initial Therapy  



 In the moderate hypertension Study V (mean SeDBP between 90 and 110 mmHg), the types and incidences of adverse events reported for patients treated with AVALIDE were similar to the adverse event profile in patients on initial irbesartan or HCTZ monotherapy. There were no reported events of syncope in the AVALIDE treatment group and there was one reported event in the HCTZ treatment group. The incidences of pre-specified adverse events on AVALIDE, irbesartan, and HCTZ, respectively, were: 0.9%, 0%, and 0% for hypotension; 3.0%, 3.8%, and 1.0% for dizziness; 5.5%, 3.8%, and 4.8% for headache; 1.2%, 0%, and 1.0% for hyperkalemia; and 0.9%, 0%, and 0% for hypokalemia. The rates of discontinuation due to adverse events on AVALIDE, irbesartan alone, and HCTZ alone were 6.7%, 3.8%, and 4.8%.



 In the severe hypertension (SeDBP &gt;=110 mmHg) Study VI, the overall pattern of adverse events reported through 7 weeks of follow-up was similar in patients treated with AVALIDE as initial therapy and in patients treated with irbesartan as initial therapy. The incidences of the pre-specified adverse events on AVALIDE and irbesartan, respectively, were: 0% and 0% for syncope; 0.6% and 0% for hypotension; 3.6% and 4.0% for dizziness; 4.3% and 6.6% for headache; 0.2% and 0% for hyperkalemia; and 0.6% and 0.4% for hypokalemia. The rates of discontinuation due to adverse events were 2.1% and 2.2%. [See    Clinical Studies (14.2)    .]



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of AVALIDE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to AVALIDE.



 The following have been very rarely reported: urticaria, angioedema (involving swelling of the face, lips, pharynx, and/or tongue), and hepatitis. Hyperkalemia has been rarely reported.



 Very rare cases of jaundice have been reported with irbesartan.



 Impaired renal function, including cases of renal failure in patients at risk, has been reported with irbesartan and AVALIDE.



 Tinnitus has been reported in patients receiving irbesartan or AVALIDE.



 Cases of increased CPK and rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers.



   6.3 Laboratory Abnormalities

  In controlled clinical trials, clinically important changes in standard laboratory parameters were rarely associated with administration of AVALIDE.



   Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen:  Minor increases in blood urea nitrogen (BUN) or serum creatinine were observed in 2.3% and 1.1%, respectively, of patients with essential hypertension treated with AVALIDE alone. No patient discontinued taking AVALIDE due to increased BUN. One patient discontinued taking AVALIDE due to a minor increase in serum creatinine.



   Liver Function Tests:  Occasional elevations of liver enzymes and/or serum bilirubin have occurred. In patients with essential hypertension treated with AVALIDE alone, one patient was discontinued due to elevated liver enzymes.



   Serum Electrolytes:  [See    Warnings and Precautions (5.2  ,  5.6)    .]
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue AVALIDE as soon as possible. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1).] 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1).] 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue AVALIDE as soon as possible. (5.1) 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypotension: Correct volume-depletion prior to administration. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Impaired renal function. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Thiazide diuretics may cause an exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Acute myopia and secondary angle-closure glaucoma. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Fetal Toxicity



   Pregnancy Category D  



 Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue AVALIDE as soon as possible [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].



 Thiazides cross the placenta, and use of thiazides during pregnancy is associated with a risk of fetal or neonatal jaundice, thrombocytopenia, and possibly other adverse reactions that have occurred in adults.



    5.2 Hypotension in Volume- or Salt-Depleted Patients



  Excessive reduction of blood pressure was rarely seen in patients with uncomplicated hypertension treated with irbesartan alone (&lt;0.1%) or with irbesartan-hydrochlorothiazide (approximately 1%). Initiation of antihypertensive therapy may cause symptomatic hypotension in patients with intravascular volume- or sodium-depletion, e.g., in patients treated vigorously with diuretics or in patients on dialysis. Such volume depletion should be corrected prior to administration of antihypertensive therapy.



 If hypotension occurs, the patient should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reaction



   Hydrochlorothiazide  



 Hypersensitivity reactions to hydrochlorothiazide may occur in patients with or without a history of allergy or bronchial asthma, but are more likely in patients with such a history.



    5.4 Systemic Lupus Erythematosus



   Hydrochlorothiazide  



 Thiazide diuretics have been reported to cause exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus.



    5.5 Electrolyte and Metabolic Imbalances



   Irbesartan-Hydrochlorothiazide  



 In double-blind clinical trials of various doses of irbesartan and hydrochlorothiazide, the incidence of hypertensive patients who developed hypokalemia (serum potassium &lt;3.5 mEq/L) was 7.5% versus 6.0% for placebo; the incidence of hyperkalemia (serum potassium &gt;5.7 mEq/L) was &lt;1.0% versus 1.7% for placebo. No patient discontinued due to increases or decreases in serum potassium. On average, the combination of irbesartan and hydrochlorothiazide had no effect on serum potassium. Higher doses of irbesartan ameliorated the hypokalemic response to hydrochlorothiazide.



 Based on experience with the use of other drugs that affect the renin-angiotensin system, concomitant use of potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium supplements, or salt substitutes containing potassium may lead to increases in serum potassium. Concurrent therapy with hydrochlorothiazide may reduce the frequency of this effect.



    Hydrochlorothiazide  



 Hydrochlorothiazide can cause hypokalemia and hyponatremia. Hypomagnesemia can result in hypokalemia which appears difficult to treat despite potassium repletion. Drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system can cause hyperkalemia. Monitor serum electrolytes periodically.



 Hyperuricemia may occur or frank gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide therapy.



 Hydrochlorothiazide may alter glucose tolerance and raise serum levels of cholesterol and triglycerides.



 The antihypertensive effects of the drug may be enhanced in the post-sympathectomy patient.



 Thiazides may decrease urinary calcium excretion. Thiazides may cause intermittent and slight elevation of serum calcium in the absence of known disorders of calcium metabolism. Marked hypercalcemia may be evidence of hidden hyperparathyroidism. Thiazides should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function.



    5.6 Hepatic Impairment



   Hydrochlorothiazide  



 Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease, since minor alterations of fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma.



    5.7 Impaired Renal Function



  As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals [see   Drug Interactions (7)    ]. In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with ACE inhibitors has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Irbesartan would be expected to behave similarly. In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or BUN have been reported. There has been no known use of irbesartan in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but a similar effect should be anticipated.



 Thiazides should be used with caution in severe renal disease. In patients with renal disease, thiazides may precipitate azotemia. Cumulative effects of the drug may develop in patients with impaired renal function.



    5.8 Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle-Closure Glaucoma



  Sulfonamide or sulfonamide derivative drugs, such as hydrochlorothiazide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma. Cases of acute angle-closure glaucoma have been reported with hydrochlorothiazide. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation. Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss. The primary treatment is to discontinue drug intake as rapidly as possible. Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled. Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
