<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="avandia" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) reported in clinical trials without regard to causality were upper respiratory tract infection, injury, and headache. (6.1)



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

    6.1  Clinical Trial Experience

    Adult  



 In clinical trials, approximately 9,900 patients with type 2 diabetes have been treated with AVANDIA.



     Short-Term Trials of AVANDIA as Monotherapy and in Combination With Other Hypoglycemic Agents  



 The incidence and types of adverse events reported in short-term clinical trials of AVANDIA as monotherapy are shown in Table 4.



 Table 4. Adverse Events (&gt;=5% in Any Treatment Group) Reported by Patients in Short-Term* Double-Blind Clinical Trials With AVANDIA as Monotherapy 
  * Short-term trials ranged from 8 weeks to 1 year.    
   Includes patients receiving glyburide (N = 514), gliclazide (N = 91), or glipizide (N = 21).    
  
  Preferred Term    AVANDIA Monotherapy    Placebo          Metformin        Sulfonylureas    
                   N = 2,526        N = 601          N = 225          N = 626          
                   %                %                %                %                
  Upper respiratory tract infection    9.9              8.7              8.9              7.3              
  Injury           7.6              4.3              7.6              6.1              
  Headache         5.9              5.0              8.9              5.4              
  Back pain        4.0              3.8              4.0              5.0              
  Hyperglycemia    3.9              5.7              4.4              8.1              
  Fatigue          3.6              5.0              4.0              1.9              
  Sinusitis        3.2              4.5              5.3              3.0              
  Diarrhea         2.3              3.3              15.6             3.0              
  Hypoglycemia     0.6              0.2              1.3              5.9              
           Overall, the types of adverse reactions without regard to causality reported when AVANDIA was used in combination with a sulfonylurea or metformin were similar to those during monotherapy with AVANDIA.
 

 Events of anemia and edema tended to be reported more frequently at higher doses, and were generally mild to moderate in severity and usually did not require discontinuation of treatment with AVANDIA.



 In double-blind studies, anemia was reported in 1.9% of patients receiving AVANDIA as monotherapy compared to 0.7% on placebo, 0.6% on sulfonylureas, and 2.2% on metformin. Reports of anemia were greater in patients treated with a combination of AVANDIA and metformin (7.1%) and with a combination of AVANDIA and a sulfonylurea plus metformin (6.7%) compared to monotherapy with AVANDIA or in combination with a sulfonylurea (2.3%). Lower pre-treatment hemoglobin/hematocrit levels in patients enrolled in the metformin combination clinical trials may have contributed to the higher reporting rate of anemia in these studies  [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .



 In clinical trials, edema was reported in 4.8% of patients receiving AVANDIA as monotherapy compared to 1.3% on placebo, 1.0% on sulfonylureas, and 2.2% on metformin. The reporting rate of edema was higher for AVANDIA 8 mg in sulfonylurea combinations (12.4%) compared to other combinations, with the exception of insulin. Edema was reported in 14.7% of patients receiving AVANDIA in the insulin combination trials compared to 5.4% on insulin alone. Reports of new onset or exacerbation of congestive heart failure occurred at rates of 1% for insulin alone, and 2% (4 mg) and 3% (8 mg) for insulin in combination with AVANDIA  [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  .



 In controlled combination therapy studies with sulfonylureas, mild to moderate hypoglycemic symptoms, which appear to be dose related, were reported. Few patients were withdrawn for hypoglycemia (&lt;1%) and few episodes of hypoglycemia were considered to be severe (&lt;1%). Hypoglycemia was the most frequently reported adverse event in the fixed-dose insulin combination trials, although few patients withdrew for hypoglycemia (4 of 408 for AVANDIA plus insulin and 1 of 203 for insulin alone). Rates of hypoglycemia, confirmed by capillary blood glucose concentration &lt;=50 mg/dL, were 6% for insulin alone and 12% (4 mg) and 14% (8 mg) for insulin in combination with AVANDIA.  [See Warnings and Precautions (5.10).]  



     Long-Term Trial of AVANDIA as Monotherapy  



 A 4- to 6-year study (ADOPT) compared the use of AVANDIA (n = 1,456), glyburide (n = 1,441), and metformin (n = 1,454) as monotherapy in patients recently diagnosed with type 2 diabetes who were not previously treated with antidiabetic medication. Table 5 presents adverse reactions without regard to causality; rates are expressed per 100 patient-years (PY) exposure to account for the differences in exposure to study medication across the 3 treatment groups.



 In ADOPT, fractures were reported in a greater number of women treated with AVANDIA (9.3%, 2.7/100 patient-years) compared to glyburide (3.5%, 1.3/100 patient-years) or metformin (5.1%, 1.5/100 patient-years). The majority of the fractures in the women who received rosiglitazone were reported in the upper arm, hand, and foot.  [See Warnings and Precautions (5.7).]  The observed incidence of fractures for male patients was similar among the 3 treatment groups.



 Table 5. On-Therapy Adverse Events (&gt;=5 Events/100 Patient-Years [PY]) in Any Treatment Group Reported in a 4- to 6-Year Clinical Trial of AVANDIA as Monotherapy (ADOPT) 
                   AVANDIA          Glyburide        Metformin        
                   N = 1,456        N = 1,441        N = 1,454        
                   PY = 4,954       PY = 4,244       PY = 4,906       
  Nasopharyngitis    6.3              6.9              6.6              
  Back pain        5.1              4.9              5.3              
  Arthralgia       5.0              4.8              4.2              
  Hypertension     4.4              6.0              6.1              
  Upper respiratory tract infection    4.3              5.0              4.7              
  Hypoglycemia     2.9              13.0             3.4              
  Diarrhea         2.5              3.2              6.8              
              Pediatric  
 

 AVANDIA has been evaluated for safety in a single, active-controlled trial of pediatric patients with type 2 diabetes in which 99 were treated with AVANDIA and 101 were treated with metformin. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;10%) without regard to causality for either AVANDIA or metformin were headache (17% versus 14%), nausea (4% versus 11%), nasopharyngitis (3% versus 12%), and diarrhea (1% versus 13%). In this study, one case of diabetic ketoacidosis was reported in the metformin group. In addition, there were 3 patients in the rosiglitazone group who had FPG of ?300 mg/dL, 2+ ketonuria, and an elevated anion gap.



     6.2  Laboratory Abnormalities

    Hematologic  



 Decreases in mean hemoglobin and hematocrit occurred in a dose-related fashion in adult patients treated with AVANDIA (mean decreases in individual studies as much as 1.0 g/dL hemoglobin and as much as 3.3% hematocrit). The changes occurred primarily during the first 3 months following initiation of therapy with AVANDIA or following a dose increase in AVANDIA. The time course and magnitude of decreases were similar in patients treated with a combination of AVANDIA and other hypoglycemic agents or monotherapy with AVANDIA. Pre-treatment levels of hemoglobin and hematocrit were lower in patients in metformin combination studies and may have contributed to the higher reporting rate of anemia. In a single study in pediatric patients, decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit (mean decreases of 0.29 g/dL and 0.95%, respectively) were reported. Small decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit have also been reported in pediatric patients treated with AVANDIA. White blood cell counts also decreased slightly in adult patients treated with AVANDIA. Decreases in hematologic parameters may be related to increased plasma volume observed with treatment with AVANDIA.



     Lipids  



 Changes in serum lipids have been observed following treatment with AVANDIA in adults  [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  . Small changes in serum lipid parameters were reported in children treated with AVANDIA for 24 weeks.



     Serum Transaminase Levels  



 In pre-approval clinical studies in 4,598 patients treated with AVANDIA (3,600 patient-years of exposure) and in a long-term 4- to 6-year study in 1,456 patients treated with AVANDIA (4,954 patient-years exposure), there was no evidence of drug-induced hepatotoxicity.



 In pre-approval controlled trials, 0.2% of patients treated with AVANDIA had elevations in ALT &gt;3X the upper limit of normal compared to 0.2% on placebo and 0.5% on active comparators. The ALT elevations in patients treated with AVANDIA were reversible. Hyperbilirubinemia was found in 0.3% of patients treated with AVANDIA compared with 0.9% treated with placebo and 1% in patients treated with active comparators. In pre-approval clinical trials, there were no cases of idiosyncratic drug reactions leading to hepatic failure.  [See Warnings and Precautions (5.6).]  



 In the 4- to 6-year ADOPT trial, patients treated with AVANDIA (4,954 patient-years exposure), glyburide (4,244 patient-years exposure), or metformin (4,906 patient-years exposure), as monotherapy, had the same rate of ALT increase to &gt;3X upper limit of normal (0.3 per 100 patient-years exposure).



     6.3  Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the events described below have been identified during post-approval use of AVANDIA. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or to always establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 In patients receiving thiazolidinedione therapy, serious adverse events with or without a fatal outcome, potentially related to volume expansion (e.g., congestive heart failure, pulmonary edema, and pleural effusions) have been reported  [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .



 There are postmarketing reports with AVANDIA of hepatitis, hepatic enzyme elevations to 3 or more times the upper limit of normal, and hepatic failure with and without fatal outcome, although causality has not been established.



 There are postmarketing reports with AVANDIA of rash, pruritus, urticaria, angioedema, anaphylactic reaction, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and new onset or worsening diabetic macular edema with decreased visual acuity  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AND MYOCARDIAL ISCHEMIA

  WARNING: CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AND MYOCARDIAL ISCHEMIA

    *  Thiazolidinediones, including rosiglitazone, cause or exacerbate congestive heart failure in some patients [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. After initiation of AVANDIA, and after dose increases, observe patients carefully for signs and symptoms of heart failure (including excessive, rapid weight gain, dyspnea, and/or edema). If these signs and symptoms develop, the heart failure should be managed according to current standards of care. Furthermore, discontinuation or dose reduction of AVANDIA must be considered. 
 *  AVANDIA is not recommended in patients with symptomatic heart failure. Initiation of AVANDIA in patients with established NYHA Class III or IV heart failure is contraindicated. [See Contraindications (4) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1).] 
 *  A meta-analysis of 42 clinical studies (mean duration 6 months; 14,237 total patients), most of which compared AVANDIA to placebo, showed AVANDIA to be associated with an increased risk of myocardial ischemic events such as angina or myocardial infarction. Three other studies (mean duration 41 months; 14,067 total patients), comparing AVANDIA to some other approved oral antidiabetic agents or placebo, have not confirmed or excluded this risk. In their entirety, the available data on the risk of myocardial ischemia are inconclusive. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.2).] 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AND MYOCARDIAL ISCHEMIA
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Thiazolidinediones, including rosiglitazone, cause or exacerbate congestive heart failure in some patients (5.1). After initiation of AVANDIA, and after dose increases, observe patients carefully for signs and symptoms of heart failure (including excessive, rapid weight gain, dyspnea, and/or edema). If these signs and symptoms develop, the heart failure should be managed according to current standards of care. Furthermore, discontinuation or dose reduction of AVANDIA must be considered. 
 *  AVANDIA is not recommended in patients with symptomatic heart failure. Initiation of AVANDIA in patients with established NYHA Class III or IV heart failure is contraindicated. (4, 5.1) 
 *  A meta-analysis of 42 clinical studies (mean duration 6 months; 14,237 total patients), most of which compared AVANDIA to placebo, showed AVANDIA to be associated with an increased risk of myocardial ischemic events such as angina or myocardial infarction. Three other studies (mean duration 41 months; 14,067 total patients), comparing AVANDIA to some other approved oral antidiabetic agents or placebo, have not confirmed or excluded this risk. In their entirety, the available data on the risk of myocardial ischemia are inconclusive. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Fluid retention, which may exacerbate or lead to heart failure, may occur. Combination use with insulin and use in congestive heart failure NYHA Class I and II may increase risk of other cardiovascular effects. (5.1, 5.3) 
 *  Increased risk of myocardial ischemic events has been observed in a meta-analysis of 42 clinical trials (incidence rate 2% versus 1.5%). (5.2) 
 *  Use of AVANDIA with nitrates is not recommended. (1.2, 5.2) 
 *  Coadministration of AVANDIA and insulin is not recommended. (1.2, 5.3) 
 *  Dose-related edema (5.4), weight gain (5.5), and anemia (5.9) may occur. 
 *  Macular edema has been reported. (5.7) 
 *  Increased incidence of bone fracture in female patients. (5.8) 
 *  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with AVANDIA or any other oral antidiabetic drug. (5.2) 
    
 

    5.1  Cardiac Failure



  AVANDIA, like other thiazolidinediones, alone or in combination with other antidiabetic agents, can cause fluid retention, which may exacerbate or lead to heart failure. Patients should be observed for signs and symptoms of heart failure. If these signs and symptoms develop, the heart failure should be managed according to current standards of care. Furthermore, discontinuation or dose reduction of rosiglitazone must be considered [see Boxed Warning]  .



 Patients with congestive heart failure (CHF) NYHA Class I and II treated with AVANDIA have an increased risk of cardiovascular events. A 52-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled echocardiographic study was conducted in 224 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus and NYHA Class I or II CHF (ejection fraction &lt;=45%) on background antidiabetic and CHF therapy. An independent committee conducted a blinded evaluation of fluid-related events (including congestive heart failure) and cardiovascular hospitalizations according to predefined criteria (adjudication). Separate from the adjudication, other cardiovascular adverse events were reported by investigators. Although no treatment difference in change from baseline of ejection fractions was observed, more cardiovascular adverse events were observed following treatment with AVANDIA compared to placebo during the 52-week study. (See Table 1.)



 Table 1. Emergent Cardiovascular Adverse Events in Patients With Congestive Heart Failure (NYHA Class I and II) Treated With AVANDIA or Placebo (in Addition to Background Antidiabetic and CHF Therapy) 
  * Includes hospitalization for any cardiovascular reason.    
  
  Events           AVANDIA          Placebo          
                   N = 110  n (%)    N = 114  n (%)    
  Adjudicated                                        
  Cardiovascular deaths    5 (5%)           4 (4%)           
  CHF worsening    7 (6%)           4 (4%)           
  - with overnight hospitalization    5 (5%)           4 (4%)           
  - without overnight hospitalization    2 (2%)           0 (0%)           
  New or worsening edema    28 (25%)         10 (9%)          
  New or worsening dyspnea    29 (26%)         19 (17%)         
  Increases in CHF medication    36 (33%)         20 (18%)         
  Cardiovascular hospitalization*    21 (19%)         15 (13%)         
                                                     
  Investigator-reported, non-adjudicated                                      
  Ischemic adverse events    10 (9%)          5 (4%)           
  - Myocardial infarction    5 (5%)           2 (2%)           
  - Angina         6 (5%)           3 (3%)           
         Initiation of AVANDIA in patients with established NYHA Class III or IV heart failure is contraindicated. AVANDIA is not recommended in patients with symptomatic heart failure. [See Boxed Warning.]  
 

 Patients experiencing acute coronary syndromes have not been studied in controlled clinical trials. In view of the potential for development of heart failure in patients having an acute coronary event, initiation of AVANDIA is not recommended for patients experiencing an acute coronary event, and discontinuation of AVANDIA during this acute phase should be considered.



 Patients with NYHA Class III and IV cardiac status (with or without CHF) have not been studied in controlled clinical trials. AVANDIA is not recommended in patients with NYHA Class III and IV cardiac status.



     5.2  Myocardial Ischemia



   Meta-Analysis of Myocardial Ischemia in a Group of 42 Clinical Trials  



 A meta-analysis was conducted retrospectively to assess cardiovascular adverse events reported across 42 double-blind, randomized, controlled clinical trials (mean duration 6 months).  1  These studies had been conducted to assess glucose-lowering efficacy in type 2 diabetes, and prospectively planned adjudication of cardiovascular events had not occurred in the trials. Some trials were placebo-controlled and some used active oral antidiabetic drugs as controls. Placebo-controlled studies included monotherapy trials (monotherapy with AVANDIA versus placebo monotherapy) and add-on trials (AVANDIA or placebo, added to sulfonylurea, metformin, or insulin). Active control studies included monotherapy trials (monotherapy with AVANDIA versus sulfonylurea or metformin monotherapy) and add-on trials (AVANDIA plus sulfonylurea or AVANDIA plus metformin, versus sulfonylurea plus metformin). A total of 14,237 patients were included (8,604 in treatment groups containing AVANDIA, 5,633 in comparator groups), with 4,143 patient-years of exposure to AVANDIA and 2,675 patient-years of exposure to comparator. Myocardial ischemic events included angina pectoris, angina pectoris aggravated, unstable angina, cardiac arrest, chest pain, coronary artery occlusion, dyspnea, myocardial infarction, coronary thrombosis, myocardial ischemia, coronary artery disease, and coronary artery disorder. In this analysis, an increased risk of myocardial ischemia with AVANDIA versus pooled comparators was observed (2% AVANDIA versus 1.5% comparators, odds ratio 1.4, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.1, 1.8). An increased risk of myocardial ischemic events with AVANDIA was observed in the placebo-controlled studies, but not in the active-controlled studies. (See Figure 1.)



 A greater increased risk of myocardial ischemic events was observed in studies where AVANDIA was added to insulin (2.8% for AVANDIA plus insulin versus 1.4% for placebo plus insulin, [OR 2.1, 95% CI 0.9, 5.1]). This increased risk reflects a difference of 3 events per 100 patient-years (95% CI -0.1, 6.3) between treatment groups. [See Warnings and Precautions (5.3).]  



 Figure 1. Forest Plot of Odds Ratios (95% Confidence Intervals) for Myocardial Ischemic Events in the Meta-Analysis of 42 Clinical Trials   A greater increased risk of myocardial ischemia was also observed in patients who received AVANDIA and background nitrate therapy. For AVANDIA (N = 361) versus control (N = 244) in nitrate users, the odds ratio was 2.9 (95% CI 1.4, 5.9), while for non-nitrate users (about 14,000 patients total), the odds ratio was 1.3 (95% CI 0.9, 1.7). This increased risk represents a difference of 12 myocardial ischemic events per 100 patient-years (95% CI 3.3, 21.4). Most of the nitrate users had established coronary heart disease. Among patients with known coronary heart disease who were not on nitrate therapy, an increased risk of myocardial ischemic events for AVANDIA versus comparator was not demonstrated.
 

    Myocardial Ischemic Events in Large, Long-Term, Prospective, Randomized, Controlled Trials of AVANDIA  



 Data from 3 other large, long-term, prospective, randomized, controlled clinical trials of AVANDIA were assessed separately from the meta-analysis. These 3 trials include a total of 14,067 patients (treatment groups containing AVANDIA N = 6,311, comparator groups N = 7,756), with patient-year exposure of 21,803 patient-years for AVANDIA and 25,998 patient-years for comparator. Duration of follow-up exceeded 3 years in each study. ADOPT (A Diabetes Outcomes Progression Trial) was a 4- to 6-year randomized, active-controlled study in recently diagnosed patients with type 2 diabetes naive to drug therapy. It was an efficacy and general safety trial that was designed to examine the durability of AVANDIA as monotherapy (N = 1,456) for glycemic control in type 2 diabetes, with comparator arms of sulfonylurea monotherapy (N = 1,441) and metformin monotherapy (N = 1,454). DREAM (Diabetes Reduction Assessment with Rosiglitazone and Ramipril Medication, published report  2  ) was a 3- to 5-year randomized, placebo-controlled study in patients with impaired glucose tolerance and/or impaired fasting glucose. It had a 2x2 factorial design, intended to evaluate the effect of AVANDIA, and separately of ramipril (an angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor [ACEI]), on progression to overt diabetes. In DREAM, 2,635 patients were in treatment groups containing AVANDIA, and 2,634 were in treatment groups not containing AVANDIA. Interim results have been published  3  for RECORD (Rosiglitazone Evaluated for Cardiac Outcomes and Regulation of Glycemia in Diabetes), an ongoing open-label, 6-year cardiovascular outcomes study in patients with type 2 diabetes with an average treatment duration of 3.75 years. RECORD includes patients who have failed metformin or sulfonylurea monotherapy; those who have failed metformin are randomized to receive either add-on AVANDIA or add-on sulfonylurea, and those who have failed sulfonylurea are randomized to receive either add-on AVANDIA or add-on metformin. In RECORD, a total of 2,220 patients are receiving add-on AVANDIA, and 2,227 patients are on one of the add-on regimens not containing AVANDIA.



 For these 3 trials, analyses were performed using a composite of major adverse cardiovascular events (myocardial infarction, cardiovascular death, or stroke), referred to hereafter as MACE. This endpoint differed from the meta-analysis' broad endpoint of myocardial ischemic events, more than half of which were angina. Myocardial infarction included adjudicated fatal and nonfatal myocardial infarction plus sudden death. As shown in Figure 2, the results for the 3 endpoints (MACE, MI, and Total Mortality) were not statistically significantly different between AVANDIA and comparators.



 Figure 2. Hazard Ratios for the Risk of MACE (Myocardial Infarction, Cardiovascular Death, or Stroke), Myocardial Infarction, and Total Mortality With AVANDIA Compared With a Control Group   In preliminary analyses of the DREAM trial, the incidence of cardiovascular events was higher among subjects who received AVANDIA in combination with ramipril than among subjects who received ramipril alone, as illustrated in Figure 2. This finding was not confirmed in ADOPT and RECORD (active-controlled trials in patients with diabetes) in which 30% and 40% of patients respectively, reported ACE-inhibitor use at baseline.
 

 In their entirety, the available data on the risk of myocardial ischemia are inconclusive. Definitive conclusions regarding this risk await completion of an adequately-designed cardiovascular outcome study.



 There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with AVANDIA or any other oral antidiabetic drug.



     5.3  Congestive Heart Failure and Myocardial Ischemia During Coadministration of AVANDIA With Insulin



  In studies in which AVANDIA was added to insulin, AVANDIA increased the risk of congestive heart failure and myocardial ischemia. (See Table 2.) Coadministration of AVANDIA and insulin is not recommended. [See Indications and Usage (1.2) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1, 5.2).]  



 In five, 26-week, controlled, randomized, double-blind trials which were included in the meta-analysis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  , patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus were randomized to coadministration of AVANDIA and insulin (N = 867) or insulin (N = 663). In these 5 trials, AVANDIA was added to insulin. These trials included patients with long-standing diabetes (median duration of 12 years) and a high prevalence of pre-existing medical conditions, including peripheral neuropathy, retinopathy, ischemic heart disease, vascular disease, and congestive heart failure. The total number of patients with emergent congestive heart failure was 21 (2.4%) and 7 (1.1%) in the AVANDIA plus insulin and insulin groups, respectively. The total number of patients with emergent myocardial ischemia was 24 (2.8%) and 9 (1.4%) in the AVANDIA plus insulin and insulin groups, respectively (OR 2.1 [95% CI 0.9, 5.1]). Although the event rate for congestive heart failure and myocardial ischemia was low in the studied population, consistently the event rate was 2-fold or higher with coadministration of AVANDIA and insulin. These cardiovascular events were noted at both the 4 mg and 8 mg daily doses of AVANDIA. (See Table 2.)



 Table 2. Occurrence of Cardiovascular Events in 5 Controlled Trials of Addition of AVANDIA to Established Insulin Treatment 
  * Events are not exclusive; i.e., a patient with a cardiovascular death due to a myocardial infarction would be counted in 4 event categories (myocardial ischemia; cardiovascular death, myocardial infarction, or stroke; myocardial infarction; cardiovascular death).    
  
  Event*           AVANDIA + Insulin  (n = 867)  n (%)    Insulin  (n = 663)  n (%)    
  Congestive heart failure    21 (2.4%)        7 (1.1%)         
  Myocardial ischemia    24 (2.8%)        9 (1.4%)         
  Composite of cardiovascular death, myocardial infarction, or stroke    10 (1.2%)        5 (0.8%)         
  Stroke           5 (0.6%)         4 (0.6%)         
  Myocardial infarction    4 (0.5%)         1 (0.2%)         
  Cardiovascular death    4 (0.5%)         1 (0.2%)         
  All deaths       6 (0.7%)         1 (0.2%)         
         In a sixth, 24-week, controlled, randomized, double-blind trial of AVANDIA and insulin coadministration, insulin was added to AVANDAMET  (r)  (rosiglitazone maleate and metformin HCl) (n = 161) and compared to insulin plus placebo (n = 158), after a single-blind 8-week run-in with AVANDAMET. Patients with edema requiring pharmacologic therapy and those with congestive heart failure were excluded at baseline and during the run-in period. In the group receiving AVANDAMET plus insulin, there was one myocardial ischemic event and one sudden death. No myocardial ischemia was observed in the insulin group, and no congestive heart failure was reported in either treatment group.
 

     5.4  Edema



  AVANDIA should be used with caution in patients with edema. In a clinical study in healthy volunteers who received 8 mg of AVANDIA once daily for 8 weeks, there was a statistically significant increase in median plasma volume compared to placebo.



 Since thiazolidinediones, including rosiglitazone, can cause fluid retention, which can exacerbate or lead to congestive heart failure, AVANDIA should be used with caution in patients at risk for heart failure. Patients should be monitored for signs and symptoms of heart failure [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1), and Patient Counseling Information (17.1)]  .



 In controlled clinical trials of patients with type 2 diabetes, mild to moderate edema was reported in patients treated with AVANDIA, and may be dose related. Patients with ongoing edema were more likely to have adverse events associated with edema if started on combination therapy with insulin and AVANDIA [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  .



     5.5  Weight Gain



  Dose-related weight gain was seen with AVANDIA alone and in combination with other hypoglycemic agents (Table 3). The mechanism of weight gain is unclear but probably involves a combination of fluid retention and fat accumulation.



 In postmarketing experience, there have been reports of unusually rapid increases in weight and increases in excess of that generally observed in clinical trials. Patients who experience such increases should be assessed for fluid accumulation and volume-related events such as excessive edema and congestive heart failure [see Boxed Warning]  .



 Table 3. Weight Changes (kg) From Baseline at Endpoint During Clinical Trials 
                                    Control Group    AVANDIA  4 mg    AVANDIA  8 mg    
  Monotherapy      Duration                          Median  (25th, 75th percentile)    Median  (25th, 75th percentile)    Median  (25th, 75th percentile)    
                   26 weeks         placebo          -0.9 (-2.8, 0.9)  N = 210    1.0 (-0.9, 3.6)  N = 436    3.1 (1.1, 5.8)  N = 439    
                   52 weeks         sulfonylurea     2.0 (0, 4.0)  N = 173    2.0 (-0.6, 4.0)  N = 150    2.6 (0, 5.3)  N = 157    
  Combination therapy                                                                                         
  Sulfonylurea     24-26 weeks      sulfonylurea     0 (-1.0, 1.3)  N = 1,155    2.2 (0.5, 4.0)  N = 613    3.5 (1.4, 5.9)  N = 841    
  Metformin        26 weeks         metformin        -1.4 (-3.2, 0.2)  N = 175    0.8 (-1.0, 2.6)  N = 100    2.1 (0, 4.3)  N = 184    
  Insulin          26 weeks         insulin          0.9 (-0.5, 2.7)  N = 162    4.1 (1.4, 6.3)  N = 164    5.4 (3.4, 7.3)  N = 150    
  Sulfonylurea + metformin    26 weeks         sulfonylurea + metformin    0.2 (-1.2, 1.6)  N = 272    2.5 (0.8, 4.6)  N = 275    4.5 (2.4, 7.3)  N = 276    
            In a 4- to 6-year, monotherapy, comparative trial (ADOPT) in patients recently diagnosed with type 2 diabetes not previously treated with antidiabetic medication [see Clinical Studies (14.1)]  , the median weight change (25  th  , 75  th  percentiles) from baseline at 4 years was 3.5 kg (0.0, 8.1) for AVANDIA, 2.0 kg (-1.0, 4.8) for glyburide, and -2.4 kg (-5.4, 0.5) for metformin.
 

 In a 24-week study in pediatric patients aged 10 to 17 years treated with AVANDIA 4 to 8 mg daily, a median weight gain of 2.8 kg (25  th  , 75  th  percentiles: 0.0, 5.8) was reported.



     5.6  Hepatic Effects



  Liver enzymes should be measured prior to the initiation of therapy with AVANDIA in all patients and periodically thereafter per the clinical judgment of the healthcare professional. Therapy with AVANDIA should not be initiated in patients with increased baseline liver enzyme levels (ALT &gt;2.5X upper limit of normal). Patients with mildly elevated liver enzymes (ALT levels &lt;=2.5X upper limit of normal) at baseline or during therapy with AVANDIA should be evaluated to determine the cause of the liver enzyme elevation. Initiation of, or continuation of, therapy with AVANDIA in patients with mild liver enzyme elevations should proceed with caution and include close clinical follow-up, including liver enzyme monitoring, to determine if the liver enzyme elevations resolve or worsen. If at any time ALT levels increase to &gt;3X the upper limit of normal in patients on therapy with AVANDIA, liver enzyme levels should be rechecked as soon as possible. If ALT levels remain &gt;3X the upper limit of normal, therapy with AVANDIA should be discontinued.



 If any patient develops symptoms suggesting hepatic dysfunction, which may include unexplained nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, fatigue, anorexia and/or dark urine, liver enzymes should be checked. The decision whether to continue the patient on therapy with AVANDIA should be guided by clinical judgment pending laboratory evaluations. If jaundice is observed, drug therapy should be discontinued. [See Adverse Reactions (6.2, 6.3).]  



     5.7  Macular Edema



  Macular edema has been reported in postmarketing experience in some diabetic patients who were taking AVANDIA or another thiazolidinedione. Some patients presented with blurred vision or decreased visual acuity, but some patients appear to have been diagnosed on routine ophthalmologic examination. Most patients had peripheral edema at the time macular edema was diagnosed. Some patients had improvement in their macular edema after discontinuation of their thiazolidinedione. Patients with diabetes should have regular eye exams by an ophthalmologist, per the Standards of Care of the American Diabetes Association. Additionally, any diabetic who reports any kind of visual symptom should be promptly referred to an ophthalmologist, regardless of the patient's underlying medications or other physical findings. [See Adverse Reactions (6.1).]  



     5.8  Fractures



  In a 4- to 6-year comparative study (ADOPT) of glycemic control with monotherapy in drug-naive patients recently diagnosed with type 2 diabetes mellitus, an increased incidence of bone fracture was noted in female patients taking AVANDIA. Over the 4- to 6-year period, the incidence of bone fracture in females was 9.3% (60/645) for AVANDIA versus 3.5% (21/605) for glyburide and 5.1% (30/590) for metformin. This increased incidence was noted after the first year of treatment and persisted during the course of the study. The majority of the fractures in the women who received AVANDIA occurred in the upper arm, hand, and foot. These sites of fracture are different from those usually associated with postmenopausal osteoporosis (e.g., hip or spine). No increase in fracture rates was observed in men treated with AVANDIA. The risk of fracture should be considered in the care of patients, especially female patients, treated with AVANDIA, and attention given to assessing and maintaining bone health according to current standards of care.



     5.9  Hematologic Effects



  Decreases in mean hemoglobin and hematocrit occurred in a dose-related fashion in adult patients treated with AVANDIA [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  . The observed changes may be related to the increased plasma volume observed with treatment with AVANDIA.



     5.10  Diabetes and Blood Glucose Control



  Patients receiving AVANDIA in combination with other hypoglycemic agents may be at risk for hypoglycemia, and a reduction in the dose of the concomitant agent may be necessary.



 Periodic fasting blood glucose and HbA1c measurements should be performed to monitor therapeutic response.



     5.11  Ovulation



  Therapy with AVANDIA, like other thiazolidinediones, may result in ovulation in some premenopausal anovulatory women. As a result, these patients may be at an increased risk for pregnancy while taking AVANDIA [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  . Thus, adequate contraception in premenopausal women should be recommended. This possible effect has not been specifically investigated in clinical studies; therefore, the frequency of this occurrence is not known.



 Although hormonal imbalance has been seen in preclinical studies [see Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)]  , the clinical significance of this finding is not known. If unexpected menstrual dysfunction occurs, the benefits of continued therapy with AVANDIA should be reviewed.



  Figure 1. Forest Plot of Odds Ratios (95% Confidence Intervals) for Myocardial Ischemic Events in the Meta-Analysis of 42 Clinical Trials  Figure 2. Hazard Ratios for the Risk of MACE (Myocardial Infarction, Cardiovascular Death, or Stroke), Myocardial Infarction, and Total Mortality With AVANDIA Compared With a Control Group   
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
