<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="avapro" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Hypertension

  AVAPRO has been evaluated for safety in more than 4300 patients with hypertension and about 5000 subjects overall. This experience includes 1303 patients treated for over 6 months and 407 patients for 1 year or more. Treatment with AVAPRO was well-tolerated, with an incidence of adverse events similar to placebo. These events generally were mild and transient with no relationship to the dose of AVAPRO.



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials, discontinuation of therapy due to a clinical adverse event was required in 3.3% of patients treated with AVAPRO, versus 4.5% of patients given placebo.



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials, the following adverse event experiences reported in at least 1% of patients treated with AVAPRO (n=1965) and at a higher incidence versus placebo (n=641), excluding those too general to be informative and those not reasonably associated with the use of drug because they were associated with the condition being treated or are very common in the treated population, include: diarrhea (3% vs 2%), dyspepsia/heartburn (2% vs 1%), and fatigue (4% vs 3%).



 The following adverse events occurred at an incidence of 1% or greater in patients treated with irbesartan, but were at least as frequent or more frequent in patients receiving placebo: abdominal pain, anxiety/nervousness, chest pain, dizziness, edema, headache, influenza, musculoskeletal pain, pharyngitis, nausea/vomiting, rash, rhinitis, sinus abnormality, tachycardia, and urinary tract infection.



 Irbesartan use was not associated with an increased incidence of dry cough, as is typically associated with ACE inhibitor use. In placebo-controlled studies, the incidence of cough in irbesartan-treated patients was 2.8% versus 2.7% in patients receiving placebo.



 The incidence of hypotension or orthostatic hypotension was low in irbesartan-treated patients (0.4%), unrelated to dosage, and similar to the incidence among placebo-treated patients (0.2%). Dizziness, syncope, and vertigo were reported with equal or less frequency in patients receiving irbesartan compared with placebo.



 In addition, the following potentially important events occurred in less than 1% of the 1965 patients and at least 5 patients (0.3%) receiving irbesartan in clinical studies, and those less frequent, clinically significant events (listed by body system). It cannot be determined whether these events were causally related to irbesartan:



   Body as a Whole:  fever, chills, facial edema, upper extremity edema



   Cardiovascular:  flushing, hypertension, cardiac murmur, myocardial infarction, angina pectoris, arrhythmic/conduction disorder, cardio-respiratory arrest, heart failure, hypertensive crisis



   Dermatologic:  pruritus, dermatitis, ecchymosis, erythema face, urticaria



   Endocrine/Metabolic/Electrolyte Imbalances:  sexual dysfunction, libido change, gout



   Gastrointestinal:  constipation, oral lesion, gastroenteritis, flatulence, abdominal distention



   Musculoskeletal/Connective Tissue:  extremity swelling, muscle cramp, arthritis, muscle ache, musculoskeletal chest pain, joint stiffness, bursitis, muscle weakness



   Nervous System:  sleep disturbance, numbness, somnolence, emotional disturbance, depression, paresthesia, tremor, transient ischemic attack, cerebrovascular accident



   Renal/Genitourinary:  abnormal urination, prostate disorder



   Respiratory:  epistaxis, tracheobronchitis, congestion, pulmonary congestion, dyspnea, wheezing



   Special Senses:  vision disturbance, hearing abnormality, ear infection, ear pain, conjunctivitis, other eye disturbance, eyelid abnormality, ear abnormality



   Nephropathy in Type 2 Diabetic Patients

  In clinical studies in patients with hypertension and type 2 diabetic renal disease, the adverse drug experiences were similar to those seen in patients with hypertension with the exception of an increased incidence of orthostatic symptoms (dizziness, orthostatic dizziness, and orthostatic hypotension) observed in IDNT (proteinuria &gt;=900 mg/day, and serum creatinine ranging from 1.0-3.0 mg/dL). In this trial, orthostatic symptoms occurred more frequently in the AVAPRO group (dizziness 10.2%, orthostatic dizziness 5.4%, orthostatic hypotension 5.4%) than in the placebo group (dizziness 6.0%, orthostatic dizziness 2.7%, orthostatic hypotension 3.2%).



   Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of AVAPRO. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to AVAPRO.



 The following have been very rarely reported: urticaria; angioedema (involving swelling of the face, lips, pharynx, and/or tongue); increased liver function tests; jaundice; and hepatitis. Hyperkalemia has been rarely reported.



 Impaired renal function, including cases of renal failure in patients at risk, has been reported.



 Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers.



   Laboratory Test Findings

  Hypertension

  In controlled clinical trials, clinically important differences in laboratory tests were rarely associated with administration of AVAPRO.



   Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen:  Minor increases in blood urea nitrogen (BUN) or serum creatinine were observed in less than 0.7% of patients with essential hypertension treated with AVAPRO alone versus 0.9% on placebo. (See    PRECAUTIONS: Impaired Renal Function    .)



   Hematologic:  Mean decreases in hemoglobin of 0.2 g/dL were observed in 0.2% of patients receiving AVAPRO compared to 0.3% of placebo-treated patients. Neutropenia (&lt;1000 cells/mm  3  ) occurred at similar frequencies among patients receiving AVAPRO (0.3%) and placebo-treated patients (0.5%).



   Nephropathy in Type 2 Diabetic Patients

    Hyperkalemia:  In IDNT (proteinuria &gt;=900 mg/day, and serum creatinine ranging from 1.0-3.0 mg/dL), the percent of patients with hyperkalemia (&gt;6 mEq/L) was 18.6% in the AVAPRO group versus 6.0% in the placebo group. Discontinuations due to hyperkalemia in the AVAPRO group were 2.1% versus 0.4% in the placebo group.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: USE IN PREGNANCY

  USE IN PREGNANCY

    When used in pregnancy during the second and third trimesters, drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus.   When pregnancy is detected, AVAPRO should be discontinued as soon as possible. See     WARNINGS: Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality    .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
