<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="aveed" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) are acne, injection site pain, prostatic specific antigen (PSA) increased, estradiol increased, hypogonadism, fatigue, irritability, hemoglobin increased, insomnia, and mood swings (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Endo Pharmaceuticals at 1-800-462-3636 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch        .    



 

    6.1  Clinical Trial Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. 



 Aveed was evaluated in an 84-week clinical study using a dose regimen of 750 mg (3 mL) at initiation, at 4 weeks, and every 10 weeks thereafter in 153 hypogonadal men.   The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;2%) were: acne (5.2%), injection site pain (4.6%), prostate specific antigen increased (4.6%), hypogonadism (2.6%)  and estradiol increased (2.6%). 



 Table 1 presents adverse reactions reported by  &gt;=  1% of patients in the 84-week clinical study.



   Table 1  



   Adverse Reactions Reported in at Least 1% of Patients in the 84-Week Clinical Study of Aveed   




     MedDRA Preferred term    Number of patients (%)    
  Aveed 750 mg (N=153)    
  Acne             8 (5.2%)         
  Injection site pain    7 (4.6%)         
  Prostatic specific antigen increased*    7 (4.6%)         
  Estradiol increased    4 (2.6%)         
  Hypogonadism     4 (2.6%)         
  Fatigue          3 (2%)           
  Irritability     3 (2%)           
  Hemoglobin increased    3 (2%)           
  Insomnia         3 (2%)           
  Mood swings      3 (2%)           
  Aggression       2 (1.3%)         
  Ejaculation disorder    2 (1.3%)         
  Injection site erythema    2 (1.3%)         
  Hematocrit increased    2 (1.3%)         
  Hyperhidrosis    2 (1.3%)         
  Prostate Cancer    2 (1.3%)         
  Prostate induration    2 (1.3%)         
  Weight increased    2 (1.3%)         
        *    Prostate specific antigen increased    defined as a serum PSA concentration &gt;4 ng/mL.
 

 In the 84-week clinical trial, 7 patients (4.6%) discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions.  Adverse reactions leading to discontinuation included:  hematocrit increased, estradiol increased, prostatic specific antigen increased, prostate cancer, mood swings, prostatic dysplasia, acne, and deep vein thrombosis.  



 During the 84-week clinical trial, the average serum PSA increased from 1.0 +/- 0.8 ng/mL at baseline to 1.5 +/-1.3 ng/mL at the end of study.  Fourteen patients (10.9%) in whom the baseline PSA was &lt; 4 ng/mL had a post-baseline serum PSA of &gt; 4 ng/mL during the 84-week treatment period.



 A total of 725 hypogonadal men received intramuscular testosterone undecanoate in a total of 7 controlled clinical trials.  In these clinical trials, the dose and dose frequency of intramuscular testosterone undecanoate varied from 750 mg to 1000 mg, and from every 9 weeks to every 14 weeks.  Several of these clinical trials incorporated additional doses upon initiation of therapy (e.g., loading doses).  In addition to those adverse reactions noted in Table 1, the following adverse events were reported by at least 3% of patients in these trials, irrespective of the investigator's assessment of relationship to study medication: sinusitis, prostatitis, arthralgia, nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, bronchitis, back pain, hypertension, diarrhea and headache.



     Pulmonary Oil Microembolism (POME) and Anaphylaxis in Controlled Clinical Studies    



 Adverse events attributable to pulmonary oil microembolism and anaphylaxis were reported in a small number of patients in controlled clinical trials.  In the 84-week clinical trial of Aveed, 1 patient experienced a mild coughing fit lasting 10 minutes after his third injection, which was retrospectively attributed to POME. In another clinical trial of intramuscular testosterone undecanoate (1000 mg), a hypogonadal male patient experienced the urge to cough and respiratory distress at 1 minute after his tenth injection, which was also retrospectively attributed to POME.



 During a review that involved adjudication of all cases meeting specific criteria, 9 POME events in 8 patients and 2 events of anaphylaxis among 3,556 patients treated with intramuscular testosterone undecanoate in 18 clinical trials were judged to have occurred.



     6.2  Postmarketing Experience  

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Aveed.  Because the reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Pulmonary Oil Microembolism (POME) and Anaphylaxis    



 Serious pulmonary oil microembolism (POME) reactions, involving cough, urge to cough, dyspnea, hyperhidrosis, throat tightening, chest pain, dizziness, and syncope, have been reported to occur during or immediately after the injection of intramuscular testosterone undecanoate 1000 mg (4 mL) in post-approval use outside the United States.  The majority of these events lasted a few minutes and resolved with supportive measures; however, some lasted up to several hours and some required emergency care and/or hospitalization.



 In addition to serious POME reactions, episodes of anaphylaxis, including life-threatening reactions, have also been reported to occur following the injection of intramuscular testosterone undecanoate in post-approval use outside of the United States.   



 Both serious POME reactions and anaphylaxis have been reported to occur after any injection of testosterone undecanoate during the course of therapy, including after the first dose.     



     Other Events    



 The following treatment emergent adverse events or adverse reactions have been identified during post-marketing clinical trials and during post-approval use outside the United States of intramuscular testosterone undecanoate.  In most cases, the dose being used was 1000 mg. 



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:   polycythemia, thrombocytopenia



   Cardiac Disorders:    angina pectoris, cardiac arrest, cardiac failure, coronary artery disease, coronary artery occlusion, myocardial infarction, tachycardia



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:    sudden hearing loss, tinnitus



   Endocrine Disorders:   hyperparathyroidism, hypoglycemia



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:    abdominal pain upper, diarrhea, vomiting



   General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions:    chest pain, edema peripheral, injection site discomfort, injection site hematoma, injection site irritation, injection site pain, injection site reaction, malaise, paresthesia, procedural pain



   Immune System Disorders:    anaphylactic reaction, anaphylactic shock, asthma, dermatitis allergic, hypersensitivity, leukocytoclastic vasculitis



   Infections and Infestations:    injection site abscess, prostate infection



   Investigations:    alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood bilirubin increased, blood glucose increased, blood pressure increased, blood prolactin increased, blood testosterone decreased, blood testosterone increased, blood triglycerides increased, gamma-glutamyltransferase increased, hematocrit increased, intraocular pressure increased, liver function test abnormal, prostate examination abnormal, prostatic specific antigen increased, transaminases increased



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:    diabetes mellitus, fluid retention, hyperlipidemia, hypertriglyceridemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:   musculoskeletal chest pain, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia, osteopenia, osteoporosis, systemic lupus erythematosus



   Neoplasms Benign, Malignant and Unspecified (including cysts and polyps):    prostate cancer, prostatic intraepithelial neoplasia



   Nervous System Disorders:   stroke, cerebrovascular insufficiency, reversible ischemic neurological deficiency, transient ischemic attack



   Psychiatric Disorders:    aggression, anxiety, depression, insomnia, irritability, Korsakoff's psychosis non-alcoholic, male orgasmic disorder, nervousness, restlessness, sleep disorder



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:    calculus urinary, dysuria, hematuria, nephrolithiasis, pollakiuria, renal colic, renal pain, urinary tract disorder



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:    benign prostatic hyperplasia, breast induration, breast pain, erectile dysfunction, gynecomastia, libido decreased, libido increased, prostate induration, prostatitis, spermatocele, testicular pain



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:    asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, cough, dysphonia, dyspnea, hyperventilation, obstructive airway disorder, pharyngeal edema, pharyngolaryngeal pain, pulmonary microemboli, pulmonary embolism, respiratory distress, rhinitis, sleep apnea syndrome, snoring



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    acne, alopecia, angioedema, angioneurotic edema, dermatitis allergic, erythema, hyperhidrosis, pruritus, rash



   Vascular Disorders:    cerebral infarction, cerebrovascular accident, circulatory collapse, deep venous thrombosis, hot flush, hypertension, syncope, thromboembolism, thrombosis, venous insufficiency.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING:  WARNING:  SERIOUS PULMONARY OIL MICROEMBOLISM (POME) REACTIONS  AND  ANAPHYLAXIS

     WARNING:  SERIOUS PULMONARY OIL MICROEMBOLISM (POME) REACTIONS  AND  ANAPHYLAXIS  

    *  Serious POME reactions, involving urge to cough, dyspnea, throat tightening, chest pain, dizziness, and syncope; and episodes of anaphylaxis, including life-threatening reactions, have been reported to occur during or immediately after the administration of testosterone undecanoate injection.  These reactions can occur after any injection of testosterone undecanoate during the course of therapy, including after the first dose [seeWarnings and Precautions (5.1)].   
 *  Following each injection of Aveed, observe patients in the healthcare setting for 30 minutes in order to provide appropriate medical treatment in the event of serious POME reactions or anaphylaxis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Because of the risks of serious POME reactions and anaphylaxis, Aveed is available only through a restricted program under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) called the Aveed REMS Program [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: SERIOUS PULMONARY OIL MICROEMBOLISM (POME) REACTIONS AND ANAPHYLAXIS  
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Serious POME reactions, involving urge to cough, dyspnea, throat tightening, chest pain, dizziness, and syncope; and episodes of anaphylaxis, including life-threatening reactions, have been reported to occur during or immediately after the administration of testosterone undecanoate injection.  These reactions can occur after any injection of testosterone undecanoate during the course of therapy, including after the first dose (5.1).   
 *  Following each injection of Aveed, observe patients in the healthcare setting for 30 minutes in order to provide appropriate medical treatment in the event of serious POME reactions or anaphylaxis (5.1). 
 *  Aveed is available only through a restricted program called the Aveed REMS Program (5.2). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Monitor patients with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) for worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH (  5.3  ). 
 *  Venous thromboembolism (VTE), including deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE) have been reported in patients using testosterone products. Evaluate patients with signs or symptoms consistent with DVT or PE. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Some postmarketing studies have shown an increased risk of myocardial infarction and stroke associated with use of testosterone replacement therapy. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Exogenous administration of androgens may lead to azoospermia (  5.8  ). 
 *  Edema with or without congestive heart failure may be a complication in patients with preexisting cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease (  5.10  ). 
 *  Sleep apnea may occur in those with risk factors (  5.12  ). 
 *  Monitor prostatic specific antigen (PSA), hemoglobin, hematocrit, and lipid concentrations periodically (  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.13  ). 
    
 

    5.1  Serious Pulmonary Oil Microembolism (POME) Reactions and Anaphylaxis  



  Serious POME reactions, involving cough, urge to cough, dyspnea, hyperhidrosis, throat tightening, chest pain, dizziness, and syncope, have been reported to occur during or immediately after the injection of intramuscular testosterone undecanoate 1000 mg (4 mL).  The majority of these events lasted a few minutes and resolved with supportive measures; however, some lasted up to several hours and some required emergency care and/or hospitalization. To minimize the risk of intravascular injection of Aveed, care should be taken to inject the preparation deeply into the gluteal muscle, being sure to follow the recommended procedure for intramuscular administration [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ,  2.3  ) and Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )]  .



 In addition to serious POME reactions, episodes of anaphylaxis, including life-threatening reactions, have also been reported to occur following the injection of intramuscular testosterone undecanoate. 



 Both serious POME reactions and anaphylaxis can occur after any injection of testosterone undecanoate during the course of therapy, including after the first dose.  Patients with suspected hypersensitivity reactions to Aveed should not be re-treated with Aveed.  



 Following each injection of Aveed, observe patients in the healthcare setting for 30 minutes in order to provide appropriate medical treatment in the event of serious POME reactions and anaphylaxis.



     5.2   Aveed Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) Program  



  Aveed is available only through a restricted program called the Aveed REMS Program because of the risk of serious POME and anaphylaxis .  



 Notable requirements of the Aveed REMS Program include the following:



 *  Healthcare providers who prescribe Aveed must be certified with the REMS Program before ordering or dispensing Aveed. 
 *  Healthcare settings must be certified with the REMS Program and have healthcare providers who are certified before ordering or dispensing Aveed. Healthcare settings must have on-site access to equipment and personnel trained to manage serious POME and anaphylaxis. 
    Further information is available at www.AveedREMS.com or call 1-855-755-0494.
 

     5.3  Worsening of Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia (BPH) and Potential Risk of Prostate Cancer  



  Patients with BPH treated with androgens are at an increased risk of worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH. Monitor patients with BPH for worsening signs and symptoms.



 Patients treated with androgens may be at an increased risk for prostate cancer.  Evaluate patients for prostate cancer prior to initiating and during treatment with androgens [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .  



     5.4 Polycythemia  



  Increases in hematocrit, reflective of increases in red blood cell mass, may require discontinuation of testosterone.



 Check hematocrit prior to initiating testosterone treatment.  It would be appropriate to re-evaluate the hematocrit 3 to 6 months after starting testosterone treatment, and then annually.  If hematocrit becomes elevated, stop therapy until hematocrit decreases to an acceptable level. An increase in red blood cell mass may increase the risk of thromboembolic events.



     5.5 Venous Thromboembolism  



   There have been postmarketing reports of venous thromboembolic events, including deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE), in patients using testosterone products, such as Aveed. Evaluate patients who report symptoms of pain, edema, warmth and erythema in the lower extremity for DVT and those who present with acute shortness of breath for PE. If a venous thromboembolic event is suspected, discontinue treatment with Aveed and initiate appropriate workup and management.  



     5.6  Cardiovascular Risk  



   Long term clinical safety trials have not been conducted to assess the cardiovascular outcomes of testosterone replacement therapy in men. To date, epidemiologic studies and randomized controlled trials have been inconclusive for determining the risk of major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE), such as non-fatal myocardial infarction, non-fatal stroke, and cardiovascular death, with the use of testosterone compared to non-use. Some studies, but not all, have reported an increased risk of MACE in association with use of testosterone replacement therapy in men. Patients should be informed of this possible risk when deciding whether to use or to continue to use Aveed.  



     5.7  Use in Women  



  Due to lack of controlled evaluations in women and potential virilizing effects, Aveed is not indicated for use in women.



     5.8  Potential for Adverse Effects on Spermatogenesis  



  With large doses of exogenous androgens, including Aveed, spermatogenesis may be suppressed through feedback inhibition of pituitary follicle- stimulating hormone (FSH) which could possibly lead to adverse effects on semen parameters including sperm count.



     5.9  Hepatic Adverse Effects  



  Prolonged use of high doses of orally active 17-alpha-alkyl androgens (e.g., methyltestosterone) has been associated with serious hepatic adverse effects (peliosis hepatis, hepatic neoplasms, cholestatic hepatitis, and jaundice).  Peliosis hepatis can be a life-threatening or fatal complication.  Long-term therapy with intramuscular testosterone enanthate, which elevates blood levels for prolonged periods, has produced multiple hepatic adenomas.  Aveed is not known to produce these adverse effects. Nonetheless, patients should be instructed to report any signs or symptoms of hepatic dysfunction (e.g., jaundice).  If these occur, promptly discontinue Aveed while the cause is evaluated.



     5.10  Edema  



  Androgens, including Aveed, may promote retention of sodium and water.  Edema with or without congestive heart failure may be a serious complication in patients with preexisting cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease.  In addition to discontinuation of the drug, diuretic therapy may be required.



     5.11  Gynecomastia  



  Gynecomastia occasionally develops and occasionally persists in patients being treated for hypogonadism [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  .



     5.12  Sleep Apnea  



  The treatment of hypogonadal men with testosterone products may potentiate sleep apnea in some patients, especially those with risk factors such as obesity or chronic lung diseases.



     5.13  Lipids  



  Changes in serum lipid profile may require dose adjustment of lipid lowering drugs or discontinuation of testosterone therapy. 



     5.14  Hypercalcemia  



  Androgens, including Aveed, should be used with caution in cancer patients at risk of hypercalcemia (and associated hypercalciuria). Regular monitoring of serum calcium concentrations is recommended in these patients.



     5.15  Decreased Thyroxine-binding Globulin  



  Androgens, including Aveed, may decrease concentrations of thyroxine-binding globulin, resulting in decreased total T4 serum concentrations and increased resin uptake of T3 and T4.  Free thyroid hormone concentrations remain unchanged, however, and there is no clinical evidence of thyroid dysfunction.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
