<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="avycaz" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in greater detail in the Warnings and Precautions section:



 *  Decreased Clinical Response in Patients with Baseline CrCL of 30 to 50 mL/min [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *   Clostridium difficile -Associated Diarrhea [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Central Nervous System Reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) ] 
 *  Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence of &gt;= 10% in either indication) are vomiting, nausea, constipation, and anxiety. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Forest Laboratories, LLC, at 1-800-678-1605 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 AVYCAZ was evaluated in two active-controlled Phase 2 clinical trials, one each in cIAI and cUTI, including pyelonephritis. The Phase 2 trials included a total of 169 adult patients treated with AVYCAZ and 169 patients treated with comparators.



     Complicated Intra-Abdominal Infections  



 The Phase 2 cIAI trial included 101 adult patients treated with AVYCAZ (2 grams ceftazidime and 0.5 grams avibactam) administered intravenously over 30 minutes every 8 hours plus 500 mg metronidazole administered intravenously over 60 minutes every 8 hours and 102 patients treated with meropenem. The median age of patients treated with AVYCAZ was 41 years (range 18 to 79 years). Patients were predominantly male (69.3%) and Caucasian (55.4%). Patients with an estimated baseline CrCL 50 mL/min or less were excluded.



 Serious adverse reactions occurred in 9/101 (8.9%) of patients receiving AVYCAZ (with metronidazole) and 11/102 (10.8%) of patients receiving meropenem. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in patients receiving AVYCAZ were skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders (3%).



 Adverse reactions occurring in 10% or more of patients receiving AVYCAZ were vomiting and nausea.



     Increased Mortality  



 In a Phase 3 cIAI trial, death occurred in 2.5% (13/529) of patients who received AVYCAZ/ metronidazole and in 1.5% (8/529) of patients who received meropenem. Among a subgroup of patients with baseline CrCL 30 to 50 mL/min, death occurred in 25.8% (8/31) of patients who received AVYCAZ/metronidazole and in 8.6% (3/35) of patients who received meropenem. Within this subgroup, patients treated with AVYCAZ received a 33% lower daily dose than is currently recommended for patients with CrCL 30 to 50 mL/min [  see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ]. In patients with normal renal function or mild renal impairment (baseline CrCL greater than 50 mL/min), death occurred in 1.0% (5/498) of patients who received AVYCAZ/metronidazole and in 1.0% (5/494) of patients who received meropenem. The causes of death varied and contributing factors included progression of underlying infection, baseline pathogens isolated that were unlikely to respond to the study drug, and delayed surgical intervention.



     Complicated Urinary Tract Infections, Including Pyelonephritis  



 The Phase 2 cUTI trial included 68 adult patients treated with AVYCAZ (0.5 grams ceftazidime + 0.125 grams avibactam) administered intravenously over 30 minutes every 8 hours and 67 patients treated with imipenem-cilastatin (0.5 grams intravenously every 6 hours). The dose of AVYCAZ in this trial was lower than the recommended dose [  see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ]. Median age of patients treated with AVYCAZ was 47.5 years (range 18 to 85 years). Patients were predominantly female (75%) and Caucasian (58.8%). Patients with CrCL less than 70 mL/min were excluded.



 Serious adverse reactions occurred in 6/68 (8.8%) of patients receiving AVYCAZ and 2/67 (3.0%) of patients receiving imipenem-cilastatin. Two patients prematurely discontinued treatment with AVYCAZ: one due to an accidental overdose and one due to atrial fibrillation.



 Adverse reactions occurring in 10% or more of patients receiving AVYCAZ were constipation and anxiety.



   Table 4  lists adverse reactions occurring in 5% or more of patients receiving AVYCAZ in the Phase 2 cIAI trial or the Phase 2 cUTI trial.



 Table 4. Incidence of Selected Adverse Drug Reactions Occurring in 5% or more of Patients Receiving AVYCAZ in the Phase 2 cIAI Trial or the Phase 2 cUTI Trial 
  a 2.5 grams (2 grams/0.5 grams) intravenously over 30 minutes every 8 hours (with metronidazole 500 mg intravenously every 8 hours)    
  b 1 gram intravenously over 30 minutes every 8 hours    
  c 0.625 grams (0.5 grams/0.125 grams) intravenously over 30 minutes every 8 hours    
  d 0.5 grams intravenously over 30 minutes every 6 hours    
  
                                       Phase 2 cIAI Trial      Phase 2 cUTI Trial     
   AVYCAZ plus    Metronidazole      a      (N = 101)      Meropenem      b      (N = 102)      AVYCAZ      c      (N = 68)      Imipenem-Cilastatin      d      (N = 67)     
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                             
      Vomiting                       14%                5%               0%               0%                  
      Nausea                         10%                6%               2%               5%                  
      Constipation                   4%                 1%               10%              3%                  
      Abdominal pain                 8%                 3%               7%               5%                  
      Upper abdominal pain           1%                 0%               7%               2%                  
   Investigations                                                         
      Increased blood alkaline phosphatase  9%                 7%               3%               2%                  
      Increased alanine aminotransferase  8%                 13%              3%               6%                  
   Nervous system disorders           
      Dizziness                      0%                 2%               6%               0%                  
   Psychiatric disorders              
      Anxiety                        5%                 1%               10%              8%                  
               Other Adverse Reactions of AVYCAZ and Ceftazidime  
 

 The following selected adverse reactions were reported in AVYCAZ-treated subjects at a rate of less than 5% in the Phase 2 trials and are not described elsewhere in the labeling.



 *      Blood and lymphatic disorders - Eosinophilia, Thrombocytopenia 
 *      Investigations - Increased gamma-glutamyltransferase, Prolonged prothrombin time 
 *      Metabolism and nutrition disorders - Hypokalemia 
 *      Renal and urinary disorders - Acute renal failure, Renal impairment 
 *      Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders - Rash 
    Additionally, adverse reactions reported with ceftazidime alone that were not reported in AVYCAZ clinical trials are listed below:
 

 *      Blood and lymphatic disorders - Agranulocytosis, Hemolytic anemia, Leukopenia, Lymphocytosis, Neutropenia, Thrombocytosis 
 *      General disorders and administration site conditions - Infusion site inflammation, Injection site hematoma, Injection site phlebitis, Injection site thrombosis 
 *      Hepatobiliary disorders - Jaundice 
 *      Infections and infestations - Candidiasis 
 *      Investigations - Increased blood lactate dehydrogenase 
 *      Nervous system disorders - Dysgeusia, Paresthesia 
 *      Renal and urinary disorders - Tubulointerstitial nephritis 
 *      Reproductive and breast disorders - Vaginal inflammation 
 *      Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders - Angioedema, Erythema multiforme, Pruritis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, Toxic epidermal necrolysis, Urticaria 
        Laboratory Changes  
 

 Seroconversion from a negative to a positive direct Coombs' test result occurred in 6/82 (7.3%) of patients receiving AVYCAZ plus metronidazole and 2/84 (2.4%) of patients receiving meropenem in the cIAI trial. Seroconversion from a negative to a positive direct Coombs' test result occurred in 1/52 (1.9%) of patients receiving AVYCAZ and 5/60 (8.3%) of patients receiving imipenem cilastatin in the cUTI trial. No adverse reactions representing hemolytic anemia were reported in any treatment group.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Decreased efficacy in patients with baseline CrCL of 30 to 50 mL/ min. Monitor CrCL at least daily in patients with changing renal function and adjust the dose of AVYCAZ accordingly. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions : Includes anaphylaxis and serious skin reactions. Cross-hypersensitivity may occur in patients with a history of penicillin allergy. If an allergic reaction occurs, discontinue AVYCAZ. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea : Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with nearly all systemic antibacterial agents, including AVYCAZ. Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Central Nervous System Reactions : Seizures and other neurologic events may occur, especially in patients with renal impairment. Adjust dose in patients with renal impairment. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Decreased Clinical Response in Patients with Baseline Creatinine Clearance of 30 to 50 mL/min



  In a Phase 3 cIAI trial, clinical cure rates were lower in a subgroup of patients with baseline CrCL of 30 to 50 mL/min compared to those with CrCL greater than 50 mL/min (  Table 3  ). The reduction in clinical cure rates was more marked in patients treated with AVYCAZ plus metronidazole compared to meropenem-treated patients. Within this subgroup, patients treated with AVYCAZ received a 33% lower daily dose than is currently recommended for patients with CrCL 30 to 50 mL/min. Monitor CrCL at least daily in patients with changing renal function and adjust the dosage of AVYCAZ accordingly [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ), and Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )].  



 Table 3. Clinical Cure Rate at Test of Cure, by Baseline Renal Function - mMITT Population1 
  1Microbiological modified intent-to-treat (mMITT) population included patients who had at least one bacterial pathogen at baseline and received at least one dose of study drug.    
  
                                        AVYCAZ + Metronidazole% (n/N)    Meropenem% (n/N)                  
 Normal function / mild impairment(CrCL greater than 50 mL/min)  85% (322/379)                    86% (321/373)                     
 Moderate impairment(CrCL 30 to 50 mL/min)  45% (14/31)                      74% (26/35)                       
            5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions
 

  Serious and occasionally fatal hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions and serious skin reactions have been reported in patients receiving beta-lactam antibacterial drugs. Before therapy with AVYCAZ is instituted, careful inquiry about previous hypersensitivity reactions to other cephalosporins, penicillins, or carbapenems should be made. Exercise caution if this product is to be given to a penicillin or other beta-lactam-allergic patient because cross sensitivity among beta-lactam antibacterial drugs has been established. Discontinue the drug if an allergic reaction to AVYCAZ occurs.



    5.3 Clostridium difficile-  associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported for nearly all systemic antibacterial drugs, including AVYCAZ, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial drugs alters the normal flora of the colon and may permit overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial use. Careful medical history is necessary because CDAD has been reported to occur more than 2 months after the administration of antibacterial drugs.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, antibacterial drugs not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Manage fluid and electrolyte levels as appropriate, supplement protein intake, monitor antibacterial treatment of C. difficile  , and institute surgical evaluation as clinically indicated.



    5.4 Central Nervous System Reactions



  Seizures, nonconvulsive status epilepticus, encephalopathy, coma, asterixis, neuromuscular excitability, and myoclonia have been reported in patients treated with ceftazidime, particularly in the setting of renal impairment. Adjust dosing based on creatinine clearance [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.5 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing AVYCAZ in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria [see Indications and Usage (  1.3  )].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
