<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="axert" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious cardiac reactions, including myocardial infarction, have occurred following the use of AXERT  (r)  (almotriptan malate) Tablets. These reactions are extremely rare and most have been reported in patients with risk factors predictive of CAD. Reactions reported in association with triptans have included coronary artery vasospasm, transient myocardial ischemia, myocardial infarction, ventricular tachycardia, and ventricular fibrillation  [see  Contraindications (4.1)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



 The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 Risk of Myocardial Ischemia and Infarction and Other Adverse Cardiac Events  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



 Sensations of Pain, Tightness, Pressure in the Chest and/or Throat, Neck, and Jaw  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  



 Cerebrovascular Events and Fatalities  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  



 Other Vasospasm-Related Events, Including Peripheral Vascular Ischemia and Colonic Ischemia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  



 Serotonin Syndrome  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  



 Increases in Blood Pressure  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  



 Adverse events were assessed in controlled clinical trials that included 1840 adult patients who received one or two doses of AXERT  (r)  and 386 adult patients who received placebo. The most common adverse reactions during treatment with AXERT  (r)  were nausea, somnolence, headache, paresthesia, and dry mouth. In long-term open-label studies where patients were allowed to treat multiple attacks for up to 1 year, 5% (63 out of 1347 patients) withdrew due to adverse experiences.



 Adverse events were assessed in controlled clinical trials that included 362 adolescent patients who received AXERT  (r)  and 172 adolescent patients who received placebo. The most common adverse reactions during treatment with AXERT  (r)  were dizziness, somnolence, headache, paresthesia, nausea, and vomiting. In a long-term, open-label study where patients were allowed to treat multiple attacks for up to 1 year, 2% (10 out of 420 adolescent patients) withdrew due to adverse events.



 Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=1% and greater than placebo) are:



 *  In adults: nausea, dry mouth and paresthesia (  6.1  ) 
 *  In adolescents: dizziness, somnolence, headache, paresthesia, nausea and vomiting (  6.2  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ortho-McNeil-Janssen Scientific Affairs Customer Communications Center at    1-800-526-7736 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  
 

 

  6.1 Commonly-Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled AXERT  (r)  Clinical Trials

  Adults



 Table 1 lists the adverse events that occurred in at least 1% of the adult patients treated with AXERT  (r)  , and at an incidence greater than in patients treated with placebo, regardless of drug relationship.



 Table 1. Incidence of Adverse Events in Controlled Clinical Trials (Reported in at Least 1% of Adult Patients Treated with AXERT(r), and at an Incidence Greater than Placebo) 
 System/Organ Class  Adverse Event   AXERT  (r)  6.25 mg(n=527)%  AXERT  (r)  12.5 mg(n=1313)%     Placebo(n=386)%       
  
   Digestive Disorders                                                                                        
   Nausea                                      1                       2                       1              
   Dry mouth                                   1                       1                      0.5             
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                   
   Paresthesia                                 1                       1                      0.5             
          The incidence of adverse events in controlled clinical trials was not affected by gender, weight, age, presence of aura, or use of prophylactic medications or oral contraceptives. There were insufficient data to assess the effect of race on the incidence of adverse events.
 

   Adolescents



 Table 2 lists the adverse reactions reported by 1% or more of AXERT  (r)  -treated adolescents age 12 to 17 years in 1 placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trial.



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=1% of Adolescent Patients Treated with AXERT(r) in 1 Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Clinical Trial 
 System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction  AXERT  (r)  6.25 mg(n=180)%  AXERT  (r)  12.5 mg(n=182)%     Placebo(n=172)%       
  
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                   
   Dizziness                                   4                       3                       2              
   Somnolence                                  &lt;1                      5                       2              
   Headache                                    1                       2                       1              
   Paresthesia                                 &lt;1                      1                       &lt;1             
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                 
   Nausea                                      1                       3                       0              
   Vomiting                                    2                       0                       &lt;1             
            6.2 Other Adverse Reactions Observed in AXERT  (r)  Clinical Trials
   In the paragraphs that follow, the frequencies of less commonly reported adverse clinical reactions are presented. The reports include adverse reactions in 5 adult controlled studies and 1 adolescent controlled study. Variability associated with adverse reaction reporting, the terminology used to describe adverse reactions, etc., limit the value of the quantitative frequency estimates provided. Reaction frequencies are calculated as the number of patients who used AXERT  (r)  and reported a reaction divided by the total number of patients exposed to AXERT  (r)  (n=3047, all doses). All reported reactions are included except those already listed in the previous table, those too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug. Reactions are further classified within system organ class and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions: frequent adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 or more patients, infrequent adverse reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/100 to 1/1000 patients, and rare adverse reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



 Body:  Frequent:  Headache.  Infrequent:  Abdominal cramp or pain, Asthenia, Chills, Back pain, Chest pain, Neck pain, Fatigue, and Rigid neck.  Rare:  Fever and Photosensitivity reaction.



 Cardiovascular:  Infrequent:  Vasodilation, Palpitations, and Tachycardia.  Rare:  Hypertension and Syncope.



 Digestive:  Infrequent:  Diarrhea, Vomiting, Dyspepsia, Gastroenteritis, and Increased thirst.  Rare:  Colitis, Gastritis, Esophageal reflux, and Increased salivation.



 Metabolic:  Infrequent:  Hyperglycemia and Increased serum creatine phosphokinase.  Rare:  Increased gamma glutamyl transpeptidase and Hypercholesteremia.



 Musculo-Skeletal:  Infrequent:  Myalgia.  Rare:  Arthralgia, Arthritis, Myopathy, and Muscle weakness.



 Nervous:  Frequent:  Dizziness and Somnolence.  Infrequent:  Tremor, Vertigo, Anxiety, Hypoesthesia, Restlessness, CNS stimulation, and Shakiness.  Rare:  Change in dreams, Impaired concentration, Abnormal coordination, Depressive symptoms, Euphoria, Hyperreflexia, Hypertonia, Nervousness, Neuropathy, Nightmares, Nystagmus, and Insomnia.



 Respiratory:  Infrequent:  Pharyngitis, Rhinitis, Dyspnea, Laryngismus, Sinusitis, and Bronchitis.  Rare:  Hyperventilation, Laryngitis, Sneezing, and Epistaxis.



 Skin:  Infrequent:  Diaphoresis, Pruritus, and Rash.  Rare:  Dermatitis and Erythema.



 Special Senses:  Infrequent:  Ear pain and Tinnitus.  Rare:  Diplopia, Dry eyes, Eye pain, Otitis media, Parosmia, Scotoma, Conjunctivitis, Eye irritation, Hyperacusis, and Taste alteration.



 Urogenital:  Infrequent:  Dysmenorrhea.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of AXERT  (r)  . Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Immune System Disorders: Anaphylactic shock



 Psychiatric Disorders: Confusional state, Restlessness



 Nervous System Disorders: Hemiplegia, Hypoesthesia, Seizures



 Eye Disorders: Blepharospasm



 Ear and Labyrinth Disorders: Vertigo



 Cardiac Disorders: Acute myocardial infarction, Coronary artery vasospasm, Angina pectoris, Tachycardia



 Gastrointestinal Disorders: Abdominal discomfort, Abdominal pain, Abdominal pain upper, Colitis, Hypoesthesia oral, Swollen tongue



 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders: Angioedema, Cold sweat, Erythema, Hyperhidrosis



 Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue, and Bone Disorders: Arthralgia, Myalgia, Pain in extremity



 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders: Breast pain



 General Disorders: Malaise, Peripheral coldness.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious adverse cardiac events, including acute myocardial infarction and life-threatening disturbances of cardiac rhythm (  5.1  ) 
 *  It is strongly recommended that AXERT  (r)  not be given to patients in whom unrecognized coronary artery disease (CAD) is predicted by the presence of risk factors. In very rare cases, serious cardiovascular events have been reported in association with AXERT  (r)  use in the absence of known cardiovascular disease. If AXERT  (r)  is considered, patients should first have a cardiovascular evaluation. If the evaluation is satisfactory, first dose should take place in a physician's office setting (  5.1  ) 
 *  Sensations of pain, tightness, pressure, and heaviness in the chest, throat, neck, and jaw: generally not associated with myocardial ischemia, but patients with signs or symptoms suggestive of angina should be evaluated for the presence of CAD (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cerebrovascular events, some fatal (  5.3  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal ischemic events and peripheral vasospastic reactions (e.g., Raynaud's syndrome) (  5.4  ) 
 *  Potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome, particularly in combination with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) or serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs). Monitor patients for neurologic changes and gastrointestinal symptoms if concomitant treatment is clinically warranted (  5.5  ,  7.3  ) 
 *  Increase in blood pressure, very rarely associated with significant clinical events (  4.4  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Use with caution in patients with a known hypersensitivity to sulfonamides (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Myocardial Ischemia and Infarction and Other Adverse Cardiac Events



  Cardiac Events and Fatalities with 5-HT1Agonists



 Serious adverse cardiac events, including acute myocardial infarction, have been reported within a few hours following administration of AXERT  (r)  (almotriptan malate). Life-threatening disturbances of cardiac rhythm and death have been reported within a few hours following the administration of other triptans. Considering the extent of use of triptans in patients with migraine, the incidence of these events is extremely low.



 AXERT  (r)  can cause coronary vasospasm; at least one of these events occurred in a patient with no cardiac history and with documented absence of coronary artery disease. Because of the close proximity of the events to use of AXERT  (r)  , a causal relationship cannot be excluded. Patients who experience signs or symptoms suggestive of angina following dosing should be evaluated for the presence of coronary artery disease (CAD) or a predisposition to Prinzmetal's variant angina before receiving additional doses of medication, and should be monitored electrocardiographically if dosing is resumed and similar symptoms recur.



    Premarketing Experience with AXERT  (r)  in Adults  



 Among the 3865 subjects/patients who received AXERT  (r)  in premarketing clinical trials, one patient was hospitalized for observation after a scheduled electrocardiogram (ECG) was found to be abnormal (negative T-waves on the left leads) 48 hours after taking a single 6.25 mg dose of almotriptan. The patient, a 48-year-old female, had previously taken 3 other doses for earlier migraine attacks. Myocardial enzymes at the time of the abnormal ECG were normal. The patient was diagnosed as having had myocardial ischemia and that she had a family history of coronary disease. An ECG performed 2 days later was normal, as was a follow-up coronary angiography. The patient recovered without incident.



    Postmarketing Experience with AXERT  (r)  in Adults  



 Serious cardiovascular events have been reported in association with the use of AXERT  (r)  . The uncontrolled nature of postmarketing surveillance, however, makes it impossible to definitively determine the proportion of the reported cases that were actually caused by almotriptan or to reliably assess causation in individual cases [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .



    Patients with Documented Coronary Artery Disease  



 Because of the potential of this class of compound (5-HT1agonists) to cause coronary vasospasm, AXERT  (r)  should not be given to patients with documented ischemic or vasospastic coronary artery disease [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  .



    Patients with Risk Factors for CAD  



 It is strongly recommended that AXERT  (r)  not be given to patients in whom unrecognized CAD is predicted by the presence of risk factors (e.g., hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, smoker, obesity, diabetes, strong family history of CAD, female with surgical or physiological menopause, or male over 40 years of age) unless a cardiovascular evaluation provides satisfactory clinical evidence that the patient is reasonably free of coronary artery and ischemic myocardial disease or other significant underlying cardiovascular disease. The sensitivity of cardiac diagnostic procedures to detect cardiovascular disease or predisposition to coronary artery vasospasm is modest, at best. If, during the cardiovascular evaluation, the patient's medical history, electrocardiographic or other investigations reveal findings indicative of, or consistent with, coronary artery vasospasm or myocardial ischemia, AXERT  (r)  should not be administered [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  .



 For patients with risk factors predictive of CAD, who are determined to have a satisfactory cardiovascular evaluation, it is strongly recommended that administration of the first dose of AXERT  (r)  take place in the setting of a physician's office or similar medically staffed and equipped facility unless the patient has previously received AXERT  (r)  . Because cardiac ischemia can occur in the absence of clinical symptoms, consideration should be given to obtaining on the first occasion of use an ECG during the interval immediately following AXERT  (r)  , in these patients with risk factors. It is recommended that patients who are intermittent long-term users of AXERT  (r)  and who have or acquire risk factors predictive of CAD, as described above, undergo periodic interval cardiovascular evaluation as they continue to use AXERT  (r)  .



 The systematic approach described above is intended to reduce the likelihood that patients with unrecognized cardiovascular disease will be inadvertently exposed to AXERT  (r)  . The ability of cardiac diagnostic procedures to detect all cardiovascular diseases or predisposition to coronary artery vasospasm is modest at best. Cardiovascular events associated with triptan treatment have occurred in patients with no cardiac history and with documented absence of coronary artery disease.



    5.2 Sensations of Pain, Tightness, Pressure in the Chest and/or Throat, Neck, and Jaw



  As with other 5-HT1agonists, sensations of tightness, pain, pressure, and heaviness in the precordium, throat, neck, and jaw have been reported after treatment with AXERT  (r)  . Because 5-HT1agonists may cause coronary vasospasm, patients who experience signs or symptoms suggestive of angina following dosing should be evaluated for the presence of CAD or a predisposition to Prinzmetal's variant angina before receiving additional doses of medication, and should be monitored electrocardiographically if dosing is resumed and similar symptoms occur. Patients shown to have CAD and those with Prinzmetal's variant angina should not receive 5-HT1agonists [see  Contraindications (4.1)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



    5.3 Cerebrovascular Events and Fatalities



  Cerebral hemorrhage, subarachnoid hemorrhage, stroke, and other cerebrovascular events have been reported in patients treated with other triptans and some events have resulted in fatalities. In a number of cases, it appeared possible that the cerebrovascular events were primary, the triptan having been administered in the incorrect belief that the symptoms experienced were a consequence of migraine, when they were not. As with other acute migraine therapies, before treating headaches in patients not previously diagnosed as migraineurs and in migraineurs who present with atypical symptoms, care should be taken to exclude other potentially serious neurological conditions. It should be noted that patients with migraine may be at increased risk of certain cerebrovascular events (e.g., stroke, hemorrhage, and transient ischemic attack) [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ]  .



    5.4 Other Vasospasm-Related Events, Including Peripheral Vascular Ischemia and Colonic Ischemia



  Triptans, including AXERT  (r)  , may cause vasospastic reactions other than coronary artery vasospasm, such as peripheral and gastrointestinal vascular ischemia with abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea. Very rare reports of transient and permanent blindness and significant partial vision loss have been reported with the use of triptans. Visual disorders may also be part of a migraine attack. Patients who experience symptoms or signs suggestive of decreased arterial flow following the use of any triptan, such as ischemic bowel syndrome or Raynaud's syndrome, are candidates for further evaluation [see  Contraindications (4.3)  ]  .



    5.5 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome may occur with triptans, including AXERT  (r)  , particularly during combined use with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) or serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs). If concomitant treatment with AXERT  (r)  and an SSRI (e.g., fluoxetine, paroxetine, sertraline, fluvoxamine, citalopram, escitalopram) or SNRI (e.g., venlafaxine, duloxetine) is clinically warranted, careful observation of the patient is advised, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases. Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination) and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea) [See  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ]  .



    5.6 Increases in Blood Pressure



  As with other triptans, significant elevations in systemic blood pressure have been reported on rare occasions with AXERT  (r)  use in patients with and without a history of hypertension; very rarely these increases in blood pressure have been associated with significant clinical events. AXERT  (r)  is contraindicated in patients with uncontrolled hypertension [see  Contraindications (4.4)  ]  . In normotensive healthy subjects and patients with hypertension controlled by medication, small, but clinically insignificant, increases in mean systolic (0.21 and 4.87 mm Hg, respectively) and diastolic (1.35 and 0.26 mm Hg, respectively) blood pressure relative to placebo were seen over the first 4 hours after oral administration of 12.5 mg of almotriptan.



 An 18% increase in mean pulmonary artery pressure was seen following dosing with another triptan in a study evaluating subjects undergoing cardiac catheterization.



    5.7 Hypersensitivity to Sulfonamides



  Caution should be exercised when prescribing AXERT  (r)  to patients with known hypersensitivity to sulfonamides. The chemical structure of almotriptan contains a sulfonyl group, which is structurally different from a sulfonamide. Cross-sensitivity to almotriptan in patients allergic to sulfonamides has not been systematically evaluated.



    5.8 Impaired Hepatic or Renal Function



  AXERT  (r)  should be administered with caution to patients with diseases that may alter the absorption, metabolism, or excretion of drugs, such as those with impaired hepatic or renal function [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ,  (2.3)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.9 Binding to Melanin-Containing Tissues



  When pigmented rats were given a single oral dose of 5 mg/kg of radiolabeled almotriptan, the elimination half-life of radioactivity from the eye was 22 days. This finding suggests that almotriptan and/or its metabolites may bind to melanin in the eye. Because almotriptan could accumulate in melanin-rich tissues over time, there is the possibility that it could cause toxicity in these tissues with extended use. However, no adverse retinal effects related to treatment with almotriptan were noted in a 52-week toxicity study in dogs given up to 12.5 mg/kg/day (resulting in exposure [AUC] to parent drug approximately 20 times that in humans receiving the maximum recommended human dose of 25 mg/day). Although no systematic monitoring of ophthalmologic function was undertaken in clinical trials, and no specific recommendations for ophthalmologic monitoring are offered, prescribers should be aware of the possibility of long-term ophthalmologic effects.



    5.10 Corneal Opacities



  Three male dogs (out of a total of 14 treated) in a 52-week toxicity study of oral almotriptan developed slight corneal opacities that were noted after 51 weeks, but not after 25 weeks of treatment. The doses at which this occurred were 2, 5, and 12.5 mg/kg/day. The opacity reversed after a 4-week drug-free period in the affected dog treated with the highest dose. Systemic exposure (plasma AUC) to parent drug at 2 mg/kg/day was approximately 2.5 times the exposure in humans receiving the maximum recommended human daily dose of 25 mg. A no-effect dose was not established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
