<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="axiron" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;4%) are skin application site reactions, increased hematocrit, headache, diarrhea, vomiting, and increased serum PSA (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Clinical Trials in Hypogonadal Men  



   Table 2  shows the treatment emergent adverse reactions that were reported by either &gt;4% of 155 patients in a 120 day, Phase 3 study or by &gt;4% of 71 patients who continued to use AXIRON for up to 180 days. These data reflect the experience primarily with a testosterone dose of 60 mg, which was taken by all patients at the start of the study, and was the maintenance dose for 97 patients. However, the doses used varied from 30 mg to 120 mg.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Seen With the Use of AXIRON in either the 120 Day Clinical Trial or in the Extension to 180 Days (&gt;4%) 
 Event                                        120 Days(155 Patients)        180 Days(71 Patients)          
  
 Application Site Irritation                  11 (7%)                       6 (8%)                         
 Application Site Erythema                    8 (5%)                        5 (7%)                         
 Headache                                     8 (5%)                        4 (6%)                         
 Hematocrit Increased                         6 (4%)                        5 (7%)                         
 Diarrhea                                     4 (3%)                        3 (4%)                         
 Vomiting                                     4 (3%)                        3 (4%)                         
 PSA Increased                                2 (1%)                        3 (4%)                         
         Other less common adverse reactions reported by at least 2 patients in the 120 day trial included: application site edema, application site warmth, increased hemoglobin, hypertension, erythema (general), increased blood glucose, acne, nasopharyngitis, anger and anxiety. Other less common adverse reactions reported in fewer than 1% of patients in the 120 day trial included: asthenia, affect lability, folliculitis, increased lacrimation, breast tenderness, increased blood pressure, increased blood testosterone, neoplasm prostate and elevated red blood cell count.
 

 During the 120 day trial one patient discontinued treatment because of affect lability/anger which was considered possibly related to AXIRON administration.



 During the 120 day clinical trial there was an increase in mean PSA values of 0.13 +/- 0.68 ng/mL from baseline. At the end of the 180 day extension clinical trial, there was an overall increase in mean PSA values of 0.1 +/- 0.54 ng/mL.



 Following the 120 day study, seventy-one (71) patients entered a two-month extension study with AXIRON. Two patients (3%) had adverse reactions that led to discontinuation of treatment during the period from Day 120 to Day 180. These reactions were: one patient with application site irritation (considered possibly related to AXIRON application) and one patient with dry skin and erythema, but not at the application site (considered not related to AXIRON administration) and application site erythema (considered possibly related to AXIRON administration).



 No serious adverse reactions to AXIRON were reported during either the 120 day trial, or the extension to 180 days.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE

    WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE  

    *  Virilization has been reported in children who were secondarily exposed to topical testosterone products [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  Children should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using AXIRON [see Dosage and Administration (2.2) and Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  Healthcare providers should advise patients to strictly adhere to recommended instructions for use [see Dosage and Administration (2.2), Warnings and Precautions (5.2) and Patient Counseling Information (17)]. 
      EXCERPT:    
 



  





   WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE  



 *  Virilization has been reported in children who were secondarily exposed to topical testosterone products (5.2) 
 *  Children should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using AXIRON (2.2, 5.2) 
 *  Healthcare providers should advise patients to strictly adhere to recommended instructions for use (2.2, 5.2, 17) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Monitor patients with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) for worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH (  5.1  ) 
 *  Avoid unintentional exposure of women or children to AXIRON. Secondary exposure to testosterone can produce signs of virilization. AXIRON should be discontinued until the cause of the virilization is identified (  2.2  ,  5.2  ) 
 *  Exogenous administration of testosterone may lead to azoospermia (  5.5  ) 
 *  Edema with or without congestive heart failure, may be a complication in patients with preexisting cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease (  5.7  ). 
 *  Sleep apnea may occur in those with risk factors (  5.9  ) 
 *  Monitor serum testosterone, prostate specific antigen (PSA), liver function, lipid concentrations, hematocrit and hemoglobin periodically (  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.6  ,  5.10  ) 
 *  AXIRON is flammable until dry (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Worsening of Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia and Potential Risk of Prostate Cancer



    *  Monitor patients with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) for worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH. 
 *  Patients treated with Androgens may be at increased risk for prostate cancer. Evaluate patients for prostate cancer prior to initiating treatment. It would be appropriate to reevaluate patients 3 to 6 months after initiation of treatment, and then in accordance with prostate cancer screening practices. [See Contraindications (  4  )] . 
       5.2 Potential for Secondary Exposure to Testosterone
 

  Cases of secondary exposure to testosterone in children and women have been reported with topical testosterone products applied to the abdomen or upper arms, including cases of secondary exposure resulting in virilization of children. Signs and symptoms have included enlargement of the penis or clitoris, development of pubic hair, increased erections and libido, aggressive behavior, and advanced bone age. In most cases, these signs and symptoms regressed with removal of the exposure to testosterone. In a few cases, however, enlarged genitalia did not fully return to age-appropriate normal size, and bone age remained modestly greater than chronological age. The risk of transfer was increased in some of these cases by not adhering to precautions for the appropriate use of the topical testosterone product. Children and women should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using AXIRON [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



 Inappropriate changes in genital size or development of pubic hair or libido in children, or changes in body hair distribution, significant increase in acne, or other signs of virilization in adult women should be brought to the attention of a physician and the possibility of secondary exposure to testosterone should also be brought to the attention of a physician. Testosterone therapy should be promptly discontinued at least until the cause of virilization has been identified. [See Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  .



    5.3 Polycythemia



  Increases in hematocrit, reflective of increases in red blood cell mass, may require lowering or discontinuation of testosterone. Check hematocrit prior to initiating testosterone treatment. It would be appropriate to re-evaluate the hematocrit 3 to 6 months after starting testosterone treatment, and then annually. If hematocrit becomes elevated, stop therapy until hematocrit decreases to an acceptable level. An increase in red blood cell mass may increase the risk of thromboembolic events.



    5.4 Use in Women



  Due to lack of controlled studies in women and potential virilizing effects, AXIRON is not indicated for use in women [see Contraindications (  4  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ,  8.3  )]  .



    5.5 Potential for Adverse Effects on Spermatogenesis



  At large doses of exogenous androgens, including AXIRON, spermatogenesis may be suppressed through feedback inhibition of pituitary follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) which could possibly lead to adverse effects on semen parameters including sperm count.



    5.6 Hepatic Adverse Effects



  Prolonged use of high doses of orally active 17-alpha-alkyl androgens (methyltestosterone) has been associated with serious hepatic adverse effects (peliosis hepatitis, hepatic neoplasms, cholestatic hepatitis, and jaundice). Peliosis hepatitis can be a life-threatening or fatal complication. Long-term therapy with intramuscular testosterone enanthate has produced multiple hepatic adenomas. AXIRON is not known to cause these adverse effects.



    5.7 Edema



  Androgens, including AXIRON, may promote retention of sodium and water. Edema, with or without congestive heart failure, may be a serious complication in patients with pre-existing cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  .



    5.8 Gynecomastia



  Gynecomastia may develop and may persist in patients being treated with androgens, including AXIRON, for hypogonadism.



    5.9 Sleep Apnea



  The treatment of hypogonadal men with testosterone may potentiate sleep apnea in some patients, especially those with risk factors such as obesity and chronic lung disease.



    5.10 Lipids



  Changes in serum lipid profile may require dose adjustment or discontinuation of testosterone therapy.



    5.11 Hypercalcemia



  Androgens, including AXIRON, should be used with caution in cancer patients at risk of hypercalcemia (and associated hypercalciuria). Regular monitoring of serum calcium concentrations is recommended in these patients.



    5.12 Decreased Thyroxine-binding Globulin



  Androgens, including AXIRON, may decrease concentrations of thyroxin-binding globulins, resulting in decreased total T4 serum concentration and increased resin uptake of T3 and T4. Free thyroid hormone concentration remain unchanged, however there is no clinical evidence of thyroid dysfunction.



    5.13 Flammability



  Alcohol based products, including AXIRON, are flammable; therefore, patients should be advised to avoid smoking, fire or flame until the AXIRON dose applied has dried.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
