<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="azithromycin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are diarrhea (5 to 14%), nausea (3 to 18%), abdominal pain (3 to 7%), or vomiting (2 to 7%).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Greenstone LLC at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical trials, most of the reported side effects were mild to moderate in severity and were reversible upon discontinuation of the drug. Potentially serious adverse reactions of angioedema and cholestatic jaundice were reported. Approximately 0.7% of the patients (adults and pediatric patients) from the 5-day multiple-dose clinical trials discontinued AZITHROMYCIN therapy because of treatment-related adverse reactions. In adults given 500 mg/day for 3 days, the discontinuation rate due to treatment-related adverse reactions was 0.6%. In clinical trials in pediatric patients given 30 mg/kg, either as a single dose or over 3 days, discontinuation from the trials due to treatment-related adverse reactions was approximately 1%. Most of the adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were related to the gastrointestinal tract, e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or abdominal pain  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  



     Adults  



 Multiple-dose regimens: Overall, the most common treatment-related adverse reactions in adult patients receiving multiple-dose regimens of AZITHROMYCIN were related to the gastrointestinal system with diarrhea/loose stools (4 to 5%), nausea (3%), and abdominal pain (2 to 3%) being the most frequently reported.



 No other adverse reactions occurred in patients on the multiple-dose regimens of AZITHROMYCIN with a frequency greater than 1%. Adverse reactions that occurred with a frequency of 1% or less included the following:



   Cardiovascular:  Palpitations, chest pain.



   Gastrointestinal:  Dyspepsia, flatulence, vomiting, melena, and cholestatic jaundice.



   Genitourinary:  Monilia, vaginitis, and nephritis.



   Nervous System:  Dizziness, headache, vertigo, and somnolence.



   General:  Fatigue.



   Allergic:  Rash, pruritus, photosensitivity, and angioedema.



   Single 1-gram dose regimen:



 Overall, the most common adverse reactions in patients receiving a single-dose regimen of 1 gram of AZITHROMYCIN were related to the gastrointestinal system and were more frequently reported than in patients receiving the multiple-dose regimen.



 Adverse reactions that occurred in patients on the single 1-gram dosing regimen of AZITHROMYCIN with a frequency of 1% or greater included diarrhea/loose stools (7%), nausea (5%), abdominal pain (5%), vomiting (2%), dyspepsia (1%), and vaginitis (1%).



   Single 2-gram dose regimen:



 Overall, the most common adverse reactions in patients receiving a single 2-gram dose of AZITHROMYCIN were related to the gastrointestinal system. Adverse reactions that occurred in patients in this study with a frequency of 1% or greater included nausea (18%), diarrhea/loose stools (14%), vomiting (7%), abdominal pain (7%), vaginitis (2%), dyspepsia (1%), and dizziness (1%). The majority of these complaints were mild in nature.



     Pediatric Patients  



 Single and Multiple-dose regimens: The types of adverse reactions in pediatric patients were comparable to those seen in adults, with different incidence rates for the dosage regimens recommended in pediatric patients.



   Acute Otitis Media:  For the recommended total dosage regimen of 30 mg/kg, the most frequent adverse reactions (&gt;=1%) attributed to treatment were diarrhea, abdominal pain, vomiting, nausea, and rash  [see  Dosage and Administration (2)    and    Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 The incidence, based on dosing regimen, is described in the table below:




 Dosage Regimen        Diarrhea %         Abdominal Pain %      Vomiting %        Nausea %          Rash %        
  
      1-day               4.3%                  1.4%               4.9%             1.0%             1.0%         
      3-day               2.6%                  1.7%               2.3%             0.4%             0.6%         
      5-day               1.8%                  1.2%               1.1%             0.5%             0.4%         
              Community-Acquired Pneumonia:  For the recommended dosage regimen of 10 mg/kg on Day 1 followed by 5 mg/kg on Days 2-5, the most frequent adverse reactions attributed to treatment were diarrhea/loose stools, abdominal pain, vomiting, nausea, and rash.
 

 The incidence is described in the table below:




 Dosage Regimen   Diarrhea/Loose stools %    Abdominal Pain %      Vomiting %        Nausea %          Rash %        
  
      5-day               5.8%                  1.9%               1.9%             1.9%             1.6%         
              Pharyngitis/tonsillitis:  For the recommended dosage regimen of 12 mg/kg on Days 1-5, the most frequent adverse reactions attributed to treatment were diarrhea, vomiting, abdominal pain, nausea, and headache.
 

 The incidence is described in the table below:




 Dosage Regimen     Diarrhea %     Abdominal Pain %    Vomiting %        Nausea %          Rash %         Headache %      
  
      5-day            5.4%           3.4%          5.6%             1.8%             0.7%             1.1%         
             With any of the treatment regimens, no other adverse reactions occurred in pediatric patients treated with AZITHROMYCIN with a frequency greater than 1%. Adverse reactions that occurred with a frequency of 1% or less included the following:
 

   Cardiovascular:  Chest pain.



   Gastrointestinal:  Dyspepsia, constipation, anorexia, enteritis, flatulence, gastritis, jaundice, loose stools, and oral moniliasis.



   Hematologic and Lymphatic:  Anemia and leukopenia.



   Nervous System:  Headache (otitis media dosage), hyperkinesia, dizziness, agitation, nervousness, and insomnia.



   General:  Fever, face edema, fatigue, fungal infection, malaise, and pain.



   Allergic:  Rash and allergic reaction.



   Respiratory:  Cough, pharyngitis, pleural effusion, and rhinitis.



   Skin and Appendages:  Eczema, fungal dermatitis, pruritus, sweating, urticaria, and vesiculobullous rash.



   Special Senses:  Conjunctivitis.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of azithromycin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions reported with azithromycin during the postmarketing period in adult and/or pediatric patients for which a causal relationship may not be established include:



   Allergic:  Arthralgia, edema, urticaria, and angioedema.



   Cardiovascular:  Arrhythmias including ventricular tachycardia and hypotension. There have been reports of QT prolongation and  torsades de pointes  .



   Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia, constipation, dyspepsia, flatulence, vomiting/diarrhea , pseudomembranous colitis, pancreatitis, oral candidiasis, pyloric stenosis, and reports of tongue discoloration.



   General:  Asthenia, paresthesia, fatigue, malaise, and anaphylaxis  Genitourinary:  Interstitial nephritis and acute renal failure and vaginitis.



   Hematopoietic:  Thrombocytopenia.



   Liver/Biliary:  Abnormal liver function, hepatitis, cholestatic jaundice, hepatic necrosis, and hepatic failure [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  



   Nervous System:  Convulsions, dizziness/vertigo, headache, somnolence, hyperactivity, nervousness, agitation, and syncope.



   Psychiatric:  Aggressive reaction and anxiety.



   Skin/Appendages:  Pruritusserious skin reactions including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis .



   Special Senses:  Hearing disturbances including hearing loss, deafness and/or tinnitus, and reports of taste/smell perversion and/or loss.



   6.3 Laboratory Abnormalities

    Adults:  



 Clinically significant abnormalities (irrespective of drug relationship) occurring during the clinical trials were reported as follows: with an incidence of greater than 1%: decreased hemoglobin, hematocrit, lymphocytes, neutrophils, and blood glucose; elevated serum creatine phosphokinase, potassium, ALT, GGT, AST, BUN, creatinine, blood glucose, platelet count, lymphocytes, neutrophils, and eosinophils; with an incidence of less than 1%: leukopenia, neutropenia, decreased sodium, potassium, platelet count, elevated monocytes, basophils, bicarbonate, serum alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin, LDH, and phosphate. The majority of subjects with elevated serum creatinine also had abnormal values at baseline. When follow-up was provided, changes in laboratory tests appeared to be reversible.



 In multiple-dose clinical trials involving more than 5000 patients, four patients discontinued therapy because of treatment-related liver enzyme abnormalities and one because of a renal function abnormality.



     Pediatric Patients:  



 One, Three, and Five Day Regimens



 Laboratory data collected from comparative clinical trials employing two 3-day regimens (30 mg/kg or 60 mg/kg in divided doses over 3 days), or two 5-day regimens (30 mg/kg or 60 mg/kg in divided doses over 5 days) were similar for regimens of azithromycin and all comparators combined, with most clinically significant laboratory abnormalities occurring at incidences of 1-5%. Laboratory data for patients receiving 30 mg/kg as a single dose were collected in one single center trial. In that trial, an absolute neutrophil count between 500-1500 cells/mm  3  was observed in 10/64 patients receiving 30 mg/kg as a single dose, 9/62 patients receiving 30 mg/kg given over 3 days, and 8/63 comparator patients. No patient had an absolute neutrophil count &lt;500 cells/mm  3  .



 In multiple-dose clinical trials involving approximately 4700 pediatric patients, no patients discontinued therapy because of treatment-related laboratory abnormalities.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious (including fatal) allergic and skin reactions: Discontinue AZITHROMYCIN if reaction occurs. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Severe, and sometimes fatal, hepatotoxicity has been reported, Discontinue AZITHROMYCIN immediately if signs and symptoms of hepatitis occur. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Prolongation of QT interval and cases of torsades de pointes have been reported. This risk which can be fatal should be considered in patients with certain cardiovascular disorders including known QT prolongation or history torsades de pointes, those with proarrhythmic conditions, and with other drugs that prolong the QT interval. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea: Evaluate patients if diarrhea occurs. (  5.4  ) 
 *  AZITHROMYCIN may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Serious allergic reactions, including angioedema, anaphylaxis, and dermatologic reactions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis have been reported in patients on azithromycin therapy. [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  



 Fatalities have been reported. Despite initially successful symptomatic treatment of the allergic symptoms, when symptomatic therapy was discontinued, the allergic symptoms recurred soon thereafter in some patients without further azithromycin exposure. These patients required prolonged periods of observation and symptomatic treatment. The relationship of these episodes to the long tissue half-life of azithromycin and subsequent prolonged exposure to antigen is presently unknown.



 If an allergic reaction occurs, the drug should be discontinued and appropriate therapy should be instituted. Physicians should be aware that allergic symptoms may reappear when symptomatic therapy has been discontinued.



    5.2 Hepatotoxicity



  Abnormal liver function, hepatitis, cholestatic jaundice, hepatic necrosis, and hepatic failure have been reported, some of which have resulted in death. Discontinue azithromycin immediately if signs and symptoms of hepatitis occur.



    5.3 QT Prolongation



  Prolonged cardiac repolarization and QT interval, imparting a risk of developing cardiac arrhythmia and torsades de pointes, have been seen with treatment with macrolides, including azithromycin. Cases of torsades de pointes have been spontaneously reported during postmarketing surveillance in patients receiving azithromycin. Providers should consider the risk of QT prolongation which can be fatal when weighing the risks and benefits of azithromycin for at-risk groups including:



 *  patients with known prolongation of the QT interval, a history of torsades de pointes, congenital long QT syndrome, bradyarrhythmias or uncompensated heart failure 
 *  patients on drugs known to prolong the QT interval 
 *  patients with ongoing proarrhythmic conditions such as uncorrected hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia, clinically significant bradycardia, and in patients receiving Class IA (quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (dofetilide, amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic agents. 
    Elderly patients may be more susceptible to drug-associated effects on the QT interval.
 

    5.4 Clostridium difficile  -Associated Diarrhea (CDAD)



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including AZITHROMYCIN, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon, leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antibacterial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.5 Exacerbation of myasthenia gravis



  Exacerbation of symptoms of myasthenia gravis and new onset of myasthenic syndrome have been reported in patients receiving azithromycin therapy.



    5.6 Use in Sexually Transmitted Infections



  AZITHROMYCIN, at the recommended dose, should not be relied upon to treat syphilis. Antibacterial agents used to treat non-gonococcal urethritis may mask or delay the symptoms of incubating syphilis. All patients with sexually transmitted urethritis or cervicitis should have a serologic test for syphilis and appropriate testing for gonorrhea performed at the time of diagnosis. Appropriate antibacterial therapy and follow-up tests for these diseases should be initiated if infection is confirmed.



    5. 7 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing AZITHROMYCIN in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
