<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="azithromycin1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In clinical trials, most of the reported side effects were mild to moderate in severity and were reversible upon discontinuation of the drug. Approximately 0.7% of the patients from the multiple-dose clinical trials discontinued azithromycin therapy because of treatment-related side effects. Most of the side effects leading to discontinuation were related to the gastrointestinal tract, e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or abdominal pain. Rarely but potentially serious side effects were angioedema and cholestatic jaundice.



   Clinical

  



   Multiple-dose regimen

  Overall, the most common side effects in adult patients receiving a multiple-dose regimen of azithromycin were related to the gastrointestinal system with diarrhea/loose stools (5%), nausea (3%), and abdominal pain (3%) being the most frequently reported.



 No other side effects occurred in patients on the multiple-dose regimen of azithromycin with a frequency greater than 1%. Side effects that occurred with a frequency of 1% or less included the following:



   Cardiovascular:  Palpitations, chest pain.  Gastrointestinal:  Dyspepsia, flatulence, vomiting, melena, and cholestatic jaundice.  Genitourinary:  Monilia, vaginitis, and nephritis.  Nervous System:  Dizziness, headache, vertigo, and somnolence.  General:  Fatigue.  Allergic:  Rash, photosensitivity, and angioedema.



   Chronic therapy with 1200 mg weekly regimen

  The nature of side effects seen with the 1200 mg weekly dosing regimen for the prevention of  Mycobacterium avium  infection in severely immunocompromised HIV-infected patients were similar to those seen with short term dosing regimens. (See  CLINICAL STUDIES  .)



   Chronic therapy with 600 mg daily regimen combined with ethambutol

  The nature of side effects seen with the 600 mg daily dosing regimen for the treatment of  Mycobacterium avium  complex infection in severely immunocompromised HIV-infected patients were similar to those seen with short term dosing regimens. Five percent of patients experienced reversible hearing impairment in the pivotal clinical trial for the treatment of disseminated MAC in patients with AIDS. Hearing impairment has been reported with macrolide antibiotics, especially at higher doses. Other treatment related side effects occurring in &gt;5% of subjects and seen at any time during a median of 87.5 days of therapy include: abdominal pain (14%), nausea (14%), vomiting (13%), diarrhea (12%), flatulence (5%), headache (5%) and abnormal vision (5%). Discontinuations from treatment due to laboratory abnormalities or side effects considered related to study drug occurred in 8/88 (9.1%) of subjects.



   Single 1-gram dose regimen

  Overall, the most common side effects in patients receiving a single-dose regimen of 1 gram of azithromycin were related to the gastrointestinal system and were more frequently reported than in patients receiving the multiple-dose regimen.



 Side effects that occurred in patients on the single one-gram dosing regimen of azithromycin with a frequency of 1% or greater included diarrhea/loose stools (7%), nausea (5%), abdominal pain (5%), vomiting (2%), dyspepsia (1%), and vaginitis (1%).



   Post-Marketing Experience

  Adverse events reported with azithromycin during the post-marketing period in adult and/or pediatric patients for which a causal relationship may not be established include:



   Allergic:  Arthralgia, edema, urticaria, angioedema.  Cardiovascular:  Arrhythmias including ventricular tachycardia, hypotension. There have been rare reports of QT prolongation and  torsades de pointes  .  Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia, constipation, dyspepsia, flatulence, vomiting/diarrhea rarely resulting in dehydration, pseudomembranous colitis, pancreatitis, oral candidiasis and rare reports of tongue discoloration.  General:  Asthenia, paresthesia, fatigue, malaise and anaphylaxis (rarely fatal).  Genitourinary:  Interstitial nephritis and acute renal failure, vaginitis.  Hematopoietic:  Thrombocytopenia.  Liver/Biliary:  Abnormal liver function including hepatitis and cholestatic jaundice, as well as rare cases of hepatic necrosis and hepatic failure, some of which have resulted in death.  Nervous System:  Convulsions, dizziness/vertigo, headache, somnolence, hyperactivity, nervousness, agitation and syncope.  Psychiatric:  Aggressive reaction and anxiety.  Skin/Appendages:  Pruritus, rarely serious skin reactions including erythema multiforme, Stevens Johnson Syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis.  Special Senses:  Hearing disturbances including hearing loss, deafness, and/or tinnitus, reports of taste/smell perversion and/or loss.



   Laboratory Abnormalities

  Significant abnormalities (irrespective of drug relationship) occurring during the clinical trials were reported as follows:



 With an incidence of 1-2%, elevated serum creatine phosphokinase, potassium, ALT (SGPT), GGT, and AST (SGOT).



 With an incidence of less than 1%, leukopenia, neutropenia, decreased platelet count, elevated serum alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin, BUN, creatinine, blood glucose, LDH, and phosphate.



 When follow-up was provided, changes in laboratory tests appeared to be reversible.



 In multiple-dose clinical trials involving more than 3000 patients, 3 patients discontinued therapy because of treatment-related liver enzyme abnormalities and 1 because of a renal function abnormality.



 In a phase I drug interaction study performed in normal volunteers, 1 of 6 subjects given the combination of azithromycin and rifabutin, 1 of 7 given rifabutin alone and 0 of 6 given azithromycin alone developed a clinically significant neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  ).



 Laboratory abnormalities seen in clinical trials for the prevention of disseminated  Mycobacterium avium  disease in severely immunocompromised HIV-infected patients are presented in the  CLINICAL STUDIES  section.



 Chronic therapy (median duration: 87.5 days, range: 1-229 days) that resulted in laboratory abnormalities in &gt;5% subjects with normal baseline values in the pivotal trial for treatment of disseminated MAC in severely immunocompromised HIV infected patients treated with azithromycin 600 mg daily in combination with ethambutol include: a reduction in absolute neutrophils to &lt;50% of the lower limit of normal (10/52, 19%) and an increase to five times the upper limit of normal in alkaline phosphatase (3/35, 9%). These findings in subjects with normal baseline values are similar when compared to all subjects for analyses of neutrophil reductions (22/75 [29%]) and elevated alkaline phosphatase (16/80 [20%]). Causality of these laboratory abnormalities due to the use of study drug has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
