<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="baraclude" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Exacerbations of hepatitis after discontinuation of treatment [see   Boxed Warning   ,     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)     ] . 
 *    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis [see   Boxed Warning   ,   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] . 
   *    Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3%, all severity grades) are headache, fatigue, dizziness, and nausea.  (6.1)   
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch      
 

 

  6.1    Clinical Trial Experience in Adults

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Compensated Liver Disease

  Assessment of adverse reactions is based on four studies (AI463014, AI463022, AI463026, and AI463027) in which 1720 subjects with chronic hepatitis B virus infection and compensated liver disease received double-blind treatment with BARACLUDE 0.5 mg/day (n=679), BARACLUDE 1 mg/day (n=183), or lamivudine (n=858) for up to 2 years. Median duration of therapy was 69 weeks for BARACLUDE-treated subjects and 63 weeks for lamivudine-treated subjects in Studies AI463022 and AI463027 and 73 weeks for BARACLUDE-treated subjects and 51 weeks for lamivudine-treated subjects in Studies AI463026 and AI463014. The safety profiles of BARACLUDE and lamivudine were comparable in these studies.



 The most common adverse reactions of any severity (&gt;=3%) with at least a possible relation to study drug for BARACLUDE-treated subjects were headache, fatigue, dizziness, and nausea. The most common adverse reactions among lamivudine-treated subjects were headache, fatigue, and dizziness. One percent of BARACLUDE-treated subjects in these four studies compared with 4% of lamivudine-treated subjects discontinued for adverse events or abnormal laboratory test results.



 Clinical adverse reactions of moderate-severe intensity and considered at least possibly related to treatment occurring during therapy in four clinical studies in which BARACLUDE was compared with lamivudine are presented in Table 3.



 Table 3:   Clinical Adverse Reactionsa of Moderate-Severe Intensity (Grades 2-4) Reported in Four Entecavir Clinical Trials Through 2 Years 
                                      Nucleoside-Inhibitor-Naive  b        Lamivudine-Refractory  c       
   Body System/         Adverse Reaction    BARACLUDE    0.5 mg    n=679      Lamivudine    100 mg    n=668      BARACLUDE    1 mg    n=183      Lamivudine    100 mg    n=190     
  
   a     Includes events of possible, probable, certain, or unknown relationship to treatment regimen.  b     Studies AI463022 and AI463027.  c     Includes Study AI463026 and the BARACLUDE 1 mg and lamivudine treatment arms of Study AI463014, a Phase 2 multinational, randomized, double-blind study of three doses of BARACLUDE (0.1, 0.5, and 1 mg) once daily versus continued lamivudine 100 mg once daily for up to 52 weeks in subjects who experienced recurrent viremia on lamivudine therapy.   
  
  Any Grade 2-4 adverse reactiona    15%                18%                22%                23%                
  Gastrointestinal                   
       Diarrhea                      &lt;1%                0                  1%                 0                  
       Dyspepsia                     &lt;1%                &lt;1%                1%                 0                  
       Nausea                        &lt;1%                &lt;1%                &lt;1%                2%                 
       Vomiting                      &lt;1%                &lt;1%                &lt;1%                0                  
  General                            
       Fatigue                       1%                 1%                 3%                 3%                 
  Nervous System                     
       Headache                      2%                 2%                 4%                 1%                 
       Dizziness                     &lt;1%                &lt;1%                0                  1%                 
       Somnolence                    &lt;1%                &lt;1%                0                  0                  
  Psychiatric                        
       Insomnia                      &lt;1%                &lt;1%                0                  &lt;1%                
             Laboratory Abnormalities
   Frequencies of selected treatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities reported during therapy in four clinical trials of BARACLUDE compared with lamivudine are listed in Table 4.



 Table 4:   Selected Treatment-Emergenta Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in Four Entecavir Clinical Trials Through 2 Years 
                                        Nucleoside-Inhibitor-Naive  b        Lamivudine-Refractory  c       
   Test                                 BARACLUDE0.5 mgn=679      Lamivudine100 mgn=668      BARACLUDE1 mgn=183      Lamivudine100 mgn=190     
  
   a     On-treatment value worsened from baseline to Grade 3 or Grade 4 for all parameters except albumin (any on-treatment value &lt;2.5 g/dL), confirmed creatinine increase &gt;=0.5 mg/dL, and ALT &gt;10 * ULN and &gt;2 * baseline.  b     Studies AI463022 and AI463027.  c     Includes Study AI463026 and the BARACLUDE 1 mg and lamivudine treatment arms of Study AI463014, a Phase 2 multinational, randomized, double-blind study of three doses of BARACLUDE (0.1, 0.5, and 1 mg) once daily versus continued lamivudine 100 mg once daily for up to 52 weeks in subjects who experienced recurrent viremia on lamivudine therapy.  d     Includes hematology, routine chemistries, renal and liver function tests, pancreatic enzymes, and urinalysis.  e     Grade 3 = 3+, large, &gt;=500 mg/dL; Grade 4 = 4+, marked, severe.  f     Grade 3 = 3+, large; Grade 4 = &gt;=4+, marked, severe, many.ULN=upper limit of normal.   
  
  Any Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalityd    35%               36%               37%               45%                
  ALT &gt;10 * ULN and &gt;2 * baseline      2%                4%                2%                11%                
  ALT &gt;5 * ULN                         11%               16%               12%               24%                
  Albumin &lt;2.5 g/dL                    &lt;1%               &lt;1%               0                 2%                 
  Total bilirubin &gt;2.5 * ULN           2%                2%                3%                2%                 
  Lipase &gt;=2.1 * ULN                   7%                6%                7%                7%                 
  Creatinine &gt;3 * ULN                  0                 0                 0                 0                  
  Confirmed creatinine increase &gt;=0.5 mg/dL    1%                1%                2%                1%                 
  Hyperglycemia, fasting &gt;250 mg/dL    2%                1%                3%                1%                 
  Glycosuriae                          4%                3%                4%                6%                 
  Hematuriaf                           9%                10%               9%                6%                 
  Platelets &lt;50,000/mm3                &lt;1%               &lt;1%               &lt;1%               &lt;1%                
           Among BARACLUDE-treated subjects in these studies, on-treatment ALT elevations greater than 10 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) and greater than 2 times baseline generally resolved with continued treatment. A majority of these exacerbations were associated with a &gt;=2 log10/mL reduction in viral load that preceded or coincided with the ALT elevation. Periodic monitoring of hepatic function is recommended during treatment.
 

   Exacerbations of Hepatitis after Discontinuation of Treatment

  An exacerbation of hepatitis or ALT flare was defined as ALT greater than 10 times ULN and greater than 2 times the subject's reference level (minimum of the baseline or last measurement at end of dosing). For all subjects who discontinued treatment (regardless of reason), Table 5 presents the proportion of subjects in each study who experienced post-treatment ALT flares. In these studies, a subset of subjects was allowed to discontinue treatment at or after 52 weeks if they achieved a protocol-defined response to therapy. If BARACLUDE is discontinued without regard to treatment response, the rate of post-treatment flares could be higher.  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  .]  



 Table 5:   Exacerbations of Hepatitis During Off-Treatment Follow-up, Subjects in Studies AI463022, AI463027, and AI463026 
                                    Subjects with ALT Elevations &gt;10 * ULN and &gt;2 * Reference  a       
                                    BARACLUDE                           Lamivudine                         
  
   a     Reference is the minimum of the baseline or last measurement at end of dosing. Median time to off-treatment exacerbation was 23 weeks for BARACLUDE-treated subjects and 10 weeks for lamivudine-treated subjects.   
  
  Nucleoside-inhibitor-naive                                                                               
     HBeAg-positive                4/174 (2%)                          13/147 (9%)                         
     HBeAg-negative                24/302 (8%)                         30/270 (11%)                        
  Lamivudine-refractory            6/52 (12%)                          0/16                                
           Decompensated Liver Disease
   Study AI463048 was a randomized, open-label study of BARACLUDE 1 mg once daily versus adefovir dipivoxil 10 mg once daily given for up to 48 weeks in adult subjects with chronic HBV infection and evidence of hepatic decompensation, defined as a Child-Turcotte-Pugh (CTP) score of 7 or higher  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  . Among the 102 subjects receiving BARACLUDE, the most common treatment-emergent adverse events of any severity, regardless of causality, occurring through Week 48 were peripheral edema (16%), ascites (15%), pyrexia (14%), hepatic encephalopathy (10%), and upper respiratory infection (10%). Clinical adverse reactions not listed in Table 3 that were observed through Week 48 include blood bicarbonate decreased (2%) and renal failure (&lt;1%).



 Eighteen of 102 (18%) subjects treated with BARACLUDE and 18/89 (20%) subjects treated with adefovir dipivoxil died during the first 48 weeks of therapy. The majority of deaths (11 in the BARACLUDE group and 16 in the adefovir dipivoxil group) were due to liver-related causes such as hepatic failure, hepatic encephalopathy, hepatorenal syndrome, and upper gastrointestinal hemorrhage. The rate of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) through Week 48 was 6% (6/102) for subjects treated with BARACLUDE and 8% (7/89) for subjects treated with adefovir dipivoxil. Five percent of subjects in either treatment arm discontinued therapy due to an adverse event through Week 48.



 No subject in either treatment arm experienced an on-treatment hepatic flare (ALT &gt;2 * baseline and &gt;10 * ULN) through Week 48. Eleven of 102 (11%) subjects treated with BARACLUDE and 11/89 (13%) subjects treated with adefovir dipivoxil had a confirmed increase in serum creatinine of 0.5 mg/dL through Week 48.



   HIV/HBV Co-infected

  The safety profile of BARACLUDE 1 mg (n=51) in HIV/HBV co-infected subjects enrolled in Study AI463038 was similar to that of placebo (n=17) through 24 weeks of blinded treatment and similar to that seen in non-HIV infected subjects  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



   Liver Transplant Recipients

  Among 65 subjects receiving BARACLUDE in an open-label, post-liver transplant trial  [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.8)  ]  , the frequency and nature of adverse events were consistent with those expected in patients who have received a liver transplant and the known safety profile of BARACLUDE.



   6.2   Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Subjects

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of BARACLUDE in pediatric subjects 2 to less than 18 years of age is based on two ongoing clinical trials in subjects with chronic HBV infection (one Phase 2 pharmacokinetic trial [AI463028] and one Phase 3 trial [AI463189]). These trials provide experience in 168 HBeAg-positive subjects treated with BARACLUDE for a median duration of 72 weeks. The adverse reactions observed in pediatric subjects who received treatment with BARACLUDE were consistent with those observed in clinical trials of BARACLUDE in adults. Adverse drug reactions reported in greater than 1% of pediatric subjects included abdominal pain, rash events, poor palatability ("product taste abnormal"), nausea, diarrhea, and vomiting.



   6.3   Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported during postmarketing use of BARACLUDE. Because these reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to BARACLUDE exposure.



   Immune system disorders:    Anaphylactoid reaction.



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:    Lactic acidosis.



   Hepatobiliary disorders:    Increased transaminases.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:    Alopecia, rash.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SEVERE ACUTE EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B, PATIENTS CO-INFECTED WITH HIV AND HBV, and LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND HEPATOMEGALY

  WARNING: SEVERE ACUTE EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B, PATIENTS CO-INFECTED WITH HIV AND HBV, and LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND HEPATOMEGALY

    Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who have discontinued anti-hepatitis B therapy, including entecavir. Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who discontinue anti-hepatitis B therapy. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .  



   Limited clinical experience suggests there is a potential for the development of resistance to HIV (human immunodeficiency virus) nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors if BARACLUDE is used to treat chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection in patients with HIV infection that is not being treated. Therapy with BARACLUDE is not recommended for HIV/HBV co-infected patients who are not also receiving highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART)   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .  



   Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogue inhibitors alone or in combination with antiretrovirals   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SEVERE ACUTE EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B, PATIENTS CO-INFECTED WITH HIV AND HBV, and LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND HEPATOMEGALY



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who have discontinued anti-hepatitis B therapy, including entecavir. Hepatic function should be monitored closely for at least several months after discontinuation. Initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted. (5.1) 
 *  BARACLUDE is not recommended for patients co-infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and hepatitis B virus (HBV) who are not also receiving highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART), because of the potential for the development of resistance to HIV nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors. (5.2) 
 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogue inhibitors. (5.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B virus infection after discontinuation: Monitor hepatic function closely for at least several months.  (5.1  ,  6.1)   
 *    Co-infection with HIV: BARACLUDE is not recommended unless the patient is also receiving HAART.  (5.2)   
 *    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis: If suspected, treatment should be suspended.  (5.3)   
    
 

   5.1    Severe Acute Exacerbations of Hepatitis B



  Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who have discontinued anti-hepatitis B therapy, including entecavir [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who discontinue anti-hepatitis B therapy. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted.



    5.2    Patients Co-infected with HIV and HBV



  BARACLUDE has not been evaluated in HIV/HBV co-infected patients who were not simultaneously receiving effective HIV treatment. Limited clinical experience suggests there is a potential for the development of resistance to HIV nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors if BARACLUDE is used to treat chronic hepatitis B virus infection in patients with HIV infection that is not being treated [see  Microbiology (12.4)  ]  . Therefore, therapy with BARACLUDE is not recommended for HIV/HBV co-infected patients who are not also receiving HAART. Before initiating BARACLUDE therapy, HIV antibody testing should be offered to all patients. BARACLUDE has not been studied as a treatment for HIV infection and is not recommended for this use.



    5.3    Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogue inhibitors, including BARACLUDE, alone or in combination with antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged nucleoside inhibitor exposure may be risk factors. Particular caution should be exercised when administering nucleoside analogue inhibitors to any patient with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors.



 Lactic acidosis with BARACLUDE use has been reported, often in association with hepatic decompensation, other serious medical conditions, or drug exposures. Patients with decompensated liver disease may be at higher risk for lactic acidosis. Treatment with BARACLUDE should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
