<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bat" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions observed in &gt;= 5 % of healthy volunteers in clinical trials were headache, nausea, pruritus, and urticaria.



 The most common adverse reactions reported in &gt;= 1% of patients in a clinical study were pyrexia, rash, chills, nausea and edema.



 The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Hypersensitivity reactions [  5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions  ] 
 *    Delayed allergic reactions/serum sickness [  5.2 Delayed Allergic Reactions (Serum Sickness)  ] 
 *    Infusion reactions [  5.3 Infusion Reactions  ] 
   *    The most common adverse reactions observed in &gt;= 5 % of healthy volunteers in clinical trials were headache, nausea, pruritus and urticaria (  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  ). 
 *    The most common adverse reactions reported in &gt;= 1% of patients in a clinical study were pyrexia, rash, chills, nausea and edema (  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  ). 
 *    One serious adverse reaction of hemodynamic instability was observed in one patient in the clinical study (  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  ). 
      EXCERPT:   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Cangene Corporation at 1-800-768-2304 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  



 In a randomized, double-blind, parallel arm trial conducted to evaluate the safety of BAT in healthy subjects, and to establish the pharmacokinetic profile of the seven botulinum antitoxin serotypes contained in BAT following intravenous (IV) administration, 40 subjects were randomized to receive either one (n=20) or two vials (n=20) of BAT.



 In a second parallel arm, randomized, double-blind pharmacodynamic trial, 26 healthy subjects were randomized to receive either BAT in saline (n=16) or placebo (0.9% saline; n=10).



 The most common adverse reactions in all healthy subjects were headache (9%), pruritus (5%), nausea (5%), and urticaria (5%). Other adverse reactions reported in less than 4% of subjects included pyrexia and throat discomfort. All reported adverse reactions were considered mild or moderate. No serious adverse reactions were reported. Two moderate acute allergic reactions that required premature termination of the infusion and treatment were reported. Reactions were predefined as mild if the subject was aware but could tolerate. Moderate reactions were predefined as discomfort enough to interfere with normal daily activity.



 A total of 231 subjects with suspected or confirmed botulism were exposed to BAT in an open-label observational expanded access clinical study sponsored by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC).



 The majority of adult (213/216) and pediatric (13/15) subjects received one dose of BAT. Three adult subjects were exposed to a second dose of BAT, and two pediatric subjects each received two infant doses (10% of the adult dose). The administration of a second dose varied from seven hours to one month after the first dose.



 Safety data was actively collected from treating physicians by the CDC. However, no on-site safety monitoring was performed, and the CDC relied on follow-up information provided by the treating physicians to determine the reporting frequencies for adverse reactions. Of the 231 subjects receiving BAT, safety information was available for 228 subjects. Adverse reactions were reported in 10% of all subjects. The most common adverse reactions were pyrexia (4%), rash (2%), chills (1%), nausea (1%), and edema (1%). Other adverse reactions were reported in less than 1% of subjects. No subject experienced anaphylaxis. One subject experienced a serious adverse reaction of hemodynamic instability characterized by bradycardia, tachycardia, and asystole during BAT administration. One subject experienced mild serum sickness (&lt; 1%) with myalgia, arthralgia, and dark urine twelve days after BAT administration.



 *     Table 3 Summary of Adverse Drug Reactions (ADR) Reported in Subjects that Received BAT through the CDC Expanded Access Clinical Study 
  
 System Organ Class                     Preferred Term            Overall(N=228)   
 No. of Events                          No. of Subjects           % of Subjects   
  
  ALL BODY SYSTEM                        OVERALL                   37             23             10.1           
  Cardiac disorders                      Cardiac arrest            1              1              0.4            
  Bradycardia                            1                         1              0.4            
  Tachycardia                            1                         1              0.4            
  Gastrointestinal disorders             Vomiting                  1              1              0.4            
  Nausea                                 2                         2              0.9            
  General disorders and administration site conditions    Pyrexia                   9              9              3.9            
  Chest discomfort                       1                         1              0.4            
  Edema                                  2                         2              0.9            
  Chills                                 3                         3              1.3            
  Feeling jittery                        1                         1              0.4            
  Immune system disorders                Serum Sickness            1              1              0.4            
  Investigations                         Blood pressure increased    1              1              0.4            
  White blood cell count increased       1                         1              0.4            
  Psychiatric disorders                  Agitation                 1              1              0.4            
  Anxiety                                1                         1              0.4            
  Renal and urinary disorders            Urinary retention         1              1              0.4            
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders    Bronchospasm              1              1              0.4            
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders    Erythema                  1              1              0.4            
  Hyperhidrosis                          1                         1              0.4            
  Rash                                   4                         4              1.8            
  Vascular disorders                     Hemodynamic instability    1              1              0.4            
  Hypotension                            1                         1              0.4            
  All adverse reactions were classified according to MedDRA Version 15.0 and are ranked according to medical significance within a given SOC.    
             6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following hypersensitivity/allergic reactions have been reported in patients treated with BAT:



 *    Anaphylactic shock 
 *    Angioedema 
 *    Urticaria 
      6.3 Immunogenicity
   As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. All subjects from the two clinical trials were tested for immunogenicity against BAT at baseline and at the end of the studies (Day 28) using a validated assay. Eleven subjects seroconverted during the course of the two trials. One subject from each clinical trial experienced a moderate allergic reaction during the administration of BAT. Both subjects were negative for anti-BAT antibodies at baseline and at the end of their respective studies. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to BAT with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis. Prepare for monitoring and management of allergic reactions (  5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions  ). 
 *    Delayed allergic reactions (serum sickness). Patient monitoring is recommended (  5.2 Delayed Allergic Reactions (Serum Sickness)  ). 
 *    Infusion reactions. Monitor and slow or interrupt infusion and administer treatment based on the severity of the reaction (  5.3 Infusion Reactions  ). 
 *    Interference with non-glucose specific blood sugar testing systems. Use glucose-specific testing systems (  5.4 Interference with Blood Glucose Testing  ). 
 *    BAT is made from equine plasma and may contain infectious agents e.g. viruses (  5.5 Transmissible Infectious Agents  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic and anaphylactoid reactions may occur following BAT administration. Patients who have had previous therapy with an equine-derived antivenom/antitoxin, with a history of hypersensitivity to horses, asthma, or hay fever are at a greater risk for developing severe hypersensitivity reactions to BAT. Administer BAT in a setting with appropriate equipment, medication including epinephrine, and personnel trained in the management of hypersensitivity, anaphylaxis, and shock.



 Monitor all patients for signs and symptoms of acute allergic reaction (e.g. urticaria, pruritus, erythema, angioedema, bronchospasm with wheezing or cough, stridor, laryngeal edema, hypotension, tachycardia) during and following the BAT infusion. In case of hypersensitivity reaction, discontinue BAT administration immediately and administer appropriate emergency care. Have immediately available medications such as epinephrine for immediate treatment of acute hypersensitivity reactions.



 For patients at risk for hypersensitivity reaction, begin BAT administration at the lowest rate achievable (&lt; 0.01 mL/min) and monitor.



    5.2 Delayed Allergic Reactions (Serum Sickness)



  Delayed allergic reactions (serum sickness e.g. fever, urticarial or maculopapular rash, myalgia, arthralgia, and lymphadenopathy) may occur following BAT administration, typically 10-21 days after infusion. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of delayed allergic reaction.



 If a delayed allergic reaction (serum sickness) is suspected, administer appropriate medical care.



    5.3 Infusion Reactions



  Chills, fever, headaches, nausea, and vomiting can be related to the rate of infusion. Arthralgia, myalgia and fatigue or vasovagal reactions may also develop. Carefully observe patients for the onset of these infusion reactions throughout the infusion period and immediately following an infusion.



 Reduce the rate of infusion if the patient experiences infusion reactions and administer symptomatic therapy. If symptoms worsen, discontinue the infusion and administer appropriate medical care.



    5.4 Interference with Blood Glucose Testing



  The maltose contained in BAT can interfere with some types of blood glucose monitoring systems i.e. those based on glucose dehydrogenase pyrroloquinoline-quinone (GDH-PQQ) method. This can result in falsely elevated glucose readings and inappropriate administration of insulin, resulting in life-threatening hypoglycemia. Cases of true hypoglycemia may go untreated if the hypoglycemic state is masked by falsely elevated results [  7 DRUG INTERACTIONS  ].



    5.5 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because BAT is made from equine plasma, it may carry the risk of transmitting infectious agents e.g. viruses. The equine plasma pools are screened for the presence of certain infectious agents and the manufacturing process for BAT includes measures to inactivate and remove certain viruses [  11 DESCRIPTION  ]. Despite these measures, such products can still potentially transmit disease. No cases of transmission of viral diseases have been associated with the use of BAT.



 Report all infections thought by a physician to have been transmitted by BAT to Cangene Corporation at 1-800-768-2304. Discuss the risks and benefits of this product with the patient or their legal guardian before administering it to the patient [  17 PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
