<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="belbuca" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions described elsewhere in the labeling include:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Interactions with other CNS Depressants [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  QTc Prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Severe Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Anaphylactic/Allergic Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.13  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.14  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions &gt;5% include nausea, constipation, headache, vomiting, dizziness, and somnolence.  (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Endo Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-462-3636 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch      .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 2,127  patients were treated with BELBUCA in controlled and open-label chronic pain trials.  There were 504 patients treated for approximately six months and 253 patients treated for approximately one year.  The clinical trial population consisted of patients with chronic moderate-to-severe pain.



 The most common serious adverse drug reactions (all &lt;= 0.2%) occurring during clinical trials with BELBUCA were: cellulitis, pneumonia, ileus, atrial fibrillation, coronary artery disease,  cerebrovascular accident, syncope, transient ischemic attack, chest pain, non-cardiac chest pain, ankle fracture, cholecystitis, osteoarthritis, and dehydration. 



 The most common adverse events (&gt;= 2%) leading to discontinuation were nausea, vomiting, and liver function test abnormality.



 The most common adverse events (&gt;= 5%) reported by opioid naive, opioid experienced, and overall patients exposed to BELBUCA in clinical trials and compared against placebo are shown in Tables 2, 3 and 4:



 Table 2: Adverse Events Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients during the Open-Label Titration Phase and Double-Blind Treatment Phase of Controlled Studies: Opioid-Naive Patients 
                                                                                                                                                       Open-Label  Titration Phase                                                                                             Double-Blind  Treatment Phase                                                                                     
  MedDRA Preferred Term                                                                                                                                BELBUCA  (N=749)                                                                                                        BELBUCA  (N=229)                                                                                                  Placebo  (N=232)                                                                                         
  
  Nausea                                                                                                                                               50%                                                                                                                     10%                                                                                                               7%                                                                                                       
  Constipation                                                                                                                                         13%                                                                                                                     4%                                                                                                                6%                                                                                                       
  Vomiting                                                                                                                                             8%                                                                                                                      4%                                                                                                                &lt;1%                                                                                                      
  Headache                                                                                                                                             8%                                                                                                                      2%                                                                                                                3%                                                                                                       
  Dizziness                                                                                                                                            6%                                                                                                                      2%                                                                                                                &lt;1%                                                                                                      
  Somnolence                                                                                                                                           7%                                                                                                                      1%                                                                                                                &lt;1%                                                                                                      
  Fatigue                                                                                                                                              5%                                                                                                                      0%                                                                                                                1%                                                                                                       
         Table 3: Adverse Events Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients during the Open-Label Titration Phase and Double-Blind Treatment Phase of Controlled Studies: Opioid-Experienced Patients 
                                                                                                                                                       Open-Label  Titration Phase                                                                                             Double-Blind  Treatment Phase                                                                                     
  MedDRA Preferred Term                                                                                                                                BELBUCA  (N=810)                                                                                                        BELBUCA  (N=254)                                                                                                  Placebo  (N=256)                                                                                         
  
  Nausea                                                                                                                                               17%                                                                                                                     7%                                                                                                                7%                                                                                                       
  Constipation                                                                                                                                         8%                                                                                                                      3%                                                                                                                1%                                                                                                       
  Vomiting                                                                                                                                             7%                                                                                                                      5%                                                                                                                2%                                                                                                       
  Headache                                                                                                                                             7%                                                                                                                      2%                                                                                                                3%                                                                                                       
  Dizziness                                                                                                                                            5%                                                                                                                      2%                                                                                                                &lt;1%                                                                                                      
  Somnolence                                                                                                                                           5%                                                                                                                      1%                                                                                                                &lt;1%                                                                                                      
  Drug Withdrawal Syndrome                                                                                                                             0%                                                                                                                      3%                                                                                                                10%                                                                                                      
         Table 4: Adverse Events Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients during the Open-Label Titration Phase and Double-Blind Treatment Phase of Controlled Studies 
                                                                                                                                                       Open-Label  Titration Phase                                                                                                      Double-Blind  Treatment Phase                                                                                         
  MedDRA Preferred Term                                                                                                                                BELBUCA  (N=1889)                                                                                                                BELBUCA  (N=600)                                                                                                      Placebo  (N=606)    
  
  Nausea                                                                                                                                               33%                                                                                                                              9%                                                                                                                    8%               
  Constipation                                                                                                                                         11%                                                                                                                              4%                                                                                                                    2%               
  Vomiting                                                                                                                                             7%                                                                                                                               5%                                                                                                                    2%               
  Headache                                                                                                                                             8%                                                                                                                               4%                                                                                                                    3%               
  Dizziness                                                                                                                                            6%                                                                                                                               2%                                                                                                                    &lt;1%              
  Somnolence                                                                                                                                           6%                                                                                                                               &lt;1%                                                                                                                   &lt;1%              
  Drug Withdrawal Syndrome                                                                                                                             1%                                                                                                                               2%                                                                                                                    5%               
          The most common (&gt;= 5%), common (&gt;= 1% to &lt; 5%), and least common (&lt; 1%) adverse reactions reported by patients taking BELBUCA in the controlled and open-label clinical studies are presented below:
 

 Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5%): nausea, constipation, headache, vomiting, fatigue, dizziness, somnolence, diarrhea, dry mouth, and upper respiratory tract infection.



 Common (&gt;= 1% to &lt; 5%) adverse reactions (organized by MedDRA [Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities] System Organ Class: 



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  anemia



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal pain



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  peripheral edema, pyrexia, drug withdrawal syndrome



   Infections and infestations:  urinary tract infection, nasopharyngitis, sinusitis, bronchitis, gastroenteritis



   Injury, poisoning, and procedural complications:  contusion, fall



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  decreased appetite



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  muscle spasms, back pain



   Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety, insomnia, depression



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  oropharyngeal pain, sinus congestion



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  hyperhidrosis, pruritus, rash



   Vascular disorders:  hot flush, hypertension



 Least common (&lt;1%) adverse reactions:



 Abdominal discomfort, acute sinusitis, dyspepsia, toothache, asthenia, chills, cellulitis, tooth abscess, excoriation, laceration, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood pressure increased, blood testosterone decreased, electrocardiogram QT prolonged, liver function test abnormal, musculoskeletal pain, neck pain, hypoesthesia, lethargy, migraine, tremor, cough, dyspnea, nasal congestion, rhinorrhea
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, and MISUSE;

LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; and NEONATAL

OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME

  WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, and MISUSE;

LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; and NEONATAL

OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME

      Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse    



   BELBUCA exposes patients and other users to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing BELBUCA, and monitor patients regularly for the development of these behaviors or conditions   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) and Overdosage (  10  )]  .  



     Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression    



   Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of BELBUCA. Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of BELBUCA or following a dose increase. Misuse or abuse of BELBUCA by chewing, swallowing, snorting or injecting buprenorphine extracted from the buccal film will result in the uncontrolled delivery of buprenorphine and pose a significant risk of overdose and death   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



     Accidental Exposure    



   Accidental exposure to even one dose of BELBUCA, especially in children, can result in a fatal overdose of buprenorphine   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



     Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome    



   Prolonged use of BELBUCA during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, and MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; and NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  BELBUCA exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death.  Assess each patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors or conditions. (5.1, 10) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients on proper administration of BELBUCA to reduce the risk. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental exposure to BELBUCA, especially in children, can result in fatal overdose of buprenorphine. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of BELBUCA during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Risk of life-threatening respiratory depression in elderly, cachectic, debilitated patients, and in patients with chronic pulmonary disease : Monitor closely. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *   Risk of prolonged QTc interval : Avoid in patients with Long QT Syndrome, family history of Long QT Syndrome, or those taking Class IA or Class III antiarrhythmic medications. (  5.7  ,  12.2  ) 
 *   Severe hypotension : Monitor during dose initiation and titration. Avoid use of BELBUCA in patients with circulatory shock. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Risk of use in patients with increased intracranial pressure, brain tumors, head injury, or impaired consciousness : Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression.  Avoid use of BELBUCA in patients with impaired consciousness or coma. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  BELBUCA contains buprenorphine, a Schedule III controlled substance. As an opioid, BELBUCA exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse. 



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing BELBUCA and monitor all patients receiving BELBUCA for the development of these behaviors or conditions.  Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed BELBUCA, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks and proper use of BELBUCA, along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, or misuse. Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed BELBUCA.  Addiction can occur at recommended dosages and if the drug is misused or abused [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )].  



 Abuse or misuse of BELBUCA by swallowing may cause choking, overdose, and death [see Overdosage (  10  )].   



 Opioid agonists such as buprenorphine are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing BELBUCA. Strategies to reduce the risk include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper disposal of unused drug [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  . Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.2  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of buprenorphine, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression, from opioid use, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death.  Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see Overdosage (  10  )]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.



 While serious, life-threatening or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of BELBUCA, the risk is greatest during initiation of therapy or following a dose increase.  Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression when initiating therapy with BELBUCA and following dose increases.



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of BELBUCA are essential [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )]  . Overestimating the dose of BELBUCA when converting patients from another opioid product may result in fatal overdose with the first dose.



 Accidental exposure to BELBUCA, especially in children, might result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of buprenorphine.



    5.3  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Prolonged use of BELBUCA during pregnancy can result in withdrawal signs in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available.



 Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome presents as irritability, hyperactivity and abnormal sleep pattern, high pitched cry, tremor, vomiting, diarrhea, failure to gain weight; and there have been reports of convulsions, apnea, respiratory depression, and bradycardia. The onset, duration, and severity of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome vary based on the specific opioid used, duration of use, timing and amount of last maternal use, and rate of elimination of the drug by the newborn [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )].  



    5.4  Risks due to Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



  Hypotension, profound sedation, coma or respiratory depression may result if BELBUCA is used concomitantly with alcohol or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids). 



 When considering the use of BELBUCA in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration of use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin BELBUCA is made, start with a lower dosage of BELBUCA, monitor patients for signs of sedation, respiratory depression, and hypotension, and consider using a lower dosage of the concomitant CNS depressant  [see Drug Interactions (  7  )].    



    5.5  Risk of Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression in Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



  Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating BELBUCA and when BELBUCA is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].  



    5.6  Risk of Apnea in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  The use of BELBUCA in patients with acute or severe bronchial asthma in an unmonitored setting or in the absence of resuscitative equipment is contraindicated.



 BELBUCA-treated  patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and those with substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression are at increased risk of decreased respiratory drive, including apnea, even at recommended dosages of BELBUCA [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].  Therefore, closely monitor these patients, especially when initiating and titrating BELBUCA.  Alternatively, consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients.



    5.7  QTc Prolongation



  BELBUCA has been observed to prolong the QTc interval in some subjects participating in clinical trials.  Consider these observations in clinical decisions when prescribing BELBUCA to patients with hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, or clinically unstable cardiac disease, including unstable atrial fibrillation, symptomatic bradycardia, unstable congestive heart failure, or active myocardial ischemia. Periodic electrocardiographic (ECG) monitoring is recommended in these patients.  Avoid the use of BELBUCA in patients with a history of Long QT Syndrome or an immediate family member with this condition or those taking Class IA antiarrhythmic medications (e.g., quinidine, procainamide, disopyramide) or Class III antiarrhythmic medications (e.g., sotalol, amiodarone, dofetilide), or other medications that prolong the QT interval. [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ), Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ), and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )].   



    5.8  Severe Hypotension



  BELBUCA may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is an increased risk in patients whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a reduced blood volume or concurrent administration of certain CNS depressant drugs (e.g., phenothiazines or general anesthetics) [see Drug Interactions (  7  )].  Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dose of BELBUCA. In patients with circulatory shock, BELBUCA may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. Avoid the use of BELBUCA in patients with circulatory shock.



    5.9  Risks of Use in Patients with Head Injury or Increased Intracranial Pressure



  In patients who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2 retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors), BELBUCA may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2 retention can further increase intracranial pressure. Monitor such patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with BELBUCA.



 Opioids may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury.  Avoid the use of BELBUCA in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.10  Hepatotoxicity



  Cases of cytolytic hepatitis and hepatitis with jaundice have been observed in individuals receiving sublingual formulations of buprenorphine for the treatment of opioid dependence, both in clinical trials and in post-marketing adverse events reports. The spectrum of abnormalities ranges from transient asymptomatic elevations in hepatic transaminases to case reports of hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatorenal syndrome, and hepatic encephalopathy.  In many cases, the presence of pre-existing liver enzyme abnormalities, infection with hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus, concomitant usage of other potentially hepatotoxic drugs, and ongoing injection drug abuse may have played a causative or contributory role.  For patients at increased risk of hepatoxicity (e.g., patients with a history of excessive alcohol intake, intravenous drug abuse or liver disease), obtain baseline liver enzyme levels and monitor periodically during treatment with BELBUCA.



    5.11  Risk of Overdose in Patients With Moderate to Severe Hepatic Impairment



  In a pharmacokinetic study in subjects dosed with buprenorphine sublingual tablets, buprenorphine plasma levels were found to be higher and the half-life was found to be longer in subjects with moderate and severe hepatic impairment, but not in subjects with mild hepatic impairment. For patients with severe hepatic impairment, a dose adjustment is recommended, and patients with moderate or severe hepatic impairment should be monitored for signs and symptoms of toxicity or overdose caused by increased levels of buprenorphine. [see Dosage and Administration (  2.5  )  , Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  )  ].



    5.12  Anaphylactic/Allergic Reactions



  Cases of acute and chronic hypersensitivity to buprenorphine have been reported both in clinical trials and in post-marketing experience.  The most common signs and symptoms include rashes, hives, and pruritus.  Cases of bronchospasm, angioneurotic edema, and anaphylactic shock have been reported.  BELBUCA is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity to buprenorphine.



    5.13  Risk of Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  BELBUCA is contraindicated in patients with known or suspected gastrointestinal obstruction, including paralytic ileus.



 BELBUCA may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Opioids may cause increases in the serum amylase.  Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, for worsening symptoms.



    5.14  Increased Risk of Seizures in Patients with Seizure Disorders



  Buprenorphine may increase the frequency of seizures in patients with seizure disorders and may increase the risk of seizures occurring in other clinical settings associated with seizures. Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during BELBUCA therapy.



    5.15  Risks of Use in Cancer Patients with Oral Mucositis



  Cancer patients with oral mucositis may absorb buprenorphine more rapidly than intended and are likely to experience higher plasma levels of the opioid.   For patients with known or suspected mucositis, a dose reduction is recommended.  Monitor these patients carefully for signs and symptoms of toxicity or overdose caused by increased levels of buprenorphine.   [see Dosage and Administration (  2.6  ), Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    5.16  Risks of Driving and Operating Machinery



  BELBUCA may impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery.  Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to side effects of BELBUCA and know how they will react to the medication.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
