<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="belviq" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following important adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Serotonin Syndrome or NMS-like Reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  Valvular Heart Disease [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Cognitive Impairment [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Psychiatric Disorders [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) ] 
 *  Hypoglycemia [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ) ] 
 *  Heart Rate Decreases [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  ) ] 
 *  Hematological Changes [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  ) ] 
 *  Prolactin Elevation [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (greater than 5%) in non-diabetic patients are headache, dizziness, fatigue, nausea, dry mouth, and constipation, and in diabetic patients are hypoglycemia, headache, back pain, cough, and fatigue. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eisai Inc. at 1-888-274-2378 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or at      www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  In the BELVIQ placebo-controlled clinical database of trials of at least one year in duration, of 6888 patients (3451 BELVIQ vs. 3437 placebo; age range 18-66 years, 79.3% women, 66.6% Caucasians, 19.2% Blacks, 11.8% Hispanics, 2.4% other, 7.4% type 2 diabetics), a total of 1969 patients were exposed to BELVIQ 10 mg twice daily for 1 year and 426 patients were exposed for 2 years.



 In clinical trials of at least one year in duration, 8.6% of patients treated with BELVIQ prematurely discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions, compared with 6.7% of placebo-treated patients. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation more often among BELVIQ treated patients than placebo were headache (1.3% vs. 0.8%), depression (0.9% vs. 0.5%) and dizziness (0.7% vs. 0.2%).



       Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most common adverse reactions for non-diabetic patients (greater than 5% and more commonly than placebo) treated with BELVIQ compared to placebo were headache, dizziness, fatigue, nausea, dry mouth, and constipation. The most common adverse reactions for diabetic patients were hypoglycemia, headache, back pain, cough, and fatigue. Adverse reactions that were reported by greater than or equal to 2% of patients and were more frequently reported by patients taking BELVIQ compared to placebo are summarized in Table 2 (non-diabetic subjects) and Table 3 (subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus).



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions Reported by Greater Than or Equal to 2% of BELVIQ Patients and More Commonly than with Placebo in Patients without Diabetes Mellitus 
    Adverse Reaction                                              Number of patients (%)     
    BELVIQ    10 mg BID    N=3195                                 Placebo    N=3185     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
       Nausea                                                    264 (8.3)             170 (5.3)            
       Diarrhea                                                  207 (6.5)             179 (5.6)            
       Constipation                                              186 (5.8)             125 (3.9)            
       Dry mouth                                                 169 (5.3)             74 (2.3)             
       Vomiting                                                  122 (3.8)             83 (2.6)             
   General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions                                                     
       Fatigue                                                   229 (7.2)             114 (3.6)            
   Infections And Infestations                                                                              
       Upper respiratory tract infection                         439 (13.7)            391 (12.3)           
       Nasopharyngitis                                           414 (13.0)            381 (12.0)           
       Urinary tract infection                                   207 (6.5)             171 (5.4)            
   Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders                                                          
       Back pain                                                 201 (6.3)             178 (5.6)            
       Musculoskeletal pain                                      65 (2.0)              43 (1.4)             
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
       Headache                                                  537 (16.8)            321 (10.1)           
       Dizziness                                                 270 (8.5)             122 (3.8)            
   Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders                                                          
       Cough                                                     136 (4.3)             109 (3.4)            
       Oropharyngeal pain                                        111 (3.5)             80 (2.5)             
       Sinus congestion                                          93 (2.9)              78 (2.4)             
   Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                   
       Rash                                                      67 (2.1)              58 (1.8)             
        Table 3. Adverse Reactions Reported by Greater Than or Equal to 2% of BELVIQ Patients and More Commonly than with Placebo in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus 
                                                                  Number of patients (%)     
    Adverse Reaction                                              BELVIQ    10 mg BID    N=256       Placebo    N=252     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
       Nausea                                                    24 (9.4)              20 (7.9)             
       Toothache                                                 7 (2.7)               0                    
   General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions                                                     
       Fatigue                                                   19 (7.4)              10 (4.0)             
       Peripheral edema                                          12 (4.7)              6 (2.4)              
   Immune System Disorders                                                                                  
       Seasonal allergy                                          8 (3.1)               2 (0.8)              
   Infections And Infestations                                                                              
       Nasopharyngitis                                           29 (11.3)             25 (9.9)             
       Urinary tract infection                                   23 (9.0)              15 (6.0)             
       Gastroenteritis                                           8 (3.1)               5 (2.0)              
   Metabolism And Nutrition Disorders                                                                       
       Hypoglycemia                                              75 (29.3)             53 (21.0)            
       Worsening of diabetes mellitus                            7 (2.7)               2 (0.8)              
       Decreased appetite                                        6 (2.3)               1 (0.4)              
   Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders                                                          
       Back pain                                                 30 (11.7)             20 (7.9)             
       Muscle spasms                                             12 (4.7)              9 (3.6)              
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
       Headache                                                  37 (14.5)             18 (7.1)             
       Dizziness                                                 18 (7.0)              16 (6.3)             
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
       Anxiety                                                   9 (3.5)               8 (3.2)              
       Insomnia                                                  9 (3.5)               6 (2.4)              
       Stress                                                    7 (2.7)               3 (1.2)              
       Depression                                                6 (2.3)               5 (2.0)              
   Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders                                                          
       Cough                                                     21 (8.2)              11 (4.4)             
   Vascular Disorders                                                                                       
       Hypertension                                              13 (5.1)              8 (3.2)              
               Other Adverse Reactions  
 

   Serotonin-associated Adverse Reactions  



 SSRIs, SNRIs, bupropion, tricyclic antidepressants, and MAOIs were excluded from the BELVIQ trials. Triptans and dextromethorphan were permitted: 2% and 15%, respectively, of patients without diabetes and 1% and 12%, respectively, of patients with type 2 diabetes experienced concomitant use at some point during the trials. Two patients treated with BELVIQ in the clinical program experienced a constellation of symptoms and signs consistent with serotonergic excess, including one patient on concomitant dextromethorphan who reported an event of serotonin syndrome. Some symptoms of possible serotonergic etiology that are included in the criteria for serotonin syndrome were reported by patients treated with BELVIQ and placebo during clinical trials of at least 1 year in duration. In both groups, chills were the most frequent of these events (1.0% vs. 0.2%, respectively), followed by tremor (0.3% vs. 0.2%), confusional state (0.2% vs. less than 0.1%), disorientation (0.1% vs. 0.1%) and hyperhidrosis (0.1% vs. 0.2%). Because serotonin syndrome has a very low incidence, an association between BELVIQ and serotonin syndrome cannot be excluded on the basis of clinical trial results [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ].



   Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes  



 In a clinical trial of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, hypoglycemia requiring the assistance of another person occurred in 4 (1.6%) of BELVIQ-treated patients and in 1 (0.4%) placebo-treated patient. Of these 4 BELVIQ-treated patients, all were concomitantly using a sulfonylurea (with or without metformin). BELVIQ has not been studied in patients taking insulin. Hypoglycemia defined as blood sugar less than or equal to 65 mg/dL and with symptoms occurred in 19 (7.4%) BELVIQ-treated patients and 16 (6.3%) placebo-treated patients.



   Cognitive Impairment  



 In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration, adverse reactions related to cognitive impairment (e.g., difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, and confusion) occurred in 2.3% of patients taking BELVIQ and 0.7% of patients taking placebo.



   Psychiatric Disorders  



 Psychiatric disorders leading to hospitalization or drug withdrawal occurred more frequently in patients treated with BELVIQ (2.2%) as compared to placebo (1.1%) in non-diabetic patients.



   Euphoria.  In short-term studies with healthy individuals, the incidence of euphoric mood following supratherapeutic doses of BELVIQ (40 and 60 mg) was increased as compared to placebo [  see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.2  )  ]. In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration in obese patients, euphoria was observed in 0.17% of patients taking BELVIQ and 0.03% taking placebo.



   Depression and Suicidality.  In trials of at least one year in duration, reports of depression/mood problems occurred in 2.6% BELVIQ-treated vs. 2.4% placebo-treated and suicidal ideation occurred in 0.6% BELVIQ-treated vs. 0.4% placebo-treated patients. 1.3% of BELVIQ patients vs. 0.6% of placebo patients discontinued drug due to depression-, mood-, or suicidal ideation-related events.



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



   Lymphocyte and Neutrophil Counts.  In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration, lymphocyte counts were below the lower limit of normal in 12.2% of patients taking BELVIQ and 9.0% taking placebo, and neutrophil counts were low in 5.6% and 4.3%, respectively.



   Hemoglobin.  In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration, 10.4% of patients taking BELVIQ and 9.3% taking placebo had hemoglobin below the lower limit of normal at some point during the trials.



   Prolactin.  In clinical trials, elevations of prolactin greater than the upper limit of normal, two times the upper limit of normal, and five times the upper limit of normal, occurred in 6.7%, 1.7%, and 0.1% of BELVIQ-treated patients and 4.8%, 0.8%, and 0.0% of placebo-treated patients, respectively.



   Eye disorders  .



 More patients on BELVIQ reported an eye disorder than patients on placebo in clinical trials of patients without diabetes (4.5% vs. 3.0%) and with type 2 diabetes (6.3% vs. 1.6%). In the population without diabetes, events of blurred vision, dry eye, and visual impairment occurred in BELVIQ-treated patients at an incidence greater than that of placebo. In the population with type 2 diabetes, visual disorders, conjunctival infections, irritations, and inflammations, ocular sensation disorders, and cataract conditions occurred in BELVIQ-treated patients at an incidence greater than placebo.



       Echocardiographic Safety Assessments  



 The possible occurrence of regurgitant cardiac valve disease was prospectively evaluated in 7794 patients in three clinical trials of at least one year in duration, 3451 of whom took BELVIQ 10 mg twice daily. The primary echocardiographic safety parameter was the proportion of patients who developed echocardiographic criteria of mild or greater aortic insufficiency and/or moderate or greater mitral insufficiency from baseline to 1 year. At 1 year, 2.4% of patients who received BELVIQ and 2.0% of patients who received placebo developed valvular regurgitation. The relative risk for valvulopathy with BELVIQ is summarized in Table 4. BELVIQ was not studied in patients with congestive heart failure or hemodynamically-significant valvular heart disease [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ].



 Table 4. Incidence of FDA-Defined Valvulopathy at Week 52 by Treatment Group1 
    1  Patients without valvulopathy at baseline who received study medication and had a post-baseline echocardiogram; ITT-intention-to-treat; LOCF-last observation carried forward   
  
                                  Study 1       Study 2       Study 3     
                                  BELVIQ    N=1278       Placebo    N=1191       BELVIQ    N=1208       Placebo    N=1153       BELVIQ    N=210       Placebo    N=209     
    FDA-defined Valvulopathy, n (%)      34 (2.7)      28 (2.4)      24 (2.0)      23 (2.0)      6 (2.9)       1 (0.5)      
    Relative Risk (95% CI)       1.13 (0.69, 1.85)    1.00 (0.57, 1.75)    5.97 (0.73, 49.17)   
    Pooled RR (95% CI)            1.16 (0.81, 1.67)     
</Section>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S2">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following important adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Serotonin Syndrome or NMS-like Reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  Valvular Heart Disease [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Cognitive Impairment [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Psychiatric Disorders [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) ] 
 *  Hypoglycemia [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ) ] 
 *  Heart Rate Decreases [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  ) ] 
 *  Hematological Changes [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  ) ] 
 *  Prolactin Elevation [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (greater than 5%) in non-diabetic patients are headache, dizziness, fatigue, nausea, dry mouth, and constipation, and in diabetic patients are hypoglycemia, headache, back pain, cough, and fatigue. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eisai Inc. at 1-888-274-2378 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or at      www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  In the BELVIQ placebo-controlled clinical database of trials of at least one year in duration, of 6888 patients (3451 BELVIQ vs. 3437 placebo; age range 18-66 years, 79.3% women, 66.6% Caucasians, 19.2% Blacks, 11.8% Hispanics, 2.4% other, 7.4% type 2 diabetics), a total of 1969 patients were exposed to BELVIQ 10 mg twice daily for 1 year and 426 patients were exposed for 2 years.



 In clinical trials of at least one year in duration, 8.6% of patients treated with BELVIQ prematurely discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions, compared with 6.7% of placebo-treated patients. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation more often among BELVIQ treated patients than placebo were headache (1.3% vs. 0.8%), depression (0.9% vs. 0.5%) and dizziness (0.7% vs. 0.2%).



       Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most common adverse reactions for non-diabetic patients (greater than 5% and more commonly than placebo) treated with BELVIQ compared to placebo were headache, dizziness, fatigue, nausea, dry mouth, and constipation. The most common adverse reactions for diabetic patients were hypoglycemia, headache, back pain, cough, and fatigue. Adverse reactions that were reported by greater than or equal to 2% of patients and were more frequently reported by patients taking BELVIQ compared to placebo are summarized in Table 2 (non-diabetic subjects) and Table 3 (subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus).



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions Reported by Greater Than or Equal to 2% of BELVIQ Patients and More Commonly than with Placebo in Patients without Diabetes Mellitus 
    Adverse Reaction                                              Number of patients (%)     
    BELVIQ    10 mg BID    N=3195                                 Placebo    N=3185     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
       Nausea                                                    264 (8.3)             170 (5.3)            
       Diarrhea                                                  207 (6.5)             179 (5.6)            
       Constipation                                              186 (5.8)             125 (3.9)            
       Dry mouth                                                 169 (5.3)             74 (2.3)             
       Vomiting                                                  122 (3.8)             83 (2.6)             
   General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions                                                     
       Fatigue                                                   229 (7.2)             114 (3.6)            
   Infections And Infestations                                                                              
       Upper respiratory tract infection                         439 (13.7)            391 (12.3)           
       Nasopharyngitis                                           414 (13.0)            381 (12.0)           
       Urinary tract infection                                   207 (6.5)             171 (5.4)            
   Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders                                                          
       Back pain                                                 201 (6.3)             178 (5.6)            
       Musculoskeletal pain                                      65 (2.0)              43 (1.4)             
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
       Headache                                                  537 (16.8)            321 (10.1)           
       Dizziness                                                 270 (8.5)             122 (3.8)            
   Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders                                                          
       Cough                                                     136 (4.3)             109 (3.4)            
       Oropharyngeal pain                                        111 (3.5)             80 (2.5)             
       Sinus congestion                                          93 (2.9)              78 (2.4)             
   Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                   
       Rash                                                      67 (2.1)              58 (1.8)             
        Table 3. Adverse Reactions Reported by Greater Than or Equal to 2% of BELVIQ Patients and More Commonly than with Placebo in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus 
                                                                  Number of patients (%)     
    Adverse Reaction                                              BELVIQ    10 mg BID    N=256       Placebo    N=252     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
       Nausea                                                    24 (9.4)              20 (7.9)             
       Toothache                                                 7 (2.7)               0                    
   General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions                                                     
       Fatigue                                                   19 (7.4)              10 (4.0)             
       Peripheral edema                                          12 (4.7)              6 (2.4)              
   Immune System Disorders                                                                                  
       Seasonal allergy                                          8 (3.1)               2 (0.8)              
   Infections And Infestations                                                                              
       Nasopharyngitis                                           29 (11.3)             25 (9.9)             
       Urinary tract infection                                   23 (9.0)              15 (6.0)             
       Gastroenteritis                                           8 (3.1)               5 (2.0)              
   Metabolism And Nutrition Disorders                                                                       
       Hypoglycemia                                              75 (29.3)             53 (21.0)            
       Worsening of diabetes mellitus                            7 (2.7)               2 (0.8)              
       Decreased appetite                                        6 (2.3)               1 (0.4)              
   Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders                                                          
       Back pain                                                 30 (11.7)             20 (7.9)             
       Muscle spasms                                             12 (4.7)              9 (3.6)              
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
       Headache                                                  37 (14.5)             18 (7.1)             
       Dizziness                                                 18 (7.0)              16 (6.3)             
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
       Anxiety                                                   9 (3.5)               8 (3.2)              
       Insomnia                                                  9 (3.5)               6 (2.4)              
       Stress                                                    7 (2.7)               3 (1.2)              
       Depression                                                6 (2.3)               5 (2.0)              
   Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders                                                          
       Cough                                                     21 (8.2)              11 (4.4)             
   Vascular Disorders                                                                                       
       Hypertension                                              13 (5.1)              8 (3.2)              
               Other Adverse Reactions  
 

   Serotonin-associated Adverse Reactions  



 SSRIs, SNRIs, bupropion, tricyclic antidepressants, and MAOIs were excluded from the BELVIQ trials. Triptans and dextromethorphan were permitted: 2% and 15%, respectively, of patients without diabetes and 1% and 12%, respectively, of patients with type 2 diabetes experienced concomitant use at some point during the trials. Two patients treated with BELVIQ in the clinical program experienced a constellation of symptoms and signs consistent with serotonergic excess, including one patient on concomitant dextromethorphan who reported an event of serotonin syndrome. Some symptoms of possible serotonergic etiology that are included in the criteria for serotonin syndrome were reported by patients treated with BELVIQ and placebo during clinical trials of at least 1 year in duration. In both groups, chills were the most frequent of these events (1.0% vs. 0.2%, respectively), followed by tremor (0.3% vs. 0.2%), confusional state (0.2% vs. less than 0.1%), disorientation (0.1% vs. 0.1%) and hyperhidrosis (0.1% vs. 0.2%). Because serotonin syndrome has a very low incidence, an association between BELVIQ and serotonin syndrome cannot be excluded on the basis of clinical trial results [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ].



   Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes  



 In a clinical trial of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, hypoglycemia requiring the assistance of another person occurred in 4 (1.6%) of BELVIQ-treated patients and in 1 (0.4%) placebo-treated patient. Of these 4 BELVIQ-treated patients, all were concomitantly using a sulfonylurea (with or without metformin). BELVIQ has not been studied in patients taking insulin. Hypoglycemia defined as blood sugar less than or equal to 65 mg/dL and with symptoms occurred in 19 (7.4%) BELVIQ-treated patients and 16 (6.3%) placebo-treated patients.



   Cognitive Impairment  



 In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration, adverse reactions related to cognitive impairment (e.g., difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, and confusion) occurred in 2.3% of patients taking BELVIQ and 0.7% of patients taking placebo.



   Psychiatric Disorders  



 Psychiatric disorders leading to hospitalization or drug withdrawal occurred more frequently in patients treated with BELVIQ (2.2%) as compared to placebo (1.1%) in non-diabetic patients.



   Euphoria.  In short-term studies with healthy individuals, the incidence of euphoric mood following supratherapeutic doses of BELVIQ (40 and 60 mg) was increased as compared to placebo [  see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.2  )  ]. In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration in obese patients, euphoria was observed in 0.17% of patients taking BELVIQ and 0.03% taking placebo.



   Depression and Suicidality.  In trials of at least one year in duration, reports of depression/mood problems occurred in 2.6% BELVIQ-treated vs. 2.4% placebo-treated and suicidal ideation occurred in 0.6% BELVIQ-treated vs. 0.4% placebo-treated patients. 1.3% of BELVIQ patients vs. 0.6% of placebo patients discontinued drug due to depression-, mood-, or suicidal ideation-related events.



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



   Lymphocyte and Neutrophil Counts.  In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration, lymphocyte counts were below the lower limit of normal in 12.2% of patients taking BELVIQ and 9.0% taking placebo, and neutrophil counts were low in 5.6% and 4.3%, respectively.



   Hemoglobin.  In clinical trials of at least 1-year duration, 10.4% of patients taking BELVIQ and 9.3% taking placebo had hemoglobin below the lower limit of normal at some point during the trials.



   Prolactin.  In clinical trials, elevations of prolactin greater than the upper limit of normal, two times the upper limit of normal, and five times the upper limit of normal, occurred in 6.7%, 1.7%, and 0.1% of BELVIQ-treated patients and 4.8%, 0.8%, and 0.0% of placebo-treated patients, respectively.



   Eye disorders  .



 More patients on BELVIQ reported an eye disorder than patients on placebo in clinical trials of patients without diabetes (4.5% vs. 3.0%) and with type 2 diabetes (6.3% vs. 1.6%). In the population without diabetes, events of blurred vision, dry eye, and visual impairment occurred in BELVIQ-treated patients at an incidence greater than that of placebo. In the population with type 2 diabetes, visual disorders, conjunctival infections, irritations, and inflammations, ocular sensation disorders, and cataract conditions occurred in BELVIQ-treated patients at an incidence greater than placebo.



       Echocardiographic Safety Assessments  



 The possible occurrence of regurgitant cardiac valve disease was prospectively evaluated in 7794 patients in three clinical trials of at least one year in duration, 3451 of whom took BELVIQ 10 mg twice daily. The primary echocardiographic safety parameter was the proportion of patients who developed echocardiographic criteria of mild or greater aortic insufficiency and/or moderate or greater mitral insufficiency from baseline to 1 year. At 1 year, 2.4% of patients who received BELVIQ and 2.0% of patients who received placebo developed valvular regurgitation. The relative risk for valvulopathy with BELVIQ is summarized in Table 4. BELVIQ was not studied in patients with congestive heart failure or hemodynamically-significant valvular heart disease [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ].



 Table 4. Incidence of FDA-Defined Valvulopathy at Week 52 by Treatment Group1 
    1  Patients without valvulopathy at baseline who received study medication and had a post-baseline echocardiogram; ITT-intention-to-treat; LOCF-last observation carried forward   
  
                                  Study 1       Study 2       Study 3     
                                  BELVIQ    N=1278       Placebo    N=1191       BELVIQ    N=1208       Placebo    N=1153       BELVIQ    N=210       Placebo    N=209     
    FDA-defined Valvulopathy, n (%)      34 (2.7)      28 (2.4)      24 (2.0)      23 (2.0)      6 (2.9)       1 (0.5)      
    Relative Risk (95% CI)       1.13 (0.69, 1.85)    1.00 (0.57, 1.75)    5.97 (0.73, 49.17)   
    Pooled RR (95% CI)            1.16 (0.81, 1.67)     
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-like Reactions: The safety of coadministration with other serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents has not been established. Manage with immediate BELVIQ discontinuation and provide supportive treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Valvular heart disease: If signs or symptoms develop consider BELVIQ discontinuation and evaluate the patient for possible valvulopathy. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cognitive Impairment: May cause disturbances in attention or memory. Caution with use of hazardous machinery when starting BELVIQ treatment. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Psychiatric Disorders, including euphoria and dissociation: Do not exceed recommended dose of 10 mg twice daily. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Monitor for depression or suicidal thoughts. Discontinue if symptoms develop. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Use of Antidiabetic Medications: weight loss may cause hypoglycemia. Monitor blood glucose. BELVIQ has not been studied in patients taking insulin. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Priapism: Patients should seek emergency treatment if an erection lasts &gt;4 hours. Use BELVIQ with caution in patients predisposed to priapism. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-like Reactions



  BELVIQ is a serotonergic drug. The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-like reactions have been reported during use of serotonergic drugs, including, but not limited to, selective serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs) and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), bupropion, triptans, dietary supplements such as St. John's Wort and tryptophan, drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (including monoamine oxidase inhibitors [MAOIs]), dextromethorphan, lithium, tramadol, antipsychotics or other dopamine antagonists, particularly when used in combination [ see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )  ].



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination) and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Serotonin syndrome, in its most severe form, can resemble neuroleptic malignant syndrome, which includes hyperthermia, muscle rigidity, autonomic instability with possible rapid fluctuation of vital signs, and mental status changes. Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome or NMS-like signs and symptoms.



 The safety of BELVIQ when coadministered with other serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents, including antipsychotics, or drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin, including MAOIs, has not been systematically evaluated and has not been established.



 If concomitant administration of BELVIQ with an agent that affects the serotonergic neurotransmitter system is clinically warranted, extreme caution and careful observation of the patient is advised, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases. Treatment with BELVIQ and any concomitant serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents, including antipsychotics, should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ) and Drug Interactions (  7.1  )  ].



    5.2 Valvular Heart Disease



  Regurgitant cardiac valvular disease, primarily affecting the mitral and/or aortic valves, has been reported in patients who took serotonergic drugs with 5-HT2Breceptor agonist activity. The etiology of the regurgitant valvular disease is thought to be activation of 5-HT2Breceptors on cardiac interstitial cells. At therapeutic concentrations, BELVIQ is selective for 5-HT2Creceptors as compared to 5-HT2Breceptors. In clinical trials of 1-year duration, 2.4% of patients receiving BELVIQ and 2.0% of patients receiving placebo developed echocardiographic criteria for valvular regurgitation at one year (mild or greater aortic regurgitation and/or moderate or greater mitral regurgitation): none of these patients was symptomatic [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ) see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.1  )  ].



 BELVIQ has not been studied in patients with congestive heart failure or hemodynamically-significant valvular heart disease. Preliminary data suggest that 5HT2Breceptors may be overexpressed in congestive heart failure, Therefore, BELVIQ should be used with caution in patients with congestive heart failure.



 BELVIQ should not be used in combination with serotonergic and dopaminergic drugs that are potent 5-HT2Breceptor agonists and are known to increase the risk for cardiac valvulopathy (e.g., cabergoline).



 Patients who develop signs or symptoms of valvular heart disease, including dyspnea, dependent edema, congestive heart failure, or a new cardiac murmur while being treated with BELVIQ should be evaluated and discontinuation of BELVIQ should be considered.



    5.3 Cognitive Impairment



  In clinical trials of at least one year in duration, impairments in attention and memory were reported adverse reactions associated with 1.9% of patients treated with BELVIQ and 0.5% of patients treated with placebo, and led to discontinuation in 0.3% and 0.1% of these patients, respectively. Other reported adverse reactions associated with BELVIQ in clinical trials included confusion, somnolence, and fatigue [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ].



 Since BELVIQ has the potential to impair cognitive function, patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that BELVIQ therapy does not affect them adversely [ see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )  ].



    5.4 Psychiatric Disorders



  Events of euphoria, hallucination, and dissociation were seen with BELVIQ at supratherapeutic doses in short-term studies [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ), Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.2  ), and Overdosage (  10  )  ]. In clinical trials of at least 1-year in duration, 6 patients (0.2%) treated with BELVIQ developed euphoria, as compared with 1 patient (&lt;0.1%) treated with placebo. Doses of BELVIQ should not exceed 10 mg twice a day.



 Some drugs that target the central nervous system have been associated with depression or suicidal ideation. Patients treated with BELVIQ should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior. Discontinue BELVIQ in patients who experience suicidal thoughts or behaviors [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ].



    5.5 Potential Risk of Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus on Anti-diabetic Therapy



  Weight loss may increase the risk of hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated with insulin and/or insulin secretagogues (e.g., sulfonylureas); hypoglycemia was observed in clinical trials with BELVIQ. BELVIQ has not been studied in combination with insulin. Measurement of blood glucose levels prior to starting BELVIQ and during BELVIQ treatment is recommended in patients with type 2 diabetes. Decreases in medication doses for anti-diabetic medications which are non-glucose-dependent should be considered to mitigate the risk of hypoglycemia. If a patient develops hypoglycemia after starting BELVIQ, appropriate changes should be made to the anti-diabetic drug regimen [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ].



    5.6 Priapism



  Priapism (painful erections greater than 6 hours in duration) is a potential effect of 5-HT2Creceptor agonism.



 If not treated promptly, priapism can result in irreversible damage to the erectile tissue. Men who have an erection lasting greater than 4 hours, whether painful or not, should immediately discontinue the drug and seek emergency medical attention.



 BELVIQ should be used with caution in men who have conditions that might predispose them to priapism (e.g., sickle cell anemia, multiple myeloma, or leukemia), or in men with anatomical deformation of the penis (e.g., angulation, cavernosal fibrosis, or Peyronie's disease). There is limited experience with the combination of BELVIQ and medication indicated for erectile dysfunction (e.g., phosphodiesterase type 5 inhibitors). Therefore, the combination of BELVIQ and these medications should be used with caution.



    5.7 Heart Rate Decreases



  In clinical trials of at least 1-year in duration, the mean change in heart rate (HR) was -1.2 beats per minute (bpm) in BELVIQ and -0.4 bpm in placebo-treated patients without diabetes and -2.0 beats per minute (bpm) in BELVIQ and -0.4 bpm in placebo-treated patients with type 2 diabetes. The incidence of HR less than 50 bpm was 5.3% in BELVIQ and 3.2% in placebo-treated patients without diabetes and 3.6% in BELVIQ and 2.0% in placebo-treated patients with type 2 diabetes. In the combined population, adverse reactions of bradycardia occurred in 0.3% of BELVIQ and 0.1% of placebo-treated patients. Use with caution in patients with bradycardia or a history of heart block greater than first degree.



    5.8 Hematological Changes



  In clinical trials of at least one year in duration, adverse reactions of decreases in white blood cell count (including leukopenia, lymphopenia, neutropenia, and decreased white cell count) were reported in 0.4% of patients treated with BELVIQ as compared to 0.2% of patients treated with placebo. Adverse reactions of decreases in red blood cell count (including anemia and decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit) were reported by 1.3% of patients treated with BELVIQ as compared to 1.2% treated with placebo [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. Consider periodic monitoring of complete blood count during treatment with BELVIQ.



    5.9 Prolactin Elevation



  Lorcaserin moderately elevates prolactin levels. In a subset of placebo-controlled clinical trials of at least one year in duration, elevations of prolactin greater than the upper limit of normal, two times the upper limit of normal, and five times the upper limit of normal, measured both before and 2 hours after dosing, occurred in 6.7%, 1.7%, and 0.1% of BELVIQ-treated patients and 4.8%, 0.8%, and 0.0% of placebo-treated patients, respectively [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. Prolactin should be measured when symptoms and signs of prolactin excess are suspected (e.g., galactorrhea, gynecomastia). There was one patient treated with BELVIQ who developed a prolactinoma during the trial. The relationship of BELVIQ to the prolactinoma in this patient is unknown.



    5.10 Pulmonary Hypertension



  Certain centrally-acting weight loss agents that act on the serotonin system have been associated with pulmonary hypertension, a rare but lethal disease. Because of the low incidence of this disease, the clinical trial experience with BELVIQ is inadequate to determine if BELVIQ increases the risk for pulmonary hypertension.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S4">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-like Reactions: The safety of coadministration with other serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents has not been established. Manage with immediate BELVIQ discontinuation and provide supportive treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Valvular heart disease: If signs or symptoms develop consider BELVIQ discontinuation and evaluate the patient for possible valvulopathy. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cognitive Impairment: May cause disturbances in attention or memory. Caution with use of hazardous machinery when starting BELVIQ treatment. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Psychiatric Disorders, including euphoria and dissociation: Do not exceed recommended dose of 10 mg twice daily. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Monitor for depression or suicidal thoughts. Discontinue if symptoms develop. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Use of Antidiabetic Medications: weight loss may cause hypoglycemia. Monitor blood glucose. BELVIQ has not been studied in patients taking insulin. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Priapism: Patients should seek emergency treatment if an erection lasts &gt;4 hours. Use BELVIQ with caution in patients predisposed to priapism. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-like Reactions



  BELVIQ is a serotonergic drug. The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-like reactions have been reported during use of serotonergic drugs, including, but not limited to, selective serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs) and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), bupropion, triptans, dietary supplements such as St. John's Wort and tryptophan, drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (including monoamine oxidase inhibitors [MAOIs]), dextromethorphan, lithium, tramadol, antipsychotics or other dopamine antagonists, particularly when used in combination [ see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )  ].



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination) and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Serotonin syndrome, in its most severe form, can resemble neuroleptic malignant syndrome, which includes hyperthermia, muscle rigidity, autonomic instability with possible rapid fluctuation of vital signs, and mental status changes. Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome or NMS-like signs and symptoms.



 The safety of BELVIQ when coadministered with other serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents, including antipsychotics, or drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin, including MAOIs, has not been systematically evaluated and has not been established.



 If concomitant administration of BELVIQ with an agent that affects the serotonergic neurotransmitter system is clinically warranted, extreme caution and careful observation of the patient is advised, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases. Treatment with BELVIQ and any concomitant serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents, including antipsychotics, should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ) and Drug Interactions (  7.1  )  ].



    5.2 Valvular Heart Disease



  Regurgitant cardiac valvular disease, primarily affecting the mitral and/or aortic valves, has been reported in patients who took serotonergic drugs with 5-HT2Breceptor agonist activity. The etiology of the regurgitant valvular disease is thought to be activation of 5-HT2Breceptors on cardiac interstitial cells. At therapeutic concentrations, BELVIQ is selective for 5-HT2Creceptors as compared to 5-HT2Breceptors. In clinical trials of 1-year duration, 2.4% of patients receiving BELVIQ and 2.0% of patients receiving placebo developed echocardiographic criteria for valvular regurgitation at one year (mild or greater aortic regurgitation and/or moderate or greater mitral regurgitation): none of these patients was symptomatic [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ) see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.1  )  ].



 BELVIQ has not been studied in patients with congestive heart failure or hemodynamically-significant valvular heart disease. Preliminary data suggest that 5HT2Breceptors may be overexpressed in congestive heart failure, Therefore, BELVIQ should be used with caution in patients with congestive heart failure.



 BELVIQ should not be used in combination with serotonergic and dopaminergic drugs that are potent 5-HT2Breceptor agonists and are known to increase the risk for cardiac valvulopathy (e.g., cabergoline).



 Patients who develop signs or symptoms of valvular heart disease, including dyspnea, dependent edema, congestive heart failure, or a new cardiac murmur while being treated with BELVIQ should be evaluated and discontinuation of BELVIQ should be considered.



    5.3 Cognitive Impairment



  In clinical trials of at least one year in duration, impairments in attention and memory were reported adverse reactions associated with 1.9% of patients treated with BELVIQ and 0.5% of patients treated with placebo, and led to discontinuation in 0.3% and 0.1% of these patients, respectively. Other reported adverse reactions associated with BELVIQ in clinical trials included confusion, somnolence, and fatigue [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ].



 Since BELVIQ has the potential to impair cognitive function, patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that BELVIQ therapy does not affect them adversely [ see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )  ].



    5.4 Psychiatric Disorders



  Events of euphoria, hallucination, and dissociation were seen with BELVIQ at supratherapeutic doses in short-term studies [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ), Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.2  ), and Overdosage (  10  )  ]. In clinical trials of at least 1-year in duration, 6 patients (0.2%) treated with BELVIQ developed euphoria, as compared with 1 patient (&lt;0.1%) treated with placebo. Doses of BELVIQ should not exceed 10 mg twice a day.



 Some drugs that target the central nervous system have been associated with depression or suicidal ideation. Patients treated with BELVIQ should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior. Discontinue BELVIQ in patients who experience suicidal thoughts or behaviors [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ].



    5.5 Potential Risk of Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus on Anti-diabetic Therapy



  Weight loss may increase the risk of hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated with insulin and/or insulin secretagogues (e.g., sulfonylureas); hypoglycemia was observed in clinical trials with BELVIQ. BELVIQ has not been studied in combination with insulin. Measurement of blood glucose levels prior to starting BELVIQ and during BELVIQ treatment is recommended in patients with type 2 diabetes. Decreases in medication doses for anti-diabetic medications which are non-glucose-dependent should be considered to mitigate the risk of hypoglycemia. If a patient develops hypoglycemia after starting BELVIQ, appropriate changes should be made to the anti-diabetic drug regimen [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ].



    5.6 Priapism



  Priapism (painful erections greater than 6 hours in duration) is a potential effect of 5-HT2Creceptor agonism.



 If not treated promptly, priapism can result in irreversible damage to the erectile tissue. Men who have an erection lasting greater than 4 hours, whether painful or not, should immediately discontinue the drug and seek emergency medical attention.



 BELVIQ should be used with caution in men who have conditions that might predispose them to priapism (e.g., sickle cell anemia, multiple myeloma, or leukemia), or in men with anatomical deformation of the penis (e.g., angulation, cavernosal fibrosis, or Peyronie's disease). There is limited experience with the combination of BELVIQ and medication indicated for erectile dysfunction (e.g., phosphodiesterase type 5 inhibitors). Therefore, the combination of BELVIQ and these medications should be used with caution.



    5.7 Heart Rate Decreases



  In clinical trials of at least 1-year in duration, the mean change in heart rate (HR) was -1.2 beats per minute (bpm) in BELVIQ and -0.4 bpm in placebo-treated patients without diabetes and -2.0 beats per minute (bpm) in BELVIQ and -0.4 bpm in placebo-treated patients with type 2 diabetes. The incidence of HR less than 50 bpm was 5.3% in BELVIQ and 3.2% in placebo-treated patients without diabetes and 3.6% in BELVIQ and 2.0% in placebo-treated patients with type 2 diabetes. In the combined population, adverse reactions of bradycardia occurred in 0.3% of BELVIQ and 0.1% of placebo-treated patients. Use with caution in patients with bradycardia or a history of heart block greater than first degree.



    5.8 Hematological Changes



  In clinical trials of at least one year in duration, adverse reactions of decreases in white blood cell count (including leukopenia, lymphopenia, neutropenia, and decreased white cell count) were reported in 0.4% of patients treated with BELVIQ as compared to 0.2% of patients treated with placebo. Adverse reactions of decreases in red blood cell count (including anemia and decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit) were reported by 1.3% of patients treated with BELVIQ as compared to 1.2% treated with placebo [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. Consider periodic monitoring of complete blood count during treatment with BELVIQ.



    5.9 Prolactin Elevation



  Lorcaserin moderately elevates prolactin levels. In a subset of placebo-controlled clinical trials of at least one year in duration, elevations of prolactin greater than the upper limit of normal, two times the upper limit of normal, and five times the upper limit of normal, measured both before and 2 hours after dosing, occurred in 6.7%, 1.7%, and 0.1% of BELVIQ-treated patients and 4.8%, 0.8%, and 0.0% of placebo-treated patients, respectively [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. Prolactin should be measured when symptoms and signs of prolactin excess are suspected (e.g., galactorrhea, gynecomastia). There was one patient treated with BELVIQ who developed a prolactinoma during the trial. The relationship of BELVIQ to the prolactinoma in this patient is unknown.



    5.10 Pulmonary Hypertension



  Certain centrally-acting weight loss agents that act on the serotonin system have been associated with pulmonary hypertension, a rare but lethal disease. Because of the low incidence of this disease, the clinical trial experience with BELVIQ is inadequate to determine if BELVIQ increases the risk for pulmonary hypertension.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
