<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bendeka" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions have been associated with bendamustine hydrochloride in clinical trials and are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the prescribing information.



 *  Myelosuppression [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Infections [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Anaphylaxis and Infusion Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Tumor Lysis Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Skin Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Other Malignancies [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Extravasation injury [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
    The data described below reflect exposure to bendamustine hydrochloride in 329 patients who participated in an actively controlled trial (N=153) for the treatment of CLL and two single arm studies (N=176) for the treatment of indolent B cell NHL. Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

    EXCERPT:    *  Adverse reactions (frequency &gt;5%) during infusion and within 24 hours post-infusion are nausea and fatigue (  6.1  ) 
 *  Most common non-hematologic adverse reactions for CLL (frequency &gt;=15%) are pyrexia, nausea, and vomiting. (  6.2  ) 
 *  Most common non-hematologic adverse reactions for NHL (frequency &gt;=15%) are nausea, fatigue, vomiting, diarrhea, pyrexia, constipation, anorexia, cough, headache, weight decreased, dyspnea, rash, and stomatitis. (  6.3  ) 
 *  Most common hematologic abnormalities (frequency &gt;=15%) are lymphopenia, anemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, and neutropenia. (  6.2  ,  6.3  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eagle Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-855-318-2170 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Adverse Events in Clinical Trials

  The safety of BENDEKA (bendamustine hydrochloride) Injection administered IV as a 50 mL admixture over a 10-minute infusion is supported by clinical trials using bendamustine hydrochloride administered IV as a 500 mL admixture over 30-60 minutes infusion time, as well as an open-label, crossover study in 81 'end-of-life' cancer patients treated with BENDEKA. In total, safety data from clinical studies are available from over 400 cancer patients exposed to bendamustine hydrochloride at doses in the range used in the treatment of CLL and NHL.



 No clinically significant differences in the adverse event profile were noted among bendamustine hydrochloride administered as a 500 mL admixture over standard infusion time (30-60 minutes) and BENDEKA administered as a 50 mL admixture in a 'short-time' infusion over 10 minutes.



 The safety and tolerability of BENDEKA was evaluated in an 8-week clinical study of BENDEKA in 81 'end-of-life' cancer patients, diagnosed with solid tumors and hematologic malignancies (excluding CLL). The population was 40-82 years of age, 58% females, 84% white, 12.3% Black, 1.2% Asian and 2.5% were classified as 'other'. BENDEKA was administered IV at a 120 mg/m  2  dose as a 50 mL admixture over 10 minutes. Patients in the study received BENDEKA(50 mL IV, over 10 minutes) or bendamustine hydrochloride (500 mL IV, over 60 minutes) on Days 1 and 2 every 28 days for two consecutive 2-day cycles.



 Adverse reactions (any grade) that occurred with a frequency greater than 5% during BENDEKA infusion and within one hour post-infusion were nausea (8.2%) and fatigue (5.5%).



 Adverse reactions (any grade) that occurred with a frequency greater than 5% within 24 hours of BENDEKA were nausea (10.9%) and fatigue (8.2%).



 The adverse reactions leading to study withdrawal in 4 patients receiving BENDEKA were pyrexia (1.2%), nausea (1.2%), vomiting (1.2%), pneumonia (1.2%) and fatigue (1.2%).



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience in CLL

  The data described below reflect exposure to bendamustine hydrochloride in 153 patients.  Bendamustine hydrochloride was studied in an active-controlled trial.  The population was 45-77 years of age, 63% male, 100% white, and had treatment naive CLL. All patients started the study at a dose of 100 mg/m  2  intravenously over 30 minutes on Days 1 and 2 every 28 days.



 Adverse reactions were reported according to NCI CTC v.2.0.  In the randomized CLL clinical study, non-hematologic adverse reactions (any grade) in the bendamustine hydrochloride group that occurred with a frequency greater than 15% were pyrexia (24%), nausea (20%), and vomiting (16%).



 Other adverse reactions seen frequently in one or more studies included asthenia, fatigue, malaise, and weakness; dry mouth; somnolence; cough; constipation; headache; mucosal inflammation and stomatitis.



 Worsening hypertension was reported in 4 patients treated with bendamustine hydrochloride in the randomized CLL clinical study and none treated with chlorambucil.  Three of these 4 adverse reactions were described as a hypertensive crisis and were managed with oral medications and resolved.



 The most frequent adverse reactions leading to study withdrawal for patients receiving bendamustine hydrochloride were hypersensitivity (2%) and pyrexia (1%).



   Table 1  contains the treatment emergent adverse reactions, regardless of attribution, that were reported in &gt;= 5% of patients in either treatment group in the randomized CLL clinical study.



 Table 1: Non-Hematologic Adverse Reactions Occurring in Randomized CLL Clinical Study in at Least 5% of Patients 
                                Number (%) of patients     
   Bendamustine Hydrochloride(N=153)      Chlorambucil(N=143)     
  
   System organ class    Preferred term      All Grades         Grade 3/4            All Grades          Grade 3/4         
   Total number of patients with at least 1 adverse reaction      121 (79)           52 (34)              96 (67)             25 (17)           
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                    
 Nausea                       31 (20)            1 (&lt;1)               21 (15)             1 (&lt;1)              
 Vomiting                     24 (16)            1 (&lt;1)               9 (6)               0                   
 Diarrhea                     14 (9)             2 (1)                5 (3)               0                   
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                                    
 Pyrexia                      36 (24)            6 (4)                8 (6)               2 (1)               
 Fatigue                      14 (9)             2 (1)                8 (6)               0                   
 Asthenia                     13 (8)             0                    6 (4)               0                   
 Chills                       9 (6)              0                    1 (&lt;1)              0                   
   Immune system disorders                                                                                    
 Hypersensitivity             7 (5)              2 (1)                3 (2)               0                   
   Infections and infestations                                                                                    
 Nasopharyngitis              10 (7)             0                    12 (8)              0                   
 Infection                    9 (6)              3 (2)                1 (&lt;1)              1 (&lt;1)              
 Herpes simplex               5 (3)              0                    7 (5)               0                   
   Investigations                                                                                             
 Weight decreased             11 (7)             0                    5 (3)               0                   
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                                    
 Hyperuricemia                11 (7)             3 (2)                2 (1)               0                   
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                                    
 Cough                        6 (4)              1 (&lt;1)               7 (5)               1 (&lt;1)              
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                                    
 Rash                         12 (8)             4 (3)                7 (5)               3 (2)               
 Pruritus                     8 (5)              0                    2 (1)               0                   
           The Grade 3 and 4 hematology laboratory test values by treatment group in the randomized CLL clinical study are described in  Table 2  . These findings confirm the myelosuppressive effects seen in patients treated with bendamustine hydrochloride. Red blood cell transfusions were administered to 20% of patients receiving bendamustine hydrochloride compared with 6% of patients receiving chlorambucil.
 

 Table 2: Incidence of Hematology Laboratory Abnormalities in Patients Who Received bendamustine hydrochloride or Chlorambucil in the Randomized CLL Clinical Study 
   Laboratory Abnormality      Bendamustine Hydrochloride    N=150      ChlorambucilN=141     
   All Grades    n (%)      Grade 3/4    n (%)      All Grades    n (%)      Grade 3/4    n (%)     
  
 HemoglobinDecreased   134 (89)              20 (13)               115 (82)              12 (9)                 
 PlateletsDecreased    116 (77)              16 (11)               110 (78)              14 (10)                
 LeukocytesDecreased   92 (61)               42 (28)               26 (18)               4 (3)                  
 LymphocytesDecreased  102 (68)              70 (47)               27 (19)               6 (4)                  
 NeutrophilsDecreased  113 (75)              65 (43)               86 (61)               30 (21)                
           In the randomized CLL trial, 34% of patients had bilirubin elevations, some without associated significant elevations in AST and ALT.  Grade 3 or 4 increased bilirubin occurred in 3% of patients.  Increases in AST and ALT of Grade 3 or 4 were limited to 1% and 3% of patients, respectively.  Patients treated with bendamustine hydrochloride may also have changes in their creatinine levels. If abnormalities are detected, monitoring of these parameters should be continued to ensure that significant deterioration does not occur.
 

   6.3 Clinical Trials Experience in NHL

  The data described below reflect exposure to bendamustine hydrochloride in 176 patients with indolent B-cell NHL treated in two single-arm studies.  The population was 31-84 years of age, 60% male, and 40% female.  The race distribution was 89% White, 7% Black, 3% Hispanic, 1% other, and &lt;1% Asian. These patients received bendamustine hydrochloride at a dose of 120 mg/m  2  intravenously on Days 1 and 2 for up to eight 21-day cycles.



 The adverse reactions occurring in at least 5% of the NHL patients, regardless of severity, are shown in  Table 3  . The most common non-hematologic adverse reactions (&gt;=30%) were nausea (75%), fatigue (57%), vomiting (40%), diarrhea (37%) and pyrexia (34%).  The most common non-hematologic Grade 3 or 4 adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) were fatigue (11%), febrile neutropenia (6%), and pneumonia, hypokalemia and dehydration, each reported in 5% of patients.



 Table 3: Non-Hematologic Adverse Reactions Occurring in at Least 5% of NHL Patients Treated with bendamustine hydrochloride by System Organ Class and Preferred Term (N=176) 
   System organ class                                        Number (%) of patients*     
   Preferred Term                                            All Grades              Grade 3/4            
  
  *Patients may have reported more than 1 adverse reaction.    
  
   Total number of patients with at    least 1 adverse reaction    176 (100)               94 (53)                
   Cardiac Disorders                                        
 Tachycardia                                               13 (7)                  0                      
   Gastrointestinal disorders                               
 Nausea                                                    132 (75)                7 (4)                  
 Vomiting                                                  71 (40)                 5 (3)                  
 Diarrhea                                                  65 (37)                 6 (3)                  
 Constipation                                              51 (29)                 1 (&lt;1)                 
 Stomatitis                                                27 (15)                 1 (&lt;1)                 
 Abdominal pain                                            22 (13)                 2 (1)                  
 Dyspepsia                                                 20 (11)                 0                      
 Gastroesophageal reflux disease                           18 (10)                 0                      
 Dry mouth                                                 15 (9)                  1 (&lt;1)                 
 Abdominal pain upper                                      8 (5)                   0                      
 Abdominal distension                                      8 (5)                   0                      
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
 Fatigue                                                   101 (57)                19 (11)                
 Pyrexia                                                   59 (34)                 3 (2)                  
 Chills                                                    24 (14)                 0                      
 Edema peripheral                                          23 (13)                 1 (&lt;1)                 
 Asthenia                                                  19 (11)                 4 (2)                  
 Chest pain                                                11 (6)                  1 (&lt;1)                 
 Infusion site pain                                        11 (6)                  0                      
 Pain                                                      10 (6)                  0                      
 Catheter site pain                                        8 (5)                   0                      
   Infections and infestations                                                      
 Herpes zoster                                             18 (10)                 5 (3)                  
 Upper respiratory tract infection                         18 (10)                 0                      
 Urinary tract infection                                   17 (10)                 4 (2)                  
 Sinusitis                                                 15 (9)                  0                      
 Pneumonia                                                 14 (8)                  9 (5)                  
 Febrile neutropenia                                       11 (6)                  11 (6)                 
 Oral candidiasis                                          11 (6)                  2 (1)                  
 Nasopharyngitis                                           11 (6)                  0                      
   Investigations                                                                   
 Weight decreased                                          31 (18)                 3 (2)                  
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                               
 Anorexia                                                  40 (23)                 3 (2)                  
 Dehydration                                               24 (14)                 8 (5)                  
 Decreased appetite                                        22 (13)                 1 (&lt;1)                 
 Hypokalemia                                               15 (9)                  9 (5)                  
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                  
 Back pain                                                 25 (14)                 5 (3)                  
 Arthralgia                                                11 (6)                  0                      
 Pain in extremity                                         8 (5)                   2 (1)                  
 Bone pain                                                 8 (5)                   0                      
   Nervous system disorders                                                         
 Headache                                                  36 (21)                 0                      
 Dizziness                                                 25 (14)                 0                      
 Dysgeusia                                                 13 (7)                  0                      
   Psychiatric disorder                                                             
 Insomnia                                                  23 (13)                 0                      
 Anxiety                                                   14 (8)                  1 (&lt;1)                 
 Depression                                                10 (6)                  0                      
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                  
 Cough                                                     38 (22)                 1 (&lt;1)                 
 Dyspnea                                                   28 (16)                 3 (2)                  
 Pharyngolaryngeal pain                                    14 (8)                  1 (&lt;1)                 
 Wheezing                                                  8 (5)                   0                      
 Nasal congestion                                          8 (5)                   0                      
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                           
 Rash                                                      28 (16)                 1 (&lt;1)                 
 Pruritus                                                  11 (6)                  0                      
 Dry skin                                                  9 (5)                   0                      
 Night sweats                                              9 (5)                   0                      
 Hyperhidrosis                                             8 (5)                   0                      
   Vascular disorders                                                               
 Hypotension                                               10 (6)                  2 (1)                  
           NOTE:  Patients counted only once in each preferred term category and once in each system organ class category.
 

 Hematologic toxicities, based on laboratory values and CTC grade, in NHL patients treated in both single arm studies combined are described in  Table 4  .  Clinically important chemistry laboratory values that were new or worsened from baseline and occurred in &gt;1% of patients at grade 3 or 4,  in NHL patients treated in both single arm studies combined were hyperglycemia (3%), elevated creatinine (2%), hyponatremia (2%), and hypocalcemia (2%).



 Table 4: Incidence of Hematology Laboratory Abnormalities in Patients Who Received bendamustine hydrochloride in the NHL Studies 
   Hematology Variable               Percent of Patients               
   All Grades                        Grade 3/4                         
  
 Lymphocytes Decreased             99                                 94                                  
 Leukocytes Decreased              94                                 56                                  
 Hemoglobin Decreased              88                                 11                                  
 Neutrophils Decreased             86                                 60                                  
 Platelets Decreased               86                                 25                                  
         In both studies, serious adverse reactions, regardless of causality, were reported in 37% of patients receiving bendamustine hydrochloride.  The most common serious adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of patients were febrile neutropenia and pneumonia.  Other important serious adverse reactions reported in clinical trials and/or post-marketing experience were acute renal failure, cardiac failure, hypersensitivity, skin reactions, pulmonary fibrosis, and myelodysplastic syndrome.
 

 Serious drug-related adverse reactions reported in clinical trials included myelosuppression, infection, pneumonia, tumor lysis syndrome and infusion reactions  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5  )]  . Adverse reactions occurring less frequently but possibly related to bendamustine hydrochloride treatment were hemolysis, dysgeusia/taste disorder, atypical pneumonia, sepsis, herpes zoster, erythema, dermatitis, and skin necrosis.



   6.4 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of bendamustine hydrochloride.  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: anaphylaxis; and injection or infusion site reactions including phlebitis, pruritus, irritation, pain, and swelling; pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia and pneumonitis.



 Skin reactions including SJS and TEN have occurred when bendamustine hydrochloride was administered concomitantly with allopurinol and other medications known to cause these syndromes.    [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Myelosuppression:  Delay or reduce dose. Restart treatment based on ANC and platelet count recovery. (  2.1  ) Complications of myelosuppression may lead to death. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Infections:  Monitor for fever and other signs of infection and treat promptly. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Anaphylaxis and Infusion Reactions: Severe anaphylactic reactions have occurred. Monitor clinically and discontinue drug for severe reactions. Pre-medicate in subsequent cycles for milder reactions. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Tumor Lysis Syndrome:  May lead to acute renal failure and death; anticipate and use supportive measures in patients at high risk. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Skin Reactions:  Discontinue for severe skin reactions. Cases of SJS and TEN, some fatal, have been reported when bendamustine hydrochloride was administered concomitantly with allopurinol and other medications known to cause these syndromes. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Other Malignancies: Pre-malignant and malignant diseases have been reported. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Extravasation: Take precautions to avoid extravasation, including monitoring intravenous infusion site during and after administration. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Embryo-fetal toxicity:  Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant when receiving bendamustine hydrochloride. (  5.8  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myelosuppression



  Bendamustine hydrochloride caused severe myelosuppression (Grade 3-4) in 98% of patients in the two NHL studies ( see    Table 4  ). Three patients (2%) died from myelosuppression-related adverse reactions; one each from neutropenic sepsis, diffuse alveolar hemorrhage with Grade 3 thrombocytopenia, and pneumonia from an opportunistic infection (CMV).



 BENDEKA (bendamustine hydrochloride) Injection causes myelosuppression. Monitor complete blood counts, including leukocytes, platelets, hemoglobin (Hgb), and neutrophils frequently. In the clinical trials, blood counts were monitored every week initially.  Hematologic nadirs occurred predominantly in the third week of therapy. Myelosuppression may require dose delays and/or subsequent dose reductions if recovery to the recommended values has not occurred by the first day of the next scheduled cycle.  Prior to the initiation of the next cycle of therapy, the ANC should be &gt;= 1 x 10  9  /L and the platelet count should be &gt;= 75 x 10  9  /L. [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )]  



    5.2 Infections



  Infection, including pneumonia, sepsis, septic shock, and death have occurred in adult and pediatric patients in clinical trials and in postmarketing reports for bendamustine hydrochloride. Patients with myelosuppression following treatment with bendamustine hydrochloride are more susceptible to infections. Advise patients with myelosuppression following BENDEKA (bendamustine hydrochloride) Injection treatment to contact a physician immediately if they have symptoms or signs of infection.



    5.3 Anaphylaxis and Infusion Reactions



  Infusion reactions to bendamustine hydrochloride have occurred commonly in clinical trials. Symptoms include fever, chills, pruritus and rash. In rare instances severe anaphylactic and anaphylactoid reactions have occurred, particularly in the second and subsequent cycles of therapy.  Monitor clinically and discontinue drug for severe reactions. Ask patients about symptoms suggestive of infusion reactions after their first cycle of therapy. Patients who experienced Grade 3 or worse allergic-type reactions were not typically rechallenged.  Consider measures to prevent severe reactions, including antihistamines, antipyretics and corticosteroids in subsequent cycles in patients who have experienced Grade 1 or 2 infusion reactions. Discontinue BENDEKA (bendamustine hydrochloride) Injection for patients with Grade 4 infusion reactions. Consider discontinuation for Grade 3 infusion reactions as clinically appropriate considering individual benefits, risks, and supportive care.



    5.4 Tumor Lysis Syndrome



  Tumor lysis syndrome associated with bendamustine hydrochloride has occurred in patients in clinical trials and in post-marketing reports. The onset tends to be within the first treatment cycle of bendamustine hydrochloride and may lead to acute renal failure and death. Preventive measures include vigorous hydration and close monitoring of blood chemistry, particularly potassium and uric acid levels.  Allopurinol has also been used during the beginning of bendamustine hydrochloride therapy. However, there may be an increased risk of severe skin toxicity when bendamustine hydrochloride and allopurinol are administered concomitantly [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  .



    5.5 Skin Reactions



  Skin reactions have been reported with bendamustine hydrochloride treatment in clinical trials and postmarketing safety reports, including rash, toxic skin reactions and bullous exanthema.



 Some events occurred when bendamustine hydrochloride was given in combination with other anticancer agents.



 In a study of bendamustine hydrochloride (90 mg/m  2  ) in combination with rituximab, one case of toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) occurred. TEN has been reported for rituximab ( see  rituximab package insert).  Cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and TEN, some fatal, have been reported when bendamustine hydrochloride was administered concomitantly with allopurinol and other medications known to cause these syndromes. The relationship to bendamustine hydrochloride cannot be determined.



 Where skin reactions occur, they may be progressive and increase in severity with further treatment. Monitor patients with skin reactions closely. If skin reactions are severe or progressive, withhold or discontinue BENDEKA (bendamustine hydrochloride) Injection.



    5.6 Other Malignancies



  There are reports of pre-malignant and malignant diseases that have developed in patients who have been treated with bendamustine hydrochloride, including myelodysplastic syndrome, myeloproliferative disorders, acute myeloid leukemia and bronchial carcinoma.  The association with BENDKA (bendamustine hydrochloride) Injection therapy has not been determined.



    5.7 Extravasation



  Bendamustine hydrochloride extravasations have been reported in post marketing resulting in hospitalizations from erythema, marked swelling, and pain. Assure good venous access prior to starting drug infusion and monitor the intravenous infusion site for redness, swelling, pain, infection, and necrosis during and after administration of BENDEKA (bendamustine hydrochloride) Injection.



    5.8 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  Bendamustine hydrochloride can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.  Single intraperitoneal doses of bendamustine in mice and rats administered during organogenesis caused an increase in resorptions, skeletal and visceral malformations, and decreased fetal body weights. [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
