<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="benefix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reactions are systemic hypersensitivity reactions, including bronchospastic reactions and/or hypotension and anaphylaxis and the development of high-titer inhibitors necessitating alternative treatments to factor IX replacement therapy.



 The most common adverse reactions observed in clinical trials (frequency &gt; 5% of PTPs or PUPs) were headaches, dizziness, nausea, injections site reaction, injection site pain and skin-related hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., rash, hives).



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;5%) from clinical trials were nausea, injection site reaction, injection site pain, headache, dizziness and rash. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-934-5556 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 During uncontrolled, open-label clinical studies with BeneFIX conducted in previously treated patients (PTPs), 113 adverse reactions with known or unknown relation to BeneFIX therapy were reported among 38.5% (25 of 65) of subjects (with some subjects reporting more than one event) who received a total of 7,573 infusions. These adverse reactions are summarized in Table 2.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported for PTPsAdverse reactions reported within 72 hours of an infusion of BeneFIX. 
 Body System                           Adverse Reaction                       Number of patients (%)        
  
 Blood and lymphatic system disorders  Factor IX inhibition                          1 (1.5%)               
 Eye disorders                         Blurred vision                                1 (1.5%)               
 Gastrointestinal disorders            Nausea                                        4 (6.2%)               
 Vomiting                              1 (1.5%)                           
 General disorders and administration site conditions  Injection site reaction                       5 (7.7%)               
 Injection site pain                   4 (6.2%)                           
 Fever                                 2 (3.1%)                           
 Infections and infestations           Cellulitis at IV site                         1 (1.5%)               
 Phlebitis at IV site                  1 (1.5%)                           
 Nervous system disorders              Headache                                     7 (10.8%)               
 Dizziness                             5 (7.7%)                           
 Taste perversion (altered taste)      3 (4.6%)                           
 Shaking                               1 (1.5%)                           
 Drowsiness                            1 (1.5%)                           
 Renal and urinary disorders           Renal infarct                                 1 (1.5%)               
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  Dry cough                                     1 (1.5%)               
 Hypoxia                               1 (1.5%)                           
 Chest tightness                       1 (1.5%)                           
 Skin and subcutaneous disorders       Rash                                          4 (6.2%)               
 Hives                                 2 (3.1%)                           
 Vascular disorders                    Flushing                                      2 (3.1%)               
         In the 63 previously untreated patients (PUPs), who received a total of 5,538 infusions, 10 adverse reactions were reported among 9.5% of the patients (6 out of 63) having known or unknown relationship to BeneFIX. These events are summarized in Table 3.
 

 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Reported for PUPsAdverse reactions reported within 72 hours of an infusion of BeneFIX. 
 Body System                               Adverse Reaction                      Number of Patients (%)     
  
 Blood and lymphatic system disorders      Factor IX inhibition                         2 (3.2%)            
 General disorders and administration site conditions  Injection site reaction                      1 (1.6%)            
 Chills                                    1 (1.6%)                              
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  Dyspnea (respiratory distress)               2 (3.2%)            
 Skin and subcutaneous disorders           Hives                                        3 (4.8%)            
 Rash                                      1 (1.6%)                              
             Immunogenicity  
 

 In clinical studies with 65 PTPs (defined as having more than 50 exposure days), a low-titer inhibitor was observed in one patient. The inhibitor was transient, the patient continued on study and had normal factor IX recovery pharmacokinetics at study completion (approximately 15 months after inhibitor detection).



 In clinical studies with pediatric PUPs, inhibitor development was observed in 2 out of 63 patients (3.2%), both were high-titer (&gt; 5 BU) inhibitors detected after 7 and 15 exposure days, respectively. Both patients were withdrawn from the study.



 The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors, including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to BeneFIX with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.



     Thromboembolic complications  



 All subjects participating in the PTP, PUP and surgery studies were monitored for clinical evidence of thrombosis. No thrombotic complications were reported in PUPs or surgery subjects. One PTP subject experienced a renal infarct (see  Table 2  ). Laboratory studies of thrombogenecity (fibrinopeptide A and prothrombin fragment 1 + 2) were obtained in 41 PTPs and 7 surgery subjects prior to infusion and up to 24 hours following infusion. The results of these studies were inconclusive. Out of 29 PTP subjects noted to have elevated fibrinopeptide A levels post-infusion of BeneFIX, 22 also had elevated levels at baseline. Surgery subjects showed no evidence of significant increase in coagulation activation.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following post-marketing adverse reactions have been reported for BeneFIX: inadequate factor IX recovery, inadequate therapeutic response, inhibitor development  [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12)  ]  , anaphylaxis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  , angioedema, dyspnea, hypotension, and thrombosis.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 There have been post-marketing reports of thrombotic events, including life-threatening SVC syndrome in critically ill neonates, while receiving continuous-infusion BeneFIX through a central venous catheter. Cases of peripheral thrombophlebitis and DVT have also been reported. In some, BeneFIX was administered via continuous infusion, which is not an approved method of administration  [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  . The safety and efficacy of BeneFIX administration by continuous infusion have not been established  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, are possible. Should symptoms occur, discontinue treatment with the product and seek emergency treatment. Patients may develop hypersensitivity to hamster (CHO) protein as BeneFIX contains trace amounts. (  5.1  ) 
 *  BeneFIX has been associated with the development of thromboembolic complications, including in patients receiving continuous infusion through a central venous catheter. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Nephrotic syndrome has been reported following immune tolerance induction with factor IX products in hemophilia B patients with factor IX inhibitors and a history of allergic reactions to factor IX. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Development of neutralizing antibodies (inhibitors) to BeneFIX may occur. If expected plasma factor IX activity levels are not attained, or if patient presents with allergic reaction, or if bleeding is not controlled with an expected dose, perform an assay that measures factor IX inhibitor concentration. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have been reported with BeneFIX and have manifested as pruritus, rash, urticaria, hives, facial swelling, dizziness, hypotension, nausea, chest discomfort, cough, dyspnea, wheezing, flushing, discomfort (generalized) and fatigue. Frequently, these events have occurred in close temporal association with the development of factor IX inhibitors.



 Closely monitor patients for signs and symptoms of acute hypersensitivity reactions, particularly during the early phases of initial exposure to product. Because of the potential for allergic reactions with factor IX concentrates, perform the initial (approximately 10 - 20) administrations of factor IX under medical supervision where proper medical care for allergic reactions could be provided. Advise patients to discontinue use of the product and contact their physician and/or seek immediate emergency care. Immediately discontinue the administration and initiate appropriate treatment if symptoms occur.



 BeneFIX contains trace amounts of hamster (CHO) proteins. Patients treated with this product may develop hypersensitivity to these non-human mammalian proteins.



    5.2 Thromboembolic Complications



  There have been post-marketing reports of thrombotic events in patients receiving continuous-infusion BeneFIX through a central venous catheter, including life-threatening superior vena cava (SVC) syndrome in critically ill neonates [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . The safety and efficacy of BeneFIX administration by continuous infusion have not been established [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1  ,  2.3)  ]  .



    5.3 Nephrotic Syndrome



  Nephrotic syndrome has been reported following immune tolerance induction with factor IX products in hemophilia B patients with factor IX inhibitors and a history of allergic reactions to factor IX. The safety and efficacy of using BeneFIX for immune tolerance induction have not been established.



    5.4 Neutralizing Antibodies (Inhibitors)



  Neutralizing antibodies (inhibitors) have been reported following administration of BeneFIX [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Evaluate patients using BeneFIX for the development of factor IX inhibitors by appropriate clinical observations and laboratory tests. If expected plasma factor IX activity levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with an expected dose, perform an assay that measures factor IX inhibitor concentration.



 Patients with factor IX inhibitors are at an increased risk of severe hypersensitivity reactions or anaphylaxis upon subsequent challenge with factor IX.  2  Evaluate patients experiencing allergic reactions for the presence of an inhibitor and closely monitor patients with inhibitors for signs and symptoms of acute hypersensitivity reactions, particularly during the early phases of initial exposure to product [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



    5.5 Monitoring Laboratory Tests



    *  Monitor patients for factor IX activity levels by the one-stage clotting assay to confirm that adequate factor IX levels have been achieved and maintained, when clinically indicated [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ] . 
 *  Monitor patients for the development of inhibitors if expected factor IX activity plasma levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with the recommended dose of BeneFIX. Determine factor IX inhibitor levels in Bethesda Units (BUs). 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
