<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bentyl" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The pattern of adverse effects seen with dicyclomine is mostly related to its pharmacological actions at muscarinic receptors [    see Clinical Pharmacology (12)    ].  They are a consequence of the inhibitory effect on muscarinic receptors within the autonomic nervous system.  These effects are dose-related and are usually reversible when treatment is discontinued. 



 The most serious adverse reactions reported with dicyclomine hydrochloride include cardiovascular and central nervous system symptoms [    see Warnings and Precautions (5.2,5.3)    ].



   EXCERPT:   The most serious adverse reactions include cardiovascular and central nervous system symptoms. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;5% of patients) are dizziness, dry mouth, vision blurred, nausea, somnolence, asthenia and nervousness  (6)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Aptalis Pharma US, Inc. at 1-800-472-2634 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.com    



 



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure in controlled clinical trials involving over 100 patients treated for functional bowel/irritable bowel syndrome with dicyclomine hydrochloride at initial doses of 160 mg daily (40 mg four times a day)



 In these trials most of the side effects were typically anticholinergic in nature and were reported by 61% of the patients. Table 1 presents adverse reactions (  MedDRA 13.0  preferred terms) by decreasing order of frequency in a side-by-side comparison with placebo.



   Table 1: Adverse reactions experienced in controlled clinical trials with decreasing order of frequency  




   MedDRA Preferred Term      Dicyclomine Hydrochloride (40 mg four times a day) %      Placebo %                 
 Dry Mouth                  33                         5                           
 Dizziness                  40                         5                           
 Vision blurred             27                         2                           
 Nausea                     14                         6                           
 Somnolence                 9                          1                           
 Asthenia                   7                          1                           
 Nervousness                6                          2                           
      Nine percent (9%) of patients were discontinued from BENTYL because of one or more of these side effects (compared with 2% in the placebo group). In 41% of the patients with side effects, side effects disappeared or were tolerated at the 160 mg daily dose without reduction. A dose reduction from 160 mg daily to an average daily dose of 90 mg was required in 46% of the patients with side effects who then continued to experience a favorable clinical response; their side effects either disappeared or were tolerated.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions, presented by system organ class in alphabetical order, have been identified during post approval use of BENTYL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *   Cardiac disorders: palpitations, tachyarrhythmias 
 *   Eye disorders: cycloplegia, mydriasis, vision blurred 
 *   Gastrointestinal disorders: abdominal distension, abdominal pain, constipation, dry mouth, dyspepsia, nausea, vomiting 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions: fatigue, malaise 
 *   Immune System Disorders: drug hypersensitivity including face edema, angioedema, anaphylactic shock 
 *   Nervous system disorders: dizziness, headache, somnolence, syncope 
 *   Psychiatric disorders: As with the other anti-cholinergic drugs, cases of delirium or symptoms of delirium such as amnesia (or transient global amnesia), agitation, confusional state, delusion, disorientation, hallucination (including visual hallucination) as well as mania, mood altered and pseudodementia, have been reported with the use of Dicyclomine. Nervousness and insomnia have also been reported. 
 *   Reproductive system and breast disorders: suppressed lactation 
 *   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders: dyspnoea, nasal congestion 
 *   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorder: dermatitis allergic, erythema, rash 
    Cases of thrombosis, thrombophlebitis and injection site reactions such as local pain, edema, skin color change and even reflex sympathetic dystrophy syndrome have been reported following inadverent IV injection of BENTYL.
 

   6.3 Adverse Reactions Reported with Similar Drugs with Anticholinergic/Antispasmodic Action

  Gastrointestinal: anorexia,



 Central Nervous System: tingling, numbness, dyskinesia, speech disturbance, insomnia



 Peripheral Nervous System: With overdosage, a curare-like action may occur (i.e., neuromuscular blockade leading to muscular weakness and possible paralysis).



 Ophthalmologic: diplopia, increased ocular tension



 Dermatologic/Allergic: urticaria, itching, and other dermal manifestations;



 Genitourinary: urinary hesitancy, urinary retention in patients with prostatic hypertrophy



 Cardiovascular: hypertension



 Respiratory: apnea



 Other: decreased sweating, sneezing, throat congestion, impotence. With the injectable form, there may be temporary sensation of light-headedness. Some local irritation and focal coagulation necrosis may occur following the intramuscular injection of BENTYL.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     
 

    EXCERPT:    *  For Intramuscular injection only; should not be administered by any other route. Intravenous injection may result in thrombosis or thrombophlebitis and injection site reactions  (5.1)   
 *   Cardiovascular conditions : worsening of conditions  (5.2)   
 *   Peripheral and central nervous system : heat prostration can occur with drug use (fever and heat stroke due to decreased sweating); drug should be discontinued and supportive measures instituted  (5.3)   
 *   Psychosis and delirium have been reported in patients sensitive to anticholinergic drugs (such as elderly patients and/or in patients with mental illness) : signs and symptoms resolve within 12 to 24 hours after discontinuation of BENTYL  (5.3)   
 *   Myasthenia Gravis : overdose may lead to muscular weakness and paralysis. BENTYL should be given to patients with myasthenia gravis only to reduce adverse muscarinic effects of an anticholinesterase  (5.4)   
 *   Incomplete intestinal obstruction : diarrhea may be an early symptom especially in patients with ileostomy or colostomy. Treatment with BENTYL would be inappropriate and possibly fatal  (5.5)   
 *   Salmonella dysenteric patients : due to risk of toxic megacolon  (5.6)   
 *   Ulcerative colitis : BENTYL should be used with caution in these patients; large doses may suppress intestinal motility or aggravate the serious complications of toxic megacolon  (5.7)   
 *   Prostatic hypertrophy : BENTYL should be used with caution in these patients; may lead to urinary retention  (5.8)   
 *   Hepatic and renal disease : should be used with caution  (5.9)   
 *   Geriatric : use with caution in elderly who may be more susceptible to BENTYL's adverse events  (5.10)   
    
 

   5.1 Inadvertent Intravenous Administration



  BENTYL solution is for intramuscular administration only. Do not administer by any other route. Inadvertent intravenous administration may result in thrombosis, thrombophlebitis and injection site reactions such as pain, edema, skin color change, and reflex sympathetic dystrophy syndrome   [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]    .



    5.2 Cardiovascular Conditions



  Dicyclomine hydrochloride needs to be used with caution in conditions characterized by tachyarrhythmia such as thyrotoxicosis, congestive heart failure and in cardiac surgery, where they may further accelerate the heart rate.  Investigate any tachycardia before administration of dicyclomine hydrochloride.  Care is required in patients with coronary heart disease, as ischemia and infarction may be worsened, and in patients with hypertension   [see Adverse Reactions (6.3)]    .



    5.3 Peripheral and Central Nervous System



  The peripheral effects of dicyclomine hydrochloride are a consequence of their inhibitory effect on muscarinic receptors of the autonomic nervous system. They include dryness of the mouth with difficulty in swallowing and talking, thirst, reduced bronchial secretions, dilatation of the pupils (mydriasis) with loss of accommodation (cycloplegia) and photophobia, flushing and dryness of the skin, transient bradycardia followed by tachycardia, with palpitations and arrhythmias, and difficulty in micturition, as well as reduction in the tone and motility of the gastrointestinal tract leading to constipation   [see Adverse Reactions (6)]    .



 In the presence of high environmental temperature heat prostration can occur with drug use (fever and heat stroke due to decreased sweating). It should also be used cautiously in patients with fever. If symptoms occur, the drug should be discontinued and supportive measures instituted. Because of the inhibitory effect on muscarinic receptors within the autonomic nervous system, caution should be taken in patients with autonomic neuropathy.



 Central nervous system (CNS) signs and symptoms include confusional state, disorientation, amnesia, hallucinations, dysarthria, ataxia, coma, euphoria, fatigue, insomnia, agitation and mannerisms, and inappropriate affect.



 Psychosis and delirium have been reported in sensitive individuals (such as elderly patients and/or in patients with mental illness) given anticholinergic drugs. These CNS signs and symptoms usually resolve within 12 to 24 hours after discontinuation of the drug.



 BENTYL may produce drowsiness, dizziness or blurred vision. The patient should be warned not to engage in activities requiring mental alertness, such as operating a motor vehicle or other machinery or performing hazardous work while taking BENTYL.



    5.4 Myasthenia Gravis



  With overdosage, a curare-like action may occur (i.e., neuromuscular blockade leading to muscular weakness and possible paralysis).  It should not be given to patients with myasthenia gravis except to reduce adverse muscarinic effects of an anticholinesterase   [see Contraindications (4)]    



    5.5 Intestinal Obstruction



  Diarrhea may be an early symptom of incomplete intestinal obstruction, especially in patients with ileostomy or colostomy. In this instance, treatment with this drug would be inappropriate and possibly harmful   [see Contraindications (4)]    .



 Rarely development of Ogilvie's syndrome (colonic pseudo-obstruction) has been reported. Ogilvie's syndrome is a clinical disorder with signs, symptoms, and radiographic appearance of an acute large bowel obstruction but with no evidence of distal colonic obstruction



    5.6 Toxic Dilatation of Intestinemegacolon



   Toxic dilatation of intestine and intestinal perforation is possible when anticholinergic agents are administered in patients with Salmonella dysentery.  
 

    5.7 Ulcerative Colitis



  Caution should be taken in patients with ulcerative colitis.  Large doses may suppress intestinal motility to the point of producing a paralytic ileus and the use of this drug may precipitate or aggravate the serious complication of toxic megacolon   [see Adverse Reactions (6.3)]    .  BENTYL is contraindicated in patients with severe ulcerative colitis   [see Contraindications (4)]    .



    5.8 Prostatic Hypertrophy



  BENTYL should be used with caution in patients with known or suspected prostatic enlargement, in whom prostatic enlargement may lead to urinary retention   [see Adverse Reactions (6.3)]    



    5.9 Hepatic and Renal Disease



   BENTYL should be used with caution in patients with known hepatic and renal impairment.  
 

    5.10 Geriatric Population



   Dicyclomine hydrochloride should be used with caution in elderly who may be more susceptible to its adverse effects.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
