<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="berinert" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reaction reported in subjects enrolled in clinical studies who received Berinert was an increase in the severity of pain associated with HAE.



 The most common adverse reaction reported in greater than 4% of the subjects and greater than placebo among subjects who received Berinert in the placebo-controlled clinical trial was dysgeusia.



    EXCERPT:    *  The most serious adverse reaction reported in subjects who received Berinert was an increase in the severity of pain associated with HAE (  6.1  ). 
 *  The most common adverse reaction reported in greater than 4% of the subjects and greater than placebo among subjects who received Berinert in the placebo-controlled clinical trial was dysgeusia (  6.1  ). 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact the CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance Department at 1-866-915-6958 or to the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  



     Placebo-controlled Clinical Study  



 In the placebo-controlled clinical study, referred to as the randomized clinical trial (RCT)  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  , 124 subjects experiencing an acute moderate to severe abdominal or facial HAE attack were treated with Berinert (either a 10 IU per kg body weight or a 20 IU per kg body weight dose), or placebo (physiological saline solution).



 The treatment-emergent serious adverse reactions/events that occurred in 5 subjects in the RCT were laryngeal edema, facial attack with laryngeal edema, swelling (shoulder and chest), exacerbation of hereditary angioedema, and laryngospasm.



 Table 1: Adverse ReactionsComprises adverse events that began within 4 hours of infusion; these events were considered adverse reactions irrespective of reported causality. Occurring up to 4 Hours After Initial Infusion in More Than 4% of SubjectsThe following abdominal symptoms were identified in the protocol as associated with HAE abdominal attacks: abdominal pain, bloating, cramps, nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea. 
 Adverse Reactions         Number (%) of Subjects Reporting Adverse ReactionsBerinert 20 IU/kg(n=43)  Number (%) of Subjects Reporting Adverse ReactionsPlacebo Group(n=42)   
  
 Nausea                                    3 (7%)                                5 (11.9%)                  
 Dysgeusia                                2 (4.7%)                                 0 (0)                    
 Abdominal Pain                           2 (4.7%)                                3 (7.1%)                  
 Vomiting                                 1 (2.3%)                                3 (7.1%)                  
 Diarrhea                                  0 (0)                                  4 (9.5%)                  
 Headache                                  0 (0)                                  2 (4.8%)                  
        Table 2: Adverse ReactionsComprises adverse events that began within 72 hours of infusion; these events were considered adverse reactions irrespective of reported causality. Occurring in More Than 4% of Subjects up to 72 Hours After Infusion of Initial or Rescue MedicationIf a subject experienced no relief or insufficient relief of symptoms within 4 hours after infusion, investigators had the option to administer a blinded second infusion ("rescue" treatment) of Berinert (20 IU/kg for the placebo group or 10 IU/kg for the 10 IU/kg group), or placebo (for the 20 IU/kg group). by Intent-to-Treat 
  Adverse Reactions        Number (%) of Subjects Reporting Adverse ReactionsBerinert 20 IU/kg(n=43)  Number (%) of Subjects Reporting Adverse ReactionsPlacebo Group(n=42)   
  
 Nausea                                    3 (7%)                                11 (26.2%)                 
 Headache                                  3 (7%)                                5 (11.9%)                  
 Abdominal Pain                            3 (7%)                                5 (11.9%)                  
 Dysgeusia                                2 (4.7%)                                1 (2.4%)                  
 Vomiting                                 1 (2.3%)                               7 (16.7%)                  
 Pain                                     1 (2.3%)                                4 (9.5%)                  
 Muscle spasms                            1 (2.3%)                                4 (9.5%)                  
 Diarrhea                                  0 (0)                                  8 (19%)                   
 Back pain                                 0 (0)                                  2 (4.8%)                  
 Facial pain                               0 (0)                                  2 (4.8%)                  
         Subjects were tested at baseline and after 3 months for possible exposure to Parvovirus B19, hepatitis B, hepatitis C, and HIV-1 and HIV-2. No subject who underwent testing evidenced seroconversion or treatment-emergent positive polymerase chain reaction testing for these pathogens.
 

     Extension Study  



 In the safety analysis of the open-label extension study, 57 subjects with 1085 acute moderate to severe abdominal, facial, peripheral, and laryngeal attacks received a 20 IU/kg body weight dose of Berinert  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . This study provides additional safety data in subjects who received multiple infusions of the product for sequential HAE attacks (one infusion per attack).



 Table 3 lists the adverse reactions that occurred in the safety analysis of the open-label extension study in &gt;=2 subjects or associated with &gt;=5 attacks during infusion or within 24 hours or 72 hours after the end of a Berinert infusion.



 Table 3: Incidence of Subjects and Attacks with Adverse Reactions (ARs)Because of the allowance of rescue medication in both study arms, all listed adverse events were considered to be at least potentially related to study medication (eg, adverse reactions), regardless of the investigator's opinion concerning causality. Starting during Infusion or Within 24 Hours or 72 Hours after End of an Infusion (Experienced by &gt;=2 Subjects or Associated with &gt;=5 Attacks Overall) by Preferred Term (Safety Subject and Attack Populations) 
                                   Number (%) of Subjects(n=57)  Number (%) of Attacks(n=1085)   
 Preferred term                    ARs within 24 hours  ARs within 72 hours  ARs within 24 hours  ARs within 72 hours   
  
 N = total number of subjects/attacks   
 Data are sorted by decreasing frequency by number of subjects.   
  
   Any preferred term                 13 (22.8%)         20 (35.1%)          27 (2.5%)          41 (3.8%)       
 Headache                              2 (3.5%)           4 (7.0%)           3 (0.3%)           6 (0.6%)        
 Nasopharyngitis                       1 (1.8%)           2 (3.5%)           1 (&lt;0.1%)          2 (0.2%)        
 Abdominal pain or discomfort          1 (1.8%)           3 (5.3%)           2 (0.2%)           6 (0.6%)        
 Upper respiratory tract infection        0 (0)            1 (1.8%)             0 (0)            1 (&lt;0.1%)       
 Hereditary angioedema                 1 (1.8%)           1 (1.8%)           1 (&lt;0.1%)          1 (&lt;0.1%)       
 Influenza like illness                1 (1.8%)           2 (3.5%)           1 (&lt;0.1%)          2 (0.2%)        
 Rash                                  2 (3.5%)           2 (3.5%)           2 (0.2%)           2 (0.2%)        
 Vulvovaginal mycotic infection          0 (0)            2 (3.5%)             0 (0)            2 (0.2%)        
 Nausea                                1 (1.8%)           1 (1.8%)           4 (0.4%)           5 (0.5%)        
          Table 4: Summary of Adverse ReactionsBecause of the allowance of rescue medication in both study arms, all listed adverse events were considered to be at least potentially related to study medication (eg, adverse reactions), regardless of the investigator's opinion concerning causality. by Type of Attack (Safety Subject Population) 
                                 Type of AttackNumber (%) of Subjects   
 Overall ARs                     Abdominal(n=51)  Peripheral(n=30)  Laryngeal(n=16)   Facial(n=21)     Other(n=3)     
  
 N = number of subjects           
 Only ARs associated with attacks of the respective subgroups were included in the analysis.   
  
 Subjects with ARs                 17 (33.3%)      7 (23.3%)       2 (12.5%)         0 (0)           0 (0)        
   Subjects with serious ARs        1 (2.0%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
   Study medication permanently discontinued due to ARs     1 (2.0%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
   Most frequent ARs (&gt;=3 subjects overall)     
 Headache                           5 (9.8%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Nasopharyngitis                    1 (2.0%)        2 (6.7%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
   Other ARs (&lt;3 subjects overall)     
 Abdominal discomfort                0 (0)          1 (3.3%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Dizziness                          1 (2.0%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Dry mouth                           0 (0)          1 (3.3%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Erythema infectiosum               1 (2.0%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Headache                           1 (2.0%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Infusion-related reaction          1 (2.0%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Influenza like illness             1 (2.0%)         0 (0)          1 (6.3%)         0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Pruritus                            0 (0)          1 (3.3%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
 Rash                                0 (0)          1 (3.3%)         0 (0)           0 (0)           0 (0)        
            The incidence and type of adverse reactions with Berinert when administered for treatment of multiple consecutive acute HAE attacks of any type was similar to those previously observed. As in the placebo-controlled study, no proven cases of infections due to HIV-1/2, HAV, HBV, HCV or Parvovirus B19 were observed during the study.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



 Adverse reactions reported in Europe since 1979 in patients receiving Berinert for treatment of HAE include hypersensitivity/anaphylactic reactions, injection-site pain, injection-site redness, chills, and fever.



     TE Events Associated with HAE Treatment  



 TE events including basilar artery thrombosis, multiple pulmonary microemboli, and thrombosis have been reported with the use of Berinert at the recommended dose following treatment of HAE.



     TE Events Associated with Use in Unapproved Indications  



 TE events have also been reported with the use of Berinert in patients receiving higher than recommended doses during cardiac surgery (unapproved indication) include carotid artery thrombosis, cerebral thrombosis, myocardial infarction, pulmonary embolism, renal vein thrombosis, sagittal sinus thrombosis, inferior vena cava thrombosis, superior vena cava thrombosis, internal jugular vein thrombosis, and peripheral venous thrombosis.  1  



 The following adverse reactions, identified by system organ class, have been attributed to Berinert during post-approval use outside the US.



 *   Immune System Disorder:  Hypersensitivity/anaphylactic reactions, and shock  
 *   General/Body as a Whole: Pain on injection, redness at injection site, chills, and fever  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions may occur. Epinephrine should be immediately available to treat any acute severe hypersensitivity reactions following discontinuation of administration (  5.1  ). 
 *  Serious arterial and venous thromboembolic (TE) events have been reported at the recommended dose of C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) products, including Berinert, following administration in patients with HAE. Risk factors may include the presence of an indwelling venous catheter/access device, prior history of thrombosis, underlying atherosclerosis, use of oral contraceptives or certain androgens, morbid obesity, and immobility. Benefits of treatment of HAE attacks should be weighed against the risks of TE events in patients with underlying risk factors. Monitor patients with known risk factors for TE events during and after Berinert administration.TE events have also been reported following administration of a C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) product when used for unapproved indications at higher than recommended doses.  1  (  5.2  ). 
 *  Berinert is made from human plasma and may contain infectious agents, eg, viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent (  5.3  ). 
 *  Laryngeal attacks: Following self-administration of Berinert for laryngeal attacks, advise patients to immediately seek medical attention (  5.4  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur. Epinephrine should be immediately available for treatment of acute severe hypersensitivity reaction [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ].  The signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity reactions may include hives, generalized urticaria, tightness of the chest, wheezing, hypotension, and/or anaphylaxis during or after injection of Berinert.



 Because hypersensitivity reactions may have symptoms similar to HAE attacks, treatment methods should be carefully considered. In case of suspected hypersensitivity, immediately discontinue administration of Berinert and institute appropriate treatment.



    5.2 Thromboembolic Events



  Serious arterial and venous thromboembolic (TE) events have been reported at the recommended dose of C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) products, including Berinert, following administration in patients with HAE. Risk factors may include the presence of an indwelling venous catheter/access device, prior history of thrombosis, underlying atherosclerosis, use of oral contraceptives or certain androgens, morbid obesity, and immobility. Benefits of treatment of HAE attacks should be weighed against the risks of TE events in patients with underlying risk factors. Monitor patients with known risk factors for TE events during and after Berinert administration.



 TE events have also been reported following administration of a C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) product when used for unapproved indications at higher than recommended doses  1,2   [see  Overdosage (10)  and  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2)  ]  .



    5.3 Transmission of Infectious Agents



  Because Berinert is made from human blood, it may contain infectious agents (eg, viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease [CJD] agent) that can cause disease. The risk that such products will transmit an infectious agent has been reduced by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, by testing for the presence of certain current virus infections, and by processes demonstrated to inactivate and/or remove certain viruses during manufacturing [see  Description (11)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  .



 Despite these measures, such products may still potentially transmit disease. There is also the possibility that unknown infectious agents may be present in such products.



 Since 1979, a few suspected cases of viral transmission have been reported with the use of Berinert outside the US, including cases of acute hepatitis C. From the incomplete information available from these cases, it was not possible to determine with certainty if the infections were or were not related to prior administration of Berinert. With the introduction of the pasteurization step (heat treatment in aqueous solution at 60 degrees C for 10 hours) in 1985, case reports on suspected transmission of viruses have not demonstrated a causal relationship to the administration of Berinert.



 The physician should discuss the risks and benefits of this product with the patient before prescribing or administering it to the patient [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ].  



 All infections thought by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by Berinert should be reported by lot number, by the physician, or other healthcare provider to the CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance Department at 1-866-915-6958.



    5.4 Laryngeal Attacks



  Given the potential for airway obstruction during acute laryngeal HAE attacks, patients self-administering Berinert should be advised to immediately seek medical attention in an appropriate healthcare facility after treatment with Berinert.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
