<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="betapace" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse events that are clearly related to Betapace AF are those which are typical of its Class II (beta-blocking) and Class III (cardiac action potential duration prolongation) effects. The common documented beta-blocking adverse events (bradycardia, dyspnea, and fatigue) and Class III effects (QT interval prolongation) are dose related.



 In a pooled clinical trial population consisting of four placebo-controlled studies with 275 patients with AFIB/AFL treated with 160-320 mg doses of Betapace AF, the following adverse events were reported at a rate of 2% or more in the 160-240 mg treated patients and greater than the rate in placebo patients (See Table 8). The data are presented by incidence of events in the Betapace AF and placebo groups by body system and daily dose. No significant irreversible non-cardiac end-organ toxicity was observed.



 Table 8 Incidence (%) of Common Adverse Events (&gt;=2% in the 160-240 mg group and more frequent than on placebo) in Four Placebo-Controlled Studies of Patients with AFIB/AFL 
                                                              Placebo         Betapace AF  Total Daily Dose    
  Body System/  Adverse Event (Preferred Term)                N=282           160-240  N=153    &gt;240-320  N=122    
  CARDIOVASCULAR                                                                                              
  Abnormality ECG                                             0.4             3.3            2.5              
  Angina Pectoris                                             1.1             2.0            1.6              
  Bradycardia                                                 2.5             13.1           12.3             
  Chest Pain Cardiac/Non-Anginal                              4.6             4.6            2.5              
  Disturbance Rhythm Atrial                                   2.1             2.0            1.6              
  Disturbance Rhythm Subjective                               9.9             9.8            7.4              
  GASTROINTESTINAL                                                                                            
  Appetite Decreased                                          0.4             2.0            1.6              
  Diarrhea                                                    2.1             5.2            5.7              
  Distention Abdomen                                          0.4             0.7            2.5              
  Dyspepsia/Heartburn                                         1.8             2.0            2.5              
  Nausea/Vomiting                                             5.3             7.8            5.7              
  Pain Abdomen                                                2.5             3.9            2.5              
  GENERAL                                                                                                     
  Fatigue                                                     8.5             19.6           18.9             
  Fever                                                       0.7             0.7            3.3              
  Hyperhidrosis                                               3.2             5.2            4.9              
  Influenza                                                   0.4             2.0            0.8              
  Sensation Cold                                              0.7             2.0            2.5              
  Weakness                                                    3.2             5.2            4.9              
  MUSCULOSKELETAL/CONNECTIVE TISSUE                                                                           
  Pain Chest Musculoskeletal                                  1.4             2.0            2.5              
  Pain Musculoskeletal                                        2.8             2.6            4.1              
  NERVOUS SYSTEM                                                                                              
  Dizziness                                                   12.4            16.3           13.1             
  Headache                                                    5.3             3.3            11.5             
  Insomnia                                                    1.1             2.6            4.1              
  RESPIRATORY                                                                                                 
  Cough                                                       2.5             3.3            2.5              
  Dyspnea                                                     7.4             9.2            9.8              
  Infection Upper Respiratory                                 1.1             2.6            3.3              
  Tracheobronchitis                                           0.7             0.7            3.3              
  SPECIAL SENSES                                                                                              
  Disturbance Vision                                          0.7             2.6            0.8              
          Overall, discontinuation because of unacceptable adverse events was necessary in 17% of the patients, and occurred in 10% of patients less than two weeks after starting treatment. The most common adverse events leading to discontinuation of Betapace AF were: fatigue 4.6%, bradycardia 2.4%, proarrhythmia 2.2%, dyspnea 2%, and QT interval prolongation 1.4%.
 

 In clinical trials involving 1292 patients with sustained VT/VF, the common adverse events (occurring in &gt;=2% of patients) were similar to those described for the AFIB/AFL population.



 Occasional reports of elevated serum liver enzymes have occurred with sotalol therapy but no cause and effect relationship has been established. One case of peripheral neuropathy which resolved on discontinuation of sotalol and recurred when the patient was rechallenged with the drug was reported in an early dose tolerance study. Elevated blood glucose levels and increased insulin requirements can occur in diabetic patients.



 In an unblinded multicenter trial of 25 patients with SVT and/or VT receiving daily doses of 30, 90 and 210 mg/m  2  with dosing every 8 hours for a total of 9 doses, no Torsades de Pointes or other serious new arrhythmias were observed. One (1) patient, receiving 30 mg/m  2  daily, was discontinued because of increased frequency of sinus pauses/bradycardia. Additional cardiovascular AEs were seen at the 90 and 210 mg/m  2  daily dose levels. They included QT prolongations (2 patients), sinus pauses/bradycardia (1 patient), increased severity of atrial flutter and reported chest pain (1 patient). Values for QTc&gt;=525 msec were seen in 2 patients at the 210 mg/m  2  daily dose level. Serious adverse events including death, Torsades de Pointes, other proarrhythmias, high-degree A-V blocks and bradycardia have been reported in infants and/or children.



   Potential Adverse Effects

  Foreign marketing experience with sotalol hydrochloride shows an adverse experience profile similar to that described above from clinical trials. Voluntary reports since introduction also include rare reports of: emotional liability, slightly clouded sensorium, incoordination, vertigo, paralysis, thrombocytopenia, eosinophilia, leukopenia, photosensitivity reaction, fever, pulmonary edema, hyperlipidemia, myalgia, pruritis, alopecia.



 The oculomucocutaneous syndrome associated with the beta-blocker practolol has not been associated with  Betapace    AF  during investigational use and foreign marketing experience.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    To minimize the risk of induced arrhythmia, patients initiated or re-initiated on     Betapace     AF  (r)   should be placed for a minimum of three days (on their maintenance dose) in a facility that can provide cardiac resuscitation, continuous electrocardiographic monitoring and calculations of     creatinine     clearance. For detailed instructions regarding dose selection, and special cautions for people with renal impairment, see   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  .   Sotalol is also indicated for the treatment of documented life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias and is marketed under the brand name Betapace  (r)  . Betapace  however, should not be substituted for Betapace AF  because of significant differences in labeling (i.e. patient package insert, dosing administration and safety information).



   Rx only



 





    BOXED WARNING: 

    PATIENT INFORMATION  



   What You Should Know About     Betapace     AF  



 (Bay' tah pace)



 (generic name: sotalol hydrochloride)



   

  This summary contains important patient information that has been reviewed and approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. This summary is not meant to take the place of your doctor's instructions. Read this patient information carefully before you start taking Betapace AF. Each time you get a refill, you will receive patient information. Be sure to read it because it may contain new information that you need to know.



     What is the most important information I should know about     Betapace     AF?  



 Because you have irregular heartbeats (atrial fibrillation) that are troublesome to you, Betapace AF has been prescribed to help your heart to beat in a more normal way. However, in some patients Betapace AF can cause a different type of abnormal heartbeat that can be dangerous, and in rare instances can even cause death. You may feel this different type of abnormal heartbeat as a fast beating of the heart with lightheadedness and fainting. The possibility of this different type of abnormal heartbeat is the reason you and your doctor have discussed whether your symptoms are troublesome enough for you to start taking Betapace AF.



 Clinical studies using Betapace AF have shown that the most important way to decrease your chance of getting this different type of dangerous abnormal heartbeat is for you to take the dose of Betapace AF that is right for you. If this abnormal heartbeat occurs, it usually happens during the first few days of treatment. This is why you should be started on Betapace AF in a hospital or another place where your heartbeat can be watched closely by health care professionals for the first few days. They can help you if problems occur. When Betapace AF is started this way, this different type of abnormal heartbeat is rare and the hospital staff is there to treat it.



 It is important that when you go home, you take the exact dose the doctor prescribed for you. At any time while you are taking Betapace AF, watch for signs that you may be getting this different type of abnormal heartbeat and call your doctor if they occur. Call your doctor right away if you:



 *  faint, 
 *  become dizzy, or 
 *  have fast heartbeats. 
    If you cannot reach your doctor, go to the nearest hospital emergency room. Take your Betapace AF tablets with you and show them to the doctor or nurse.
 

 Also, call your doctor right away if you have any of the following conditions: 



 *  severe diarrhea 
 *   unusual sweating 
 *  vomiting 
 *  less appetite than normal, or 
 *  more thirst than normal. 
    These are conditions that will make you more likely to get the different type of abnormal heartbeat. 
 

 If you take Betapace AF with certain other medicines, you will increase your chance of getting this different type of abnormal heartbeat. These medicines are listed below under "  Who should not take     Betapace     AF?  "



 Once your doctor finds the right dose for you, always take that exact amount of Betapace AF. Never take an extra dose and never skip a dose of Betapace AF.



   What is     Betapace     AF?  



 Betapace AF is a medicine that is given to patients with atrial fibrillation (irregular heartbeats). Atrial fibrillation happens when certain parts of the heart (the chambers known as atria) beat too fast or irregularly. When this happens, your heart cannot pump blood through your body as well as it should. This may make you feel weak and tired, or get out of breath easily. You may get an uncomfortable feeling in your chest and "fluttering" or "palpitations." Atrial fibrillation can be changed back (converted) to normal heart rhythm by an electric shock or by using certain medicines. However, atrial fibrillation can return. Betapace AF may help your heart stay beating regularly for a longer period of time. 



 This information about Betapace AF was developed to ensure that you and your doctor get the right information about your type of irregular heartbeats. Consult your doctor before you accept any other sotalol product that does not provide this patient information.



   Who should not take     Betapace     AF?  



 Betapace AF is not for everyone with irregular heartbeats (atrial fibrillation). This is why you and your doctor need to discuss the benefits and risks of Betapace AF and whether your symptoms are troublesome enough for you to start taking Betapace AF. 



 Do not take Betapace AF if you: 



 *  have serious kidney problems or are on kidney dialysis; 
 *  have lung disease causing shortness of breath (such as asthma, chronic bronchitis or emphysema); 
 *  have symptoms of heart failure (such as shortness of breath when you exercise or are physically active and swelling of the ankles or legs); 
 *  have a very slow heart beat and do not have an implanted artificial pacemaker; 
    Taking certain other medicines with Betapace AF can increase the chance that you will get the dangerous abnormal heartbeat discussed in "  What is the most important information I should know about     Betapace     AF?  " These include medicines used to treat abnormal heart rhythms and some other heart problems as well as medicines used to treat depression and other mental problems, night-time heartburn, asthma and infections. Therefore, you should be sure to tell your health care provider about all prescription and non-prescription medicines you are taking, as well as vitamins, dietary supplements, and any natural or herbal remedies. In addition, tell your doctor about any problems you have with your heart or kidneys.
 

 If you are pregnant, you should know that there is no information about the safety of Betapace AF in pregnant women. Some reports indicate that Betapace AF is passed into the breast milk. Women who are taking Betapace AF should not breast feed a child.



   How should I take     Betapace     AF?  



 Your doctor will start you on Betapace AF in the hospital and will check your heart rhythm for the first 2 or more days of treatment. This will allow your doctor to find the right dose for you. Always take the exact amount your doctor prescribes. Never change your Betapace AF dose unless your doctor tells you to. Your doctor will do regular tests to check that the amount you're taking is still right for you. 



 Keep taking your Betapace AF until your doctor tells you to stop. Keep taking it even if you feel fine. However, never take an extra dose of Betapace AF even if you do not feel well. When it is time to stop taking Betapace AF, your doctor will give you instructions on how to gradually reduce your dose over a period of 1 to 2 weeks. 



 You may take Betapace AF with or without food. However, it is important to take Betapace AF at the same time every day. This gives your heart a steady supply of the medicine. It might be helpful to take Betapace AF at the same time as something you regularly do every day. 



 If you are taking an antacid containing aluminum or magnesium to treat heartburn or upset stomach wait at least 2 hours after your dose of Betapace AF before you take the antacid. 



 Never try to make up for a missed dose of Betapace AF. You could increase your chance of getting the different type of abnormal heartbeat. If you miss taking a dose of Betapace AF, just take your normal amount at the next scheduled time. 



 If you take more Betapace AF than you should have, call your doctor right away. If you cannot reach your doctor, go to the nearest hospital emergency room. Take your Betapace AF tablets with you to show to the doctor or nurse.



   What should I avoid while taking     Betapace     AF?  



 Certain other medicines taken with Betapace AF may increase the chance that you will get the dangerous abnormal heartbeat (see   "Who should not take     Betapace     AF?"  ). Do not take Betapace AF with these medicines. Before you start taking Betapace AF tell your doctor about all prescription and non-prescription medicines you are taking (see also   "Who should not take     Betapace     AF?"  ). Once you begin taking Betapace AF, do not start taking any new medicines until you check with your doctor. 



 Carry a list of all the medicines and supplements you take. If you have to go to the hospital or are treated by new or different health care providers, tell them you are taking Betapace AF and show them the list of other medicines you take. They need this information to make sure your medicines are safe to take at the same time. 



 Tell your doctor or dentist you are taking Betapace AF before you have an operation or dental surgery. Betapace AF can affect how well some anesthetics work.



   What are the possible side effects of     Betapace     AF?  



 Betapace AF's most serious side effect, a different type of dangerous abnormal heartbeat, is discussed in "  What is the most important information I should know about     Betapace     AF?  " Dangerous abnormal heartbeats happen rarely. But they can be serious and, in rare instances, can even cause death. 



  Betapace AF's most common side effects are tiredness, slow rate, shortness of breath, and dizziness. Betapace AF can also cause other side effects. If you are concerned about these or any other side effects, ask your doctor.



   Important points about     Betapace     AF  



 Betapace AF can help you best if you take it as your doctor has prescribed it. 



 *  Take your medicine every day as prescribed. 
 *  Do not miss doses or take extra doses. 
 *  Call your doctor right away if you feel new fast heartbeats with lightheadedness and fainting. These can be serious and in rare instances can even cause death. 
 *  Do not take Betapace AF if you have serious kidney problems, lung disease causing shortness of breath, symptoms of heart failure. 
 *  Tell your doctor and pharmacist the name of all medications (prescription, non-prescription, and natural/herbal remedies) you are taking. 
 *  Do not start taking any other medicines without telling your doctor. 
 *  Go for all your regular checkups. 
 *  Get your refills on time. 
 *  Do not stop taking Betapace AF until your doctor tells you to stop. 
    This leaflet provides a summary of information about Betapace AF. Your doctor or pharmacist has a longer leaflet written for healthcare professionals that you can ask to read. Betapace AF was prescribed for your particular condition. Do not use it for another condition or give it to others.
 

 (c) 2011, Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. All rights reserved.



 Manufactured for Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. All rights reserved.Wayne, NJ 07470



 Manufactured in Finland 



 6700802 US Rev. February 2011
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
