<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bethkis" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions (more than 5%) occurring more frequently in BETHKIS patients are forced expiratory volume decreased, rales, red blood cell sedimentation rate increased, and dysphonia. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Chiesi USA, Inc. at 1-888- 661-9260 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of drugs cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to BETHKIS in two placebo-controlled studies in 305 cystic fibrosis patients. Patients receiving BETHKIS ranged in age from 6 to 31 years.



 In Study 1, an eight week study, 29 patients received BETHKIS versus 30 patients who received placebo for a total of four weeks on drug and four weeks off drug.  All patients were &lt;= 30 years of age (mean age 12.6 years) and 46% were females. 52.5% of patients were 6 to 12 years of age while 30.5% of patients were 13-17 years old. Only 16.5% of patients were adults (&gt; 17 years old). Eighty percent (80%) of patients were chronically colonized with  Pseudomonas aeruginosa  while 20.3% of patients were initially or intermittently colonized with  Pseudomonas aeruginosa  during the study.



 More patients in the placebo group discontinued/dropped out of Study 1 than in the BETHKIS group (23% [7/30] vs 3.4% [1/29], respectively). Five patients in the placebo group compared to none in the BETHKIS group discontinued/dropped out because of treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs) such as pulmonary exacerbations and respiratory disorders.



 In Study 2, a 24 week study, 161 patients received BETHKIS versus 85 patients who received placebo in alternating four week on-off cycles for three cycles. All patients were &lt;= 46 years of age (mean age 14.8 years) and 45% were females. 41% of patients were 6-12 years old while 29% of patients were 13-17 years old. Only 30% were adults (&gt;17 years). Eighty-seven percent (87%) of patients were chronically colonized with  P. aeruginosa  . Only 13% were either initially or intermittently colonized with  P. aeruginosa  during the study.



 More patients in the placebo group discontinued/dropped out of Study 2 than in the BETHKIS group (9.4% [8/85] vs 4.3% [7/161], respectively). Of these, 3 patients in the BETHKIS group (1.9%) compared to 2 patients in the placebo group (2.4%) withdrew due to a TEAE. The most common TEAEs causing patients to discontinue from the study drug are respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders.



 The most common adverse experiences reported were respiratory disorders, consistent with the underlying disease in the patient population being evaluated and these were similarly distributed between both BETHKIS- and placebo-treated patients. The following adverse reactions were reported in at least 5% of Bethkis-treated patients and at rates &gt;= 2% more common compared to the placebo-treated patients: decreased forced expiratory volume, rales, red blood cell sedimentation rate increased, and dysphonia (Table 1).    



 Table 1: Patients with Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 2% of BETHKIS Patients 
   Adverse Reactions                                      BETHKISN=190(%)                 PlaceboN=115(%)              
   Forced expiratory volume decreased                     59 (31%)                        33 (29%)                     
   Rales                                                  36 (19%)                        18 (16%)                     
   Red blood cell sedimentation rate increased            16 (8%)                         6 (5%)                       
   Dysphonia                                              11 (6%)                         2 (2%)                       
   Wheezing                                               10 (5%)                         4 (4%)                       
   Epistaxis                                              6 (3%)                          0                            
   Pharyngolaryngeal pain                                 5 (3%)                          2 (2%)                       
   Bronchitis                                             5 (3%)                          1 (1%)                       
   Tonsillitis                                            4 (2%)                          0                            
   Diarrhea                                               3 (2%)                          1 (1%)                       
   Eosinophilia                                           3 (2%)                          0                            
   Immunoglobulins increased                              3 (2%)                          0                            
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   In postmarketing experience, some patients receiving inhaled tobramycin have reported hearing loss. Some of these reports occurred in patients with previous or concomitant treatment with systemic aminoglycosides. Patients with hearing loss frequently reported tinnitus (  see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS, Ototoxicity (  5.1  )  ).



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Caution should be exercised when prescribing BETHKIS to patients with known or suspected auditory, vestibular, renal, or neuromuscular dysfunction. (  5.1  ,  5.2  ,  5.3  and  5.5  ) 
 *  Aminoglycoside may aggravate muscle weakness because of a potential curare-like effect on neuromuscular function. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Bronchospasm can occur with inhalation of BETHKIS. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Audiograms, serum concentration, and renal function should be monitored as appropriate. (  5.2  and  5.5  ) 
 *  Fetal harm can occur when aminoglycosides are administered to a pregnant woman. Apprise women of the potential hazard to the fetus. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Ototoxicity



  Caution should be exercised when prescribing BETHKIS to patients with known or suspected auditory or vestibular dysfunction.



 Findings related to ototoxicity as measured by audiometric evaluations and auditory adverse event reports were similar between BETHKIS and placebo in controlled clinical trials. Hearing loss was reported in two (1.1%) BETHKIS-treated patients and in one (0.9%) placebo-treated patient during clinical studies. Additionally, dizziness and vertigo, both of which may be manifestations of vestibular forms of ototoxicity, were observed in similar numbers of BETHKIS- and placebo-treated patients. Dizziness occurred in two (1.1%) BETHKIS-treated patients and one (0.9%) placebo-treated patient and vertigo occurred in two (1.1%) BETHKIS-treated patients versus no placebo patients in clinical studies. None of the BETHKIS patients discontinued their therapy due to hearing loss, dizziness or vertigo.



 Tinnitus may be a sentinel symptom of ototoxicity. No reports of tinnitus occurred in patients during clinical studies with BETHKIS, but because it has been observed with inhaled tobramycin solutions, onset of this symptom warrants caution.  Ototoxicity, manifested as both auditory and vestibular toxicity, has been reported with parenteral aminoglycosides.  Vestibular toxicity may be manifested by vertigo, ataxia or dizziness. 



    5.2 Nephrotoxicity



  Caution should be exercised when prescribing BETHKIS to patients with known or suspected renal dysfunction.



 Nephrotoxicity was not seen during BETHKIS clinical studies but has been associated with aminoglycosides as a class. If nephrotoxicity occurs in a patient receiving BETHKIS, therapy should be discontinued until serum concentrations fall below 2 mcg/mL.



 Twenty-six (14%) BETHKIS patients and 15 (13%) placebo patients had increases in serum creatinine of at least 50% over baseline. Follow-up values were obtained for 17 of the 26 BETHKIS patients, all of which decreased to serum creatinine values that were within normal laboratory ranges.  Patients who experience an increase in serum creatinine during treatment with BETHKIS should have their renal function closely monitored.



    5.3 Neuromuscular Disorders



  BETHKIS should be used cautiously in patients with muscular disorders, such as myasthenia gravis or Parkinson's disease, since aminoglycosides may aggravate muscle weakness because of a potential curare-like effect on neuromuscular function.



    5.4 Bronchospasm



  Bronchospasm can occur with inhalation of tobramycin. In clinical studies with BETHKIS, bronchospasm was observed in one (0.5%) BETHKIS-treated patient and in no placebo-treated patients. Wheezing occurred in ten (5%) BETHKIS-treated patients and four (4%) placebo-treated patients. Bronchospasm and wheezing should be treated as medically appropriate.



    5.5 Laboratory Tests



    5.5.1 Audiograms  



  Clinical studies of inhaled tobramycin solutions did not identify hearing loss using audiometric tests which evaluated hearing up to 8000 Hz. Physicians should consider an audiogram for patients who show any evidence of auditory dysfunction, or who are at increased risk for auditory dysfunction.Tinnitus may be a sentinel symptom of ototoxicity, and therefore the onset of this symptom warrants caution.



     5.5.2 Serum Concentrations  



  In patients with normal renal function treated with BETHKIS, serum tobramycin concentrations range from approximately 0.06-1.89 mcg/mL one hour after dose administration and do not require routine monitoring. Serum concentrations of tobramycin in patients with renal dysfunction or patients treated with concomitant parenteral tobramycin should be monitored at the discretion of the treating physician. ( See  12.3    )



     5.5.3 Renal Function  



  The clinical studies of BETHKIS did not reveal any imbalance in the percentage of patients who experienced at least a 50% rise in serum creatinine from baseline in either the BETHKIS group (n=26, 14%) or the placebo group (n=15, 13%). Laboratory tests of urine and renal function should be conducted at the discretion of the treating physician.



    5.6 Use in Pregnancy



  Aminoglycosides can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Aminoglycosides cross the placenta, and streptomycin has been associated with several reports of total irreversible, bilateral congenital deafness in pediatric patients exposed in utero  . Patients who use BETHKIS during pregnancy, or become pregnant while taking BETHKIS should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
