<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="betimol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most frequently reported ocular event in clinical trials was burning/stinging on instillation and was comparable between Betimol  (r)  and timolol maleate (approximately one in eight patients).



 The following adverse events were associated with use of Betimol  (r)  in frequencies of more than 5% in two controlled, double-masked clinical studies in which 184 patients received 0.25% or 0.5% Betimol  (r)  :



   OCULAR:  



 Dry eyes, itching, foreign body sensation, discomfort in the eye, eyelid erythema, conjunctival injection, and headache.



   BODY AS A WHOLE:  



 Headache.



 The following side effects were reported in frequencies of 1 to 5%:



   OCULAR:  



 Eye pain, epiphora, photophobia, blurred or abnormal vision, corneal fluorescein staining, keratitis, blepharitis and cataract.



   BODY AS A WHOLE:  



 Allergic reaction, asthenia, common cold and pain in extremities.



   CARDIOVASCULAR:  



 Hypertension.



   DIGESTIVE:  



 Nausea.



   METABOLlC/NUTRITIONAL:  



 Peripheral edema.



   NERVOUS SYSTEM/PSYCHIATRY:  



 Dizziness and dry mouth.



   RESPIRATORY:  



 Respiratory infection and sinusitis.



 In addition, the following adverse reactions have been reported with ophthalmic use of beta blockers:



   OCULAR:  



 Conjunctivitis, blepharoptosis, decreased corneal sensitivity, visual disturbances including refractive changes, diplopia and retinal vascular disorder.



   BODY AS A WHOLE:  



 Chest pain.



   CARDIOVASCULAR:  



 Arrhythmia, palpitation, bradycardia, hypotension, syncope, heart block, cerebral vascular accident, cerebral ischemia, cardiac failure and cardiac arrest.



   DIGESTIVE:  



 Diarrhea.



   ENDOCRINE:  



 Masked symptoms of hypoglycemia in insulin dependent diabetics (See  WARNINGS  ).



   NERVOUS SYSTEM/PSYCHIATRY:  



 Depression, impotence, increase in signs and symptoms of myasthenia gravis and paresthesia.



   RESPIRATORY:  



 Dyspnea, bronchospasm, respiratory failure and nasal congestion.



   SKIN:  



 AIOPecia, hypersensitivity including localized and generalized rash, urticaria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
