<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bexsero" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common solicited adverse reactions observed in clinical trials were pain at the injection site (&gt;=83%), myalgia (&gt;=48%), erythema (&gt;=45%), fatigue (&gt;=35%), headache (&gt;=33%), induration (&gt;=28%), nausea (&gt;=18%), and arthralgia (&gt;=13%).



   EXCERPT:   The most common solicited adverse reactions observed in clinical trials were pain at the injection site (&gt;=83%), myalgia (&gt;=48%), erythema (&gt;=45%), fatigue (&gt;=35%), headache (&gt;=33%), induration (&gt;= 28%), nausea (&gt;=18%), and arthralgia (&gt;=13%). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Vaccines at 1-877-683-4732 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or    http://vaers.hhs.gov    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In four clinical trials, 3058 individuals 10 through 25 years of age received at least one dose of BEXSERO, 1436 participants received only BEXSERO, 2089 received only placebo or a control vaccine, and 1622 participants received a mixed regimen (placebo or control vaccine and BEXSERO).



 In a randomized controlled study  1  conducted in US and Poland, 120 participants 10 through 25 years of age received at least one dose of BEXSERO, including 112 participants who received 2 doses of BEXSERO 2 months apart; 97 participants received saline placebo followed by Menveo [Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y, and W-135) Oligosaccharide Diphtheria CRM197Conjugate Vaccine]. Across groups, median age was 13 years, males comprised 49% and 60% were White; 34% were Hispanic, 4% were Black,&lt;1% were Asian, and 2% were other.



 In a second randomized controlled study  2  conducted in Chile, all subjects (N=1,622) 11 through 17 years of age received at least one dose of BEXSERO. This study included a subset of 810 subjects who received 2 doses of BEXSERO 1 or 2 months apart. A control group of 128 subjects received at least 1 dose of placebo containing aluminum hydroxide. A subgroup of 128 subjects received 2 doses of BEXSERO 6 months apart. In this study, median age was 14 years, males comprised 44%, and 99% were Hispanic.



 In a third randomized controlled study  3  conducted in the United Kingdom (UK), 974 university students 18 through 24 years of age received at least 1 dose of BEXSERO, including 932 subjects who received 2 doses of BEXSERO 1 month apart. Comparator groups received 1 dose of Menveo followed by 1 dose of placebo containing aluminum hydroxide (N=956) or 2 doses of IXIARO (Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine, Inactivated, Adsorbed) (N=947). Across groups, median age was 20 years, males comprised 46%, and 88% were White, 5% were Asian, 2% were Black, &lt;1% were Hispanic, and 4% were other.



 In an uncontrolled study  4  conducted in Canada and Australia, 342 participants 11 through 17 years of age received at least 1 dose of BEXSERO, including 338 participants who received 2 doses of BEXSERO 1 month apart. The median age was 13 years, males comprised 55%, and 80% were White, 10% were Asian, 4% were Native American/Alaskan, and 4% were other.



 Local and systemic reactogenicity data were solicited from all participants in the studies conducted in Chile, US/Poland, Canada/Australia, and in a subset of participants in the UK study. Reports of unsolicited adverse events occurring within the first 7 days after each vaccination were collected in all studies. In the US/Poland study, reports of unsolicited adverse events were collected up to one month after the second vaccination.



 Reports of all serious adverse events, medically attended adverse events and adverse events leading to premature withdrawal were collected throughout the study period for the studies conducted in Chile (12 months), UK (12 months), US/Poland (8 months), and Canada/Australia (2 months).



   Solicited Adverse Reactions  



 The reported rates of local and systemic reactions among participants 10 through 25 years of age following each dose of BEXSERO administered 2 months apart or control in the US/Polish study  1  are presented in  Table 1  .



 Table 1: Percentage of US and Polish Participants 10 through 25 Years of Age Reporting Solicited Local and Systemic Adverse Reactions within 7 Days after BEXSERO or Control, by Dose 
  Clinicaltrials.gov Identifier NCT01272180.    
  a Erythema, and induration: Any (&gt;= 1 mm).Pain and systemic reactions: mild (transient with no limitation in normal daily activity); moderate (some limitation in normal daily activity); severe (unable to perform normal daily activity)    
  b Administered 2 months after Dose 1    
  
   Solicited Reaction      a        Dose 1               Dose 2      b       
   BEXSERO           Placebo    (Saline)      BEXSERO           Menveo           
 N=110-114         N= 94-96             N=107-109         N=90-92            
   Local Adverse Reactions     
 Pain              Any                  90                27                83                43                 
 Mild              27                   20                18                26                 
 Moderate          44                   5                 37                9                  
 Severe            20                   2                 29                8                  
 Erythema          Any                  50                13                45                26                 
 1-25 mm           41                   11                36                13                 
 &gt;25-50 mm         6                    1                 5                 6                  
 &gt;50-100 mm        3                    0                 5                 4                  
 &gt;100 mm           0                    0                 0                 2                  
 Induration        Any                  32                10                28                23                 
 1-25 mm           24                   9                 22                16                 
 &gt;25-50 mm         7                    0                 4                 0                  
 &gt; 50-100 mm       1                    1                 2                 4                  
 &gt; 100 mm          0                    0                 0                 2                  
   Systemic Adverse Reactions     
 Fatigue           Any                  37                22                35                20                 
 Mild              19                   17                18                11                 
 Moderate          14                   5                 10                7                  
 Severe            4                    0                 6                 2                  
 Nausea            Any                  19                4                 18                4                  
 Mild              12                   3                 10                3                  
 Moderate          4                    1                 5                 1                  
 Severe            4                    0                 4                 0                  
 Myalgia           Any                  49                26                48                25                 
 Mild              21                   20                16                14                 
 Moderate          16                   5                 19                7                  
 Severe            12                   1                 13                4                  
 Arthralgia        Any                  13                4                 16                4                  
 Mild              9                    3                 8                 2                  
 Moderate          3                    1                 6                 2                  
 Severe            2                    0                 2                 0                  
 Headache          Any                  33                20                34                23                 
 Mild              19                   15                21                8                  
 Moderate          9                    4                 6                 12                 
 Severe            4                    1                 6                 3                  
 Fever             &gt;=38 degrees C       1                 1                 5                 0                  
 38.0-38.9 degrees C  1                    1                 4                 0                  
 39.0-39.9 degrees C  0                    0                 1                 0                  
 &gt;=40 degrees C    0                    0                 0                 0                  
            Solicited adverse reaction rates were similar among participants 11 through 24 years of age who received BEXSERO in the other three clinical studies,  2,3,4  except for severe myalgia which was reported by 3-7% of subjects. Severe pain was reported by 8% of university students in the UK  3  .
 

     Non-serious Adverse Events  



 In the 3 controlled studies  1,2,3  (BEXSERO N=2221, control N=2204), non-serious unsolicited adverse events that occurred within 7 days of any dose were reported by 439 (20%) BEXSERO and 197 (9%) control recipients. Unsolicited adverse events that were reported among at least 2% of participants and were more frequently reported in BEXSERO recipients than in control recipients were injection site pain, headache, and injection site induration unresolved within 7 days, and nasopharyngitis.



     Serious Adverse Events  



 Overall, in clinical studies, among 3,058 participants 10 through 25 years of age who received at least 1 dose of BEXSERO, 66 (2.1%) participants reported serious adverse events at any time during the study. In the 3 controlled studies  1,2,3  (BEXSERO N=2716, Control N=2078), serious adverse events within 30 days after any dose were reported in 23 (0.8%) BEXSERO recipients and 10 (0.5%) control recipients.



   6.2 Additional Pre-licensure Safety Experience

  In response to outbreaks of serogroup B meningococcal disease at two universities in the US, BEXSERO was administered as a 2 dose series at least 1 month apart. Information on serious adverse events was collected for a period of 30 days after each dose from 15,351 individuals 16 through 65 years of age who received at least 1 dose. Overall 50 individuals (0.3%) reported serious adverse events, including one event considered related to vaccination, a case of anaphylaxis within 30 minutes following vaccination.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  Adverse event reports received for BEXSERO marketed outside the US are listed below. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate reliably their frequency, or to establish a causal relationship to vaccination. This list includes serious events or events which have suspected causal association to BEXSERO.



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  Blisters at or around the injection site.



   Immune System Disorders:  Allergic reactions (including anaphylactic reactions), rash, eye swelling.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Syncope, vasovagal responses to injection.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   The tip caps of the pre-filled syringes contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals. (  5.3  )



 



   5.1 Preventing and Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate observation and medical treatment should always be readily available in case of an anaphylactic event following the administration of the vaccine.



    5.2 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of BEXSERO. Ensure procedures are in place to avoid injury from falling associated with syncope.



    5.3 Latex



  The tip caps of the pre-filled syringes contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals.



    5.4 Limitation of vaccine effectiveness



  BEXSERO may not protect all vaccine recipients. BEXSERO may not provide protection against all meningococcal serogroup B strains [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.1  )].  



    5.5 Altered Immunocompetence



  Individuals with altered immunocompetence may have reduced immune responses to BEXSERO.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
