<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="biothrax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common (&gt;=10%) local (injection-site) adverse reactions observed in clinical studies were tenderness, pain, erythema, edema, and arm motion limitation. The most common (&gt;=5%) systemic adverse reactions were muscle aches, headache, and fatigue.



   EXCERPT:   The most common (&gt;=10%) local (injection-site) adverse reactions observed in clinical studies were tenderness, pain, erythema, edema, and arm motion limitation. The most common (&gt;=5%) systemic adverse reactions were muscle aches, fatigue, and headache. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Emergent BioSolutions at 1-877-246-8472 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another product and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In an open-label safety study of 15,907 doses of BioThrax administered by the subcutaneous route to approximately 7,000 textile employees, laboratory workers and other at risk individuals, local and systemic reactions were monitored. Over the course of the 5-year study the following local adverse reactions were reported: 24 (0.15% of doses administered) severe local adverse reactions (defined as edema or induration measuring greater than 120 mm in diameter or accompanied by marked limitation of arm motion or marked axillary node tenderness), 150 (0.94% of doses administered) moderate local adverse reactions (edema or induration greater than 30 mm but less than 120 mm in diameter), and 1,373 (8.63% of doses administered) mild local adverse reactions (erythema only or induration measuring less than 30 mm in diameter). Four cases of systemic adverse reactions were reported during the 5-year reporting period (&lt;0.06% of doses administered). These reactions, which were reported to have been transient, included fever, chills, nausea, and general body aches.



 In a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled, and active-controlled multi-center clinical study, [NCT00119067] 1,564 healthy subjects were enrolled. The objective of this study was to evaluate the effect of (1) changing the route of vaccine administration from subcutaneous (SC) to intramuscular (IM), and (2) of reducing the number of doses on the safety and immunogenicity of BioThrax. The dosing schedules and routes studied are provided in Table 1. [See  Clinical Studies (  14  )  ]



            Group A (8SC) (N=259) received BioThrax via the SC route of administration at           Weeks 0, 2, 4, and Months 6, 12, 18 followed by 2 annual boosters (original U.S. licensed           route/schedule). Group A served as the active control in this study.



            Group B (8IM) (N=262) received BioThrax via the IM route of administration at           Weeks 0, 2, 4, and Months 6, 12, 18 followed by 2 annual boosters.



            Group C (COM) (N=782) received BioThrax via the IM route of administration at           Weeks 0, 4 (no Week 2 dose), and Month 6 with various schedules thereafter. (Group C           represents data from 3 randomized groups [Groups D, E, and F] combined for the analysis           through Month 7 because the schedules are identical through the Month 6 dose.)



            Group D (7IM) (N=256) received BioThrax via the IM route of administration at           Weeks 0, 4 (no Week 2 dose), and Months 6, 12, 18 followed by 2 annual boosters.



            Group E (5IM) (N=258) received BioThrax via the IM route of administration at           Weeks 0, 4 (no Week 2 dose), and Months 6, 18 followed by 1 booster dose at           Month 42 (2 year interval).



            Group F (4IM) (N=268) received BioThrax via the IM route of administration at           Weeks 0, 4 (no Week 2 dose), and Month 6 followed by 1 booster dose at           Month 42 (3 year interval).



   Table 1: Vaccination Schedules and Routes Evaluated  




 SC: subcutaneous; IM: intramuscular; V: vaccine, S: saline.   
 *Active Control.            
 ^Subjects randomized to the control group were then re-randomized (1:1) to receive saline by the IM or SC route. The IM and SC placebo groups are combined in analyses.   
  
   Group/Route                Weeks                      Months                    
                            0                          2                          4                          6                          12                         18                         30                         42                          
 Group A (8SC)*             V                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                           
 Group B (8IM)              V                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                           
 Group D (7IM)              V                          S                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                          V                           
 Group E (5IM)              V                          S                          V                          V                          S                          V                          S                          V                           
 Group F (4IM)              V                          S                          V                          V                          S                          S                          S                          V                           
 Placebo^                   S                          S                          S                          S                          S                          S                          S                          S                           
      Subjects were instructed to complete a 14-day post-vaccination diary card after the first 2 doses and a 28-day diary card after the subsequent doses to capture solicited and unsolicited adverse reactions. Adverse reaction data were also collected from in-clinic exams, which were performed prior to, and 15 to 60 minutes after each injection, at 1 to 3 days after each injection, and at 28 days after injections 3 through 8. The mean age, gender ratio, and race distribution were not significantly different across treatment groups among the vaccinated cohort (N=1563). The mean age was 39 years (range 18 to 62 years). Fifty-one percent of participants were female and 49% were male. Seventy-four percent were white, 21% were black and 5% were categorized as "other".
 

 Shown in Table 2 are the rates (percentage) of prospectively defined local and systemic solicited adverse reactions observed in the in-clinic exams for doses 1-4 as well as the rates (percentage) of local and systemic solicited adverse reactions observed in the in-clinic exams for doses 5-8.



 Analysis of injection site (local) adverse reactions by study group was performed after each dose. It was observed that groups receiving BioThrax by the IM route had a statistically significantly lower incidence of any (one or more) local adverse reactions compared to the BioThrax SC route, by dose in the in-clinic data set, in almost all analyses. Injection site adverse reactions, including warmth, tenderness, itching, erythema, induration, edema, and nodule occurred at lower frequencies in participants given BioThrax by the IM route after each dose, in almost all comparisons. However, by dose, the incidence of arm motion limitation was usually higher in each BioThrax IM group compared to the 8SC group (excluding doses where IM groups received a placebo). The incidence of any moderate or severe local adverse reactions was consistently lower in BioThrax IM groups, compared to the 8SC group after each dose. Route of administration did not affect the occurrence of systemic adverse reactions, with the exception of muscle ache (increased incidence in the BioThrax IM groups after most doses). There was no clear pattern for differences in the incidence of any moderate or severe systemic adverse reactions for BioThrax IM groups compared to the 8SC group after each dose. The proportion of participants with severe local or systemic adverse reactions reported by adverse reaction category after each dose was very low (generally &lt;1%).



 Overall, women had a higher incidence of any local adverse reaction than did men, by dose, within BioThrax groups, regardless of the route of administration. Overall, women also had a higher incidence of any systemic adverse reaction than men, within BioThrax groups, regardless of the route of administration. A brief pain or burning sensation, felt immediately after vaccine injection, and distinct from injection site pain, was reported by 45 - 97% of all study participants receiving BioThrax. Reporting frequency and event intensity varied with route of administration and vaccine dose. Up to 11% of subjects rated the brief pain or burning they experienced immediately after vaccine injection as 8 out of 10 or greater. Female participants generally experienced a higher pain scale rating than male participants.



 Eight serious adverse events (SAEs) were reported with 6 subjects and determined to be possibly related to the administration of BioThrax: (1) a case of generalized allergic reaction, (2) a case of ANA positive autoimmune disorder manifesting as a moderate bilateral arthalgia of the metacarpophalangeal (MCP) joints, (3) a right shoulder supraspinatus tendon tear, (4) a case of bilateral pseudotumor cerebri with bilateral disc edema, (5) a case of generalized seizure and hospitalization for evaluation of hydrocephalus and endoscopic fluid ventriculostomy, (6) a case of bilateral ductal carcinoma of the breast. No SAEs were determined by the investigator to be probably or definitely related to administration of BioThrax. The percent of serious adverse events was similar between the BioThrax combined groups (193/1303 or 15%) and the placebo group (38/260 or 15%).



 Out of a total of 51 pregnancies reported in this study, no distinct patterns of infant outcome were seen, with the majority of pregnancies uncomplicated and healthy term infants delivered. Of women who received vaccine within 90 days of the estimated date of conception (n = 14), 2 spontaneous abortions and a first trimester intra-utero fetal death were reported, along with one report of a healthy term infant with mild right clubbed foot abnormality.



   Table 2: Adverse Reactions: In-Clinic Day 0 - 3, Solicited by Dose Number*  




   *  Per-dose, statistical assessment performed on Intent-to-Treat population data. Evaluations performed at 15-60 minutes and 1-3 days following each injection and prior to the next scheduled injection.   
   **  N is the highest number per treatment arm (received at least one dose); denominator (N) varied with dose number due to attrition over time.   
     Subjects received saline (instead of BioThrax) for the Week 2 dose. Placebo dose data for 7IM group is in italics.   
   ?  The two saline groups (SC and IM) were combined.   
   S  Moderate = causes discomfort and interferes with normal daily activities; Severe = incapacitating and completely prevents performing normal daily activities. This is based on the local AE categories of warmth, tenderness, itching, pain, and arm motion limitation.   
   |  Large = an occurrence of induration, erythema, edema, nodule, and bruise with a largest diameter greater than 120 mm.   
     Moderate = causes discomfort and interferes with normal daily activities; Severe = incapacitating and completely prevents performing normal daily activities. This is based on the systemic AE categories of fatigue, muscle ache, headache, and fever.   
  
                            STUDY GROUP                 
                            Group DBioThrax 7IM(BioThrax Doses 1, 3-8)Weeks-0-4-26    Months 12-18-30-42  Placebo  ?  Control SC/IM(Doses 1-8)Weeks-0-2-4-26Months 12-18-30-42  Group ABioThrax 8SC(BioThrax Doses 1-8)Weeks-0-2-4-26Months 12-18-30-42   
 Number of Subjects(N)**    256                        260                        259                         
                            Dose                       Dose                       Dose                        
                            1                          2                          3                          4                          5                          6                          7                          8                          1                          2                          3                          4                          5                          6                          7                          8                          1                          2                          3                          4                          5                          6                          7                          8                           
                            %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                          %                           
 Local Adverse Reactions     
 Presence of any localadverse reaction  60                           23                       68                         68                         69                         77                         76                         73                         22                         22                         19                         27                         25                         29                         25                         18                         81                         89                         80                         84                         81                         84                         84                         92                          
 Warmth                     4                            1                        8                          10                         11                         13                         14                         19                         1                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          1                          1                          29                         41                         32                         39                         34                         40                         51                         49                          
 Tenderness                 46                           7                        51                         47                         41                         44                         44                         48                         6                          8                          7                          10                         6                          7                          7                          4                          64                         72                         48                         65                         53                         57                         61                         63                          
 Itching                    1                            0                        2                          4                          7                          7                          7                          10                         0                          0                          0                          0                          1                          0                          0                          0                          3                          16                         23                         20                         17                         22                         25                         26                          
 Pain                       16                           4                        20                         15                         16                         13                         16                         15                         4                          2                          3                          4                          4                          2                          3                          2                          16                         22                         12                         19                         16                         14                         18                         20                          
 Arm motion limitation      14                           1                        15                         11                         10                         10                         15                         9                          1                          0                          2                          1                          1                          1                          1                          0                          8                          12                         5                          11                         10                         5                          8                          5                           
 Erythema                   15                           10                       20                         30                         35                         48                         40                         37                         11                         12                         7                          13                         14                         17                         14                         11                         53                         64                         57                         65                         64                         64                         68                         71                          
 Induration                 7                            7                        12                         16                         21                         23                         15                         17                         1                          3                          2                          3                          4                          4                          3                          3                          26                         35                         28                         40                         38                         36                         38                         35                          
 Edema                      5                            2                        11                         20                         15                         23                         30                         25                         3                          4                          4                          4                          4                          7                          8                          5                          17                         33                         31                         33                         31                         35                         37                         46                          
 Nodule                     3                            0                        4                          5                          8                          9                          6                          5                          0                          2                          0                          1                          2                          0                          2                          0                          39                         42                         36                         26                         26                         23                         21                         27                          
 Bruise                     5                            4                        5                          3                          2                          4                          3                          2                          4                          5                          1                          4                          3                          5                          5                          4                          6                          7                          6                          6                          3                          6                          5                          6                           
 Presence of anymoderate/severe localadverse reactions  S    5                            1                        8                          7                          4                          5                          6                          4                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          7                          16                         8                          13                         10                         7                          12                         14                          
 Presence of any large localadverse reaction  |    0                            0                        0                          2                          2                          4                          2                          2                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          1                          4                          2                          1                          2                          2                          4                           
 Systemic Adverse Reactions   
 Presence of any systemicadverse reaction  18                           12                       24                         19                         15                         19                         10                         9                          10                         10                         13                         11                         13                         8                          13                         4                          16                         20                         18                         21                         18                         14                         20                         17                          
 Fatigue                    9                            4                        12                         10                         9                          11                         4                          6                          5                          4                          7                          7                          8                          5                          10                         3                          9                          12                         8                          12                         12                         10                         10                         13                          
 Muscle ache                8                            4                        13                         6                          5                          5                          3                          5                          2                          2                          3                          4                          5                          3                          1                          1                          5                          8                          4                          5                          4                          3                          9                          5                           
 Headache                   6                            6                        9                          7                          8                          8                          5                          4                          4                          6                          5                          4                          7                          4                          6                          1                          7                          9                          8                          11                         7                          5                          9                          2                           
 Fever &gt;100.4 degrees F     0                            0                        0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          1                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                           
 Tender/painful axillaryadenopathy  0                            0                        0                          1                          1                          1                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          0                          1                          0                          1                          2                          1                          1                          0                          1                          0                           
 Presence of anymoderate/severe systemicadverse reactions      2                            2                        6                          3                          3                          5                          4                          3                          1                          2                          2                          1                          3                          1                          2                          1                          2                          5                          4                          3                          3                          2                          3                          2                           
      Solicited and unsolicited adverse reactions observed from Day 0 through month 43 at a higher frequency (by at least 5%) in the BioThrax groups (IM and SC) as compared to the placebo (P) group were: headache (70.4% IM, 78.4% SC, 68.1% P); myalgia (72% IM, 76.1% SC, 50% P); and fatigue (70.1% IM, 76.8% SC, 60.8% P).
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events, not previously listed in Section 6.1, have been identified during post-approval use of BioThrax. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The reports included below are listed due to one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the event, (2) number of reports, or (3) strength of causal relationship to the drug.



 *  *      Lymphadenopathy 
    Blood and lymphatic system disorders  
   *  *      Nausea 
    Gastrointestinal Disorders  
   *  *      Allergic reactions (including anaphylaxis, angioedema, rash, urticaria, pruritus, erythema multiforme, anaphylactoid reaction, and Stevens Johnson syndrome) 
    Immune system disorders  
   *  *      Paresthesia syncope, dizziness, tremor, ulnar nerve neuropathy 
    Nervous system disorders  
   *  *      Arthralgia, arthropathy, myalgia, rhabdomyolysis, alopecia 
    Musculoskeletal, connective tissue, and bone disorders  
   *  *      Malaise, pain, cellulitis, flu-like symptoms 
    General disorders and administration site conditions  
   *  *      Insomnia 
    Psychiatric disorders  
   *  *      Pruritis, rash, urticaria 
    Skin and Subcutaneous disorders  
   *  *      Flushing 
    Vascular disorders  
    Infrequent reports were also received of multisystem disorders defined as chronic symptoms involving at least two of the following three categories: fatigue, mood-cognition, and musculoskeletal system.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  The stopper of the vial contains dry natural rubber and may cause allergic reactions to patients with a possible history of latex sensitivity. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Pregnancy: Avoid use in pregnancy unless the potential benefit outweighs the potential risk to the fetus (  5.3  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Acute allergic reactions, including anaphylaxis, have occurred with BioThrax. Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine. [See Contraindications (  4  )  ]



    5.2 Latex



  The stopper of the vial contains dry natural rubber and may cause allergic reactions to patients with a possible history of latex sensitivity.



    5.3 Pregnancy



  BioThrax can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus. Weigh the potential benefits of vaccination against the potential risk to the fetus. [See Use in Specific Populations (  8  ), Pregnancy (  8.1  )  ]



 Pregnant women should not be vaccinated against anthrax unless the potential benefits of vaccination have been determined to outweigh the potential risk to the fetus. Results of a large observational study that examined the rate of birth defects among 37,140 infants born to U.S. military service women who received anthrax vaccine in pregnancy between 1998 and 2004 showed that birth defects were slightly more common in first trimester-exposed infants (odds ratio = 1.18, 95% confidence interval: 0.997, 1.41) when compared with infants of women vaccinated outside of the first trimester and compared to unvaccinated women.  1  While the increased birth defect rates were not statistically significant when compared with infants born to women vaccinated outside of pregnancy, pregnant women should not be vaccinated against anthrax unless the potential benefits of vaccination have been determined to outweigh the potential risk to the fetus.



 The effect of BioThrax on embryo-fetal and pre-weaning development was evaluated in a developmental toxicity study using pregnant rabbits. One group of rabbits was administered BioThrax twice prior to gestation and during the period of organogenesis (gestation day 7). A second group of rabbits was administered BioThrax twice prior to gestation and on gestation day 17. BioThrax was administered at 0.5 ml/rabbit/occasion, by intramuscular injection. No adverse effects on mating, fertility, pregnancy, parturition, lactation, embryo-fetal or pre-weaning development were observed. There were no vaccine-related fetal malformations or other evidence of teratogenesis noted in this study.



    5.4 History of Anthrax Disease



  History of anthrax disease may increase the potential for severe local adverse reactions.



    5.5 Altered Immunocompetence



  If BioThrax is administered to immunocompromised persons, including those receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the immune response may be diminished.



    5.6 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with BioThrax may not protect all individuals.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
