<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bivalirudin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reaction was bleeding (28%). Other adverse reactions (incidence &gt;0.5%) were headache, thrombocytopenia and fever. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact The Medicines Company at 1-800-264-4662 or the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Bleeding  



 In 6010 patients undergoing PCI treated in the REPLACE-2 trial, Bivalirudin patients exhibited statistically significantly lower rates of bleeding, transfusions, and thrombocytopenia as noted in  Table 2  .



 Table 2: Major Hematologic Outcomes REPLACE-2 Study (Safety Population) 
   1  GPIs were administered to 7.2% of patients in the Bivalirudin with provisional GPI group  2  Defined as the occurence of any of the following: intracranial bleeding, retroperitoneal bleeding, a transfusion of &gt;=2 units of blood/blood products, a fall in hemoglobin &gt; 4g/dL, whether of not bleeding site is identified, spontaneous or non-spontaneous blood loss with a decrease in hemoglobin &gt;3 g/dL  3  Defined as observed bleeding that does not meet the criteria for major hemorrhage  4  TIMI major bleeding is defined as intracranial, or a fall in adjusted Hgb &gt;5g/dL or Hct of &gt;15%: TIMI minor bleeding is defined as a fall in adjusted Hgb of 3 to &lt;5 g/dL or a fall in adjusted Hct of 9 to &lt;15%, with a bleeding site such as hematuria, hematemesis, hematomas, retroperitoneal bleeding or a decrease in Hgb of &gt;4 g/dL with no bleeding site  5  If &lt;100,000 and &gt;25% reduction from baseline, or &lt;50,000   
  
                                   Bivalirudin with"provisional" GPI  1  (n=2914)      HEPARIN +GPI(n=2987)           p-value          
   Protocol defined major hemorrhage  2  (%)              2.3%                       4.0%                    &lt;0.001          
   Protocol defined minor hemorrhage  3  (%)              13.6%                      25.8%                   &lt;0.001          
   TIMI defined bleeding  4                                                                                   
   - Major                                 0.6%                       0.9%                    0.259           
   - Minor                                 1.3%                       2.9%                    &lt;0.001          
   Non-access site bleeding                                                                                   
   - Retroperitoneal bleeding              0.2%                       0.5%                    0.069           
   - Intracranial bleeding                 &lt;0.1%                      0.1%                     1.0            
   Access site bleeding                                                                                       
   - Sheath site bleeding                  0.9%                       2.4%                    &lt;0.001          
   Thrombocytopenia  5                                                                                        
   &lt;100,000                                0.7%                       1.7%                    &lt;0.001          
   &lt;50,000                                 0.3%                       0.6%                    0.039           
   Transfusions                                                                                               
    - RBC                                  1.3%                       1.9%                     0.08           
    - Platelets                            0.3%                       0.6%                    0.095           
          In 4312 patients undergoing PTCA for treatment of unstable angina in 2 randomized, double-blind studies comparing Bivalirudin to heparin, Bivalirudin patients exhibited lower rates of major bleeding and lower requirements for blood transfusions. The incidence of major bleeding is presented in  Table 3  . The incidence of major bleeding was lower in the Bivalirudin group than in the heparin group.
 

 Table 3: Major Bleeding and Transfusions in BAT Trial (all patients) 1 
   1  No monitoring of ACT (or PTT) was done after a target ACT was achieved.  2  Major hemorrhage was defined as the occurence of any of the following, intracranial bleeding, retroperitoneal bleeding, clinically overt bleeding with a decrease in hemoglobin &gt;=3 g/dL or leading to a transfusion of &gt;=2 units of blood. This table includes data from the entire hospitalization period.   
  
                                                  Bivalirudin(n=2161)              Heparin(n=2151)          
 No. (%) Patients with Major hemorrhage  2              79 (3.7)                       199 (9.3)             
      - with &gt;=3 g/dL fall in Hgb                      41 (1.9)                       124 (5.8)             
      - with &gt;=5 g/dL fall in Hgb                      14 (0.6)                       47 (2.2)              
      - retroperitoneal bleeding                        5 (0.2)                       15 (0.7)              
      - intracranial bleeding                          1 (&lt;0.1)                        2 (0.1)              
      - Required transfusions                          43 (2.0)                       123 (5.7)             
         In the AT-BAT study, of the 51 patients with HIT/HITTS, 1 patient who did not undergo PCI had major bleeding during CABG on the day following angiography. Nine patients had minor bleeding (mostly due to access site bleeding), and 2 patients developed thrombocytopenia.
 

   Other Adverse Reactions  



 Adverse reactions, other than bleeding, observed in clinical trials were similar between the Bivalirudin treated patients and the control groups.



 Adverse reactions (related adverse events ) seen in clinical studies in patients undergoing PCI and PTCA are shown in  Tables 4  and  5  .



 Table 4: Most Frequent (&gt;=0.2%) Treatment-related Adverse Events (reactions) (through 30 days) in the REPLACE-2 Safety Population 
   1    Note: A patient could have more than one event in any category.Abbreviation: AE = adverse event.   
  
                                                 Bivalirudin with"provisional" GPI  1  (n=2914)      Heparin+GPI(n=2987)     
 Patients with at least one treatment-related AE        n              (%)              n              (%)         
 78                                                (2.7)            115            (3.9)        
                                                                                                                
 Thrombocytopenia                                    9             (0.3)             30            (1.0)        
 Nausea                                              15            (0.5)             7             (0.2)        
 Hypotension                                         7             (0.2)             11            (0.4)        
 Angina pectoris                                     5             (0.2)             12            (0.4)        
 Headache                                            6             (0.2)             5             (0.2)        
 Injection site pain                                 3             (0.1)             8             (0.3)        
 Nausea and vomiting                                 2             (0.1)             6             (0.2)        
 Vomiting                                            3             (0.1)             5             (0.2)        
          Table 5: Adverse Events Other Than Bleeding Occurring In &gt;= 5% Of Patients In Either Treatment Group In BAT Trial 
   Event                                          Treatment Groups          
   BIVALIRUDIN(n=2161)                            HEPARIN(n=2151)           
   Number of Patients (%)                   
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
 Hypotension                                          262 (12)                        371 (17)              
 Hypertension                                         135 (6)                         115 (5)               
 Bradycardia                                          118 (5)                         164 (8)               
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
 Nausea                                               318 (15)                        347 (16)              
 Vomiting                                             138 (6)                         169 (8)               
 Dyspepsia                                            100 (5)                         111 (5)               
   Genitourinary                                                                                            
 Urinary retention                                     89 (4)                          98 (5)               
   Miscellaneous                                                                                            
 Back pain                                            916 (42)                        944 (44)              
 Pain                                                 330 (15)                        358 (17)              
 Headache                                             264 (12)                        225 (10)              
 Injection site pain                                  174 (8)                         274 (13)              
 Insomnia                                             142 (7)                         139 (6)               
 Pelvic pain                                          130 (6)                         169 (8)               
 Anxiety                                              127 (6)                         140 (7)               
 Abdominal pain                                       103 (5)                         104 (5)               
 Fever                                                103 (5)                         108 (5)               
 Nervousness                                          102 (5)                          87 (4)               
         Serious, non-bleeding adverse events were experienced in 2% of 2161 Bivalirudin-treated patients and 2% of 2151 heparin-treated patients. The following individual serious non-bleeding adverse events were rare (&gt;0.1% to &lt;1%) and similar in incidence between Bivalirudin- and heparin-treated patients. These events are listed by body system:  Body as a Whole  : fever, infection, sepsis;  Cardiovascular  : hypotension, syncope, vascular anomaly, ventricular fibrillation;  Nervous  : cerebral ischemia, confusion, facial paralysis;  Respiratory  : lung edema;  Urogenital  : kidney failure, oliguria. In the BAT trial, there was no causality assessment for adverse events.
 

   6.2 Immunogenicity/Re-Exposure

  In  in vitro  studies, Bivalirudin exhibited no platelet aggregation response against sera from patients with a history of HIT/HITTS.



 Among 494 subjects who received Bivalirudin in clinical trials and were tested for antibodies, 2 subjects had treatment-emergent positive bivalirudin antibody tests. Neither subject demonstrated clinical evidence of allergic or anaphylactic reactions and repeat testing was not performed. Nine additional patients who had initial positive tests were negative on repeat testing.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  Because postmarketing adverse reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Bivalirudin: fatal bleeding; hypersensitivity and allergic reactions including reports of anaphylaxis; lack of anticoagulant effect; thrombus formation during PCI with and without intracoronary brachytherapy, including reports of fatal outcomes.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Bleeding events: Hemorrhage can occur at any site. Discontinue Bivalirudin for an unexplained fall in blood pressure or hematocrit. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Coronary artery brachytherapy: Risk of thrombus formation, including fatal outcomes, in gamma brachytherapy. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Bleeding Events



  Although most bleeding associated with the use of Bivalirudin in PCI/PTCA occurs at the site of arterial puncture, hemorrhage can occur at any site. An unexplained fall in blood pressure or hematocrit should lead to serious consideration of a hemorrhagic event and cessation of Bivalirudin administration [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Bivalirudin should be used with caution in patients with disease states associated with an increased risk of bleeding.



    5.2 Coronary Artery Brachytherapy



  An increased risk of thrombus formation, including fatal outcomes, has been associated with the use of Bivalirudin in gamma brachytherapy.



 If a decision is made to use Bivalirudin during brachytherapy procedures, maintain meticulous catheter technique, with frequent aspiration and flushing, paying special attention to minimizing conditions of stasis within the catheter or vessels [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
