<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bivigam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions observed in clinical trial subjects receiving BIVIGAM were vomiting and dehydration in one subject.



 The most common adverse reactions to BIVIGAM (reported in more than equal to 5% of clinical study subjects) were headache, fatigue, infusion site reaction, nausea, sinusitis, blood pressure increased, diarrhea, dizziness, and lethargy.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions to BIVIGAM (reported more than equal to 5% of clinical study subjects) were headache, fatigue, infusion site reaction, nausea, sinusitis, blood pressure increased, diarrhea, dizziness, and lethargy. [  6  ]  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Kedrion Biopharma Inc. at 1-800-XXX-XXXX or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another product and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In a multicenter, open-label, non-randomized clinical trial, 63 subjects with PI, on regular IGIV replacement therapy, received doses of BIVIGAM ranging from 254 to 1029 mg/kg (median dose 462.8 mg/kg) every 3 weeks or 4 weeks for up to 12 months (mean 317.3 days; range 66 386 days) (see  Clinical Studies [14]  ). The use of pre-medication was discouraged; however, if subjects required pre-medication (antipyretic, antihistamine, or antiemetic agent) for recurrent reactions to immune globulins, they were allowed to continue those medications for this trial. Of the 746 infusions administered, 41 (65%) subjects received premedication prior to 415 (56%) infusions.



 Fifty-nine subjects (94%) had an adverse reaction at some time during the study. The proportion of subjects who had at least one adverse reaction was the same for both the 3- and 4-week cycles. The most common adverse reactions observed in this clinical trial were headache (32 subjects, 51%), sinusitis (24 subjects, 38%), fatigue (18 subjects, 29%), upper respiratory tract infection (16 subjects, 25%), diarrhea (13 subjects, 21%), cough (14 subjects, 22%), bronchitis (12 subjects, 19%), pyrexia (12 subjects, 19%), and nausea (9 subjects, 14%).



 Adverse reactions (ARs) are those occurring during or within 72 hours after the end of an infusion. In this study, the upper bound of the 1-sided 95% confidence interval for the proportion of BIVIGAM infusions with one or more temporally associated adverse reactions was 31%. The total number of adverse reactions was 431 (a rate of 0.58 ARs per infusion).



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions (ARs) (within 72 hours after the end of a BIVIGAM infusion) in &gt;=5% Subjects) 
   ARs                               
 Headache                            
 Fatigue                             
 Infusion Site Reaction              
 Nausea                              
 Sinusitis                           
 Blood PressureIncreased             
 Diarrhea                            
 Dizziness                           
 Lethargy                            
 Back Pain                           
 Blood Pressure DiastolicDecreased   
 Fibromyalgia                        
 Migraine                            
 Myalgia                             
 Pharyngolaryngeal Pain              
      Seven subjects (11.1%) experienced 11 serious ARs. Two of these were related serious ARs (vomiting and dehydration) that occurred in one subject.
 

 One subject withdrew from the study due to ARs related to BIVIGAM (lethargy, headache, tachycardia and pruritus).



 All 63 subjects enrolled in this study had a negative direct antiglobulin (Coombs) test at baseline. During the study, no subjects showed clinical evidence of hemolytic anemia.



 No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have been associated with the use of BIVIGAM. During the clinical trial no subjects tested positive for infection due to human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C virus (HCV). There was a single positive finding for parvovirus (B19 virus) during the study. This subject came in contact with acute B19 virus from working at a school greeting children where a child was reported to have symptomatic Fifth's disease. There was no cluster (no other cases in other subjects) of B19 virus transmission with the IGIV batch concerned.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure. The following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during the post-approval use of IGIV products:  



     



 *  Respiratory: Apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS), Transfusion Associated Lung Injury (TRALI), cyanosis, hypoxemia, pulmonary edema, dyspnea, bronchospasm. 
 *  Cardiovascular: Cardiac arrest, thromboembolism, vascular collapse, hypotension. 
 *  Neurological: Coma, loss of consciousness, seizures, tremor. 
 *  Integumentary: Stevens-Johnson syndrome, epidermolysis, erythema multiforme, bullous dermatitis. 
 *  Hematologic: Pancytopenia, leukopenia, hemolysis, positive direct antiglobulin (Coombs) test. 
 *  General/Body as a Whole: Pyrexia, rigors. 
 *  Musculoskeletal: Back pain. 
 *  Gastrointestinal: Hepatic dysfunction, abdominal pain. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION AND ACUTE RENAL FAILURE  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin (IGIV) products, including BIVIGAM. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors. (see Warnings and Precautions [5.1], Patient Counseling Information [17.2]). 
 *  Use of Immune Globulin Intravenous (IGIV) products, particularly those containing sucrose, has been reported to be associated with renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death 1,2. Patients at risk of acute renal failure include those with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, advanced age (above 65 years of age), volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or receiving known nephrotoxic drugs (see Warnings and Precautions [5.3]).                     
 *  Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose. BIVIGAM does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, renal dysfunction or renal failure, administer BIVIGAM at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity (see Dosage and Administration [2.2,2.3], Warnings and Precautions [5.3]). 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION AND ACUTE RENAL FAILURE  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products, including BIVIGAM. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur with the administration of Immune Globulin Intravenous (Human) (IGIV) products in predisposed patients. [5.3] 
 *  Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose. BIVIGAM does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, renal dysfunction or renal failure, administer BIVIGAM at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity.[2.3,5.3] 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  Thrombotic events have occurred in patients receiving IGIV therapy. Monitor patients with known risk factors for thrombotic events; consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity for those at risk of hyperviscosity. [  5.1  ,  5.4  ] 
 *  IgA deficient patients with antibodies against IgA are at greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. Have medications such as epinephrine available immediately to treat any acute severe hypersensitivity reactions. [  4,    5.2  ] 
 *  Monitor renal function, including blood urea nitrogen (BUN), serum creatinine, and urine output in patients at risk of developing acute renal failure. [  5.3,    5.9  ] 
 *  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia or pseudohyponatremia can occur in patients receiving IGIV therapy. [  5.4  ] 
 *  Aseptic meningitis syndrome (AMS) has been reported with IGIV treatments, especially with high doses or rapid infusion. [  5.5  ] 
 *  Hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to treatment with IGIV products. Monitor patients for hemolysis and hemolytic anemia. [  5.6  ] 
 *  Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions (Transfusion-related acute lung injury [TRALI]). If transfusion-related acute lung injury is suspected, test the product and patient for antineutrophil antibodies. [  5.7  ] 
 *  Because this product is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. [  5.8  ] 
    
 

   5.1 Thrombosis



  Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products, including BIVIGAM.4,5,6 Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors



 Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer BIVIGAM at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity (see  Boxed Warning,    Dosage and Administration [2.3]  ,  Patient Counseling Information [17.2]  ).



    5.2 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur with IGIV products, including BIVIGAM. In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue BIVIGAM infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment. Medications such as epinephrine should be available for immediate treatment of acute hypersensitivity reactions.



 BIVIGAM contains trace amounts of IgA (&lt;= 200 micrograms per milliliter) (see  Description [11]  ). Patients with known antibodies to IgA may have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. BIVIGAM is contraindicated in IgA deficient patients with antibodies against IgA and a history of hypersensitivity reaction (see  Contraindications [4]  ).



    5.3 Acute Renal Dysfunction and Acute Renal Failure



  Acute renal dysfunction/failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death1,2 may occur upon use of human IGIV products. Ensure that patients are not volume depleted before administering BIVIGAM. Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure.2 Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of BIVIGAM and at appropriate intervals thereafter. If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuing BIVIGAM (see  Patient Counseling Information [17.1]  ). In patients who are at risk of developing renal dysfunction, because of pre-existing renal insufficiency or predisposition to acute renal failure (such as diabetes mellitus, hypovolemia, overweight, use of concomitant nephrotoxic medicinal products or age of more than 65 years), administer BIVIGAM at the minimum infusion rate practicable (see  Dosage and Administration [2.3]  ).



    5.4 Hyperproteinemia, Increased Serum Viscosity, and Hyponatremia



  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia may occur in patients receiving IGIV therapy, including BIVIGAM. It is critical to clinically distinguish true hyponatremia from a pseudohyponatremia that is associated with or causally related to hyperproteinemia with concomitant decreased calculated serum osmolality or elevated osmolar gap, because treatment aimed at decreasing serum free water in patients with pseudohyponatremia may lead to volume depletion, a further increase in serum viscosity, and a possible predisposition to thrombotic events.



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



  AMS may occur infrequently with IGIV treatments including BIVIGAM. AMS usually begins within several hours to 2 days following IGIV treatment. Discontinuation of IGIV treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae.  7,8,9  



 AMS is characterized by the following signs and symptoms: severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea, and vomiting (see  Patient Counseling Information [17.3]  ). Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies frequently reveal pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per cubic millimeter, predominantly from the granulocytic series, and elevated protein levels up to several hundred mg/dL, but negative culture results. Conduct a thorough neurological examination on patients exhibiting such signs and symptoms, including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis.



 AMS may occur more frequently in association with high doses (2 g/kg) and/or rapid infusion of IGIV.



    5.6 Hemolysis



  IGIV products, including BIVIGAM, may contain blood group antibodies that can act as hemolysins and induce in vivo coating of red blood cells (RBCs) with immunoglobulin, causing a positive direct antiglobulin reaction and, rarely, hemolysis.  10,11,12  Delayed hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to IGIV therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration,13 and acute hemolysis, consistent with intravascular hemolysis, has been reported.



 Monitor patients for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis (see  Patient Counseling Information [17.4]  ). If these are present after BIVIGAM infusion, perform appropriate confirmatory laboratory testing. If transfusion is indicated for patients who develop hemolysis with clinically compromising anemia after receiving IGIV, perform adequate cross-matching to avoid exacerbating on-going hemolysis.



    5.7 Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Noncardiogenic pulmonary edema may occur in patients following IGIV treatment  14  including BIVIGAM. TRALI is characterized by severe respiratorydistress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function, and fever. Symptoms typically appear within 1 to 6 hours following treatment.



 Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions. If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies in both the product and the patient s serum (see  Patient Counseling Information [17.5]  ).



 TRALI may be managed using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



    5.8 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because BIVIGAM is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent.



 No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have been associated with the use of BIVIGAM. All infections suspected by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Biotest Pharmaceuticals Corporation at



 1-800-458-4244. Before prescribing BIVIGAM, the physician should discuss the risks and benefits of its use with the patient (see  Patient Counseling Information [17.6]  ).



    5.9 Monitoring Laboratory Tests



    *  Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of BIVIGAM and at appropriate intervals thereafter. 
 *  Because of the potentially increased risk of thrombosis with IGIV treatment, consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. 
 *  If signs and/or symptoms of hemolysis are present after an infusion of BIVIGAM, perform appropriate laboratory testing for confirmation. 
 *  If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies in both the product and patient s serum. 
       5.10 Interference with Laboratory Tests
 

  After infusion of immunoglobulin, the transitory rise of the various passively transferred antibodies in the patient s blood may yield positive serological testing results, with the potential for misleading interpretation. Passive transmission of antibodies to erythrocyte antigens (e.g., A, B, and D) may cause a positive direct or indirect antiglobulin (Coombs) test.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
