<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="boniva0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions that appear in other sections of the labeling include:



 *  Hypocalcemia and Mineral Metabolism [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Anaphylactic Reaction [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Renal Impairment [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Tissue Damage Related to Inappropriate Drug Administration [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Osteonecrosis of the Jaw [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Musculoskeletal Pain [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Atypical Subtrochanteric and Diaphyseal Femoral Fractures [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;5%) are arthralgia, back pain, and abdominal pain. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Quarterly Intravenous Injection -  



 In a 1-year, double-blind, multicenter study comparing BONIVA Injection administered intravenously as 3 mg every 3 months to BONIVA 2.5 mg daily oral tablet in women with postmenopausal osteoporosis, the overall safety and tolerability profiles of the two dosing regimens were similar. The incidence of serious adverse reactions was 8.0% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and 7.5% in the BONIVA Injection 3 mg once every 3 months group. The percentage of patients who withdrew from treatment due to adverse reactions was approximately 6.7% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and 8.5% in the BONIVA Injection 3 mg every 3 months group.    Table 1    lists the adverse reactions reported in greater than 2% of patients.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions With an Incidence of at Least 2% in Patients Treated with BONIVA Injection (3 mg once every 3 months) or BONIVA Daily Oral Tablet (2.5 mg) 
 Body System/Adverse Reaction                        BONIVA2.5 mg Daily (Oral)%(n=465)  BONIVA3 mg every 3 months (Intravenous)%(n=469)   
  
   Infections and Infestations                                                                              
   Influenza                                                     8                          5               
   Nasopharyngitis                                               6                          3               
   Cystitis                                                      3                          2               
   Gastroenteritis                                               3                          2               
   Urinary Tract Infection                                       3                          3               
   Bronchitis                                                    3                          2               
   Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                             3                          1               
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
   Abdominal Pain                                                6                          5               
   Dyspepsia                                                     4                          4               
   Nausea                                                        4                          2               
   Constipation                                                  4                          3               
   Diarrhea                                                      2                          3               
   Gastritis                                                     2                          2               
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                           
   Arthralgia                                                    9                         10               
   Back Pain                                                     8                          7               
   Localized Osteoarthritis                                      2                          2               
   Pain in Extremity                                             2                          3               
   Myalgia                                                       1                          3               
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
   Dizziness                                                     3                          2               
   Headache                                                      3                          4               
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                                      3                          1               
   Depression                                                    2                          1               
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                           
   Influenza-like Illness                                        1                          5               
   Fatigue                                                       1                          3               
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                   
   Rash                                                          3                          2               
             Acute Phase Reaction-like Events  
 

 Symptoms consistent with acute phase reaction (APR) have been reported with intravenous bisphosphonate use. The overall incidence of patients with APR-like events was higher in the intravenous treatment group (4% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily oral tablet group vs. 10% in the BONIVA Injection 3 mg once every 3 months group). These incidence rates are based upon reporting of any of 33 potential APR-like symptoms within 3 days of an intravenous dose and lasting 7 days or less. In most cases, no specific treatment was required and the symptoms subsided within 24 to 48 hours.



     Injection Site Reactions  



 Local reactions at the injection site, such as redness or swelling, were observed at a higher incidence in patients treated with BONIVA Injection 3 mg every 3 months (1.7%; 8/469) than in patients treated with placebo injections (0.2%; 1/465). In most cases, the reaction was of mild to moderate severity.



     Daily Oral Tablet -  



 The safety of BONIVA 2.5 mg once daily in the treatment and prevention of postmenopausal osteoporosis was assessed in 3577 patients aged 41 - 82 years. The duration of the trials was 2 to 3 years, with 1134 patients exposed to placebo and 1140 exposed to BONIVA 2.5 mg. Patients with pre-existing gastrointestinal disease and concomitant use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, proton pump inhibitors and H2 antagonists were included in these clinical trials. All patients received 500 mg calcium plus 400 international units vitamin D supplementation daily.



 The incidence of all-cause mortality was 1% in the placebo group and 1.2% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group. The incidence of serious adverse reactions was 20% in the placebo group and 23% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily oral tablet group. The percentage of patients who withdrew from treatment due to adverse reactions was approximately 17% in both the placebo group and the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily oral tablet group.    Table 2    lists adverse reactions from the Treatment and Prevention Studies reported in greater than or equal to 2% of patients and in more patients treated with BONIVA 2.5 mg daily oral tablet than patients treated with placebo.



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence greater than or equal to 2% and in More Patients Treated with BONIVA 2.5 mg Daily Oral Tablet than in Patients Treated with Placebo in the Osteoporosis Treatment and Prevention Studies 
 Body System                                 Placebo%(n=1134)             BONIVA 2.5 mg daily%(n=1140)      
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Back Pain                                        12                                 14                   
   Pain in Extremity                                6                                   8                   
   Asthenia                                         2                                   4                   
   Allergic Reaction                                2                                   3                   
   Digestive System                                                                                         
   Dyspepsia                                        10                                 12                   
   Diarrhea                                         5                                   7                   
   Tooth Disorder                                   2                                   4                   
   Vomiting                                         2                                   3                   
   Gastritis                                        2                                   2                   
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                                   
   Myalgia                                          5                                   6                   
   Joint Disorder                                   3                                   4                   
   Arthritis                                        3                                   3                   
   Nervous System                                                                                           
   Headache                                         6                                   7                   
   Dizziness                                        3                                   4                   
   Vertigo                                          3                                   3                   
   Respiratory System                                                                                       
   Upper Respiratory Infection                      33                                 34                   
   Bronchitis                                       7                                  10                   
   Pneumonia                                        4                                   6                   
   Pharyngitis                                      2                                   3                   
   Urogenital System                                                                                        
   Urinary Tract Infection                          4                                   6                   
             Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions  
 

 The incidence of selected gastrointestinal adverse reactions in the placebo and BONIVA 2.5 mg daily groups were: dyspepsia (10% vs. 12%), diarrhea (5% vs. 7%), and abdominal pain (5% vs. 6%).



     Musculoskeletal Adverse Reactions  



 The incidence of selected musculoskeletal adverse reactions in the placebo and BONIVA 2.5 mg daily groups were: back pain (12% vs. 14%), arthralgia (14% vs. 14%) and myalgia (5% vs. 6%).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of BONIVA Injection. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Hypersensitivity  : Allergic reactions including anaphylaxis with fatalities, angioedema, asthma exacerbation, bronchospasm, rash, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiforme, and dermatitis bullous  [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



   Hypocalcemia  : Hypocalcemia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



   Renal Toxicity  : Acute renal failure  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw  : Osteonecrosis of the jaw  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



   Musculoskeletal Pain  : Bone, joint, or muscle pain (musculoskeletal pain), described as severe or incapacitating  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  .



   Atypical Femoral Shaft Fracture  : Atypical, low-energy, or low-trauma fractures of the femoral shaft  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ].  



   Eye Inflammation  : Iritis and uveitis. In some cases with other bisphosphonates, these events did not resolve until the bisphosphonate was discontinued.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hypocalcemia can worsen. Correct hypocalcemia prior to use.Adequately supplement patients with calcium and vitamin D (  5.1  ) 
 *   Anaphylaxis , including fatal events, has been reported. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Renal Toxicity may be greater in patients with underlying renal impairment. Do not administer BONIVA injection to patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min). Monitor serum creatinine prior to each dose. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Tissue Damage with Inappropriate Drug Administration can occur. Do not administer BONIVA Injection intra-arterially or paravenously. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ) has been reported. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Severe Bone, Joint, and/or Muscle Pain may occur, consider discontinuing use if symptoms occur. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Atypical Femur Fractures have been reported. Patients with new thigh or groin pain should be evaluated to rule out a femoral fracture. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypocalcemia and Mineral Metabolism



  BONIVA Injection may cause a decrease in serum calcium values. Treat hypocalcemia, hypovitaminosis D, and other disturbances of bone and mineral metabolism before starting BONIVA Injection therapy.



 Adequate intake of calcium and vitamin D is important in all patients. It is recommended that patients receive supplemental calcium and vitamin D if dietary intake is inadequate.



    5.2 Anaphylactic Reaction



  Cases of anaphylaxis, including fatal events, have been reported in patients treated with BONIVA Injection.



 Appropriate medical support and monitoring measures should be readily available when BONIVA Injection is administered. If anaphylactic or other severe hypersensitivity/allergic reactions occur, immediately discontinue the injection and initiate appropriate treatment.



    5.3 Renal Impairment



  Treatment with intravenous bisphosphonates has been associated with renal toxicity manifested as deterioration in renal function and acute renal failure. Although no cases of acute renal failure were observed in controlled clinical trials in which intravenous BONIVA was administered as a 15- to 30-second bolus, acute renal failure has been reported postmarketing. Do not administer BONIVA Injection to patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min).



 Obtain serum creatinine prior to each BONIVA Injection. After BONIVA Injection, assess renal function, as clinically appropriate, in patients with concomitant diseases or taking medications that have the potential for adverse effects on the kidney. BONIVA Injection should be withheld in patients with renal deterioration.



    5.4 Tissue Damage Related to Inappropriate Drug Administration



  BONIVA Injection must only be administered intravenously. Care must be taken not to administer BONIVA Injection intra-arterially or paravenously as this could lead to tissue damage.



 Do not administer BONIVA Injection by any other route of administration. The safety and efficacy of BONIVA Injection following non-intravenous routes of administration have not been established.



    5.5 Osteonecrosis of the Jaw



   Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ) has been reported in patients treated with bisphosphonates, including BONIVA Injection. Most cases have been in cancer patients treated with intravenous bisphosphonates undergoing dental procedures. Some cases have occurred in patients with postmenopausal osteoporosis treated with either oral or intravenous bisphosphonates. A routine oral examination should be performed by the prescriber prior to initiation of bisphosphonate treatment. Consider a dental examination with appropriate preventive dentistry prior to treatment with bisphosphonates in patients with a history of concomitant risk factors (e.g., cancer, chemotherapy, angiogenesis inhibitors, radiotherapy, corticosteroids, poor oral hygiene, pre-existing dental disease or infection, anemia, coagulopathy). Concomitant administration of drugs associated with ONJ may increase the risk of developing ONJ. The risk of ONJ may increase with duration of exposure to bisphosphonates.  



 While on treatment, patients with concomitant risk factors should avoid invasive dental procedures if possible. For patients who develop ONJ while on bisphosphonate therapy, dental surgery may exacerbate the condition. For patients requiring dental procedures, there are no data available to suggest whether discontinuation of bisphosphonate treatment reduces the risk of ONJ. The clinical judgment of the treating physician should guide the management plan of each patient based on individual benefit/risk assessment [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.6 Musculoskeletal Pain



  Severe and occasionally incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain has been reported in patients taking BONIVA and other bisphosphonates [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ]. The time to onset of symptoms varied from one day to several months after starting the drug. Most patients had relief of symptoms after stopping the bisphosphonate. A subset of patients had recurrence of symptoms when rechallenged with the same drug or another bisphosphonate. Discontinue BONIVA if severe symptoms develop.



    5.7 Atypical Subtrochanteric and Diaphyseal Femoral Fractures



  Atypical, low-energy, or low-trauma fractures of the femoral shaft have been reported in bisphosphonate-treated patients. These fractures can occur anywhere in the femoral shaft from just below the lesser trochanter to above the supracondylar flare and are transverse or short oblique in orientation without evidence of comminution. Causality has not been established as these fractures also occur in osteoporotic patients who have not been treated with bisphosphonates.



 Atypical femur fractures most commonly occur with minimal or no trauma to the affected area. They may be bilateral and many patients report prodromal pain in the affected area, usually presenting as dull, aching thigh pain, weeks to months before a complete fracture occurs. A number of reports note that patients were also receiving treatment with glucocorticoids (e.g., prednisone) at the time of fracture.



 Any patient with a history of bisphosphonate exposure who presents with thigh or groin pain should be suspected of having an atypical fracture and should be evaluated to rule out an incomplete femur fracture. Patients presenting with an atypical fracture should also be assessed for symptoms and signs of fracture in the contralateral limb. Interruption of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered, pending a risk/benefit assessment, on an individual basis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
