<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="boniva1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (greater than 5%) are back pain, dyspepsia, pain in extremity, diarrhea, headache, and myalgia. (  6  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Treatment and Prevention of Postmenopausal Osteoporosis  



     Daily Dosing  



 The safety of BONIVA 2.5 mg once daily in the treatment and prevention of postmenopausal osteoporosis was assessed in 3577 patients aged 41 - 82 years. The duration of the trials was 2 to 3 years, with 1134 patients exposed to placebo and 1140 exposed to BONIVA 2.5 mg. Patients with pre-existing gastrointestinal disease and concomitant use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, proton pump inhibitors and H2 antagonists were included in these clinical trials. All patients received 500 mg calcium plus 400 international units vitamin D supplementation daily.



 The incidence of all-cause mortality was 1% in the placebo group and 1.2% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group. The incidence of serious adverse reactions was 20% in the placebo group and 23% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group. The percentage of patients who withdrew from treatment due to adverse reactions was approximately 17% in both the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and the placebo group.    Table 1    lists adverse reactions from the treatment and prevention studies reported in greater than or equal to 2% of patients and more frequently in patients treated daily with BONIVA than patients treated with placebo.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence Greater Than or Equal to 2% and in More Patients Treated with BONIVA Than in Patients Treated with Placebo Daily in the Osteoporosis Treatment and Prevention Studies 
 Body System                                             Placebo%(n=1134)        BONIVA 2.5 mg%(n=1140)     
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Back Pain                                                    12                         14               
   Pain in Extremity                                             6                          8               
   Asthenia                                                      2                          4               
   Allergic Reaction                                             2                          3               
   Digestive System                                                                                         
   Dyspepsia                                                    10                         12               
   Diarrhea                                                      5                          7               
   Tooth Disorder                                                2                          4               
   Vomiting                                                      2                          3               
   Gastritis                                                     2                          2               
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                                   
   Myalgia                                                       5                          6               
   Joint Disorder                                                3                          4               
   Arthritis                                                     3                          3               
   Nervous System                                                                                           
   Headache                                                      6                          7               
   Dizziness                                                     3                          4               
   Vertigo                                                       3                          3               
   Respiratory System                                                                                       
   Upper Respiratory Infection                                  33                         34               
   Bronchitis                                                    7                         10               
   Pneumonia                                                     4                          6               
   Pharyngitis                                                   2                          3               
   Urogenital System                                                                                        
   Urinary Tract Infection                                       4                          6               
             Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions  
 

 The incidence of selected gastrointestinal adverse reactions in the placebo and BONIVA 2.5 mg daily groups were: dyspepsia (10% vs. 12%), diarrhea (5% vs. 7%), and abdominal pain (5% vs. 6%).



     Musculoskeletal Adverse Reactions  



 The incidence of selected musculoskeletal adverse reactions in the placebo and BONIVA 2.5 mg daily groups were: back pain (12% vs. 14%), arthralgia (14% vs. 14%) and myalgia (5% vs. 6%).



     Ocular Adverse Events  



 Reports in the medical literature indicate that bisphosphonates may be associated with ocular inflammation such as iritis and scleritis. In some cases, these events did not resolve until the bisphosphonate was discontinued. There were no reports of ocular inflammation in studies with BONIVA 2.5 mg daily.



     Monthly Dosing  



 The safety of BONIVA 150 mg once monthly in the treatment of postmenopausal osteoporosis was assessed in a two year trial which enrolled 1583 patients aged 54 - 81 years, with 395 patients exposed to BONIVA 2.5 mg daily and 396 exposed to BONIVA 150 mg monthly. Patients with active or significant pre-existing gastrointestinal disease were excluded from this trial. Patients with dyspepsia or concomitant use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, proton pump inhibitors and H2 antagonists were included in this study. All patients received 500 mg calcium plus 400 international units vitamin D supplementation daily.



 After one year, the incidence of all-cause mortality was 0.3% in both the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and the BONIVA 150 mg monthly group. The incidence of serious adverse events was 5% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and 7% in the BONIVA 150 mg monthly group. The percentage of patients who withdrew from treatment due to adverse events was 9% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and 8% in the BONIVA 150 mg monthly group.    Table 2    lists the adverse events reported in greater than or equal to 2% of patients.



 Table 2 Adverse Events with an Incidence of at Least 2% in Patients Treated with BONIVA 2.5 mg Daily or 150 mg Once-Monthly for Treatment of Postmenopausal Osteoporosis 
 Body System/Adverse Event                           BONIVA2.5 mg Daily%(n=395)  BONIVA150 mg Monthly%(n=396)   
  
   Vascular Disorders                                                                                       
   Hypertension                                                 7.3                        6.3              
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
   Dyspepsia                                                    7.1                        5.6              
   Nausea                                                       4.8                        5.1              
   Diarrhea                                                     4.1                        5.1              
   Constipation                                                 2.5                        4.0              
   Abdominal Pain                                               5.3                        7.8              
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                           
   Arthralgia                                                   3.5                        5.6              
   Back Pain                                                    4.3                        4.5              
   Pain in Extremity                                            1.3                        4.0              
   Localized Osteoarthritis                                     1.3                        3.0              
   Myalgia                                                      0.8                        2.0              
   Muscle Cramp                                                 2.0                        1.8              
   Infections and Infestations                                                                              
   Influenza                                                    3.8                        4.0              
   Nasopharyngitis                                              4.3                        3.5              
   Bronchitis                                                   3.5                        2.5              
   Urinary Tract Infection                                      1.8                        2.3              
   Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                            2.0                        2.0              
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
   Headache                                                     4.1                        3.3              
   Dizziness                                                    1.0                        2.3              
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                           
   Influenza-like Illness                                       0.8                        3.3              
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                   
   Rash                                                         1.3                        2.3              
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                                     0.8                        2.0              
             Gastrointestinal Adverse Events  
 

 The incidence of adverse events in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily and BONIVA 150 mg monthly groups were: dyspepsia (7% vs. 6%), diarrhea (4% vs. 5%), and abdominal pain (5% vs. 8%).



     Musculoskeletal Adverse Events  



 The incidence of adverse events in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily and BONIVA 150 mg monthly groups were: back pain (4% vs. 5%), arthralgia (4% vs. 6%) and myalgia (1% vs. 2%).



     Acute Phase Reactions  



 Symptoms consistent with acute phase reactions have been reported with bisphosphonate use. Over the two years of the study, the overall incidence of acute phase reaction symptoms was 3% in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and 9% in the BONIVA 150 mg monthly group. These incidence rates are based on the reporting of any of 33 acute-phase reaction like symptoms within 3 days of the monthly dosing and lasting 7 days or less. Influenza like illness was reported in no patients in the BONIVA 2.5 mg daily group and 2% in the BONIVA 150 mg monthly group.



     Ocular Adverse Events  



 Two patients who received BONIVA 150 mg once-monthly experienced ocular inflammation, one was a case of uveitis and the other scleritis.



 One hundred sixty (160) postmenopausal women without osteoporosis participated in a 1-year, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of BONIVA 150 mg once-monthly for prevention of bone loss. Seventy-seven subjects received BONIVA and 83 subjects received placebo. The overall pattern of adverse events was similar to that previously observed.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of BONIVA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Hypersensitivity  



 Allergic reactions including anaphylactic reaction/shock with fatalities, angioedema, bronchospasm, asthma exacerbations, rash, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiforme, and dermatitis bullous have been reported (  see  CONTRAINDICATIONS [4]    ).



     Hypocalcemia  



 Hypocalcemia has been reported in patients treated with BONIVA (  see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS [5.2]  ).  



     Musculoskeletal Pain  



 Bone, joint, or muscle pain (musculoskeletal pain), described as severe or incapacitating, has been reported (  see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS [5.3]    ).



     Jaw Osteonecrosis  



 Osteonecrosis of the jaw has been reported in patients treated with BONIVA (  see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS [5.4]    ).



     Atypical Femoral Shaft Fracture  



 Atypical, low-energy, or low-trauma fractures of the femoral shaft (  see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS [5.5]    ).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Upper gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions can occur. Instruct patients to follow dosing instructions and discontinue use if new or worsening symptoms occur. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Hypocalcemia may worsen during treatment. Correct hypocalcemia before use. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Severe Bone, Joint, and Muscle Pain may occur. Consider discontinuing use if symptoms develop. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw has been reported. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Atypical Femur Fractures have been reported. Patients with new thigh or groin pain should be evaluated to rule out a femoral fracture. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Upper Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions



  BONIVA, like other bisphosphonates administered orally, may cause local irritation of the upper gastrointestinal mucosa. Because of these possible irritant effects and a potential for worsening of the underlying disease, caution should be used when BONIVA is given to patients with active upper gastrointestinal problems (such as known Barrett's esophagus, dysphagia, other esophageal diseases, gastritis, duodenitis or ulcers).



 Esophageal adverse experiences, such as esophagitis, esophageal ulcers and esophageal erosions, occasionally with bleeding and rarely followed by esophageal stricture or perforation, have been reported in patients receiving treatment with oral bisphosphonates. In some cases, these have been severe and required hospitalization. Physicians should therefore be alert to any signs or symptoms signaling a possible esophageal reaction and patients should be instructed to discontinue BONIVA and seek medical attention if they develop dysphagia, odynophagia, retrosternal pain or new or worsening heartburn.



 The risk of severe esophageal adverse experiences appears to be greater in patients who lie down after taking oral bisphosphonates and/or who fail to swallow it with the recommended full glass (6-8 oz) of water, and/or who continue to take oral bisphosphonates after developing symptoms suggestive of esophageal irritation. Therefore, it is very important that the full dosing instructions are provided to, and understood by, the patient (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION [2.2]  )  . In patients who cannot comply with dosing instructions due to mental disability, therapy with BONIVA should be used under appropriate supervision.



 There have been post-marketing reports of gastric and duodenal ulcers with oral bisphosphonate use, some severe and with complications, although no increased risk was observed in controlled clinical trials.



    5.2 Hypocalcemia and Mineral Metabolism



  Hypocalcemia has been reported in patients taking BONIVA. Treat hypocalcemia and other disturbances of bone and mineral metabolism before starting BONIVA therapy. Instruct patients to take supplemental calcium and vitamin D if their dietary intake is inadequate. (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION [2.3]  )  .



    5.3 Musculoskeletal Pain



  Severe and occasionally incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain has been reported in patients taking BONIVA and other bisphosphonates (see  ADVERSE REACTIONS [6]  )  . The time to onset of symptoms varied from one day to several months after starting the drug. Most patients had relief of symptoms after stopping. A subset had recurrence of symptoms when rechallenged with the same drug or another bisphosphonate. Consider discontinuing use if severe symptoms develop.



    5.4 Jaw Osteonecrosis



   Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ), which can occur spontaneously, is generally associated with tooth extraction and/or local infection with delayed healing, and has been reported in patients taking bisphosphonates, including BONIVA. Known risk factors for osteonecrosis of the jaw include invasive dental procedures (e.g., tooth extraction, dental implants, boney surgery), diagnosis of cancer, concomitant therapies (e.g., chemotherapy, corticosteroids, angiogenesis inhibitors), poor oral hygiene, and co-morbid disorders (e.g., periodontal and/or other pre-existing dental disease, anemia, coagulopathy, infection, ill-fitting dentures). The risk of ONJ may increase with duration of exposure to bisphosphonates.  



 For patients requiring invasive dental procedures, discontinuation of bisphosphonate treatment may reduce the risk for ONJ. Clinical judgment of the treating physician and/or oral surgeon should guide the management plan of each patient based on individual benefit/risk assessment.



 Patients who develop osteonecrosis of the jaw while on bisphosphonate therapy should receive care by an oral surgeon. In these patients, extensive dental surgery to treat ONJ may exacerbate the condition. Discontinuation of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered based on individual benefit/risk assessment.



    5.5 Atypical Subtrochanteric and Diaphyseal Femoral Fractures



  Atypical, low-energy, or low-trauma fractures of the femoral shaft have been reported in bisphosphonate-treated patients. These fractures can occur anywhere in the femoral shaft from just below the lesser trochanter to above the supracondylar flare and are transverse or short oblique in orientation without evidence of comminution. Causality has not been established as these fractures also occur in osteoporotic patients who have not been treated with bisphosphonates.



 Atypical femur fractures most commonly occur with minimal or no trauma to the affected area. They may be bilateral and many patients report prodromal pain in the affected area, usually presenting as dull, aching thigh pain, weeks to months before a complete fracture occurs. A number of reports note that patients were also receiving treatment with glucocorticoids (e.g., prednisone) at the time of fracture.



 Any patient with a history of bisphosphonate exposure who presents with thigh or groin pain should be suspected of having an atypical fracture and should be evaluated to rule out an incomplete femur fracture. Patients presenting with an atypical fracture should also be assessed for symptoms and signs of fracture in the contralateral limb. Interruption of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered, pending a risk/benefit assessment, on an individual basis.



    5.6 Severe Renal Impairment



  BONIVA is not recommended for use in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance of less than 30 mL/min).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
