<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="boostrix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    Common solicited adverse events (&gt;=15%) in adolescents (10 to 18 years of age) were pain, redness, and swelling at the injection site, increase in arm circumference of injected arm, headache, fatigue, and gastrointestinal symptoms. (  6.1  ) 
 *    Common solicited adverse events (&gt;=15%) in adults (19 to 64 years of age) were pain, redness, and swelling at the injection site, headache, fatigue, and gastrointestinal symptoms. (  6.1  ) 
 *    The most common solicited adverse event (&gt;=15%) in the elderly (65 years of age and older) was pain at the injection site. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. As with any vaccine, there is the possibility that broad use of BOOSTRIX could reveal adverse reactions not observed in clinical trials.



 In clinical studies, 4,949 adolescents (10 to 18 years of age) and 4,076 adults (19 years of age and older) were vaccinated with a single dose of BOOSTRIX. Of these adolescents, 1,341 were vaccinated with BOOSTRIX in a coadministration study with meningococcal conjugate vaccine  [see Drug Interactions (7.1), Clinical Studies (14.5)]  . Of these adults, 1,104 were 65 years of age and older  [see Clinical Studies (14.4)]  . A total of 860 adults 19 years of age and older received concomitant vaccination with BOOSTRIX and influenza vaccines in a coadministration study  [see Drug Interactions (7.1), Clinical Studies (14.5)]  . An additional 1,092 adolescents 10 to 18 years of age received a non-U.S. formulation of BOOSTRIX (formulated to contain 0.5 mg aluminum per dose) in non-U.S. clinical studies.



 In a randomized, observer-blinded, controlled study in the U.S., 3,080 adolescents 10 to 18 years of age received a single dose of BOOSTRIX and 1,034 received the comparator Td vaccine, manufactured by MassBioLogics. There were no substantive differences in demographic characteristics between the vaccine groups. Among BOOSTRIX and comparator vaccine recipients, approximately 75% were 10 to 14 years of age and approximately 25% were 15 to 18 years of age. Approximately 98% of participants in this study had received the recommended series of 4 or 5 doses of either Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids and Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed (DTwP) or a combination of DTwP and DTaP in childhood. Subjects were monitored for solicited adverse events using standardized diary cards (Day 0-14). Unsolicited adverse events were monitored for the 31-day period following vaccination (Day 0-30). Subjects were also monitored for 6 months post-vaccination for non-routine medical visits, visits to an emergency room, onset of new chronic illness, and serious adverse events. Information regarding late onset adverse events was obtained via a telephone call 6 months following vaccination. At least 97% of subjects completed the 6-month follow-up evaluation.



 In a study conducted in Germany, BOOSTRIX was administered to 319 children 10 to 12 years of age previously vaccinated with 5 doses of acellular pertussis antigen-containing vaccines; 193 of these subjects had previously received 5 doses of INFANRIX  (r)  (Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed). Adverse events were recorded on diary cards during the 15 days following vaccination. Unsolicited adverse events that occurred within 31 days of vaccination (Day 0-30) were recorded on the diary card or verbally reported to the investigator. Subjects were monitored for 6 months post-vaccination for physician office visits, emergency room visits, onset of new chronic illness, and serious adverse events. The 6-month follow-up evaluation, conducted via telephone interview, was completed by 90% of subjects.



 The U.S. adult (19 to 64 years of age) study, a randomized, observer-blinded study, evaluated the safety of BOOSTRIX (N = 1,522) compared with ADACEL  (r)  (Tetanus Toxoid, Reduced Diphtheria Toxoid and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed) (N = 762), a Tdap vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA. Vaccines were administered as a single dose. There were no substantive differences in demographic characteristics between the vaccine groups. Subjects were monitored for solicited adverse events using standardized diary cards (Day 0-14). Unsolicited adverse events were monitored for the 31-day period following vaccination (Day 0-30). Subjects were also monitored for 6 months post-vaccination for serious adverse events, visits to an emergency room, hospitalizations, and onset of new chronic illness. Approximately 95% of subjects completed the 6-month follow-up evaluation.



 The U.S. elderly (65 years of age and older) study, a randomized, observer-blinded study, evaluated the safety of BOOSTRIX (N = 887) compared with DECAVAC  (r)  (Tetanus and Diphtheria Toxoids Adsorbed) (N = 445), a U.S.-licensed Td vaccine, manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA. Vaccines were administered as a single dose. Among all vaccine recipients, the mean age was approximately 72 years; 54% were female and 95% were white. Subjects were monitored for solicited adverse events using standardized diary cards (Day 0-3). Unsolicited adverse events were monitored for the 31-day period following vaccination (Day 0-30). Subjects were also monitored for 6 months post-vaccination for serious adverse events. Approximately 99% of subjects completed the 6-month follow-up evaluation.



   Solicited Adverse Events in the U.S. Adolescent Study  



 Table 1 presents the solicited local adverse reactions and general adverse events within 15 days of vaccination with BOOSTRIX or Td vaccine for the total vaccinated cohort.



 The primary safety endpoint was the incidence of Grade 3 pain (spontaneously painful and/or prevented normal activity) at the injection site within 15 days of vaccination. Grade 3 pain was reported in 4.6% of those who received BOOSTRIX compared with 4.0% of those who received the Td vaccine. The difference in rate of Grade 3 pain was within the pre-defined clinical limit for non-inferiority (upper limit of the 95% CI for the difference [BOOSTRIX minus Td] &lt;=4%).



 Table 1. Rates of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or General Adverse Events within the 15-Daya Post-vaccination Period in Adolescents 10 to 18 Years of Age (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                                               BOOSTRIX  (N = 3,032)  %    Td  (N = 1,013)  %    
  Local                                                                                                    
  Pain, anyb                                                   75.3                   71.7                 
  Pain, Grade 2 or 3b                                          51.2                   42.5                 
  Pain, Grade 3c                                               4.6                    4.0                  
  Redness, any                                                 22.5                   19.8                 
  Redness, &gt;20 mm                                              4.1                    3.9                  
  Redness, &gt;=50 mm                                             1.7                    1.6                  
  Swelling, any                                                21.1                   20.1                 
  Swelling, &gt;20 mm                                             5.3                    4.9                  
  Swelling, &gt;=50 mm                                            2.5                    3.2                  
  Arm circumference increase, &gt;5 mmd                           28.3                   29.5                 
  Arm circumference increase, &gt;20 mmd                          2.0                    2.2                  
  Arm circumference increase, &gt;40 mmd                          0.5                    0.3                  
  General                                                                                                  
  Headache, any                                                43.1                   41.5                 
  Headache, Grade 2 or 3b                                      15.7                   12.7                 
  Headache, Grade 3                                            3.7                    2.7                  
  Fatigue, any                                                 37.0                   36.7                 
  Fatigue, Grade 2 or 3                                        14.4                   12.9                 
  Fatigue, Grade 3                                             3.7                    3.2                  
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, anye                              26.0                   25.8                 
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, Grade 2 or 3e                     9.8                    9.7                  
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, Grade 3e                          3.0                    3.2                  
  Fever, &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)f                    13.5                   13.1                 
  Fever, &gt;100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)f                    5.0                    4.7                  
  Fever, &gt;102.2 degrees F (39.0 degrees C)f                    1.4                    1.0                  
        *     Td = Tetanus and Diphtheria Toxoids Adsorbed For Adult Use manufactured by MassBioLogics. 
 *     N = Number of subjects in the total vaccinated cohort with local/general symptoms sheets completed. 
 *     Grade 2 = Local: painful when limb moved; General: interfered with normal activity. 
 *     Grade 3 = Local: spontaneously painful and/or prevented normal activity; General: prevented normal activity. 
   *       a  Day of vaccination and the next 14 days. 
 *       b  Statistically significantly higher ( P &lt;0.05) following BOOSTRIX as compared with Td vaccine. 
 *       c  Grade 3 injection site pain following BOOSTRIX was not inferior to Td vaccine (upper limit of two-sided 95% CI for the difference [BOOSTRIX minus Td] in the percentage of subjects &lt;=4%). 
 *       d  Mid-upper region of the vaccinated arm. 
 *       e  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain. 
 *       f  Oral temperatures or axillary temperatures. 
      Unsolicited Adverse Events in the U.S. Adolescent Study  
 

 The incidence of unsolicited adverse events reported in the 31 days after vaccination was comparable between the 2 groups (25.4% and 24.5% for BOOSTRIX and Td vaccine, respectively).



   Solicited Adverse Events in the German Adolescent Study  



 Table 2 presents the rates of solicited local adverse reactions and fever within 15 days of vaccination for those subjects who had previously been vaccinated with 5 doses of INFANRIX. No cases of whole arm swelling were reported. Two individuals (2/193) reported large injection site swelling (range: 110 to 200 mm diameter), in one case associated with Grade 3 pain. Neither individual sought medical attention. These episodes were reported to resolve without sequelae within 5 days.



 Table 2. Rates of Solicited Adverse Events Reported within the 15-Daya Post-vaccination Period following Administration of BOOSTRIX in Adolescents 10 to 12 Years of Age Who Had Previously Received 5 Doses of INFANRIX 
                                                                     BOOSTRIX  (N = 193)  %               
  Pain, any                                                          62.2                                 
  Pain, Grade 2 or 3                                                 33.2                                 
  Pain, Grade 3                                                      5.7                                  
  Redness, any                                                       47.7                                 
  Redness, &gt;20 mm                                                    15.0                                 
  Redness, &gt;=50 mm                                                   10.9                                 
  Swelling, any                                                      38.9                                 
  Swelling, &gt;20 mm                                                   17.6                                 
  Swelling, &gt;=50 mm                                                  14.0                                 
  Fever, &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)b                          8.8                                  
  Fever, &gt;100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)b                          4.1                                  
  Fever, &gt;102.2 degrees F (39.0 degrees C)b                          1.0                                  
       *     N = Number of subjects with local/general symptoms sheets completed. 
 *     Grade 2 = Painful when limb moved. 
 *     Grade 3 = Spontaneously painful and/or prevented normal activity. 
   *       a  Day of vaccination and the next 14 days. 
 *       b  Oral temperatures or axillary temperatures. 
      Solicited Adverse Events in the U.S. Adult (19 to 64 Years of Age) Study  
 

 Table 3 presents solicited local adverse reactions and general adverse events within 15 days of vaccination with BOOSTRIX or the comparator Tdap vaccine for the total vaccinated cohort.



 Table 3. Rates of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or General Adverse Events within the 15-Daya Post-vaccination Period in Adults 19 to 64 Years of Age (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                                                 BOOSTRIX  (N = 1,480)  %    Tdap  (N = 741)  %    
  Local                                                                                                     
  Pain, any                                                      61.0                    69.2               
  Pain, Grade 2 or 3                                             35.1                    44.4               
  Pain, Grade 3                                                  1.6                     2.3                
  Redness, any                                                   21.1                    27.1               
  Redness, &gt;20 mm                                                4.0                     6.2                
  Redness, &gt;=50 mm                                               1.6                     2.3                
  Swelling, any                                                  17.6                    25.6               
  Swelling, &gt;20 mm                                               3.9                     6.3                
  Swelling, &gt;=50 mm                                              1.4                     2.8                
  General                                                                                                   
  Headache, any                                                  30.1                    31.0               
  Headache, Grade 2 or 3                                         11.1                    10.5               
  Headache, Grade 3                                              2.2                     1.5                
  Fatigue, any                                                   28.1                    28.9               
  Fatigue, Grade 2 or 3                                          9.1                     9.4                
  Fatigue, Grade 3                                               2.5                     1.2                
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, anyb                                15.9                    17.5               
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, Grade 2 or 3b                       4.3                     5.7                
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, Grade 3b                            1.2                     1.3                
  Fever, &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)c                      5.5                     8.0                
  Fever, &gt;100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)c                      1.0                     1.5                
  Fever, &gt;102.2 degrees F (39.0 degrees C)c                      0.1                     0.4                
        *     Tdap = Tetanus Toxoid, Reduced Diphtheria Toxoid and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed, a Tdap vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA. 
 *     N = Number of subjects in the total vaccinated cohort with local/general symptoms sheets completed. 
 *     Grade 2 = Local: painful when limb moved; General: interfered with normal activity. 
 *     Grade 3 = Local/General: prevented normal activity. 
   *       a  Day of vaccination and the next 14 days. 
 *       b  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain. 
 *       c  Oral temperatures. 
      Unsolicited Adverse Events in the U.S. Adult (19 to 64 Years of Age) Study  
 

 The incidence of unsolicited adverse events reported in the 31 days after vaccination was comparable between the 2 groups (17.8% and 22.2% for BOOSTRIX and Tdap vaccine, respectively).



   Solicited Adverse Events in the U.S. Elderly (65 Years of Age and Older) Study  



 Table 4 presents solicited local adverse reactions and general adverse events within 4 days of vaccination with BOOSTRIX or the comparator Td vaccine for the total vaccinated cohort.



 Table 4. Rates of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or General Adverse Events within 4 Daysa of Vaccination in the Elderly 65 Years of Age and Older (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                                                 BOOSTRIX  %             Td  %              
  Local                                                          (N = 882)               (N = 444)          
  Pain, any                                                      21.5                    27.7               
  Pain, Grade 2 or 3                                             7.5                     10.1               
  Pain, Grade 3                                                  0.2                     0.7                
  Redness, any                                                   10.8                    12.6               
  Redness, &gt;20 mm                                                1.4                     2.5                
  Redness, &gt;=50 mm                                               0.6                     0.9                
  Swelling, any                                                  7.5                     11.7               
  Swelling, &gt;20 mm                                               2.2                     3.4                
  Swelling, &gt;=50 mm                                              0.7                     0.7                
  General                                                        (N = 882)               (N = 445)          
  Fatigue, any                                                   12.5                    14.8               
  Fatigue, Grade 2 or 3                                          2.5                     2.9                
  Fatigue, Grade 3                                               0.7                     0.7                
  Headache, any                                                  11.5                    11.7               
  Headache, Grade 2 or 3                                         1.9                     2.2                
  Headache, Grade 3                                              0.6                     0.0                
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, anyb                                7.6                     9.2                
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, Grade 2 or 3b                       1.7                     1.8                
  Gastrointestinal symptoms, Grade 3b                            0.3                     0.4                
  Fever, &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)c                      2.0                     2.5                
  Fever, &gt;100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)c                      0.2                     0.2                
  Fever, &gt;102.2 degrees F (39.0 degrees C)c                      0.0                     0.0                
        *     Td = Tetanus and Diphtheria Toxoids Adsorbed, a U.S.-licensed Td vaccine, manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA. 
 *     N = Number of subjects with a documented dose. 
 *     Grade 2 = Local: painful when limb moved; General: interfered with normal activity. 
 *     Grade 3 = Local/General: prevented normal activity. 
   *       a  Day of vaccination and the next 3 days. 
 *       b  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain. 
 *       c  Oral temperatures. 
      Unsolicited Adverse Events in the U.S. Elderly (65 Years of Age and Older) Study  
 

 The incidence of unsolicited adverse events reported in the 31 days after vaccination was comparable between the 2 groups (17.1% and 14.4% for BOOSTRIX and Td vaccine, respectively).



   Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)  



 In the U.S. and German adolescent safety studies, no serious adverse events were reported to occur within 31 days of vaccination. During the 6-month extended safety evaluation period, no serious adverse events that were of potential autoimmune origin or new onset and chronic in nature were reported to occur. In non-U.S. adolescent studies in which serious adverse events were monitored for up to 37 days, one subject was diagnosed with insulin-dependent diabetes 20 days following administration of BOOSTRIX. No other serious adverse events of potential autoimmune origin or that were new onset and chronic in nature were reported to occur in these studies. In the U.S. adult (19 to 64 years of age) study, serious adverse events were reported to occur during the entire study period (0-6 months) by 1.4% and 1.7% of subjects who received BOOSTRIX and the comparator Tdap vaccine, respectively. During the 6-month extended safety evaluation period, no serious adverse events of a neuroinflammatory nature or with information suggesting an autoimmune etiology were reported in subjects who received BOOSTRIX. In the U.S. elderly (65 years of age and older) study, serious adverse events were reported to occur by 0.7% and 0.9% of subjects who received BOOSTRIX and the comparator Td vaccine, respectively, during the 31-day period after vaccination. Serious adverse events were reported to occur by 4.2% and 2.2% of subjects who received BOOSTRIX and the comparator Td vaccine, respectively, during the 6-month period after vaccination.



   Concomitant Vaccination with Meningococcal Conjugate Vaccine in Adolescents  



 In a randomized study in the U.S., 1,341 adolescents (11 to 18 years of age) received either BOOSTRIX administered concomitantly with MENACTRA  (r)  (Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y, and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine), (Sanofi Pasteur SA), or each vaccine administered separately 1 month apart  [see Drug Interactions (7.1), Clinical Studies (14.5)]  . Safety was evaluated in 446 subjects who received BOOSTRIX administered concomitantly with meningococcal conjugate vaccine at different injection sites, 446 subjects who received BOOSTRIX followed by meningococcal conjugate vaccine 1 month later, and 449 subjects who received meningococcal conjugate vaccine followed by BOOSTRIX 1 month later. Solicited local adverse reactions and general adverse events were recorded on diary cards for 4 days (Day 0-3) following each vaccination. Unsolicited adverse events were monitored for the 31-day period following each vaccination (Day 0-30). Table 5 presents the percentages of subjects experiencing local reactions at the injection site for BOOSTRIX and solicited general events following BOOSTRIX. The incidence of unsolicited adverse events reported in the 31 days after any vaccination was similar following each dose of BOOSTRIX in all cohorts.



 Table 5. Rates of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions or General Adverse Events Reported within the 4-Day Post-vaccination Period following Administration of BOOSTRIX in Individuals 11 to 18 Years of Age (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                BOOSTRIX+MCV4a  (N = 441)  %    BOOSTRIX-&gt;MCV4b  (N = 432-433)  %    MCV4-&gt;BOOSTRIXc  (N = 441)  %    
  Local (at injection site for BOOSTRIX)    
  Pain, any                     70.1                     70.4                      47.8                      
  Redness, any                  22.7                     25.7                      17.9                      
  Swelling, any                 17.7                     18.1                      12.0                      
  General (following administration of BOOSTRIX)    
  Fatigue                       34.0                     32.1                      20.4                      
  Headache                      34.0                     30.7                      17.0                      
  Gastrointestinal symptomsd    15.2                     14.5                      7.7                       
  Fever, &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)e    5.2                      3.5                       2.3                       
         *     MCV4 = MENACTRA (Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y, and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine), Sanofi Pasteur SA. 
 *     N = number of subjects in the total vaccinated cohort with local/general symptoms sheets completed. 
   *       a  BOOSTRIX+MCV4 = Concomitant vaccination with BOOSTRIX and MENACTRA. 
 *       b  BOOSTRIX-&gt;MCV4 = BOOSTRIX followed by MCV4 1 month later. 
 *       c  MCV4-&gt;BOOSTRIX = MCV4 followed by BOOSTRIX 1 month later. 
 *       d  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain. 
 *       e  Oral temperatures. 
      6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   In addition to reports in clinical trials, worldwide voluntary reports of adverse events received for BOOSTRIX in persons 10 years of age and older since market introduction of this vaccine are listed below. This list includes serious events or events that have causal connection to components of this or other vaccines or drugs. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Lymphadenitis, lymphadenopathy.



   Immune System Disorders  



 Allergic reactions, including anaphylactic and anaphylactoid reactions.



   Cardiac Disorders  



 Myocarditis.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  



 Extensive swelling of the injected limb, injection site induration, injection site inflammation, injection site mass, injection site pruritus, injection site nodule, injection site warmth, injection site reaction.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  



 Arthralgia, back pain, myalgia.



   Nervous System Disorders  



 Convulsions (with and without fever), encephalitis, facial palsy, loss of consciousness, paraesthesia, syncope.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Angioedema, exanthem, Henoch-Schonlein purpura, rash, urticaria.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    The tip caps of the prefilled syringes contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions. (  5.1  ) 
 *    If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk of Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following a subsequent dose of tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine, including BOOSTRIX. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including BOOSTRIX. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Progressive or unstable neurologic conditions are reasons to defer vaccination with a pertussis-containing vaccine, including BOOSTRIX. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Persons who experienced an Arthus-type hypersensitivity reaction following a prior dose of a tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine should not receive BOOSTRIX unless at least 10 years have elapsed since the last dose of a tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Latex



  The tip caps of the prefilled syringes contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions.



    5.2 Guillain-Barre Syndrome and Brachial Neuritis



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk of Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following a subsequent dose of tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine, including BOOSTRIX. A review by the Institute of Medicine (IOM) found evidence for a causal relationship between receipt of tetanus toxoid and both brachial neuritis and Guillain-Barre syndrome.  1  



    5.3 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including BOOSTRIX. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.



    5.4 Progressive or Unstable Neurologic Disorders



  Progressive or unstable neurologic conditions (e.g., cerebrovascular events and acute encephalopathic conditions) are reasons to defer vaccination with a pertussis-containing vaccine, including BOOSTRIX. It is not known whether administration of BOOSTRIX to persons with an unstable or progressive neurologic disorder might hasten manifestations of the disorder or affect the prognosis. Administration of BOOSTRIX to persons with an unstable or progressive neurologic disorder may result in diagnostic confusion between manifestations of the underlying illness and possible adverse effects of vaccination.



    5.5 Arthus-Type Hypersensitivity



  Persons who experienced an Arthus-type hypersensitivity reaction following a prior dose of a tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine usually have a high serum tetanus antitoxin level and should not receive BOOSTRIX or other tetanus toxoid-containing vaccines unless at least 10 years have elapsed since the last dose of tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine.



    5.6 Altered Immunocompetence



  As with any vaccine, if administered to immunosuppressed persons, including individuals receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained.



    5.7 Prevention and Management of Acute Allergic Reactions



  Prior to administration, the healthcare provider should review the immunization history for possible vaccine sensitivity and previous vaccination-related adverse reactions to allow an assessment of benefits and risks. Epinephrine and other appropriate agents used for the control of immediate allergic reactions must be immediately available should an acute anaphylactic reaction occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
