<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bridion" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Anaphylaxis and Hypersensitivity [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Marked Bradycardia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (reported in &gt;=10% of patients at a 2, 4, or 16 mg/kg BRIDION dose and higher than the placebo rate): vomiting, pain, nausea, hypotension, and headache. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect 2914 subjects exposed to 2, 4, or 16 mg/kg BRIDION and 544 to placebo in pooled Phase 1-3 studies. The population was 18 to 92 years old, 47% male and 53% female, 34% ASA (American Society of Anesthesiologists) Class 1, 51% ASA Class 2, and 14% ASA Class 3, and 82% Caucasian. Most subjects received a single dose of BRIDION 2 mg/kg or 4 mg/kg.



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=10% of patients at a 2, 4, or 16 mg/kg BRIDION dose with a rate higher than the placebo rate are: vomiting, pain, nausea, hypotension, and headache.



 All adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=2% of subjects treated with BRIDION and more often than placebo for adult subjects who received anesthesia and/or neuromuscular blocking agent in pooled Phase 1 to 3 studies are presented in Table 2.



 Table 2: Percent of Subject Exposures in Pooled Phase 1 to 3 Studies with Adverse Reactions Incidence &gt;= 2% 
                                          Sugammadex         Placebo        
 Body System  Preferred Term           2 mg/kg(N=895)n (%)  4 mg/kg(N=1921)n (%)  16 mg/kg(N=98)n (%)    (N=544)n (%)     
  
   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications                                                                             
   Incision site pain                       58 (6)           106 (6)            4 (4)             6 (1)         
   Procedural complication                  13 (1)            27 (1)            8 (8)             3 (1)         
   Airway complication of anesthesia        11 (1)            13 (1)            9 (9)               0           
   Anesthetic complication                  8 (1)             14 (1)            9 (9)             1 (&lt;1)        
   Wound hemorrhage                         5 (1)             38 (2)              0               8 (1)         
   Recurrence of neuromuscular blockade         0               1 (&lt;1)            2 (2)               0           
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                   
   Nausea                                  208 (23)          503 (26)          23 (23)           127 (23)       
   Vomiting                                98 (11)           236 (12)          15 (15)           57 (10)        
   Abdominal pain                           48 (5)            68 (4)            6 (6)             17 (3)        
   Flatulence                               17 (2)            51 (3)            1 (1)             10 (2)        
   Dry mouth                                9 (1)             5 (&lt;1)            2 (2)               0           
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                             
   Pain                                    434 (48)          993 (52)          35 (36)           207 (38)       
   Pyrexia                                  77 (9)           109 (6)            5 (5)             17 (3)        
   Chills                                   30 (3)            61 (3)            7 (7)             27 (5)        
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                     
   Headache                                 61 (7)            99 (5)           10 (10)            42 (8)        
   Dizziness                                44 (5)            67 (3)            6 (6)             13 (2)        
   Hypoesthesia                             12 (1)            24 (1)            3 (3)             9 (2)         
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                             
   Oropharyngeal pain                       42 (5)            66 (3)            5 (5)             27 (5)        
   Cough                                    13 (1)            49 (3)            8 (8)             11 (2)        
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                             
   Pain in extremity                        13 (1)            35 (2)            6 (6)             15 (3)        
   Musculoskeletal pain                     16 (2)            33 (2)            1 (1)             6 (1)         
   Myalgia                                  5 (1)             17 (1)            2 (2)             3 (1)         
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                        
   Insomnia                                 20 (2)           103 (5)            5 (5)             22 (4)        
   Anxiety                                  14 (2)            19 (1)            3 (3)             1 (&lt;1)        
   Restlessness                             3 (&lt;1)            17 (1)            2 (2)             2 (&lt;1)        
   Depression                               2 (&lt;1)            5 (&lt;1)            2 (2)               0           
   Investigations                                                                                               
   Red blood cell count decreased           13 (1)            34 (2)            1 (1)             2 (&lt;1)        
   Electrocardiogram QT interval abnormal       13 (1)            7 (&lt;1)            6 (6)             4 (1)         
   Blood creatine phosphokinase increased       9 (1)             14 (1)            2 (2)             1 (&lt;1)        
   Vascular disorders                                                                                           
   Hypertension                             48 (5)            96 (5)            9 (9)             38 (7)        
   Hypotension                              33 (4)           102 (5)           13 (13)            20 (4)        
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                             
   Pruritus                                 17 (2)            50 (3)            2 (2)             9 (2)         
   Erythema                                 5 (1)             31 (2)              0               6 (1)         
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                             
   Hypocalcemia                             15 (2)            12 (1)              0               4 (1)         
   Cardiac disorders                                                                                            
   Tachycardia                              17 (2)            29 (2)            5 (5)             4 (1)         
   Bradycardia                              9 (1)             21 (1)            5 (5)             6 (1)         
   Surgical and medical procedures                                                                              
   Hysterectomy                               0                 0               2 (2)               0           
               Anaphylaxis and Hypersensitivity  
 

 Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have occurred in both premarketing clinical trials and in post-marketing spontaneous reports. In a dedicated hypersensitivity study in healthy volunteers, the frequency of anaphylaxis was 0.3%  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . These reactions varied from isolated skin reactions to serious systemic reactions (i.e., anaphylaxis, anaphylactic shock) and have occurred in patients with no prior exposure to sugammadex.



 Symptoms associated with these reactions can include: flushing, urticaria, erythematous rash, (severe) hypotension, tachycardia, swelling of tongue, swelling of pharynx, bronchospasm and pulmonary obstructive events. Severe hypersensitivity reactions can be fatal.



 A randomized, double-blind study examined the incidence of drug hypersensitivity reactions in healthy volunteers given up to 3 doses of placebo (N=76), sugammadex 4 mg/kg (N=151) or sugammadex 16 mg/kg (N=148). Reports of suspected hypersensitivity were adjudicated by a blinded committee. The incidence of adjudicated hypersensitivity was 1%, 7% and 9% in the placebo, sugammadex 4 mg/kg and sugammadex 16 mg/kg groups, respectively. There were no reports of anaphylaxis after placebo or sugammadex 4 mg/kg. There was a single case of adjudicated anaphylaxis after the first dose of sugammadex 16 mg/kg. The frequency of anaphylaxis for the 299 healthy volunteers treated with intravenous sugammadex was 0.3%. There was no evidence of increased frequency or severity of hypersensitivity with repeat dosing.



 In a previous study of similar design, there were three adjudicated cases of anaphylaxis, all after sugammadex 16 mg/kg (incidence 1% in the 298 healthy volunteers treated with sugammadex).



     Recurrence of Neuromuscular Blockade  



 In clinical studies with subjects treated with rocuronium or vecuronium, where BRIDION was administered using a dose labeled for the depth of neuromuscular blockade (N=2022), an incidence of &lt;1% was observed for recurrence of neuromuscular blockade as based on neuromuscular monitoring or clinical evidence  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  .



     Bronchospasm  



 In one dedicated clinical trial and in post-marketing data, in patients with a history of pulmonary complications  [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.9)  ]  , bronchospasm was reported as a possibly related adverse event.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of BRIDION. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Cardiac Disorders:  Cases of marked bradycardia and bradycardia with cardiac arrest have been observed within minutes after administration of sugammadex  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  . Other cardiac rhythm abnormalities have included atrial fibrillation, atrioventricular block, cardiac/cardiorespiratory arrest, ST segment changes, supraventricular tachycardia/extrasystoles, tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, and ventricular tachycardia.



     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Cases of BRIDION not having the intended effect.



     Immune System Disorders:  Hypersensitivity events including anaphylactic shock, anaphylactic reaction, anaphylactoid reaction, and Type 1 hypersensitivity have been reported  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



     Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  Events of laryngospasm, dyspnea, wheezing, pulmonary edema, and respiratory arrest have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Anaphylaxis : Anaphylaxis has occurred in 0.3% of healthy volunteers. Observe patients for an appropriate period of time after administration. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Marked Bradycardia : Cases of marked bradycardia, some of which have resulted in cardiac arrest, have been observed within minutes after administration. Monitor for hemodynamic changes and administer anticholinergic agents such as atropine if clinically significant bradycardia is observed. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Respiratory Function Monitoring : Ventilatory support is mandatory for patients until adequate spontaneous respiration is restored and the ability to maintain a patent airway is assured. Should neuromuscular blockade persist after BRIDION or recur following extubation, take appropriate steps to provide adequate ventilation. (  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
 *   Waiting Times for Re-Administration of Neuromuscular Blocking Agent : If re-administration of a neuromuscular blocking agent is required after reversal with BRIDION, waiting times should be based on the dose of BRIDION, and the renal function of the patient. Consider use of a nonsteroidal neuromuscular blocking agent. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylaxis and Hypersensitivity



  Clinicians should be prepared for the possibility of drug hypersensitivity reactions (including anaphylactic reactions) and take the necessary precautions [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Potentially serious hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have occurred in patients treated with BRIDION. The nature and frequency of anaphylaxis and hypersensitivity associated with BRIDION administration were evaluated in a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group, repeat-dose study in which 375 subjects were randomized to receive 3 doses of BRIDION IV with a 5 week washout period: 151 subjects received 4 mg/kg, 148 received 16 mg/kg and 76 received placebo. The frequency of anaphylaxis for the 299 healthy volunteers treated with intravenous BRIDION was 0.3% (n=1 in the BRIDION 16 mg/kg group on the first dose). Signs and symptoms included conjunctival edema, urticaria, erythema, swelling of the uvula and reduction in peak expiratory flow within 5 minutes of dose administration. The most common hypersensitivity adverse reactions reported were nausea, pruritus and urticaria and showed a dose response relationship, occurring more frequently in the 16 mg/kg group compared to the 4 mg/kg and placebo groups.



 Anaphylaxis has also been reported in the post-marketing setting, including at doses less than 16 mg/kg. The most commonly described clinical features in reports of anaphylaxis were dermatologic symptoms (including urticaria, rash, erythema, flushing and skin eruption); and clinically important hypotension often requiring the use of vasopressors for circulatory support. In addition prolonged hospitalization and/or the use of additional respiratory support until full recovery (re-intubation, prolonged intubation, manual or mechanical ventilation) have been noted in a number of the anaphylaxis reports.



    5.2 Marked Bradycardia



  Cases of marked bradycardia, some of which have resulted in cardiac arrest, have been observed within minutes after the administration of BRIDION [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . Patients should be closely monitored for hemodynamic changes during and after reversal of neuromuscular blockade. Treatment with anticholinergic agents, such as atropine, should be administered if clinically significant bradycardia is observed.



    5.3 Respiratory Function Monitoring During Recovery



  Ventilatory support is mandatory for patients until adequate spontaneous respiration is restored and the ability to maintain a patent airway is assured. Even if recovery from neuromuscular blockade is complete, other drugs used in the peri- and post-operative period could depress respiratory function and therefore ventilatory support might still be required.



 Should neuromuscular blockade persist after BRIDION administration or recur following extubation, take appropriate steps to provide adequate ventilation.



    5.4 Risk of Prolonged Neuromuscular Blockade



  In clinical trials, a small number of patients experienced a delayed or minimal response to the administration of BRIDION [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  . Thus, it is important to monitor ventilation until recovery occurs.



    5.5 Waiting Times for Re-Administration of Neuromuscular Blocking Agents for Intubation Following Reversal with BRIDION



  A minimum waiting time is necessary before administration of a steroidal neuromuscular blocking agent after administration of BRIDION.



 Table 1: Re-administration of Rocuronium or Vecuronium after Reversal (up to 4 mg/kg BRIDION) 
        Minimum Waiting Time                          NMBA and Dose to be Administered                    
  
              5 minutes                                     1.2 mg/kg rocuronium                          
               4 hours                           0.6 mg/kg rocuronium or0.1 mg/kg vecuronium              
        When rocuronium 1.2 mg/kg is administered within 30 minutes after reversal with BRIDION, the onset of neuromuscular blockade may be delayed up to approximately 4 minutes and the duration of neuromuscular blockade may be shortened up to approximately 15 minutes.
 

 The recommended waiting time in patients with mild or moderate renal impairment for re-use of 0.6 mg/kg rocuronium or 0.1 mg/kg vecuronium after reversal with up to 4 mg/kg BRIDION should be 24 hours. If a shorter waiting time is required, the rocuronium dose for a new neuromuscular blockade should be 1.2 mg/kg.



 For re-administration of rocuronium or administration of vecuronium after reversal of rocuronium with 16 mg/kg BRIDION, a waiting time of 24 hours is suggested.



 If neuromuscular blockade is required before the recommended waiting time has elapsed, use a nonsteroidal neuromuscular blocking agent  . The onset of a depolarizing neuromuscular blocking agent might be slower than expected, because a substantial fraction of postjunctional nicotinic receptors can still be occupied by the neuromuscular blocking agent.



    5.6 Interactions Potentially Affecting the Efficacy of Other Drugs



  Due to the administration of BRIDION, certain drugs, including hormonal contraceptives, could become less effective due to a lowering of the (free) plasma concentrations. In this situation, consider the re-administration of the other drug, the administration of a therapeutically equivalent drug (preferably from a different chemical class), and/or non-pharmacological interventions as appropriate [see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ]  .



    5.7 Risk of Recurrence of Neuromuscular Blockade Due to Displacement Interactions



  Recurrence of neuromuscular blockade may occur due to displacement of rocuronium or vecuronium from BRIDION by other drugs [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  . In this situation the patient may require mechanical ventilation. Administration of the drug which caused displacement should be stopped in case of an infusion. The risk of displacement reactions will be the highest in the time period equivalent to 3 times the half-life of BRIDION [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.8 Risk of Recurrence of Neuromuscular Blockade with Lower Than Recommended Dosing



  The use of lower than recommended doses of BRIDION may lead to an increased risk of recurrence of neuromuscular blockade after initial reversal and is not recommended [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ,  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.9 Risk of Recurrence of Neuromuscular Blockade Due to the Administration of Drugs that Potentiate Neuromuscular Blockade



  When drugs which potentiate neuromuscular blockade are used in the post-operative phase, special attention should be paid to the possibility of recurrence of neuromuscular blockade. Refer to the package insert for rocuronium or vecuronium for a list of the specific drugs which potentiate neuromuscular blockade. In case recurrence of neuromuscular blockade is observed, the patient may require mechanical ventilation.



    5.10 Risk of Coagulopathy and Bleeding



  BRIDION doses up to 16 mg/kg were associated with increases in the coagulation parameters activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) and prothrombin time/international normalized ratio [PT(INR)] of up to 25% for up to 1 hour in healthy volunteers.



 In patients undergoing major orthopedic surgery of the lower extremity who were concomitantly treated with heparin or low molecular weight heparin for thromboprophylaxis, increases in aPTT and PT(INR) of 5.5% and 3.0%, respectively, were observed in the hour following BRIDION 4 mg/kg administration. This clinical trial did not demonstrate an increased blood loss or anemia incidence with BRIDION compared with usual treatment. The rate of adjudicated bleeding events within 24 hours was 2.9% for sugammadex and 4.1% for usual care. The rate of post-operative anemia was 21% for sugammadex and 22% for usual care. The mean 24-hour drainage volume was 0.46 L for sugammadex and 0.48 L for usual care. The need for any post-operative transfusion was 37% for sugammadex and 39% for usual care.



  In vitro  experiments demonstrated additional aPTT and PT(INR) prolongations for sugammadex in combination with vitamin K antagonists, unfractionated heparin, low molecular weight heparinoids, rivaroxaban, and dabigatran up to ~25% and ~50% at Cmaxlevels of sugammadex corresponding to 4 mg/kg and 16 mg/kg doses, respectively.



 Since bleeding risk has been studied systematically with only heparin and low molecular weight heparin thromboprophylaxis and 4 mg/kg doses of sugammadex coagulation parameters should be carefully monitored in patients with known coagulopathies, being treated with therapeutic anticoagulation, receiving thromboprophylaxis drugs other than heparin and low molecular weight heparin, or receiving thromboprophylaxis drugs and who then receive a dose of 16 mg/kg sugammadex.



    5.11 Renal Impairment



  BRIDION is not recommended for use in patients with severe renal impairment, including those requiring dialysis [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ]  . With regard to the recommended waiting time for re-administration in patients with mild or moderate renal impairment, see Waiting Times for Re-administration of Neuromuscular Blocking Agents for Intubation Following Reversal with BRIDION   [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



    5.12 Light Anesthesia



  When neuromuscular blockade was reversed intentionally in the middle of anesthesia in clinical trials, e.g., when investigating urgent reversal, signs of light anesthesia were noted occasionally (movement, coughing, grimacing and suckling of the tracheal tube).



    5.13 Reversal after Rocuronium or Vecuronium Administration in the ICU



  BRIDION has not been studied for reversal following rocuronium or vecuronium administration in the ICU.



    5.14 Reversal of Neuromuscular Blocking Agents Other Than Rocuronium or Vecuronium



  Do not use BRIDION to reverse blockade induced by nonsteroidal  neuromuscular blocking agents such as succinylcholine or benzylisoquinolinium compounds.



 Do not use BRIDION to reverse neuromuscular blockade induced by steroidal  neuromuscular blocking agents other than rocuronium or vecuronium.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
