<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="brisdelle" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6      ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Suicidality [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Serotonin syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Abnormal bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Angle-Closure Glaucoma [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )] 
 *  Hyponatremia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Bone Fracture [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Mania/Hypomania [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Seizure [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Akathisia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) reported in clinical trials were: headache, fatigue, and nausea/vomiting (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Noven Therapeutics, LLC at 1-800-455-8070 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1      Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot directly be compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to BRISDELLE in the one 8-week Phase 2 randomized, placebo-controlled trial and the two Phase 3 randomized, placebo-controlled, 12-week and 24-week trials for the treatment of moderate to severe VMS  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  . In these trials, a total of 635 women were exposed to BRISDELLE 7.5 mg administered orally once daily and 641 women received placebo. The majority of BRISDELLE-treated patients were Caucasian (68%) and African American (30%), with a mean age of 55 years (range 40 to 73 years). Women with a history of suicidal ideation or suicidal behavior were excluded from these studies.



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Study Discontinuation  : A total of 4.7% of women taking BRISDELLE discontinued from the clinical trials due to an adverse reaction, compared to 3.7% of women on placebo; the most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation among paroxetine-treated women were: abdominal pain (0.3%), attention disturbances (0.3%), headache (0.3%), and suicidal ideation (0.3%).



   Common Adverse Reactions  : Overall, based on investigators' determinations about what events were likely to be drug-related, about 20% of women treated with BRISDELLE reported at least 1 adverse reaction in the three controlled studies. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2% and more common among BRISDELLE-treated women) reported in these studies were headache, fatigue/malaise/lethargy, and nausea/vomiting. Of these commonly reported adverse reactions, nausea occurred primarily within the first 4 weeks of treatment and fatigue occurred primarily within the first week of treatment, and decreased in frequency with continued therapy.



 The adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients in the BRISDELLE group and at a higher incidence than placebo are shown in  Table 1  for the pooled Phase 2 and Phase 3 trials.



 Table 1      Frequency of Adverse Reactions in the Phase 2 and Phase 3 Trials (&gt;= 2% and at a higher incidence than placebo) 
                              Frequency n (%)           
   BRISDELLE (n = 635)        Placebo (n = 641)         
   Nervous system disorders     
 Headache                   40 (6.3)                   31 (4.8)                    
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
 Fatigue, malaise, lethargy  31 (4.9)                   18 (2.8)                    
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
 Nausea, vomiting           27 (4.3)                   15 (2.3)                    
      Certain symptoms were seen more frequently in women at the time of discontinuation of BRISDELLE compared to women discontinuing placebo, and have also been reported upon discontinuation of other formulations of paroxetine, particularly when abrupt. These include increased dreaming/nightmares, muscle cramps/spasms/twitching, headache, nervousness/anxiety, fatigue/tiredness, restless feeling in legs, and trouble sleeping/insomnia. While these events are generally self-limiting, there have been reports of serious discontinuation symptoms with other formulations of paroxetine.
 

   Serious Adverse Reactions  : In the pooled Phase 2 and Phase 3 trials, three BRISDELLE-treated patients reported a serious adverse reaction of suicidal ideation and one BRISDELLE-treated patient reported a serious adverse reaction of suicide attempt. There were no serious adverse reactions of suicidal ideation or suicide attempt reported among the placebo-treated patients.



   6.2      Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified from clinical studies of paroxetine and during post-approval use of other formulations of paroxetine. Because some of these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  : Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, Events related to impaired hematopoiesis (including aplastic anemia, pancytopenia, bone marrow aplasia, agranulocytosis).



   Cardiac Disorders  : Atrial fibrillation, Pulmonary edema, Ventricular fibrillation, Ventricular tachycardia (including torsades de pointes).



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : Pancreatitis, Pancreatitis hemorrhagic, Vomiting.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  : Death, Drug withdrawal syndrome, Malaise.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders  : Drug-induced liver injury, Hepatic failure, Jaundice.



   Immune System Disorders  : Anaphylactoid reaction, Angioedema, Toxic epidermal necrolysis.



   Investigations  : Elevated liver tests (the most severe cases were deaths due to liver necrosis, and grossly elevated transaminases associated with severe liver dysfunction).



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  : Diabetes mellitus inadequate control, Type 2 diabetes mellitus.



   Nervous System Disorders  : Neuroleptic malignant syndrome, Paresthesia, Somnolence, Tremor.



   Psychiatric Disorders  : Aggression, Agitation, Anxiety, Confusional state, Depression, Disorientation, Homicidal ideation, Insomnia, Restlessness.



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  : Pulmonary hypertension.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  : Hyperhidrosis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS

  WARNING:  SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS

    Antidepressants, including selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), have been shown to increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in pediatric and young adult patients when used to treat major depressive disorder and other psychiatric disorders.  Because BRISDELLE is an SSRI, monitor patients closely for worsening and for emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS



   See full prescribing information for complete   boxed warning  .  



 *  Potential for increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (5.1) 
 *  Monitor for worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5      WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Suicidality : Monitor for suicidality or unusual changes in behavior (  5.1  ) 
 *   Serotonin Syndrome : Serotonin syndrome, which is potentially life-threatening, has been reported with SSRIs. Discontinue BRISDELLE and initiate supportive treatment (  5.2  ,  7.3  ) 
 *   Tamoxifen : Efficacy of tamoxifen may be reduced when administered concomitantly with BRISDELLE (  5.3  ,  7.1  ) 
 *   Abnormal Bleeding : Caution patients about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of BRISDELLE and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation (  5.4  ,  7.1  ) 
 *   Angle-Closure Glaucoma: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients who have untreated anatomically narrow angles and who are treated with antidepressants. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Hyponatremia : Can occur in association with syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH) (  5.6  ) 
 *   Bone Fracture : Epidemiological studies have reported an association between SSRI treatment and fractures (  5.7  ) 
 *   Activation of Mania/Hypomania : Screen for bipolar disorder and monitor for mania/hypomania (  5.8  ) 
 *   Seizures : Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold (  5.9  ) 
 *   Akathisia : Can occur, most likely in the first few weeks of treatment (  5.10  ) 
 *   Cognitive and Motor Impairment : May cause impairment; patients should not operate machinery or motor vehicles until certain that BRISDELLE does not affect them adversely (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1      Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviors



  BRISDELLE is not approved for any psychiatric condition.



 Antidepressants, including those that contain an SSRI, increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in pediatric and young adult patients when used to treat major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. There is limited information regarding suicidality in women who use BRISDELLE for treatment of VMS. The BRISDELLE trials excluded women with a presence or history of previous psychiatric disorders.



 Consider discontinuing BRISDELLE in patients with worsening depression or those who experience emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  All patients being treated with BRISDELLE should be observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of treatment.  



 Anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania have been reported in patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD as well as for other psychiatric and nonpsychiatric indications. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with BRISDELLE should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to healthcare providers.  



    5.2      Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with SSRIs, including paroxetine, alone but particularly with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort), and with drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (in particular, MAOIs, both those intended to treat depression and others such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue).



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Monitor patients for the emergence of serotonin syndrome.



 The concomitant use of BRISDELLE with MAOIs is contraindicated. Do not start BRISDELLE in a patient who is being treated with MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue. All reports with methylene blue that provided information on the route of administration involved intravenous administration in the dose range of 1 mg/kg to 8 mg/kg. No reports involved the administration of methylene blue by other routes (such as oral tablets or local tissue injection) or at lower doses. There may be circumstances when it is necessary to initiate treatment with an MAOI such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue in a patient taking BRISDELLE. BRISDELLE should be discontinued before initiating treatment with the MAOI [see Contraindications (  4.1  ) and Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  .



 If concomitant use of BRISDELLE with other serotonergic drugs (e.g., triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort) is clinically warranted, consider the increased risk of serotonin syndrome and carefully observe the patient, particularly during treatment initiation [see Contraindications (  4.1  ) Drug Interactions (  7.3  )]  .



  Discontinue BRISDELLE and any concomitant serotonergic agents immediately if the above events occur and initiate supportive symptomatic treatment.  



    5.3      Potential Impact on Tamoxifen Efficacy



  It is uncertain whether the co-administration of paroxetine and tamoxifen has a significant adverse effect on the efficacy of tamoxifen. Some studies have shown that the efficacy of tamoxifen, as measured by the risk of breast cancer relapse/mortality, may be reduced when co-prescribed with paroxetine as a result of paroxetine's irreversible inhibition of CYP2D6 [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  . However, other studies have failed to demonstrate such a risk. When tamoxifen is used for the treatment or prevention of breast cancer, weigh the likely benefit of BRISDELLE for treating VMS vs. the risk of possible decreased tamoxifen effectiveness, and consider avoiding the concomitant use of BRISDELLE for VMS treatment.



    5.4      Abnormal Bleeding



  SSRIs, including BRISDELLE, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), warfarin, and other anticoagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding events related to SSRIs have ranged from ecchymosis, hematoma, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages. Caution patients about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of BRISDELLE and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



     5.5      Angle-Closure Glaucoma  



   The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressants and BRISDELLE may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.  



    5.6      Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia may occur as a result of treatment with SSRIs, including BRISDELLE. Elderly patients may be at greater risk. In many cases, the hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported in patients using SSRIs. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are volume-depleted can be at greater risk. Consider discontinuation of BRISDELLE in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia and institute appropriate medical intervention.



 Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which can lead to falls. Signs and symptoms associated with more severe and/or acute cases have included hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.7      Bone Fracture



  Epidemiological studies on bone fracture risk following exposure to SSRIs have reported an association between SSRI treatment and fractures. It is unknown to what extent fracture risk is directly attributable to SSRI treatment. If a BRISDELLE-treated patient presents with unexplained bone pain, point tenderness, swelling, or bruising, consider the possibility of a fragility fracture.



    5.8      Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder and Monitoring for Mania/Hypomania



  BRISDELLE is only indicated for the treatment of moderate to severe VMS and is not approved for use in treating either depression or bipolar depression. However, prior to initiating treatment with BRISDELLE, all patients should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that use of an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder.



    5.9      Seizures



  In premarketing testing of paroxetine, seizures occurred in 0.1% of paroxetine-treated patients. Use BRISDELLE cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold. Evaluate and consider discontinuing use in any patient who develops seizures.



    5.10      Akathisia



  The use of paroxetine or other SSRIs has been associated with the development of akathisia, which is characterized by an inner sense of restlessness and psychomotor agitation such as an inability to sit or stand still usually associated with subjective distress. This is most likely to occur within the first few weeks of treatment. Discontinue treatment with BRISDELLLE if akathisia occurs.



    5.11      Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  BRISDELLE has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including motor vehicles, until they are reasonably certain that the drug treatment does not affect them adversely.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
