<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="briviact" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Neurological Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity: Bronchospasm and Angioedema [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Withdrawal of Antiepileptic Drugs [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (at least 5% for BRIVIACT and at least 2% more frequently than placebo) are somnolence/sedation, dizziness, fatigue, and nausea/vomiting. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact UCB, Inc. at 1-844-599-2273 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In all controlled and uncontrolled trials performed in adult epilepsy patients, BRIVIACT was administered as adjunctive therapy to 2437 patients. Of these patients, 1929 were treated for at least 6 months, 1500 for at least 12 months, 1056 for at least 24 months, and 758 for at least 36 months. A total of 1558 patients (1099 patients treated with BRIVIACT and 459 patients treated with placebo) constituted the safety population in the pooled analysis of Phase 3 placebo-controlled studies in patients with partial-onset seizures (Studies 1, 2, and 3)  [see      Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . The adverse reactions presented in Table 2 are based on this safety population; the median length of treatment in these studies was 12 weeks. Of the patients in those studies, approximately 51% were male, 74% were Caucasian, and the mean age was 38 years.



 In the Phase 3 controlled epilepsy studies, adverse events occurred in 68% of patients treated with BRIVIACT and 62% treated with placebo. The most common adverse reactions occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in patients treated with BRIVIACT doses of at least 50 mg/day and greater than placebo were somnolence and sedation (16%), dizziness (12%), fatigue (9%), and nausea and vomiting symptoms (5%).



 The discontinuation rates due to adverse events were 5%, 8%, and 7% for patients randomized to receive BRIVIACT at the recommended doses of 50 mg, 100 mg, and 200 mg/day, respectively, compared to 4% in patients randomized to receive placebo.



 Table 2 lists adverse reactions for BRIVIACT that occurred at least 2% more frequently for BRIVIACT doses of at least 50 mg/day than placebo.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions in Pooled Placebo-Controlled Adjunctive Therapy Studies in Patients with Partial-Onset Seizures (BRIVIACT 50 mg/day, 100 mg/day, and 200 mg/day) 
 Adverse Reactions                                       BRIVIACT(N=803)%            Placebo(N=459)%        
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
 Nausea/vomiting symptoms                                        5                          3               
 Constipation                                                    2                          0               
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
 Somnolence and sedation                                        16                          8               
 Dizziness                                                      12                          7               
 Fatigue                                                         9                          4               
 Cerebellar coordination and balance disturbances                3                          1               
     Psychiatric disorders                                                                                  
 Irritability                                                    3                          1               
         There was no apparent dose-dependent increase in adverse reactions listed in Table 2 with the exception of somnolence and sedation.
 

     Hematologic Abnormalities  



 BRIVIACT can cause hematologic abnormalities. In the Phase 3 controlled adjunctive epilepsy studies, a total of 1.8% of BRIVIACT-treated patients and 1.1% of placebo-treated patients had at least one clinically significant decreased white blood cell count (&lt;3.0 * 10  9  /L), and 0.3% of BRIVIACT-treated patients and 0% of placebo-treated patients had at least one clinically significant decreased neutrophil count (&lt;1.0 * 10  9  /L).



     Adverse Reactions with BRIVIACT Injection  



 Adverse reactions with BRIVIACT injection were generally similar to those observed with BRIVIACT tablets. Other adverse events that occurred in at least 3% of patients who received BRIVIACT injection included dysgeusia, euphoric mood, feeling drunk, and infusion site pain.



     Comparison by Sex  



 There were no significant differences by sex in the incidence of adverse reactions.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Suicidal Behavior and Ideation : Monitor patients for suicidal behavior and ideation. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Neurological Adverse Reactions : Monitor for somnolence and fatigue, and advise patients not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on BRIVIACT. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Psychiatric Adverse Reactions : Behavioral reactions including psychotic symptoms, irritability, depression, aggressive behavior, and anxiety; monitor patients for symptoms. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity: Bronchospasm and Angioedema : Advise patients to seek immediate medical care. Discontinue and do not restart BRIVIACT if hypersensitivity occurs. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Withdrawal of Antiepileptic Drugs : BRIVIACT should be gradually withdrawn. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including BRIVIACT, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed. Table 1 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 1: Risk of Suicidal Thoughts or Behaviors by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis 
 Indication        Placebo Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients  Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients  Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients  Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients   
  
 Epilepsy          1.0                 3.4                 3.5                       2.4                        
 Psychiatric       5.7                 8.5                 1.5                       2.9                        
 Other             1.0                 1.8                 1.9                       0.9                        
 Total             2.4                 4.3                 1.8                       1.9                        
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials in patients with epilepsy than in clinical trials in patients with psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing BRIVIACT or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behaviors with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



    5.2 Neurological Adverse Reactions



  BRIVIACT causes somnolence, fatigue, dizziness, and disturbance in coordination. Patients should be monitored for these signs and symptoms and advised not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on BRIVIACT to gauge whether it adversely affects their ability to drive or operate machinery.



    Somnolence and Fatigue  



 BRIVIACT causes dose-dependent increases in somnolence and fatigue-related adverse reactions (fatigue, asthenia, malaise, hypersomnia, sedation, and lethargy) [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . In the Phase 3 controlled adjunctive epilepsy trials, these events were reported in 25% of patients randomized to receive BRIVIACT at least 50 mg/day (20% at 50 mg/day, 26% at 100 mg/day, and 27% at 200 mg/day) compared to 14% of patients who received placebo. The risk is greatest early in treatment but can occur at any time.



    Dizziness and Disturbance in Gait and Coordination  



 BRIVIACT causes adverse reactions related to dizziness and disturbance in gait and coordination (dizziness, vertigo, balance disorder, ataxia, nystagmus, gait disturbance, and abnormal coordination) [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  In the Phase 3 controlled adjunctive epilepsy trials, these events were reported in 16% of patients randomized to receive BRIVIACT at least 50 mg/day compared to 10% of patients who received placebo. The risk is greatest early in treatment but can occur at any time.



    5.3 Psychiatric Adverse Reactions



  BRIVIACT causes psychiatric adverse reactions. In the Phase 3 controlled adjunctive epilepsy trials, psychiatric adverse reactions were reported in approximately 13% of patients who received BRIVIACT (at least 50 mg/day) compared to 8% of patients who received placebo. Psychiatric events included both non-psychotic symptoms (irritability, anxiety, nervousness, aggression, belligerence, anger, agitation, restlessness, depression, depressed mood, tearfulness, apathy, altered mood, mood swings, affect lability, psychomotor hyperactivity, abnormal behavior, and adjustment disorder) and psychotic symptoms (psychotic disorder along with hallucination, paranoia, acute psychosis, and psychotic behavior). A total of 1.7% of adult patients treated with BRIVIACT discontinued treatment because of psychiatric reactions compared to 1.3% of patients who received placebo.



    5.4 Hypersensitivity: Bronchospasm and Angioedema



  BRIVIACT can cause hypersensitivity reactions. Bronchospasm and angioedema have been reported in patients taking BRIVIACT. If a patient develops hypersensitivity reactions after treatment with BRIVIACT, the drug should be discontinued. BRIVIACT is contraindicated in patients with a prior hypersensitivity reaction to brivaracetam or any of the inactive ingredients [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.5 Withdrawal of Antiepileptic Drugs



  As with most antiepileptic drugs, BRIVIACT should generally be withdrawn gradually because of the risk of increased seizure frequency and status epilepticus [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  and  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . But if withdrawal is needed because of a serious adverse event, rapid discontinuation can be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
