<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="buprenex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS:

  The most frequent side effect in clinical studies involving 1,133 patients was sedation which occurred in approximately two-thirds of the patients. Although sedated, these patients could easily be aroused to an alert state.



   Other less frequent adverse reactions occurring in 5-10% of the patients were:  



 Nausea Dizziness/Vertigo



   Occurring in 1-5% of the patients  :



 Sweating Headache



 Hypotension Nausea/Vomiting



 Vomiting Hypoventilation



 Miosis



   The following adverse reactions were reported to have occurred in less than 1% of the patients:  



   CNS Effect:  confusion, blurred vision, euphoria, weakness/fatigue, dry mouth, nervousness, depression, slurred speech, paresthesia.



   Cardiovascular:  hypertension, tachycardia, bradycardia.



   Gastrointestinal:  constipation.



   Respiratory:  dyspnea, cyanosis.



   Dermatological:  pruritus.



   Ophthalmological:  diplopia, visual abnormalities.



   Miscellaneous:  injection site reaction, urinary retention, dreaming, flushing/warmth, chills/cold, tinnitus, conjunctivitis, Wenckebach block, and psychosis.



 Other effects observed infrequently include malaise, hallucinations, depersonalization, coma, dyspepsia, flatulence, apnea, rash, amblyopia, tremor, and pallor.



 The following reactions have been reported to occur rarely: loss of appetite, dysphoria/agitation, diarrhea, urticaria, and convulsions/lack of muscle coordination.



   Allergic Reactions:  Cases of acute and chronic hypersensitivity to buprenorphine have been reported both in clinical trials and in the postmarketing experience of Buprenex and other buprenorphine- containing products. The most common signs and symptoms include rashes, hives, and pruritus. Cases of bronchospasm, angioneurotic edema, and anaphylactic shock have been reported. A history of hypersensitivity to buprenorphine is a contraindication to Buprenex.



 In the United Kingdom, buprenorphine hydrochloride was made available under monitored release regulation during the first year of sale, and yielded data from 1,736 physicians on 9,123 patients (17,120 administrations). Data on 240 children under the age of 18 years were included in this monitored release program. No important new adverse effects attributable to buprenorphine hydrochloride were observed.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
