<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="busulfex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Myelosuppression [see    Warnings and Precautions (     5.1   )]  
 *    Seizures [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2    )]  
 *    HVOD [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3    )]  
 *    Embryo-fetal Toxicity [see    Warnings and Precautions (     5.4  )] 
 *    Cardiac Tamponade [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5    )]  
 *    Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia [see    Warnings and Precautions (     5.6   )]  
 *    Cellular Dysplasia [see    Warnings and Precautions (     5.7   )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than 60%) were: myelosuppression, nausea, stomatitis, vomiting, anorexia, diarrhea, insomnia, fever, hypomagnesemia, abdominal pain, anxiety, headache, hyperglycemia and hypokalemia (  6.1)  
 

 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Otsuka America Pharmaceutical, Inc. at 1-800-438-9927 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reaction information is primarily derived from the clinical study (N=61) of BUSULFEX and the data obtained for high-dose oral busulfan conditioning in the setting of randomized, controlled trials identified through a literature review.



 In the BUSULFEX (busulfan) Injection allogeneic stem cell transplantation clinical trial, all patients were treated with BUSULFEX 0.8 mg per kg as a two-hour infusion every six hours for 16 doses over four days, combined with cyclophosphamide 60 mg per kg x2 days. Ninety-three percent (93%) of evaluable patients receiving this dose of BUSULFEX maintained an AUC less than 1,500 uMmin for dose 9, which has generally been considered the level that minimizes the risk of HVOD.



 Table 1 lists the non-hematologic adverse reactions events through BMT Day +28 at a rate greater than or equal to 20% in patients treated with BUSULFEX prior to allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation.



 Table 1: Summary of the Incidence (greater than or equal to 20%) of Non-Hematologic Adverse Reactions through BMT Day +28 in Patients who Received BUSULFEX Prior to Allogeneic Hematopoietic Progenitor Cell Transplantation 
  Non-Hematological Adverse ReactionsIncludes all reported adverse reactions regardless of severity (toxicity grades 1-4)    Percent Incidence                 
  BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                            
                                                          Fever                                                   
                                                                                                                    80                                
                                                          Headache                                                
                                                                                                                    69                                
                                                          Asthenia                                                
                                                                                                                    51                                
                                                          Chills                                                  
                                                                                                                    46                                
                                                          Pain                                                    
                                                                                                                    44                                
                                                          Edema General                                           
                                                                                                                    28                                
                                                          Allergic Reaction                                       
                                                                                                                    26                                
                                                          Chest Pain                                              
                                                                                                                    26                                
                                                          Inflammation at Injection Site                          
                                                                                                                    25                                
                                                          Back Pain                                               
                                                                                                                    23                                
  CARDIOVASCULAR SYSTEM                                                                      
                                                          Tachycardia                                             
                                                                                                                    44                                
                                                          Hypertension                                            
                                                                                                                    36                                
                                                          Thrombosis                                              
                                                                                                                    33                                
                                                          Vasodilation                                            
                                                                                                                    25                                
  DIGESTIVE SYSTEM                                                                           
                                                          Nausea                                                  
                                                                                                                    98                                
                                                          Stomatitis (Mucositis)                                  
                                                                                                                    97                                
                                                          Vomiting                                                
                                                                                                                    95                                
                                                          Anorexia                                                
                                                                                                                    85                                
                                                          Diarrhea                                                
                                                                                                                    84                                
                                                          Abdominal Pain                                          
                                                                                                                    72                                
                                                          Dyspepsia                                               
                                                                                                                    44                                
                                                          Constipation                                            
                                                                                                                    38                                
                                                          Dry Mouth                                               
                                                                                                                    26                                
                                                          Rectal Disorder                                         
                                                                                                                    25                                
                                                          Abdominal Enlargement                                   
                                                                                                                    23                                
  METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL SYSTEM                                                           
                                                          Hypomagnesemia                                          
                                                                                                                    77                                
                                                          Hyperglycemia                                           
                                                                                                                    66                                
                                                          Hypokalemia                                             
                                                                                                                    64                                
                                                          Hypocalcemia                                            
                                                                                                                    49                                
                                                          Hyperbilirubinemia                                      
                                                                                                                    49                                
                                                          Edema                                                   
                                                                                                                    36                                
                                                          SGPT Elevation                                          
                                                                                                                    31                                
                                                          Creatinine Increased                                    
                                                                                                                    21                                
  NERVOUS SYSTEM                                                                             
                                                          Insomnia                                                
                                                                                                                    84                                
                                                          Anxiety                                                 
                                                                                                                    72                                
                                                          Dizziness                                               
                                                                                                                    30                                
                                                          Depression                                              
                                                                                                                    23                                
  RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                                                                         
                                                          Rhinitis                                                
                                                                                                                    44                                
                                                          Lung Disorder                                           
                                                                                                                    34                                
                                                          Cough                                                   
                                                                                                                    28                                
                                                          Epistaxis                                               
                                                                                                                    25                                
                                                          Dyspnea                                                 
                                                                                                                    25                                
  SKIN AND APPENDAGES                                                                        
                                                          Rash                                                    
                                                                                                                    57                                
                                                          Pruritus                                                
                                                                                                                    28                                
            Additional Adverse Reactions by Body System    
 

   Hematologic    :      Prolonged prothrombin time



   Gastrointestinal:      Esophagitis, ileus, hematemesis, pancreatitis, rectal discomfort



   Hepatic:      Alkaline phosphatase increases, jaundice, hepatomegaly



   Graft-versus-host disease:  Graft-versus-host disease. There were 3 deaths (5%) attributed to GVHD.



   Edema:  Hypervolemia, or documented weight increase



   Infection:  Infection, pneumonia (fatal in one patient and life-threatening in 3% of patients)



   Cardiovascular:  Arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, ventricular extrasystoles, third degree heart block, thrombosis (all episodes were associated with the central venous catheter), hypotension, flushing and hot flashes, cardiomegaly, ECG abnormality, left-sided heart failure, and pericardial effusion



   Pulmonary    :      Hyperventilation, alveolar hemorrhage (fatal in 3%), pharyngitis, hiccup, asthma, atelectasis, pleural effusion, hypoxia, hemoptysis, sinusitis, and interstitial fibrosis (fatal in a single case)



   Neurologic:  Cerebral hemorrhage, coma, delirium, agitation, encephalopathy, confusion, hallucinations, lethargy, somnolence



   Renal:  BUN increased, dysuria, oliguria, hematuria, hemorrhagic cystitis



   Skin:  Alopecia, vesicular rash, maculopapular rash, vesiculo-bullous rash, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema nodosum, acne, skin discoloration



   Metabolic:  Hypophosphatemia, hyponatremia



   Other Events:  Injection site pain, myalgia, arthralgia, ear disorder



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.    The following adverse reactions (reported as MedRA terms) have been identified during post-approval use of BUSULFEX (busulfan) Injection:



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  : febrile neutropenia



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  : tumor lysis syndrome



   Vascular Disorders  : thrombotic microangiopathy (TMA)



   Infections and Infestations  : severe bacterial, viral (e.g., cytomegalovirus viremia) and fungal infections; and sepsis.



   6.3 Oral Busulfan Literature Review

  A literature review identified four randomized, controlled trials that evaluated a high-dose oral busulfan-containing conditioning regimen for allogeneic bone marrow transplantation in the setting of CML  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  . The safety outcomes reported in those trials are summarized in Table 2 below for a mixed population of hematological malignancies (AML, CML, and ALL).



 Table 2: Summary of safety analyses from the randomized, controlled trials utilizing a high dose oral busulfan-containing conditioning regimen that were identified in a literature review. 
  Clift       
  CML Chronic Phase    
  TRMTRM = Transplantation Related Mortality    VODVOD = Veno-Occlusive Disease of the liver    GVHDGVHD = Graft versus Host Disease    Pulmonary            Hemorrhagic           Seizure              
                                                           Cystitis                                   
  Death       No Report            Acute&gt;=Grade 2    1 death from         No Report             No Report            
  &lt;=100d                           =35%    Idiopathic                                                      
  =4.1%                            Chronic=41%    Interstitial                                                    
  (3/73)                           (30/73)    Pneumonitis                                                     
                                      And                                                             
                                      1 death from                                                    
                                      Pulmonary                                                       
                                      Fibrosis                                                        
  Devergie    
  CML Chronic Phase    
  TRM         VOD                  GVHD    Pulmonary            Hemorrhagic           Seizure              
                                                           Cystitis                                   
  38%         7.7% (5/65)          Acute&gt;=Grade 2    Interstitial         10.8% (7/65)          No report            
              Deaths=4.6%          =41%    Pneumonitis=                                                    
              (3/65)               (24/59 at risk)    16.9% (11/65)                                                   
  Ringden     
  CML, AML, ALL    
  TRM         VOD                  GVHD    Pulmonary            Hemorrhagic           Seizure              
                                                           Cystitis                                   
  28%         12%                  Acute&gt;=Grade 2    Interstitial         24%                   6%                   
                                   GVHD=26%    Pneumonitis                                                     
                                   Chronic GVHD    =14%                                                            
                                   =45%                                                                    
  Blume       
  CML, AML, ALL    
  TRM         VOD                  GVHD    Pulmonary            Hemorrhagic           Seizure              
                                                           Cystitis                                   
  No Report    Deaths               Acute&gt;=Grade 2    No Report            No Report             No Report            
              =4.9%                GVHD=22%                                                                    
                                   (13/58 at risk)                                                                    
                                   Chronic GVHD                                                                    
                                   =31%                                                                    
                                   (14/45 at risk)                                                                    
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: MYELOSUPPRESSION 

  WARNING: MYELOSUPPRESSION 

    BUSULFEX  (r)   (busulfan) Injection causes severe and prolonged myelosuppression at the recommended dosage. Hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation is required to prevent potentially fatal complications of the prolonged myelosuppression [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: MYELOSUPPRESSION 



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Causes severe and prolonged myelosuppression. (5.1) 
 *  Hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation is required to prevent potentially fatal complications of the prolonged myelosuppression. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  The following warnings pertain to different physiologic effects of BUSULFEX in the setting of allogeneic transplantation.



    EXCERPT:    *    Seizures: Initiate anticonvulsant prophylactic therapy prior to treatment with BUSULFEX. Monitor patients with history of seizure disorder, head trauma or receiving epileptogenic drugs  (5.2  ) 
 *    Hepatic Veno-Occlusive Disease (HVOD): Increased risk of developing HVOD at AUC greater than 1,500 uMmin. Monitor serum transaminases, alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin daily (  5.3)   
 *    Embryo-fetal Toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise of potential risk to a fetus and use of effective contraception (  5.4  ,  8.1  ,  8.3)   
 *    Cardiac tamponade has been reported in pediatric patients with thalassemia who received high doses of oral busulfan and cyclophosphamide. Abdominal pain and vomiting preceded the tamponade in most patients (  5.5)   
    
 

   5.1 Myelosuppression



  The most frequent serious consequence of treatment with BUSULFEX at the recommended dose and schedule is prolonged myelosuppression, occurring in all patients (100%). Severe granulocytopenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, or any combination thereof may develop. Hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation is required to prevent potentially fatal complications of the prolonged myelosuppression. Monitor complete blood counts, including white blood cell differentials, and quantitative platelet counts daily during treatment and until engraftment is demonstrated [see     Patient Counseling Information (17     )].  Absolute neutrophil counts dropped below 0.5x10  9  /L at a median of 4 days post-transplant in 100% of patients treated in the BUSULFEX clinical trial. The absolute neutrophil count recovered at a median of 13 days following allogeneic transplantation when prophylactic G-CSF was used in the majority of patients. Thrombocytopenia (less than 25,000/mm  3  or requiring platelet transfusion) occurred at a median of 5-6 days in 98% of patients. Anemia (hemoglobin less than 8.0 g/dL) occurred in 69% of patients. Use antibiotic therapy and platelet and red blood cell support when medically indicated.



    5.2 Seizures



  Seizures have been reported in patients receiving high-dose oral busulfan at doses producing plasma drug levels similar to those achieved following the recommended dosage of BUSULFEX. Despite prophylactic therapy with phenytoin, one seizure (1/42 patients) was reported during an autologous transplantation clinical trial of BUSULFEX. This episode occurred during the cyclophosphamide portion of the conditioning regimen, 36 hours after the last BUSULFEX dose. Initiate phenytoin therapy or any other alternative anti-convulsant prophylactic therapy (e.g., benzodiazepines, valproic acid or levetiracetam) prior to BUSULFEX treatment [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1  )]  . Use caution when administering the recommended dose of BUSULFEX to patients with a history of a seizure disorder or head trauma or who are receiving other potentially epileptogenic drugs [see  Patient Counseling Information (17  )]  .



    5.3 Hepatic Veno-Occlusive Disease (HVOD)



  Current literature suggests that high busulfan area under the plasma concentration verses time curve (AUC) values (greater than 1,500 uMmin) may be associated with an increased risk of developing HVOD. Patients who have received prior radiation therapy, greater than or equal to three cycles of chemotherapy, or a prior progenitor cell transplant may be at an increased risk of developing HVOD with the recommended BUSULFEX dose and regimen. Based on clinical examination and laboratory findings, HVOD was diagnosed in 8% (5/61) of patients treated with BUSULFEX in the setting of allogeneic transplantation, was fatal in 2/5 cases (40%), and yielded an overall mortality from HVOD in the entire study population of 2/61 (3%).Three of the five patients diagnosed with HVOD were retrospectively found to meet the Jones' criteria. The incidence of HVOD reported in the literature from the randomized, controlled trials was 7.7%-12% [see     Clinical Studies (14     )].  Monitor serum transaminases, alkaline phosphatase, and bilirubin daily through BMT Day +28 to detect hepatotoxicity, which may herald the onset of HVOD [see     Patient Counseling Information (17     )].  



    5.4 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  BUSULFEX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman based on animal data. Busulfan was teratogenic in mice, rats, and rabbits. The solvent, DMA, may also cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman based on findings in animals. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus. Advise females and males of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during and after treatment with BUSULFEX [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  ) and (  8.3  )].



    5.5 Cardiac Tamponade



  Cardiac tamponade has been reported in pediatric patients with thalassemia (8/400 or 2% in one series) who received high doses of oral busulfan and cyclophosphamide as the preparatory regimen for hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation. Six of the eight children died and two were saved by rapid pericardiocentesis. Abdominal pain and vomiting preceded the tamponade in most patients. Monitor for signs and symptoms, promptly evaluate and treat if cardiac tamponade is suspected.



    5.6 Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia



  Bronchopulmonary dysplasia with pulmonary fibrosis is a rare but serious complication following chronic busulfan therapy. The average onset of symptoms is 4 years after therapy (range 4 months to 10 years) .  



    5.7 Cellular Dysplasia



  Busulfan may cause cellular dysplasia in many organs. Cytologic abnormalities characterized by giant, hyperchromatic nuclei have been reported in lymph nodes, pancreas, thyroid, adrenal glands, liver, lungs and bone marrow. This cytologic dysplasia may be severe enough to cause difficulty in the interpretation of exfoliative cytologic examinations of the lungs, bladder, breast and the uterine cervix .  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
