<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="butalbital1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Commonly Observed  

  The most commonly reported adverse events associated with the use of Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP and not reported at an equivalent incidence by placebo-treated patients were nausea and/or abdominal pain, drowsiness, and dizziness.



     Associated with Treatment Discontinuation  

  Of the 382 patients treated with Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP in controlled clinical trials, three (0.8%) discontinued treatment with Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP because of adverse events. One patient each discontinued treatment for the following reasons: gastrointestinal upset; lightheadedness and heavy eyelids; and drowsiness and generalized tingling.



     Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials  

  The following table summarizes the incidence rates of the adverse events reported by at least 1% of the Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP treated patients in controlled clinical trials comparing Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP to placebo, and provides a comparison to the incidence rates reported by the placebo-treated patients.



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators.



 Adverse Events Reported by at Least 1% of Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP Treated Patients During Placebo Controlled Clinical Trials 
 Incidence Rate of Adverse Events   
                     Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and                      
    Body System/       Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP       Placebo        
    Adverse Event       (N = 382)        (N = 377)      
  
    Central Nervous                                       
               Drowsiness   2.4%             0.5%             
               Dizziness/Lightheadedness   2.6%             0.5%             
               Intoxicated Feeling   1.0%             0%               
    Gastrointestinal                                       
               Nausea/Abdominal Pain   3.7%             0.8%             
             Other Adverse Events Reported During Controlled Clinical Trials  
   The listing that follows represents the proportion of the 382 patients exposed to Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP while participating in the controlled clinical trials who reported, on at least one occasion, an adverse event of the type cited. All reported adverse events, except those already presented in the previous table, are included. It is important to emphasize that, although the adverse events reported did occur while the patient was receiving Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP, the adverse events were not necessarily caused by Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP.



 Adverse events are classified by body system and frequency. "Frequent" is defined as an adverse event which occurred in at least 1/100 (1%) of the patients; all adverse events listed in the previous table are frequent. "Infrequent" is defined as an adverse event that occurred in less than 1/100 patients but at least 1/1000 patients. All adverse events tabulated below are classified as infrequent.



     Central Nervous:    headache, shaky feeling, tingling, agitation, fainting, fatigue, heavy eyelids, high energy, hot spells, numbness, and sluggishness.



     Autonomic Nervous:    dry mouth and hyperhidrosis.



     Gastrointestinal:    vomiting, difficulty swallowing, and heartburn.



     Cardiovascular:    tachycardia.



     Musculoskeletal:    leg pain and muscle fatigue.



     Genitourinary:    diuresis.



     Miscellaneous:    pruritus, fever, earache, nasal congestion, and tinnitus.



 Voluntary reports of adverse drug events, temporally associated with Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP, that have been received since market introduction and that were not reported in clinical trials by the patients treated with Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP, are listed below. Many or most of these events may have no causal relationship with the drug and are listed according to body system.



     Central Nervous:    abuse, addiction, anxiety, depression, disorientation, hallucination, hyperactivity, insomnia, libido decrease, nervousness, neuropathy, psychosis, sedation, sexual activity increase, slurred speech, twitching, unconsciousness, vertigo.



     Autonomic Nervous:    epistaxis, flushing, miosis, salivation.



     Gastrointestinal:    anorexia, appetite increased, constipation, diarrhea, esophagitis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal spasm, hiccup, mouth burning, pyloric ulcer.



     Cardiovascular:    chest pain, hypotensive reaction, palpitations, syncope.



     Skin:    erythema, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, hives, rash, toxic epidermal necrolysis.



     Urinary:    kidney impairment, urinary difficulty.



     Miscellaneous:    allergic reaction, anaphylactic shock, cholangiocarcinoma, drug interaction with erythromycin (stomach upset), edema.



 The following adverse drug events may be borne in mind as potential effects of the components of Butalbital, Aspirin, Caffeine, and Codeine Phosphate Capsules, USP. Potential effects of high dosage are listed in the    OVERDOSAGE    section of this insert.



     Aspirin:    occult blood loss, hemolytic anemia, iron deficiency anemia, gastric distress, heartburn, nausea, peptic ulcer, prolonged bleeding time, acute airway obstruction, renal toxicity when taken in high doses for prolonged periods, impaired urate excretion, hepatitis.



     Caffeine:    cardiac stimulation, irritability, tremor, dependence, nephrotoxicity, hyperglycemia.



     Codeine:    nausea, vomiting, drowsiness, lightheadedness, constipation, pruritus.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: DEATH RELATED TO ULTRA-RAPID METABOLISM OF CODEINE TO MORPHINE

    WARNING: DEATH RELATED TO ULTRA-RAPID METABOLISM OF CODEINE TO MORPHINE  

    Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine due to a CYP2D6 polymorphism.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
