<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="butrans" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  QTc Prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Hypotensive Effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Interactions with Other CNS Depressants [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Application Site Skin Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
 *  Anaphylactic/Allergic Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.15  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.16  )]  
    
 

   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5%) include: nausea, headache, application site pruritus, dizziness, constipation, somnolence, vomiting, application site erythema, dry mouth, and application site rash. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Purdue Pharma L.P. at 1-888-726-7535 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 5,415 patients were treated with BUTRANS in controlled and open-label chronic pain clinical trials. Nine hundred twenty-four subjects were treated for approximately six months and 183 subjects were treated for approximately one year. The clinical trial population consisted of patients with persistent moderate to severe pain.



 The most common serious adverse drug reactions (all &lt;0.1%) occurring during clinical trials with BUTRANS were: chest pain, abdominal pain, vomiting, dehydration, and hypertension/blood pressure increased.



 The most common adverse events (&gt;= 2%) leading to discontinuation were: nausea, dizziness, vomiting, headache, and somnolence.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5%) reported by patients in clinical trials comparing BUTRANS 10 or 20 mcg/hour to placebo are shown in Table 2, and comparing BUTRANS 20 mcg/hour to BUTRANS 5 mcg/hour are shown in Table 3 below:



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients during the Open-Label Titration Period and Double-Blind Treatment Period: Opioid-Naive Patients 
                    Open-LabelTitration Period      Double-Blind Treatment Period     
                    BUTRANS          BUTRANS          Placebo         
   MedDRA Preferred Term      (N = 1024)       (N = 256)        (N = 283)       
 Nausea           23%              13%              10%               
 Dizziness        10%              4%               1%                
 Headache         9%               5%               5%                
 Application site pruritus  8%               4%               7%                
 Somnolence       8%               2%               2%                
 Vomiting         7%               4%               1%                
 Constipation     6%               4%               1%                
     Table 3: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients during the Open-Label Titration Period and Double-Blind Treatment Period: Opioid-Experienced Patients 
                    Open-LabelTitration Period      Double-Blind Treatment Period     
                    BUTRANS          BUTRANS 20       BUTRANS 5       
   MedDRA Preferred Term      (N = 1160)       (N = 219)        (N = 221)       
 Nausea           14%              11%              6%                
 Application site pruritus  9%               13%              5%                
 Headache         9%               8%               3%                
 Somnolence       6%               4%               2%                
 Dizziness        5%               4%               2%                
 Constipation     4%               6%               3%                
 Application site erythema  3%               10%              5%                
 Application site rash  3%               8%               6%                
 Application site irritation  2%               6%               2%                
      The following table lists adverse reactions that were reported in at least 2.0% of patients in four placebo/active-controlled titration-to-effect trials.
 

 Table 4: Adverse Reactions Reported in Titration-to-Effect Placebo/Active-Controlled Clinical Trials with Incidence &gt;= 2% 
   MedDRA Preferred Term      BUTRANS(N = 392)      Placebo(N = 261)     
 Nausea           21%              6%                
 Application site pruritus  15%              12%               
 Dizziness        15%              7%                
 Headache         14%              9%                
 Somnolence       13%              4%                
 Constipation     13%              5%                
 Vomiting         9%               1%                
 Application site erythema  7%               2%                
 Application site rash  6%               6%                
 Dry mouth        6%               2%                
 Fatigue          5%               1%                
 Hyperhidrosis    4%               1%                
 Peripheral edema  3%               1%                
 Pruritus         3%               0%                
 Stomach discomfort  2%               0%                
      The adverse reactions seen in controlled and open-label studies are presented below in the following manner: most common (&gt;= 5%), common (&gt;= 1% to &lt; 5%), and less common (&lt; 1%).
 

 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5%) reported by patients treated with BUTRANS in the clinical trials were nausea, headache, application site pruritus, dizziness, constipation, somnolence, vomiting, application site erythema, dry mouth, and application site rash.



 The common (&gt;= 1% to &lt; 5%) adverse reactions reported by patients treated with BUTRANS in the clinical trials organized by MedDRA (Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities) System Organ Class were:



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  diarrhea, dyspepsia, and upper abdominal pain



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  fatigue, peripheral edema, application site irritation, pain, pyrexia, chest pain, and asthenia



   Infections and infestations:  urinary tract infection, upper respiratory tract infection, nasopharyngitis, influenza, sinusitis, and bronchitis



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications:  fall



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  anorexia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  back pain, arthralgia, pain in extremity, muscle spasms, musculoskeletal pain, joint swelling, neck pain, and myalgia



   Nervous system disorders:  hypoesthesia, tremor, migraine, and paresthesia



   Psychiatric disorders:  insomnia, anxiety, and depression



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  dyspnea, pharyngolaryngeal pain, and cough



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  pruritus, hyperhidrosis, rash, and generalized pruritus



   Vascular disorders:  hypertension



 Other less common adverse reactions, including those known to occur with opioid treatment, that were seen in &lt; 1% of the patients in the BUTRANS trials include the following in alphabetical order:



 Abdominal distention, abdominal pain, accidental injury, affect lability, agitation, alanine aminotransferase increased, angina pectoris, angioedema, apathy, application site dermatitis, asthma aggravated, bradycardia, chills, confusional state, contact dermatitis, coordination abnormal, dehydration, depersonalization, depressed level of consciousness, depressed mood, disorientation, disturbance in attention, diverticulitis, drug hypersensitivity, drug withdrawal syndrome, dry eye, dry skin, dysarthria, dysgeusia, dysphagia, euphoric mood, face edema, flatulence, flushing, gait disturbance, hallucination, hiccups, hot flush, hyperventilation, hypotension, hypoventilation, ileus, insomnia, libido decreased, loss of consciousness, malaise, memory impairment, mental impairment, mental status changes, miosis, muscle weakness, nervousness, nightmare, orthostatic hypotension, palpitations, psychotic disorder, respiration abnormal, respiratory depression, respiratory distress, respiratory failure, restlessness, rhinitis, sedation, sexual dysfunction, syncope, tachycardia, tinnitus, urinary hesitation, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urticaria, vasodilatation, vertigo, vision blurred, visual disturbance, weight decreased, and wheezing.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, and MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY

DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; and NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME

    WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, and MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY

DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; and NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME  

        Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse  BUTRANS  (r)   exposes patients and other users

to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead

to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing

BUTRANS, and monitor all patients regularly for the development of

these behaviors or conditions   [see Warnings and Precautions

(  5.1  ) and Overdosage (  10  )].    Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression  Serious,

life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use

of BUTRANS.  Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during

initiation of BUTRANS or following a dose increase. Misuse or abuse

of BUTRANS by chewing, swallowing, snorting or injecting buprenorphine

extracted from the transdermal system will result in the uncontrolled

delivery of buprenorphine and pose a significant risk of overdose

and death   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    Accidental Exposure  Accidental exposure to

even one dose of BUTRANS, especially by children, can result in a

fatal overdose of buprenorphine   [see Warnings and Precautions

(  5.2  )]  .  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome  Prolonged use of BUTRANS during pregnancy can result in neonatal

opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized

and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed

by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged

period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal

opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will

be available   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, and MISUSE;

LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; and

NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME  See full prescribing

information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  BUTRANS exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor for development of these behaviors or conditions. (5.1, 10) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients on proper administration of BUTRANS to reduce the risk. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental exposure to BUTRANS, especially in children, can result in fatal overdose of buprenorphine. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of BUTRANS during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Interactions with CNS depressants: Concomitant use may cause profound sedation, respiratory depression, and death. If coadministration is required, consider dose reduction of one or both drugs because of additive pharmacological effects. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Elderly, cachectic, debilitated patients, and those with chronic pulmonary disease: Monitor closely because of increased risk of respiratory depression. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Avoid in patients with Long QT Syndrome, family history of Long QT Syndrome, or those taking Class IA or Class III antiarrhythmic medications. (  5.7  ,  12.2  ) 
 *  Hypotensive effects: Monitor during dose initiation and titration. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Patients with head injury or increased intracranial pressure: Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression and avoid use of BUTRANS in patients with impaired consciousness or coma susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



   BUTRANS contains buprenorphine, a Schedule III controlled substance. As an opioid, BUTRANS exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse. As modified-release products such as BUTRANS deliver the opioid over an extended period of time, there is a greater risk for overdose and death, due to the larger amount of buprenorphine present.  



  Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed BUTRANS and in those who obtain the drug illicitly. Addiction can occur at recommended doses and if the drug is misused or abused [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  .  



  Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing BUTRANS, and monitor all patients receiving BUTRANS for the development of these behaviors or conditions. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed modified-release opioid formulations such as BUTRANS, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks and proper use of BUTRANS, along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, or misuse.  



  Abuse or misuse of BUTRANS by placing it in the mouth, chewing it, swallowing it, or using it in ways other than indicated may cause choking, overdose and death [see Overdosage (  10  )]  .  



  Opioid agonists such as BUTRANS are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing BUTRANS. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper disposal of unused drug [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  . Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.  



    5.2 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



   Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of modified-release opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression, from opioid use, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see Overdosage (  10  )]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.  



  While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of BUTRANS, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dose increase. Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression when initiating therapy with BUTRANS and following dose increases.  



  To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of BUTRANS are essential [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  . Overestimating the BUTRANS dose when converting patients from another opioid product can result in fatal overdose with the first dose.  



  Accidental exposure to BUTRANS, especially in children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of buprenorphine.  



    5.3 Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



   Prolonged use of BUTRANS during pregnancy can result in withdrawal signs in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available.  



  Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome presents as irritability, hyperactivity and abnormal sleep pattern, high pitched cry, tremor, vomiting, diarrhea and failure to gain weight. The onset, duration, and severity of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome vary based on the specific opioid used, duration of use, timing and amount of last maternal use, and rate of elimination of the drug by the newborn.  



    5.4 Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



   Hypotension, profound sedation, coma, respiratory depression, and death may result if BUTRANS is used concomitantly with alcohol or other (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids).  



  When considering the use of BUTRANS in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration of use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin BUTRANS therapy is made, start with BUTRANS 5 mcg/hour patch, monitor patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression and consider using a lower dose of the concomitant CNS depressant [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  )]  .  



    5.5 Use in Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



   Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating BUTRANS and when BUTRANS is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



    5.6 Use in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



   Monitor patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression for respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy and titrating with BUTRANS, as in these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of BUTRANS may decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  . Consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients if possible.  



    5.7 QTc Prolongation



   A positive-controlled study of the effects of BUTRANS on the QTc interval in healthy subjects demonstrated no clinically meaningful effect at a BUTRANS dose of 10 mcg/hour; however, a BUTRANS dose of 40 mcg/hour (given as two BUTRANS 20 mcg/hour Transdermal Systems) was observed to prolong the QTc interval [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  .  



  Consider these observations in clinical decisions when prescribing BUTRANS to patients with hypokalemia or clinically unstable cardiac disease, including: unstable atrial fibrillation, symptomatic bradycardia, unstable congestive heart failure, or active myocardial ischemia. Avoid the use of BUTRANS in patients with a history of Long QT Syndrome or an immediate family member with this condition, or those taking Class IA antiarrhythmic medications (e.g., quinidine, procainamide, disopyramide) or Class III antiarrhythmic medications (e.g., sotalol, amiodarone, dofetilide).  



    5.8 Hypotensive Effects



   BUTRANS may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is an increased risk in patients whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a reduced blood volume or concurrent administration of certain CNS depressant drugs (e.g., phenothiazines or general anesthetics) [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  )]  . Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dose of BUTRANS.  



    5.9 Use in Patients with Head Injury or Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Monitor patients taking BUTRANS who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors) for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with BUTRANS. BUTRANS may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2retention can further increase intracranial pressure. Opioids may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury.



 Avoid the use of BUTRANS in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.10 Hepatotoxicity



  Although not observed in BUTRANS chronic pain clinical trials, cases of cytolytic hepatitis and hepatitis with jaundice have been observed in individuals receiving sublingual buprenorphine for the treatment of opioid dependence, both in clinical trials and in post-marketing adverse event reports. The spectrum of abnormalities ranges from transient asymptomatic elevations in hepatic transaminases to case reports of hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatorenal syndrome, and hepatic encephalopathy. In many cases, the presence of pre-existing liver enzyme abnormalities, infection with hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus, concomitant usage of other potentially hepatotoxic drugs, and ongoing injection drug abuse may have played a causative or contributory role. For patients at increased risk of hepatotoxicity (e.g., patients with a history of excessive alcohol intake, intravenous drug abuse or liver disease), obtain baseline liver enzyme levels and monitor periodically and during treatment with BUTRANS.



    5.11 Application Site Skin Reactions



  In rare cases, severe application site skin reactions with signs of marked inflammation including "burn," "discharge," and "vesicles" have occurred. Time of onset varies, ranging from days to months following the initiation of BUTRANS treatment. Instruct patients to promptly report the development of severe application site reactions and discontinue therapy.



    5.12 Anaphylactic/Allergic Reactions



  Cases of acute and chronic hypersensitivity to buprenorphine have been reported both in clinical trials and in the post-marketing experience. The most common signs and symptoms include rashes, hives, and pruritus. Cases of bronchospasm, angioneurotic edema, and anaphylactic shock have been reported. A history of hypersensitivity to buprenorphine is a contraindication to the use of BUTRANS.



    5.13 Application of External Heat



  Advise patients and their caregivers to avoid exposing the BUTRANS application site and surrounding area to direct external heat sources, such as heating pads or electric blankets, heat or tanning lamps, saunas, hot tubs, and heated water beds while wearing the system because an increase in absorption of buprenorphine may occur  [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  . Advise patients against exposure of the BUTRANS application site and surrounding area to hot water or prolonged exposure to direct sunlight. There is a potential for temperature-dependent increases in buprenorphine released from the system resulting in possible overdose and death.



    5.14 Patients with Fever



  Monitor patients wearing BUTRANS systems who develop fever or increased core body temperature due to strenuous exertion for opioid side effects and adjust the BUTRANS dose if signs of respiratory or central nervous system depression occur.



    5.15 Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  BUTRANS is contraindicated in patients with paralytic ileus. Avoid the use of BUTRANS in patients with other GI obstruction.



 The buprenorphine in BUTRANS may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, for worsening symptoms. Opioids may cause increases in the serum amylase.



    5.16 Use in Patients with Convulsive or Seizure Disorders



  The buprenorphine in BUTRANS may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings. Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during BUTRANS therapy.



    5.17 Driving and Operating Machinery



  BUTRANS may impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to the effects of BUTRANS and know how they will react to the medication.



    5.18 Use in Addiction Treatment



  BUTRANS has not been studied and is not approved for use in the management of addictive disorders.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
