<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="bystolic" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:     Most common adverse reactions ( ):  6.1    



 *  Headache, fatigue 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, Contact Forest Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-678-1605 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  BYSTOLIC has been evaluated for safety in patients with hypertension and in patients with heart failure. The observed adverse reaction profile was consistent with the pharmacology of the drug and the health status of the patients in the clinical trials. Adverse reactions reported for each of these patient populations are provided below. Excluded are adverse reactions considered too general to be informative and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug because they were associated with the condition being treated or are very common in the treated population.



 The data described below reflect worldwide clinical trial exposure to BYSTOLIC in 6545 patients, including 5038 patients treated for hypertension and the remaining 1507 subjects treated for other cardiovascular diseases. Doses ranged from 0.5 mg to 40 mg. Patients received BYSTOLIC for up to 24 months, with over 1900 patients treated for at least 6 months, and approximately 1300 patients for more than one year.



   In placebo-controlled clinical trials comparing BYSTOLIC with placebo, discontinuation of therapy due to adverse reactions was reported in 2.8% of patients treated with nebivolol and 2.2% of patients given placebo. The most common adverse reactions that led to discontinuation of BYSTOLIC were headache (0.4%), nausea (0.2%) and bradycardia (0.2%).  HYPERTENSION:  



 lists treatment-emergent adverse reactions that were reported in three 12-week, placebo-controlled monotherapy trials involving 1597 hypertensive patients treated with either 5 mg, 10 mg, or 20-40 mg of BYSTOLIC and 205 patients given placebo and for which the rate of occurrence was at least 1% of patients treated with nebivolol and greater than the rate for those treated with placebo in at least one dose group.    Table 1    



 Table 1. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions with an Incidence (over 6 weeks) &gt;= 1% in BYSTOLIC-Treated Patients and at a Higher Frequency than Placebo-Treated Patients 
 System Organ Class - Preferred Term           Placebo (n = 205) (%)  Nebivolol 5 mg (n = 459) (%)  Nebivolol 10 mg (n = 461) (%)  Nebivolol 20-40 mg (n = 677) (%)   
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                                           
     Bradycardia                               0              0               0               1                
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                  
     Diarrhea                                  2              2               2               3                
     Nausea                                    0              1               3               2                
   General Disorders                                                                                           
     Fatigue                                   1              2               2               5                
     Chest pain                                0              0               1               1                
     Peripheral edema                          0              1               1               1                
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                    
     Headache                                  6              9               6               7                
     Dizziness                                 2              2               3               4                
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                       
     Insomnia                                  0              1               1               1                
   Respiratory Disorders                                                                                       
     Dyspnea                                   0              0               1               1                
   Skin and subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                      
     Rash                                      0              0               1               1                
           Listed below are other reported adverse reactions with an incidence of at least 1% in the more than 4300 patients treated with BYSTOLIC in controlled or open-label trials except for those already appearing in , terms too general to be informative, minor symptoms, or adverse reactions unlikely to be attributable to drug because they are common in the population. These adverse reactions were in most cases observed at a similar frequency in placebo-treated patients in the controlled studies.    Table 1    
 

 asthenia.  Body as a Whole:  



 abdominal pain  Gastrointestinal System Disorders:  



 hypercholesterolemia  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  



 paraesthesia  Nervous System Disorders:  



   6.2 Laboratory Abnormalities

  In controlled monotherapy trials of hypertensive patients, BYSTOLIC was associated with an increase in BUN, uric acid, triglycerides and a decrease in HDL cholesterol and platelet count.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified from spontaneous reports of BYSTOLIC received worldwide and have not been listed elsewhere. These adverse reactions have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of seriousness, frequency of reporting or potential causal connection to BYSTOLIC. Adverse reactions common in the population have generally been omitted. Because these adverse reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to BYSTOLIC exposure: abnormal hepatic function (including increased AST, ALT and bilirubin), acute pulmonary edema, acute renal failure, atrioventricular block (both second and third degree), bronchospasm, erectile dysfunction, hypersensitivity (including urticaria, allergic vasculitis and rare reports of angioedema), myocardial infarction, pruritus, psoriasis, Raynaud's phenomenon, peripheral ischemia/claudication, somnolence, syncope, thrombocytopenia, various rashes and skin disorders, vertigo, and vomiting.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute exacerbation of coronary artery disease upon cessation of therapy: Do not abruptly discontinue ( )  5.1   
 *  Diabetes: Monitor glucose as beta-blockers may mask symptoms of hypoglycemia ( )  5.5   
    
 

   5.1 Abrupt Cessation of Therapy



  Do not abruptly discontinue BYSTOLIC therapy in patients with coronary artery disease. Severe exacerbation of angina, myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias have been reported in patients with coronary artery disease following the abrupt discontinuation of therapy with beta-blockers. Myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias may occur with or without preceding exacerbation of the angina pectoris. Caution patients without overt coronary artery disease against interruption or abrupt discontinuation of therapy. As with other beta-blockers, when discontinuation of BYSTOLIC is planned, carefully observe and advise patients to minimize physical activity. Taper BYSTOLIC over 1 to 2 weeks when possible. If the angina worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, re-start BYSTOLIC promptly, at least temporarily.



    5.2 Angina and Acute Myocardial Infarction



  BYSTOLIC was not studied in patients with angina pectoris or who had a recent MI.



    5.3 Bronchospastic Diseases



  In general, patients with bronchospastic diseases should not receive beta-blockers.



    5.4 Anesthesia and Major Surgery



  Because beta-blocker withdrawal has been associated with an increased risk of MI and chest pain, patients already on beta-blockers should generally continue treatment throughout the perioperative period. If BYSTOLIC is to be continued perioperatively, monitor patients closely when anesthetic agents which depress myocardial function, such as ether, cyclopropane, and trichloroethylene, are used. If beta-blocking therapy is withdrawn prior to major surgery, the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.



 The beta-blocking effects of BYSTOLIC can be reversed by beta-agonists, e.g., dobutamine or isoproterenol. However, such patients may be subject to protracted severe hypotension. Additionally, difficulty in restarting and maintaining the heartbeat has been reported with beta-blockers.



    5.5 Diabetes and Hypoglycemia



  beta-blockers may mask some of the manifestations of hypoglycemia, particularly tachycardia. Nonselective beta-blockers may potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and delay recovery of serum glucose levels. It is not known whether nebivolol has these effects. Advise patients subject to spontaneous hypoglycemia and diabetic patients receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents about these possibilities.



    5.6 Thyrotoxicosis



  beta-blockers may mask clinical signs of hyperthyroidism, such as tachycardia. Abrupt withdrawal of beta-blockers may be followed by an exacerbation of the symptoms of hyperthyroidism or may precipitate a thyroid storm.



    5.7 Peripheral Vascular Disease



  beta-blockers can precipitate or aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency in patients with peripheral vascular disease.



    5.8 Non-dihydropyridine Calcium Channel Blockers



  Because of significant negative inotropic and chronotropic effects in patients treated with beta-blockers and calcium channel blockers of the verapamil and diltiazem type, monitor the ECG and blood pressure in patients treated concomitantly with these agents.



    5.9 Use with CYP2D6 Inhibitors



  Nebivolol exposure increases with inhibition of CYP2D6 . The dose of BYSTOLIC may need to be reduced. [see Drug Interactions ( )]  7    



    5.10 Impaired Renal Function



  Renal clearance of nebivolol is decreased in patients with severe renal impairment. BYSTOLIC has not been studied in patients receiving dialysis . [see Clinical Pharmacology ( ) and Dosage and Administration ( )]  12.4    2.1    



    5.11 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Metabolism of nebivolol is decreased in patients with moderate hepatic impairment. BYSTOLIC has not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment . [see Clinical Pharmacology ( ) and Dosage and Administration ( )]  12.4    2.1    



    5.12 Risk of Anaphylactic Reactions



  While taking beta-blockers, patients with a history of severe anaphylactic reactions to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated accidental, diagnostic, or therapeutic challenge. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reactions.



    5.13 Pheochromocytoma



  In patients with known or suspected pheochromocytoma, initiate an alpha-blocker prior to the use of any beta-blocker.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
