<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cabergoline" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The safety of cabergoline tablets has been evaluated in more than 900 patients with hyperprolactinemic disorders. Most adverse events were mild or moderate in severity.



 In a 4-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled study, treatment consisted of placebo or cabergoline at fixed doses of 0.125, 0.5, 0.75, or 1.0 mg twice weekly. Doses were halved during the first week. Since a possible dose-related effect was observed for nausea only, the four cabergoline treatment groups have been combined. The incidence of the most common adverse events during the placebo-controlled study is presented in the following table.



 Incidence of Reported Adverse Events During the 4-Week, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial 
 Adverse Event                                   Cabergoline(n=168)0.125 to 1 mg two times a week         Placebo(n=20)          
                                                      Number (percent)         
  
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
   Nausea                                                  45 (27)                      4 (20)              
   Constipation                                            16 (10)                         0                
   Abdominal pain                                           9 (5)                        1 (5)              
   Dyspepsia                                                4 (2)                          0                
   Vomiting                                                 4 (2)                          0                
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System                                                                    
   Headache                                                43 (26)                      5 (25)              
   Dizziness                                               25 (15)                       1 (5)              
   Paresthesia                                              2 (1)                          0                
   Vertigo                                                  2 (1)                          0                
   Body As a Whole                                                                                          
   Asthenia                                                15 (9)                       2 (10)              
   Fatigue                                                 12 (7)                          0                
   Hot flashes                                              2 (1)                        1 (5)              
   Psychiatric                                                                                              
   Somnolence                                               9 (5)                        1 (5)              
   Depression                                               5 (3)                        1 (5)              
   Nervousness                                              4 (2)                          0                
   Autonomic Nervous System                                                                                 
   Postural hypotension                                     6 (4)                          0                
   Reproductive - Female                                                                                    
   Breast pain                                              2 (1)                          0                
   Dysmenorrhea                                             2 (1)                          0                
   Vision                                                                                                   
   Abnormal vision                                          2 (1)                          0                
         In the 8-week, double-blind period of the comparative trial with bromocriptine, Cabergoline (at a dose of 0.5 mg twice weekly) was discontinued because of an adverse event in 4 of 221 patients (2%) while bromocriptine (at a dose of 2.5 mg two times a day) was discontinued in 14 of 231 patients (6%). The most common reasons for discontinuation from cabergoline were headache, nausea and vomiting (3, 2 and 2 patients respectively); the most common reasons for discontinuation from bromocriptine were nausea, vomiting, headache, and dizziness or vertigo (10, 3, 3, and 3 patients respectively). The incidence of the most common adverse events during the double-blind portion of the comparative trial with bromocriptine is presented in the following table.
 

 Incidence of Reported Adverse Events During the 8-Week, Double-Blind Period of the Comparative Trial With Bromocriptine 
 Adverse Event                                          Cabergoline(n=221)        Bromocriptine(n=231)      
                                                         Number (percent)        
  
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
   Nausea                                                     63 (29)                   100 (43)            
   Constipation                                               15 (7)                     21 (9)             
   Abdominal pain                                             12 (5)                     19 (8)             
   Dyspepsia                                                  11 (5)                     16 (7)             
   Vomiting                                                    9 (4)                     16 (7)             
   Dry mouth                                                   5 (2)                      2 (1)             
   Diarrhea                                                    4 (2)                      7 (3)             
   Flatulence                                                  4 (2)                      3 (1)             
   Throat irritation                                           2 (1)                        0               
   Toothache                                                   2 (1)                        0               
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System                                                                    
   Headache                                                   58 (26)                    62 (27)            
   Dizziness                                                  38 (17)                    42 (18)            
   Vertigo                                                     9 (4)                     10 (4)             
   Paresthesia                                                 5 (2)                      6 (3)             
   Body As a Whole                                                                                          
   Asthenia                                                   13 (6)                     15 (6)             
   Fatigue                                                    10 (5)                     18 (8)             
   Syncope                                                     3 (1)                      3 (1)             
   Influenza-like symptoms                                     2 (1)                        0               
   Malaise                                                     2 (1)                        0               
   Periorbital edema                                           2 (1)                      2 (1)             
   Peripheral edema                                            2 (1)                        1               
   Psychiatric                                                                                              
   Depression                                                  7 (3)                      5 (2)             
   Somnolence                                                  5 (2)                      5 (2)             
   Anorexia                                                    3 (1)                      3 (1)             
   Anxiety                                                     3 (1)                      3 (1)             
   Insomnia                                                    3 (1)                      2 (1)             
   Impaired concentration                                      2 (1)                        1               
   Nervousness                                                 2 (1)                      5 (2)             
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
   Hot flashes                                                 6 (3)                      3 (1)             
   Hypotension                                                 3 (1)                      4 (2)             
   Dependent edema                                             2 (1)                        1               
   Palpitation                                                 2 (1)                      5 (2)             
   Reproductive - Female                                                                                    
   Breast pain                                                 5 (2)                      8 (3)             
   Dysmenorrhea                                                2 (1)                        1               
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                      
   Acne                                                        3 (1)                        0               
   Pruritus                                                    2 (1)                        1               
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                          
   Pain                                                        4 (2)                      6 (3)             
   Arthralgia                                                  2 (1)                        0               
   Respiratory                                                                                              
   Rhinitis                                                    2 (1)                      9 (4)             
   Vision                                                                                                   
   Abnormal vision                                             2 (1)                      2 (1)             
         Other adverse events that were reported at an incidence of &lt;1.0% in the overall clinical studies follow.
 

   Body As a Whole:  facial edema, influenza-like symptoms, malaise  Cardiovascular System:  hypotension, syncope, palpitations  Digestive System:  dry mouth, flatulence, diarrhea, anorexia  Metabolic and Nutritional System:  weight loss, weight gain  Nervous System:  somnolence, nervousness, paresthesia, insomnia, anxiety  Respiratory System:  nasal stuffiness, epistaxis  Skin and Appendages:  acne, pruritus  Special Senses:  abnormal vision  Urogenital System:  dysmenorrhea, increased libido



 The safety of cabergoline has been evaluated in approximately 1,200 patients with Parkinson's disease in controlled and uncontrolled studies at dosages of up to 11.5 mg/day which greatly exceeds the maximum recommended dosage of cabergoline for hyperprolactinemic disorders. In addition to the adverse events that occurred in the patients with hyperprolactinemic disorders, the most common adverse events in patients with Parkinson's disease were dyskinesia, hallucinations, confusion, and peripheral edema. Heart failure, pleural effusion, pulmonary fibrosis, and gastric or duodenal ulcer occurred rarely. One case of constrictive pericarditis has been reported.



   Post-marketing Surveillance data

  The following events have been reported in association with cabergoline: cardiac valvulopathy and extracardiac fibrotic reactions, (See    WARNINGS, Cardiac Valvulopathy    and    Extracardiac Fibrotic Reactions    ).



 Other events have been reported in association with cabergoline: hypersexuality, increased libido and pathological gambling (See    PRECAUTIONS, Psychiatric    ). In addition, cases of alopecia, aggression, and psychotic disorder have been reported in patients taking cabergoline. Some of these reports have been in patients who have had prior adverse reactions to dopamine agonist products.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
