<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cabometyx" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the label:



 *  Hemorrhage [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  GI Perforations and Fistulas [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Thrombotic Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypertension and Hypertensive Crisis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Diarrhea [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported (&gt;= 25%) adverse reactions are: diarrhea, fatigue, nausea, decreased appetite, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES), hypertension, vomiting, weight decreased, and constipation. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Exelixis, Inc. at 1-855-500-3935 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of CABOMETYX was evaluated in Study 1, a randomized, open-label trial in which 331 patients with advanced renal cell carcinoma received 60 mg CABOMETYX and 322 patients received 10 mg everolimus administered daily until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients on both arms who had disease progression could continue treatment at the discretion of the investigator  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . The median duration of treatment was 7.6 months (range 0.3 - 20.5) for patients receiving CABOMETYX and 4.4 months (range 0.21 - 18.9) for patients receiving everolimus.



 Adverse reactions which occurred in &gt;= 25% of CABOMETYX-treated patients included, in order of decreasing frequency: diarrhea, fatigue, nausea, decreased appetite, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES), hypertension, vomiting, weight decreased, and constipation. Grade 3-4 adverse reactions and laboratory abnormalities which occurred in &gt;= 5% of patients were hypertension, diarrhea, fatigue, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, hypomagnesemia, lymphocytes decreased, anemia, hypokalemia, and GGT increased.



 The dose was reduced in 60% of patients receiving CABOMETYX and in 24% of patients receiving everolimus. Twenty percent (20%) of patients received 20 mg CABOMETYX as their lowest dose. The most frequent adverse reactions leading to dose reduction in patients treated with CABOMETYX were: diarrhea, PPES, fatigue, and hypertension. Adverse reactions led to study treatment being held in 70% patients receiving CABOMETYX and in 59% patients receiving everolimus. Adverse reactions led to study treatment discontinuation in 10% of patients receiving CABOMETYX and in 10% of patients receiving everolimus. The most frequent adverse reactions leading to permanent discontinuation in patients treated with CABOMETYX were decreased appetite (2%) and fatigue (1%).



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 10% Patients Who Received CABOMETYX 
    Adverse Reaction                                 CABOMETYX(n=331)  Everolimus(n=322)   
 AllGrades                                            Grades3-4     AllGrades     Grades3-4     
                                                     Percentage (%) of Patients   
  
    Gastrointestinal Disorders                        
         Diarrhea                                         74            11            28            2         
         Nausea                                           50            4             28            &lt;1        
         Vomiting                                         32            2             14            &lt;1        
         Stomatitis                                       22            2             24            2         
         Constipation                                     25            &lt;1            19            &lt;1        
         Abdominal pain                                   23            4             13            2         
         Dyspepsia                                        12            &lt;1            5             0         
    General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions   
         Fatigue                                          56            9             47            7         
         Mucosal inflammation                             19            &lt;1            23            3         
         Asthenia                                         19            4             16            2         
    Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                
         Decreased appetite                               46            3             34            &lt;1        
    Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders            
         Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome       42            8             6             &lt;1        
         Rash                                             23            &lt;1            43            &lt;1        
         Dry skin                                         11            0             10            0         
    Vascular Disorders                                
         Hypertension                                     39            16            8             3         
    Investigations                                    
         Weight decreased                                 31            2             12            0         
    Nervous System Disorders                          
         Dysgeusia                                        24            0             9             0         
         Headache                                         11            &lt;1            12            &lt;         
         Dizziness                                        11            0             7             0         
    Endocrine Disorders                               
         Hypothyroidism                                   21            0             &lt;1            &lt;1        
    Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders   
         Dysphonia                                        20            &lt;1            4             0         
         Dyspnea                                          19            3             29            4         
         Cough                                            18            &lt;1            33            &lt;1        
    Blood and Lymphatic Disorders                     
         Anemia                                           17            5             38            16        
    Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders   
         Pain in extremity                                14            1             8             &lt;1        
         Muscle spasms                                    13            0             5             0         
         Arthralgia                                       11            &lt;1            14            1         
    Renal and Urinary Disorders                       
         Proteinuria                                      12            2             9             &lt;1        
           Other clinically important adverse reactions (all grades) that were reported in &lt;10% of patients treated with CABOMETYX included: wound complications (2%), convulsion (&lt;1%), pancreatitis (&lt;1%), osteonecrosis of the jaw (&lt;1%), and hepatitis cholestatic (&lt;1%).
 

 Table 2. Laboratory Abnormalities Occurring in &gt;= 25% Patients Who Received CABOMETYX 
    Test                                             CABOMETYX(n=331)  Everolimus(n=322)   
 AllGrades                                            Grade 3-4     AllGrades     Grade 3-4     
  
    Chemistry                                                                                                 
         AST increased                                    74            3             40            &lt;1        
         ALT increased                                    68            3             32            &lt;1        
         Creatinine increased                             58            &lt;1            71            0         
         Triglycerides increased                          53            4             73            13        
         Hypophosphatemia                                 48            8             36            5         
         Hyperglycemia                                    37            2             59            8         
         Hypoalbuminemia                                  36            2             28            &lt;1        
         ALP increased                                    35            2             29            1         
         Hypomagnesemia                                   31            7             4             &lt;1        
         Hyponatremia                                     30            8             26            6         
         GGT increased                                    27            5             43            9         
    Hematology                                                                                                
         White blood cells decreased                      35            &lt;1            31            &lt;1        
         Absolute neutrophil count decreased              31            2             17            &lt;1        
         Hemoglobin decreased                             31            4             71            17        
         Lymphocytes decreased                            25            7             39            12        
         Platlets decreased                               25            &lt;1            27            &lt;1        
    ALP, alkaline phosphatase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, gamma glutamyl transferase.     
    National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, Version 4.0     
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hemorrhage: Do not administer CABOMETYX if recent history of severe hemorrhage. (  5.1  ) 
 *  GI Perforations and Fistulas: Monitor for symptoms. Discontinue CABOMETYX for fistulas that cannot be adequately managed or perforations. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Thrombotic Events: Discontinue CABOMETYX for myocardial infarction, cerebral infarction, or other serious arterial thromboembolic events. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hypertension and Hypertensive Crisis: Monitor blood pressure regularly. Discontinue CABOMETYX for hypertensive crisis or severe hypertension that cannot be controlled with anti-hypertensive therapy. (  5.4  ). 
 *  Diarrhea: May be severe. Interrupt CABOMETYX treatment immediately until diarrhea resolves or decreases to Grade 1. Recommend standard antidiarrheal treatments. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES): Interrupt CABOMETYX treatment until PPES resolves or decreases to Grade 1. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS): Discontinue CABOMETYX. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise females of reproductive potential of the potential risk to a fetus and to use effective contraception. (  5.8  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hemorrhage



  Severe hemorrhage occurred with CABOMETYX. The incidence of Grade &gt;= 3 hemorrhagic events was 2.1% in CABOMETYX-treated patients and 1.6% in everolimus-treated patients. Fatal hemorrhages also occurred in the cabozantinib clinical program.



 Do not administer CABOMETYX to patients that have or are at risk for severe hemorrhage.



    5.2 GI Perforations and Fistulas



  In a randomized study in renal cell carcinoma, fistulas were reported in 1.2% (including 0.6% anal fistula) of CABOMETYX-treated patients and 0% of everolimus-treated patients. Gastrointestinal (GI) perforations were reported in 0.9% of CABOMETYX-treated patients and 0.6% of everolimus-treated patients. Fatal perforations occurred in the cabozantinib clinical program.



 Monitor patients for symptoms of fistulas and perforations. Discontinue CABOMETYX in patients who experience a fistula which cannot be appropriately managed or a GI perforation.



    5.3 Thrombotic Events



  CABOMETYX treatment results in an increased incidence of thrombotic events. Venous thromboembolism was reported in 7.3% of CABOMETYX-treated patients and 2.5% of everolimus-treated patients. Pulmonary embolism occurred in 3.9% of CABOMETYX-treated patients and 0.3% of everolimus-treated patients. Events of arterial thromboembolism were reported in 0.9% of CABOMETYX-treated patients and 0.3% of everolimus-treated patients. Fatal thrombotic events occurred in the cabozantinib clinical program.



 Discontinue CABOMETYX in patients who develop an acute myocardial infarction or any other arterial thromboembolic complication.



    5.4 Hypertension and Hypertensive Crisis



  CABOMETYX treatment results in an increased incidence of treatment-emergent hypertension. Hypertension was reported in 37% (15% Grade &gt;= 3) of CABOMETYX-treated patients and 7.1% (3.1% Grade &gt;= 3) of everolimus-treated patients. Monitor blood pressure prior to initiation and regularly during CABOMETYX treatment. Withhold CABOMETYX for hypertension that is not adequately controlled with medical management; when controlled, resume CABOMETYX at a reduced dose. Discontinue CABOMETYX for severe hypertension that cannot be controlled with anti-hypertensive therapy. Discontinue CABOMETYX if there is evidence of hypertensive crisis or severe hypertension despite optimal medical management.



    5.5 Diarrhea



  Diarrhea occurred in 74% of patients treated with CABOMETYX and in 28% of patients treated with everolimus. Grade 3 diarrhea occurred in 11% of CABOMETYX-treated patients and in 2% of everolimus-treated patients. Withhold CABOMETYX in patients who develop intolerable Grade 2 diarrhea or Grade 3-4 diarrhea that cannot be managed with standard antidiarrheal treatments until improvement to Grade 1; resume CABOMETYX at a reduced dose. Dose modification due to diarrhea occurred in 26% of patients.



    5.6 Palmar-Plantar Erythrodysesthesia Syndrome



  Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES) occurred in 42% of patients treated with CABOMETYX and in 6% of patients treated with everolimus. Grade 3 PPES occurred in 8.2% of CABOMETYX-treated patients and in &lt;1% of everolimus-treated patients. Withhold CABOMETYX in patients who develop intolerable Grade 2 PPES or Grade 3 PPES until improvement to Grade 1; resume CABOMETYX at a reduced dose. Dose modification due to PPES occurred in 16% of patients.



    5.7 Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome



  Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS), a syndrome of subcortical vasogenic edema diagnosed by characteristic finding on MRI, occurred in the cabozantinib clinical program. Perform an evaluation for RPLS in any patient presenting with seizures, headache, visual disturbances, confusion or altered mental function. Discontinue CABOMETYX in patients who develop RPLS.



    5.8 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  Based on data from animal studies and its mechanism of action, CABOMETYX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Cabozantinib administration to pregnant animals during organogenesis resulted in embryolethality at exposures below those occurring clinically at the recommended dose, and in increased incidences of skeletal variations in rats and visceral variations and malformations in rabbits. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with CABOMETYX and for 4 months after the last dose [See  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ,  (8.3)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.1)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
