<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cafcit" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Overall, the reported number of adverse events in the double-blind period of the controlled trial was similar for the CAFCIT (caffeine citrate) and placebo groups. The following table shows adverse events that occurred in the double-blind period of the controlled trial and that were more frequent in CAFCIT-treated patients than placebo.



 ADVERSE EVENTS THAT OCCURRED MORE FREQUENTLY IN CAFCIT-TREATED PATIENTS THAN PLACEBO DURING DOUBLE-BLIND THERAPY 
  Adverse Event (AE)    CAFCIT N=46  n (%)    Placebo N=39  n (%)    
  BODY AS A WHOLE                                      
    Accidental Injury    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
    Feeding Intolerance    4 (8.7)          2 (5.1)          
    Sepsis         2 (4.3)          0 (0.0)          
  CARDIOVASCULAR SYSTEM                                      
    Hemorrhage     1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  DIGESTIVE SYSTEM                                      
    Necrotizing Enterocolitis    2 (4.3)          1 (2.6)          
    Gastritis      1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
    Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  HEMIC AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM                                      
    Disseminated Intravascular Coagulation    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  METABOLIC AND NUTRITIVE DISORDERS                                      
    Acidosis       1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
    Healing Abnormal    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  NERVOUS SYSTEM                                      
    Cerebral Hemorrhage    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                                      
    Dyspnea        1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
    Lung Edema     1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  SKIN AND APPENDAGES                                      
    Dry Skin       1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
    Rash           4 (8.7)          3 (7.7)          
    Skin Breakdown    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  SPECIAL SENSES                                      
    Retinopathy of Prematurity    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
  UROGENITAL SYSTEM                                      
    Kidney Failure    1 (2.2)          0 (0.0)          
         In addition to the cases above, three cases of necrotizing enterocolitis were diagnosed in patients receiving CAFCIT (caffeine citrate) during the open-label phase of the study.
 

 Three of the infants who developed necrotizing enterocolitis during the trial died. All had been exposed to caffeine. Two were randomized to caffeine, and one placebo patient was "rescued" with open-label caffeine for uncontrolled apnea.



 Adverse events described in the published literature include: central nervous system stimulation (i.e., irritability, restlessness, jitteriness), cardiovascular effects (i.e., tachycardia, increased left ventricular output, and increased stroke volume), gastrointestinal effects (i.e., increased gastric aspirate, gastrointestinal intolerance), alterations in serum glucose (i.e., hypoglycemia and hyperglycemia), and renal effects (i.e., increased urine flow rate, increased creatinine clearance, and increased sodium and calcium excretion). Published long-term follow-up studies have not shown caffeine to adversely affect neurological development or growth parameters.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
