<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="calcipotriene0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 1%) are pruritus and scaly rash.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact LEO Pharma Inc. at 1-877-494-4536 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Study Experience

  The data described below reflect exposure to Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment in 2448 subjects, including 1992 exposed for 4 weeks, and 289 exposed for 8 weeks. Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment was studied primarily in placebo- and active-controlled trials (N = 1176, and N = 1272, respectively). The population was 15-97 years old, 61% males and 39% females, mostly white (97%) and had a baseline disease severity ranging from mild to very severe. Most subjects received once daily application, and the median weekly dose was 24.5 g.The percentage of subjects reporting at least one adverse event was 27.1% in the Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment group, 33.0% in the calcipotriene group, 28.3% in the betamethasone group, and 33.4% in the vehicle group.



 Table 1



 Adverse Events Reported by &gt;=1% of Subjects by Preferred Term




                            Calcipotriene and Betamethasone Dipropionate OintmentN = 2448  CalcipotrieneN = 3197      Betamethasone dipropionateN = 1164  VehicleN = 470              
 Any Adverse Event          663 (27.1)                 1055 (33.0)                329 (28.3)                 157 (33.4)                  
 Preferred Term             # of subjects (%)                                                                                            
 Pruritis                   75 (3.1)                   183 (5.7)                  38 (3.3)                   43 (9.1)                    
 Headache                   69 (2.8)                   75 (2.3)                   44 (3.8)                   12 (2.6)                    
 Nasopharyngitis            56 (2.3)                   77 (2.4)                   34 (2.9)                   9 (1.9)                     
 Psoriasis                  30 (1.2)                   47 (1.5)                   14 (1.2)                   5 (1.1)                     
 Rash scaly                 30 (1.2)                   40 (1.3)                   0 (0.0)                    1 (0.2)                     
 Influenza                  23 (0.9)                   34 (1.1)                   14 (1.2)                   6 (1.3)                     
 Upper respiratory tract infection  20 (0.8)                   19 (0.6)                   12 (1.0)                   3 (0.6)                     
 Erythema                   15 (0.6)                   54 (1.7)                   3 (0.3)                    5 (1.1)                     
 Application site pruritus  13 (0.5)                   24 (0.8)                   10 (0.9)                   6 (1.3)                     
 Skin irritation            11 (0.4)                   60 (1.9)                   8 (0.7)                    5 (1.1)                     
 Pain                       7 (0.3)                    12 (0.4)                   3 (0.3)                    5 (1.1)                     
 Burning sensation          6 (0.2)                    30 (0.9)                   3 (0.3)                    6 (1.3)                     
      A lesional/perilesional adverse event was generally defined as an adverse event located &lt;= 2 cm from the lesional border.Table 2Lesional/Perilesional Adverse Events Reported by &gt;=1% of Subjects
 


                            Calcipotriene and Betamethasone Dipropionate OintmentN = 2448  CalcipotrieneN = 3197      Betamethasone dipropionateN = 1164  VehicleN = 470              
 Any Adverse Event          213 (8.7)                  419 (13.1)                 85 (7.3)                   76 (16.2)                   
 Preferred Term             # of subjects (%)                                                                                            
 Pruritis                   69 (2.8)                   170 (5.3)                  31 (2.7)                   41 (8.7)                    
 Rash scaly                 29 (1.2)                   38 (1.2)                   0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
 Application site pruritus  12 (0.5)                   24 (0.8)                   10 (0.9)                   6 (1.3)                     
 Erythema                   9 (0.4)                    36 (1.1)                   2 (0.2)                    4 (0.9)                     
 Skin irritation            9 (0.4)                    51 (1.6)                   8 (0.7)                    5 (1.1)                     
 Burning sensation          6 (0.2)                    25 (0.8)                   3 (0.3)                    5 (1.1)                     
      For subjects who reported lesional/perilesional adverse events, the median time to onset was 7 days for Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment, 7 days for calcipotriene, 5 days for betamethasone dipropionate, and 3 days for vehicle.Other less common reactions (less than 1% but more than 0.1%) were, in decreasing order of incidence, folliculitis, rash papular, rash pustular, and skin hypopigmentation. Skin atrophy, telangiectasia and skin hyperpigmentation were reported infrequently (0.1%).In a separate study, subjects (N = 207) with at least moderate disease severity were given Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment intermittently on an "as needed" basis for up to 52 weeks. The median use was 15.4 g per week. The effects of Calcipotriene and Betamethasone Dipropionate Ointment on calcium metabolism were not studied and the effects on the HPA axis were not adequately studied. The following adverse reactions were reported by 1% or more of the subjects: pruritus (7.2%), psoriasis (3.4%), skin atrophy (1.9%), folliculitis (1.4%), burning sensation (1.4%), skin depigmentation (1.4%), ecchymosis (1.0%), erythema (1.0%) and hand dermatitis (1.0%). One case of serious flare-up of psoriasis was reported.
 

   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions associated with the use of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment have been identified post-approval: pustular psoriasis and rebound effect.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     
 

    EXCERPT:    *  Hypercalcemia and hypercalciuria have been reported. If it occurs, discontinue treatment until parameters of calcium metabolism normalize (  5.1  ) 
 *  Topical corticosteroids can produce reversible hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis suppression, Cushing's syndrome and unmask latent diabetes (  5.2  ) 
 *  Systemic absorption may require evaluation for HPA axis suppression (  5.2  ) 
 *  Modify use should HPA axis suppression develop (  5.2  ) 
 *  Potent corticosteroids, use on large areas, prolonged use or occlusive use may increase systemic absorption (  5.3  ) 
 *  Local adverse reactions with topical steroids may include atrophy, striae, irritation, acneiform eruptions, hypopigmentation and allergic contact dermatitis and may be more likely with occlusive use or more potent corticosteroids (  5.3  ,  6.1  ) 
 *  Children may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity when treated with topical corticosteroids (  5.2  ,  8.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Effects on Calcium Metabolism



  Hypercalcemia and hypercalciuria have been reported with use of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064%. If hypercalcemia or hypercalciuria develop, treatment should be discontinued until parameters of calcium metabolism have normalized. In the trials that included assessment of the effects of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment on calcium metabolism, such testing was done after 4 weeks of treatment. The effects of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment on calcium metabolism following treatment durations of longer than 4 weeks have not been evaluated.



    5.2 Effects on Endocrine System



  Systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids can produce reversible hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis suppression with the potential for clinical glucocorticosteroid insufficiency. This may occur during treatment or upon withdrawal of the topical corticosteroid.



 HPA axis suppression has been observed with Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment [ see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ]. The effects of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment on the HPA axis following treatment durations of longer than 4 weeks have not been adequately studied.



 In a study of 32 subjects concomitantly treated with Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Scalp Topical Suspension on the scalp and Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment on the body, adrenal suppression was identified in 5 of 32 subjects (15.6%) after 4 weeks of treatment [ see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY Pharmacodynamics (12.2)    ].



 Because of the potential for systemic absorption, use of topical corticosteroids may require that patients be periodically evaluated for HPA axis suppression. Factors that predispose a patient using a topical corticosteroid to HPA axis suppression include the use of more potent steroids, use over large surface areas, use over prolonged periods, use under occlusion, use on an altered skin barrier, and use in patients with liver failure.



 An ACTH stimulation test may be helpful in evaluating patients for HPA axis suppression. If HPA axis suppression is documented, an attempt should be made to gradually withdraw the drug, to reduce the frequency of application, or to substitute a less potent steroid. Manifestations of adrenal insufficiency may require supplemental systemic corticosteroids. Recovery of HPA axis function is generally prompt and complete upon discontinuation of topical corticosteroids.



 Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and unmasking of latent diabetes mellitus can also result from systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids.



 Use of more than one corticosteroid-containing product at the same time may increase the total systemic corticosteroid exposure.



 Pediatric patients may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity from use of topical corticosteroids [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ].



    5.3 Local Adverse Reactions with Topical Corticosteroids



   Local adverse reactions may be more likely to occur with occlusive use, prolonged use or use of higher potency corticosteroids. Reactions may include atrophy, striae, telangiectasias, burning, itching, irritation, dryness, folliculitis, acneiform eruptions, hypopigmentation, perioral dermatitis, allergic contact dermatitis, secondary infection, and miliaria. Some local adverse reactions may be irreversible.  
 

    5.4 Allergic Contact Dermatitis with Topical Corticosteroids



   Allergic contact dermatitis to any component of topical corticosteroids is usually diagnosed by a failure to heal  rather than a clinical exacerbation. Clinical diagnosis of allergic contact dermatitis can be confirmed by patch testing.  
 

    5.5 Allergic Contact Dermatitis with Topical Calcipotriene



   Allergic contact dermatitis has been observed with use of topical calcipotriene. Clinical diagnosis of allergic contact dermatitis can be confirmed by patch testing.  
 

    5.6 Concomitant Skin Infections



  Concomitant skin infections should be treated with an appropriate antimicrobial agent. If the infection persists, Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment should be discontinued until the infection has been adequately treated.



    5.7 Skin Irritation



  If irritation develops, treatment with Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted.



    5.8 Unevaluated Uses



  The safety and efficacy of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment in patients with known or suspected disorders of calcium metabolism have not been evaluated.



 The safety and efficacy of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment in patients with erythrodermic, exfoliative, or pustular psoriasis have not been evaluated.



 The safety and efficacy of Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment in patients with severe renal insufficiency or severe hepatic disorders have not been evaluated.



    5.9 Ultraviolet Light Exposure



  Patients who apply Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment to exposed skin should avoid excessive exposure to either natural or artificial sunlight, including tanning booths, sun lamps, etc. Physicians may wish to limit or avoid use of phototherapy in patients who use Calcipotriene 0.005% and Betamethasone Dipropionate 0.064% Ointment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
