<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="calcitriol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rate observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:    Most common adverse reactions (incidence  &gt;  3%) were lab test abnormality, urine abnormality, psoriasis, hypercalciuria, and pruritus (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Perrigo at 1-866-634-9120 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Calcitriol Ointment was studied in two vehicle-controlled studies (419 subjects), and in one open label study (324 subjects). The table below describes exposure to Calcitriol Ointment in 743 subjects, including 239 exposed for 6 months and 116 exposed for one year.



 Four hundred and nineteen subjects were treated with Calcitriol Ointment twice daily for 8 weeks. The population included subjects ages 13 to 87, males (284) and females (135), Caucasians (372) and non-Caucasians (47); with mild (105) to moderate (313) chronic plaque psoriasis.



 



 Among subjects having laboratory monitoring, hypercalcemia was observed in 24% (18/74) of subjects exposed to active drug and in 16% (13/79) of subjects exposed to vehicle, however the elevation were less than 10% above the upper limit of normal [  see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (  5.1  )  ]



 The open label study enrolled 324 subjects with psoriasis who were then treated for up to 52 weeks. Adverse events reported at a rate of greater than or equal to 3% of subjects treated with Calcitriol Ointment were lab test abnormality (8%), urine abnormality (4%), psoriasis (4%), hyperciuria (3%), and pruritus (3%). Kidney stones were reported in 3 subjects and confirmed in two.



  table-01   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during the world-wide post-approval use of Calcitriol Ointment: acute blistering dermatitis, erythema, pruritus, skin burning sensation, and skin discomfort. Because these reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 

    17 PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION

  This information is intended to aid in the safe and effective use of this medication. It is not a disclosure of all possible adverse or intended effects. Patients using Calcitriol Ointment should receive the following information:



   17.1 Instructions for Use

  This medication is to be used as directed by the physician. It is for external use only. This medication is to be applied only to areas of the skin affected by psoriasis, as directed. It should be gently rubbed into the skin so that no medication remains visible.



   17.2 Adverse Reactions

  Patients should report any signs of adverse reactions to their physician.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Perrigo at    1-866-634-9120 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  If aberrations in parameters of calcium metabolism are noted discontinue Calcitriol Ointment until these normalize. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Avoid excessive exposure of Calcitriol Ointment treated areas to either natural or artificial sunlight. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Effects on Calcium Metabolism



  In controlled clinical trials with Calcitriol Ointment, among subjects having laboratory monitoring, hypercalcemia was observed in 24% (18/74) of subjects exposed to active drug and in 16% (13/79) of subjects exposed to vehicle. However, the increases in calcium and albumin-adjusted calcium levels were less than 10% above the upper limit of normal.



 If aberrations in parameters of calcium metabolism occur, treatment should be discontinued until these parameters have normalized. The effects of Calcitriol Ointment on calcium metabolism following treatment durations greater than 52 weeks have not been evaluated. Increase absorption may occur with occlusive use.



    5.2 Ultraviolet Light Exposure



  Animal data suggest that the vehicle of calcitriol Ointment may enhance the ability of ultraviolent radiation (UVR) to induce skin tumors [ see Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility (13.1  )] Subjects who apply Calcitriol Ointment to exposed skin should avoid excessive exposure to the treated areas to either natural or artificial sunlight, including tanning booths and sun lamps. Physicians may wish to limit or avoid use of phototherapy in patients who use Calcitriol Ointment.



    5.3 Unevaluated Uses



  The safety and effectiveness of Calcitriol Ointment in patients with known or suspected disorders of calcium metabolism have not been evaluated. The safety and effectiveness of Calcitriol Ointment in patients with erythrodermic, exfoliative, or pustular psoriasis have not been evaluated.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
