<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="caldolor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular thrombotic events [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal effects [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Hepatic effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Congestive heart failure and edema [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Renal effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Anaphylactoid reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Serious skin reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
    The most common adverse reactions reported in clinical studies are nausea, flatulence, vomiting, and headache.
 

 The most common reason for discontinuation due to adverse events in controlled trials of Caldolor is pruritus (&lt;1%).



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions are nausea, flatulence, vomiting, headache, hemorrhage and dizziness (&gt;5%). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Cumberland Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-877-484-2700 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be compared directly to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During clinical development, 560 patients were exposed to Caldolor, 438 in pain and 122 with fever. In the pain studies, Caldolor was started intra-operatively and administered at a dose of 400 mg or 800 mg every six hours for up to three days. In the fever studies, Caldolor was administered at doses of 100 mg, 200 mg, or 400 mg every four or six hours for up to 3 days.



 The most frequent type of adverse reaction occurring with oral ibuprofen is gastrointestinal.



     Pain Studies  



 The incidence rates of adverse reactions listed in the following table were derived from multi-center, controlled clinical studies in post-operative patients comparing Caldolor to placebo in patients also receiving morphine as needed for post-operative pain.



 Table 1: Post-operative Patients with Adverse Reactions Observed in &gt;= 3% of Patients in any Caldolor Treatment Group in Pain Studies* 
  * All patients received concomitant morphine during these studies.    
  
   Event                                  Caldolor              Placebo(N=287)       
   400 mg(N=134)                          800 mg(N=304)        
   Any Reaction                           118 (88%)             260 (86%)             258 (90%)            
     Nausea                             77 (57%)              161 (53%)             179 (62%)              
     Vomiting                           30 (22%)              46 (15%)              50 (17%)               
     Flatulence                         10 (7%)               49 (16%)              44 (15%)               
     Headache                           12 (9%)               35 (12%)              31 (11%)               
     Hemorrhage                         13 (10%)              13 (4%)               16 (6%)                
     Dizziness                          8 (6%)                13 (4%)               5 (2%)                 
     Edema peripheral                   1 (&lt;1%)               9 (3%)                4 (1%)                 
     Urinary retention                  7 (5%)                10 (3%)               10 (3%)                
     Anemia                             5 (4%)                7 (2%)                6 (2%)                 
     Decreased hemoglobin               4 (3%)                6 (2%)                3 (1%)                 
     Dyspepsia                          6 (4%)                4 (1%)                2 (&lt;1%)                
     Wound hemorrhage                   4 (3%)                4 (1%)                4 (1%)                 
     Abdominal discomfort               4 (3%)                2 (&lt;1%)               0                      
     Cough                              4 (3%)                2 (&lt;1%)               1 (&lt;1%)                
     Hypokalemia                        5 (4%)                3 (&lt;1%)               8 (3%)                 
              Fever Studies  
 

 Fever studies were conducted in febrile hospitalized patients with malaria and febrile hospitalized patients with varying causes of fever. In hospitalized febrile patients with malaria, the adverse reactions observed in at least two Caldolor-treated patients included abdominal pain and nasal congestion.



 In hospitalized febrile patients (all causes), adverse reactions observed in more than two patients in any given treatment group are presented in the table below.



 Table 2: Patients with Adverse Reactions Observed in &gt;= 3% of Patients in any Caldolor Treatment Group in All-Cause Fever Study 
   Event                                Caldolor        Placebo    N=28     
   100 mg    N=30                       200 mg    N=30      400 mg    N=31     
  
   Any Reaction                         27 (87%)        25 (83%)          23 (74%)          25 (89%)         
     Anemia                           5 (17%)         6 (20%)           11 (36%)          4 (14%)            
     Eosinophilia                     7 (23%)         7 (23%)           8 (26%)           7 (25%)            
     Hypokalemia                      4 (13%)         4 (13%)           6 (19%)           5 (18%)            
     Hypoproteinemia                  3 (10%)         0                 4 (13%)           2 (7%)             
     Neutropenia                      2 (7%)          2 (7%)            4 (13%)           2 (7%)             
     Blood urea increased             0               0                 3 (10%)           0                  
     Hypernatremia                    2 (7%)          0                 3 (10%)           0                  
     Hypertension                     0               0                 3 (10%)           0                  
     Hypoalbuminemia                  3 (10%)         1 (3%)            3 (10%)           1 (4%)             
     Hypotension                      0               2 (7%)            3 (10%)           1 (4%)             
     Diarrhea                         3 (10%)         3 (10%)           2 (7%)            2 (7%)             
     Pneumonia bacterial              3 (10%)         1 (3%)            2 (7%)            0                  
     Blood LDH increased              3 (10%)         2 (7%)            1 (3%)            1 (4%)             
     Thrombocythemia                  3 (10%)         2 (7%)            1 (3%)            0                  
     Bacteremia                       4 (13%)         0                 0                 0                  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS



  WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS



    Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may increase the risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Caldolor is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery [see Contraindications (4.3) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may increase the risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. Risk may increase with duration of use. (5.1) 
 *  Caldolor is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4.3, 5.1) 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. Events can occur at any time without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious and potentially fatal CV thrombotic events: Use lowest effective dose of Caldolor for shortest possible duration. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Serious and potentially fatal GI reactions: Use lowest effective dose of Caldolor for shortest possible duration. Use with caution in patients with prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hepatic effects: Range from transaminase elevations to liver failure. Discontinue Caldolor immediately if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen. (  5.3  ,  5.15  ) 
 *  Hypertension: Can occur with NSAID treatment. Monitor blood pressure closely during treatment with Caldolor. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Congestive heart failure and edema: Fluid retention and edema can occur with NSAID treatment. Use Caldolor with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Renal effects: Long-term administration of NSAIDs can result in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Use Caldolor with caution in patients at risk (e.g., the elderly, those with renal impairment, heart failure, liver impairment, and those taking diuretics or ACE inhibitors). (  5.6  ) 
 *  Anaphylactoid reactions: May occur in patients with the aspirin triad or in patients without prior exposure to Caldolor. Discontinue Caldolor immediately if an anaphylactoid reaction occurs. (  5.7  ,  5.12  ) 
 *  Serious skin reactions: Include exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which can be fatal. Discontinue Caldolor if rash or other signs of local skin reaction occur. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Patients should be informed about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 Two large, controlled clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10-14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke [see Contraindications (  4.3  )]  .



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID does increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) events [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2    ) ]  .



    5.2 Gastrointestinal Effects: Risk of Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, can cause serious GI adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs occur in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3-6 months and in about 2-4% of patients treated for one year. These trends continue with longer duration of use, increasing the likelihood of developing a serious GI event at some time during the course of therapy. However, even short-term therapy is not without risk.



 Prescribe NSAIDs, including Caldolor, with extreme caution in those with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or GI bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing a GI bleed compared to treated patients with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk of GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants, longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most reports of spontaneous fatal GI events are in elderly or debilitated patients, and therefore special care should be taken in treating this population.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest possible duration. Patients and physicians should remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulcerations and bleeding during NSAID therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI event is suspected. This should include discontinuation of the NSAID until a serious GI adverse event is ruled out. For high-risk patients, alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs should be considered.



    5.3 Hepatic Effects



  Borderline elevations of one or more liver tests may occur in up to 15% of patients taking NSAIDs, including ibuprofen. These laboratory abnormalities may progress, may remain unchanged, or may be transient with continuing therapy. Notable elevations of ALT or AST (approximately three or more times the upper limit of normal) have been reported in approximately 1% of patients in clinical trials with NSAIDs. In addition, rare cases of severe hepatic reactions have been reported, including jaundice, fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis and hepatic failure, some with fatal outcomes. A patient with symptoms and/or signs suggesting liver dysfunction, or with abnormal liver test values, should be evaluated for evidence of the development of a more severe hepatic reaction while on therapy with ibuprofen. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.), ibuprofen should be discontinued.



    5.4 Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, can lead to onset of new hypertension or worsening of pre-existing hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. Use NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, with caution in patients with hypertension. Monitor blood pressure closely during the initiation of NSAID treatment and throughout the course of therapy.



 Patients taking ACE inhibitors, thiazides, or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs.



    5.5 Congestive Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention and edema have been observed in some patients taking NSAIDs. Use Caldolor with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure.



    5.6 Renal Effects



  Use caution when initiating treatment with Caldolor in patients with considerable dehydration.



 Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of an NSAID may cause a dose dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics or ACE inhibitors, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



 No information is available from controlled clinical studies regarding the use of Caldolor in patients with advanced renal disease. If Caldolor therapy must be initiated in patients with advanced renal disease, closely monitor the patient's renal function.



    5.7 Anaphylactoid Reactions



  As with other NSAIDs, anaphylactoid reactions may occur in patients without known prior exposure to ibuprofen. Caldolor is contraindicated in patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [see Contraindications (  4.2  )]  .



    5.8 Serious Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, can cause serious skin adverse reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations, and to discontinue Caldolor at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity.



    5.9 Pregnancy



  Starting at 30 weeks gestation, Caldolor, and other NSAIDs, should be avoided by pregnant women as premature closure of the ductus arteriosus in the fetus may occur [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



    5.10 Masking Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of ibuprofen in reducing fever and inflammation may diminish the utility of these diagnostic signs in detecting complications of presumed noninfectious, painful conditions.



    5.11 Hematological Effects



  Caldolor must be diluted prior to use. Infusion of the drug product without dilution can cause hemolysis [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )]  .



 Anemia may occur in patients receiving NSAIDs, including ibuprofen. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect on erythropoiesis. In patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, check hemoglobin or hematocrit if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia or blood loss.



 NSAIDs inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effects on platelet function are less severe quantitatively, of shorter duration, and reversible. Carefully monitor patients who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants.



    5.12 Pre-existing Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm, which can be fatal. Since cross-reactivity between aspirin and NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, including bronchospasm, Caldolor is contraindicated in patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and should be used with caution in all patients with pre-existing asthma.



    5.13 Ophthalmological Effects



  Blurred or diminished vision, scotomata, and changes in color vision have been reported with oral ibuprofen. Discontinue ibuprofen if a patient develops such complaints, and refer the patient for an ophthalmologic examination that includes central visual fields and color vision testing.



    5.14 Aseptic Meningitis



  Aseptic meningitis with fever and coma has been observed in patients on oral ibuprofen therapy. Although it is probably more likely to occur in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus and related connective tissue diseases, it has been reported in patients who do not have underlying chronic disease. If signs or symptoms of meningitis develop in a patient on ibuprofen, give consideration to whether or not the signs or symptoms are related to ibuprofen therapy.



    5.15 Monitoring



  Because serious GI tract ulcerations and bleeding can occur without warning symptoms, physicians should monitor for signs or symptoms of GI bleeding.



 Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs should have CBC and chemistry profiles checked periodically. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver or renal disease develop, systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash), or abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, discontinue Caldolor.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
