<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="camptosar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions (&gt;=30%) observed in combination therapy clinical studies are: nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, constipation, anorexia, mucositis, neutropenia, leukopenia (including lymphocytopenia), anemia, thrombocytopenia, asthenia, pain, fever, infection, abnormal bilirubin, alopecia. (  6.1  )



 Common adverse reactions (&gt;=30%) observed in single agent therapy clinical studies are: nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, constipation, anorexia, neutropenia, leukopenia (including lymphocytopenia), anemia, asthenia, fever, body weight decreasing, alopecia. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc at 1-800-438-1985 or www.pfizer.com or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Common adverse reactions (&gt;=30%) observed in combination therapy clinical studies are: nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, constipation, anorexia, mucositis, neutropenia, leukopenia (including lymphocytopenia), anemia, thrombocytopenia, asthenia, pain, fever, infection, abnormal bilirubin, and alopecia.



 Common adverse reactions (&gt;=30%) observed in single agent therapy clinical studies are: nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, constipation, anorexia, neutropenia, leukopenia (including lymphocytopenia), anemia, asthenia, fever, body weight decreasing, and alopecia.



 Serious opportunistic infections have not been observed, and no complications have specifically been attributed to lymphocytopenia.



     First-Line Combination Therapy  



 A total of 955 patients with metastatic colorectal cancer received the recommended regimens of irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV, 5-FU/LV alone, or irinotecan alone. In the two phase 3 studies, 370 patients received irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV, 362 patients received 5-FU/LV alone, and 223 patients received irinotecan alone  [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



 In Study 1, 49 (7.3%) patients died within 30 days of last study treatment: 21 (9.3%) received irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV, 15 (6.8%) received 5-FU/LV alone, and 13 (5.8%) received irinotecan alone. Deaths potentially related to treatment occurred in 2 (0.9%) patients who received irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV (2 neutropenic fever/sepsis), 3 (1.4%) patients who received 5-FU/LV alone (1 neutropenic fever/sepsis, 1 CNS bleeding during thrombocytopenia, 1 unknown) and 2 (0.9%) patients who received irinotecan alone (2 neutropenic fever). Deaths from any cause within 60 days of first study treatment were reported for 15 (6.7%) patients who received irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV, 16 (7.3%) patients who received 5-FU/LV alone, and 15 (6.7%) patients who received irinotecan alone. Discontinuations due to adverse events were reported for 17 (7.6%) patients who received irinotecan in combination with 5FU/LV, 14 (6.4%) patients who received 5-FU/LV alone, and 26 (11.7%) patients who received irinotecan alone.



 In Study 2, 10 (3.5%) patients died within 30 days of last study treatment: 6 (4.1%) received irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV and 4 (2.8%) received 5-FU/LV alone. There was one potentially treatment-related death, which occurred in a patient who received irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV (0.7%, neutropenic sepsis). Deaths from any cause within 60 days of first study treatment were reported for 3 (2.1%) patients who received irinotecan in combination with 5-FU/LV and 2 (1.4%) patients who received 5-FU/LV alone. Discontinuations due to adverse events were reported for 9 (6.2%) patients who received irinotecan in combination with 5FU/LV and 1 (0.7%) patient who received 5-FU/LV alone.



 The most clinically significant adverse events for patients receiving irinotecan-based therapy were diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, neutropenia, and alopecia. The most clinically significant adverse events for patients receiving 5-FU/LV therapy were diarrhea, neutropenia, neutropenic fever, and mucositis. In Study 1, grade 4 neutropenia, neutropenic fever (defined as grade 2 fever and grade 4 neutropenia), and mucositis were observed less often with weekly irinotecan/5-FU/LV than with monthly administration of 5-FU/LV.



 Tables 5 and 6 list the clinically relevant adverse events reported in Studies 1 and 2, respectively.



 Table 5. Study 1: Percent (%) of Patients Experiencing Clinically Relevant Adverse Events in Combination TherapiesSeverity of adverse events based on NCI CTC (version 1.0) 
 Adverse Event                              Study 1     
 Irinotecan + Bolus 5-FU/LV weekly * 4 every 6 weeksN=225  Bolus 5-FU/LV daily * 5 every 4 weeksN=219  Irinotecan weekly * 4 every 6 weeksN=223   
 Grade 1-4                                 Grade 3&amp;4   Grade 1-4   Grade 3&amp;4   Grade 1-4   Grade 3&amp;4    
  
 TOTAL Adverse Events                         100         53.3        100         45.7        99.6        45.7      
   GASTROINTESTINAL                                                                                                 
   Diarrhea                                   84.9        22.7        69.4        13.2        83.0        31.0      
     late                                      --         15.1         --         5.9          --         18.4      
       grade 3                                 --         7.6          --         7.3          --         12.6      
       grade 4                                45.8        4.9         31.5        1.4         43.0        6.7       
     early                                                                                                          
   Nausea                                     79.1        15.6        67.6        8.2         81.6        16.1      
   Abdominal pain                             63.1        14.6        50.2        11.5        67.7        13.0      
   Vomiting                                   60.4        9.7         46.1        4.1         62.8        12.1      
   Anorexia                                   34.2        5.8         42.0        3.7         43.9        7.2       
   Constipation                               41.3        3.1         31.5        1.8         32.3        0.4       
   Mucositis                                  32.4        2.2         76.3        16.9        29.6        2.2       
   HEMATOLOGIC                                                                                                      
   Neutropenia                                96.9        53.8        98.6        66.7        96.4        31.4      
     grade 3                                   --         29.8         --         23.7         --         19.3      
     grade 4                                   --         24.0         --         42.5         --         12.1      
   Leukopenia                                 96.9        37.8        98.6        23.3        96.4        21.5      
   Anemia                                     96.9        8.4         98.6        5.5         96.9        4.5       
   Neutropenic fever                           --         7.1          --         14.6         --         5.8       
   Thrombocytopenia                           96.0        2.6         98.6        2.7         96.0        1.7       
   Neutropenic infection                       --         1.8          --          0           --         2.2       
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                                  
   Asthenia                                   70.2        19.5        64.4        11.9        69.1        13.9      
   Pain                                       30.7        3.1         26.9        3.6         22.9        2.2       
   Fever                                      42.2        1.7         32.4        3.6         43.5        0.4       
   Infection                                  22.2         0          16.0        1.4         13.9        0.4       
   METABOLIC &amp; NUTRITIONAL                                                                                          
   Bilirubin                                  87.6        7.1         92.2        8.2         83.9        7.2       
   DERMATOLOGIC                               0.9          0          3.2         0.5          0           0        
   Exfoliative dermatitis                     19.1         0          26.5        0.9         14.3        0.4       
   Rash                                       43.1         --         26.5         --         46.1         --       
   Alopecia                                                                                                         
   RESPIRATORY                                                                                                      
   Dyspnea                                    27.6        6.3         16.0        0.5         22.0        2.2       
   Cough                                      26.7        1.3         18.3         0          20.2        0.4       
   Pneumonia                                  6.2         2.7         1.4         1.0         3.6         1.3       
   NEUROLOGIC                                                                                                       
   Dizziness                                  23.1        1.3         16.4         0          21.1        1.8       
   Somnolence                                 12.4        1.8         4.6         1.8         9.4         1.3       
   Confusion                                  7.1         1.8         4.1          0          2.7          0        
   CARDIOVASCULAR                             9.3         0.9         5.0          0          9.0          0        
   Vasodilatation                             5.8         1.3         2.3         0.5         5.8         1.7       
   Hypotension                                9.3          --         11.4         --         5.4          --       
   Thromboembolic events                                                                                            
            Table 6. Study 2: Percent (%) of Patients Experiencing Clinically Relevant Adverse Events in Combination TherapiesSeverity of adverse events based on NCI CTC (version 1.0) 
 Adverse Event                                 Study 2       
 Irinotecan + 5-FU/LV infusional days 1&amp;2 every 2 weeksN= 145  5-FU/LV infusional days 1&amp;2 every 2 weeksN=143   
                                             Grades 1-4       Grades 3&amp;4       Grades 1-4       Grades 3&amp;4      
  
 TOTAL Adverse Events                            100             72.4              100             39.2         
   GASTROINTESTINAL                                                                                             
   Diarrhea                                     72.4             14.4             44.8              6.3         
     late                                        --              10.3              --               4.2         
       grade 3                                   --               4.1              --               2.1         
       grade 4                                  28.3              1.4              0.7               0          
   Cholinergic syndrome                                                                                         
   Nausea                                       66.9              2.1             55.2              3.5         
   Abdominal pain                               17.2              2.1             16.8              0.7         
   Vomiting                                     44.8              3.5             32.2              2.8         
   Anorexia                                     35.2              2.1             18.9              0.7         
   Constipation                                 30.3              0.7             25.2              1.4         
   Mucositis                                    40.0              4.1             28.7              2.8         
   HEMATOLOGIC                                                                                                  
   Neutropenia                                  82.5             46.2             47.9             13.4         
     grade 3                                     --              36.4              --              12.7         
     grade 4                                     --               9.8              --               0.7         
   Leukopenia                                   81.3             17.4             42.0              3.5         
   Anemia                                       97.2              2.1             90.9              2.1         
   Neutropenic fever                             --               3.4              --               0.7         
   Thrombocytopenia                             32.6               0              32.2               0          
   Neutropenic infection                         --               2.1              --                0          
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                              
   Asthenia                                     57.9              9.0             48.3              4.2         
   Pain                                         64.1              9.7             61.5              8.4         
   Fever                                        22.1              0.7             25.9              0.7         
   Infection                                    35.9              7.6             33.6              3.5         
   METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL                                                                                    
   Bilirubin                                    19.1              3.5             35.9             10.6         
   DERMATOLOGIC                                 10.3              0.7             12.6              0.7         
   Hand and foot syndrome                       17.2              0.7             20.3               0          
   Cutaneous signs                              56.6              --              16.8              --          
   Alopecia                                                                                                     
   RESPIRATORY                                                                                                  
   Dyspnea                                       9.7              1.4              4.9               0          
   CARDIOVASCULAR                                3.4              1.4              0.7               0          
   Hypotension                                  11.7              --               5.6              --          
   Thromboembolic events                                                                                        
               Second-Line Single-Agent Therapy  
 

     Weekly Dosage Schedule  



 In three clinical studies evaluating the weekly dosage schedule, 304 patients with metastatic carcinoma of the colon or rectum that had recurred or progressed following 5-FU-based therapy were treated with CAMPTOSAR. Seventeen of the patients died within 30 days of the administration of CAMPTOSAR; in five cases (1.6%, 5/304), the deaths were potentially drug-related. One of the patients died of neutropenic sepsis without fever. Neutropenic fever occurred in nine (3.0%) other patients; these patients recovered with supportive care.



 One hundred nineteen (39.1%) of the 304 patients were hospitalized because of adverse events; 81 (26.6%) patients were hospitalized for events judged to be related to administration of CAMPTOSAR. The primary reasons for drug-related hospitalization were diarrhea, with or without nausea and/or vomiting (18.4%); neutropenia/leukopenia, with or without diarrhea and/or fever (8.2%); and nausea and/or vomiting (4.9%).



 The first dose of at least one cycle of CAMPTOSAR was reduced for 67% of patients who began the studies at the 125-mg/m  2  starting dose. Within-cycle dose reductions were required for 32% of the cycles initiated at the 125-mg/m  2  dose level. The most common reasons for dose reduction were late diarrhea, neutropenia, and leukopenia. Thirteen (4.3%) patients discontinued treatment with CAMPTOSAR because of adverse events. The adverse events in Table 7 are based on the experience of the 304 patients enrolled in the three studies described in    Clinical Studies (14.1)    .



 Table 7. Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;10% of 304 Previously Treated Patients with Metastatic Carcinoma of the Colon or RectumSeverity of adverse events based on NCI CTC (version 1.0) 
                                              % of Patients Reporting       
 Body System &amp; Event                               NCI Grades 1-4                 NCI Grades 3 &amp; 4          
  
   GASTROINTESTINAL                                                                                         
   Diarrhea (late)                                       88                              31                 
     7-9 stools/day (grade 3)                            -                              (16)                
     &gt;=10 stools/day (grade 4)                           -                              (14)                
   Nausea                                                86                              17                 
   Vomiting                                              67                              12                 
   Anorexia                                              55                              6                  
   Diarrhea (early)                                      51                              8                  
   Constipation                                          30                              2                  
   Flatulence                                            12                              0                  
   Stomatitis                                            12                              1                  
   Dyspepsia                                             10                              0                  
   HEMATOLOGIC                                                                                              
   Leukopenia                                            63                              28                 
   Anemia                                                60                              7                  
   Neutropenia                                           54                              26                 
     500 to &lt;1000/mm  3  (grade 3)                       -                              (15)                
     &lt;500/mm  3  (grade 4)                               -                              (12)                
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                          
   Asthenia                                              76                              12                 
   Abdominal cramping/pain                               57                              16                 
   Fever                                                 45                              1                  
   Pain                                                  24                              2                  
   Headache                                              17                              1                  
   Back pain                                             14                              2                  
   Chills                                                14                              0                  
   Minor infection                                       14                              0                  
   Edema                                                 10                              1                  
   Abdominal enlargement                                 10                              0                  
   METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL                                                                                
   ? Body weight                                         30                              1                  
   Dehydration                                           15                              4                  
   ? Alkaline phosphatase                                13                              4                  
   ? SGOT                                                10                              1                  
   DERMATOLOGIC                                                                                             
   Alopecia                                              60                              NA                 
   Sweating                                              16                              0                  
   Rash                                                  13                              1                  
   RESPIRATORY                                                                                              
   Dyspnea                                               22                              4                  
   ? Coughing                                            17                              0                  
   Rhinitis                                              16                              0                  
   NEUROLOGIC                                                                                               
   Insomnia                                              19                              0                  
   Dizziness                                             15                              0                  
   CARDIOVASCULAR                                                                                           
   Vasodilation (flushing)                               11                              0                  
             Once-Every-3-Week Dosage Schedule  
 

 A total of 535 patients with metastatic colorectal cancer whose disease had recurred or progressed following prior 5-FU therapy participated in the two phase 3 studies: 316 received irinotecan, 129 received 5-FU, and 90 received best supportive care. Eleven (3.5%) patients treated with irinotecan died within 30 days of treatment. In three cases (1%, 3/316), the deaths were potentially related to irinotecan treatment and were attributed to neutropenic infection, grade 4 diarrhea, and asthenia, respectively. One (0.8%, 1/129) patient treated with 5-FU died within 30 days of treatment; this death was attributed to grade 4 diarrhea.



 Hospitalizations due to serious adverse events occurred at least once in 60% (188/316) of patients who received irinotecan, 63% (57/90) who received best supportive care, and 39% (50/129) who received 5-FU-based therapy. Eight percent of patients treated with irinotecan and 7% treated with 5-FU-based therapy discontinued treatment due to adverse events.



 Of the 316 patients treated with irinotecan, the most clinically significant adverse events (all grades, 1-4) were diarrhea (84%), alopecia (72%), nausea (70%), vomiting (62%), cholinergic symptoms (47%), and neutropenia (30%). Table 8 lists the grade 3 and 4 adverse events reported in the patients enrolled to all treatment arms of the two studies described in    Clinical Studies (14.1)    .



 Table 8: Percent Of Patients Experiencing Grade 3 &amp; 4 Adverse Events In Comparative Studies Of Once-Every-3-Week Irinotecan TherapySeverity of adverse events based on NCI CTC (version 1.0) 
                                      Study 1             Study 2        
 Adverse Event                    IrinotecanN=189         BSCN=90        IrinotecanN=127        5-FUN=129       
  
 TOTAL Grade 3/4 Adverse Events          79                 67                  69                 54           
   GASTROINTESTINAL                                                                                             
   Diarrhea                              22                  6                  22                 11           
   Vomiting                              14                  8                  14                  5           
   Nausea                                14                  3                  11                  4           
   Abdominal pain                        14                 16                  9                   8           
   Constipation                          10                  8                  8                   6           
   Anorexia                              5                   7                  6                   4           
   Mucositis                             2                   1                  2                   5           
   HEMATOLOGIC                                                                                                  
   Leukopenia/Neutropenia                22                  0                  14                  2           
   Anemia                                7                   6                  6                   3           
   Hemorrhage                            5                   3                  1                   3           
   Thrombocytopenia                      1                   0                  4                   2           
   Infection                                                                                                    
   without grade 3/4 neutropenia          8                   3                  1                   4           
   with grade 3/4 neutropenia            1                   0                  2                   0           
   Fever                                                                                                        
   without grade 3/4 neutropenia          2                   1                  2                   0           
   with grade 3/4 neutropenia            2                   0                  4                   2           
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                              
   Pain                                  19                 22                  17                 13           
   Asthenia                              15                 19                  13                 12           
   METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL                                                                                    
 Hepatic                                 9                   7                  9                   6           
   DERMATOLOGIC                                                                                                 
   Hand and foot syndrome                0                   0                  0                   5           
   Cutaneous signs                       2                   0                  1                   3           
   RESPIRATORY                           10                  8                  5                   7           
   NEUROLOGIC                            12                 13                  9                   4           
   CARDIOVASCULAR                        9                   3                  4                   2           
   OTHER                                 32                 28                  12                 14           
           The incidence of akathisia in clinical trials of the weekly dosage schedule was greater (8.5%, 4/47 patients) when prochlorperazine was administered on the same day as CAMPTOSAR than when these drugs were given on separate days (1.3%, 1/80 patients). The 8.5% incidence of akathisia, however, is within the range reported for use of prochlorperazine when given as a premedication for other chemotherapies.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of CAMPTOSAR. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Myocardial ischemic events have been observed following CAMPTOSAR therapy. Thromboembolic events have been observed in patients receiving CAMPTOSAR.



 Symptomatic pancreatitis, asymptomatic pancreatic enzyme elevation have been reported. Increases in serum levels of transaminases (i.e., AST and ALT) in the absence of progressive liver metastasis have been observed.



 Hyponatremia, mostly with diarrhea and vomiting, has been reported.



 Transient dysarthria has been reported in patients treated with CAMPTOSAR; in some cases, the event was attributed to the cholinergic syndrome observed during or shortly after infusion of irinotecan.



 Interaction between CAMPTOSAR and neuromuscular blocking agents cannot be ruled out. Irinotecan has anticholinesterase activity, which may prolong the neuromuscular blocking effects of suxamethonium and the neuromuscular blockade of non-depolarizing drugs may be antagonized.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  DIARRHEA and MYELOSUPPRESSION

    WARNING:  DIARRHEA and MYELOSUPPRESSION  

    *  Early and late forms of diarrhea can occur. Early diarrhea may be accompanied by cholinergic symptoms which may be prevented or ameliorated by atropine. Late diarrhea can be life threatening and should be treated promptly with loperamide. Monitor patients with diarrhea and give fluid and electrolytes as needed. Institute antibiotic therapy if patients develop ileus, fever, or severe neutropenia. Interrupt CAMPTOSAR and reduce subsequent doses if severe diarrhea occurs. 
 *  Severe myelosuppression may occur. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: DIARRHEA and MYELOSUPPRESSION
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .



 *  Early and late forms of diarrhea can occur. Early diarrhea may be accompanied by cholinergic symptoms which may be prevented or ameliorated by atropine. Late diarrhea can be life threatening and should be treated promptly with loperamide. Monitor patients with diarrhea and give fluid and electrolytes as needed. Institute antibiotic therapy if patients develop ileus, fever, or severe neutropenia. Interrupt CAMPTOSAR and reduce subsequent doses if severe diarrhea occurs. 
 *  Severe myelosuppression may occur. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Diarrhea and Cholinergic Reactions : Early diarrhea (occurring during or shortly after infusion of CAMPTOSAR) is usually transient and may be accompanied by cholinergic symptoms. Consider prophylactic or therapeutic administration of 0.25 mg to 1 mg of intravenous or subcutaneous atropine (unless clinically contraindicated). Late diarrhea (generally occurring more than 24 hours after administration of CAMPTOSAR) can occur. Monitor and replace fluid and electrolytes. Treat with loperamide. Use antibiotic support for ileus and fever. Interrupt CAMPTOSAR and reduce subsequent doses if severe diarrhea occurs. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Myelosuppression : Manage promptly with antibiotic support. Interrupt CAMPTOSAR and reduce subsequent doses if necessary. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Patients with Reduced UGT1A1 Activity: Individuals who are homozygous for the UGT1A1*28 allele are at increased risk for neutropenia following initiation of CAMPTOSAR treatment. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity: Hypersensitivity reactions including severe anaphylactic or anaphylactoid reactions have been observed. Discontinue CAMPTOSAR if this occurs. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Renal Impairment/Renal Failure: Rare cases of renal impairment and acute renal failure have been identified, usually in patients who became volume depleted from severe vomiting and/or diarrhea. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Pulmonary Toxicity: Interstitial Pulmonary Disease (IPD)-like events, including fatalities, have occurred. Interrupt for new or progressive dysnpnea, cough, and fever pending evaluation. If IPD diagnosed, discontinue and institute appropriate treatment as needed. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Toxicity of the 5 Day Regimen: CAMPTOSAR should not be used in combination with a regimen of 5-FU/LV administered for 4-5 consecutive days every 4 weeks outside of a clinical study. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Embryofetal Toxicity: CAMPTOSAR can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. (  5.9  ) 
 *   Patients with Hepatic Impairment: In clinical trials, CAMPTOSAR has not been administered to patients with serum bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mg/dL, or transaminases &gt; 3 times ULN if no liver metastases, or transaminases &gt; 5 times ULN if liver metastases. With the weekly dosage schedule, patients with total bilirubin levels 1.0-2.0 mg/dL had greater likelihood of grade 3-4 neutropenia. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Diarrhea and Cholinergic Reactions



  Early diarrhea (occurring during or shortly after infusion of CAMPTOSAR) is usually transient and infrequently severe. It may be accompanied by cholinergic symptoms of rhinitis, increased salivation, miosis, lacrimation, diaphoresis, flushing, and intestinal hyperperistalsis that can cause abdominal cramping. Bradycardia may also occur. Early diarrhea and other cholinergic symptoms may be prevented or treated. Consider prophylactic or therapeutic administration of 0.25 mg to 1 mg of intravenous or subcutaneous atropine (unless clinically contraindicated). These symptoms are expected to occur more frequently with higher irinotecan doses.



 Late diarrhea (generally occurring more than 24 hours after administration of CAMPTOSAR) can be life threatening since it may be prolonged and may lead to dehydration, electrolyte imbalance, or sepsis. Grade 3-4 late diarrhea occurred in 23-31% of patients receiving weekly dosing. In the clinical studies, the median time to the onset of late diarrhea was 5 days with 3-week dosing and 11 days with weekly dosing. Late diarrhea can be complicated by colitis, ulceration, bleeding, ileus, obstruction, and infection. Cases of megacolon and intestinal perforation have been reported. Patients should have loperamide readily available to begin treatment for late diarrhea. Begin loperamide at the first episode of poorly formed or loose stools or the earliest onset of bowel movements more frequent than normal. One dosage regimen for loperamide is 4 mg at the first onset of late diarrhea and then 2 mg every 2 hours until the patient is diarrhea-free for at least 12 hours. Loperamide is not recommended to be used for more than 48 consecutive hours at these doses, because of the risk of paralytic ileus. During the night, the patient may take 4 mg of loperamide every 4 hours. Monitor and replace fluid and electrolytes. Use antibiotic support for ileus, fever, or severe neutropenia. Subsequent weekly chemotherapy treatments should be delayed in patients until return of pretreatment bowel function for at least 24 hours without anti-diarrhea medication. Patients must not be treated with CAMPTOSAR until resolution of the bowel obstruction. If grade 2, 3, or 4 late diarrhea recurs, subsequent doses of CAMPTOSAR should be decreased [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



 Avoid diuretics or laxatives in patients with diarrhea.



    5.2 Myelosuppression



  Deaths due to sepsis following severe neutropenia have been reported in patients treated with CAMPTOSAR. In the clinical studies evaluating the weekly dosage schedule, neutropenic fever (concurrent NCI grade 4 neutropenia and fever of grade 2 or greater) occurred in 3% of the patients; 6% of patients received G-CSF for the treatment of neutropenia. Manage febrile neutropenia promptly with antibiotic support [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  . Hold CAMPTOSAR if neutropenic fever occurs or if the absolute neutrophil count drops &lt;1000/mm  3  . After recovery to an absolute neutrophil count &gt;=1000/mm  3  , subsequent doses of CAMPTOSAR should be reduced [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



 When evaluated in the trials of weekly administration, the frequency of grade 3 and 4 neutropenia was higher in patients who received previous pelvic/abdominal irradiation than in those who had not received such irradiation (48% [13/27] versus 24% [67/277]; p=0.04). Patients who have previously received pelvic/abdominal irradiation are at increased risk of severe myelosuppression following the administration of CAMPTOSAR. Based on sparse available data, the concurrent administration of CAMPTOSAR with irradiation is not recommended.



 Patients with baseline serum total bilirubin levels of 1.0 mg/dL or more also had a greater likelihood of experiencing first-cycle grade 3 or 4 neutropenia than those with bilirubin levels that were less than 1.0 mg/dL (50% [19/38] versus 18% [47/266]; p&lt;0.001). Patients with deficient glucuronidation of bilirubin, such as those with Gilbert's syndrome, may be at greater risk of myelosuppression when receiving therapy with CAMPTOSAR.



    5.3 Patients With Reduced UGT1A1 Activity



  Individuals who are homozygous for the UGT1A1*28 allele (UGT1A1 7/7 genotype) are at increased risk for neutropenia following initiation of CAMPTOSAR treatment.



 In a study of 66 patients who received single-agent CAMPTOSAR (350 mg/m  2  once-every-3-weeks), the incidence of grade 4 neutropenia in patients homozygous for the UGT1A1*28 allele was 50%, and in patients heterozygous for this allele (UGT1A1 6/7 genotype) the incidence was 12.5%. No grade 4 neutropenia was observed in patients homozygous for the wild-type allele (UGT1A1 6/6 genotype).



 In a prospective study (n=250) to investigate the role of UGT1A1*28 polymorphism in the development of toxicity in patients treated with CAMPTOSAR (180 mg/m  2  ) in combination with infusional 5-FU/LV, the incidence of grade 4 neutropenia in patients homozygous for the UGT1A1*28 allele was 4.5%, and in patients heterozygous for this allele the incidence was 5.3%. Grade 4 neutropenia was observed in 1.8% of patients homozygous for the wild-type allele.



 In another study in which 109 patients were treated with CAMPTOSAR (100-125 mg/m  2  ) in combination with bolus 5-FU/LV, the incidence of grade 4 neutropenia in patients homozygous for the UGT1A1*28 allele was 18.2%, and in patients heterozygous for this allele the incidence was 11.1%. Grade 4 neutropenia was observed in 6.8% of patients homozygous for the wild-type allele.



 When administered in combination with other agents or as a single-agent, a reduction in the starting dose by at least one level of CAMPTOSAR should be considered for patients known to be homozygous for the UGT1A1*28 allele. However, the precise dose reduction in this patient population is not known and subsequent dose modifications should be considered based on individual patient tolerance to treatment [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



    UGT1A1 Testing  



 A laboratory test is available to determine the UGT1A1 status of patients. Testing can detect the UGT1A1 6/6, 6/7 and 7/7 genotypes.



    5.4 Hypersensitivity



  Hypersensitivity reactions including severe anaphylactic or anaphylactoid reactions have been observed. Discontinue CAMPTOSAR if anaphylactic reaction occurs.



    5.5 Renal Impairment/Renal Failure



  Renal impairment and acute renal failure have been identified, usually in patients who became volume depleted from severe vomiting and/or diarrhea.



    5.6 Pulmonary Toxicity



  Interstitial Pulmonary Disease (IPD)-like events, including fatalities, have occurred in patients receiving irinotecan (in combination and as monotherapy). Risk factors include pre-existing lung disease, use of pneumotoxic drugs, radiation therapy, and colony stimulating factors. Patients with risk factors should be closely monitored for respiratory symptoms before and during CAMPTOSAR therapy. In Japanese studies, a reticulonodular pattern on chest x-ray was observed in a small percentage of patients. New or progressive, dyspnea, cough, and fever should prompt interruption of chemotherapy, pending diagnostic evaluation. If IPD is diagnosed, CAMPTOSAR and other chemotherapy should be discontinued and appropriate treatment instituted as needed [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.7 Toxicity of the 5 Day Regimen



  Outside of a well-designed clinical study, CAMPTOSAR Injection should not be used in combination with a regimen of 5-FU/LV administered for 4-5 consecutive days every 4 weeks because of reports of increased toxicity, including toxic deaths. CAMPTOSAR should be used as recommended in Table 2 [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



    5.8 Increased Toxicity in Patients with Performance Status 2



  In patients receiving either irinotecan/5-FU/LV or 5-FU/LV in the clinical trials, higher rates of hospitalization, neutropenic fever, thromboembolism, first-cycle treatment discontinuation, and early deaths were observed in patients with a baseline performance status of 2 than in patients with a baseline performance status of 0 or 1.



    5.9 Embryofetal Toxicity



  CAMPTOSAR can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Irinotecan was embryotoxic in rats and rabbits at doses significantly lower than those administered to humans on a mg/m  2  basis. In rats, at exposures approximately 0.2 times those achieved in humans at the 125 mg/m  2  dose, irinotecan was embryotoxic and resulted in decreased learning ability and female fetal body weight in surviving pups; the drug was teratogenic at lower exposures (approximately 0.025 times the AUC in humans at the 125 mg/m  2  dose). There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of irinotecan in pregnant women. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving treatment with CAMPTOSAR.



    5.10 Patients with Hepatic Impairment



  The use of CAMPTOSAR in patients with significant hepatic impairment has not been established. In clinical trials of either dosing schedule, irinotecan was not administered to patients with serum bilirubin &gt;2.0 mg/dL, or transaminase &gt;3 times the upper limit of normal if no liver metastasis, or transaminase &gt;5 times the upper limit of normal with liver metastasis. In clinical trials of the weekly dosage schedule, patients with modestly elevated baseline serum total bilirubin levels (1.0 to 2.0 mg/dL) had a significantly greater likelihood of experiencing first-cycle, grade 3 or 4 neutropenia than those with bilirubin levels that were less than 1.0 mg/dL (50% [19/38] versus 18% [47/226]; p&lt;0.001) [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
