<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cancidas" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in detail in another section of the labeling:



 *  Hepatic effects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of CANCIDAS cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does provide a basis for identifying adverse reactions that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.
 

    EXCERPT:    *   Adults: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=10%) are diarrhea, pyrexia, ALT/AST increased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, and blood potassium decreased. (  6.1  ) 
 *   Pediatric patients: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=10%) are pyrexia, diarrhea, rash, ALT/AST increased, blood potassium decreased, hypotension, and chills. (  6.2  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience in Adults

  The overall safety of CANCIDAS was assessed in 1865 adult individuals who received single or multiple doses of CANCIDAS: 564 febrile, neutropenic patients (empirical therapy study); 382 patients with candidemia and/or intra-abdominal abscesses, peritonitis, or pleural space infections (including 4 patients with chronic disseminated candidiasis); 297 patients with esophageal and/or oropharyngeal candidiasis; 228 patients with invasive aspergillosis; and 394 individuals in phase I studies. In the empirical therapy study patients had undergone hematopoietic stem-cell transplantation or chemotherapy. In the studies involving patients with documented  Candida  infections, the majority of the patients had serious underlying medical conditions (e.g., hematologic or other malignancy, recent major surgery, HIV) requiring multiple concomitant medications. Patients in the noncomparative  Aspergillus  studies often had serious predisposing medical conditions (e.g., bone marrow or peripheral stem cell transplants, hematologic malignancy, solid tumors or organ transplants) requiring multiple concomitant medications.



     Empirical Therapy    



 In the randomized, double-blinded empirical therapy study, patients received either CANCIDAS 50 mg/day (following a 70-mg loading dose) or AmBisome  (r)  (amphotericin B liposome for injection, 3 mg/kg/day). In this study clinical or laboratory hepatic adverse reactions were reported in 39% and 45% of patients in the CANCIDAS and AmBisome groups, respectively. Also reported was an isolated, serious adverse reaction of hyperbilirubinemia considered possibly related to CANCIDAS. Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=7.5% of the patients in either treatment group are presented in Table 2.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Among Patients with Persistent Fever and NeutropeniaRegardless of causality Incidence &gt;=7.5% for at Least One Treatment Group by System Organ Class or Preferred Term 
 Adverse Reaction(MedDRA v10.1 System Organ Class and Preferred Term)  CANCIDASN=564 (percent)  AmBisomeN=547 (percent)   
  
 Within any system organ class, individuals may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.   
  
   All Systems, Any Adverse Reaction                            95                   97                    
   Investigations                                               58                   63                    
    Alanine Aminotransferase Increased                        18                   20                      
    Blood Alkaline Phosphatase Increased                      15                   23                      
    Blood Potassium Decreased                                 15                   23                      
    Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased                      14                   17                      
    Blood Bilirubin Increased                                 10                   14                      
    Blood Albumin Decreased                                   7                    8                       
    Blood Magnesium Decreased                                 7                    9                       
    Blood Glucose Increased                                   6                    9                       
    Bilirubin Conjugated Increased                            5                    9                       
    Blood Urea Increased                                      4                    8                       
    Blood Creatinine Increased                                3                    11                      
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions         57                   63                    
    Pyrexia                                                   27                   29                      
    Chills                                                    23                   31                      
    Edema Peripheral                                          11                   12                      
    Mucosal Inflammation                                      6                    8                       
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                   50                   55                    
    Diarrhea                                                  20                   16                      
    Nausea                                                    11                   20                      
    Abdominal Pain                                            9                    11                      
    Vomiting                                                  9                    17                      
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders              47                   49                    
    Cough                                                     11                   10                      
    Dyspnea                                                   9                    10                      
    Rales                                                     7                    8                       
   Infections and Infestations                                  45                   42                    
    Pneumonia                                                 11                   10                      
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                       42                   37                    
    Rash                                                      16                   14                      
   Nervous System Disorders                                     25                   27                    
    Headache                                                  11                   12                      
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                           21                   24                    
    Hypokalemia                                               6                    8                       
   Vascular Disorders                                           20                   23                    
    Hypotension                                               6                    10                      
   Cardiac Disorders                                            16                   19                    
    Tachycardia                                               7                    9                       
         The proportion of patients who experienced an infusion-related adverse reaction (defined as a systemic event, such as pyrexia, chills, flushing, hypotension, hypertension, tachycardia, dyspnea, tachypnea, rash, or anaphylaxis, that developed during the study therapy infusion and one hour following infusion) was significantly lower in the group treated with CANCIDAS (35%) than in the group treated with AmBisome (52%).
 

 To evaluate the effect of CANCIDAS and AmBisome on renal function, nephrotoxicity was defined as doubling of serum creatinine relative to baseline or an increase of &gt;=1 mg/dL in serum creatinine if baseline serum creatinine was above the upper limit of the normal range. Among patients whose baseline creatinine clearance was &gt;30 mL/min, the incidence of nephrotoxicity was significantly lower in the group treated with CANCIDAS (3%) than in the group treated with AmBisome (12%). Clinical renal events, regardless of causality, were similar between CANCIDAS (75/564, 13%) and AmBisome (85/547, 16%).



     Candidemia and Other Candida Infections    



 In the randomized, double-blinded invasive candidiasis study, patients received either CANCIDAS 50 mg/day (following a 70-mg loading dose) or amphotericin B 0.6 to 1 mg/kg/day. Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=10% of the patients in either treatment group are presented in Table 3.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Among Patients with Candidemia or other Candida InfectionsIntra-abdominal abscesses, peritonitis and pleural space infections., Regardless of causality Incidence &gt;=10% for at Least One Treatment Group by System Organ Class or Preferred Term 
 Adverse Reaction(MedDRA v10.1 System Organ Class and Preferred Term)  CANCIDAS50 mgN=114(percent)  Amphotericin BN=125 (percent)   
  
 Within any system organ class, individuals may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.   
  
   All Systems, Any Adverse Reaction                             96                 99                     
   Investigations                                                67                 82                     
    Blood Potassium Decreased                                  23                 32                       
    Blood Alkaline Phosphatase Increased                       21                 32                       
    Hemoglobin Decreased                                       18                 23                       
    Alanine Aminotransferase Increased                         16                 15                       
    Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased                       16                 14                       
    Blood Bilirubin Increased                                  13                 17                       
    Hematocrit Decreased                                       13                 18                       
    Blood Creatinine Increased                                 11                 28                       
    Red Blood Cells Urine Positive                             10                 10                       
    Blood Urea Increased                                       9                  23                       
    Bilirubin Conjugated Increased                             8                  14                       
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                    49                 53                     
    Vomiting                                                   17                 16                       
    Diarrhea                                                   14                 10                       
    Nausea                                                     9                  17                       
   Infections and Infestations                                   48                 54                     
    Septic Shock                                               11                 9                        
    Pneumonia                                                  4                  10                       
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions          47                 63                     
    Pyrexia                                                    13                 33                       
    Edema Peripheral                                           11                 12                       
    Chills                                                     9                  30                       
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders               40                 54                     
    Respiratory Failure                                        11                 12                       
    Pleural Effusion                                           9                  14                       
    Tachypnea                                                  1                  11                       
   Cardiac Disorders                                             26                 34                     
    Tachycardia                                                8                  12                       
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                        25                 28                     
    Rash                                                       4                  10                       
   Vascular Disorders                                            25                 38                     
     Hypotension                                               10                 16                       
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders                          15                 13                     
    Anemia                                                     11                 9                        
         The proportion of patients who experienced an infusion-related adverse reaction (defined as a systemic event, such as pyrexia, chills, flushing, hypotension, hypertension, tachycardia, dyspnea, tachypnea, rash, or anaphylaxis, that developed during the study therapy infusion and one hour following infusion) was significantly lower in the group treated with CANCIDAS (20%) than in the group treated with amphotericin B (49%).
 

 To evaluate the effect of CANCIDAS and amphotericin B on renal function, nephrotoxicity was defined as doubling of serum creatinine relative to baseline or an increase of &gt;=1 mg/dL in serum creatinine if baseline serum creatinine was above the upper limit of the normal range. In a subgroup of patients whose baseline creatinine clearance was &gt;30 mL/min, the incidence of nephrotoxicity was significantly lower in the group treated with CANCIDAS than in the group treated with amphotericin B.



 In a second randomized, double-blinded invasive candidiasis study, patients received either CANCIDAS 50 mg/day (following a 70-mg loading dose) or CANCIDAS 150 mg/day. The proportion of patients who experienced any adverse reaction was similar in the 2 treatment groups; however, this study was not large enough to detect differences in rare or unexpected adverse events. Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of the patients in either treatment group are presented in Table 4.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions Among Patients with Candidemia or other Candida InfectionsIntra-abdominal abscesses, peritonitis and pleural space infections., Regardless of causality Incidence &gt;=5% for at Least One Treatment Group by System Organ Class or Preferred Term 
  Adverse Reaction (MedDRA v11.0 System Organ Class and Preferred Term)   CANCIDAS 50 mgPatients received CANCIDAS 70 mg on Day 1, then 50 mg once daily for the remainder of their treatment. N=104 (percent)   CANCIDAS 150 mg N=100 (percent)   
  
 Within any system organ class, individuals may experience more than 1 adverse event   
  
   All Systems, Any Adverse Reaction                         83                      83                   
   Infections and Infestations                               44                      43                   
    Septic Shock                                           13                      14                     
    Pneumonia                                              5                       7                      
    Sepsis                                                 5                       7                      
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions      33                      27                   
    Pyrexia                                                6                       6                      
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                30                      33                   
    Vomiting                                               11                      6                      
    Diarrhea                                               6                       7                      
    Nausea                                                 5                       7                      
   Investigations                                            28                      35                   
    Alkaline Phosphatase Increased                         12                      9                      
    Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased                   6                       9                      
    Blood potassium decreased                              6                       8                      
    Alanine Aminotransferase Increased                     4                       7                      
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders           23                      26                   
    Respiratory Failure                                    6                       2                      
   Vascular Disorders                                        19                      18                   
    Hypotension                                            7                       3                      
    Hypertension                                           5                       6                      
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                    15                      15                   
    Decubitus Ulcer                                        3                       5                      
             Esophageal Candidiasis and Oropharyngeal Candidiasis    
 

 Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=10% of patients with esophageal and/or oropharyngeal candidiasis are presented in Table 5.



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions Among Patients with Esophageal and/or Oropharyngeal CandidiasisRegardless of causality Incidence &gt;=10% for at Least One Treatment Group by System Organ Class or Preferred Term 
 Adverse Reaction(MedDRA v10.1 System Organ Class and Preferred Term)  CANCIDAS50 mgN=83(percent)  Fluconazole IV200 mgN=94(percent)   
  
 Within any system organ class, individuals may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.   
  
   All Systems, Any Adverse Reaction                            90                  93                    
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                   58                  50                    
    Diarrhea                                                  27                  18                      
    Nausea                                                    15                  15                      
   Investigations                                               53                  61                    
    Hemoglobin Decreased                                      21                  16                      
    Hematocrit Decreased                                      18                  16                      
    Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased                      13                  19                      
    Blood Alkaline Phosphatase Increased                      13                  17                      
    Alanine Aminotransferase Increased                        12                  17                      
    White Blood Cell Count Decreased                          12                  19                      
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions         31                  36                    
    Pyrexia                                                   21                  21                      
   Vascular Disorders                                           19                  15                    
    Phlebitis                                                 18                  11                      
   Nervous System Disorders                                     18                  17                    
    Headache                                                  15                  9                       
             Invasive Aspergillosis    
 

 In an open-label, noncomparative aspergillosis study, in which 69 patients received CANCIDAS (70-mg loading dose on Day 1 followed by 50 mg daily), the following treatment-emergent adverse reactions were observed with an incidence of &gt;=12.5%: blood alkaline phosphatase increased (22%), hypotension (20%), respiratory failure (20%), pyrexia (17%), diarrhea (15%), nausea (15%), headache (15%), rash (13%), aspergillosis (13%), alanine aminotransferase increased (13%), aspartate aminotransferase increased (13%), blood bilirubin increased (13%), and blood potassium decreased (13%). Also reported infrequently in this patient population were pulmonary edema, ARDS (adult respiratory distress syndrome), and radiographic infiltrates.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience in Pediatric Patients (3 months to 17 years of age)

  The overall safety of CANCIDAS was assessed in 171 pediatric patients who received single or multiple doses of CANCIDAS. The distribution among the 153 pediatric patients who were over the age of 3 months was as follows: 104 febrile, neutropenic patients; 38 patients with candidemia and/or intra-abdominal abscesses, peritonitis, or pleural space infections; 1 patient with esophageal candidiasis; and 10 patients with invasive aspergillosis. The overall safety profile of CANCIDAS in pediatric patients is comparable to that in adult patients. Table 6 shows the incidence of adverse reactions reported in &gt;=7.5% of pediatric patients in clinical studies.



 One patient (0.6%) receiving CANCIDAS, and three patients (12%) receiving AmBisome developed a serious drug-related adverse reaction. Two patients (1%) were discontinued from CANCIDAS and three patients (12%) were discontinued from AmBisome due to a drug-related adverse reaction. The proportion of patients who experienced an infusion-related adverse reaction (defined as a systemic event, such as pyrexia, chills, flushing, hypotension, hypertension, tachycardia, dyspnea, tachypnea, rash, or anaphylaxis, that developed during the study therapy infusion and one hour following infusion) was 22% in the group treated with CANCIDAS and 35% in the group treated with AmBisome.



 Table 6: Adverse Reactions Among Pediatric Patients (0 months to 17 years of age)Regardless of causality Incidence &gt;=7.5% for at Least One Treatment Group by System Organ Class or Preferred Term 
                                                    NoncomparativeClinical Studies  Comparator-Controlled Clinical Study of Empirical Therapy   
 Adverse Reaction(MedDRA v10.0 System Organ Class and Preferred Term)  CANCIDASAny DoseN=115(percent)  CANCIDAS50 mg/m  2  N=56(percent)  AmBisome3 mg/kgN=26(percent)   
  
 Within any system organ class, individuals may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.   
  
   All Systems, Any Adverse Reaction                  95                  96                89              
   Investigations                                     55                  41                50              
    Blood Potassium Decreased                       18                  9                 27                
    Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased            17                  2                 12                
    Alanine Aminotransferase Increased              14                  5                 12                
    Blood Potassium Increased                       3                   0                 8                 
    Protein Total Decreased                         0                   0                 8                 
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions      47                  59                42              
    Pyrexia                                         29                  30                23                
    Chills                                          10                  13                8                 
    Mucosal Inflammation                            10                  4                 4                 
    Edema                                           3                   4                 8                 
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders      43                  32                27              
    Respiratory Distress                            8                   0                 4                 
    Cough                                           6                   9                 8                 
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                         42                  41                35              
    Diarrhea                                        17                  7                 15                
    Vomiting                                        8                   11                12                
    Abdominal Pain                                  7                   4                 12                
    Nausea                                          4                   4                 8                 
   Infections and Infestations                        40                  30                35              
   Central Line Infection                           1                   9                 0                 
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders             33                  41                39              
    Pruritus                                        7                   6                 8                 
    Rash                                            6                   23                8                 
    Erythema                                        4                   9                 0                 
   Vascular Disorders                                 24                  21                19              
    Hypotension                                     12                  9                 8                 
    Hypertension                                    10                  9                 4                 
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                 22                  11                23              
    Hypokalemia                                     8                   5                 4                 
   Cardiac Disorders                                  17                  13                19              
    Tachycardia                                     4                   11                19                
   Nervous System Disorders                           13                  16                8               
    Headache                                        5                   9                 4                 
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders      11                  14                12              
    Back Pain                                       4                   0                 8                 
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders               10                  2                 15              
    Anemia                                          2                   0                 8                 
   Immune System Disorders                            7                   7                 12              
    Graft Versus Host Disease                       1                   4                 8                 
            6.3 Overall Safety Experience of CANCIDAS in Clinical Trials
   The overall safety of CANCIDAS was assessed in 2036 individuals (including 1642 adult or pediatric patients and 394 volunteers) from 34 clinical studies. These individuals received single or multiple (once daily) doses of CANCIDAS, ranging from 5 mg to 210 mg. Full safety data is available from 1951 individuals, as the safety data from 85 patients enrolled in 2 compassionate use studies was limited solely to serious adverse reactions. Treatment emergent adverse reactions, regardless of causality, which occurred in &gt;=5% of all individuals who received CANCIDAS in these trials, are shown in Table 7.



 Overall, 1665 of the 1951 (85%) patients/volunteers who received CANCIDAS experienced an adverse reaction.



 Table 7: Treatment-EmergentDefined as an adverse reaction, regardless of causality, while on CANCIDAS or during the 14-day post-CANCIDAS follow-up period. Adverse Reactions in Patients Who Received CANCIDAS in Clinical TrialsIncidence for each preferred term is &gt;=5% among individuals who received at least 1 dose of CANCIDAS. Incidence &gt;=5% for at Least One Treatment Group by System Organ Class or Preferred Term 
 Adverse Reaction(MedDRA v10 System Organ Class and Preferred Term)  CANCIDAS(N = 1951)   
                                                                     n               (%)                  
  
   All Systems, Any Adverse Reaction                                   1665            (85)               
   Investigations                                                      901             (46)               
    Alanine Aminotransferase Increased                               258             (13)                 
    Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased                             233             (12)                 
    Blood Alkaline Phosphatase Increased                             232             (12)                 
    Blood Potassium Decreased                                        220             (11)                 
    Blood Bilirubin Increased                                        117             (6)                  
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                843             (43)               
    Pyrexia                                                          381             (20)                 
    Chills                                                           192             (10)                 
    Edema Peripheral                                                 110             (6)                  
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                          754             (39)               
    Diarrhea                                                         273             (14)                 
    Nausea                                                           166             (9)                  
    Vomiting                                                         146             (8)                  
    Abdominal Pain                                                   112             (6)                  
   Infections and Infestations                                         730             (37)               
    Pneumonia                                                        115             (6)                  
   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders                    613             (31)               
    Cough                                                            111             (6)                  
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                              520             (27)               
    Rash                                                             159             (8)                  
    Erythema                                                         98              (5)                  
   Nervous System Disorders                                            412             (21)               
    Headache                                                         193             (10)                 
   Vascular Disorders                                                  344             (18)               
    Hypotension                                                      118             (6)                  
         Clinically significant adverse reactions, regardless of causality or incidence which occurred in less than 5% of patients are listed below.
 

 *    Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  anemia, coagulopathy, febrile neutropenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia 
 *    Cardiac disorders:  arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, cardiac arrest, myocardial infarction, tachycardia 
 *    Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal distension, abdominal pain upper, constipation, dyspepsia 
 *    General disorders and administration site conditions:  asthenia, fatigue, infusion site pain/pruritus/swelling, mucosal inflammation, edema 
 *    Hepatobiliary disorders:  hepatic failure, hepatomegaly, hepatotoxicity, hyperbilirubinemia, jaundice 
 *    Infections and infestations:  bacteremia, sepsis, urinary tract infection 
 *    Metabolic and nutrition disorders:  anorexia, decreased appetite, fluid overload, hypomagnesemia, hypercalcemia, hyperglycemia, hypokalemia 
 *    Musculoskeletal, connective tissue, and bone disorders:  arthralgia, back pain, pain in extremity 
 *    Nervous system disorders:  convulsion, dizziness, somnolence, tremor 
 *    Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety, confusional state, depression, insomnia 
 *    Renal and urinary disorders:  hematuria, renal failure 
 *    Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:  dyspnea, epistaxis, hypoxia, tachypnea 
 *    Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  erythema, petechiae, skin lesion, urticaria 
 *    Vascular disorders:  flushing, hypertension, phlebitis 
      6.4 Postmarketing Experience
   The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during the post-approval use of CANCIDAS. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *   Gastrointestinal disorders: pancreatitis 
 *   Hepatobiliary disorders: hepatic necrosis 
 *   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders: erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson, skin exfoliation 
 *   Renal and urinary disorders: clinically significant renal dysfunction 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions: swelling and peripheral edema 
 *   Laboratory abnormalities: gamma-glutamyltransferase increased 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity:Anaphylaxis has been reported. If this occurs, CANCIDAS should be discontinued and appropriate treatment administered. Possible histamine-mediated adverse reactions, including rash, facial swelling, angioedema, pruritus, sensation of warmth or bronchospasm have been reported and may require discontinuation and/or administration of appropriate treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Use with cyclosporine: Limit use to patients for whom potential benefit outweighs potential risk. Monitor patients who develop abnormal liver function tests (LFTs) during concomitant therapy and evaluate risk/benefit of continuing CANCIDAS. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hepatic effects: Can cause abnormalities in LFTs and isolated cases of clinically significant hepatic dysfunction, hepatitis, or hepatic failure. Monitor patients who develop abnormal LFTs for evidence of worsening hepatic function, and evaluate risk/benefit of continuing CANCIDAS. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Anaphylaxis has been reported during administration of CANCIDAS. If this occurs, CANCIDAS should be discontinued and appropriate treatment administered.



 Possible histamine-mediated adverse reactions, including rash, facial swelling, angioedema, pruritus, sensation of warmth or bronchospasm have been reported and may require discontinuation and/or administration of appropriate treatment.



    5.2 Concomitant Use with Cyclosporine



  Concomitant use of CANCIDAS with cyclosporine should be limited to patients for whom the potential benefit outweighs the potential risk. In one clinical study, 3 of 4 healthy adult subjects who received CANCIDAS 70 mg on Days 1 through 10, and also received two 3 mg/kg doses of cyclosporine 12 hours apart on Day 10, developed transient elevations of alanine transaminase (ALT) on Day 11 that were 2 to 3 times the upper limit of normal (ULN). In a separate panel of adult subjects in the same study, 2 of 8 who received CANCIDAS 35 mg daily for 3 days and cyclosporine (two 3 mg/kg doses administered 12 hours apart) on Day 1 had small increases in ALT (slightly above the ULN) on Day 2. In both groups, elevations in aspartate transaminase (AST) paralleled ALT elevations, but were of lesser magnitude. In another clinical study, 2 of 8 healthy men developed transient ALT elevations of less than 2X ULN. In this study, cyclosporine (4 mg/kg) was administered on Days 1 and 12, and CANCIDAS was administered (70 mg) daily on Days 3 through 13. In one subject, the ALT elevation occurred on Days 7 and 9 and, in the other subject, the ALT elevation occurred on Day 19. These elevations returned to normal by Day 27. In all groups, elevations in AST paralleled ALT elevations but were of lesser magnitude. In these clinical studies, cyclosporine (one 4 mg/kg dose or two 3 mg/kg doses) increased the AUC of caspofungin by approximately 35%.



 In a retrospective postmarketing study, 40 immunocompromised patients, including 37 transplant recipients, were treated with CANCIDAS and cyclosporine for 1 to 290 days (median 17.5 days). Fourteen patients (35%) developed transaminase elevations &gt;5X upper limit of normal or &gt;3X baseline during concomitant therapy or the 14-day follow-up period; five were considered possibly related to concomitant therapy. One patient had elevated bilirubin considered possibly related to concomitant therapy. No patient developed clinical evidence of hepatotoxicity or serious hepatic events. Discontinuations due to laboratory abnormalities in hepatic enzymes from any cause occurred in four patients. Of these, 2 were considered possibly related to therapy with CANCIDAS and/or cyclosporine as well as to other possible causes.



 In the prospective invasive aspergillosis and compassionate use studies, there were 4 adult patients treated with CANCIDAS (50 mg/day) and cyclosporine for 2 to 56 days. None of these patients experienced increases in hepatic enzymes.



 Given the limitations of these data, CANCIDAS and cyclosporine should only be used concomitantly in those patients for whom the potential benefit outweighs the potential risk. Patients who develop abnormal liver function tests during concomitant therapy should be monitored and the risk/benefit of continuing therapy should be evaluated.



    5.3 Hepatic Effects



  Laboratory abnormalities in liver function tests have been seen in healthy volunteers and in adult and pediatric patients treated with CANCIDAS. In some adult and pediatric patients with serious underlying conditions who were receiving multiple concomitant medications with CANCIDAS, isolated cases of clinically significant hepatic dysfunction, hepatitis, and hepatic failure have been reported; a causal relationship to CANCIDAS has not been established. Patients who develop abnormal liver function tests during CANCIDAS therapy should be monitored for evidence of worsening hepatic function and evaluated for risk/benefit of continuing CANCIDAS therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
