<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="candin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Immediate hypersensitivity local reactions can include itching, swelling, pain and blistering at the test site occurring 15-20 minutes after administration. Necrosis is possible. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Systemic reactions to CANDIN have not been observed, however all foreign antigens have the remote possibility of causing Type 1 anaphylaxis and even death when injected intradermally. (  6.2  ) 
 *  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Nielsen Biosciences, Inc. at (855) 855-1212 or Food and Drug Administration (FDA) at 1-800-332-1088 or www.vaers.hhs.gov . (  6.3  ) 
    
     6.1  Local reactions to CANDIN have included swelling, pruritus and vesiculation. Reactions involving necrosis and ulceration have not been observed, but such reactions are theoretically possible and might occur in persons with exquisite cellular hypersensitivity to the antigen. Local reactions may be treated with a cold compress and topical steroids. Severe local reactions may require additional measures as appropriate.



 In a published study of 479 HIV positive adults tested with CANDIN, adverse local reactions were observed in six subjects as follows: pruritus (three), swelling at the test site (one), vesiculation (one) and vesiculation with weeping edema (one). Pruritus and swelling cleared within 48 hours; vesiculation with edema required approximately 1 week to resolve  6  



 In two studies involving 171 persons discussed under CLINICAL STUDIES in Tables 1, 2, 3, and text, one adverse reaction was observed. This reaction consisted of induration 22 x 55 mm at 48 hours which resolved within 1 week  8  .



 Testing of CANDIN for consistency of potency is performed in healthy human subjects who are known to be skin-test positive to the antigen. In 58 subjects tested to-date, there have been no cases of Type 1 allergy manifested as either generalized or adverse local reactions. One subject had induration with a central vesicle which subsided within a few days  8  .



 Severe local reactions, including rash, vesiculation, bullae, dermal exfoliation and cellulitis, have been reported to MedWatch for unstandardized allergenic extracts of  Candida albicans  used for anergy testing



     6.2  Systemic reactions to CANDIN have not been observed. However, all foreign antigens have the remote possibility of causing Type 1 anaphylaxis (7) and even death when injected intradermally. Systemic reactions usually occur within 30 minutes after the injection of antigen and may include the following symptoms: sneezing, coughing, itching, shortness of breath, abdominal cramps, vomiting, diarrhea, tachycardia, hypotension and respiratory failure in severe cases. Systemic allergic reactions including anaphylaxis must be immediately treated with Epinephrine HCL 1:1,000. Additional measures may be required, depending upon the severity of the reaction.



 Immediate Hypersensitivity reactions to CANDIN occur in some individuals. These reactions are characterized by the presence of an edematous hive surrounded by a zone of erythema. They occur approximately 15 - 20 minutes after the intradermal injection of the antigen. The size of the immediate reaction varies depending upon the sensitivity of the individual. Immediate hypersensitivity reactions were observed in the control and HIV-infected (AIDS and HIV positive) subjects reported in Table 2 as follows: HIV-infected subjects (20% with erythema of 10 - 21 mm in diameter; 13% with erythema of 5 - 9 mm). Control subjects (22% with erythema of 10 - 15 mm; 5% with erythema of 8.5 mm). Cancer subjects (Group 1, Table 3), 17% with erythema of 10 - 24 mm and 11% with erythema of 6 - 9 mm.



     6.3 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Nielsen Biosciences, Inc. at (855) 855-1212 or FDA at 1-800-833-7967 or  www.vaers.hhs.gov  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

    WARNING  

    *  The expected response to CANDIN is a local area of inflammation at the site of the skin test. The size of reaction depends upon the sensitivity of the person receiving the test, but is usually dime to quarter size reaching maximum diameter between 24 and 48 hours. Larger accelerated reactions can occur which may require treatment with local cold compresses and anti-inflammatory medication. (2.3, 6.1) 
 *  Systemic reactions can occur with skin test antigens and in certain individuals these reactions may be life-threatening or cause death. Emergency measures as well as personnel trained in their use should be immediately available in the event of a life-threatening reaction. Patients should be observed for at least 20 minutes following the administration of a skin test. (6.2) 
 *  CANDIN should never be given intravenously. See also Warnings and Precautions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious adverse reactions to CANDIN should be reported to Nielsen Biosciences, Inc. at (855) 855-1212 or MEDWATCH, Food and Drug Administration, 5600 Fishers Lane, Rockville, MD 20852-9782. Telephone: (800) 332-1088 or www.vaers.hhs.gov. (6.3) 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  The expected response to CANDIN is a local area of inflammation at the site of the skin test. The size of reaction depends upon the sensitivity of the person receiving the test, but is usually dime to quarter size reaching maximum diameter between 24 and 48 hours. Larger accelerated reactions can occur which may require treatment with local cold compresses and anti-inflammatory medication. (2.3, 6.1) 
 *  Systemic reactions can occur with skin test antigens and in certain individuals these reactions may be life-threatening or cause death. Emergency measures as well as personnel trained in their use should be immediately available in the event of a life-threatening reaction. Patients should be observed for at least 20 minutes following the administration of a skin test. (6.2) 
 *  CANDIN should never be given intravenously. See also Warnings and Precautions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious adverse reactions to CANDIN should be reported to Nielsen Biosciences, Inc. at (855) 855-1212 or MEDWATCH, Food and Drug Administration, 5600 Fishers Lane, Rockville, MD 20852-9782. Telephone: (800) 822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov. (6.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  The antigen must be injected intradermally. Do not inject intravenously. (  5.1  ) 
 *  As has been observed with other, unstandardized, antigens used for DTH skin testing, it is possible that some patients may have exquisite immediate hypersensitivity to CANDIN. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Physicians using this product must have facilities, equipment and medication necessary to treat potential side effects. Epinephrine and oxygen must be immediately available in the event of a serious systemic response. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1  The antigen must be injected intradermally as superficially as possible, causing a distinct, sharply defined bleb at the skin test site. An unreliable reaction may result if the product is injected subcutaneously. It must not be given intravenously; care should be taken to avoid injection into a blood vessel. A separate sterile syringe and needle should be used for each patient to prevent transmission of infectious agents. Needles should be disposed of properly and should not be recapped.



    5.2  As has been observed with other, unstandardized, antigens used for DTH skin testing  (10)  , it is possible that some patients may have exquisite immediate hypersensitivity to CANDIN. In persons with bleeding tendency, bruising and non-specific induration may occur due to the trauma of the skin test. As with all skin test antigens, local and systemic allergic reactions can occur following administration.



    5.3  Physicians using this product must have facilities, equipment and medication necessary to treat potential side effects. Epinephrine and oxygen must be immediately available in the event of a serious systemic response.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
