<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="carbidopa0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in the Warnings and Precautions sections of labeling:



 *    Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *    Hypotension/Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *    Dyskinesia [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *    Depression and suicidality [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *    Hallucinations/Psychotic-Like Behavior [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *    Impulse Control and/or Compulsive Behaviors [ see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *    Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *    Diarrhea and Colitis [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *    Rhabdomyolysis [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *    Peptic Ulcer Disease [ see     Warnings and Precautions (5.13)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence 3% or higher than placebo incidence) are dyskinesias, urine discoloration, diarrhea, nausea, abdominal pain, vomiting, and dry mouth (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Mylan Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-877-446-3679 (1-877-4-INFO-RX) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the incidence of adverse reactions (number of unique patients experiencing an adverse reaction associated with treatment/total number of patients treated) observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the incidence of adverse reactions in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the incidence of adverse reactions observed in clinical practice.



       Entacapone    

  The most commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence at least 3% greater than placebo incidence) in the double-blind, carbidopa-levodopa-placebo-controlled trials of entacapone (N=1,003 patients) associated with the use of carbidopa-levodopa-entacapone alone and not seen at an equivalent frequency among the placebo-treated patients were: dyskinesia, urine discoloration, diarrhea, nausea, hyperkinesia, vomiting, and dry mouth.



 The treatment difference incidence for premature study discontinuation for entacapone with levodopa and dopa decarboxylase inhibitor in the double-blind, placebo-controlled trials was 5%. The treatment difference incidence for the most frequent causes of study discontinuation was 2% for diarrhea, and 1% for other specific adverse reactions including psychiatric reasons, dyskinesia/ hyperkinesia, nausea, or abdominal pain.



       Adverse Reaction Incidence in Controlled Clinical Studies of Entacapone    

  Table 2 lists treatment emergent adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of patients treated with carbidopa/levodopa and 200 mg of entacapone who participated in the double-blind, placebo-controlled studies, and that were numerically more common in this group than in the carbidopa/levodopa plus placebo group. In these studies, either entacapone or placebo was added to carbidopa/levodopa (or benserazide/levodopa).



 Table 2: Summary of Patients With Adverse Reactions After Start of Trial Drug Administration At Least 1% in Entacapone Group and Greater Than Placebo 
  SYSTEM ORGAN CLASS    Carbidopa/levodopa plus  Entacapone    Carbidopa/levodopa plus Placebo    
      Preferred Term                     (n=603)                           (n=400)                           
      % of patients                      % of patients                     
  SKIN AND APPENDAGES DISORDERS                                                                         
      Sweating Increased                 2                                 1                                 
  MUSCULOSKELETAL SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                         
      Back Pain                          5                                 3                                 
  CENTRAL AND PERIPHERAL NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                         
      Dyskinesia                         25                                15                                
      Hyperkinesia                       10                                5                                 
      Hypokinesia                        9                                 8                                 
      Dizziness                          8                                 6                                 
  SPECIAL SENSES, OTHER DISORDERS                                                                         
      Taste Perversion                   1                                 0                                 
  PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                                                                         
      Anxiety                            2                                 1                                 
      Somnolence                         2                                 0                                 
      Agitation                          1                                 0                                 
  GASTROINTESTINAL SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                         
      Nausea                             14                                8                                 
      Diarrhea                           10                                4                                 
      Abdominal Pain                     8                                 4                                 
      Constipation                       6                                 4                                 
      Vomiting                           4                                 1                                 
      Mouth Dry                          3                                 0                                 
      Dyspepsia                          2                                 1                                 
      Flatulence                         2                                 0                                 
      Gastritis                          1                                 0                                 
      Gastrointestinal Disorders NOS     1                                 0                                 
  RESPIRATORY SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                         
      Dyspnea                            3                                 1                                 
  PLATELET, BLEEDING AND CLOTTING DISORDERS                                                                         
      Purpura                            2                                 1                                 
  URINARY SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                         
      Urine Discoloration                10                                0                                 
  BODY AS A WHOLE-GENERAL DISORDERS                                                                         
      Fatigue                            6                                 4                                 
      Asthenia                           2                                 1                                 
  RESISTANCE MECHANISM DISORDERS                                                                         
      Infection Bacterial                1                                 0                                 
            6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following spontaneous reports of adverse events temporally associated with entacapone or carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets have been identified since market introduction and are not listed in Table 2. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish causal relationship to entacapone or carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets exposure.



 Hepatitis with mainly cholestatic features has been reported.



       Effects of Gender and Age on Adverse Reactions    

  No differences were noted in the rate of adverse reactions attributable to entacapone alone by age or gender.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  The following adverse reactions described in this section are related to at least one of the components of carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets (i.e., levodopa, carbidopa, and/or entacapone) based upon the safety experience in clinical trials (especially pivotal trials) or in postmarketing reports.



    EXCERPT:    *    May cause falling asleep during activities of daily living without apparent warning, and daytime drowsiness and somnolence (  5.1  ) 
 *    May cause syncope and hypotension/orthostatic hypotension (  5.2  ) 
 *    May cause or exacerbate dyskinesia (  5.3  ) 
 *    May cause depression and suicidality (  5.4  ) 
 *    May cause hallucinations and/or other psychotic-like behavior (  5.5  ) 
 *    May cause problems with impulse control and compulsive behaviors (  5.6  ) 
 *    Abrupt discontinuation may cause hyperpyrexia and confusion (  5.7  ) 
 *    May cause diarrhea and/or drug-induced colitis (  5.8  ) 
 *    May cause rhabdomyolysis (  5.9  ) 
 *    Increased risk of melanoma (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence



  Patients with Parkinson's disease treated with carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets or other carbidopa/levodopa products have reported suddenly falling asleep without prior warning of sleepiness while engaged in activities of daily living (including the operation of motor vehicles). Some of these episodes resulted in accidents. Although many of these patients reported somnolence while taking entacapone, some did not perceive warning signs, such as excessive drowsiness, and believed that they were alert immediately prior to the event. Some of these events have been reported to occur up to one year after initiation of treatment.



 Somnolence was reported in 2% of patients taking entacapone and 0% in placebo in controlled trials. It is reported that falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living always occurs in a setting of pre-existing somnolence, although patients may not give such a history. For this reason, prescribers should reassess patients for drowsiness or sleepiness especially since some of the events occur well after the start of treatment. Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge drowsiness or sleepiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities. Patients who have already experienced somnolence and/or an episode of sudden sleep onset should not participate in these activities during treatment with carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets.



 Before initiating treatment with carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets, advise patients of the potential to develop drowsiness and specifically ask about factors that may increase this risk such as use of concomitant sedating medications and the presence of sleep disorders. If a patient develops daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require active participation (e.g., conversations, eating, etc.), carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets should ordinarily be discontinued [ see      Dosage and Administration (2.5)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ]. If the decision is made to continue carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets, patients should be advised not to drive and to avoid other potentially dangerous activities. There is insufficient information to establish whether dose reduction will eliminate episodes of falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living.



    5.2 Hypotension, Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope



  Reports of syncope were generally more frequent in patients in both treatment groups who had had a prior episode of documented hypotension (although the episodes of syncope, obtained by history, were themselves not documented with vital sign measurement). Hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, and syncope are observed in patients treated with drugs that increase central dopaminergic tone including carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets.



    5.3 Dyskinesia



  Dyskinesia (involuntary movements) may occur or be exacerbated at lower dosages and sooner with carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets than with preparations containing only carbidopa and levodopa. The occurrence of dyskinesias may require dosage reduction.



 In pivotal trials, the treatment difference incidence of dyskinesia was 10% and for carbidopa-levodopa plus 200 mg entacapone. Although decreasing the dose of levodopa may ameliorate this side effect, many patients in controlled trials continued to experience frequent dyskinesias despite a reduction in their dose of levodopa. The treatment difference incidence of study withdrawal for dyskinesia was 1% for carbidopa-levodopa-entacapone.



    5.4 Depression and Suicidality



  All patients should be observed carefully for the development of depression with concomitant suicidal tendencies. Patients with past or current psychoses should be treated with caution.



    5.5 Hallucinations and/or Psychotic-Like Behavior



  Dopaminergic therapy in patients with Parkinson's disease has been associated with hallucinations. Hallucinations led to drug discontinuation and premature withdrawal from clinical trials in 0.8% and 0% of patients treated with carbidopa, levodopa, entacapone and carbidopa, levodopa, respectively. Hallucinations led to hospitalization in 1.0% and 0.3% of patients in the carbidopa, levodopa, entacapone and carbidopa, levodopa, groups, respectively. Agitation occurred in 1% of patients treated with carbidopa, levodopa, entacapone and 0% treated with carbidopa, levodopa.



    5.6 Impulse Control and/or Compulsive Behaviors



  Postmarketing reports suggest that patients treated with anti-Parkinson medications can experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money uncontrollably, and other intense urges. Patients may be unable to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications generally used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease and which increase central dopaminergic tone, including entacapone taken with levodopa and carbidopa. In some cases, although not all, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose of anti-Parkinson medications was reduced or discontinued. Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal it is important for prescribers to specifically ask patients or their caregivers about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending or other urges while being treated with entacapone. Physicians should consider dose reduction or stopping carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets if a patient develops such urges while taking carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets [ see      Dosage and Administration (2.5)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ].



    5.7 Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion



  Cases of hyperpyrexia and confusion resembling neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS) have been reported in association with dose reduction or withdrawal of therapy with carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone. However, in some cases, hyperpyrexia and confusion were reported after initiation of treatment with entacapone. Hyperpyrexia and confusion are uncommon but they may be life-threatening with a variety of features, including hyperpyrexia/fever/hyperthermia, muscle rigidity, involuntary movements, altered consciousness/mental status changes, delirium, autonomic dysfunction, tachycardia, tachypnea, sweating, hyper- or hypotension, and abnormal laboratory findings (e.g., creatine phosphokinase elevation, leukocytosis, myoglobinuria, and increased serum myoglobin).



 If a patient needs to discontinue or reduce their daily dose of carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets, the dose should be decreased slowly, with supervision from a health care provider [ see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)    ]. Specific methods for tapering entacapone have not been systematically evaluated.



    5.8 Diarrhea and Colitis



  In clinical trials of entacapone, diarrhea developed in 60 of 603 (10.0%) and 16 of 400 (4.0%) of patients treated with 200 mg of entacapone or placebo in combination with levodopa and dopa decarboxylase inhibitor, respectively. In patients treated with entacapone, diarrhea was generally mild to moderate in severity (8.6%) but was regarded as severe in 1.3%. Diarrhea resulted in withdrawal in 10 of 603 (1.7%) patients, 7 (1.2%) with mild and moderate diarrhea and 3 (0.5%) with severe diarrhea. Diarrhea generally resolved after discontinuation of entacapone. Two patients with diarrhea were hospitalized. Typically, diarrhea presents within 4 to 12 weeks after entacapone is started, but it may appear as early as the first week and as late as many months after the initiation of treatment. Diarrhea may be associated with weight loss, dehydration, and hypokalemia.



 Postmarketing experience has shown that diarrhea may be a sign of drug-induced microscopic colitis, primarily lymphocytic colitis. In these cases diarrhea has usually been moderate to severe, watery and non-bloody, at times associated with dehydration, abdominal pain, weight loss, and hypokalemia. In the majority of cases, diarrhea and other colitis-related symptoms resolved or significantly improved when entacapone treatment was stopped. In some patients with biopsy confirmed colitis, diarrhea had resolved or significantly improved after discontinuation of entacapone but recurred after retreatment with entacapone.



 If prolonged diarrhea is suspected to be related to carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets, the drug should be discontinued and appropriate medical therapy considered. If the cause of prolonged diarrhea remains unclear or continues after stopping entacapone, then further diagnostic investigations including colonoscopy and biopsies should be considered.



    5.9 Rhabdomyolysis



  Cases of severe rhabdomyolysis have been reported with entacapone when used in combination with carbidopa and levodopa. Severe prolonged motor activity including dyskinesia may possibly account for rhabdomyolysis. Most of the cases were manifested by myalgia and increased values of creatine phosphokinase (CPK) and myoglobin. Some of the reactions also included fever and/or alteration of consciousness. It is also possible that rhabdomyolysis may be a result of the syndrome described in Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion[ see      Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ].



    5.10 Melanoma



  Epidemiological studies have shown that patients with Parkinson's disease have a higher risk (2- to approximately 6-fold higher) of developing melanoma than the general population. Whether the increased risk observed was due to Parkinson's disease or other factors, such as drugs used to treat Parkinson's disease, is unclear.



 For the reasons stated above, patients and providers are advised to monitor for melanomas frequently and on a regular basis when using carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets, for any indication. Ideally, periodic skin examination should be performed by appropriately qualified individuals (e.g., dermatologists).



    5.11 Interaction with Drugs Metabolized by COMT



  Drugs known to be metabolized by COMT, such as isoproterenol, epinephrine, norepinephrine, dopamine, dobutamine, alpha-methyldopa, apomorphine, isoetherine, and bitolterol should be administered with caution in patients receiving entacapone regardless of the route of administration (including inhalation), as their interaction may result in increased heart rate, arrhythmia, and/or increased blood pressure.



    5.12 Fibrotic Complications



  Cases of retroperitoneal fibrosis, pulmonary infiltrates, pleural effusion, and pleural thickening have been reported in some patients treated with ergot derived dopaminergic agents. These complications may resolve when the drug is discontinued, but complete resolution does not always occur. Although these adverse reactions may be related to the ergoline structure of these compounds, a possible causal role of nonergot derived drugs (e.g., entacapone, levodopa), which increase dopaminergic activity, has also been considered. The expected incidence of fibrotic complications is so low that even if entacapone caused these complications at rates similar to those attributable to other dopaminergic therapies, it is unlikely that it would have been detected in a cohort of the size exposed to entacapone during its clinical development. Four cases of pulmonary fibrosis have been reported during clinical development of entacapone; 3 of these patients were also treated with pergolide and 1 with bromocriptine. The duration of treatment with entacapone ranged from 7 months to 17 months.



    5.13 Peptic Ulcer Disease



  As with levodopa, treatment with carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets may increase the possibility of upper gastrointestinal hemorrhage in patients with a history of peptic ulcer.



    5.14 Hepatic Impairment



  Patients with hepatic impairment should be treated with caution [see   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ] .  As with levodopa, periodic evaluation of hepatic function is recommended during extended therapy.



    5.15 Laboratory Tests



  Abnormalities in laboratory tests may include elevations of liver function tests such as alkaline phosphatase, SGOT (AST), SGPT (ALT), lactic dehydrogenase, and bilirubin. Abnormalities in blood urea nitrogen and positive Coombs test have also been reported. Commonly, levels of blood urea nitrogen, creatinine, and uric acid are lower during administration of carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets than with levodopa.



 Carbidopa, levodopa and entacapone tablets may cause a false-positive reaction for urinary ketone bodies when a test tape is used for determination of ketonuria. This reaction will not be altered by boiling the urine specimen. False-negative tests may result with the use of glucose-oxidase methods of testing for glucosuria.



 Cases of falsely diagnosed pheochromocytoma in patients on carbidopa/levodopa therapy have been reported very rarely. Caution should be exercised when interpreting the plasma and urine levels of catecholamines and their metabolites in patients on carbidopa/levodopa therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
