<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="carbidopa1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Carbidopa has not been demonstrated to have any overt pharmacodynamic actions in the recommended doses. The only adverse reactions that have been observed have been with concomitant use of carbidopa with other drugs such as levodopa, and with carbidopa-levodopa combination products.



 When Carbidopa is administered concomitantly with levodopa or carbidopa-levodopa combination products, the most common adverse reactions have included dyskinesias such as choreiform, dystonic, and other involuntary movements, and nausea. Other adverse reactions reported with Carbidopa when administered concomitantly with levodopa alone or carbidopa-levodopa combination products were psychotic episodes including delusions, hallucinations, and paranoid ideation, depression with or without development of suicidal tendencies, and dementia. Convulsions also have occurred; however, a causal relationship with concomitant use of Carbidopa and levodopa has not been established.



 The following other adverse reactions have been reported with levodopa and carbidopa-levodopa combination products. These same adverse reactions may also occur when Carbidopa is administered with these products.



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain and distress, asthenia, chest pain, fatigue.



   Cardiovascular:  cardiac irregularities, hypertension, myocardial infarction, hypotension including orthostatic hypotension, palpitation, phlebitis, syncope.



   Gastrointestinal:  anorexia, bruxism, burning sensation of the tongue, constipation, dark saliva, development of duodenal ulcer, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, dysphagia, flatulence, gastrointestinal bleeding, gastrointestinal pain, heartburn, hiccups, sialorrhea, taste alterations, vomiting.



   Hematologic:  hemolytic and non-hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, agranulocytosis.



   Hypersensitivity:  angioedema, urticaria, pruritus, Henoch-Schonlein purpura, bullous lesions (including pemphigus-like reactions).



   Metabolic:  edema, weight gain, weight loss.



   Musculoskeletal:  back pain, leg pain, muscle cramps, shoulder pain.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Psychotic episodes including delusions, hallucinations and paranoid ideation, neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS, see  WARNINGS  ), bradykinetic episodes ("on-off" phenomenon), confusion, agitation, dizziness, somnolence, dream abnormalities including nightmares, insomnia, paresthesia, headache, depression with or without development of suicidal tendencies, dementia, pathological gambling, increased libido including hypersexuality, impulse control symptoms. Convulsions also have occurred; however, a causal relationship with Carbidopa and levodopa, has not been established.



   Respiratory:  upper respiratory infection, dyspnea, pharyngeal pain, cough.



   Skin:  flushing, increased sweating, malignant melanoma (see also    CONTRAINDICATIONS    ), rash, alopecia, dark sweat.



   Special Senses:  oculogyric crises, diplopia, blurred vision, dilated pupils.



   Urogenital:  dark urine, priapism, urinary frequency, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urinary tract infection.



   Laboratory Tests:  abnormalities in alkaline phosphatase, SGOT (AST), SGPT (ALT), lactic dehydrogenase, bilirubin, blood urea nitrogen (BUN), Coombs test; elevated serum glucose; decreased hemoglobin and hematocrit; decreased white blood cell count and serum potassium; increased serum creatinine and uric acid; white blood cells, bacteria and blood in the urine; protein and glucose in the urine.



   Miscellaneous:  bizarre breathing patterns, faintness, hoarseness, hot flashes, malaise, neuroleptic malignant syndrome, sense of stimulation.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
