<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cardizem0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions have been rare in studies carried out to date, but it should be recognized that patients with impaired ventricular function and cardiac conduction abnormalities have usually been excluded from these studies.



 The following table presents the most common adverse reactions reported in placebo-controlled angina and hypertension trials in patients receiving CARDIZEM CD up to 360 mg with rates in placebo patients shown for comparison.




 CARDIZEM CD Capsule Placebo-Controlled Angina and Hypertension Trials Combined   
 Adverse Reactions                          Cardizem CD(n=607)                   Placebo(n=301)             
  
 Headache                                          5.4%                               5.0%                  
 Dizziness                                         3.0%                               3.0%                  
 Bradycardia                                       3.3%                               1.3%                  
 AV Block First Degree                             3.3%                               0.0%                  
 Edema                                             2.6%                               1.3%                  
 ECG Abnormality                                   1.6%                               2.3%                  
 Asthenia                                          1.8%                               1.7%                  
         In clinical trials of CARDIZEM CD capsules, CARDIZEM tablets, and CARDIZEM SR capsules involving over 3200 patients, the most common events (i.e., greater than 1%) were edema (4.6%), headache (4.6%), dizziness (3.5%), asthenia (2.6%), first-degree AV block (2.4%), bradycardia (1.7%), flushing (1.4%), nausea (1.4%), and rash (1.2%).
 

 In addition, the following events were reported infrequently (less than 1%) in angina or hypertension trials:



   Cardiovascular:  Angina, arrhythmia, AV block (second- or third-degree), bundle branch block, congestive heart failure, ECG abnormalities, hypotension, palpitations, syncope, tachycardia, ventricular extrasystoles.



   Nervous System:  Abnormal dreams, amnesia, depression, gait abnormality, hallucinations, insomnia, nervousness, paresthesia, personality change, somnolence, tinnitus, tremor.



   Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia, constipation, diarrhea, dry mouth, dysgeusia, dyspepsia, mild elevations of SGOT, SGPT, LDH, and alkaline phosphatase (see    WARNINGS, Acute Hepatic Injury    ), thirst, vomiting, weight increase.



   Dermatological:  Petechiae, photosensitivity, pruritus, urticaria.



   Other:  Amblyopia, CPK increase, dyspnea, epistaxis, eye irritation, hyperglycemia, hyperuricemia, impotence, muscle cramps, nasal congestion, nocturia, osteoarticular pain, polyuria, sexual difficulties.



 The following postmarketing events have been reported infrequently in patients receiving CARDIZEM: acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, allergic reactions, alopecia, angioedema (including facial or periorbital edema), asystole, erythema multiforme (including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis), exfoliative dermatitis, extrapyramidal symptoms, gingival hyperplasia, hemolytic anemia, increased bleeding time, leukopenia, photosensitivity (including lichenoid keratosis and hyperpigmentation at sun-exposed skin areas), purpura, retinopathy, myopathy, and thrombocytopenia. In addition, events such as myocardial infarction have been observed which are not readily distinguishable from the natural history of the disease in these patients. A number of well-documented cases of generalized rash, some characterized as leukocytoclastic vasculitis, have been reported. However, a definitive cause and effect relationship between these events and CARDIZEM therapy is yet to be established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
