<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cardiolite" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse events were evaluated in 3741 adults who were evaluated in clinical studies. Of these patients, 3068 (77% men, 22% women, and 0.7% of the patient's genders were not recorded) were in cardiac clinical trials and 673 (100% women) in breast imaging trials. Cases of angina, chest pain, and death have occurred (see  Section 5  ). Adverse events reported at a rate of 0.5% or greater after receiving Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi administration are shown in the following table:



 Table 2.0 Selected Adverse Events Reported in &lt;= 0.5% of Patients Who Received Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi in Either Breast or Cardiac Clinical Studies* 
 Body System                     Breast Studies     Cardiac Studies     
  
 *Excludes the 22 patients whose gender were not recorded.   
  
                                 Womenn = 673       Womenn = 685       Menn = 2361        Totaln = 3046       
 Body as a Whole                 21 (3.1%)          6 (0.9%)           17 (0.7%)          23 (0.8%)           
 Headache                        11 (1.6%)          2 (0.3%)           4 (0.2%)           6 (0.2%)            
 Cardiovascular                  9 (1.3%)           24 (3.5%)          75 (3.2%)          99 (3.3%)           
 Chest Pain/Angina               0 (0%)             18 (2.6%)          46 (1.9%)          64 (2.1%)           
 ST segment changes              0 (0%)             11 (1.6%)          29 (1.2%)          40 (1.3%)           
 Digestive System                8 (1.2%)           4 (0.6%)           9 (0.4%)           13 (0.4%)           
 Nausea                          4 (0.6%)           1 (0.1%)           2 (0.1%)           3 (0.1%)            
 Special Senses                  132 (19.6%)        62 (9.1%)          160 (6.8%)         222 (7.3%)          
 Taste Perversion                129 (19.2%)        60 (8.8%)          157 (6.6%)         217 (7.1%)          
 Parosmia                        8 (1.2%)           6 (0.9%)           10 (0.4%)          16 (0.5%)           
      In the clinical studies for breast imaging, breast pain was reported in 12 (1.7%) of the patients. In 11 of these patients the pain appears to be associated with biopsy/surgical procedures.
 

 The following adverse reactions have been reported in &lt;= 0.5% of patients: signs and symptoms consistent with seizure occurring shortly after administration of the agent; transient arthritis, angioedema, arrythmia, dizziness, syncope, abdominal pain, vomiting, and severe hypersensitivity characterized by dyspnea, hypotension, bradycardia, asthenia, and vomiting within two hours after a second injection of Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi. A few cases of flushing, edema, injection site inflammation, dry mouth, fever, pruritis, rash, urticaria and fatigue have also been attributed to administration of the agent.



    EXCERPT:    *  The following adverse reactions have been reported in &lt;= 0.5% of patients: signs and symptoms consistent with seizure occurring shortly after administration of the agent; transient arthritis, angioedema, arrythmia, dizziness, syncope, abdominal pain, vomiting, and severe hypersensitivity characterized by dyspnea, hypotension, bradycardia, asthenia, and vomiting within two hours after a second injection of Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi. A few cases of flushing, edema, injection site inflammation, dry mouth, fever, pruritis, rash, urticaria and fatigue have also been attributed to administration of the agent. 
    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Lantheus Medical Imaging at 1-800-362-2668 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Pharmacologic induction of cardiovascular stress may be associated with serious adverse events such as myocardial infarction, arrhythmia, hypotension, bronchoconstriction and cerebrovascular events. 
 *  CARDIOLITE  (r)  has been rarely associated with acute severe allergic and anaphylactic events of angioedema and generalized urticaria. In some patients the allergic symptoms developed on the second injection during CARDIOLITE(r) imaging. 
 *  Caution should be exercised and emergency equipment should be available when administering CARDIOLITE(r). 
 *  Before administering CARDIOLITE(r) patients should be asked about the possibility of allergic reactions to either drug. 
 *  The contents of the vial are intended only for use in the preparation of Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi and are not to be administered directly to the patient without first undergoing the preparative procedure. 
    
 

   5.1 Warnings



  In studying patients in whom cardiac disease is known or suspected, care should be taken to assure continuous monitoring and treatment in accordance with safe, accepted clinical procedure. Infrequently, death has occurred 4 to 24 hours after Tc99m Sestamibi use and is usually associated with exercise stress testing (See  Section 5.2  ).



 Pharmacologic induction of cardiovascular stress may be associated with serious adverse events such as myocardial infarction, arrhythmia, hypotension, bronchoconstriction and cerebrovascular events. Caution should be used when pharmacologic stress is selected as an alternative to exercise; it should be used when indicated and in accordance with the pharmacologic stress agent's labeling.



 Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi has been rarely associated with acute severe allergic and anaphylactic events of angioedema and generalized urticaria. In some patients the allergic symptoms developed on the second injection during CARDIOLITE(r) imaging. Patients who receive CARDIOLITE(r) or MIRALUMA(r) imaging are receiving the same drug. Caution should be exercised and emergency equipment should be available when administering Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi. Also, before administering either CARDIOLITE(r) or MIRALUMA(r), patients should be asked about the possibility of allergic reactions to either drug.



    5.2 General Precautions



  The contents of the vial are intended only for use in the preparation of Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi and are not to be administered directly to the patient without first undergoing the preparative procedure.



 Radioactive drugs must be handled with care and appropriate safety measures should be used to minimize radiation exposure to clinical personnel. Also, care should be taken to minimize radiation exposure to the patients consistent with proper patient management.



 Contents of the kit before preparation are not radioactive. However, after the Sodium Pertechnetate Tc99m Injection is added, adequate shielding of the final preparation must be maintained. The components of the kit are sterile and non-pyrogenic. It is essential to follow directions carefully and to adhere to strict aseptic procedures during preparation.



 Technetium Tc99m labeling reactions depend on maintaining the stannous ion in the reduced state. Hence, Sodium Pertechnetate Tc99m Injection containing oxidants should not be used.



 Technetium Tc99m Sestamibi should not be used more than six hours after preparation.



 Radiopharmaceuticals should be used only by physicians who are qualified by training and experience in the safe use and handling of radionuclides and whose experience and training have been approved by the appropriate government agency authorized to license the use of radionuclides.



 Stress testing should be performed only under the supervision of a qualified physician and in a laboratory equipped with appropriate resuscitation and support apparatus.



 The most frequent exercise stress test endpoints sufficient to stop the test reported during controlled studies (two-thirds were cardiac patients) were:




 Fatigue                                                                                            35%   
 Dyspnea                                                                                            17%   
 Chest Pain                                                                                         16%   
 ST-depression                                                                                       7%   
 Arrhythmia                                                                                          1%   
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
