<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cardizem2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described in greater detail, in other sections:



 *    Bradycardia and AV block [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Heart failure [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    Acute hepatic injury [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    Severe Skin reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions ( &gt;= 2% ) are lower limb edema, sinus congestion and rash in patients treated for hypertension, and lower limb edema, headache, dizziness, fatigue, bradycardia, first-degree AV block and cough in patients treated for angina (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 For the hypertension studies, the following table presents adverse reactions more common on diltiazem than on placebo (but excluding events with no plausible relationship to treatment), as reported in placebo-controlled hypertension trials in patients receiving a diltiazem hydrochloride extended-release formulation (once-a-day dosing) up to 540 mg.




                                     Placebo                  Diltiazem    hydrochloride    extended-release     
   Adverse Reactions    (MedDRA Term)      n=120    # pts. (%)      120-360 mg    n=501    # pts. (%)      540 mg    n=123    # pts. (%)     
  
  Edema lower limb                  4 (3)                    24 (5)                   10 (8)                   
  Sinus congestion                  0 (0)                    2 (1)                    2 (2)                    
  Rash                              0 (0)                    3 (1)                    2 (2)                    
          In the angina study, the adverse event profile of CARDIZEM LA was consistent with what has been previously described for CARDIZEM LA and other formulations of diltiazem HCl. The most frequent adverse effects experienced by CARDIZEM LA-treated patients were edema lower-limb (6.8%), dizziness (6.4%), fatigue (4.8%), bradycardia (3.6%), first-degree atrioventricular block (3.2%), and cough (2%).
 

 In addition, the following events have been reported infrequently (less than 1%) in angina or hypertension trials:



   Cardiovascular:  Angina, bundle branch block, palpitations, syncope, tachycardia, ventricular extrasystoles  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,  5.2  ,  5.3  )].  



   Nervous System:  Abnormal dreams, amnesia, depression, gait abnormality, hallucinations, insomnia, nervousness, paresthesia, personality change, somnolence, tinnitus, tremor.



   Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia, constipation, diarrhea, dry mouth, dysgeusia, dyspepsia, thirst, vomiting, weight increase.



   Dermatological:  Petechiae, photosensitivity, pruritus, urticarial  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )].  



   Other:  Amblyopia, CPK increase, dyspnea, epistaxis, eye irritation, hyperglycemia, hyperuricemia, impotence, muscle cramps, nasal congestion, nocturia, osteoarticular pain, polyuria, sexual difficulties.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post  -  approval use of diltiazem. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following post  -  marketing reactions have been reported infrequently in patients receiving diltiazem: acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, allergic reactions, alopecia, angioedema (including facial or periorbital edema), erythema multiforme, extrapyramidal symptoms, gingival hyperplasia, hemolytic anemia, increased bleeding time, leukopenia, photosensitivity (including lichenoid keratosis and hyperpigmentation at sun-exposed skin areas), purpura, retinopathy, myopathy, and thrombocytopenia.



 In addition, events such as myocardial infarction have been observed which are not readily distinguishable from the natural history of the disease in these patients.



 A number of well-documented cases of generalized rash, some characterized as leukocytoclastic vasculitis, have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Bradycardia, second or third degree AV block: Monitor heart rate and rhythm. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Heart failure: Monitor for signs and symptoms. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Increased liver enzymes and acute hepatic injury. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Serious skin reactions. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Bradycardia or AV Block



  CARDIZEM LA may cause abnormally slow heart rates or second- or third-degree AV block. Patients with sick sinus syndrome are at increased risk of bradycardia. Concomitant use of diltiazem with beta-blockers or digitalis may result in additive effects on cardiac conduction. A patient with Prinzmetal's angina developed periods of asystole (2 to 5 seconds) after a single dose of 60 mg of diltiazem [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  . Monitor for effects on heart rate and cardiac conduction.



    5.2 Heart Failure



  Worsening of heart failure has been reported in patients with impairment of ventricular function. Experience with the use of diltiazem in combination with beta-blockers in patients with impaired ventricular function is limited.



    5.3 Acute Hepatic Injury



  Significant elevations in liver enzymes such as alkaline phosphatase, LDH, AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT) and signs of acute hepatic injury have been reported with diltiazem therapy. These reactions tended to occur early after therapy initiation (1 to 8 weeks) and have been reversible upon discontinuation of drug therapy. Mild elevations of transaminases with and without concomitant elevation in alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin have also been observed. Such elevations were usually transient and frequently resolved even with continued diltiazem treatment.



    5.4 Severe Skin Reactions



  Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolusis, erythema multiforme and/or exfoliative dermatitis have been reported.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
