<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cardura" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions from clinical trials are asthenia, headache, hypotension, and dizziness. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The incidence of adverse reactions was derived from two controlled efficacy and safety trials involving 1473 BPH patients. In Study 1, CARDURA XL (n=317) was compared to doxazosin IR tablets (n=322) and to placebo (n=156). In Study 2, CARDURA XL (n=350) was compared just to doxazosin IR tablets (n=330). In both of these studies, CARDURA XL was initiated at a dose of 4 mg, which could be increased by the investigator to 8 mg after seven weeks if an adequate response was not seen [see    Clinical Studies (14.1)    ]. Similarly, doxazosin IR was begun at a dose of 1 mg, which was increased in all patients to 2 mg after 1 week, followed by the option to increase to 4 mg after 4 weeks, and 8 mg after 7 weeks.



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in the CARDURA XL group were: dizziness, dyspnea, asthenia, headache, hypotension, postural hypotension, and somnolence. The rates of discontinuation for adverse reactions were 6%, 7% and 3% in the CARDURA XL, doxazosin IR, and placebo groups, respectively.



 Table 1 lists the incidence rates of adverse reactions derived from all reported adverse events in the two controlled studies (Studies 1 and 2) combined, at a rate greater than placebo and in 1% or more of patients treated with CARDURA XL.



 TABLE 1 Adverse Reactions, Derived from All Adverse Events Exceeding Placebo Rate and Occurring in &gt;=1% of BPH Patients Treated with CARDURA XL 
 Body System                               CARDURA XL(N = 666)   Doxazosin IR(N = 651)    Placebo(N = 156)     
  
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                            
   Abdominal Pain                                  1.8%                  2.3%                  0.6%           
   Asthenia                                        3.9%                  6.9%                  1.3%           
   Headache                                        6.0%                  5.1%                  4.5%           
   CARDIOVASCULAR                                                                                             
   Hypotension                                     1.7%                  1.8%                  0.0%           
   Postural Hypotension                            1.2%                  2.2%                  0.6%           
   DIGESTIVE                                                                                                  
   Dyspepsia                                       1.4%                  1.2%                  0.0%           
   Nausea                                          1.2%                  2.3%                  0.6%           
   MUSCULOSKELETAL                                                                                            
   Myalgia                                         1.4%                  0.5%                  0.0%           
   NERVOUS                                                                                                    
   Dizziness                                       5.3%                  9.1%                  1.9%           
   Somnolence                                      1.5%                  1.2%                  0.0%           
   Vertigo                                         1.5%                  4.1%                  0.6%           
   RESPIRATORY                                                                                                
   Dyspnea                                         1.2%                  1.2%                  0.0%           
   Respiratory Tract Infection                     4.8%                  4.5%                  1.9%           
   UROGENITAL                                                                                                 
   Urinary Tract Infection                         1.4%                  0.8%                  0.6%           
          Additional adverse events reported with CARDURA XL, reported by less than 1% of patients, and those of clinical interest include:  Cardiovascular System:  angina pectoris, syncope, tachycardia, chest pain, palpitations;  Digestive System:  diarrhea;  Musculoskeletal System:  arthralgia;  Nervous System:  libido decreased;  Urogenital System:  impotence, dysuria.
 

 In general, the adverse events reported in the open-label safety extension, in approximately 295 BPH patients treated for up to 37 weeks, were similar in type and frequency to the events described above in the controlled trials.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been identified during post-approval use of doxazosin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Autonomic Nervous System:  priapism;  Cardiovascular System:  cerebrovascular accidents, dizziness postural, myocardial infarction;  Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  hypoesthesia, paresthesia  ; Endocrine System:  gynecomastia;  Gastrointestinal System:  gastrointestinal obstruction, vomiting  ; General Body System:  fatigue, hot flushes, malaise  ; Heart Rate/Rhythm:  bradycardia, cardiac arrhythmias;  Hematopoietic:  leukopenia, purpura, thrombocytopenia;  Liver/Biliary System:  abnormal liver function tests, hepatitis, hepatitis cholestatic, jaundice;  Musculoskeletal System:  muscle cramps, muscle weakness;  Psychiatric:  agitation, anorexia, nervousness;  Respiratory System:  bronchospasm aggravated;  Skin Disorders:  alopecia, urticaria, skin rash, pruritus;  Special Senses:  blurred vision, Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ];  Urinary System:  hematuria, micturition disorder, micturition frequency, nocturia, polyuria.



 There have been rare reports of gastrointestinal irritation and gastrointestinal bleeding with use of another drug in this non-deformable sustained release formulation, although causal relationship to the drug is uncertain.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Postural hypotension with or without syncope may occur in the first few hours after administration. (  5.1  )



 Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients. Advise patients considering cataract surgery to tell their ophthalmologist that they have taken CARDURA XL tablets. (  5.2  )



 Caution should be used when administering to patients with preexisting severe gastrointestinal narrowing or coronary insufficiency. (  5.3  ,  5.7  )



 Advise patients to be screened for the presence of prostate cancer prior to treatment and at regular intervals afterwards. (  5.4  )



 



   5.1 Postural Hypotension



  Postural hypotension with or without symptoms (e.g., dizziness) may develop within a few hours following administration of CARDURA XL. However, infrequently, symptomatic postural hypotension has also been reported later than a few hours after dosing. As with other alpha-blockers, there is a potential for syncope, especially after the initial dose or after an increase in dosage strength. Patients should be warned of the possible occurrence of such events and should avoid situations where injury could result should syncope occur. Care should be taken when CARDURA XL is administered to patients with symptomatic hypotension or patients who have had a hypotensive response to other medications.



    5.2 Cataract Surgery



  Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients on or previously treated with alpha1blockers. This variant of small pupil syndrome is characterized by the combination of a flaccid iris that billows in response to intraoperative irrigation currents, progressive intraoperative miosis despite preoperative dilation with standard mydriatic drugs, and potential prolapse of the iris toward the phacoemulsification incisions. The patient's surgeon should be prepared for possible modifications to their surgical technique, such as the utilization of iris hooks, iris dilator rings, or viscoelastic substances. There does not appear to be a benefit from stopping alpha1blocker therapy prior to cataract surgery.



    5.3 Gastrointestinal Disorders



  As with any other non-deformable material, caution should be used when administering CARDURA XL to patients with preexisting severe gastrointestinal narrowing (pathologic or iatrogenic). There have been rare reports of obstructive symptoms in patients with known strictures in association with the ingestion of another drug in this non-deformable extended release formulation. Markedly increased GI retention times, as may occur in patients with chronic constipation, can increase systemic exposure to doxazosin and thereby potentially increase adverse reactions.



    5.4 Prostate Cancer



  Carcinoma of the prostate causes many of the same symptoms associated with BPH and the two disorders frequently co-exist. Carcinoma of the prostate should therefore be ruled out prior to commencing therapy with CARDURA XL.



    5.5 PDE-5 Inhibitors



  Concomitant administration of CARDURA XL with a PDE-5 inhibitor can result in additive blood pressure lowering effects and symptomatic hypotension. Pharmacodynamic interactions between CARDURA XL and antihypertensive medications or other vasodilating agents have not been determined.



    5.6 Patients with Hepatic Impairment



  CARDURA XL is not recommended for patients with severe hepatic impairment and should be administered with caution to patients with mild or moderate hepatic impairment [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



    5.7 Patients with Coronary Insufficiency



  Patients with congestive heart failure, angina pectoris, or acute myocardial infarction within the last 6 months were excluded from the Phase 3 studies. If symptoms of angina pectoris should newly appear or worsen, CARDURA XL should be discontinued.



    5.8 CYP 3A4 Inhibitors



  Caution should be exercised when concomitantly administering CARDURA XL with a strong CYP 3A4 inhibitor, such as atanazavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, ketoconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, ritonavir, saquinavir, telithromycin, or voriconazole.



    5.9 Priapism



   Rarely (probably less frequently than once in every several thousand patients), alpha-1 antagonists, including doxazosin, have been associated with priapism (painful penile erection, sustained for hours and unrelieved by sexual intercourse or masturbation). Because this condition can lead to permanent impotence if not promptly treated, patients must be advised about the seriousness of the condition.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
