<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="carticel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Information on the safety of implanted autologous chondrocytes is derived from the Study of the Treatment of Articular Repair (STAR) [  see  Clinical Studies (14)    ], the Cartilage Repair Registry, the Swedish Series, and post-marketing adverse event reporting.



 The most common serious adverse events (&gt; 5% of patients) derived from the STAR study include arthrofibrosis/joint adhesion, graft overgrowth, chondromalacia or chondrosis, cartilage injury, graft complication, meniscal lesion and graft delamination. Only serious adverse events were collected in this study.



   EXCERPT:   The most common serious adverse events (&gt; 5% of patients), derived from the STAR study include arthrofibrosis/joint adhesions, graft overgrowth, chondromalacia or chondrosis, cartilage injury, graft complication, meniscal lesion and graft delamination. (  6.2  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Vericel at 1-800-453-6948 or contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  The adverse reaction rates as well as the rate and type of subsequent surgical procedures from Carticel  (r)  studies of different designs cannot be directly compared amongst each other. Adverse reaction data from these studies do, however, provide a basis for identifying adverse reactions that may be related to product use and for estimating their frequency.



   Study of the Treatment of Articular Repair (STAR)



 In the STAR study [  see  Study of the Treatment of Articular Repair (STAR) (14.2.2)    ], patients who had experienced an inadequate response to a prior cartilage repair procedure underwent Carticel implantation to the index lesion. A total of 154 patients were implanted with Carticel; 28 patients discontinued the study early. The numbers of patients completing the 24 and 48 month follow-up visits are 136 and 115, respectively. Mean patient age was 35 years at consent. The majority of patients were Caucasian (135; 88%) and male (106; 69%).



 Seventy-six (76) (49% of 154) patients underwent 113 subsequent surgical procedures (SSPs) on the treated knee, irrespective of relationship to Carticel, during the 4 year follow-up. Of the 76 patients, 52 patients had 1 SSP, 15 patients had 2 SSPs, and 9 patients had 3 or more SSPs. Sixty-one (61) (80%) of the 76 patients who had an SSP underwent a procedure within the first 24 months after implantation. The majority of patients, 83% (63 of the 76), underwent an arthroscopy or manipulation under anesthesia only.  Table 1  shows the interventions during SSPs in &gt; 2% of patients.



 Table 1: Interventions during Subsequent Surgical Procedures, Regardless of Relationship, in &gt; 2% of Patients 
 Intervention                                             % of 154 Patients                               
  
 Debridement of Cartilage Lesion                          31% (47/154)                                    
 Lysis of Adhesions                                       14% (21/154)                                    
 Synovectomy / Synovial Plica Excision                    12% (19/154)                                    
 Other Debridement                                        10% (16/154)                                    
 Chondroplasty                                            6% (10/154)                                     
 Meniscectomy                                             6% (10/154)                                     
 Loose Body Removal                                       5% (7/154)                                      
 Microfracture - Index Lesion                             5% (7/154)                                      
 Scar Tissue Removal                                      5% (7/154)                                      
 Release of Patellar Retinaculum                          4% (6/154)                                      
 Hardware Removal                                         4% (6/154)                                      
 Microfracture - New Lesion                               4% (6/154)                                      
 Osteotomy                                                3% (5/154)                                      
        Lysis of adhesions was the most frequent surgical intervention performed in the first 6 months. After 6 months, cartilage debridement was the most frequently performed intervention. In the STAR study, 61% (46/76) of patients who required an SSP after Carticel did not meet failure criteria by either modified Cincinnati score or surgical criteria (e.g., graft delamination or surgical procedure violating the subchondral bone).
 

 The most clinically significant interventions or findings involving the Carticel graft or periosteal patch are as follows: 3 Carticel grafts were completely removed and 1 was partially removed due to delamination. Partial delamination or fraying of the graft or periosteal patch was reported in 10 additional patients. Four (4) of these patients underwent reattachment/repair of the periosteal patch. Finally, a partially intact graft was found in 1 patient who was re-implanted. Detailed lists of interventions and findings that may have been associated with the graft or periosteal patch are presented in  Tables 1 and 2  , respectively.



   Table 2  shows the serious adverse events (SAEs) that occurred in &gt;= 5% of patients, regardless of relationship to study treatment.



 Table 2: Most Frequent Serious Adverse Events (in &gt;= 5% of Patients), Regardless of Relationship, in the STAR Study 
 Serious Adverse Events                                   % of 154 Patients                               
  
 Arthrofibrosis/Joint Adhesions                           16% (25/154)                                    
 Graft Overgrowth                                         15% (23/154)                                    
 Chondromalacia or Chondrosis                             12% (18/154)                                    
 Cartilage Injury                                         11% (17/154)                                    
 Graft Complication                                       10% (15/154)                                    
 Meniscal Lesion                                          8% (12/154)                                     
 Graft Delamination                                       6% (9/154)                                      
 Osteoarthritis                                           5% (7/154)                                      
          Registry Based Study (RBS)
 

 Data from a cohort of 97 Carticel  (r)  treated patients, who were retrospectively evaluated in the Registry Based Study [  see  Registry-Based Study (RBS) (14.2.1)    ], showed that 39% (38/97) of patients had a SSP within 3 years of which 63% (24/38) were assessed as related to Carticel. Shaving or trimming (debridement) of overgrown tissue (hypertrophic) commonly relieved patients' symptoms. In the RBS, 67% (16/24) of patients who required arthroscopy after Carticel had a good clinical benefit in terms of improved function and relief of symptoms.  Table 3  shows the findings at surgery for the 38 patients who underwent a surgical procedure after Carticel.



 Table 3: Most Frequent Findings (in &gt;= 5% of Patients) at Subsequent Surgical Procedures in the Registry Based Study 
 Symptoms or Surgical Findings(MedDRA preferred term)     % of 97 Patients                                
  
 Graft Overgrowth                                         10% (10/97)                                     
 Partial Graft Delamination                               8% (8/97)                                       
 Chondromalacia                                           8% (8/97)                                       
 Arthrofibrosis/Joint Adhesions                           8% (8/97)                                       
 Arthralgia                                               7% (7/97)                                       
 Synovitis                                                6% (6/97)                                       
 Meniscal Lesion                                          5% (5/97)                                       
 Loose Body                                               5% (5/97)                                       
          Swedish Series
 

 Of 153 patients treated with autologous cultured chondrocyte implantation in the Swedish Series [  see  Clinical Studies (14)    ], 22% (34/153) of patients experienced the adverse reactions presented in  Table 4  below.



 Table 4: Initial ACI Experience Swedish Series Serious Adverse Reactions (Occurring at a frequency of 1% or more) 
 Serious Adverse Reactions                                              % of 153 Patients                 
  
 Tissue Hypertrophy                                                         See below                     
 Intra-articular Adhesions                                                     8%                         
 Superficial Wound Infection                                                   3%                         
 Hypertrophic Synovitis                                                        3%                         
 Post-operative Hematoma                                                       2%                         
 Adhesions of the Bursa Suprapatellaris                                        2%                         
 Hypertrophic Synovium                                                         1%                         
        About 1% of patients developed severe adhesions resulting in "frozen knee" and requiring lysis. Adverse reactions noted at a level of less than 1% included keloid-like scar, pannus formation, significant swelling of the joint, pain with post-operative fever, and hematoma following arthroscopy.
 

 In this series, arthroscopy was scheduled to be undertaken at 18 months of follow-up, regardless of patient symptoms. Of the patients who had arthroscopy, 43% (37/86) had hypertrophic tissue.



 Forty of the 85 patients had femoral condyle defects. Of these, 25% (10/40) of patients had some hypertrophic tissue noted at follow-up arthroscopy. Some patients had clinical symptoms that included painful crepitations or catching, and these symptoms generally resolved after arthroscopic resection of the hypertrophic tissue. Ten percent (10%) of patients with hypertrophy required additional treatment after hypertrophic tissue recurred following initial resection. Not all patients with tissue hypertrophy noted at arthroscopy were symptomatic.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Carticel  (r)  . Most of these reactions are reported voluntarily, and it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Furthermore, the reported frequency of spontaneous reports underestimates the true frequency of adverse reactions. As of July 31, 2006, approximately 12,500 patients have been implanted with Carticel and 559 patients have reported serious adverse reactions after treatment. The most frequently identified operative findings in these patients, in descending order of frequency, were graft overgrowth, graft delamination (partial or complete), arthrofibrosis, joint adhesions, meniscus lesion or tear, graft complications, chondromalacia, loose body in knee joint, and joint malalignment.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  The necessity of subsequent surgical procedures, primarily arthroscopic, following Carticel implantation is common. In the STAR study, 49% of patients underwent a subsequent surgical procedure, irrespective of relationship to Carticel. (  5.1  ,  6.2  ) 
 *  Carticel is not routinely tested for transmissible infectious diseases and may transmit diseases to the health care provider handling the product. Carticel is intended for autologous use only. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Pre-existing conditions, including meniscal tears, joint instability, or malalignment should be assessed and treated prior to or concurrent with Carticel implantation. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Carticel should not be used in patients who have previously had cancer in the bones, cartilage, fat or muscle of the treated limb. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Subsequent Surgical Procedures



  Review of the data from the Study of the Treatment of Articular Repair (STAR) and the Registry Based Study (RBS) [ see  Clinical Trials Experience (6.1)    ] as well as the Carticel worldwide experience (adverse reactions solicited through the Cartilage Repair Registry (CRR) and spontaneous reports) as of November 21, 1997 showed that the occurrence of a subsequent surgical procedure, primarily arthroscopic, following Carticel implantation is common. In the STAR study, 49% of patients underwent a subsequent surgical procedure, irrespective of relationship to Carticel (6.2). Symptoms leading to arthroscopic intervention included catching, locking, clicking or pain. Patients who develop clinical signs of tissue hypertrophy, including catching or clicking, should be evaluated and arthroscopy may be indicated for treatment or further assessment.



    5.2 Risk of Transmissible Infectious Diseases



  The Carticel product is intended solely for autologous use. Patients undergoing the surgical procedures associated with Carticel are not routinely tested for transmissible infectious diseases. Therefore, the cartilage biopsy and the Carticel product may carry the risk of transmitting infectious diseases to the health care provider handling these tissues. Accordingly, health care providers should employ universal precautions in handling the biopsy samples and the Carticel product.



    5.3 Pre-surgical Assessment of Comorbidities



  The following conditions should be assessed and treated prior to or concurrent with implantation with Carticel:



 *  Unstable meniscus tears should be repaired or resected. 
 *  If the patient has had a total meniscectomy, absent meniscus should be reconstructed. 
 *  Instability of the knee may adversely affect the success of the procedure and should be corrected. The anterior and posterior cruciate ligaments should be free of laxity as well as stable and intact. It is recommended that cruciate deficiencies be corrected. 
 *  Abnormal weight-distribution within the joint may adversely affect the success of the procedure and should be corrected. The tibial/femoral joint should be properly aligned. When treating trochlear defects, abnormal patellar mechanics should be assessed and corrected. 
       5.4 Product Safety and Sterility
 

  The safety of the Carticel product is unknown in patients with malignancy in the area of cartilage biopsy or implant. The potential exists for in vitro  expansion and subsequent implantation of malignant or dysplastic cells present in biopsy tissue. In addition, implantation of normal autologous chondrocytes could theoretically stimulate growth of malignant cells in the area of the implant, although there have been no reported incidents in humans or animals.



 The Carticel product is shipped following a preliminary sterility test with a 48-hour incubation to determine absence of microbial growth. Final (14 day incubation) sterility test results are not available at the time of implantation.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
