<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="casodex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions that occurred in more than 10% of patients receiving CASODEX plus an LHRH-A were: hot flashes, pain (including general, back, pelvic and abdominal), asthenia, constipation, infection, nausea, peripheral edema, dyspnea, diarrhea, hematuria, nocturia and anemia.  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals LP at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1. Clinical Trials Experience

  In patients with advanced prostate cancer treated with CASODEX in combination with an LHRH analog, the most frequent adverse reaction was hot flashes (53%).



 In the multicenter, double-blind, controlled clinical trial comparing CASODEX 50 mg once daily with flutamide 250 mg three times a day, each in combination with an LHRH analog, the following adverse reactions with an incidence of 5% or greater, regardless of causality, have been reported.



 Table 1. Incidence of Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5% in Either Treatment Group) Regardless of Causality 
   Body System Adverse Reaction                    Treatment Group Number of Patients (%)     
                                                   CASODEX Plus LHRH Analog (n=401)      Flutamide Plus LHRH Analog (n=407)     
  
  Body as a Whole                                                         
  Pain (General)                                  142 (35)                127 (31)                  
  Back Pain                                       102 (25)                105 (26)                  
  Asthenia                                        89 (22)                 87 (21)                   
  Pelvic Pain                                     85 (21)                 70 (17)                   
  Infection                                       71 (18)                 57 (14)                   
  Abdominal Pain                                  46 (11)                 46 (11)                   
  Chest Pain                                      34 (8)                  34 (8)                    
  Headache                                        29 (7)                  27 (7)                    
  Flu Syndrome                                    28 (7)                  30 (7)                    
  Cardiovascular                                                          
  Hot Flashes                                     211 (53)                217 (53)                  
  Hypertension                                    34 (8)                  29 (7)                    
  Digestive                                                               
  Constipation                                    87 (22)                 69 (17)                   
  Nausea                                          62 (15)                 58 (14)                   
  Diarrhea                                        49 (12)                 107 (26)                  
  Increased Liver Enzyme Test                     30 (7)                  46 (11)                   
  Dyspepsia                                       30 (7)                  23 (6)                    
  Flatulence                                      26 (6)                  22 (5)                    
  Anorexia                                        25 (6)                  29 (7)                    
  Vomiting                                        24 (6)                  32 (8)                    
  Hemic and Lymphatic                                                     
  Anemia                                          45 (11)                 53 (13)                   
  Metabolic and Nutritional                                               
  Peripheral Edema                                53 (13)                 42 (10)                   
  Weight Loss                                     30 (7)                  39 (10)                   
  Hyperglycemia                                   26 (6)                  27 (7)                    
  Alkaline Phosphatase Increased                  22 (5)                  24 (6)                    
  Weight Gain                                     22 (5)                  18 (4)                    
  Muscoloskeletal                                                         
  Bone Pain                                       37 (9)                  43 (11)                   
  Myasthenia                                      27 (7)                  19 (5)                    
  Arthritis                                       21 (5)                  29 (7)                    
  Pathological Fracture                           17 (4)                  32 (8)                    
  Nervous System                                                          
  Dizziness                                       41 (10)                 35 (9)                    
  Paresthesia                                     31 (8)                  40 (10)                   
  Insomnia                                        27 (7)                  39 (10)                   
  Anxiety                                         20 (5)                  9 (2)                     
  Depression                                      16 (4)                  33 (8)                    
  Respiratory System                                                      
  Dyspnea                                         51 (13)                 32 (8)                    
  Cough Increased                                 33 (8)                  24 (6)                    
  Pharyngitis                                     32 (8)                  23 (6)                    
  Bronchitis                                      24 (6)                  22 (3)                    
  Pneumonia                                       18 (4)                  19 (5)                    
  Rhinitis                                        15 (4)                  22 (5)                    
  Skin and Appendages                                                     
  Rash                                            35 (9)                  30 (7)                    
  Sweating                                        25 (6)                  20 (5)                    
  Urogenital                                                              
  Nocturia                                        49 (12)                 55 (14)                   
  Hematuria                                       48 (12)                 26 (6)                    
  Urinary Tract Infection                         35 (9)                  36 (9)                    
  Gynecomastia                                    36 (9)                  30 (7)                    
  Impotence                                       27 (7)                  35 (9)                    
  Breast Pain                                     23 (6)                  15 (4)                    
  Urinary Frequency                               23 (6)                  29 (7)                    
  Urinary Retention                               20 (5)                  14 (3)                    
  Urinary Impaired                                19 (5)                  15 (4)                    
  Urinary Incontinence                            15 (4)                  32 (8)                    
         Other adverse reactions (greater than or equal to 2%, but less than 5%) reported in the CASODEX-LHRH analog treatment group are listed below by body system and are in order of decreasing frequency within each body system regardless of causality.
 

   Body as a Whole:  Neoplasm; Neck Pain; Fever; Chills; Sepsis; Hernia; Cyst



   Cardiovascular:  Angina Pectoris; Congestive Heart Failure; Myocardial Infarct; Heart Arrest; Coronary Artery Disorder; Syncope



   Digestive:  Melena; Rectal Hemorrhage; Dry Mouth; Dysphagia; Gastrointestinal Disorder; Periodontal Abscess; Gastrointestinal Carcinoma



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Edema; BUN Increased; Creatinine Increased; Dehydration; Gout; Hypercholesteremia



   Musculoskeletal:  Myalgia; Leg Cramps



   Nervous:  Hypertonia; Confusion; Somnolence; Libido Decreased; Neuropathy; Nervousness



   Respiratory:  Lung Disorder; Asthma; Epistaxis; Sinusitis



   Skin and Appendages:  Dry Skin; Alopecia; Pruritus; Herpes Zoster; Skin Carcinoma; Skin Disorder



   Special Senses:  Cataract Specified



   Urogenital:  Dysuria; Urinary Urgency; Hydronephrosis; Urinary Tract Disorder



   Abnormal Laboratory Test Values:  



 Laboratory abnormalities including: elevated AST, ALT, bilirubin, BUN, and creatinine; and decreased hemoglobin and white cell count, have been reported in both CASODEX-LHRH analog treated and flutamide-LHRH analog treated patients.



   6.2. Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of CASODEX. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Respiratory disorders:  Interstitial lung disease (some fatal) including interstitial pneumonitis and pulmonary fibrosis, most often at doses greater than 50 mg.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Photosensitivity
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Severe hepatic injury and fatal hepatic failure have been observed. Monitor serum transaminase levels prior to starting treatment with CASODEX, at regular intervals for the first four months of treatment and periodically thereafter, and for symptoms or signs suggestive of hepatic dysfunction. Use CASODEX with caution in patients with hepatic impairment.  (5.1)   
 *    Gynecomastia and breast pain have been reported during treatment with CASODEX 150 mg when used as a single agent.  (5.2)   
 *    CASODEX is used in combination with a LHRH agonist. LHRH agonists have been shown to cause a reduction in glucose tolerance in males. Consideration should be given to monitoring blood glucose in patients receiving CASODEX in combination with LHRH agonists.  (5.3)   
 *    Monitoring Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) is recommended. Evaluate for clinical progression if PSA increases.  (5.4)   
    
 

   5.1. Hepatitis



  Cases of death or hospitalization due to severe liver injury (hepatic failure) have been reported post-marketing in association with the use of CASODEX. Hepatotoxicity in these reports generally occurred within the first three to four months of treatment. Hepatitis or marked increases in liver enzymes leading to drug discontinuation occurred in approximately 1% of CASODEX patients in controlled clinical trials.



 Serum transaminase levels should be measured prior to starting treatment with CASODEX, at regular intervals for the first four months of treatment, and periodically thereafter. If clinical symptoms or signs suggestive of liver dysfunction occur (e.g., nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, fatigue, anorexia, "flu-like" symptoms, dark urine, jaundice, or right upper quadrant tenderness), the serum transaminases, in particular the serum ALT, should be measured immediately. If at any time a patient has jaundice, or their ALT rises above two times the upper limit of normal, CASODEX should be immediately discontinued with close follow-up of liver function.



    5.2. Gynecomastia and Breast Pain



  In clinical trials with CASODEX 150 mg as a single agent for prostate cancer, gynecomastia and breast pain have been reported in up to 38% and 39% of patients, respectively.



    5.3. Glucose Tolerance



  A reduction in glucose tolerance has been observed in males receiving LHRH agonists. This may manifest as diabetes or loss of glycemic control in those with pre-existing diabetes. Consideration should therefore be given to monitoring blood glucose in patients receiving CASODEX in combination with LHRH agonists.



    5.4. Laboratory Tests



  Regular assessments of serum Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) may be helpful in monitoring the patient's response. If PSA levels rise during CASODEX therapy, the patient should be evaluated for clinical progression. For patients who have objective progression of disease together with an elevated PSA, a treatment-free period of antiandrogen, while continuing the LHRH analog, may be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
