<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cat2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Severe anaphvlactic reactions to this extract can occur in extremely allergic patients and at any dosage level. Do not use this extract unless you are prepared to deal with these    reactions, and    until you have read and understood the warnings, precautions, and dosage and administration sections of this insert.  



 The most serious systemic reaction that can occur is anaphylactic shock which while rare, is life threatening and must be treated immediately. Among other systemic reactions that have occurred are laryngeal edema, fainting, pallor bradycardia, hypotension, bronchospasm, angioedema, cough, sneezing, conjunctivitis, rhinitis, and urticaria.



 Should a serious systemic reaction occur:



 *  Inject 0.3-0.5 ml of 1:1000 epinephrine into the opposite arm; this may be repeated every 5 to 10 minutes, as a succession of smaller doses is more effective and less dangerous than a single larger one. Use a smaller dose for infants and children, in the range of 0.01 ml/kg of body weight. 
 *  Apply a tourniquet proximal to the injection site; loosen it at least every 10 minutes interval. 
 *  Inject no more than 0.1 ml of 1:1000 epinephrine at the injection site, to delay the absorption of the remaining extract. 
 *  Beta adrenergic agonists or aminophylline may be helpful in alleviating bronchospasm and airway obstruction. Other treatments that may be of benefit include H1antihistamines (e.g., 1 mg/kg diphenhydramine) and glococorticoids (e.g., 120 mg methylprednisolone). 
    These measures will almost always reverse the reaction but in the rare instances when they do not, then the full armamentarium of emergency medicine may be required, among them: direct laryngoscopy direct current cardioversion, tracheotomy, and intracardiac injection of drugs  8  .
 

 The occurrence of a severe systemic reaction to an injection of this extract does not contraindicate further therapy, but the next dose given should be reduced by at least 90% and raised very slowly thereafter. If a pattern of systemic reactions- even very mild ones- appears, then the benefits of continued treatment must be carefully weighed against the substantial demonstrated risk.



 Local reactions, even relatively severe but transient redness, swelling and discomfort, are the normal physiologic response to the allergens and to the volume of the fluid injected, and in their milder forms are not unexpected. Local reactions generally subside quickly and do not require treatment, but application of cold to the injection site or other symptomatic measures may be useful. However, severe local reactions should be considered a warning of potential systemic reaction if that dosage is continued. Always reduce the dose substantially if such a local reaction occurs.



     Overdosage:  

  See  Adverse Reactions  section.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

    WARNING  

    This product should be used only by or under the direction of physicians experienced in administering allergens to the maximum tolerated dose and the emerg    ency treatment of anaphylaxis,     and only where adequate means         for treating severe systemic reactions are immediately available  .



 This standardized cat hair extract is not interchangeable with non-standardized extracts, cat pelt extracts or with extracts labeled in allergy units per mL (AU/mL).



 See   Description  ,   Warnings  , and   Dosage and Administration   sections for further information.



 Allergenic extracts may potentially elicit a severe life-threatening systemic reaction, rarely resulting in death  1  . Because of the possibility of severe systemic reactions, the patient should be instructed in the recognition of anaphylactic symptoms, observed in the office for 20 to 30 minutes after each injection, and warned to return to the office if symptoms of an allergic reaction occur. Serious adverse events should be reported to the FDA MedWatch Program:



   MedWatch  



 5600 Fishers Lane Rockville, MD 20852-9787, (1 -800-FDA-1088)



 Patients receiving beta-blockers may not be responsive to epinephrine or inhaled bronchodilators, and the risk of severely complicating the treatment of systemic reactions should be carefully considered before a decision to treat is reached. Care should also be taken with patients with unstable or steroid-dependent asthma, or with underlying cardiovascular disease.



 Before administering this or any allergenic extract, physicians should be thoroughly familiar with the information in this insert, especially the Warnings, Precautions, and Adverse Reactions sections.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
