<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="catapres1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinical trial experience with CATAPRES-TTS

  Most systemic adverse effects during Catapres-TTS(r) (clonidine) transdermal therapeutic system therapy have been mild and have tended to diminish with continued therapy. In a 3-month multi-clinic trial of CATAPRES-TTS transdermal therapeutic system in 101 hypertensive patients, the systemic adverse reactions were, dry mouth (25 patients) and drowsiness (12), fatigue (6), headache (5), lethargy and sedation (3 each), insomnia, dizziness, impotence/sexual dysfunction, dry throat (2 each) and constipation, nausea, change in taste and nervousness (1 each).



 In the above mentioned 3-month controlled clinical trial, as well as other uncontrolled clinical trials, the most frequent adverse reactions were dermatological and are described below.



 In the 3-month trial, 51 of the 101 patients had localized skin reactions such as erythema (26 patients) and/or pruritus, particularly after using an adhesive cover throughout the 7-day dosage interval. Allergic contact sensitization to CATAPRES-TTS transdermal therapeutic system was observed in 5 patients. Other skin reactions were localized vesiculation (7 patients), hyperpigmentation (5), edema (3), excoriation (3), burning (3), papules (1), throbbing (1), blanching (1), and a generalized macular rash (1).



 In additional clinical experience, contact dermatitis resulting in treatment discontinuation was observed in 128 of 673 patients (about 19 in 100) after a mean duration of treatment of 37 weeks. The incidence of contact dermatitis was about 34 in 100 among white women, about 18 in 100 in white men, about 14 in 100 in black women, and approximately 8 in 100 in black men. Analysis of skin reaction data showed that the risk of having to discontinue CATAPRES-TTS transdermal therapeutic system treatment because of contact dermatitis was greatest between treatment weeks 6 and 26, although sensitivity may develop either earlier or later in treatment.



 In a large-scale clinical acceptability and safety study by 451 physicians in a total of 3539 patients, other allergic reactions were recorded for which a causal relationship to CATAPRES-TTS transdermal therapeutic system was not established: maculopapular rash (10 cases); urticaria (2 cases); and angioedema of the face (2 cases), which also affected the tongue in one of the patients.



   Marketing Experience with CATAPRES-TTS

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of CATAPRES-TTS transdermal therapeutic system. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate reliably their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to CATAPRES-TTS transdermal therapeutic system.



   Body as a Whole:  Fever; malaise; weakness; pallor; and withdrawal syndrome.



   Cardiovascular:  Congestive heart failure; cerebrovascular accident; electrocardiographic abnormalities (i.e., bradycardia, sick sinus syndrome disturbances and arrhythmias); chest pain; orthostatic symptoms; syncope; increases in blood pressure; sinus bradycardia and atrioventricular (AV) block with and without the use of concomitant digitalis; Raynaud's phenomenon; tachycardia; bradycardia; and palpitations.



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Delirium; mental depression; hallucinations (including visual and auditory); localized numbness; vivid dreams or nightmares; restlessness; anxiety; agitation; irritability; other behavioral changes; and drowsiness.



   Dermatological:  Angioneurotic edema; localized or generalized rash; hives; urticaria; contact dermatitis; pruritus; alopecia; and localized hypo or hyper pigmentation.



   Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia and vomiting.



   Genitourinary:  Difficult micturition; loss of libido; and decreased sexual activity.



   Metabolic:  Gynecomastia or breast enlargement and weight gain.



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle or joint pain; and leg cramps.



   Ophthalmological:  Blurred vision; burning of the eyes and dryness of the eyes.



   Adverse Events Associated with Oral CATAPRES Therapy:  Most adverse effects are mild and tend to diminish with continued therapy. The most frequent (which appear to be dose-related) are dry mouth, occurring in about 40 of 100 patients; drowsiness, about 33 in 100; dizziness, about 16 in 100; constipation and sedation, each about 10 in 100. The following less frequent adverse experiences have also been reported in patients receiving CATAPRES (clonidine hydrochloride, USP) tablets, but in many cases patients were receiving concomitant medication and a causal relationship has not been established.



   Body as a Whole:  Fatigue, fever, headache, pallor, weakness, and withdrawal syndrome. Also reported were a weakly positive Coombs' test and increased sensitivity to alcohol.



   Cardiovascular:  Bradycardia, congestive heart failure, electrocardiographic abnormalities (i.e., sinus node arrest, junctional bradycardia, high degree AV block and arrhythmias), orthostatic symptoms, palpitations, Raynaud's phenomenon, syncope, and tachycardia. Cases of sinus bradycardia and AV block have been reported, both with and without the use of concomitant digitalis.



   Central Nervous System:  Agitation, anxiety, delirium, delusional perception, hallucinations (including visual and auditory), insomnia, mental depression, nervousness, other behavioral changes, paresthesia, restlessness, sleep disorder, and vivid dreams or nightmares.



   Dermatological:  Alopecia, angioneurotic edema, hives, pruritus, rash, and urticaria.



   Gastrointestinal:  Abdominal pain, anorexia, constipation, hepatitis, malaise, mild transient abnormalities in liver function tests, nausea, parotitis, pseudo-obstruction (including colonic pseudo-obstruction), salivary gland pain, and vomiting.



   Genitourinary:  Decreased sexual activity, difficulty in micturition, erectile dysfunction, loss of libido, nocturia, and urinary retention.



   Hematologic:  Thrombocytopenia.



   Metabolic:  Gynecomastia, transient elevation of blood glucose or serum creatine phosphokinase, and weight gain.



   Musculoskeletal:  Leg cramps and muscle or joint pain.



   Oro-otolaryngeal:  Dryness of the nasal mucosa.



   Ophthalmological:  Accommodation disorder, blurred vision, burning of the eyes, decreased lacrimation, and dryness of the eyes.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
