<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="caverject" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Local Adverse Reactions

  The following local adverse reaction information was derived from controlled and uncontrolled studies, including an uncontrolled 18-month safety study.



 Local Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;= 1% of Patients Treated with CAVERJECT for up to 18 MonthsExcept for penile pain (2%), no significant local adverse reactions were reported by 294 patients who received 1 to 3 injections of placebo. 
   Event                                                                CAVERJECT  N = 1861               
  
 Penile pain                                                                     37%                      
 Prolonged erection                                                               4%                      
 Penile fibrosis                                                                  3%                      
 Injection site hematoma                                                          3%                      
 Penis disorder                                                                   3%                      
 Injection site ecchymosis                                                        2%                      
 Penile rash                                                                      1%                      
 Penile edema                                                                     1%                      
          Penile Pain
   Penile pain after intracavernosal administration of CAVERJECT was reported at least once by 37% of patients in clinical studies of up to 18 months in duration. In the majority of the cases, penile pain was rated mild or moderate in intensity. Three percent of patients discontinued treatment because of penile pain. The frequency of penile pain was 2% in 294 patients who received 1 to 3 injections of placebo.



   Prolonged Erection/Priapism

  In clinical trials, prolonged erection was defined as an erection that lasted for 4 to 6 hours; priapism was defined as erection that lasted 6 hours or longer. The frequency of prolonged erection after intracavernosal administration of CAVERJECT was 4%, while the frequency of priapism was 0.4%. In the majority of cases, spontaneous detumescence occurred. To minimize the chances of prolonged erection or priapism, CAVERJECT should be titrated slowly to the lowest effective dose (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  section). The patient must be instructed to immediately report to his physician or, if unavailable, to seek immediate medical assistance for any erection that persists for longer than 4 hours. If priapism is not treated immediately, penile tissue damage and permanent loss of potency may result.



   Hematoma/Ecchymosis

  The frequency of hematoma and ecchymosis was 3% and 2%, respectively. In most cases, hematoma/ecchymosis was judged to be a complication of a faulty injection technique. Accordingly, proper instruction of the patient in self-injection is of importance to minimize the potential of hematoma/ecchymosis (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ).



 The following local adverse reactions were reported by fewer than 1% of patients after injection of CAVERJECT: balanitis, injection site hemorrhage, injection site inflammation, injection site itching, injection site swelling, injection site edema, urethral bleeding, penile warmth, numbness, yeast infection, irritation, sensitivity, phimosis, pruritus, erythema, venous leak, painful erection, and abnormal ejaculation.



   Systemic Adverse Events

  The following systemic adverse event information was derived from controlled and uncontrolled studies, including an uncontrolled 18-month safety study.



 Systemic Adverse Events Reported by &gt;= 1% of Patients Treated with CAVERJECT for up to 18 MonthsNo significant adverse events were reported by 294 patients who received 1 to 3 injections of placebo. 
   Body System/Reaction                                                 CAVERJECT  N = 1861               
  
 Cardiovascular System                                                                                    
   Hypertension                                                                   2%                      
 Central Nervous System                                                                                   
   Headache                                                                       2%                      
   Dizziness                                                                      1%                      
 Musculoskeletal System                                                                                   
   Back pain                                                                      1%                      
 Respiratory System                                                                                       
   Upper respiratory infection                                                    4%                      
   Flu syndrome                                                                   2%                      
   Sinusitis                                                                      2%                      
   Nasal congestion                                                               1%                      
   Cough                                                                          1%                      
 Urogenital System                                                                                        
   Prostatic Disorder                                                             2%                      
 Miscellaneous                                                                                            
   Localized pain                                                                 2%                      
   Trauma                                                                         2%                      
        The following systemic events, which were reported for &lt; 1% of patients in clinical studies, were judged by investigators to be possibly related to use of CAVERJECT: testicular pain, scrotal disorder, scrotal edema, hematuria, testicular disorder, impaired urination, urinary frequency, urinary urgency, pelvic pain, hypotension, vasodilation, peripheral vascular disorder, supraventricular extrasystoles, vasovagal reactions, hypesthesia, non-generalized weakness, diaphoresis, rash, non-application site pruritus, skin neoplasm, nausea, dry mouth, increased serum creatinine, leg cramps, and mydriasis.
 

 Hemodynamic changes, manifested as decreases in blood pressure and increases in pulse rate, were observed during clinical studies, principally at doses above 20 micrograms and above 30 micrograms of alprostadil, respectively, and appeared to be dose-dependent. However, these changes were usually clinically unimportant; only three patients discontinued the treatment because of symptomatic hypotension.



 CAVERJECT had no clinically important effect on serum or urine laboratory tests.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
