<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cefazolin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions to cefazolin are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Hypersensitivity reactions [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ]  
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
   *   Most common adverse reactions: gastrointestinal (nausea, vomiting, diarrhea), and allergic reactions (anaphylaxis, urticaria, skin rash). (  6  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact B. Braun Medical Inc. at 1-800-227-2862 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  The following adverse reactions were reported from clinical trials:



 Gastrointestinal: Diarrhea, oral candidiasis (oral thrush), mouth ulcers, vomiting, nausea, stomach cramps, epigastric pain, heartburn, flatus, anorexia and pseudomembranous colitis. Onset of pseudomembranous colitis symptoms may occur during or after antibacterial treatment [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ].



 Allergic: Anaphylaxis, eosinophilia, urticaria, itching, drug fever, skin rash, Stevens-Johnson syndrome.



 Hematologic: Neutropenia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, thrombocythemia.



 Hepatic: Transient rise in SGOT, SGPT, and alkaline phosphatase levels has been observed. As with other cephalosporins, reports of hepatitis have been received.



 Renal: As with other cephalosporins, reports of increased BUN and creatinine levels, as well as renal failure, have been received.



 Local Reactions: Instances of phlebitis have been reported at site of injection. Some induration has occurred.



 Other Reactions: Pruritus (including genital, vulvar and anal pruritus, genital moniliasis, and vaginitis). Dizziness, fainting, lightheadedness, confusion, weakness, tiredness, hypotension, somnolence and headache.



   6.2 Cephalosporin-class Adverse Reactions

  In addition to the adverse reactions listed above that have been observed in patients treated with cefazolin, the following adverse reactions and altered laboratory tests have been reported for cephalosporin-class antibacterials: Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis, renal impairment, toxic nephropathy, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, hemorrhage, hepatic impairment including cholestasis, and pancytopenia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions: Cross-hypersensitivity may occur in up to 10% of patients with a history of penicillin allergy. If an allergic reaction occurs, discontinue the drug. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Use in patients with renal impairment: Dose adjustment required for patients with CrCl less than 55 mL/min. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea: May range from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions to Cefazolin, Cephalosporins, Penicillins, or Other Beta-lactams



  Serious and occasionally fatal hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions have been reported in patients receiving beta-lactam antibacterial drugs. Before therapy with Cefazolin for Injection USP and Dextrose Injection USP is instituted, careful inquiry should be made to determine whether the patient has had previous immediate hypersensitivity reactions to cefazolin, cephalosporins, penicillins, or carbapenems. Exercise caution if this product is to be given to penicillin-sensitive patients because cross-hypersensitivity among beta-lactam antibacterial drugs has been clearly documented and may occur in up to 10% of patients with a history of penicillin allergy. If an allergic reaction to Cefazolin for Injection USP and Dextrose Injection USP occurs, discontinue the drug.



    5.2 Use In Patients with Renal Impairment



  As with other beta-lactam antibacterial drugs, seizures may occur if inappropriately high doses are administered to patients with impaired renal function (creatinine clearance less than 55 mL/min.) [see   Dosage and Administration (2.3)    ].



    5.3 Clostridium difficile  -associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including cefazolin, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B, which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin-producing isolates of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial drug use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibacterial drug use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial drug treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.4 Hypersensitivity to Dextrose-containing Products



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have been reported with administration of dextrose-containing products. These reactions have been reported in patients receiving high concentrations of dextrose (i.e. 50% dextrose)  1  .  The reactions have also been reported when corn-derived dextrose solutions were administered to patients with or without a history of hypersensitivity to corn products.  2  



    5.5 Risk of Development of Drug-resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing Cefazolin for Injection USP and Dextrose Injection USP in the absence of proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.



 As with other antimicrobials, prolonged use of Cefazolin for Injection USP and Dextrose Injection USP may result in overgrowth of nonsusceptible microorganisms. Repeated evaluation of the patient's condition is essential. Should superinfection occur during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.



    5.6 Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions



   Urinary Glucose



  The administration of cefazolin may result in a false-positive reaction with glucose in the urine when using CLINITEST(r) tablets. It is recommended that glucose tests based on enzymatic glucose oxidase reactions (e.g., CLINISTIX(r)) be used. 



    Coombs' Test



  Positive direct Coombs' tests have been reported during treatment with cefazolin. In hematologic studies or in transfusion cross-matching procedures when antiglobulin tests are performed on the minor side or in Coombs' testing of newborns whose mothers have received cephalosporin antibacterial drugs before parturition, it should be recognized that a positive Coombs' test may be due to the drug.



    5.7 Patients with Overt or Known Subclinical Diabetes Mellitus or Carbohydrate Intolerance



  As with other dextrose-containing solutions, Cefazolin for Injection USP and Dextrose Injection USP should be prescribed with caution in patients with overt or known subclinical diabetes mellitus or carbohydrate intolerance for any reason.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
