<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cefepime" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Hypersensitivity reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ] 
 *    Renal Impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] 
 *    Neurotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] 
 *     Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ] 
   *     The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 1 %) were local reactions (including phlebitis), pain and/or inflammation, and rash. (   6   )To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter at 1-866-888-2472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
      EXCERPT:   
   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical trials using multiple doses of cefepime, 4137 patients were treated with the recommended dosages of cefepime (500 mg to 2 g intravenously every 12 hours). Sixty-four (1.5%) patients discontinued medication due to adverse events thought by the investigators to be possibly, probably, or almost certainly related to drug toxicity. Thirty-three (51%) of these 64 patients who discontinued therapy did so because of rash. The percentage of cefepime-treated patients who discontinued study drug because of drug-related adverse events was very similar at daily doses of 500 mg, 1 g, and 2 g every 12 hours (0.8%, 1.1%, and 2.0%, respectively). However, the incidence of discontinuation due to rash increased with the higher recommended doses.



 The following adverse events were thought to be probably related to cefepime during evaluation of the drug in clinical trials conducted in North America (n=3125 cefepime-treated patients).



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Cefepime Multiple-Dose Dosing Regimens Clinical Trials-North America 
  INCIDENCE EQUAL TO OR GREATER THAN 1%           Local reactions (3%), including phlebitis (1.3%), pain and/or inflammation (0.6%)Local reactions, irrespective of relationship to cefepime in those patients who received intravenous infusion (n=3048).; rash (1.1%)    
  INCIDENCE LESS THAN 1% BUT GREATER THAN 0.1%    Colitis (including pseudomembranous colitis), diarrhea, fever, headache, nausea, oral moniliasis, pruritus, urticaria, vaginitis, vomiting    
        At the higher dose of 2 g every 8 hours, the incidence of probably-related adverse events was higher among the 795 patients who received this dose of cefepime. They consisted of rash (4%), diarrhea (3%), nausea (2%), vomiting (1%), pruritus (1%), fever (1%), and headache (1%).
 

 The following adverse laboratory changes, irrespective of relationship to therapy with cefepime, were seen during clinical trials conducted in North America.



 Table 4: Adverse Laboratory Changes Cefepime Multiple-Dose Dosing Regimens Clinical Trials-North America 
  INCIDENCE EQUAL TO OR GREATER THAN 1%           Positive Coombs' test (without hemolysis) (16.2%); decreased phosphorus (2.8%); increased ALT/SGPT (2.8%), AST/SGOT (2.4%), eosinophils (1.7%); abnormal PTT (1.6%), PT (1.4%)    
  INCIDENCE LESS THAN 1% BUT GREATER THAN 0.1%    Increased alkaline phosphatase, BUN, calcium, creatinine, phosphorus, potassium, total bilirubin; decreased calciumHypocalcemia was more common among elderly patients. Clinical consequences from changes in either calcium or phosphorus were not reported., hematocrit, neutrophils, platelets, WBC    
        A similar safety profile was seen in clinical trials of pediatric patients [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to the events reported during North American clinical trials with cefepime, the following adverse experiences have been reported during worldwide postmarketing experience. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Encephalopathy (disturbance of consciousness including confusion, hallucinations, stupor, and coma), myoclonus, seizures, and nonconvulsive status epilepticus have been reported. Although most cases occurred in patients with renal impairment who received doses of cefepime that exceeded the recommended dosage schedules, some cases of neurotoxicity occurred in patients receiving an appropriate dosage adjustment for their degree of renal impairment. If neurotoxicity associated with cefepime therapy occurs, consider discontinuing cefepime or making appropriate dosage adjustments in patients with renal impairment.



 As with other cephalosporins, anaphylaxis including anaphylactic shock, transient leukopenia, neutropenia, agranulocytosis, and thrombocytopenia has been reported.



   6.3 Cephalosporin-class Adverse Reactions

  In addition to the adverse reactions listed above that have been observed in patients treated with cefepime, the following adverse reactions have been reported for cephalosporin-class antibiotics:



 Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis, renal impairment, toxic nephropathy, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, hemorrhage, hepatic impairment including cholestasis, and pancytopenia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Cross-hypersensitivity among beta-lactam antibiotics may occur in up to 10% of patients with a history of penicillin allergy. If an allergic reaction to Cefepime Injection occurs, discontinue the drug. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Use in patients with renal impairment: dosage adjustment required for patients with CrCL &lt;= 60 mL/min. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Neurotoxicity: May occur in patients receiving inappropriate dosage adjustment(s) for renal impairment. Discontinue cefepime or make appropriate dosage adjustments in patients with renal impairment in the event of neurotoxicity. (  5.3  ) 
 *     Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea: May range from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Before therapy with Cefepime Injection is instituted, careful inquiry should be made to determine whether the patient has had previous immediate hypersensitivity reactions to cefepime, cephalosporins, penicillins, or other drugs. If this product is to be given to penicillin-sensitive patients, caution should be exercised because cross-hypersensitivity among beta-lactam antibiotics has been clearly documented and may occur in up to 10% of patients with a history of penicillin allergy. If an allergic reaction to Cefepime Injection occurs, discontinue the drug. Serious acute hypersensitivity reactions may require treatment with epinephrine and other emergency measures including oxygen, corticosteroids, intravenous fluids, intravenous antihistamines, pressor amines, and airway management, as clinically indicated.



    5.2 Renal Impairment



  In patients with creatinine clearance less than or equal to 60 mL/min, the dose of Cefepime Injection should be adjusted to compensate for the slower rate of renal elimination. Because high and prolonged cefepime concentrations can occur from usual dosages in patients with renal impairment or other conditions that may compromise renal function, the maintenance dosage should be reduced when Cefepime Injection is administered to such patients. Continued dosage should be determined by degree of renal impairment, severity of infection, and susceptibility of the causative organisms. Refer to specific recommendations for dosing adjustment [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ].



    5.3 Neurotoxicity



  During postmarketing surveillance, serious adverse reactions have been reported including life-threatening or fatal occurrences of the following: encephalopathy (disturbance of consciousness including confusion, hallucinations, stupor, and coma), myoclonus, seizures, and nonconvulsive status epilepticus [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]. Most cases occurred in patients with renal impairment who did not receive appropriate dosage adjustment. However, some cases of neurotoxicity occurred in patients receiving a dosage adjustment appropriate for their degree of renal impairment.



 In the majority of cases, symptoms of neurotoxicity were reversible and resolved after discontinuation of cefepime and/or after hemodialysis. If neurotoxicity associated with cefepime therapy occurs, consider discontinuing cefepime or making appropriate dosage adjustments in patients with renal impairment.



    5.4 Clostridium difficile  Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including Cefepime Injection, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.5 Risk of Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing cefepime in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.



 As with other antimicrobials, prolonged use of cefepime may result in overgrowth of nonsusceptible microorganisms. Repeated evaluation of the patient's condition is essential. Should superinfection occur during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.



    5.6 Patients with Meningeal Seeding/Meningitis



  In those patients in whom meningeal seeding from a distant infection site or in whom meningitis is suspected or documented, an alternate agent with demonstrated clinical efficacy in this setting should be used.



    5.7 Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions



    Urinary Glucose    



 The administration of cefepime may result in a false-positive reaction for glucose in the urine when using CLINITEST tablets. It is recommended that glucose tests based on enzymatic glucose oxidase reactions (such as CLINISTIX) be used.



     Coombs' Test    



 Positive direct Coombs' tests have been reported during treatment with cefepime. In hematologic studies or in transfusion cross-matching procedures when antiglobulin tests are performed on the minor side or in Coombs' testing of newborns whose mothers have received cephalosporin antibiotics before parturition, it should be recognized that a positive Coombs' test may be due to the drug.



     Prothrombin Time    



 Many cephalosporins, including cefepime, have been associated with a fall in prothrombin activity. Those at risk include patients with renal or hepatic impairment, or poor nutritional state, as well as patients receiving a protracted course of antimicrobial therapy. Prothrombin time should be monitored in patients at risk, and exogenous vitamin K administered as indicated.



    5.8 Patients with a History of Gastrointestinal Disease



  Cefepime Injection should be prescribed with caution in individuals with a history of gastrointestinal disease, particularly colitis.



    5.9 Possible Effects of Arginine on Glucose Metabolism



  Cefepime Injection contains arginine to adjust pH [see  Description (11)  ]. Arginine has been shown to alter glucose metabolism and elevate serum potassium transiently when administered at 33 times the amount provided by the maximum recommended human dose of cefepime. The effect of lower doses is not presently known.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
