<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cefoxitin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Cefoxitin is generally well tolerated. The most common adverse reactions have been local reactions following intravenous injection. Other adverse reactions have been encountered infrequently.



   

      Local Reactions    



 Thrombophlebitis has occurred with intravenous administration.



     Allergic Reactions    



 Rash (including exfoliative dermatitis and toxic epidermal necrolysis), urticaria, flushing, pruritus, eosinophilia, fever, dyspnea, and other allergic reactions including anaphylaxis, interstitial nephritis and angioedema have been noted.



     Cardiovascular    



 Hypotension.



     Gastrointestinal    



 Diarrhea, including documented pseudomembranous colitis which can appear during or after antibiotic treatment. Nausea and vomiting have been reported rarely.



     Neuromuscular    



 Possible exacerbation of myasthenia gravis.



     Blood    



 Eosinophilia, leukopenia including granulocytopenia, neutropenia, anemia, including hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, and bone marrow depression. A positive direct Coombs test may develop in some individuals, especially those with azotemia.



     Liver Function    



 Transient elevation in SGOT, SGPT, serum LDH, and serum alkaline phosphatase; and jaundice have been reported.



     Renal Function    



 Elevations in serum creatinine and/or blood urea nitrogen levels have been observed. As with the cephalosporins, acute renal failure has been reported rarely. The role of cefoxitin in changes in renal function tests is difficult to assess, since factors predisposing to prerenal azotemia or to impaired renal function usually have been present.



 In addition to the adverse reactions listed above which have been observed in patients treated with cefoxitin, the following adverse reactions and altered laboratory test results have been reported for cephalosporin class antibiotics:



 Urticaria, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, serum sickness-like reactions, abdominal pain, colitis, renal dysfunction, toxic nephropathy, false-positive test for urinary glucose, hepatic dysfunction including cholestasis, elevated bilirubin, aplastic anemia, hemorrhage, prolonged prothrombin time, pancytopenia, agranulocytosis, superinfection, vaginitis including vaginal candidiasis.



 Several cephalosporins have been implicated in triggering seizures, particularly in patients with renal impairment when the dosage was not reduced. (See    DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION    .) If seizures associated with drug therapy occur, the drug should be discontinued. Anticonvulsant therapy can be given if clinically indicated.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
