<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ceftin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse reaction is described in greater detail in the Warnings and Precautions section of the label:



 Anaphylactic Reactions  [see Warnings and Precautions [5.1)]  



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3%) for CEFTIN tablets are diarrhea, nausea/vomiting, Jarisch-Herxheimer reaction and vaginitis (early Lyme disease). (  6.1  )



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) for CEFTIN for oral suspension are diarrhea, dislike of taste, diaper rash, and nausea/vomiting. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Tablets  



   Multiple  -  dose Dosing Regimens with 7 to 10 Days' Duration:  In multiple-dose clinical trials, 912 subjects were treated with CEFTIN (125 to 500 mg twice daily). It is noted that 125 mg twice daily is not an approved dosage. Twenty (2.2%) subjects discontinued medication due to adverse reactions. Seventeen (85%) of the 20 subjects who discontinued therapy did so because of gastrointestinal disturbances, including diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, and abdominal pain. The percentage of subjects treated with CEFTIN who discontinued study drug because of adverse reactions was similar at daily doses of 1,000, 500, and 250 mg (2.3%, 2.1%, and 2.2%, respectively). However, the incidence of gastrointestinal adverse reactions increased with the higher recommended doses.



 The adverse reactions in Table 5 are for subjects (n = 912) treated with CEFTIN in multiple-dose clinical trials.



 Table 5. Adverse Reactions (&gt;=1%) after Multiple-dose Regimens with CEFTIN Tablets 
  Adverse Reaction                                 CEFTIN  (n = 912)    
  Blood and lymphatic system disorders                            
  Eosinophilia                                     1%             
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                      
  Diarrhea                                         4%             
  Nausea/Vomiting                                  3%             
  Investigations                                                  
  Transient elevation in AST                       2%             
  Transient elevation in ALT                       2%             
  Transient elevation in LDH                       1%             
        The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 1% but greater than 0.1% of subjects (n = 912) treated with CEFTIN in multiple-dose clinical trials.
 

   Immune System Disorders:  Hives, swollen tongue.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Anorexia.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Headache.



   Cardiac Disorders:  Chest pain.



   Respiratory Disorders:  Shortness of breath.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Abdominal pain, abdominal cramps, flatulence, indigestion, mouth ulcers.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Rash, itch.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Dysuria.



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  Vaginitis, vulvar itch.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Chills, sleepiness, thirst.



   Investigations:  Positive Coombs' test.



   5-Day Regimen:  In clinical trials using CEFTIN 250 mg twice daily in the treatment of secondary bacterial infections of acute bronchitis, 399 subjects were treated for 5 days and 402 subjects were treated for 10 days. No difference in the occurrence of adverse reactions was found between the 2 regimens.



   Early Lyme Disease with 20-Day Regimen:  Two multicenter trials assessed CEFTIN 500 mg twice daily for 20 days. The most common drug-related adverse experiences were diarrhea (10.6%), Jarisch-Herxheimer reaction (5.6%), and vaginitis (5.4%). Other adverse experiences occurred with frequencies comparable to those reported with 7 to 10 days' dosing.



   Single  -  dose Regimen for Uncomplicated Gonorrhea:  In clinical trials using a single 1,000-mg dose of CEFTIN, 1,061 subjects were treated for uncomplicated gonorrhea.



 The adverse reactions in Table 6 were for subjects treated with a single dose of 1,000 mg CEFTIN in US clinical trials.



 Table 6. Adverse Reactions (&gt;=1%) after Single-dose Regimen with 1,000-mg CEFTIN Tablets for Uncomplicated Gonorrhea 
  Adverse Reaction                      CEFTIN  (n = 1,061)    
  Gastrointestinal disorders                               
  Nausea/Vomiting                       7%                 
  Diarrhea                              4%                 
        The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 1% but greater than 0.1% of subjects (n = 1,061) treated with a single dose of CEFTIN 1,000 mg for uncomplicated gonorrhea in US clinical trials.
 

   Infections and Infestations:  Vaginal candidiasis.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Headache, dizziness, somnolence.



   Cardiac Disorders:  Tightness/pain in chest, tachycardia.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Abdominal pain, dyspepsia.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Erythema, rash, pruritus.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Muscle cramps, muscle stiffness, muscle spasm of neck, lockjaw-type reaction.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Bleeding/pain in urethra, kidney pain.



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  Vaginal itch, vaginal discharge.



     Oral Suspension  



 In clinical trials using multiple doses of CEFTIN, pediatric subjects (96.7% were younger than 12 years) were treated with CEFTIN (20 to 30 mg/kg/day divided twice daily up to a maximum dose of 500 or 1,000 mg/day, respectively). Eleven (1.2%) US subjects discontinued medication due to adverse reactions. The discontinuations were primarily for gastrointestinal disturbances, usually diarrhea or vomiting. Thirteen (1.4%) US pediatric subjects discontinued therapy due to the taste and/or problems with drug administration.



 The adverse reactions in Table 7 are for US subjects (n = 931) treated with CEFTIN in multiple-dose clinical trials.



 Table 7. Adverse Reactions (&gt;=1%) after Multiple-dose Regimens with CEFTIN for Oral Suspension 
  Adverse Reaction                             CEFTIN  (n = 931)    
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                
  Diarrhea                                     9%           
  Dislike of taste                             5%           
  Nausea/vomiting                              3%           
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                    
  Diaper rash                                  3%           
        The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 1% but greater than 0.1% of US subjects (n = 931) treated with CEFTIN for oral suspension in multiple-dose clinical trials.
 

   Infections and Infestations:  Gastrointestinal infection, candidiasis, viral illness, upper respiratory infection, sinusitis, urinary tract infection.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Eosinophilia.



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Hyperactivity, irritable behavior.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Abdominal pain, flatulence, ptyalism.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Rash.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Joint swelling, arthralgia.



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  Vaginal irritation.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Cough, fever.



   Investigations:  Elevated liver enzymes, positive Coombs' test.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of CEFTIN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenia.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  



 Pseudomembranous colitis  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



   Hepatobiliary Disorders  



 Hepatic impairment including hepatitis and cholestasis, jaundice.



   Immune System Disorders  



 Anaphylaxis, serum sickness-like reaction.



   Investigations  



 Increased prothrombin time.



   Nervous System Disorders  



 Seizure, encephalopathy.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders  



 Renal dysfunction.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Angioedema, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, urticaria.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Serious hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions: In the event of a serious reaction, discontinue CEFTIN and institute appropriate therapy. (  5.1  ) 
 *     Clostridium difficile- associated diarrhea (CDAD): If diarrhea occurs, evaluate patients for CDAD. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylactic Reactions



  Serious and occasionally fatal hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions have been reported in patients on beta-lactam antibacterials. These reactions are more likely to occur in individuals with a history of beta-lactam hypersensitivity and/or a history of sensitivity to multiple allergens. There have been reports of individuals with a history of penicillin hypersensitivity who have experienced severe reactions when treated with cephalosporins. CEFTIN is contraindicated in patients with a known hypersensitivity to CEFTIN or other beta-lactam antibacterial drugs [see Contraindications (4)]  . Before initiating therapy with CEFTIN, inquire about previous hypersensitivity reactions to penicillins, cephalosporins, or other allergens. If an allergic reaction occurs, discontinue CEFTIN and institute appropriate therapy.



    5.2 Clostridium difficile  -associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile-  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including CEFTIN, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin-producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over 2 months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.3 Potential for Microbial Overgrowth



  The possibility of superinfections with fungal or bacterial pathogens should be considered during therapy.



    5.4 Development of Drug-resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing CEFTIN either in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.



    5.5 Phenylketonuria



  CEFTIN for oral suspension 125 mg/5 mL contains phenylalanine 11.8 mg per 5 mL (1 teaspoonful) of reconstituted suspension. CEFTIN for oral suspension 250 mg/5 mL contains phenylalanine 25.2 mg per 5 mL (1 teaspoonful) of reconstituted suspension.



    5.6 Interference with Glucose Tests



  A false-positive result for glucose in the urine may occur with copper reduction tests, and a false-negative result for blood/plasma glucose may occur with ferricyanide tests in subjects receiving CEFTIN [see Drug Interactions (7.4)]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
