<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="celexa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The premarketing development program for Celexa included citalopram exposures in patients and/or normal subjects from 3 different groups of studies: 429 normal subjects in clinical pharmacology/pharmacokinetic studies; 4422 exposures from patients in controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials, corresponding to approximately 1370 patient-exposure years. There were, in addition, over 19,000 exposures from mostly open-label, European postmarketing studies. The conditions and duration of treatment with Celexa varied greatly and included (in overlapping categories) open-label and double-blind studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, fixed-dose and dose-titration studies, and short-term and long-term exposure. Adverse reactions were assessed by collecting adverse events, results of physical examinations, vital signs, weights, laboratory analyses, ECGs, and results of ophthalmologic examinations.



 Adverse events during exposure were obtained primarily by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of events into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and tabulations that follow, standard World Health Organization (WHO) terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events.



 The stated frequencies of adverse events represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



   Adverse Findings Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials

  Adverse Events Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment

  Among 1063 depressed patients who received Celexa at doses ranging from 10 to 80 mg/day in placebo-controlled trials of up to 6 weeks in duration, 16% discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, as compared to 8% of 446 patients receiving placebo. The adverse events associated with discontinuation and considered drug-related (i.e., associated with discontinuation in at least 1% of Celexa-treated patients at a rate at least twice that of placebo) are shown in    TABLE 2    . It should be noted that one patient can report more than one reason for discontinuation and be counted more than once in this table.



 TABLE 2 Adverse Events Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled, Depression Trials 
   Percentage of Patients Discontinuing     
   Due to Adverse Event               
                                       Citalopram                       Placebo                           
                                       (N=1063)                         (N=446)                           
   Body System/Adverse Event                                                                              
   General                                                                                                
      Asthenia                       1%                               &lt;1%                                 
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                             
      Nausea                         4%                               0%                                  
      Dry Mouth                      1%                               &lt;1%                                 
      Vomiting                       1%                               0%                                  
   Central and Peripheral                                                                                 
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                               
      Dizziness                      2%                               &lt;1%                                 
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                  
      Insomnia                       3%                               1%                                  
      Somnolence                     2%                               1%                                  
      Agitation                      1%                               &lt;1%                                 
           Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More Among Celexa -Treated Patients
       Table 3    enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse events that occurred among 1063 depressed patients who received Celexa at doses ranging from 10 to 80 mg/day in placebo-controlled trials of up to 6 weeks in duration. Events included are those occurring in 2% or more of patients treated with Celexa and for which the incidence in patients treated with Celexa was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidence rate in the population studied.



 The only commonly observed adverse event that occurred in Celexa patients with an incidence of 5% or greater and at least twice the incidence in placebo patients was ejaculation disorder (primarily ejaculatory delay) in male patients (see    TABLE 3    ).



 TABLE 3 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events: Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials* 
  *Events reported by at least 2% of patients treated with Celexa are reported, except for the following events which had an incidence on placebo &gt;= Celexa: headache, asthenia, dizziness, constipation, palpitation, vision abnormal, sleep disorder, nervousness, pharyngitis, micturition disorder, back pain.    
  1Denominator used was for females only (N=638 Celexa; N=252 placebo).    
  2Primarily ejaculatory delay.                 
  3Denominator used was for males only (N=425 Celexa; N=194 placebo).    
  
   (Percentage of Patients Reporting Event)     
                                                                                                          
   Body System/Adverse Event                     Celexa                           Placebo                 
                                                 (N=1063)                         (N=446)                 
   Autonomic Nervous System                                                                               
   Disorders                                                                                              
      Dry Mouth                                20%                              14%                       
      Sweating Increased                       11%                              9%                        
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous                                                                           
   System Disorders                                                                                       
      Tremor                                   8%                               6%                        
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                             
      Nausea                                   21%                              14%                       
      Diarrhea                                 8%                               5%                        
      Dyspepsia                                5%                               4%                        
      Vomiting                                 4%                               3%                        
      Abdominal Pain                           3%                               2%                        
   General                                                                                                
      Fatigue                                  5%                               3%                        
      Fever                                    2%                               &lt;1%                       
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                                 
   Disorders                                                                                              
      Arthralgia                               2%                               1%                        
      Myalgia                                  2%                               1%                        
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                  
      Somnolence                               18%                              10%                       
      Insomnia                                 15%                              14%                       
      Anxiety                                  4%                               3%                        
      Anorexia                                 4%                               2%                        
      Agitation                                3%                               1%                        
      Dysmenorrhea  1                          3%                               2%                        
      Libido Decreased                         2%                               &lt;1%                       
      Yawning                                  2%                               &lt;1%                       
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                           
      Upper Respiratory Tract Infection        5%                               4%                        
      Rhinitis                                 5%                               3%                        
      Sinusitis                                3%                               &lt;1%                       
   Urogenital                                                                                             
      Ejaculation Disorder  2,3                6%                               1%                        
      Impotence  3                             3%                               &lt;1%                       
           Dose Dependency of Adverse Events
   The potential relationship between the dose of Celexa administered and the incidence of adverse events was examined in a fixed-dose study in depressed patients receiving placebo or Celexa 10, 20, 40, and 60 mg. Jonckheere's trend test revealed a positive dose response (p&lt;0.05) for the following adverse events: fatigue, impotence, insomnia, sweating increased, somnolence, and yawning.



   Male and Female Sexual Dysfunction with SSRIs

  Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that SSRIs can cause such untoward sexual experiences.



 Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, however, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling, are likely to underestimate their actual incidence.



 The table below displays the incidence of sexual side effects reported by at least 2% of patients taking Celexa in a pool of placebo-controlled clinical trials in patients with depression.




   Treatment                                          Celexa  (425 males)        Placebo  (194 males)      
 Abnormal Ejaculation(mostly ejaculatory delay)     6.1%(males only)           1%(males only)              
 Libido Decreased                                   3.8%(males only)           &lt;1%(males only)             
 Impotence                                          2.8%(males only)           &lt;1%(males only)             
         In female depressed patients receiving Celexa, the reported incidence of decreased libido and anorgasmia was 1.3% (n=638 females) and 1.1% (n=252 females), respectively.
 

 There are no adequately designed studies examining sexual dysfunction with citalopram treatment.



 Priapism has been reported with all SSRIs.



 While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



   Vital Sign Changes

  Celexa and placebo groups were compared with respect to (1) mean change from baseline in vital signs (pulse, systolic blood pressure, and diastolic blood pressure) and (2) the incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially clinically significant changes from baseline in these variables. These analyses did not reveal any clinically important changes in vital signs associated with Celexa treatment. In addition, a comparison of supine and standing vital sign measures for Celexa and placebo treatments indicated that Celexa treatment is not associated with orthostatic changes.



   Weight Changes

  Patients treated with Celexa in controlled trials experienced a weight loss of about 0.5 kg compared to no change for placebo patients.



   Laboratory Changes

  Celexa and placebo groups were compared with respect to (1) mean change from baseline in various serum chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis variables, and (2) the incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially clinically significant changes from baseline in these variables. These analyses revealed no clinically important changes in laboratory test parameters associated with Celexa treatment.



   ECG Changes

  In a thorough QT study, Celexa was found to be associated with a dose-dependent increase in the QTc interval (see    WARNINGS - QT-Prolongation and Torsade de Pointes  )  .



 Electrocardiograms from Celexa (N=802) and placebo (N=241) groups were compared with respect to outliers defined as subjects with QTc changes over 60 msec from baseline or absolute values over 500 msec post-dose, and subjects with heart rate increases to over 100 bpm or decreases to less than 50 bpm with a 25% change from baseline (tachycardic or bradycardic outliers, respectively). In the Celexa group 1.9% of the patients had a change from baseline in QTcF &gt;60 msec compared to 1.2% of the patients in the placebo group. None of the patients in the placebo group had a post-dose QTcF &gt;500 msec compared to 0.5% of the patients in the Celexa group. The incidence of tachycardic outliers was 0.5% in the Celexa group and 0.4% in the placebo group. The incidence of bradycardic outliers was 0.9% in the Celexa group and 0.4% in the placebo group.



   Other Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Celexa (citalopram HBr)

  Following is a list of WHO terms that reflect treatment-emergent adverse events, as defined in the introduction to the    ADVERSE REACTIONS    section, reported by patients treated with Celexa at multiple doses in a range of 10 to 80 mg/day during any phase of a trial within the premarketing database of 4422 patients. All reported events are included except those already listed in    Table 3    or elsewhere in labeling, those events for which a drug cause was remote, those event terms which were so general as to be uninformative, and those occurring in only one patient. It is important to emphasize that, although the events reported occurred during treatment with Celexa, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: frequent adverse events are those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events are those occurring in less than 1/100 patients but at least 1/1000 patients; rare events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



     Cardiovascular  -  Frequent:  tachycardia, postural hypotension, hypotension.  Infrequent:  hypertension, bradycardia, edema (extremities), angina pectoris, extrasystoles, cardiac failure, flushing, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular accident, myocardial ischemia.  Rare:  transient ischemic attack, phlebitis, atrial fibrillation, cardiac arrest, bundle branch block.



     Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders  -  Frequent:  paresthesia, migraine.  Infrequent:  hyperkinesia, vertigo, hypertonia, extrapyramidal disorder, leg cramps, involuntary muscle contractions, hypokinesia, neuralgia, dystonia, abnormal gait, hypesthesia, ataxia.  Rare:  abnormal coordination, hyperesthesia, ptosis, stupor.



     Endocrine Disorders  -  Rare:  hypothyroidism, goiter, gynecomastia.



     Gastrointestinal Disorders  -  Frequent:  saliva increased, flatulence.  Infrequent:  gastritis, gastroenteritis, stomatitis, eructation, hemorrhoids, dysphagia, teeth grinding, gingivitis, esophagitis.  Rare:  colitis, gastric ulcer, cholecystitis, cholelithiasis, duodenal ulcer, gastroesophageal reflux, glossitis, jaundice, diverticulitis, rectal hemorrhage, hiccups.



     General  -  Infrequent:  hot flushes, rigors, alcohol intolerance, syncope, influenza-like symptoms.  Rare:  hayfever.



     Hemic and Lymphatic Disorders  -  Infrequent:  purpura, anemia, epistaxis, leukocytosis, leucopenia, lymphadenopathy.  Rare:  pulmonary embolism, granulocytopenia, lymphocytosis, lymphopenia, hypochromic anemia, coagulation disorder, gingival bleeding.



     Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  -  Frequent:  decreased weight, increased weight.  Infrequent:  increased hepatic enzymes, thirst, dry eyes, increased alkaline phosphatase, abnormal glucose tolerance.  Rare:  bilirubinemia, hypokalemia, obesity, hypoglycemia, hepatitis, dehydration.



     Musculoskeletal System Disorders  -  Infrequent:  arthritis, muscle weakness, skeletal pain.  Rare:  bursitis, osteoporosis.



     Psychiatric Disorders  -  Frequent:  impaired concentration, amnesia, apathy, depression, increased appetite, aggravated depression, suicide attempt, confusion.  Infrequent:  increased libido, aggressive reaction, paroniria, drug dependence, depersonalization, hallucination, euphoria, psychotic depression, delusion, paranoid reaction, emotional lability, panic reaction, psychosis.  Rare:  catatonic reaction, melancholia.



   Reproductive Disorders/Female*  -  Frequent:  amenorrhea.  Infrequent:  galactorrhea, breast pain, breast enlargement, vaginal hemorrhage.



   *% based on female subjects only: 2955



     Respiratory System Disorders  -  Frequent:  coughing.  Infrequent:  bronchitis, dyspnea, pneumonia.  Rare:  asthma, laryngitis, bronchospasm, pneumonitis, sputum increased.



     Skin and Appendages Disorders  -  Frequent:  rash, pruritus.  Infrequent:  photosensitivity reaction, urticaria, acne, skin discoloration, eczema, alopecia, dermatitis, skin dry, psoriasis.  Rare:  hypertrichosis, decreased sweating, melanosis, keratitis, cellulitis, pruritus ani.



     Special Senses  -  Frequent:  accommodation abnormal, taste perversion.  Infrequent:  tinnitus, conjunctivitis, eye pain.  Rare:  mydriasis, photophobia, diplopia, abnormal lacrimation, cataract, taste loss.



     Urinary System Disorders  -  Frequent:  polyuria.  Infrequent:  micturition frequency, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, dysuria.  Rare:  facial edema, hematuria, oliguria, pyelonephritis, renal calculus, renal pain.



   Other Events Observed During the Postmarketing Evaluation of Celexa (citalopram HBr)

  It is estimated that over 30 million patients have been treated with Celexa since market introduction. Although no causal relationship to Celexa treatment has been found, the following adverse events have been reported to be temporally associated with Celexa treatment, and have not been described elsewhere in labeling: acute renal failure, akathisia, allergic reaction, anaphylaxis, angioedema, choreoathetosis, chest pain, delirium, dyskinesia, ecchymosis, epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, angle closure glaucoma, grand mal convulsions, hemolytic anemia, hepatic necrosis, myoclonus, nystagmus, pancreatitis, priapism, prolactinemia, prothrombin decreased, QT prolonged, rhabdomyolysis, spontaneous abortion, thrombocytopenia, thrombosis, ventricular arrhythmia, torsade de pointes, and withdrawal syndrome.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

  Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of Celexa or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. Celexa is not approved for use in pediatric patients. (See   WARNINGS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk  ,   PRECAUTIONS: Information for Patients  , and   PRECAUTIONS: Pediatric Use  .)  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
