<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cerezyme" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Since the approval of    Cerezyme(r)    (imiglucerase for injection) in May 1994, Genzyme has maintained a worldwide post-marketing database of spontaneously reported adverse events and adverse events discussed in the medical literature. The percentage of events for each reported adverse reaction term has been calculated using the number of patients from these sources as the denominator for total patient exposure to    Cerezyme    since 1994. Actual patient exposure is difficult to obtain due to the voluntary nature of the database and the continuous accrual and loss of patients over that span of time. The actual number of patients exposed to    Cerezyme    since 1994 is likely to be greater than estimated from these voluntary sources and, therefore, the percentages calculated for the frequencies of adverse reactions are most likely greater than the actual incidences.



 Experience in patients treated with    Cerezyme(r)    has revealed that approximately 13.8% of patients experienced adverse events which were judged to be related to    Cerezyme    administration and which occurred with an increase in frequency. Some of the adverse events were related to the route of administration. These include discomfort, pruritus, burning, swelling or sterile abscess at the site of venipuncture. Each of these events was found to occur in &lt; 1% of the total patient population.



 Symptoms suggestive of hypersensitivity have been noted in approximately 6.6% of patients. Onset of such symptoms has occurred during or shortly after infusions; these symptoms include pruritus, flushing, urticaria, angioedema, chest discomfort, dyspnea, coughing, cyanosis, and hypotension. Anaphylactoid reaction has also been reported (see      WARNINGS      ). Each of these events was found to occur in &lt; 1.5% of the total patient population. Pre-treatment with antihistamines and/or corticosteroids and reduced rate of infusion have allowed continued use of    Cerezyme    in most patients.



 Additional adverse reactions that have been reported in approximately 6.5% of patients treated with    Cerezyme    include: nausea, abdominal pain, vomiting, diarrhea, rash, fatigue, headache, fever, dizziness, chills, backache, and tachycardia. Each of these events was found to occur in &lt; 1.5% of the total patient population.



 Incidence rates cannot be calculated from the spontaneously reported adverse events in the post-marketing database. From this database, the most commonly reported adverse events in children (defined as ages 2 - 12 years) included dyspnea, fever, nausea, flushing, vomiting, and coughing, whereas in adolescents (&gt;12 - 16 years) and in adults (&gt;16 years) the most commonly reported events included headache, pruritis, and rash.



 In addition to the adverse reactions that have been observed in patients treated with    Cerezyme    , transient peripheral edema has been reported for this therapeutic class of drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
