<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cesamet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Commonly Encountered Reactions

  During controlled clinical trials of Cesamet, virtually all patients experienced at least one adverse reaction. The most commonly encountered events were drowsiness, vertigo, dry mouth, euphoria (feeling "high"), ataxia, headache, and concentration difficulties.



   Comparative Incidence of Reactions

  Accurate estimates of the incidence of adverse events associated with the use of any drug are difficult to obtain. Estimates are influenced by factors such as drug dose, detection technique, setting, and physician judgments, among others. Consequently, the tables presented below are presented solely to indicate the relative frequency of adverse events reported in representative controlled clinical studies conducted to evaluate the safety and efficacy of Cesamet under relatively similar conditions of use. The figures cited cannot be used to predict precisely the incidence of untoward events in the course of usual medical practice, in which patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. These incidence figures also cannot be compared with those obtained from other clinical studies involving related drug products because each group of drug trials is conducted under a different set of conditions.



 Finally, it is important to emphasize that these tabulations do not reflect the relative severity and/or clinical importance of the adverse events. A better perspective on the serious adverse events associated with the use of Cesamet is provided in the    WARNINGS    and    PRECAUTIONS    sections.



 The following tables list in order of decreasing frequency the adverse reactions encountered by a substantial proportion of patients treated with Cesamet participating in representative controlled clinical trials.



 Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Studies 
                                           Nabilone (n=132)  Placebo (n=119)   
 Adverse Event                                Patients          Percent         Patients          Percent       
  
 Vertigo                                         69               52                3                3          
 Drowsiness                                      69               52                6                5          
 Dry Mouth                                       47               36                2                2          
 Ataxia                                          19               14                0                0          
 Euphoria                                        14               11                1                1          
 Sleep Disturbance                               14               11                1                1          
 Dysphoria                                       12                9                0                0          
 Headache                                         8                6                0                0          
 Nausea                                           5                4                0                0          
 Disorientation                                   3                2                0                0          
 Depersonalization                                2                2                1                1          
          Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Active-Controlled Studies 
                                           Nabilone(n=250)  Prochlorperazine(n=232)   
 Adverse Event                                Patients          Percent         Patients          Percent       
  
 Drowsiness                                      165              66               108              47          
 Vertigo/Dizziness                               147              59               53               23          
 Euphoria                                        95               38               12                5          
 Dry Mouth                                       54               22               11                5          
 Depression                                      35               14               37               16          
 Ataxia                                          32               13                4                2          
 Visual Disturbance                              32               13                9                4          
 Concentration Difficulties                      31               12                3                1          
 Hypotension                                     20                8                3                1          
 Asthenia                                        19                8               10                4          
 Anorexia                                        19                8               22                9          
 Headache                                        18                7               14                6          
 Sedation                                         7                3                2                1          
 Increased Appetite                               6                2                2                1          
             Adverse Reactions by Body System
   The following list of adverse events is organized by decreasing frequency within body systems for patients treated with Cesamet in controlled clinical trials. All events are listed regardless of causality assessment.



   Blood and Hematopoietic  -Anemia



   Cardiovascular  -Orthostatic hypotension, hypotension, tachycardia, syncope, palpitation, flushing, hypertension, arrhythmia, and cerebral vascular accident.



   Eye and Ear  -Vision disturbance, ear tightness, eye irritation, eye dryness, equilibrium dysfunction, tinnitus, eye disorder, amblyopia, eye swelling, eyelid diseases, pupil dilation, photophobia, and visual field defect.



   Gastrointestinal  -Dry mouth, nausea, anorexia, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain, constipation, aphthous ulcer, mouth irritation, gastritis, and dyspepsia.



   Genitourinary  -Increased urination, decreased urination, hot flashes, urinary retention, and frequency of micturition.



   Infection  -Bacterial infection



   Metabolic and Endocrine  -Thirst



   Musculoskeletal  -Muscle pain, back pain, neck pain, joint pain, and unspecified pain.



   Nervous System  -Drowsiness, vertigo, ataxia, decreased concentration, sedation, hallucinations, paresthesia, tremor, memory disturbance, perception disturbance, convulsions, dystonia, numbness, and akathisia.



   Psychiatric  -Euphoria (feeling "high"), sleep disturbance, depression, confusion, disorientation, anxiety, depersonalization syndrome, speech disorder, abnormal dreams, insomnia, mood swings, inebriated feeling, toxic psychosis, paranoia, apathy, thought disorder, withdrawal, panic disorder, phobic neurosis, emotional disorder, and hyperactivity.



   Respiratory  -Dyspnea, pharyngitis, nasal congestion, sinus headache, thick tongue, dry throat, dry nose, wheezing, nosebleed, cough, voice change, and chest pain.



   Skin and Appendages  -Anhidrosis, photosensitivity, pruritus, rash, and allergic reactions.



   Miscellaneous and Ill-Defined Conditions  -Headache, fatigue, lightheadedness, coordination disturbance, asthesia, dysphoria, dizziness, taste change, excessive appetite, chills, excessive sweating, nervousness, malaise, postural dizziness, twitch, irritability, fever, inhibited walking, unconsciousness, hypotonia, and impaired urination.



   Postmarketing Adverse Reactions

  Cesamet has been marketed internationally since 1982. The following adverse reactions listed in order of decreasing frequency by body system have been reported since Cesamet has been marketed. All events are listed regardless of causality assessment.



   Blood and Hematopoietic  -Leukopenia



   Cardiovascular  -Hypotension and tachycardia



   Eye and Ear  -Visual disturbances



   Gastrointestinal  -Dry mouth, nausea, vomiting, and constipation



   Nervous System  -Hallucinations, CNS depression, CNS stimulation, ataxia, stupor, vertigo, convulsion, and circumoral paresthesia



   Psychiatric  -Somnolence, confusion, euphoria, depression, dysphoria, depersonalization, anxiety, psychosis, and emotional lability



   Miscellaneous and Ill-Defined Conditions  -Dizziness, headache, insomnia, abnormal thinking, chest pain, lack of effect, and face edema
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
