<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cetrotide" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The safety of Cetrotide  (r)  (cetrorelix acetate for injection) in 949 patients undergoing controlled ovarian stimulation in clinical studies was evaluated. Women were between 19 and 40 years of age (mean: 32). 94.0% of them were Caucasian. Cetrotide  (r)  was given in doses ranging from 0.1 mg to 5 mg as either a single or multiple dose.



 Table 3 shows systemic adverse events, reported in clinical studies without regard to causality, from the beginning of Cetrotide  (r)  treatment until confirmation of pregnancy by ultrasound at an incidence &gt;= 1% in Cetrotide  (r)  treated subjects undergoing COS.



 Table 3: Adverse Events in &gt;=1% 
 (WHO preferred term)                                                   Cetrotide  (r)  N=949% (n)        
  
 Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome                                               3.5 (33)                 
 Nausea                                                                          1.3 (12)                 
 Headache                                                                        1.1 (10)                 
        Local site reactions (e.g. redness, erythema, bruising, itching, swelling, and pruritus) were reported. Usually, they were of a transient nature, mild intensity and short duration. During post-marketing surveillance, rare cases of hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactoid reactions have been reported.
 

 Two stillbirths were reported in Phase 3 studies of Cetrotide  (r)  .



   Congenital Anomalies

  Clinical follow-up studies of 316 newborns of women administered Cetrotide  (r)  were reviewed. One infant of a set of twin neonates was found to have anencephaly at birth and died after four days. The other twin was normal. Developmental findings from ongoing baby follow-up included a child with a ventricular septal defect and another child with bilateral congenital glaucoma.



 Four pregnancies that resulted in therapeutic abortion in Phase 2 and Phase 3 controlled ovarian stimulation studies had major anomalies (diaphragmatic hernia, trisomy 21, Klinefelter syndrome, polymalformation, and trisomy 18). In three of these four cases, intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) was the fertilization method employed; in the fourth case,  in vitro  fertilization (IVF) was the method employed.



 The minor congenital anomalies reported include: supernumerary nipple, bilateral strabismus, imperforate hymen, congenital nevi, hemangiomata, and QT syndrome.



 The causal relationship between the reported anomalies and Cetrotide  (r)  is unknown. Multiple factors, genetic and others (including, but not limited to ICSI, IVF, gonadotropins, and progesterone) make causal attribution difficult to study.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
