<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="chantix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions were reported in postmarketing experience and are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Neuropsychiatric symptoms and suicidality [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *    Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *    Interaction with Alcohol [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *    Accidental injury [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *    Cardiovascular Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *    Angioedema and hypersensitivity reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *    Serious skin reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
    In the placebo-controlled premarketing studies, the most common adverse events associated with CHANTIX (&gt;5% and twice the rate seen in placebo-treated patients) were nausea, abnormal (vivid, unusual, or strange) dreams, constipation, flatulence, and vomiting.
 

 The treatment discontinuation rate due to adverse events in patients dosed with 1 mg twice daily was 12% for CHANTIX, compared to 10% for placebo in studies of three months' treatment. In this group, the discontinuation rates that are higher than placebo for the most common adverse events in CHANTIX-treated patients were as follows: nausea (3% vs. 0.5% for placebo), insomnia (1.2% vs. 1.1% for placebo), and abnormal dreams (0.3% vs. 0.2% for placebo).



 Smoking cessation, with or without treatment, is associated with nicotine withdrawal symptoms and has also been associated with the exacerbation of underlying psychiatric illness.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5% and twice the rate seen in placebo-treated patients) were nausea, abnormal (e.g., vivid, unusual, or strange) dreams, constipation, flatulence, and vomiting. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reactions rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 During the premarketing development of CHANTIX, over 4500 subjects were exposed to CHANTIX, with over 450 treated for at least 24 weeks and approximately 100 for a year. Most study participants were treated for 12 weeks or less.



 The most common adverse event associated with CHANTIX treatment is nausea, occurring in 30% of patients treated at the recommended dose, compared with 10% in patients taking a comparable placebo regimen  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  .



 Table 5 shows the adverse events for CHANTIX and placebo in the 12- week fixed dose premarketing studies with titration in the first week [Studies 2 (titrated arm only), 4, and 5]. Adverse events were categorized using the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA, Version 7.1).



 MedDRA High Level Group Terms (HLGT) reported in &gt;= 5% of patients in the CHANTIX 1 mg twice daily dose group, and more commonly than in the placebo group, are listed, along with subordinate Preferred Terms (PT) reported in &gt;= 1% of CHANTIX patients (and at least 0.5% more frequent than placebo). Closely related Preferred Terms such as 'Insomnia', 'Initial insomnia', 'Middle insomnia', 'Early morning awakening' were grouped, but individual patients reporting two or more grouped events are only counted once.



 Table 5: Common Treatment Emergent AEs (%) in the Fixed-Dose, Placebo-Controlled Studies (HLGTs &gt;= 5% of patients in the 1 mg BID CHANTIX Group and more commonly than placebo and PT &gt;= 1% in the 1 mg BID CHANTIX Group, and 1 mg BID CHANTIX at least 0.5% more than Placebo) 
   SYSTEM ORGAN CLASS    High Level Group Term      CHANTIX    0.5 mg BID      CHANTIX    1 mg BID      Placebo          
   Preferred Term                         N=129              N=821              N=805            
  
  GASTROINTESTINAL (GI)                                                                          
    GI Signs and Symptoms                                                                        
      Nausea                             16                 30                 10                
      Abdominal Pain Includes PTs Abdominal (pain, pain upper, pain lower, discomfort, tenderness, distension) and Stomach discomfort    5                  7                  5                 
      Flatulence                         9                  6                  3                 
      Dyspepsia                          5                  5                  3                 
      Vomiting                           1                  5                  2                 
    GI Motility/Defecation Conditions                                                            
      Constipation                       5                  8                  3                 
      Gastroesophageal reflux disease    1                  1                  0                 
    Salivary Gland Conditions                                                                    
      Dry mouth                          4                  6                  4                 
  PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                                                                          
    Sleep Disorder/Disturbances                                                                  
      Insomnia Includes PTs Insomnia/Initial insomnia/Middle insomnia/Early morning awakening    19                 18                 13                
      Abnormal dreams                    9                  13                 5                 
      Sleep disorder                     2                  5                  3                 
      Nightmare                          2                  1                  0                 
  NERVOUS SYSTEM                                                                                 
    Headaches                                                                                    
      Headache                           19                 15                 13                
    Neurological Disorders NEC                                                                   
      Dysgeusia                          8                  5                  4                 
      Somnolence                         3                  3                  2                 
      Lethargy                           2                  1                  0                 
  GENERAL DISORDERS                                                                              
    General Disorders NEC                                                                        
    Fatigue/Malaise/Asthenia             4                  7                  6                 
  RESPIR/THORACIC/MEDIAST                                                                        
    Respiratory Disorders NEC                                                                    
      Rhinorrhea                         0                  1                  0                 
      Dyspnea                            2                  1                  1                 
      Upper Respiratory Tract Disorder    7                  5                  4                 
  SKIN/SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE                                                                       
    Epidermal and Dermal Conditions                                                              
      Rash                               1                  3                  2                 
      Pruritis                           0                  1                  1                 
  METABOLISM &amp; NUTRITION                                                                         
    Appetite/General Nutrit. Disorders                                                            
      Increased appetite                 4                  3                  2                 
      Decreased appetite/Anorexia        1                  2                  1                 
          The overall pattern and frequency of adverse events during the longer-term premarketing trials was similar to those described in Table 5, though several of the most common events were reported by a greater proportion of patients with long-term use (e.g., nausea was reported in 40% of patients treated with CHANTIX 1 mg twice daily in a one-year study, compared to 8% of placebo-treated patients).
 

 Following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse events reported by patients treated with CHANTIX during all premarketing clinical trials and updated based on pooled data from 18 placebo-controlled pre- and post-marketing studies, including approximately 5,000 patients treated with varenicline. Adverse events were categorized using MedDRA, Version 16.0. The listing does not include those events already listed in the previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, those events for which a drug cause was remote, those events which were so general as to be uninformative, and those events reported only once which did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life-threatening.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  .  Infrequent:  anemia, lymphadenopathy.  Rare:  leukocytosis, splenomegaly, thrombocytopenia.



   Cardiac Disorders  .  Infrequent:  angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, palpitations, tachycardia.  Rare:  acute coronary syndrome, arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, cardiac flutter, cor pulmonale, coronary artery disease, ventricular extrasystoles.



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders  .  Infrequent:  tinnitus, vertigo.  Rare:  deafness, Meniere's disease.



   Endocrine Disorders  .  Infrequent:  thyroid gland disorders.



   Eye Disorders  .  Infrequent:  conjunctivitis, eye irritation, eye pain, vision blurred, visual impairment.  Rare:  blindness transient, cataract subcapsular, dry eye, night blindness, ocular vascular disorder, photophobia, vitreous floaters.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  .  Frequent:  diarrhea, toothache  . Infrequent:  dysphagia, eructation, gastritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, mouth ulceration.  Rare:  enterocolitis, esophagitis, gastric ulcer, intestinal obstruction, pancreatitis acute.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  .  Frequent:  chest pain.  Infrequent:  chest discomfort, chills, edema, influenza-like illness, pyrexia.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders  .  Rare:  gall bladder disorder.



   Investigations  .  Frequent:  liver function test abnormal, weight increased.  Infrequent:  electrocardiogram abnormal.  Rare:  muscle enzyme increased, urine analysis abnormal.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  .  Infrequent:  diabetes mellitus, hypoglycemia.  Rare:  hyperlipidemia, hypokalemia.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  .  Frequent  : arthralgia, back pain, myalgia.  Infrequent:  arthritis, muscle cramp, musculoskeletal pain.  Rare:  myositis, osteoporosis.



   Nervous System Disorders  .  Frequent:  disturbance in attention, dizziness.  Infrequent:  amnesia, convulsion, migraine, parosmia, syncope, tremor.  Rare:  balance disorder, cerebrovascular accident, dysarthria, mental impairment, multiple sclerosis, VII  th  nerve paralysis, nystagmus, psychomotor hyperactivity, psychomotor skills impaired, restless legs syndrome, sensory disturbance, transient ischemic attack, visual field defect.



   Psychiatric Disorders  .  Infrequent:  dissociation, libido decreased, mood swings, thinking abnormal.  Rare:  bradyphrenia, disorientation, euphoric mood.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders  .  Infrequent:  nocturia, pollakiuria, urine abnormality.  Rare:  nephrolithiasis, polyuria, renal failure acute, urethral syndrome, urinary retention.



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders  .  Frequent:  menstrual disorder.  Infrequent:  erectile dysfunction.  Rare:  sexual dysfunction.



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders.    Frequent:  respiratory disorders.  Infrequent:  asthma, epistaxis, rhinitis allergic, upper respiratory tract inflammation.  Rare:  pleurisy, pulmonary embolism.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  .  Infrequent:  acne, dry skin, eczema, erythema, hyperhidrosis, urticaria.  Rare:  photosensitivity reaction, psoriasis.



   Vascular Disorders  .  Infrequent:  hot flush.  Rare:  thrombosis.



 CHANTIX has also been studied in postmarketing trials including (1) a trial conducted in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), (2) a trial conducted in generally healthy patients (similar to those in the premarketing studies) in which they were allowed to select a quit date between days 8 and 35 of treatment ("alternative quit date instruction trial"), (3) a trial conducted in patients who did not succeed in stopping smoking during prior CHANTIX therapy, or who relapsed after treatment ("re-treatment trial"), (4) a trial conducted in patients with stable cardiovascular disease, (5) a trial conducted in patients with stable schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder and (6) a trial conducted in patients with major depressive disorder.



 Adverse events in the trial of patients with COPD, in the alternative quit date instruction trial, were quantitatively and qualitatively similar to those observed in premarketing studies. In the re-treatment trial, the profile of common adverse events was similar to that previously reported, but, in addition, varenicline-treated patients also commonly reported diarrhea (6% vs 4% in placebo-treated patients), depressed mood disorders and disturbances (6% vs 1%), and other mood disorders and disturbances (5% vs 2%).



 In the trial of patients with stable cardiovascular disease, more types and a greater number of cardiovascular events were reported compared to premarketing studies. Treatment-emergent (on-treatment or 30 days after treatment) cardiovascular events reported with a frequency &gt;= 1% in either treatment group in this study were angina pectoris (3.7% and 2.0% for varenicline and placebo, respectively), chest pain (2.5% vs. 2.3%), peripheral edema (2.0% vs. 1.1%), hypertension (1.4% vs. 2.6%), and palpitations (0.6 % vs. 1.1%). Deaths and serious cardiovascular events occurring over the 52 weeks of the study (treatment emergent and non-treatment emergent) were adjudicated by a blinded, independent committee. The following treatment-emergent adjudicated events occurred with a frequency &gt;=1% in either treatment group: nonfatal MI (1.1% vs. 0.3% for varenicline and placebo, respectively), and hospitalization for angina pectoris (0.6% vs. 1.1%). During non-treatment follow up to 52 weeks, the adjudicated events included need for coronary revascularization (2.0% vs. 0.6%), hospitalization for angina pectoris (1.7% vs. 1.1%), and new diagnosis of peripheral vascular disease (PVD) or admission for a PVD procedure (1.4% vs. 0.6%). Some of the patients requiring coronary revascularization underwent the procedure as part of management of nonfatal MI and hospitalization for angina. Cardiovascular death occurred in 0.3% of patients in the varenicline arm and 0.6% of patients in the placebo arm over the course of the 52-week study.



 In the trial of patients with stable schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder, 128 smokers on antipsychotic medication were randomized 2:1 to varenicline (1 mg twice daily) or placebo for 12 weeks with 12-week non-drug follow-up. The most common adverse events in patients taking varenicline were nausea (24% vs. 14.0% on placebo), headache (11% vs. 19% on placebo) and vomiting (11% vs. 9% on placebo). Among reported neuropsychiatric adverse events, insomnia was the only event that occurred in either treatment group in &gt;=5% of subjects at a rate higher in the varenicline group than in placebo (10% vs. 5%). These common and neuropsychiatric adverse events occurred on treatment or within 30 days after the last dose of study drug. There was no consistent worsening of schizophrenia in either treatment group as measured by the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale. There were no overall changes in extra-pyramidal signs, as measured by the Simpson-Angus Rating Scale. The Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale was administered at baseline and at clinic visits during the treatment and non-treatment follow-up phases. Over half of the patients had a lifetime history of suicidal behavior and/or ideation (62% on varenicline vs. 51% on placebo), but at baseline, no patients in the varenicline group reported suicidal behavior and/or ideation vs. one patient in the placebo group (2%). Suicidal behavior and/or ideation were reported in 11% of the varenicline-treated and 9% of the placebo-treated patients during the treatment phase. During the post-treatment phase, suicidal behavior and/or ideation were reported in 11% of patients in the varenicline group and 5% of patients in the placebo group. Many of the patients reporting suicidal behavior and ideation in the follow-up phase had not reported such experiences in the treatment phase. However, no new suicidal ideation or behavior emerged in either treatment group shortly (within one week) after treatment discontinuation (a phenomenon noted in post-marketing reporting). There were no completed suicides. There was one suicide attempt in a varenicline-treated patient. The limited data available from this single smoking cessation study are not sufficient to allow conclusions to be drawn.



 In the trial of patients with major depressive disorder, the most common adverse events (&gt;= 10%) in subjects taking varenicline were nausea (27% vs. 10% on placebo), headache (17 vs 11%), abnormal dreams (11% vs 8%), insomnia (11% vs 5%) and irritability (11% vs. 8%). Additionally, the following psychiatric AEs were reported in &gt;= 2% of patients in either treatment group (varenicline or placebo, respectively): anxiety (7% vs. 9%), agitation (7% vs. 4%), depressed mood disorders and disturbances (11% vs. 9%), tension (4% vs. 3%), hostility (2% vs. 0.4%) and restlessness (2% vs. 2%). Patients treated with varenicline were more likely than patients treated with placebo to report one of various events related to hostility and aggression (3% vs 1%). Psychiatric scales showed no differences between the varenicline and placebo groups and no overall worsening of depression during the study in either treatment group. The percentage of subjects with suicidal ideation and/or behavior was similar between the varenicline and placebo groups during treatment (6% and 8%, respectively) and the non-treatment follow-up (6% and 6%, respectively). There was one event of intentional self-injury/possible suicide attempt during treatment (Day 73) in a subject in the placebo group. Suicide could not be ruled out in one subject who died by an overdose of illicit drugs 76 days after last dose of study drug in the varenicline group.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been reported during post-approval use of CHANTIX. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 There have been reports of depression, mania, psychosis, hallucinations, paranoia, delusions, homicidal ideation, aggression, hostility, anxiety, and panic, as well as suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide in patients attempting to quit smoking while taking CHANTIX  [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . Smoking cessation with or without treatment is associated with nicotine withdrawal symptoms and the exacerbation of underlying psychiatric illness. Not all patients had known pre-existing psychiatric illness and not all had discontinued smoking.



 There have been post-marketing reports of new or worsening seizures in patients treated with CHANTIX  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  



 There have been post-marketing reports of patients experiencing increased intoxicating effects of alcohol while taking CHANTIX. Some reported neuropsychiatric events, including unusual and sometimes aggressive behavior  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  and (  5.3  )]  .



 There have been reports of hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  .



 There have also been reports of serious skin reactions, including Stevens- Johnson Syndrome and erythema multiforme, in patients taking CHANTIX  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ].  



 There have been reports of myocardial infarction (MI) and cerebrovascular accident (CVA) including ischemic and hemorrhagic events in patients taking CHANTIX. In the majority of the reported cases, patients had pre-existing cardiovascular disease and/or other risk factors. Although smoking is a risk factor for MI and CVA, based on temporal relationship between medication use and events, a contributory role of varenicline cannot be ruled out.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SERIOUS NEUROPSYCHIATRIC EVENTS

    WARNING: SERIOUS NEUROPSYCHIATRIC EVENTS  

      Serious neuropsychiatric events including, but not limited to, depression, suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide have been reported in patients taking CHANTIX. Some reported cases may have been complicated by the symptoms of nicotine withdrawal in patients who stopped smoking.  Depressed mood may be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. Depression, rarely including suicidal ideation, has been reported in smokers undergoing a smoking cessation attempt without medication.  However, some of these symptoms have occurred in patients taking CHANTIX who continued to smoke.   



   All patients being treated with CHANTIX should be observed for neuropsychiatric symptoms including changes in behavior, hostility, agitation, depressed mood, and suicide-related events, including ideation, behavior, and attempted suicide. These symptoms, as well as worsening of pre-existing psychiatric illness and completed suicide, have been reported in some patients attempting to quit smoking while taking CHANTIX in the postmarketing experience.  When symptoms were reported, most were during CHANTIX treatment, but some were following discontinuation of CHANTIX therapy.    



   These events have occurred in patients with and without pre-existing psychiatric disease. Patients with serious psychiatric illness such as schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, and major depressive disorder did not participate in the premarketing studies of CHANTIX.   



     Advise patients and caregivers that the patient should stop taking CHANTIX and contact a healthcare provider immediately if agitation, hostility, depressed mood, or changes in behavior or thinking that are not typical for the patient are observed, or if the patient develops suicidal ideation or suicidal behavior.  In many postmarketing cases, resolution of symptoms after discontinuation of CHANTIX was reported, although in some cases the symptoms persisted; therefore, ongoing monitoring and supportive care should be provided until symptoms resolve.    



     The risks of CHANTIX should be weighed against the benefits of its use. CHANTIX has been demonstrated to increase the likelihood of abstinence from smoking for as long as one year compared to treatment with placebo. The health benefits of quitting smoking are immediate and substantial.   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   and   Adverse Reactions  (6.2)  ]    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SERIOUS NEUROPSYCHIATRIC EVENTS



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Serious neuropsychiatric events have been reported in patients taking CHANTIX. (5.1 and 6.2) 
 *  Advise patients and caregivers that the patient should stop taking CHANTIX and contact a healthcare provider immediately if agitation, hostility, depressed mood, or changes in behavior or thinking that are not typical for the patient are observed, or if the patient develops suicidal ideation or suicidal behavior while taking CHANTIX or shortly after discontinuing CHANTIX. (5.1 and 6.2) 
 *  Weigh the risks of CHANTIX against benefits of its use. CHANTIX has been demonstrated to increase the likelihood of abstinence from smoking for as long as one year compared to treatment with placebo. The health benefits of quitting smoking are immediate and substantial. (5.1 and 6.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Seizures: New or worsening seizures have been observed in patients taking CHANTIX. CHANTIX should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or other factors that can lower the seizure threshold. (  5.2  ) 
 *     Interaction with alcohol: Increased effects of alcohol have been reported. Instruct patients to reduce the amount of alcohol they consume until they know whether CHANTIX affects them. (  5.3  ) 
 *     Accidental injury: Accidental injuries (e.g., traffic accidents) have been reported. Instruct patients to use caution driving or operating machinery until they know how CHANTIX may affect them. (  5.4  ) 
 *     Cardiovascular events: A meta-analysis of 15 clinical trials, including a trial in patients with stable cardiovascular disease, demonstrated that while cardiovascular events were infrequent overall, some were reported more frequently in patients treated with CHANTIX. These events occurred primarily in patients with known cardiovascular disease. In both the clinical trial and meta-analysis, all-cause and cardiovascular mortality was lower in patients treated with CHANTIX. Instruct patients to notify their health care providers of new or worsening cardiovascular symptoms and to seek immediate medical attention if they experience signs and symptoms of myocardial infarction or stroke. (  5.5  and  6.1  ) 
 *     Angioedema and hypersensitivity reactions: Such reactions, including angioedema, infrequently life threatening, have been reported. Instruct patients to discontinue CHANTIX and immediately seek medical care if symptoms occur. (  5.6  and  6.2  ) 
 *     Serious skin reactions: Rare, potentially life-threatening skin reactions have been reported. Instruct patients to discontinue CHANTIX and contact a healthcare provider immediately at first appearance of skin rash with mucosal lesions. (  5.7  and  6.2)   
 *     Nausea: Nausea is the most common adverse reaction (up to 30% incidence rate). Dose reduction may be helpful. (  5.8)   
    
 

   5.1 Neuropsychiatric Symptoms and Suicidality



  Serious neuropsychiatric symptoms have been reported in patients being treated with CHANTIX [see  Boxed Warning  and  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . These postmarketing reports have included changes in mood (including depression and mania), psychosis, hallucinations, paranoia, delusions, homicidal ideation, hostility, agitation, anxiety, and panic, as well as suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide. Some reported cases may have been complicated by the symptoms of nicotine withdrawal in patients who stopped smoking. Depressed mood may be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. Depression, rarely including suicidal ideation, has been reported in smokers undergoing a smoking cessation attempt without medication. However, some of these symptoms have occurred in patients taking CHANTIX who continued to smoke. When symptoms were reported, most were during CHANTIX treatment, but some were following discontinuation of CHANTIX therapy.



  These events have occurred in patients with and without pre-existing psychiatric disease; some patients have experienced worsening of their psychiatric illnesses. All patients being treated with CHANTIX should be observed for neuropsychiatric symptoms or worsening of pre-existing psychiatric illness. Patients with serious psychiatric illness such as schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, and major depressive disorder did not participate in the premarketing studies of CHANTIX. Limited safety data are available from post-marketing smoking cessation studies in two patient groups: 1) patients with major depressive disorder, and 2) patients with stable schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder [see       Adverse Reactions (6.1)   ,    Clinical Studies (14.5)   ]     .  



  Some reported neuropsychiatric events, including unusual and sometimes aggressive behavior directed to oneself or others, may have been worsened by concomitant use of alcohol [see       Interaction with Alcohol (5.3)   ,    Adverse Reactions (6.2)   ]     .  



 Advise patients and caregivers that the patient should stop taking CHANTIX and contact a healthcare provider immediately if agitation, depressed mood, changes in behavior or thinking that are not typical for the patient are observed, or if the patient develops suicidal ideation or suicidal behavior. In many postmarketing cases, resolution of symptoms after discontinuation of CHANTIX was reported, although in some cases the symptoms persisted, therefore, ongoing monitoring and supportive care should be provided until symptoms resolve.



 The risks of CHANTIX should be weighed against the benefits of its use. CHANTIX has been demonstrated to increase the likelihood of abstinence from smoking for as long as one year compared to treatment with placebo. The health benefits of quitting smoking are immediate and substantial.



 *     Since the initial signal of neuropsychiatric symptoms and suicidality emerged, additional analyses and studies have been conducted to further evaluate this association. 
   *      Analyses of clinical trials  
 *     A meta-analysis of 5 randomized, double blind, placebo controlled trials, including 1907 patients (1130 CHANTIX, 777 placebo) was conducted to assess suicidal ideation and behavior as reported on the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C SSRS). This meta-analysis included one trial (N=127) in patients with a history of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder and another trial (N=525) in patients with a history of depression. The results showed no increase in the incidence of suicidal ideation and/or behavior in patients treated with CHANTIX compared to patients treated with placebo, with a Risk Ratio (RR) of 0.79 (95% Confidence Interval [CI]: 0.46, 1.36), as shown in Table 1. Forty-eight (48) of the 55 patients who reported suicidal ideation or behavior (24 CHANTIX, 24 placebo) were observed in the two trials that enrolled patients with a history of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, or depression. Few events were observed in the other three trials (4 CHANTIX, 3 placebo). 
   Table 1. Number of Patients and Risk Ratio for Suicidal Ideation and/or Behavior Reported on C-SSRS from a Meta-Analysis of 5 Clinical Trials Comparing CHANTIX to Placebo 
                                              CHANTIX   (N=1130)       Placebo   (N=777)       
  
  Patients with Suicidal ideation and/or behaviorOf the events, one patient in each treatment arm reported suicidal behavior [n (%)]Patients with events up to 30 days after treatment; % are not weighted by study    28 (2.5)                 27 (3.5)                
  Patient-years of exposure                   325                      217                     
  Risk Ratio # RR of incidence rates per 100 patient years (RR; 95% CI)    0.79 (0.46, 1.36)        
            A pooled analysis of 18 double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trials, which includes the 5 trials that collected C-SSRS described in Table 1, was conducted to assess the psychiatric safety of CHANTIX. This pooled analysis included 8521 patients (5072 CHANTIX, 3449 placebo), some of whom had psychiatric conditions at baseline. Table 2 describes the most frequently (&gt;= 1%) reported adverse events related to psychiatric safety. The results showed a similar incidence of common psychiatric events in patients treated with CHANTIX compared to patients treated with placebo.  
 

 Table 2. Psychiatric Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;= 1% of Patients from Pooled Analysis of 18 Clinical Trials 
                                              CHANTIX   (N=5072)      Placebo   (N=3449)      
  
  Anxiety disorders and symptoms              253 (5.0)               206 (6.0)               
  Depressed mood disorders and disturbances    179 (3.5)               108 (3.1)               
  Mood disorders and disturbances NECNEC = Not Elsewhere ClassifiedCounts (percentages) corresponds to the number of patients reporting the event    116 (2.3)               53 (1.5)                
             Observational Studies    
 

  Four observational studies, each including 10,000 to 30,000 users of CHANTIX in the adjusted analyses, compared the risk of selected serious neuropsychiatric events (neuropsychiatric hospitalizations, fatal and non-fatal self-harm), between CHANTIX users and prescription NRT or bupropion users. All studies were retrospective cohort studies and included patients with and without a psychiatric history.  



  Two of the studies found no difference in risk of neuropsychiatric hospitalizations between CHANTIX users and nicotine patch users (Hazard Ratio [HR] 1.14; 95% Confidence Interval [CI]: 0.56-2.34 in the first study, and 0.76; 95% CI: 0.40-1.46 in the second study). However, neither study validated the diagnostic codes used to identify outcomes against medical records. A third study reported no difference in risk of psychiatric adverse events diagnosed during an emergency department visit or inpatient admission between CHANTIX users and bupropion users (HR 0.85; 95% CI: 0.55-1.30). Bupropion has also been associated with neuropsychiatric adverse events. A fourth study examined risk of fatal and non-fatal self-harm in users of CHANTIX compared to users of NRT. Although the occurrence of detected suicide was rare during the three months after patients initiated any drug treatment (two cases in 31,260 CHANTIX users and six cases in 81,545 NRT users), this study has important limitations. Most importantly, these data were captured following public awareness of reports of neuropsychiatric adverse events in CHANTIX users. CHANTIX users had fewer comorbid conditions that could put them at risk for neuropsychiatric adverse events, suggesting that patients with a history of neuropsychiatric illness were preferentially prescribed NRT, and healthier patients were preferentially prescribed CHANTIX.  



  Outcomes examined in these studies did not include the full range of neuropsychiatric adverse events that have been reported.  



    5.2 Seizures



   During clinical trials and the post-marketing experience, there have been reports of seizures in patients treated with CHANTIX. Some patients had no history of seizures, whereas others had a history of seizure disorder that was remote or well-controlled. In most cases, the seizure occurred within the first month of therapy. Weigh this potential risk against the potential benefits before prescribing CHANTIX in patients with a history of seizures or other factors that can lower the seizure threshold. Advise patients to discontinue CHANTIX and contact a healthcare provider immediately if they experience a seizure while on treatment [see       Adverse Reactions (6.2)   ].    



    5.3 Interaction with Alcohol



   There have been post-marketing reports of patients experiencing increased intoxicating effects of alcohol while taking CHANTIX. Some cases described unusual and sometimes aggressive behavior, and were often accompanied by amnesia for the events. Advise patients to reduce the amount of alcohol they consume while taking CHANTIX until they know whether CHANTIX affects their tolerance for alcohol [see       Adverse Reactions (6.2)   ]     .  



    5.4 Accidental Injury



  There have been postmarketing reports of traffic accidents, near-miss incidents in traffic, or other accidental injuries in patients taking CHANTIX. In some cases, the patients reported somnolence, dizziness, loss of consciousness or difficulty concentrating that resulted in impairment, or concern about potential impairment, in driving or operating machinery. Advise patients to use caution driving or operating machinery or engaging in other potentially hazardous activities until they know how CHANTIX may affect them.



    5.5 Cardiovascular Events



  In a placebo-controlled clinical trial of CHANTIX administered to patients with stable cardiovascular disease, with approximately 350 patients per treatment arm, all-cause and cardiovascular mortality was lower in patients treated with CHANTIX, but certain nonfatal cardiovascular events occurred more frequently in patients treated with CHANTIX than in patients treated with placebo [see  Clinical Trials Experience (6.1)  ]  . Table 3 below shows the incidence of deaths and of selected nonfatal serious cardiovascular events occurring more frequently in the CHANTIX arm compared to the placebo arm. These events were adjudicated by an independent blinded committee. Nonfatal serious cardiovascular events not listed occurred at the same incidence or more commonly in the placebo arm. Patients with more than one cardiovascular event of the same type are counted only once per row. Some of the patients requiring coronary revascularization underwent the procedure as part of management of nonfatal MI and hospitalization for angina.



 Table 3. Mortality and Adjudicated Nonfatal Serious Cardiovascular Events in the Placebo-Controlled CHANTIX Trial in Patients with Stable Cardiovascular Disease 
  Mortality and Cardiovascular Events                 CHANTIX   (N=353)   n (%)     Placebo   (N=350)   n (%)     
  
  Mortality (Cardiovascular &amp; All-cause up to 52 wks)                                            
    Cardiovascular death                              1 (0.3)             2 (0.6)             
    All-cause mortality                               2 (0.6)             5 (1.4)             
  Nonfatal Cardiovascular Events (rate on CHANTIX &gt; Placebo)                                            
    Up to 30 days after treatment                                                             
      Nonfatal myocardial infarction                  4 (1.1)             1 (0.3)             
      Nonfatal Stroke                                 2 (0.6)             0 (0)               
    Beyond 30 days after treatment &amp; up to 52 weeks                                            
      Nonfatal myocardial infarction                  3 (0.8)             2 (0.6)             
      Need for coronary revascularization             7 (2.0)             2 (0.6)             
      Hospitalization for angina pectoris             6 (1.7)             4 (1.1)             
      Transient ischemia attack                       1 (0.3)             0 (0)               
      New diagnosis of peripheral vascular disease (PVD) or admission for a PVD procedure    5 (1.4)             2 (0.6)             
         A meta-analysis of 15 clinical trials of &gt;= 12 weeks treatment duration, including 7002 patients (4190 CHANTIX, 2812 placebo), was conducted to systematically assess the cardiovascular safety of CHANTIX. The study in patients with stable cardiovascular disease described above was included in the meta-analysis. There were lower rates of all-cause mortality (CHANTIX 6 [0.14%]; placebo 7 [0.25%]) and cardiovascular mortality (CHANTIX 2 [0.05%]; placebo 2 [0.07%]) in the CHANTIX arms compared with the placebo arms in the meta-analysis.
 

 The key cardiovascular safety analysis included occurrence and timing of a composite endpoint of Major Adverse Cardiovascular Events (MACE), defined as cardiovascular death, nonfatal MI, and nonfatal stroke. These events included in the endpoint were adjudicated by a blinded, independent committee. Overall, a small number of MACE occurred in the trials included in the meta-analysis, as described in Table 4. These events occurred primarily in patients with known cardiovascular disease.



 Table 4. Number of MACE cases, Hazard Ratio and Rate Difference in a Meta-Analysis of 15 Clinical Trials Comparing CHANTIX to PlaceboIncludes MACE occurring up to 30 days post treatment. 
                                              CHANTIX   N=4190         Placebo   N=2812        
  
  MACE cases, n (%)                           13 (0.31%)               6 (0.21%)               
  Patient-years of exposure                   1316                     839                     
  Hazard Ratio (95% CI)                       
                                              1.95 (0.79, 4.82)                                
  Rate Difference per 1,000 patient-years (95% CI)    
                                              6.30 (-2.40, 15.10)                              
         The meta-analysis showed that exposure to CHANTIX resulted in a hazard ratio for MACE of 1.95 (95% confidence interval from 0.79 to 4.82) for patients up to 30 days after treatment; this is equivalent to an estimated increase of 6.3 MACE events per 1,000 patient-years of exposure. The meta-analysis showed higher rates of CV endpoints in patients on CHANTIX relative to placebo across different time frames and pre-specified sensitivity analyses, including various study groupings and CV outcomes. Although these findings were not statistically significant they were consistent. Because the number of events was small overall, the power for finding a statistically significant difference in a signal of this magnitude is low.
 

 CHANTIX was not studied in patients with unstable cardiovascular disease or cardiovascular events occurring within two months before screening. Patients should be advised to notify a health care provider of new or worsening symptoms of cardiovascular disease. The risks of CHANTIX should be weighed against the benefits of its use in smokers with cardiovascular disease. Smoking is an independent and major risk factor for cardiovascular disease. CHANTIX has been demonstrated to increase the likelihood of abstinence from smoking for as long as one year compared to treatment with placebo.



    5.6 Angioedema and Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema in patients treated with CHANTIX [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  , and  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . Clinical signs included swelling of the face, mouth (tongue, lips, and gums), extremities, and neck (throat and larynx). There were infrequent reports of life-threatening angioedema requiring emergent medical attention due to respiratory compromise. Instruct patients to discontinue CHANTIX and immediately seek medical care if they experience these symptoms.



    5.7 Serious Skin Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of rare but serious skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome and erythema multiforme, in patients using CHANTIX [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  As these skin reactions can be life-threatening, instruct patients to stop taking CHANTIX and contact a healthcare provider immediately at the first appearance of a skin rash with mucosal lesions or any other signs of hypersensitivity.



    5.8 Nausea



  Nausea was the most common adverse reaction reported with CHANTIX treatment. Nausea was generally described as mild or moderate and often transient; however, for some patients, it was persistent over several months. The incidence of nausea was dose-dependent. Initial dose-titration was beneficial in reducing the occurrence of nausea. For patients treated to the maximum recommended dose of 1 mg twice daily following initial dosage titration, the incidence of nausea was 30% compared with 10% in patients taking a comparable placebo regimen. In patients taking CHANTIX 0.5 mg twice daily following initial titration, the incidence was 16% compared with 11% for placebo. Approximately 3% of patients treated with CHANTIX 1 mg twice daily in studies involving 12 weeks of treatment discontinued treatment prematurely because of nausea. For patients with intolerable nausea, a dose reduction should be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
