<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cinryze" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The only serious adverse reaction observed in clinical studies of CINRYZE was cerebrovascular accident.



 The most common adverse reactions observed were headache, nausea, rash, and vomiting.



 Because CINRYZE is a therapeutic protein, there is potential for immunogenicity. Using a validated assay there was no evidence of antibody development following administration of CINRYZE. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of anti-C1 Esterase Inhibitor antibody positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibody development across products cannot be made.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions observed were headache, nausea, rash and vomiting. (  5.1  ,  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Shire Medical Information at 1-866-888-0660 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  



     Routine Prophylaxis  



 Twenty-four subjects were evaluated in the randomized, placebo-controlled, crossover, routine prophylaxis trial.



 There were no serious adverse reactions in the randomized, placebo-controlled, crossover, routine prophylaxis trial.



 Adverse reactions in the randomized, placebo-controlled, crossover, routine prophylaxis trial (n=24) that occurred in at least two subjects (&gt;=8%) receiving CINRYZE are given in the following table:



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions in the Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Crossover, Routine Prophylaxis Trial 
   Adverse Reaction                                        Number of    Adverse    Reactions      Number    of    Subjects    (N = 24)     
 Rash                                                    8                            5                   
 Headache                                                4                            4                   
 Pruritus                                                2                            2                   
 Vomiting                                                2                            2                   
         In an open-label follow-on trial, 146 patients received a median of 243.5 days of CINRYZE (maximum = 959 days).  The most common adverse reaction observed was headache. No patients were discontinued due to an adverse reaction.
 

 Adverse reactions in the open-label follow-on trial (n=146) that occurred in at least three subjects (&gt;=2%) receiving CINRYZE, are given in the following table:



 Table 3 Adverse Reactions in the Open-Label Follow-On Trial 
   Adverse Reaction                   Number (%) of Subjects    (N=146) with Adverse Reaction      Number (%) of Infusion Days    (N=11,435) with Adverse    Reaction     
 Headache                           28 (19)                            62 (0.5)                            
 Nausea                             26 (18)                            29 (0.3)                            
 Rash                               15 (10)                            30 (0.3)                            
 Vomiting                           15 (10)                            17 (0.1)                            
 Pyrexia                            7 (5)                              7 (&lt;0.1)                            
 Catheter Site Pain                 4 (3)                              5 (&lt;0.1)                            
 Dizziness                          3 (2)                              4 (&lt;0.1)                            
 Erythema                           3 (2)                              3 (&lt;0.1)                            
 Pruritus                           3 (2)                              4 (&lt;0.1)                            
         More than 14,000 doses of CINRYZE have been administered to over 260 different patients in all completed, controlled and open-label clinical studies. All patients who were evaluated were found negative for seroconversion to parvovirus B19, Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C and HIV.(See Section  5.3  Transmissible Infectious Agents)
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



 Postmarketing adverse reactions include local infusion site reactions (including inflammation or hematoma at the infusion site) and hypersensitivity.



 Postmarketing thromboembolic events have been reported, including catheter-related and deep venous thromboses, transient ischemic attack, and stroke.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions may occur. Have epinephrine immediately available for treatment of acute severe hypersensitivity reaction (  5.1  ). 
 *  Serious arterial and venous thromboembolic (TE) events have been reported at the recommended dose of C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) products, including CINRYZE, following administration in patients with HAE. Risk factors may include presence of an indwelling venous catheter/access device, prior history of thrombosis, underlying atherosclerosis, use of oral contraceptives, certain androgens, morbid obesity, and immobility. Benefits of CINRYZE for routine prophylaxis of HAE attacks should be weighed against the risks of TE events in patients with underlying risk factors. Monitor patients with known risk factors for TE events during and after CINRYZE administration. TE events have been reported following administration of a C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) product when used off-label at higher than labeled doses. (  5.2  ).
 
    

 item{CINRYZE is made from human plasma and may contain infectious agents e.g. viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent. (  5.3  ) 
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur. The signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity reactions may include the appearance of hives, urticaria, tightness of the chest, wheezing, hypotension and/or anaphylaxis experienced during or after injection of CINRYZE.



 Consider treatment methods carefully, because hypersensitivity reactions may have symptoms similar to HAE attacks.



 In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue CINRYZE infusion and institute appropriate treatment. Have epinephrine immediately available for treatment of acute severe hypersensitivity reaction. (See Patient Counseling Information [  17  ])  



    5.2 Thromboembolic Events



  Serious arterial and venous thromboembolic (TE) events have been reported at the recommended dose of C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) products, including CINRYZE, following administration in patients with HAE. Risk factors may include presence of an indwelling venous catheter/access device, prior history of thrombosis, underlying atherosclerosis, use of oral contraceptives, certain androgens, morbid obesity, and immobility. Benefits of CINRYZE for routine prophylaxis of HAE attacks should be weighed against the risks of TE events in patients with underlying risk factors. Monitor patients with known risk factors for TE events during and after CINRYZE administration.



 TE events have been reported following administration of a C1 Esterase Inhibitor (Human) product when used off-label at higher than labeled doses  2,3  . (see Section  13.2  Animal Toxicology and/or Pharmacology)  



 In an open-label trial further investigating the use of CINRYZE for prevention (n=146) of HAE attacks, 5 serious thromboembolic events (including myocardial infarction, deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism and 2 events of cerebrovascular accident) occurred. Subjects had underlying risk factors for thromboembolic events.



    5.3 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because CINRYZE is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g. viruses, and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent [11]. ALL infections thought by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by CINRYZE should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Shire Medical Information. [1-866-888-0660]. The physician should discuss the risks and benefits of this product with the patient, before prescribing or administering it to the patient. (See Patient Counseling Information [  17  ])  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
