<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cipro1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse drug reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of labeling:



 *    Tendon Effects [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Exacerbation of Myasthenia Gravis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    Other Serious and Sometimes Fatal Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    Hepatotoxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *    Serious Adverse Reactions with Concomitant Theophylline [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *    Central Nervous System Effects [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *     Clostridium difficile -Associated Diarrhea [see  Warnings and Precautions (    5.8  )]  
 *    Peripheral Neuropathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (    5.9  )]  
 *    Prolongation of the QT Interval [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.10  )]  
 *    Musculoskeletal Disorders in Pediatric Patients [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.11  )]  
 *    Photosensitivity/Phototoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (    5.13  )]  
 *    Development of Drug Resistant Bacteria [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.14  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions &gt;=1% were nausea, diarrhea, liver function tests abnormal, vomiting, and rash. (6)
 

 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-888-842-2937 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adult Patients

  During clinical investigations with oral and parenteral CIPRO, 49,038 patients received courses of the drug.



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions, from clinical trials of all formulations, all dosages, all drug-therapy durations, and for all indications of ciprofloxacin therapy were nausea (2.5%), diarrhea (1.6%), liver function tests abnormal (1.3%), vomiting (1%), and rash (1%).



 Table 6: Medically Important Adverse Reactions That Occurred In less than 1% of Ciprofloxacin Patients 
   System Organ Class                             Adverse Reactions                                       
  
  Body as a Whole                                Headache  Abdominal Pain/Discomfort  Pain                
  Cardiovascular                                 Syncope  Angina Pectoris  Myocardial Infarction  Cardiopulmonary Arrest  Tachycardia  Hypotension    
  Central Nervous System                         Restlessness  Dizziness  Insomnia  Nightmares  Hallucinations  Paranoia  Psychosis (toxic)  Manic Reaction  Irritability  Tremor  Ataxia  Seizures (including Status Epilepticus)  Malaise  Anorexia  Phobia  Depersonalization  Depression (potentially culminating in self-injurious behavior  (such as suicidal ideations/thoughts and attempted or completed suicide)  Paresthesia  Abnormal Gait  Migraine    
  Gastrointestinal                               Intestinal Perforation  Gastrointestinal Bleeding  Cholestatic Jaundice  Hepatitis  Pancreatitis    
  Hemic/Lymphatic                                Petechia                                                 
  Metabolic/Nutritional                          Hyperglycemia  Hypoglycemia                              
  Musculoskeletal                                Arthralgia  Joint Stiffness  Muscle Weakness             
  Renal/Urogenital                               Interstitial Nephritis  Renal Failure                    
  Respiratory                                    Dyspnea  Laryngeal Edema  Hemoptysis  Bronchospasm       
  Skin/Hypersensitivity                          Anaphylactic Reactions including life-threatening anaphylactic shock  Erythema Multiforme/Stevens-Johnson Syndrome  Exfoliative Dermatitis  Toxic Epidermal Necrolysis  Pruritus  Urticaria  Photosensitivity/Phototoxicity reaction  Flushing  Fever  Angioedema  Erythema Nodosum  Sweating    
  Special Senses                                 Blurred Vision  Disturbed Vision (chromatopsia and photopsia)  Decreased Visual Acuity  Diplopia  Tinnitus  Hearing Loss  Bad Taste    
        In randomized, double-blind controlled clinical trials comparing CIPRO tablets [500 mg two times daily (BID)] to cefuroxime axetil (250 mg-500 mg BID) and to clarithromycin (500 mg BID) in patients with respiratory tract infections, CIPRO demonstrated a CNS adverse reaction profile comparable to the control drugs.
 

   Pediatric Patients

  Short (6 weeks) and long term (1 year) musculoskeletal and neurological safety of oral/intravenous ciprofloxacin, was compared to a cephalosporin for treatment of cUTI or pyelonephritis in pediatric patients 1 to 17 years of age (mean age of 6 +/- 4 years) in an international multicenter trial. The duration of therapy was 10 to 21 days (mean duration of treatment was 11 days with a range of 1 to 88 days). A total of 335 ciprofloxacin- and 349 comparator-treated patients were enrolled.



 An Independent Pediatric Safety Committee (IPSC) reviewed all cases of musculoskeletal adverse reactions including abnormal gait or abnormal joint exam (baseline or treatment-emergent). Within 6 weeks of treatment initiation, the rates of musculoskeletal adverse reactions were 9.3% (31/335) in the ciprofloxacin-treated group versus 6% (21/349) in comparator-treated patients. All musculoskeletal adverse reactions occurring by 6 weeks resolved (clinical resolution of signs and symptoms), usually within 30 days of end of treatment. Radiological evaluations were not routinely used to confirm resolution of the adverse reactions. Ciprofloxacin-treated patients were more likely to report more than one adverse reaction and on more than one occasion compared to control patients. The rate of musculoskeletal adverse reactions was consistently higher in the ciprofloxacin group compared to the control group across all age subgroups. At the end of 1 year, the rate of these adverse reactions reported at any time during that period was 13.7% (46/335) in the ciprofloxacin-treated group versus 9.5% (33/349) in the comparator-treated patients (Table 7).



 Table 7: Musculoskeletal Adverse Reactions1 as Assessed by the IPSC 
                                                                          CIPRO                    
                                                                                    Comparator                
                                                          
                                              All Patients (within 6 weeks)               
                                                                                                                      31/335 (9.3%)             
                                                                                   21/349 (6%)                
                                                          
                                              95% Confidence Interval                     
                                                                                                                      (-0.8%, +7.2%)            
                                                        
                                              Age Group                                   
                                                                                            
                                              12 months &lt; 24 months                       
                                                                                                                      1/36 (2.8%)               
                                                                                   0/41                       
                                                          
                                              2 years &lt; 6 years                           
                                                                                                                      5/124 (4%)                
                                                                                   3/118 (2.5%)               
                                                          
                                              6 years &lt; 12 years                          
                                                                                                                      18/143 (12.6%)            
                                                                                   12/153 (7.8%)              
                                                          
                                              12 years to 17 years                        
                                                                                                                      7/32 (21.9%)              
                                                                                   6/37 (16.2 %)              
                                                          
                                               
                                              All Patients (within 1 year)                
                                                                                                                      46/335 (13.7%)            
                                                                                   33/349 (9.5%)              
                                                          
                                              95% Confidence Interval                     
                                                                                                                      (-0.6%, + 9.1%)           
                                                        
         The incidence rates of neurological adverse reactions within 6 weeks of treatment initiation were 3% (9/335) in the CIPRO group versus 2% (7/349) in the comparator group and included dizziness, nervousness, insomnia, and somnolence.
 

 In this trial, the overall incidence rates of adverse reactions within 6 weeks of treatment initiation were 41% (138/335) in the ciprofloxacin group versus 31% (109/349) in the comparator group. The most frequent adverse reactions were gastrointestinal: 15% (50/335) of ciprofloxacin patients compared to 9% (31/349) of comparator patients. Serious adverse reactions were seen in 7.5% (25/335) of ciprofloxacin-treated patients compared to 5.7% (20/349) of control patients. Discontinuation of drug due to an adverse reaction was observed in 3% (10/335) of ciprofloxacin-treated patients versus 1.4% (5/349) of comparator patients. Other adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of ciprofloxacin patients were diarrhea 4.8%, vomiting 4.8%, abdominal pain 3.3%, dyspepsia 2.7%, nausea 2.7%, fever 2.1%, asthma 1.8% and rash 1.8%.



 Short-term safety data for ciprofloxacin was also collected in a randomized, double-blind clinical trial for the treatment of acute pulmonary exacerbations in cystic fibrosis patients (ages 5-17 years). Sixty seven patients received CIPRO IV 10 mg/kg/dose every 8 hours for one week followed by CIPRO tablets 20 mg/kg/dose every 12 hours to complete 10-21 days treatment and 62 patients received the combination of ceftazidime intravenous 50 mg/kg/dose every 8 hours and tobramycin intravenous 3 mg/kg/dose every8 hours for a total of 10-21 days. Periodic musculoskeletal assessments were conducted by treatment-blinded examiners. Patients were followed for an average of 23 days after completing treatment (range 0-93 days). Musculoskeletal adverse reactions were reported in 22% of the patients in the ciprofloxacin group and 21% in the comparison group. Decreased range of motion was reported in 12% of the subjects in the ciprofloxacin group and 16% in the comparison group. Arthralgia was reported in 10% of the patients in the ciprofloxacin group and 11% in the comparison group. Other adverse reactions were similar in nature and frequency between treatment arms. The efficacy of CIPRO for the treatment of acute pulmonary exacerbations in pediatric cystic fibrosis patients has not been established.



 In addition to the adverse reactions reported in pediatric patients in clinical trials, it should be expected that adverse reactions reported in adults during clinical trials or postmarketing experience may also occur in pediatric patients.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported from worldwide marketing experience with fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure (Table 8).



 Table 8: Postmarketing Reports of Adverse Drug Reactions 
  System Organ Class                                  Adverse Reactions                                   
  Cardiovascular                                      QT prolongation  Torsade de Pointes  Vasculitis and ventricular arrhythmia    
  Central Nervous System                              Hypertonia  Myasthenia  Exacerbation of myasthenia gravis  Peripheral neuropathy  Polyneuropathy  Twitching    
  Eye Disorders                                       Nystagmus                                           
  Gastrointestinal                                    Pseudomembranous colitis                            
  Hemic/Lymphatic                                     Pancytopenia (life threatening or fatal outcome)  Methemoglobinemia    
  Hepatobiliary                                       Hepatic failure (including fatal cases)             
  Infections and Infestations                         Candidiasis (oral, gastrointestinal, vaginal)       
  Investigations                                      Prothrombin time prolongation or decrease  Cholesterol elevation (serum)  Potassium elevation (serum)    
  Musculoskeletal                                     Myalgia  Myoclonus  Tendinitis  Tendon rupture      
  Psychiatric Disorders                               Agitation  Confusion  Delirium                      
  Skin/Hypersensitivity                               Acute generalize exanthematous pustulosis (AGEP)  Fixed eruption  Serum sickness-like reaction    
  Special Senses                                      Anosmia  Hyperesthesia  Hypesthesia  Taste loss     
          6.3 Adverse Laboratory Changes
   Changes in laboratory parameters while on CIPRO are listed below:



 *     Hepatic -Elevations of ALT (SGPT), AST (SGOT), alkaline phosphatase, LDH, serum bilirubin. 
    Hematologic-Eosinophilia, leukopenia, decreased blood platelets, elevated blood platelets, pancytopenia.
 

 Renal-Elevations of serum creatinine, BUN, crystalluria, cylindruria, and hematuria have been reported.



 Other changes occurring were: elevation of serum gammaglutamyl transferase, elevation of serum amylase, reduction in blood glucose, elevated uric acid, decrease in hemoglobin, anemia, bleeding diathesis, increase in blood monocytes, and leukocytosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: TENDON EFFECTS and MYASTHENIA GRAVIS 

  WARNING: TENDON EFFECTS and MYASTHENIA GRAVIS 

    Fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO  (r)  , are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages. This risk is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart, or lung transplants   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   Fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO, may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. Avoid CIPRO in patients with known history of myasthenia gravis   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: TENDON EFFECTS and MYASTHENIA GRAVIS 



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO(r), are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages. This risk is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants. (5.1) 
 *  Fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO, may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. Avoid CIPRO in patients with known history of myasthenia gravis. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity and other serious reactions: Serious and sometimes fatal reactions may occur after first or subsequent doses. Discontinue at first sign of skin rash, jaundice or any sign of hypersensitivity. (  4.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
 *    Hepatotoxicity: Discontinue immediately if signs and symptoms of hepatitis occur. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Central nervous system effects, including convulsions, increased intracranial pressure (pseudotumor cerebri) and toxic psychosis have been reported. Caution should be taken in patients predisposed to seizures. (  5.7  ) 
 *     Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea: Evaluate if colitis occurs. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Peripheral neuropathy: Discontinue if symptoms occur in order to prevent irreversibility. (  5.9  ) 
 *    QT Prolongation: Prolongation of the QT interval and isolated cases of torsade de pointes have been reported. Avoid use in patients with known prolongation, those with hypokalemia, and with other drugs that prolong the QT interval. (  5.10  ,  7  ,  8.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Tendinopathy and Tendon Rupture



  Fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO, are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages. This adverse reaction most frequently involves the Achilles tendon, and rupture of the Achilles tendon may require surgical repair. Tendinitis and tendon rupture in the rotator cuff (the shoulder), the hand, the biceps, the thumb, and other tendon sites have also been reported. The risk of developing fluoroquinolone-associated tendinitis and tendon rupture is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants. Factors, in addition to age and corticosteroid use, that may independently increase the risk of tendon rupture include strenuous physical activity, renal failure, and previous tendon disorders such as rheumatoid arthritis. Tendinitis and tendon rupture have also occurred in patients taking fluoroquinolones who do not have the above risk factors. Inflammation and tendon rupture can occur, sometimes bilaterally, even within the first 48 hours, during or after completion of therapy; cases occurring up to several months after completion of therapy have been reported. CIPRO should be used with caution in patients with a history of tendon disorders. CIPRO should be discontinued if the patient experiences pain, swelling, inflammation or rupture of a tendon. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.2  ).]  



    5.2 Exacerbation of Myasthenia Gravis



  Fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO, have neuromuscular blocking activity and may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. Postmarketing serious adverse events, including deaths and requirement for ventilatory support, have been associated with fluoroquinolone use in persons with myasthenia gravis. Avoid CIPRO in patients with known history of myasthenia gravis. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.2  ).]  



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious and occasionally fatal hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions, some following the first dose, have been reported in patients receiving quinolone therapy, including CIPRO. Some reactions were accompanied by cardiovascular collapse, loss of consciousness, tingling, pharyngeal or facial edema, dyspnea, urticaria, and itching. Only a few patients had a history of hypersensitivity reactions. Serious anaphylactic reactions require immediate emergency treatment with epinephrine and other resuscitation measures, including oxygen, intravenous fluids, intravenous antihistamines, corticosteroids, pressor amines, and airway management, including intubation, as indicated. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ).]  



    5.4 Other Serious and Sometimes Fatal Reactions



  Other serious and sometimes fatal events, some due to hypersensitivity, and some due to uncertain etiology, have been reported in patients receiving therapy with quinolones, including CIPRO. These events may be severe and generally occur following the administration of multiple doses. Clinical manifestations may include one or more of the following:



 *    Fever, rash, or severe dermatologic reactions (for example, toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome); 
 *    Vasculitis; arthralgia; myalgia; serum sickness; 
 *    Allergic pneumonitis; 
 *    Interstitial nephritis; acute renal insufficiency or failure; 
 *    Hepatitis; jaundice; acute hepatic necrosis or failure; 
 *    Anemia, including hemolytic and aplastic; thrombocytopenia, including thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura; leukopenia; agranulocytosis; pancytopenia; and/or other hematologic abnormalities. 
    Discontinue CIPRO immediately at the first appearance of a skin rash, jaundice, or any other sign of hypersensitivity and supportive measures instituted [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ,  6.2  )].  
 

    5.5 Hepatotoxicity



  Cases of severe hepatotoxicity, including hepatic necrosis, life-threatening hepatic failure, and fatal events, have been reported with CIPRO. Acute liver injury is rapid in onset (range 1-39 days), and is often associated with hypersensitivity. The pattern of injury can be hepatocellular, cholestatic, or mixed. Most patients with fatal outcomes were older than 55 years old. In the event of any signs and symptoms of hepatitis (such as anorexia, jaundice, dark urine, pruritus, or tender abdomen), discontinue treatment immediately.



 There can be a temporary increase in transaminases, alkaline phosphatase, or cholestatic jaundice, especially in patients with previous liver damage, who are treated with CIPRO. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.2  ,  6.3  ).]  



    5.6 Serious Adverse Reactions with Concomitant Theophylline



  Serious and fatal reactions have been reported in patients receiving concurrent administration of CIPRO and theophylline. These reactions have included cardiac arrest, seizure, status epilepticus, and respiratory failure. Instances of nausea, vomiting, tremor, irritability, or palpitation have also occurred.



 Although similar serious adverse reactions have been reported in patients receiving theophylline alone, the possibility that these reactions may be potentiated by CIPRO cannot be eliminated. If concomitant use cannot be avoided, monitor serum levels of theophylline and adjust dosage as appropriate. [See Drug Interactions (  7  ).]  



    5.7 Central Nervous System Effects



  Convulsions, increased intracranial pressure (including pseudotumor cerebri), and toxic psychosis have been reported in patients receiving fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO. CIPRO may also cause central nervous system (CNS) events including: nervousness, agitation, insomnia, anxiety, nightmares, paranoia, dizziness, confusion, tremors, hallucinations, depression, and psychotic reactions have progressed to suicidal ideations/thoughts and self-injurious behavior such as attempted or completed suicide. These reactions may occur following the first dose. Advise patients receiving CIPRO to inform their healthcare provider immediately if these reactions occur, discontinue the drug, and institute appropriate care. CIPRO, like other fluoroquinolones, is known to trigger seizures or lower the seizure threshold. As with all fluoroquinolones, use CIPRO with caution in epileptic patients and patients with known or suspected CNS disorders that may predispose to seizures or lower the seizure threshold (for example, severe cerebral arteriosclerosis, previous history of convulsion, reduced cerebral blood flow, altered brain structure, or stroke), or in the presence of other risk factors that may predispose to seizures or lower the seizure threshold (for example, certain drug therapy, renal dysfunction). Use CIPRO when the benefits of treatment exceed the risks, since these patients are endangered because of possible undesirable CNS side effects. Cases of status epilepticus have been reported. If seizures occur, discontinue CIPRO. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ) and Drug Interactions (  7  ).]  



    5.8 Clostridium Difficile  -Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile (C. difficile)-  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including CIPRO, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile.  



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing isolates of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy.   CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibacterial use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial treatment of C. difficile  , and institute surgical evaluation as clinically indicated. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ).]  



    5.9 Peripheral Neuropathy



  Cases of sensory or sensorimotor axonal polyneuropathy affecting small and/or large axons resulting in paresthesias, hypoesthesias, dysesthesias and weakness have been reported in patients receiving fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO. Symptoms may occur soon after initiation of CIPRO and may be irreversible. Discontinue CIPRO immediately if the patient experiences symptoms of peripheral neuropathy including pain, burning, tingling, numbness, and/or weakness, or other alterations in sensations including light touch, pain, temperature, position sense and vibratory sensation, and/or motor strength in order to minimize the development of an irreversible condition. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ,  6.2  ).]  



    5.10 Prolongation of the QT Interval



  Some fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO, have been associated with prolongation of the QT interval on the electrocardiogram and cases of arrhythmia. Cases of torsade de pointes have been reported during postmarketing surveillance in patients receiving fluoroquinolones, including CIPRO. Avoid CIPRO in patients with known prolongation of the QT interval, risk factors for QT prolongation or torsade de pointes (for example, congenital long QT syndrome, uncorrected electrolyte imbalance, such as hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia and cardiac disease, such as heart failure, myocardial infarction, or bradycardia), and patients receiving Class IA antiarrhythmic agents (quinidine, procainamide), or Class III antiarrhythmic agents (amiodarone, sotalol), tricyclic antidepressants, macrolides, and antipsychotics. Elderly patients may also be more susceptible to drug-associated effects on the QT interval. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.2  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ).]  



    5.11 Musculoskeletal Disorders in Pediatric Patients and Arthropathic Effects in Animals



  CIPRO is indicated in pediatric patients (less than 18 years of age) only for cUTI, prevention of inhalational anthrax (post exposure), and plague [see Indications and Usage (  1.12  ,  1.13  ,  1.14  )]  . An increased incidence of adverse reactions compared to controls, including reactions related to joints and/or surrounding tissues, has been observed [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  .



 In pre-clinical studies, oral administration of CIPRO caused lameness in immature dogs. Histopathological examination of the weight-bearing joints of these dogs revealed permanent lesions of the cartilage. Related quinolone-class drugs also produce erosions of cartilage of weight-bearing joints and other signs of arthropathy in immature animals of various species. [See Use in Specific Populations (8.4) and Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.2  ).]  



    5.12 Crystalluria



  Crystals of ciprofloxacin have been observed rarely in the urine of human subjects but more frequently in the urine of laboratory animals, which is usually alkaline [see Nonclinical Toxicology (     13.2  )].  Crystalluria related to ciprofloxacin has been reported only rarely in humans because human urine is usually acidic. Avoid alkalinity of the urine in patients receiving CIPRO. Hydrate patients well to prevent the formation of highly concentrated urine [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .



    5.13 Photosensitivity/Phototoxicity



  Moderate to severe photosensitivity/phototoxicity reactions, the latter of which may manifest as exaggerated sunburn reactions (for example, burning, erythema, exudation, vesicles, blistering, edema) involving areas exposed to light (typically the face, "V" area of the neck, extensor surfaces of the forearms, dorsa of the hands), can be associated with the use of quinolones including CIPRO after sun or UV light exposure. Therefore, avoid excessive exposure to these sources of light. Discontinue CIPRO if phototoxicity occurs. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ).]  



    5.14 Development of Drug Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing CIPRO Tablets and CIPRO Oral Suspension in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.



    5.15 Potential Risks with Concomitant Use of Drugs Metabolized by Cytochrome P450 1A2 Enzymes



  CIPRO is an inhibitor of the hepatic CYP1A2 enzyme pathway. Co-administration of CIPRO and other drugs primarily metabolized by CYP1A2 (for example, theophylline, methylxanthines, caffeine, tizanidine, ropinirole, clozapine, olanzapine) results in increased plasma concentrations of the co-administered drug and could lead to clinically significant pharmacodynamic adverse reactions of the co-administered drug. [See Drug Interactions (  7  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  ).]  



    5.16 Interference with Timely Diagnosis of Syphilis



  CIPRO has not been shown to be effective in the treatment of syphilis. Antimicrobial agents used in high dose for short periods of time to treat gonorrhea may mask or delay the symptoms of incubating syphilis. Perform a serologic test for syphilis in all patients with gonorrhea at the time of diagnosis. Perform follow-up serologic test for syphilis three months after CIPRO treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
