<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cleocin1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinical Trials

  In clinical trials, 3 (0.5%) of 589 nonpregnant women who received treatment with CLEOCIN Vaginal Ovules discontinued therapy due to drug-related adverse events. Adverse events judged to have a reasonable possibility of having been caused by clindamycin phosphate vaginal suppositories were reported for 10.5% of patients. Events reported by 1% or more of patients receiving CLEOCIN Vaginal Ovules were as follows:



   Urogenital system  : Vulvovaginal disorder (3.4%), vaginal pain (1.9%), and vaginal moniliasis (1.5%).



   Body as a whole  : Fungal infection (1.0%).



 Other events reported by &lt;1% of patients included:



   Urogenital system  : Menstrual disorder, dysuria, pyelonephritis, vaginal discharge, and vaginitis/vaginal infection.



   Body as a whole  : Abdominal cramps, localized abdominal pain, fever, flank pain, generalized pain, headache, localized edema, and moniliasis.



   Digestive system  : Diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting.



   Skin  : Nonapplication-site pruritis, rash, application-site pain, and application-site pruritis.



   Other clindamycin formulations

  The overall systemic exposure to clindamycin from CLEOCIN Vaginal Ovules is substantially lower than the systemic exposure from therapeutic doses of oral clindamycin hydrochloride (two-fold to 20-fold lower) or parenteral clindamycin phosphate (40-fold to 50-fold lower). (See  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY  .) Although these lower levels of exposure are less likely to produce the common reactions seen with oral or parenteral clindamycin, the possibility of these and other reactions cannot be excluded.



 The following adverse reactions and altered laboratory tests have been reported with the  oral or parenteral  use of clindamycin and may also occur following administration of CLEOCIN Vaginal Ovules:



   Gastrointestinal  : Abdominal pain, esophagitis, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and pseudomembranous colitis. (See  WARNINGS  .)



   Hematopoietic  : Transient neutropenia (leukopenia), eosinophilia, agranulocytosis, and thrombocytopenia have been reported. No direct etiologic relationship to concurrent clindamycin therapy could be made in any of these reports.



   Hypersensitivity Reactions  : Maculopapular rash and urticaria have been observed during drug therapy. Generalized mild to moderate morbilliform-like skin rashes are the most frequently reported of all adverse reactions. Rare instances of erythema multiforme, some resembling Stevens-Johnson syndrome, have been associated with clindamycin. A few cases of anaphylactoid reactions have been reported. If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, the drug should be discontinued.



   Liver  : Jaundice and abnormalities in liver function tests have been observed during clindamycin therapy.



   Musculoskeletal  : Rare instances of polyarthritis have been reported.



   Renal  : Although no direct relationship of clindamycin to renal damage has been established, renal dysfunction as evidenced by azotemia, oliguria, and/or proteinuria has been observed in rare instances.



 There have been reports of pseudomembranous colits following the administration of clindamycin vaginal cream.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
