<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="clobetasol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions are burning/stinging, pruritus, edema, folliculitis, acne, dry skin, irritant dermatitis, alopecia, urticaria, skin atrophy and telangiectasia. (6.1)  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sandoz Inc. at 1-800-525-8747 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.In clinical trials with Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo, 0.05%, the following adverse reactions have been reported: headache, burning/stinging, pruritus, edema, folliculitis, acne, dry skin, irritant dermatitis, alopecia, urticaria, skin atrophy and telangiectasia.Table 1 summarizes selected adverse reactions that occurred in  at least  1% of subjects in the Phase 2 and 3 studies for scalp psoriasis.



 Table 1: Summary of Selected Adverse Reactions &gt;=1% by Body System 
 Body System                 Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo, 0.05%  N=558    Vehicle Shampoo  N=127     
 Skin and Appendages        49 (8.8%)                  28 (22.0%)                  
 Discomfort Skin            26 (4.7%)                  16 (12.6%)                  
 Pruritus                   3 (0.5%)                   9 (7.1%)                    
 Body As A Whole            33 (5.9%)                  12 (9.4%)                   
 Headache                   10 (1.8%)                  1 (0.8%)                    
      Systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids has produced reversible HPA axis suppression, manifestations of Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and glucosuria in some patients.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo, 0.05%.



 *   Endocrine disorders: Cushing's syndrome, Adrenal suppression 
 *   Eye: Eye pain, Vision blurred, Eye irritation 
 *   CNS: Dizziness 
 *   GI: Nausea 
 *   Skin: Erythema, Skin exfoliation, Rash, Skin irritation, Hair color changes, Allergic contact dermatitis, Pain of skin, Skin tightness 
 *   Other: Psoriasis (aggravation) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



       EXCERPT:   Clobetasol propionate is a highly potent topical corticosteroid that has been shown to suppress the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis at the lowest doses tested (5.1)Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia and unmasking of latent diabetes mellitus can also result from systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids. (5.1)Systemic absorption may require periodic evaluation for HPA axis suppression. Modify use if HPA axis suppression develops. (5.1)Children may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity from use of topical corticosteroids (5.1, 8.4)If irritation develops in the presence of dermatological infections, the use of an appropriate antifungal or antibacterial agent should be instituted. If a favorable response does not occur promptly, use of Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo should be discontinued until the infection has been adequately controlled (5.3)Local adverse reactions with topical corticosteroids may occur more frequently with the use of occlusive dressings and higher potency corticosteroids, including clobetasol propionate. These reactions include: folliculitis, acneiform eruptions, hypopigmentation, perioral dermatitis, allergic contact dermatitis, secondary infection, striae and miliaria. (5.4)
 

 



   5.1 Effects on the Endocrine System



   Clobetasol propionate is a highly potent topical corticosteroid that has been shown to suppress the HPA axis at the lowest doses tested.  Systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids can produce reversible hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis suppression with the potential for clinical glucocorticosteroid insufficiency. This may occur during treatment or upon withdrawal of the topical corticosteroid.The effect of Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo, 0.05% on HPA axis suppression was evaluated in one trial in adolescents 12 to 17 years of age. In this trial, 5 of 12 evaluable subjects developed suppression of their HPA axis following 4 weeks of treatment with Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo, 0.05% applied once daily for 15 minutes to a dry scalp before lathering and rinsing.Because of the potential for systemic absorption, use of topical corticosteroids may require that patients be periodically evaluated for HPA axis suppression. Factors that predispose a patient using a topical corticosteroid to HPA axis suppression include the use of more potent steroids, use over large surface areas, use over prolonged periods, use under occlusion, use on an altered skin barrier, and use in patients with liver failure.An adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) stimulation test may be helpful in evaluating patients for HPA axis suppression. If HPA axis suppression is documented, an attempt should be made to gradually withdraw the drug, to reduce the frequency of application, or to substitute a less potent steroid. Manifestations of adrenal insufficiency may require supplemental systemic corticosteroids. Recovery of HPA axis function is generally prompt and complete upon discontinuation of topical corticosteroids.Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and unmasking of latent diabetes mellitus can also result from systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids.Use of more than one corticosteroid-containing product at the same time may increase the total systemic exposure.Pediatric patients may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity from equivalent doses due to their larger skin surface to body mass ratios [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].
 

    5.2 Allergic Contact Dermatitis



  If irritation develops, Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo, 0.05%, should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted. Allergic contact dermatitis with corticosteroids is usually diagnosed by observing a failure to heal rather than noting a clinical exacerbation. Clinical diagnosis of allergic contact dermatitis can be confirmed with patch testing.



    5.3 Concomitant Skin Infections



  In the presence of dermatologic infections, the use of an appropriate antifungal or antibacterial agent should be instituted. If a favorable response does not occur promptly, use of Clobetasol Propionate Shampoo, 0.05%, should be discontinued until the infection has been adequately controlled.



    5.4 Local Adverse Reactions with Topical Corticosteroids



   Local adverse reactions may be more likely to occur with occlusive use, prolonged use or use of higher potency corticosteroids.  Reactions may include atrophy, striae, telangiectasias, burning, itching, irritation, dryness, folliculitis, acneiform eruptions, hypopigmentation, perioral dermatitis, allergic contact dermatitis, secondary infection, and miliaria. Some local adverse reactions may be irreversible. Clobetasol propionate is not recommended in patients with acne vulgaris, rosacea or perioral dermatitis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
