<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="clolar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Myelosuppression [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Hemorrhage [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Serious Infections [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Hyperuricemia (Tumor Lysis) [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Systemic Inflammatory Response Syndrome (SIRS) and Capillary Leak Syndrome [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Venous Occlusive Disease of the Liver [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Hepatotoxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *  Renal Toxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *  Enterocolitis [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *  Skin Reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 10%): nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, febrile neutropenia, headache, rash, pruritus, pyrexia, fatigue, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome, anxiety, flushing, and mucosal inflammation. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genzyme Corporation at 1-800-RX-CLOLAR or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to Clolar in 115 pediatric patients with relapsed or refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) (70 patients) or Acute Myelogenous Leukemia (AML) (45 patients).



 In total, 115 pediatric patients treated in clinical trials received the recommended dose of Clolar 52 mg/m  2  daily * 5. The median number of cycles was 2. The median cumulative amount of Clolar received by pediatric patients during all cycles was 540 mg.



 The most common adverse reactions occurring in 10% or more of patients treated with Clolar are: nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, febrile neutropenia, headache, rash, pruritus, pyrexia, fatigue, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome, anxiety, flushing, and mucosal inflammation.



 Table 1 lists adverse reactions by System Organ Class, including severe or life-threatening (NCI CTC Grade 3 or Grade 4), reported in &gt;= 5% of the 115 patients in the 52 mg/m  2  /day dose group (pooled analysis of pediatric patients with ALL and AML). More detailed information and follow-up of certain events is given below.



 Table 1: Most Commonly Reported (&gt;= 5% Overall) Adverse Reactions by System Organ Class (N=115 pooled analysis) 
                                                                         Worst NCI Common Terminology Criteria Grade   
                                                       ALL/AML (N=115)     3        4       5      
 System Organ Class         Preferred Term               N        %        N       %       N       %       N       %      
  
 Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  Febrile neutropenia          63       55       59      51      3       3       .       .      
 Neutropenia                11                           10       3        3       8       7       .       .      
 Cardiac Disorders          Pericardial effusion         9        8        .       .       1       1       .       .      
 Tachycardia                40                           35       6        5       .       .       .       .      
 Gastrointestinal Disorders  Abdominal pain               40       35       8       7       .       .       .       .      
 Abdominal pain upper       9                            8        1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Diarrhea                   64                           56       14       12      .       .       .       .      
 Gingival or mouth bleeding  20                           17       8        7       1       1       .       .      
 Nausea                     84                           73       16       14      1       1       .       .      
 Oral mucosal petechiae     6                            5        4        4       .       .       .       .      
 Proctalgia                 9                            8        2        2       .       .       .       .      
 Stomatitis                 8                            7        1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Vomiting                   90                           78       9        8       1       1       .       .      
 General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  Asthenia                     12       10       1       1       1       1       .       .      
 Chills                     39                           34       3        3       .       .       .       .      
 Fatigue                    39                           34       3        3       2       2       .       .      
 Irritability               11                           10       1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Mucosal inflammation       18                           16       2        2       .       .       .       .      
 Edema                      14                           12       2        2       .       .       .       .      
 Pain                       17                           15       7        6       1       1       .       .      
 Pyrexia                    45                           39       16       14      .       .       .       .      
 Hepatobiliary Disorder     Jaundice                     9        8        2       2       .       .       .       .      
 Infections and Infestations  Bacteremia                   10       9        10      9       .       .       .       .      
 Candidiasis                8                            7        1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Catheter related infection  14                           12       13       11      .       .       .       .      
 Cellulitis                 9                            8        7        6       .       .       .       .      
 Clostridium colitis        8                            7        6        5       .       .       .       .      
 Herpes simplex             11                           10       6        5       .       .       .       .      
 Herpes zoster              8                            7        6        5       .       .       .       .      
 Oral candidiasis           13                           11       2        2       .       .       .       .      
 Pneumonia                  11                           10       6        5       1       1       1       1      
 Sepsis, including septic shock  19                           17       6        5       4       4       9       8      
 Staphylococcal bacteremia  7                            6        5        4       1       1       .       .      
 Staphylococcal sepsis      6                            5        5        4       1       1       .       .      
 Upper respiratory tract infection  6                            5        1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  Anorexia                     34       30       6       5       8       7       .       .      
 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  Arthralgia                   10       9        3       3       .       .       .       .      
 Back pain                  12                           10       3        3       .       .       .       .      
 Bone pain                  11                           10       3        3       .       .       .       .      
 Myalgia                    16                           14       .        .       .       .       .       .      
 Pain in extremity          34                           30       6        5       .       .       .       .      
 Neoplasms Benign, Malignant and Unspecified (incl. cysts and polyps)  Tumor lysis syndrome         7        6        7       6       .       .       .       .      
 Nervous System Disorders   Headache                     49       43       6       5       .       .       .       .      
 Lethargy                   12                           10       1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Somnolence                 11                           10       1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Psychiatric Disorders      Agitation                    6        5        1       1       .       .       .       .      
 Anxiety                    24                           21       2        2       .       .       .       .      
 Renal and Urinary Disorders  Hematuria                    15       13       2       2       .       .       .       .      
 Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  Dyspnea                      15       13       6       5       2       2       .       .      
 Epistaxis                  31                           27       15       13      .       .       .       .      
 Pleural effusion           14                           12       4        4       2       2       .       .      
 Respiratory distress       12                           10       5        4       4       4       1       1      
 Tachypnea                  10                           9        4        4       1       1       .       .      
 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  Erythema                     13       11       .       .       .       .       .       .      
 Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome  18                           16       8        7       .       .       .       .      
 Petechiae                  30                           26       7        6       .       .       .       .      
 Pruritus                   49                           43       1        1       .       .       .       .      
 Rash                       44                           38       8        7       .       .       .       .      
 Rash pruritic              9                            8        .        .       .       .       .       .      
 Vascular Disorders         Flushing                     22       19       .       .       .       .       .       .      
 Hypertension               15                           13       6        5       .       .       .       .      
 Hypotension                33                           29       13       11      9       8       .       .      
                  The following less common adverse reactions have been reported in 1-4% of the 115 pediatric patients with ALL or AML:
 

   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  cecitis, pancreatitis



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  hyperbilirubinemia



   Immune System Disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Infections and Infestations:  bacterial infection, Enterococcal bacteremia, Escherichia bacteremia, Escherichia sepsis, fungal infection, fungal sepsis, gastroenteritis adenovirus, infection, influenza, parainfluenza virus infection, pneumonia fungal, pneumonia primary atypical, Respiratory syncytial virus infection, sinusitis, staphylococcal infection



   Investigations:  blood creatinine increased



   Psychiatric Disorders:  mental status change



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorder:  pulmonary edema



 Table 2 lists the incidence of treatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities after Clolar administration at 52 mg/m  2  among pediatric patients with ALL and AML (N=115).



 Table 2: Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Laboratory Abnormalities after Clolar Administration 
 Parameter                                                     Any Grade            Grade 3 or higher       
  
 Anemia (N=114)                                                   83%                      75%              
 Leukopenia (N=114)                                               88%                      88%              
 Lymphopenia (N=113)                                              82%                      82%              
 Neutropenia (N=113)                                              64%                      64%              
 Thrombocytopenia (N=114)                                         81%                      80%              
 Elevated Creatinine (N=115)                                      50%                      8%               
 Elevated SGOT (N=100)                                            74%                      36%              
 Elevated SGPT (N=113)                                            81%                      43%              
 Elevated Total Bilirubin (N=114)                                 45%                      13%              
           6.2 Post-marketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Clolar. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) reported frequency of the reaction, or (3) strength of causal connection to Clolar.



 *  Gastrointestinal disorders: Gastrointestinal hemorrhage including fatalities. 
 *  Metabolism and nutrition disorders: hyponatremia 
 *  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders: Occurrences of Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), including fatal cases, have been reported in patients who were receiving or had recently been treated with Clolar and other medications (e.g., allopurinol or antibiotics) known to cause these syndromes. Other exfoliative conditions have also been reported. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Myelosuppression: May be severe and prolonged. Monitor complete blood counts and platelet counts during Clolar therapy. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hemorrhage: Serious and fatal cerebral, gastrointestinal and pulmonary hemorrhage. Monitor platelets and coagulation parameters and treat accordingly. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Infections: Severe and fatal sepsis as a result of bone marrow suppression. Monitor for signs and symptoms of infection; discontinue Clolar and treat promptly. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Tumor Lysis syndrome: Anticipate, monitor for signs and symptoms and treat promptly.  (5.4  ) 
 *  Systemic Inflammatory Response Syndrome (SIRS) or Capillary Leak Syndrome: Monitor for and discontinue Clolar immediately if suspected. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Venous Occlusive Disease of the Liver: Monitor for and discontinue Clolar if suspected. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Severe and fatal hepatotoxicity. Monitor liver enzymes and discontinue Clolar. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Renal Toxicity: Increased creatinine and acute renal failure; monitor renal function and interrupt or discontinue Clolar. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Enterocolitis: Serious and fatal enterocolitis, occurring more frequently within 30 days of treatment and with combination chemotherapy. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of enterocolitis and treat promptly (  5.9  ) 
 *  Skin Reactions: Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), including fatal cases. Discontinue for exfoliative or bullous rash, or if SJS or TEN is suspected. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myelosuppression



  Clolar causes myelosuppression which may be severe and prolonged. Febrile neutropenia occurred in 55% and non-febrile neutropenia in an additional 10% of pediatric patients in clinical trials. At initiation of treatment, most patients in the clinical studies had hematological impairment as a manifestation of leukemia. Myelosuppression is usually reversible with interruption of Clolar treatment and appears to be dose-dependent. Monitor complete blood counts [see   Dosage and Administration (2.3)    ].



    5.2 Hemorrhage



   Serious and fatal hemorrhage, including cerebral, gastrointestinal and pulmonary hemorrhage, has occurred. The majority of the cases were associated with thrombocytopenia. Monitor platelets and coagulation parameters and treat accordingly [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].  



    5.3 Infections



  Clolar increases the risk of infection, including severe and fatal sepsis, and opportunistic infections. At baseline, 48% of the pediatric patients had one or more concurrent infections. A total of 83% of patients experienced at least one infection after Clolar treatment, including fungal, viral and bacterial infections. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of infection, discontinue Clolar, and treat promptly.



    5.4 Hyperuricemia (Tumor Lysis)



  Administration of Clolar may result in tumor lysis syndrome associated with the break-down metabolic products from peripheral leukemia cell death. Monitor patients undergoing treatment for signs and symptoms of tumor lysis syndrome and initiate preventive measures including adequate intravenous fluids and measures to control uric acid.



    5.5 Systemic Inflammatory Response Syndrome (SIRS) and Capillary Leak Syndrome



  Clolar may cause a cytokine release syndrome (e.g., tachypnea, tachycardia, hypotension, pulmonary edema) that may progress to the systemic inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS) with capillary leak syndrome and organ impairment which may be fatal. Monitor patients frequently for these conditions. In clinical trials, SIRS was reported in two patients (2%); capillary leak syndrome was reported in four patients (4%). Symptoms included rapid onset of respiratory distress, hypotension, pleural and pericardial effusion, and multi-organ failure. Close monitoring for this syndrome and early intervention may reduce the risk. Immediately discontinue Clolar and provide appropriate supportive measures. The use of prophylactic steroids (e.g., 100 mg/m  2  hydrocortisone on Days 1 through 3) may be of benefit in preventing signs or symptoms of SIRS or capillary leak. Consider use of diuretics and/or albumin. After the patient is stabilized and organ function has returned to baseline, re-treatment with Clolar can be considered with a 25% dose reduction.



    5.6 Venous Occlusive Disease of the Liver



  Patients who have previously received a hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) are at higher risk for veno-occlusive disease (VOD) of the liver following treatment with clofarabine (40 mg/m  2  ) when used in combination with etoposide (100 mg/m  2  ) and cyclophosphamide (440 mg/m  2  ). Severe hepatotoxic events have been reported in a combination study of clofarabine in pediatric patients with relapsed or refractory acute leukemia. Two cases (2%) of VOD in the mono-therapy studies were considered related to study drug. Monitor for and discontinue Clolar if VOD is suspected.



    5.7 Hepatotoxicity



  Severe and fatal hepatotoxicity has occurred with the use of Clolar. In clinical studies, Grade 3-4 liver enzyme elevations were observed in pediatric patients during treatment with Clolar at the following rates: elevated aspartate aminotransferase (AST) occurred in 36% of patients; elevated alanine aminotransferase (ALT) occurred in 44% of patients. AST and ALT elevations typically occurred within 10 days of Clolar administration and returned to Grade 2 or less within 15 days. Grade 3 or 4 elevated bilirubin occurred in 13% of patients, with 2 events reported as Grade 4 hyperbilirubinemia (2%), one of which resulted in treatment discontinuation and one patient had multi-organ failure and died. Eight patients (7%) had Grade 3 or 4 elevations in serum bilirubin at the last time point measured; these patients died due to sepsis and/or multi-organ failure. Monitor hepatic function and discontinue Clolar for Grade 3 or greater liver enzyme elevations [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.8 Renal Toxicity



  In clinical studies, Grade 3 or 4 elevated creatinine occurred in 8% of patients; acute renal failure was reported as Grade 3 in three patients (3%) and Grade 4 in two patients (2%). Hematuria was observed in 13% of patients overall. Monitor patients for renal toxicity and interrupt or discontinue Clolar as necessary.



    5.9 Enterocolitis



   Fatal and serious cases of enterocolitis, including neutropenic colitis, cecitis, and C. difficile colitis, have occurred during treatment with clofarabine. This has occurred more frequently within 30 days of treatment, and in the setting of combination chemotherapy. Enterocolitis may lead to necrosis, perforation, hemorrhage or sepsis complications . Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of enterocolitis and treat promptly [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2  )  ].  



    5.10 Skin Reactions



   Serious and fatal cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have been reported. Discontinue Clofarabine for exfoliative or bullous rash, or if SJS or TEN is suspected [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].  



    5.11 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  Clolar can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Intravenous doses of clofarabine in rats and rabbits administered during organogenesis caused an increase in resorptions, malformations, and variations [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
