<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="clonidine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are described in greater detail elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Hypotension/bradycardia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Sedation and somnolence [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Rebound hypertension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Allergic reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence at least 5% and twice the rate of placebo) as monotherapy in ADHD : somnolence, fatigue, irritability, nightmare, insomnia, constipation, dry mouth. (  6.1  )
 

 Most common adverse reactions (incidence at least 5% and twice the rate of placebo) as adjunct therapy to psychostimulant in ADHD: somnolence, fatigue, decreased appetite, dizziness. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Prasco Laboratories at 1-866-525-0688 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6.1 Clinical Trial Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Two clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets ADHD clinical studies (Study 1, CLON-301 and Study 2, CLON-302) evaluated 256 patients in two 8-week placebo-controlled studies.



 A third clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets ADHD clinical study (Study 3, SHN-KAP-401) evaluated 135 children and adolescents in a 40-week placebo-controlled randomized-withdrawal study.



   Study 1: Fixed-dose Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets Monotherapy  



 Study 1 (CLON-301) was a short-term, multi-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of two fixed doses (0.2 mg/day or 0.4 mg/day) of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets in children and adolescents (6 to 17 years of age) who met DSM-IV criteria for ADHD hyperactive or combined inattentive/hyperactive subtypes.



   Most Common Adverse Reactions  (incidence of &gt;=5% and at least twice the rate of placebo): somnolence, fatigue, irritability, insomnia, nightmare, constipation, dry mouth.



   Adverse Events Leading to Discontinuation of Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets  - Five patients (7%) in the low dose group (0.2 mg), 15 patients (20%) in the high dose group (0.4 mg), and 1 patient in the placebo group (1%) reported adverse reactions that led to discontinuation. The most common adverse reactions that led to discontinuation were somnolence and fatigue.



 Commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence of &gt;=2% in either active treatment group and greater than the rate on placebo) during the treatment period are listed in Table 2.



 Table 2 Common Adverse Reactions in the Fixed-Dose Monotherapy Trial-Treatment Period (Study 1) 
                   Percentage of Patients Reporting Event    
  Preferred Term    Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets  0.2 mg/day  N=76    Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets0.4 mg/dayN=78    Placebo(N=76)    
  PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS    Somnolence Somnolence includes the terms "somnolence" and "sedation".    Nightmare    Emotional Disorder    Aggression    Tearfulness    Enuresis    Sleep Terror    Poor Quality Sleep    38%  4%  4%  3%  1%  0%  3%  0%    31%  9%  4%  1%  3%  4%  0%  3%    4%  0%  1%  0%  0%  0%  0%  1%    
  NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS    Headache    Insomnia    Tremor    Abnormal Sleep-Related Event    20%  5%  1%  3%    13%  6%  4%  1%    16%  1%  0%  0%    
  GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS    Upper Abdominal Pain    Nausea    Constipation    Dry Mouth    15%  4%  1%  0%    10%  5%  6%  5%    12%  3%  0%  1%    
  GENERAL DISORDERS    FatigueFatigue includes the terms "fatigue" and "lethargy".    Irritability       16%  9%          13%  5%          1%  4%        
  CARDIAC DISORDERS    Dizziness    Bradycardia       7%  0%           3%  4%           5%  0%        
  INVESTIGATIONS    Increased Heart Rate           0%               3%               0%          
  METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS    Decreased Appetite          3%               4%               4%          
      Commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence of &gt;2% in either active treatment group and greater than the rate on placebo) during the taper period are listed in Table 3.
 

 Table 3 Common Adverse Reactions in the Fixed-Dose Monotherapy Trial-Taper PeriodTaper Period: 0.2 mg dose, week 8; 0.4 mg dose, weeks 6-8; Placebo dose, weeks 6-8 (Study 1) 
                    Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Preferred Term      Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets    0.2 mg/day    N=76      Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets    0.4    mg/day    N=78      Placebo    (N=76)     
  Abdominal Pain Upper    0%               6%               3%               
 Headache          5%               2%               3%               
  Gastrointestinal Viral    0%               5%               0%               
 Somnolence        2%               3%               0%               
  Heart Rate Increased    0%               3%               0%               
  Otitis Media Acute    3%               0%               0%               
        Study 2: Flexible-dose Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets as Adjunctive Therapy to Psychostimulants  
 

 Study 2 (CLON-302) was a short-term, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of a flexible dose of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets as adjunctive therapy to a psychostimulant in children and adolescents (6 to 17 years) who met DSM-IV criteria for ADHD hyperactive or combined inattentive/hyperactive subtypes during which clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets were initiated at 0.1 mg/day and titrated up to 0.4 mg/day over a 3-week period. Most clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets treated patients (75.5%) were escalated to the maximum dose of 0.4 mg/day.



   Most Common Adverse Reactions  (incidence of &gt;=5% and at least twice the rate of placebo): somnolence, fatigue, decreased appetite, dizziness.



   Adverse Events Leading to Discontinuation -  There was one patient in the CLON+STM group (1%) who discontinued because of an adverse event (severe bradyphrenia, with severe fatigue).



 Commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence of &gt;=2% in the treatment group and greater than the rate on placebo) during the treatment period are listed in Table 4.



 Table 4 Common Adverse Reactions in the Flexible-Dose Adjunctive to Stimulant Therapy Trial-Treatment Period (Study 2) 
                   Percentage of Patients Reporting Event    
  Preferred Term    Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets+STM (N=102)    PBO+STM (N=96)    
  PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS     SomnolenceSomnolence includes the terms: "somnolence" and "sedation".    Aggression    Affect Lability    Emotional Disorder    19%  2%  2%  2%    7%  1%  1%  0%    
  GENERAL DISORDERS    FatigueFatigue includes the terms "fatigue" and "lethargy".    Irritability       14%  2%          4%  7%        
  NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS     Headache    Insomnia       7%  4%           12%  3%       
  GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS     Upper Abdominal Pain         7%               4%          
  RESPIRATORY DISORDERS    Nasal Congestion         2%               2%          
  METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS     Decreased Appetite         6%               3%          
  CARDIAC DISORDERS     Dizziness         5%               1%          
      Commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence of &gt;=2% in the treatment group and greater than the rate on placebo) during the taper period are listed in Table 5.
 

 Table 5 Common Adverse Reactions in the Flexible-Dose Adjunctive to Stimulant Therapy Trial- Taper PeriodTaper Period: weeks 6-8 (Study 2) 
                    Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Preferred Term      Clonidine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets+STM    (N=102)      PBO+STM    (N=96)     
  Nasal Congestion   4%               2%               
  Headache         3%               1%               
  Irritability     3%               2%               
  Throat Pain      3%               1%               
  Gastroenteritis Viral   2%               0%               
  Rash             2%               0%               
        Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  
 

 Thirteen percent (13%) of patients receiving clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets discontinued from the pediatric monotherapy study due to adverse events, compared to 1% in the placebo group. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets monotherapy treated patients were from somnolence/sedation (5%) and fatigue (4%).



   Effect on Blood Pressure and Heart Rate  



 In patients that completed 5 weeks of treatment in a controlled, fixed-dose monotherapy study in pediatric patients, during the treatment period the maximum placebo-subtracted mean change in systolic blood pressure was -4.0 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.2 mg/day and -8.8 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.4 mg/day. The maximum placebo-subtracted mean change in diastolic blood pressure was -4.0 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.2 mg/day and -7.3 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.4 mg/day. The maximum placebo-subtracted mean change in heart rate was -4.0 beats per minute on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.2 mg/day and -7.7 beats per minute on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.4 mg/day.



 During the taper period of the fixed-dose monotherapy study the maximum placebo-subtracted mean change in systolic blood pressure was +3.4 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.2 mg/day and -5.6 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.4 mg/day. The maximum placebo-subtracted mean change in diastolic blood pressure was +3.3 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.2 mg/day and -5.4 mmHg on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.4 mg/day. The maximum placebo-subtracted mean change in heart rate was -0.6 beats per minute on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.2 mg/day and -3.0 beats per minute on clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets 0.4 mg/day.



     6.2 Postmarketing Experience  

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events exclude those already mentioned in 6.1:



     Psychiatric:    hallucinations    Cardiovascular:    Q-T prolongation
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypotension/bradycardia/syncope: Titrate slowly and monitor vital signs frequently in patients at risk for hypotension, heart block, bradycardia, syncope, cardiovascular disease, vascular disease, cerebrovascular disease or chronic renal failure. Measure heart rate and blood pressure prior to initiation of therapy, following dose increases, and periodically while on therapy. Avoid concomitant use of drugs with additive effects unless clinically indicated. Advise patients to avoid becoming dehydrated or overheated. (  5.1  ) 
   *  Somnolence/Sedation: Has been observed with clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets. Consider the potential for additive sedative effects with CNS depressant drugs. Caution patients against operating heavy equipment or driving until they know how they respond to clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities: May worsen sinus node dysfunction and atrioventricular (AV) block, especially in patients taking other sympatholytic drugs. Titrate slowly and monitor vital signs frequently. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

    5.1 Hypotension/Bradycardia  



  Treatment with clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets can cause dose-related decreases in blood pressure and heart rate [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Measure heart rate and blood pressure prior to initiation of therapy, following dose increases, and periodically while on therapy. Titrate clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets slowly in patients with a history of hypotension, and those with underlying conditions that may be worsened by hypotension and bradycardia; e.g., heart block, bradycardia, cardiovascular disease, vascular disease, cerebrovascular disease, or chronic renal failure. In patients who have a history of syncope or may have a condition that predisposes them to syncope, such as hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, bradycardia, or dehydration, advise patients to avoid becoming dehydrated or overheated. Monitor blood pressure and heart rate, and adjust dosages accordingly in patients treated concomitantly with antihypertensives or other drugs that can reduce blood pressure or heart rate or increase the risk of syncope.



     5.2 Sedation and Somnolence  



  Somnolence and sedation were commonly reported adverse reactions in clinical studies. In patients that completed 5 weeks of therapy in a controlled, fixed dose pediatric monotherapy study, 31% of patients treated with 0.4 mg/day and 38% treated with 0.2 mg/day versus 4% of placebo treated patients reported somnolence as an adverse event. In patients that completed 5 weeks of therapy in a controlled flexible dose pediatric adjunctive to stimulants study, 19% of patients treated with clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets+stimulant versus 7% treated with placebo+stimulant reported somnolence. Before using clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets with other centrally active depressants (such as phenothiazines, barbiturates, or benzodiazepines), consider the potential for additive sedative effects. Caution patients against operating heavy equipment or driving until they know how they respond to treatment with clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets. Advise patients to avoid use with alcohol.



     5.3 Rebound Hypertension  



  Abrupt discontinuation of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets can cause rebound hypertension. In adults with hypertension, sudden cessation of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release formulation treatment in the 0.2 to 0.6 mg/day range resulted in reports of headache, tachycardia, nausea, flushing, warm feeling, brief lightheadedness, tightness in chest, and anxiety. In adults with hypertension, sudden cessation of treatment with immediate-release clonidine has, in some cases, resulted in symptoms such as nervousness, agitation, headache, and tremor accompanied or followed by a rapid rise in blood pressure and elevated catecholamine concentrations in the plasma.



 No studies evaluating abrupt discontinuation of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets in children with ADHD have been conducted; however, to minimize the risk of rebound hypertension, gradually reduce the dose of clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets in decrements of no more than 0.1 mg every 3 to 7 days. Patients should be instructed not to discontinue clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets therapy without consulting their physician due to the potential risk of withdrawal effects.



 



     5.4 Allergic Reactions  



  In patients who have developed localized contact sensitization to clonidine transdermal system, continuation of clonidine transdermal system or substitution of oral clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets therapy may be associated with the development of a generalized skin rash.



 In patients who develop an allergic reaction from clonidine transdermal system, substitution of oral clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets may also elicit an allergic reaction (including generalized rash, urticaria, or angioedema).



     5.5 Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities  



  The sympatholytic action of clonidine may worsen sinus node dysfunction and atrioventricular (AV) block, especially in patients taking other sympatholytic drugs. There have been post-marketing reports of patients with conduction abnormalities and/or taking other sympatholytic drugs who developed severe bradycardia requiring IV atropine, IV isoproterenol, and temporary cardiac pacing while taking clonidine. Titrate clonidine hydrochloride extended-release tablets slowly and monitor vital signs frequently in patients with cardiac conduction abnormalities or patients concomitantly treated with other sympatholytic drugs.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
