<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="clozaril" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Agranulocytosis . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension, Bradycardia, and Syncope . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *  Seizures . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *  Myocarditis and Cardiomyopathy . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
 *  Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]  
 *  Eosinophilia . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)]  
 *  QT Interval Prolongation . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  
 *  Metabolic Changes (Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus, Dyslipidemia, and Weight Gain) . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)]  
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)]  
 *  Fever . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.11)]  
 *  Pulmonary Embolism . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.12)]  
 *  Anticholinergic Toxicity . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.13)]  
 *  Interference with Cognitive and Motor Performance . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.14)]  
 *  Tardive Dyskinesia . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.15)]  
 *  Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.16)]  
 *  Recurrence of Psychosis and Cholinergic Rebound after Abrupt Discontinuation . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.17)]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) were: CNS reactions (sedation, dizziness/vertigo, headache, and tremor); cardiovascular reactions (tachycardia, hypotension, and syncope); autonomic nervous system reactions (hypersalivation, sweating, dry mouth, and visual disturbances); gastrointestinal reactions (constipation and nausea); and fever. ( )  6.1    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;5%) across CLOZARIL clinical trials were: CNS reactions, including sedation, dizziness/vertigo, headache, and tremor; cardiovascular reactions, including tachycardia, hypotension, and syncope; autonomic nervous system reactions, including hypersalivation, sweating, dry mouth, and visual disturbances; gastrointestinal reactions, including constipation and nausea; and fever. Table 8 summarizes the most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;5%) in CLOZARIL-treated patients (compared to chlorpromazine-treated patients) in the pivotal, 6-week, controlled trial in treatment-resistant schizophrenia.



 Table 8. Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;=5%) in the 6-Week, Randomized, Chlorpromazine-controlled Trial in Treatment-Resistant Schizophrenia 
   Adverse Reaction      CLOZARIL (N=126) (%)      Chlorpromazine (N=142) (%)     
   Sedation       21               13                
   Tachycardia    17               11                
   Constipation    16               12                
   Dizziness      14               16                
   Hypotension    13               38                
   Fever (hyperthermia)    13               4                 
   Hypersalivation    13               1                 
   Hypertension    12               5                 
   Headache       10               10                
   Nausea/vomiting    10               12                
   Dry mouth      5                20                
         Table 9 summarizes the adverse reactions reported in CLOZARIL-treated patients at a frequency of 2% or greater across all CLOZARIL studies (excluding the 2-year InterSePTTM Study). These rates are not adjusted for duration of exposure.
 

 Table 9. Adverse Reactions (&gt;=2%) Reported in CLOZARIL-treated Patients (N=842) Across all CLOZARIL Studies (excluding the 2-year InterSePT Study) TM 
  Rate based on population of approximately 1700 exposed during premarket clinical evaluation of CLOZARIL.   
  
   Body System      Adverse Reaction*      CLOZARIL N=842 Percentage of Patients     
   Central Nervous System                      
      Drowsiness/Sedation  39                
      Dizziness/Vertigo  19                
      Headache    7                 
      Tremor      6                 
      Syncope     6                 
      Disturbed Sleep/Nightmares  4                 
      Restlessness  4                 
      Hypokinesia/Akinesia  4                 
      Agitation   4                 
      Seizures (convulsions)  3                 
      Rigidity    3                 
      Akathisia   3                 
      Confusion   3                 
      Fatigue     2                 
      Insomnia    2                 
   Cardiovascular                      
      Tachycardia  25                
      Hypotension  9                 
      Hypertension  4                 
   Gastrointestinal                      
      Constipation  14                
      Nausea      5                 
      Abdominal Discomfort/Heartburn  4                 
      Nausea/Vomiting  3                 
      Vomiting    3                 
      Diarrhea    2                 
   Urogenital                       
      Urinary Abnormalities  2                 
   Autonomic Nervous System                      
      Salivation  31                
      Sweating    6                 
      Dry Mouth   6                 
      Visual Disturbances  5                 
   Skin                             
      Rash        2                 
   Hemic/Lymphatic                      
      Leukopenia/Decreased WBC/Neutropenia  3                 
   Miscellaneous                      
      Fever       5                 
      Weight Gain  4                 
        Table 10 summarizes the most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;10% of the CLOZARIL or olanzapine group) in the InterSePT Study. This was an adequate and well-controlled, 2-year study evaluating the efficacy of CLOZARIL relative to olanzapine in reducing the risk of suicidal behavior in patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder. The rates are not adjusted for duration of exposure.  TM  
 

 Table 10. Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Patients Treated with CLOZARIL or Olanzapine in the InterSePT Study (&gt;10% in the CLOZARIL or olanzapine group) TM 
   Adverse Reactions      CLOZARIL    N=479    % Reporting      Olanzapine    N=477    % Reporting     
 Salivary hypersecretion  48               6                 
 Somnolence       46               25                
 Weight increased  31               56                
 Dizziness (excluding vertigo)  27               12                
 Constipation     25               10                
 Insomnia         20               33                
 Nausea           17               10                
 Vomiting         17               9                 
 Dyspepsia        14               8                 
           Dystonia  
 

 Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.  Class effect:  



   6.2     Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of clozapine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Central Nervous System  



 Delirium, EEG abnormal, myoclonus, paresthesia, possible cataplexy, status epilepticus, obsessive compulsive symptoms, and post-discontinuation cholinergic rebound adverse reactions.



   Cardiovascular System  



 Atrial or ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia, QT interval prolongation, Torsades de Pointes, myocardial infarction, cardiac arrest, and periorbital edema.



   Gastrointestinal System  



 Acute pancreatitis, dysphagia, salivary gland swelling.



   Hepatobiliary System  



 Cholestasis, hepatitis, jaundice, hepatotoxicity, hepatic steatosis, hepatic necrosis, hepatic fibrosis, hepatic cirrhosis, liver injury (hepatic, cholestatic, and mixed), and liver failure.



   Urogenital System  



 Acute interstitial nephritis, nocturnal enuresis, priapism, and renal failure.



   Skin  



 Hypersensitivity reactions: photosensitivity, vasculitis, erythema multiforme, and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome.



   Musculoskeletal System  



 Myasthenic syndrome and rhabdomyolysis.



   Respiratory System  



 Aspiration, pleural effusion, pneumonia, lower respiratory tract infection.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  



 Deep-vein thrombosis, elevated hemoglobin/hematocrit, erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) increased, sepsis, thrombocytosis, and thrombocytopenia.



   Vision Disorders  



 Narrow-angle glaucoma.



   Miscellaneous  



 Creatine phosphokinase elevation, hyperuricemia, hyponatremia, and weight loss.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: AGRANULOCYTOSIS; ORTHOSTATIC HYPOTENSION, BRADYCARDIA, AND SYNCOPE; SEIZURE; MYOCARDITIS AND CARDIOMYOPATHY; INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    WARNING: AGRANULOCYTOSIS; ORTHOSTATIC HYPOTENSION, BRADYCARDIA, AND SYNCOPE; SEIZURE; MYOCARDITIS AND CARDIOMYOPATHY; INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  

    Agranulocytosis  



   CLOZARIL treatment has caused agranulocytosis, defined as an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) less than 500/mm . Agranulocytosis can lead to serious infection and death. Prior to initiating treatment with CLOZARIL, obtain a baseline white blood cell (WBC) count  and ANC. The ANC must be greater than or equal to 2000/mm and the WBC must be greater than or equal to 3500/mm for a patient to begin treatment with CLOZARIL. During treatment, patients must have regular monitoring of ANC and WBC. Discontinue CLOZARIL and do not rechallenge if the ANC is less than 1000/mm or the WBC is less than 2000/mm . Advise patients to immediately report symptoms consistent with agranulocytosis or infection (e.g., fever, weakness, lethargy, or sore throat) .

                                  3    3    3    3    3    [see Dosage and Administration (2.1) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]    



   Because of the risk of agranulocytosis, CLOZARIL is available only through a restricted program called the CLOZARIL National Registry. Under the CLOZARIL National Registry, prescribers, patients, and pharmacies must enroll in the program .

                                  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]    



   Orthostatic Hypotension, Bradycardia, Syncope  



   Orthostatic hypotension, bradycardia, syncope, and cardiac arrest have occurred with CLOZARIL treatment. The risk is highest during the initial titration period, particularly with rapid dose escalation. These reactions can occur with the first dose, with doses as low as 12.5 mg per day. Initiate treatment at 12.5 mg once or twice daily; titrate slowly; and use divided dosages. Use CLOZARIL cautiously in patients with cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease or conditions predisposing to hypotension (e.g., dehydration, use of antihypertensive medications) .

                                  [see Dosage and Administration (2.2, and 2.5) and Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]    



   Seizures  



   Seizures have occurred with CLOZARIL treatment. The risk is dose-related. Initiate treatment at 12.5 mg, titrate gradually, and use divided dosing. Use caution when administering CLOZARIL to patients with a history of seizures or other predisposing risk factors for seizure (CNS pathology, medications that lower the seizure threshold, alcohol abuse). Caution patients about engaging in any activity where sudden loss of consciousness could cause serious risk to themselves or others .

                                  [see Dosage and Administration (2.2), Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]    



   Myocarditis and Cardiomyopathy  



   Fatal myocarditis and cardiomyopathy have occurred with CLOZARIL treatment.  Discontinue CLOZARIL and obtain a cardiac evaluation upon suspicion of these reactions. Generally, patients with CLOZARIL-related myocarditis or cardiomyopathy should not be rechallenged with CLOZARIL. Consider the possibility of myocarditis or cardiomyopathy if chest pain, tachycardia, palpitations, dyspnea, fever, flu-like symptoms, hypotension, or ECG changes occur .

                                  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]    



   Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis  



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. CLOZARIL is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis .

                                  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: AGRANULOCYTOSIS; ORTHOSTATIC HYPOTENSION, BRADYCARDIA, AND SYNCOPE; SEIZURE; MYOCARDITIS AND CARDIOMYOPATHY; INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Agranulocytosis: Can lead to serious infection and death. Monitor white blood cell count and absolute neutrophil count prior to and during treatment. Monitor for symptoms of agranulocytosis and infection. ( , ) 2.15.1 
 *  Because of risk of agranulocytosis, CLOZARIL is available only through a restricted program called the CLOZARIL National Registry. Prescribers, patients, and pharmacies must enroll in the program. ( ) 5.2 
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension, Bradycardia, and Syncope: Risk is dose-related. Starting dose is 12.5 mg. Titrate gradually and use divided dosages. ( , , ) 2.22.55.3 
 *  Seizure: Risk is dose-related. Titrate gradually and use divided doses. Use with caution in patients with history of seizure or risk factors for seizure. ( , ) 2.25.4 
 *  Myocarditis and Cardiomyopathy: Can be fatal. Discontinue and obtain cardiac evaluation if findings suggest these cardiac reactions. ( ) 5.5 
 *  Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: CLOZARIL is not approved for this condition. ( ) 5.6 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Assess for organ involvement (e.g., myocarditis, pancreatitis, hepatitis, colitis, nephritis). Discontinue if these occur. ( ) Eosinophilia:   5.7   
 *  Can be fatal. Consider additional risk factors for prolonged QT interval (disorders and drugs). ( ) QT Interval Prolongation:   5.8   
 *  *  Monitor for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Monitor glucose regularly in patients with diabetes or at risk for diabetes. ( ) Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus:   5.9   
 *  Undesirable alterations in lipids have occurred in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. ( ) Dyslipidemia:   5.9   
 *  Significant weight gain has occurred. Monitor weight gain. ( ) Weight Gain:   5.9   
   Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/ cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include: Metabolic Changes:  
 *  Immediately discontinue and monitor closely. Assess for co-morbid conditions. ( ) Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS):   5.10   
 *  Evaluate for infection, agranulocytosis, NMS. ( ) Fever:   5.11   
 *  Consider PE if respiratory distress, chest pain, or deep vein thrombosis occur. ( ) Pulmonary Embolism (PE):   5.12   
 *  Use cautiously in presence of specific conditions (e.g., narrow angle glaucoma, use of anticholinergic drugs). ( ) Anticholinergic Toxicity:   5.13   
 *  Advise caution when operating machinery, including automobiles. ( ) Interference with Cognitive and Motor Performance:   5.14   
    
 

   5.1     Agranulocytosis



   Background  



 Agranulocytosis, defined as an ANC of less than 500/mm , has been estimated to occur in association with clozapine use at a cumulative incidence at 1 year of approximately 1.3%, based on the occurrence of 15 US cases out of 1743 patients exposed to CLOZARIL during its clinical testing prior to domestic marketing. All of these cases occurred at a time when the need for close monitoring of WBC counts was already recognized. A hematologic risk analysis was conducted based upon the available information in the CLOZARIL National Registry for US patients. Based upon a cut-off date of April 30, 1995, the incidence rates of agranulocytosis based upon a weekly monitoring schedule rose steeply during the first 2 months of therapy, peaking in the third month. Among clozapine patients who continued the drug beyond the third month, the weekly incidence of agranulocytosis fell a substantial degree. After 6 months, the weekly incidence of agranulocytosis declines still further; however, it never reaches zero. It should be noted that any type of reduction in the frequency of monitoring WBC counts may result in an increased incidence of agranulocytosis.  3  



  Risk Factors  



 Experience from clinical development, as well as from examples in the medical literature, suggests that patients who have developed agranulocytosis during clozapine therapy are at increased risk of subsequent episodes of agranulocytosis. Analysis of WBC count data from the CLOZARIL National Registry also suggests that patients who have an initial episode of moderate leukopenia (3000/mm &gt;WBC count &gt;=2000/mm ) are at an increased risk of subsequent episodes of agranulocytosis. Except for bone-marrow suppression during initial clozapine therapy, there are no other established risk factors based on worldwide experience for the development of agranulocytosis in association with clozapine use. However, a disproportionate number of the US cases of agranulocytosis occurred in patients of Jewish background compared to the overall proportion of such patients exposed during domestic development of clozapine. Most of the US cases of agranulocytosis occurred within 4-10 weeks of exposure, but neither dose nor duration is a reliable predictor of this problem. Agranulocytosis associated with other antipsychotic drugs has been reported to occur with a greater frequency in women, the elderly, and in patients who are cachectic or have serious underlying medical illness; such patients may also be at particular risk with clozapine, although this has not been definitively demonstrated.  3    3  



  WBC Count and ANC Clinical Monitoring Schedule  



 CLOZARIL is available only through a distribution system that ensures monitoring of WBC count and ANC according to the schedule described below prior to delivery of the next supply of medication.



 As described in Table 2, patients who are being treated with CLOZARIL must have a baseline WBC count and ANC before initiation of treatment, and a WBC count and ANC every week for the first 6 months. Thereafter, if acceptable WBC counts and ANCs (WBC count &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm ) have been maintained during the first 6 months of continuous therapy, WBC counts and ANCs can be monitored every 2 weeks for the next 6 months. Thereafter, if acceptable WBC counts and ANCs (WBC count &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm ) have been maintained during the second 6 months of continuous therapy, WBC count and ANC can be monitored every 4 weeks.  3    3    3    3  



 When treatment with CLOZARIL is discontinued (regardless of the reason), WBC count and ANC must be monitored weekly for at least 4 weeks from the day of discontinuation or until WBC count &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm .  3    3  



 Table 2 provides a summary of the frequency of monitoring that should occur based on various stages of therapy (e.g., initiation of therapy) or results from WBC count and ANC monitoring tests (e.g., moderate leukopenia). The text that follows should be consulted for additional details regarding the treatment of patients under the various conditions (e.g., severe leukopenia).



 Advise patients to immediately report the appearance of signs/symptoms consistent with agranulocytosis or infection (e.g., fever, weakness, lethargy, or sore throat) at any time during CLOZARIL therapy. Such patients should have a WBC count and an ANC performed promptly.



 Table 2. Frequency of Monitoring Based on Stage of Therapy or Results from WBC Count and ANC Monitoring Tests 
 WBC=White blood cell   
 ANC=Absolute neutrophil count   
  
  Situation        Hematological Values for Monitoring     Frequency of WBC Count and ANC Monitoring     
 Initiation of therapy  WBC count&gt;=3500/mm and ANC&gt;=2000/mm Note: Do not initiate in patients with a history of clozapine-induced agranulocytosis or severe granulocytopenia.  3    3    Weekly for 6 months   
 6 to 12 months of therapy  WBC &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm  3    3    Every 2 weeks for 6 months   
 12 months of therapy  WBC &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm  3    3    Every 4 weeks ad infinitum   
 Immature forms present  N/A              Repeat WBC and ANC   
 Discontinuation of therapy  N/A              Weekly for at least 4 weeks from day of discontinuation or until WBC &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm  3    3     
 Substantial drop in WBC or ANC  Single drop or cumulative drop within 3 weeks of: WBC &gt;=3000/mm or ANC &gt;=1500/mm  3    3    Repeat WBC and ANC 
 If repeat values are: WBC 3000/mm to 3500 and ANC &gt;2000/mm , then monitor twice weekly  3    3   
                                    
 Mild leukopenia and/or Mild granulocytopenia  If WBC 3000 mm to &lt;3500/mm and/or ANC 1500/mm to &lt;2000/mm  3    3    3    3    Twice weekly until WBC &gt;3500/mm and ANC &gt;2000/mm then return to previous monitoring frequency  3    3     
 Moderate leukopenia and/or Moderate granulocytopenia  WBC 2000/mm to &lt;3000/mm and/or ANC 1000/mm to &lt;1500/mm  3    3    3    3    Interrupt therapy 
 Daily until WBC &gt;3000/mm and ANC &gt;1500/mm  3    3   
 Twice weekly until WBC &gt;3500/mm and ANC &gt;2000/mm  3    3   
 May rechallenge when WBC &gt;3500/mm and ANC &gt;2000/mm  3    3   
 If rechallenged, monitor weekly for 1 year before returning to the usual monitoring schedule of every 2 weeks for 6 months and then every 4 weeks ad infinitum 
                                    
 Severe leukopenia and/or Severe granulocytopenia  WBC count &lt;2000/mm and/or ANC &lt;1000/mm  3    3    Discontinue treatment and do not rechallenge patient 
 *  Daily until WBC &gt;3000/mm and ANC &gt;1500/mm  3    3   
 *  Twice weekly until WBC &gt;3500/mm and ANC &gt;2000/mm  3    3   
 *  Weekly after WBC &gt;3500/mm  3   
                  Monitor until normal and for at least 4 weeks from day of discontinuation as follows: 
                                    
 Agranulocytosis  ANC &lt;500/mm  3    Discontinue treatment and do not rechallenge patient 
 *  Daily until WBC &gt;3000/mm and ANC &gt;1500/mm  3    3   
 *  Twice weekly until WBC &gt;3500/mm and ANC &gt;2000/mm  3    3   
 *  Weekly after WBC &gt;3500/mm  3   
                  Monitor until normal and for at least 4 weeks from day of discontinuation as follows: 
                                    
          Decrements in WBC Count and/or ANC  
 

 Consult Table 2 above to determine how to monitor patients who experience decrements in WBC count and/or ANC at any point during treatment. Additionally, patients should be carefully monitored for flu-like symptoms or other symptoms suggestive of infection.



  Nonrechallengeable Patients  



 If the total WBC count falls below 2000/mm or the ANC falls below 1000/mm , bone-marrow aspiration should be considered to ascertain granulopoietic status and patients should not be rechallenged with clozapine. Protective isolation with close observation may be indicated if granulopoiesis is determined to be deficient. Should evidence of infection develop, the patient should have appropriate cultures performed and an appropriate antibiotic regimen instituted.  3    3  



 Patients discontinued from clozapine therapy due to significant granulopoietic suppression have been found to develop agranulocytosis upon rechallenge, often with a shorter latency on re-exposure. To reduce the chances of rechallenge occurring in patients who have experienced significant bone-marrow suppression during clozapine therapy, a single, national master file (i.e., Nonrechallengeable Database) is confidentially maintained.



  Treatment of Rechallengeable Patients  



 Patients may be rechallenged with clozapine if their WBC count does not fall below 2000/mm and the ANC does not fall below 1000/mm . However, analysis of the data from the CLOZARIL National Registry suggests that patients who have an initial episode of moderate leukopenia (3000/mm &gt;WBC count &gt;=2000/mm ) have up to a 12-fold increased risk of having a subsequent episode of agranulocytosis when rechallenged as compared to the full cohort of patients treated with clozapine. Although CLOZARIL therapy may be resumed if no symptoms of infection develop and when the WBC count rises above 3500/mm and the ANC rises above 2000/mm , prescribers are strongly advised to consider whether the benefit of continuing CLOZARIL treatment outweighs the increased risk of agranulocytosis.  3    3    3    3    3    3  



 Analyses of the CLOZARIL National Registry have shown an increased risk of having a subsequent episode of granulopoietic suppression up to a year after recovery from the initial episode. Therefore, as noted in Table 2, patients must undergo weekly WBC count and ANC monitoring for 1 year following recovery from an episode of moderate leukopenia and/or moderate granulocytopenia regardless of when the episode develops. If acceptable WBC counts and ANC (WBC count &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm ) have been maintained during the year of weekly monitoring, WBC counts can be monitored every 2 weeks for the next 6 months. If acceptable WBC counts and ANC (WBC count &gt;=3500/mm and ANC &gt;=2000/mm ) continue to be maintained during the 6 months of every 2-week monitoring, WBC counts can be monitored every 4 weeks thereafter, ad infinitum.  3    3    3    3  



  Interruptions in Therapy  



 Figure 1 provides instructions regarding re-initiating therapy and subsequently the frequency of WBC count and ANC monitoring after a period of interruption.



  Figure 1. Resuming Monitoring Frequency after Interruption of Therapy  



  Figure 1: Resuming Monitoring Frequency after Interruption in Therapy    5.2     CLOZARIL National Registry Because of the Risk of Agranulocytosis



   Because of the risk of agranulocytosis, CLOZARIL is available only through a restricted program called the CLOZARIL National Registry. Under the CLOZARIL National Registry, prescribers, patients, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program.  



  Required components of the CLOZARIL National Registry are:  



 *   Healthcare professionals who prescribe CLOZARIL must enroll in the program and comply with the Registry requirements.  
 *   Pharmacies that dispense CLOZARIL must enroll in the program and comply with the Registry requirements.  
 *   Routine monitoring and submission of laboratory results (WBC and ANC) is required during treatment with CLOZARIL . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]   
 *   Patients who receive CLOZARIL must be enrolled in a registry.  
     Further information is available at or 1-888-669-6682.  http://www.clozarilregistry.com    
 

    5.3     Orthostatic Hypotension, Bradycardia, and Syncope



   Hypotension, bradycardia, syncope, and cardiac arrest have occurred with clozapine treatment. The risk is highest during the initial titration period, particularly with rapid dose-escalation. These reactions can occur with the first dose, at doses as low as 12.5 mg. These reactions can be fatal. The syndrome is consistent with neurally mediated reflex bradycardia (NMRB).  



  Treatment must begin at a maximum dose of 12.5 mg once daily or twice daily. The total daily dose can be increased in increments of 25 mg to 50 mg per day, if well-tolerated, to a target dose of 300 mg to 450 mg per day (administered in divided doses) by the end of 2 weeks. Subsequently, the dose can be increased weekly or twice weekly, in increments of up to 100 mg. The maximum dose is 900 mg per day. Use cautious titration and a divided dosage schedule to minimize the risk of serious cardiovascular reactions . Consider reducing the dose if hypotension occurs. When restarting patients who have had even a brief interval off CLOZARIL (i.e., 2 days or more since the last dose), re-initiate treatment at 12.5 mg once daily or twice daily . [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)]   [see Dosage and Administration (2.5)]    



  Use CLOZARIL cautiously in patients with cardiovascular disease (history of myocardial infarction or ischemia, heart failure, or conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, and conditions which would predispose patients to hypotension (e.g., concomitant use of antihypertensives, dehydration and hypovolemia).  



    5.4     Seizures



  Seizure has been estimated to occur in association with clozapine use at a cumulative incidence at 1 year of approximately 5%, based on the occurrence of 1 or more seizures in 61 of 1743 patients exposed to clozapine during its clinical testing prior to domestic marketing (i.e., a crude rate of 3.5%). The risk of seizure is dose-related. Initiate treatment with a low dose (12.5 mg), titrate slowly, and use divided dosing.



 Use caution when administering CLOZARIL to patients with a history of seizures or other predisposing risk factors for seizure (e.g., head trauma or other CNS pathology, use of medications that lower the seizure threshold, or alcohol abuse). Because of the substantial risk of seizure associated with CLOZARIL use, caution patients about engaging in any activity where sudden loss of consciousness could cause serious risk to themselves or others (e.g., driving an automobile, operating complex machinery, swimming, climbing).



    5.5     Myocarditis and Cardiomyopathy



  Myocarditis and cardiomyopathy have occurred with the use of CLOZARIL. These reactions can be fatal. Discontinue CLOZARIL and obtain a cardiac evaluation upon suspicion of myocarditis or cardiomyopathy. Generally, patients with a history of clozapine-associated myocarditis or cardiomyopathy should not be rechallenged with CLOZARIL. However, if the benefit of CLOZARIL treatment is judged to outweigh the potential risks of recurrent myocarditis or cardiomyopathy, the clinician may consider rechallenge with CLOZARIL in consultation with a cardiologist, after a complete cardiac evaluation, and under close monitoring.



 Consider the possibility of myocarditis or cardiomyopathy in patients receiving CLOZARIL who present with chest pain, dyspnea, persistent tachycardia at rest, palpitations, fever, flu-like symptoms, hypotension, other signs or symptoms of heart failure, or electrocardiographic findings (low voltages, ST-T abnormalities, arrhythmias, right axis deviation, and poor R wave progression). Myocarditis most frequently presents within the first 2 months of clozapine treatment. Symptoms of cardiomyopathy generally occur later than clozapine-associated myocarditis and usually after 8 weeks of treatment. However, myocarditis and cardiomyopathy can occur at any period during treatment with CLOZARIL. It is common for nonspecific flu-like symptoms such as malaise, myalgia, pleuritic chest pain, and low-grade fevers to precede more overt signs of heart failure. Typical laboratory findings include elevated troponin I or T, elevated creatinine kinase-MB, peripheral eosinophilia, and elevated C-reactive protein (CRP). Chest roentgenogram may demonstrate cardiac silhouette enlargement, and cardiac imaging (echocardiogram, radionucleotide studies, or cardiac catheterization) may reveal evidence of left ventricular dysfunction.



    5.6     Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality in this population. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. CLOZARIL is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis . [see Boxed Warning]  



    5.7     Eosinophilia



  Eosinophilia, defined as a blood eosinophil count of greater than 700/mm , has occurred with CLOZARIL treatment. In clinical trials, approximately 1% of patients developed eosinophilia. Clozapine-related eosinophilia usually occurs during the first month of treatment. In some patients, it has been associated with myocarditis, pancreatitis, hepatitis, colitis, and nephritis. Such organ involvement could be consistent with a drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS) syndrome, also known as drug induced hypersensitivity syndrome (DIHS). If eosinophilia develops during CLOZARIL treatment, evaluate promptly for signs and symptoms of systemic reactions, such as rash or other allergic symptoms, myocarditis, or other organ-specific disease associated with eosinophilia. If CLOZARIL-related systemic disease is suspected, discontinue CLOZARIL immediately.  3  



 If a cause of eosinophilia unrelated to CLOZARIL is identified (e.g., asthma, allergies, collagen vascular disease, parasitic infections, and specific neoplasms), treat the underlying cause and continue CLOZARIL.



 Clozapine-related eosinophilia has also occurred in the absence of organ involvement and can resolve without intervention. There are reports of successful rechallenge after discontinuation of clozapine, without recurrence of eosinophilia. In the absence of organ involvement, continue CLOZARIL under careful monitoring. If the total eosinophil count continues to increase over several weeks in the absence of systemic disease, the decision to interrupt CLOZARIL therapy and rechallenge after the eosinophil count decreases should be based on the overall clinical assessment, in consultation with an internist or hematologist.



    5.8     QT Interval Prolongation



  QT prolongation, Torsades de Pointes and other life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias, cardiac arrest, and sudden death have occurred with CLOZARIL treatment. When prescribing CLOZARIL, consider the presence of additional risk factors for QT prolongation and serious cardiovascular reactions. Conditions that increase these risks include the following: history of QT prolongation, long QT syndrome, family history of long QT syndrome or sudden cardiac death, significant cardiac arrhythmia, recent myocardial infarction, uncompensated heart failure, treatment with other medications that cause QT prolongation, treatment with medications that inhibit the metabolism of clozapine, and electrolyte abnormalities.



 Prior to initiating treatment with CLOZARIL, perform a careful physical examination, medical history, and concomitant medication history. Consider obtaining a baseline ECG and serum chemistry panel. Correct electrolyte abnormalities. Discontinue CLOZARIL if the QTc interval exceeds 500 msec. If patients experience symptoms consistent with Torsades de Pointes, or other arrhythmias, (e.g., syncope, presyncope, dizziness, or palpitations), obtain a cardiac evaluation and discontinue CLOZARIL.



 Use caution when administering concomitant medications that prolong the QT interval or inhibit the metabolism of CLOZARIL. Drugs that cause QT prolongation include: specific antipsychotics (e.g., ziprasidone, iloperidone, chlorpromazine, thioridazine, mesoridazine, droperidol, pimozide), specific antibiotics (e.g., erythromycin, gatifloxacin, moxifloxacin, sparfloxacin), Class 1A antiarrhythmic medications (e.g., quinidine, procainamide) or Class III antiarrhythmics (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol), and others (e.g., pentamidine, levomethadyl acetate, methadone, halofantrine, mefloquine, dolasetron mesylate, probucol or tacrolimus). Clozapine is primarily metabolized by CYP isoenzymes 1A2, 2D6, and 3A4. Concomitant treatment with inhibitors of these enzymes can increase the concentration of CLOZARIL . [see Drug Interactions (7.1) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  



 Hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia increase the risk of QT prolongation. Hypokalemia can result from diuretic therapy, diarrhea, and other causes. Use caution when treating patients at risk for significant electrolyte disturbance, particularly hypokalemia. Obtain baseline measurements of serum potassium and magnesium levels, and periodically monitor electrolytes. Correct electrolyte abnormalities before initiating treatment with CLOZARIL.



    5.9     Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs, including CLOZARIL have been associated with metabolic changes that can increase cardiovascular and cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and body weight gain. While atypical antipsychotic drugs may produce some metabolic changes, each drug in the class has its own specific risk profile.



  Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus  



 Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics including CLOZARIL. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of treatment-emergent, hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. Precise risk estimates for hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics are not available.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on CLOZARIL should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



 In a pooled data analysis of 8 studies in adult subjects with schizophrenia, the mean changes in fasting glucose concentration in the CLOZARIL and chlorpromazine groups were +11 mg/dL and +4 mg/dL respectively. A higher proportion of the CLOZARIL group demonstrated categorical increases from baseline in fasting glucose concentrations, compared to the chlorpromazine group (Table 3). The CLOZARIL doses were 100-900 mg per day (mean modal dose: 512 mg per day). The maximum chlorpromazine dose was 1800 mg per day (mean modal dose: 1029 mg per day). The median duration of exposure was 42 days for CLOZARIL and chlorpromazine.



 Table 3. Categorical Changes in Fasting Glucose Level in Studies in Adult Subjects with Schizophrenia 
  Laboratory Parameter     Category Change (at least once) from baseline     Treatment Arm     N                n (%)            
 Fasting Glucose  Normal (&lt;100 mg/dL) to High (&gt;=126 mg/dL)  CLOZARIL         198              53 (27)           
 Chlorpromazine   135              14 (10)           
 Borderline (100 to 125 mg/dL) to High (&gt;=126 mg/dL)  CLOZARIL         57               24 (42)           
 Chlorpromazine   43               12 (28)           
                   
            Dyslipidemia  
 

 Undesirable alterations in lipids have occurred in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics, including CLOZARIL. Clinical monitoring, including baseline and periodic follow-up lipid evaluations in patients using CLOZARIL, is recommended.



 In a pooled data analysis of 10 studies in adult subjects with schizophrenia, CLOZARIL treatment was associated with increases in serum total cholesterol. No data were collected on LDL and HDL cholesterol. The mean increase in total cholesterol was 13 mg/dL in the CLOZARIL group and 15 mg/dL in the chlorpromazine group. In a pooled data analysis of 2 studies in adult subjects with schizophrenia, CLOZARIL treatment was associated with increases in fasting serum triglyceride. The mean increase in fasting triglyceride was 71 mg/dL (54%) in the CLOZARIL group and 39 mg/dL (35%) in the chlorpromazine group (Table 4). In addition, CLOZARIL treatment was associated with categorical increases in serum total cholesterol and triglyceride, as illustrated in Table 5.The proportion of patients with categorical increases in total cholesterol or fasting triglyceride increased with the duration of exposure. The median duration of CLOZARIL and chlorpromazine exposure was 45 days and 38 days, respectively. The CLOZARIL dose range was 100 mg to 900 mg daily; the maximum chlorpromazine dose was 1800 mg daily.



 Table 4. Mean Changes in Total Cholesterol and Triglyceride Concentration in Studies in Adult Subjects with Schizophrenia 
  Treatment Arm     Baseline total cholesterol concentration (mg/dL)     Change from baseline mg/dL (%)     
 CLOZARIL (N=334)  184              +13 (7)           
 Chlorpromazine (185)  182              +15 (8)           
                   Baseline triglyceride concentration (mg/dL)     Change from baseline mg/dL (%)     
 CLOZARIL (N=6)   130              +71 (54)          
 Chlorpromazine (N=7)  110              +39 (35)          
        Table 5. Categorical Changes in Lipid Concentrations in Studies in Adult Subjects with Schizophrenia 
  Laboratory Parameter     Category Change (at least once) from baseline     Treatment Arm     N                n (%)            
 Total Cholesterol (random or fasting)  Increase by &gt;=40 mg/dL  CLOZARIL         334              111 (33)          
 Chlorpromazine   185              46 (25)           
 Normal (&lt;200 mg/dL) to High (&gt;=240 mg/dL)  CLOZARIL         222              18 (8)            
 Chlorpromazine   132              3 (2)             
 Borderline (200-239 mg/dL) to High (&gt;=240 mg/dL)  CLOZARIL         79               30 (38)           
 Chlorpromazine   34               14 (41)           
 Triglycerides (fasting)  Increase by &gt;=50 mg/dL  CLOZARIL         6                3 (50)            
 Chlorpromazine   7                3 (43)            
 Normal (&lt;150 mg/dL) to High (&gt;=200 mg/dL)  CLOZARIL         4                0 (0)             
 Chlorpromazine   6                2 (33)            
 Borderline (&gt;=150 mg/dL and &lt;200 mg/dL) to High (&gt;=200 mg/dL)  CLOZARIL         1                1 (100)           
 Chlorpromazine   1                0 (0)             
                   
            Weight Gain  
 

 Weight gain has occurred with the use of antipsychotics, including CLOZARIL. Monitor weight during treatment with CLOZARIL. Table 6 summarizes the data on weight gain by the duration of exposure pooled from 11 studies with CLOZARIL and active comparators. The median duration of exposure was 609, 728, and 42 days, in the CLOZARIL, olanzapine, and chlorpromazine group, respectively.



 Table 6. Mean Change in Body Weight (kg) by duration of exposure from studies in adult subjects with schizophrenia 
  Metabolic parameter     Exposure duration     CLOZARIL (N=669)     Olanzapine (N=442)     Chlorpromazine (N=155)     
  n                Mean             n                Mean             n                Mean             
  Weight change from baseline    2 weeks (Day 11-17)  6                +0.9             3                +0.7             2                -0.5              
 4 weeks (Day 21-35)  23               +0.7             8                +0.8             17               +0.6              
 8 weeks (Day 49-63)  12               +1.9             13               +1.8             16               +0.9              
 12 weeks (Day 70-98)  17               +2.8             5                +3.1             0                0                 
 24 weeks (154-182)  42               - 0.6            12               +5.7             0                0                 
 48 weeks (Day 322-350)  3                +3.7             3                +13.7            0                0                 
                   
              Table 7 summarizes pooled data from 11 studies in adult subjects with schizophrenia demonstrating weight gain &gt;=7% of body weight relative to baseline. The median duration of exposure was 609, 728, and 42 days, in the CLOZARIL, olanzapine, and chlorpromazine group, respectively.
 

 Table 7. Proportion of Adult Subjects in Schizophrenia Studies with Weight Gain &gt;=7% Relative to Baseline Body Weight 
  Weight change     CLOZARIL         Olanzapine       Chlorpromazine     
  N               669              442              155               
  &gt;=7% (inclusive)    236 (35%)        203 (46%)        13 (8%)           
             5.10     Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome
 

  Antipsychotic drugs including CLOZARIL can cause a potentially fatal symptom complex referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS). Clinical manifestations of NMS include hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmias). Associated findings can include elevated creatine phosphokinase (CPK), myoglobinuria, rhabdomyolysis, and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. It is important to consider the presence of other serious medical conditions (e.g., agranulocytosis, infection, heat stroke, primary CNS pathology, central anticholinergic toxicity, extrapyramidal symptoms, and drug fever).



 The management of NMS should include (1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy, (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring, and (3) treatment of comorbid medical conditions. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatments for NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. NMS can recur. Monitor closely if restarting treatment with antipsychotics.



 NMS has occurred with CLOZARIL monotherapy and with concomitant CNS-active medications, including lithium.



    5.11     Fever



  During clozapine therapy, patients have experienced transient, clozapine-related fever. The peak incidence is within the first 3 weeks of treatment. While this fever is generally benign and self-limited, it may necessitate discontinuing treatment. The fever can be associated with an increase or decrease in WBC count. Carefully evaluate patients with fever to rule out agranulocytosis or infection. Consider the possibility of NMS . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)]  



    5.12     Pulmonary Embolism



  Pulmonary embolism and deep vein thrombosis have occurred in patients treated with CLOZARIL. Consider the possibility of pulmonary embolism in patients who present with deep-vein thrombosis, acute dyspnea, chest pain, or with other respiratory signs and symptoms. Whether pulmonary embolus and deep vein thrombosis can be attributed to clozapine or some characteristic(s) of patients is not clear.



    5.13     Anticholinergic Toxicity



  CLOZARIL has potent anticholinergic effects. Treatment with CLOZARIL can result in CNS and peripheral anticholinergic toxicity. Use with caution in the presence of narrow-angle glaucoma, concomitant anticholinergic medications, prostatic hypertrophy, or other conditions in which anticholinergic effects can lead to significant adverse reactions.



 Treatment with CLOZARIL can result in gastrointestinal adverse reactions, including constipation, intestinal obstruction, fecal impaction, and paralytic ileus. Such reactions can be fatal. Constipation should be initially treated by ensuring adequate hydration and use of ancillary therapy such as bulk laxatives. Consultation with a gastroenterologist is advisable in more serious cases.



    5.14     Interference with Cognitive and Motor Performance



  CLOZARIL can cause sedation and impairment of cognitive and motor performance. Caution patients about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that CLOZARIL does not affect them adversely. These reactions may be dose-related. Consider reducing the dose if they occur.



    5.15     Tardive Dyskinesia



  Tardive dyskinesia (TD) has occurred in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs, including CLOZARIL. The syndrome consists of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements. The risk of TD and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase with greater durations of treatment and higher total cumulative doses. However, the syndrome can develop after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses. Prescribe CLOZARIL in a manner that is most likely to minimize the risk of developing TD. Use the lowest effective dose and the shortest duration necessary to control symptoms. Periodically assess the need for continued treatment. Consider discontinuing treatment if TD occurs. However, some patients may require treatment with CLOZARIL despite the presence of the syndrome.



 There is no known treatment for TD. However, the syndrome may remit partially or completely if treatment is discontinued. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms, and it has the potential to mask the underlying process. The effect of symptom suppression on the long-term course of TD is unknown.



    5.16     Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions



  In controlled trials, elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with some atypical antipsychotics had an increased risk (compared to placebo) of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack), including fatalities. The mechanism for this increased risk is not known. An increased risk cannot be excluded for CLOZARIL or other antipsychotics or other patient populations. CLOZARIL should be used with caution in patients with risk factors for cerebrovascular adverse reactions.



    5.17     Recurrence of Psychosis and Cholinergic Rebound after Abrupt Discontinuation of CLOZARIL



  If abrupt discontinuation of CLOZARIL is necessary (because of agranulocytosis or another medical condition, for example), monitor carefully for the recurrence of psychotic symptoms and adverse reactions related to cholinergic rebound, such as profuse sweating, headache, nausea, vomiting and diarrhea.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
