<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="colazal" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence  &gt;  3%) are headache, abdominal pain, diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, respiratory infection, and arthralgia. Adverse reactions in children were similar. (  6.1  )



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Salix Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-508-0024 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adult Ulcerative Colitis  



 During clinical development, 259 adult patients with active ulcerative colitis were exposed to 6.75 g/day COLAZAL in 4 controlled trials.



 In the 4 controlled clinical trials patients receiving a COLAZAL dose of 6.75 g/day most frequently reported the following adverse reactions: headache (8%), abdominal pain (6%), diarrhea (5%), nausea (5%), vomiting (4%), respiratory infection (4%), and arthralgia (4%). Withdrawal from therapy due to adverse reactions was comparable among patients on COLAZAL and placebo.



 Adverse reactions reported by 1% or more of patients who participated in the 4 well-controlled, Phase 3 trials are presented by treatment group (Table 1).



 The number of placebo patients (35), however, is too small for valid comparisons. Some adverse reactions, such as abdominal pain, fatigue, and nausea were reported more frequently in women than in men. Abdominal pain, rectal bleeding, and anemia can be part of the clinical presentation of ulcerative colitis.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=1% of Adult COLAZAL Patients in Controlled Trials* 
 Adverse Reaction  COLAZAL 6.75 g/day[N=259]  Placebo[N=35]     
  
  *  Adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of Colazal patients which were less frequent than placebo for the same event were not included in the table.     
                   
  
  Abdominal pain   16 (6%)          1 (3%)           
  Diarrhea         14 (5%)          1 (3%)           
  Arthralgia       9 (4%)           0%               
  Rhinitis         6 (2%)           0%               
  Insomnia         6 (2%)           0%               
  Fatigue          6 (2%)           0%               
  Flatulence       5 (2%)           0%               
  Fever            5 (2%)           0%               
  Dyspepsia        5 (2%)           0%               
  Pharyngitis      4 (2%)           0%               
  Coughing         4 (2%)           0%               
  Anorexia         4 (2%)           0%               
  Urinary tract infection   3 (1%)           0%               
  Myalgia          3 (1%)           0%               
  Flu-like disorder   3 (1%)           0%               
  Dry mouth        3 (1%)           0%               
  Cramps           3 (1%)           0%               
  Constipation     3 (1%)           0%               
           Pediatric Ulcerative Colitis  
 

 In a clinical trial in 68 pediatric patients aged 5 to 17 years with mildly to moderately active ulcerative colitis who received 6.75 g/day or 2.25 g/day COLAZAL for 8 weeks, the most frequently reported adverse reactions were headache (15%), abdominal pain upper (13%), abdominal pain (12%), vomiting (10%), diarrhea (9%), colitis ulcerative (6%), nasopharyngitis (6%), and pyrexia (6%).  [see Table 2]  



 One patient who received COLAZAL 6.75 g/day and 3 patients who received COLAZAL 2.25 g/day discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions. In addition, 2 patients in each dose group discontinued because of a lack of efficacy.



 Adverse reactions reported by 3% or more of pediatric patients within either treatment group in the Phase 3 trial and presented in Table 2.



 Table 2: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=3% of Patients in Either Treatment Group in a Controlled Study of 68 Pediatric Patients 
 Adverse Reaction  COLAZAL          Total[N=68]       
 6.75 g/day[N=33]  2.25 g/day[N=35]   
  
                   
  
  Headache         5 (15%)          5 (14%)          10 (15%)         
  Abdominal pain upper   3 (9%)           6 (17%)          9 (13%)          
  Abdominal pain   4 (12%)          4 (11%)          8 (12%)          
  Vomiting         1 (3%)           6 (17%)          7 (10%)          
  Diarrhea         2 (6%)           4 (11%)          6 (9%)           
  Colitis ulcerative   2 (6%)           2 (6%)           4 (6%)           
  Nasopharyngitis   3 (9%)           1 (3%)           4 (6%)           
  Pyrexia          0 (0%)           4 (11%)          4 (6%)           
  Hematochezia     0 (0%)           3 (9%)           3 (4%)           
  Nausea           0 (0%)           3 (9%)           3 (4%)           
  Influenza        1 (3%)           2 (6%)           3 (4%)           
  Fatigue          2 (6%)           1 (3%)           3 (4%)           
  Stomatitis       0 (0%)           2 (6%)           2 (3%)           
  Cough            0 (0%)           2 (6%)           2 (3%)           
  Pharyngolaryngeal pain   2 (6%)           0 (0%)           2 (3%)           
  Dysmenorrhea     2 (6%)           0 (0%)           2 (3%)           
            6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of balsalazide in clinical practice:



 myocarditis, pericarditis, vasculitis, pruritus, pleural effusion, pneumonia (with and without eosinophilia), alveolitis, renal failure, interstitial nephritis, pancreatitis, and alopecia.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These adverse reactions have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to balsalazide.



   Hepatic  



 Postmarketing adverse reactions of hepatotoxicity have been reported for products which contain (or are metabolized to) mesalamine, including elevated liver function tests (SGOT/AST, SGPT/ALT, GGT, LDH, alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin), jaundice, cholestatic jaundice, cirrhosis, hepatocellular damage including liver necrosis and liver failure. Some of these cases were fatal; however, no fatalities associated with these adverse reactions were reported in COLAZAL clinical trials. One case of Kawasaki-like syndrome which included hepatic function changes was also reported, however, this adverse reaction was not reported in COLAZAL clinical trials.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Exacerbation of the symptoms of ulcerative colitis was reported in both adult and pediatric patients. Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Prolonged gastric retention of COLAZAL may occur in patients with pyloric stenosis. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Exacerbations of Ulcerative Colitis



  In the adult clinical trials, 3 out of 259 patients reported exacerbation of the symptoms of ulcerative colitis. In the pediatric clinical trials, 4 out of 68 patients reported exacerbation of the symptoms of ulcerative colitis.



 Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment.



    5.2 Pyloric Stenosis



  Patients with pyloric stenosis may have prolonged gastric retention of COLAZAL capsules.



    5.3 Renal



  Renal toxicity has been observed in animals and patients given other mesalamine products. Therefore, caution should be exercised when administering COLAZAL to patients with known renal dysfunction or a history of renal disease. [See  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2)  ]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
