<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="combipatch" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  See    BOXED WARNING    ,    WARNINGS    , and    PRECAUTIONS    .



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Table 9. All Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship Reported at a Frequency of Greater than or Equal to 5 percent with CombiPatch 
                                      VASOMOTOR SYMPTOM STUDIES                                                              
                                        CombiPatch  0.05/0.14mg per day    CombiPatch  0.05/0.25mg per day    Placebo                   
                                      n=113                           n=112                      n=107                       
 Body as a Whole                      46%                             48%                        41%                         
       Abdominal Pain                 7%                              6%                         4%                          
       Accidental Injury              4%                              5%                         8%                          
       Asthenia                       8%                              12%                        4%                          
       Back Pain                      11%                             9%                         5%                          
       Flu Syndrome                   9%                              5%                         7%                          
       Headache                       18%                             20%                        20%                         
       Pain                           6%                              4%                         9%                          
 Digestive                            19%                             23%                        24%                         
       Diarrhea                       4%                              5%                         7%                          
       Dyspepsia                      1%                              5%                         5%                          
       Flatulence                     4%                              5%                         4%                          
       Nausea                         11%                             8%                         7%                          
 Nervous                              16%                             28%                        28%                         
       Depression                     3%                              5%                         9%                          
       Insomnia                       3%                              6%                         7%                          
       Nervousness                    3%                              5%                         1%                          
 Respiratory                          24%                             38%                        26%                         
       Pharyngitis                    4%                              10%                        2%                          
       Respiratory Disorder           7%                              12%                        7%                          
       Rhinitis                       7%                              13%                        9%                          
       Sinusitis                      4%                              9%                         9%                          
 Skin and Appendages                  8%                              17%                        16%                         
       Application Site Reaction*     2%                              6%                         4%                          
 Urogenital                           54%                             63%                        28%                         
       Breast Pain                    25%                             31%                        7%                          
       Dysmenorrhea                   20%                             21%                        5%                          
       Leukorrhea                     5%                              5%                         3%                          
       Menstrual Disorder             6%                              12%                        2%                          
       Papanicolaou Smear Suspicious  8%                              4%                         5%                          
       Vaginitis                      6%                              13%                        5%                          
 Represents milligrams of estradiol/NETA delivered daily by each system.   
 *Application site reactions includes localized bleeding, bruising, burning, discomfort, dryness, eczema, edema, erythema, inflammation, irritation, pain, papules, paresthesia, pruritus, rash, skin discoloration, skin pigmentation, swelling, urticaria, and vesicles.   
         Table 10. All Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship Reported at a Frequency of Greater than or Equal to 5 percent with CombiPatch 
                                      ENDOMETRIAL HYPERPLASIA STUDIES                                                         
                                        CombiPatch  0.05/0.14mg per dayn=325    CombiPatch  0.05/0.25mg per dayn=312    Vivelle  0.05mg per dayn=318   
 Body as a Whole                      61%                             60%                        59%                         
       Abdominal Pain                 12%                             14%                        16%                         
       Accidental Injury              10%                             11%                        8%                          
       Asthenia                       10%                             13%                        11%                         
       Back Pain                      15%                             14%                        13%                         
       Flu Syndrome                   14%                             10%                        7%                          
       Headache                       25%                             17%                        21%                         
       Infection                      5%                              3%                         3%                          
       Pain                           19%                             15%                        13%                         
 Digestive                            42%                             32%                        31%                         
       Constipation                   2%                              5%                         3%                          
       Diarrhea                       14%                             9%                         7%                          
       Dyspepsia                      8%                              6%                         5%                          
       Flatulence                     7%                              5%                         6%                          
       Nausea                         8%                              12%                        11%                         
       Tooth Disorder                 6%                              4%                         1%                          
 Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  12%                             13%                        11%                         
       Peripheral Edema               6%                              6%                         5%                          
 Musculoskeletal                      17%                             17%                        15%                         
       Arthralgia                     6%                              6%                         5%                          
 Nervous                              33%                             30%                        28%                         
       Depression                     8%                              9%                         8%                          
       Dizziness                      6%                              7%                         5%                          
       Insomnia                       8%                              6%                         4%                          
       Nervousness                    5%                              6%                         3%                          
 Respiratory                          45%                             43%                        40%                         
       Bronchitis                     5%                              3%                         4%                          
       Pharyngitis                    9%                              9%                         8%                          
       Respiratory Disorder           13%                             9%                         13%                         
       Rhinitis                       19%                             22%                        17%                         
       Sinusitis                      10%                             12%                        12%                         
 Skin and Appendages                  38%                             37%                        31%                         
       Acne                           4%                              5%                         4%                          
       Application Site Reaction*     20%                             23%                        17%                         
       Rash                           6%                              5%                         3%                          
 Urogenital                           71%                             79%                        74%                         
       Breast Enlargement             2%                              7%                         2%                          
       Breast Pain                    34%                             48%                        40%                         
       Dysmenorrhea                   30%                             31%                        19%                         
       Leukorrhea                     10%                             8%                         9%                          
       Menorrhagia                    2%                              5%                         9%                          
       Menstrual Disorder             17%                             19%                        14%                         
       Vaginal Hemorrhage             3%                              6%                         12%                         
       Vaginitis                      9%                              13%                        13%                         
 Represents milligrams of estradiol/NETA delivered daily by each system.   
 *Application site reactions includes localized bleeding, bruising, burning, discomfort, dryness, eczema, edema, erythema, inflammation, irritation, pain, papules, paresthesia, pruritus, rash, skin discoloration, skin pigmentation, swelling, urticaria, and vesicles.   
          Postmarketing Experience
 

 The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of CombiPatch. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Genitourinary System



 Endometrial hyperplasia, endocervical polyp, uterine leiomyomata, fallopian tube cyst, uterine spasms.



 Breast



 Breast cancer.



 Cardiovascular



 Hypertension, varicose veins.



 Gastrointestinal



 Jaundice cholestatic, cholelithiasis, gall bladder disorder, transaminases increased.



 Skin



 Skin discoloration.



 Central Nervous System



 Affect lability, libido disorder, migraine, vertigo, paresthesia.



 Miscellaneous



 Angioedema, hypersensitivity, weight increased.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    WARNING:CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER, ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, AND PROBABLE DEMENTIA  



 Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy



 Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia



   Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia. (See   CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS    ,     Cardiovascular Disorders     and     Probable Dementia  ).  



 The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen plus progestin substudy reported an increased risk of deep vein thrombosis (DVT), pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg] combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo. (See    CLINICAL STUDIES   and     WARNINGS    ,   Cardiovascular Disorders  ).



   The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women. (See   CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS    ,     Probable Dementia     and     PRECAUTIONS    ,     Geriatric Use    ).



 Breast Cancer



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer. (See   CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS    ,      Malignant Neoplasms  ,   Breast Cancer    ).



 In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.



 Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.



 Estrogen-Alone Therapy



 Endometrial Cancer



 There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding. (See     WARNINGS    ,      Malignant Neoplasms  ,   Endometrial Cancer    ).



 Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia



   Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia. (See   CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS    ,     Cardiovascular Disorders     and     Probable Dementia  ).  



   The WHI estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and DVT in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo. (See   CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS    ,     Cardiovascular Disorders    ).



   The WHIMS estrogen-alone ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women. (See   CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS    ,     Probable Dementia     and     PRECAUTIONS    ,     Geriatric Use    ).



 In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and other dosage forms of estrogens. 



 Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
