<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="combigan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions occurring in approximately 5 to 15% of patients included allergic conjunctivitis, conjunctival folliculosis, conjunctival hyperemia, eye pruritus, ocular burning, and stinging. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Allergan at 1-800-433-8871 or the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     COMBIGAN  (r)    



 In clinical trials of 12 months duration with  COMBIGAN  (r)    , the most frequent reactions associated with its use occurring in approximately 5% to 15% of the patients included: allergic conjunctivitis, conjunctival folliculosis, conjunctival hyperemia, eye pruritus, ocular burning, and stinging. The following adverse reactions were reported in 1% to 5% of patients: asthenia, blepharitis, corneal erosion, depression, epiphora, eye discharge, eye dryness, eye irritation, eye pain, eyelid edema, eyelid erythema, eyelid pruritus, foreign body sensation, headache, hypertension, oral dryness, somnolence, superficial punctate keratitis, and visual disturbance.



 Other adverse reactions that have been reported with the individual components are listed below.



     Brimonidine Tartrate (0.1%-0.2%)  



 Abnormal taste, allergic reaction, blepharoconjunctivitis, blurred vision, bronchitis, cataract, conjunctival edema, conjunctival hemorrhage, conjunctivitis, cough, dizziness, dyspepsia, dyspnea, fatigue, flu syndrome, follicular conjunctivitis, gastrointestinal disorder, hypercholesterolemia, hypotension, infection (primarily colds and respiratory infections), hordeolum, insomnia, keratitis, lid disorder, nasal dryness, ocular allergic reaction, pharyngitis, photophobia, rash, rhinitis, sinus infection, sinusitis, taste perversion, tearing, visual field defect, vitreous detachment, vitreous disorder, vitreous floaters, and worsened visual acuity.



     Timolol (Ocular Administration)  



   Body as a whole  : chest pain;  Cardiovascular  : Arrhythmia, bradycardia, cardiac arrest, cardiac failure, cerebral ischemia, cerebral vascular accident, claudication, cold hands and feet, edema, heart block, palpitation, pulmonary edema, Raynaud's phenomenon, syncope, and worsening of angina pectoris;  Digestive  : Anorexia, diarrhea, nausea;  Immunologic  : Systemic lupus erythematosus;  Nervous System/Psychiatric  : Increase in signs and symptoms of myasthenia gravis, insomnia, nightmares, paresthesia, behavioral changes and psychic disturbances including confusion, hallucinations, anxiety, disorientation, nervousness, and memory loss;  Skin  : Alopecia, psoriasiform rash or exacerbation of psoriasis;  Hypersensitivity  : Signs and symptoms of systemic allergic reactions, including anaphylaxis, angioedema, urticaria, and generalized and localized rash;  Respiratory  : Bronchospasm (predominantly in patients with pre-existing bronchospastic disease), dyspnea, nasal congestion, respiratory failure;  Endocrine  : Masked symptoms of hypoglycemia in diabetes patients (see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  ,  5.7  );  Special Senses  : diplopia, choroidal detachment following filtration surgery, cystoid macular edema, decreased corneal sensitivity, pseudopemphigoid, ptosis, refractive changes, tinnitus;  Urogenital  : Decreased libido, impotence, Peyronie's disease, retroperitoneal fibrosis.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Brimonidine  



 The following reactions have been identified during post-marketing use of brimonidine tartrate ophthalmic solutions in clinical practice. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. The reactions, which have been chosen for inclusion due to either their seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to brimonidine tartrate ophthalmic solutions, or a combination of these factors, include: bradycardia, depression, iritis, keratoconjunctivitis sicca, miosis, nausea, skin reactions (including erythema, eyelid pruritus, rash, and vasodilation), and tachycardia. Apnea, bradycardia, hypotension, hypothermia, hypotonia, and somnolence have been reported in infants receiving brimonidine tartrate ophthalmic solutions.



     Oral Timolol/Oral Beta-blockers  



 The following additional adverse reactions have been reported in clinical experience with ORAL timolol maleate or other ORAL beta-blocking agents and may be considered potential effects of ophthalmic timolol maleate:  Allergic  : Erythematous rash, fever combined with aching and sore throat, laryngospasm with respiratory distress;  Body as a whole  : Decreased exercise tolerance, extremity pain, weight loss;  Cardiovascular  : Vasodilatation, worsening of arterial insufficiency;  Digestive  : Gastrointestinal pain, hepatomegaly, ischemic colitis, mesenteric arterial thrombosis, vomiting;  Hematologic  : Agranulocytosis, nonthrombocytopenic purpura, thrombocytopenic purpura;  Endocrine  : Hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia;  Skin  : Increased pigmentation, pruritus, skin irritation, sweating;  Musculoskeletal  : Arthralgia;  Nervous System/Psychiatric  : An acute reversible syndrome characterized by disorientation for time and place, decreased performance on neuropsychometrics, diminished concentration, emotional lability, local weakness, reversible mental depression progressing to catatonia, slightly clouded sensorium, vertigo;  Respiratory  : Bronchial obstruction, rales;  Urogenital  : Urination difficulties.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Potentiation of Respiratory Reactions Including Asthma (  5.1  ) 
 *  Cardiac Failure (  5.2  ) 
 *  Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (  5.3  ) 
 *  Potentiation of Vascular Insufficiency (  5.4  ) 
 *  Increased Reactivity to Allergens (  5.5  ) 
 *  Potentiation of Muscle Weakness (  5.6  ) 
 *  Masking of Hypoglycemic Symptoms in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus (  5.7  ) 
 *  Masking of Thyrotoxicosis (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Potentiation of Respiratory Reactions Including Asthma



   COMBIGAN  (r)    contains timolol maleate; and although administered topically can be absorbed systemically. Therefore, the same types of adverse reactions found with systemic administration of beta-adrenergic blocking agents may occur with topical administration. For example, severe respiratory reactions including death due to bronchospasm in patients with asthma have been reported following systemic or ophthalmic administration of timolol maleate (see CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  4  ).



    5.2 Cardiac Failure



  Sympathetic stimulation may be essential for support of the circulation in individuals with diminished myocardial contractility, and its inhibition by beta-adrenergic receptor blockade may precipitate more severe failure.



 In patients without a history of cardiac failure, continued depression of the myocardium with beta-blocking agents over a period of time can, in some cases, lead to cardiac failure. At the first sign or symptom of cardiac failure, COMBIGAN  (r)    should be discontinued (see also CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  4  ).



    5.3 Obstructive Pulmonary Disease



  Patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (e.g., chronic bronchitis, emphysema) of mild or moderate severity, bronchospastic disease, or a history of bronchospastic disease [other than bronchial asthma or a history of bronchial asthma, in which COMBIGAN  (r)    is contraindicated (see CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  4  )] should, in general, not receive beta-blocking agents, including COMBIGAN  (r)    .



    5.4 Potentiation of Vascular Insufficiency



   COMBIGAN  (r)    may potentiate syndromes associated with vascular insufficiency. COMBIGAN  (r)       should be used with caution in patients with depression, cerebral or coronary insufficiency, Raynaud's phenomenon, orthostatic hypotension, or thromboangiitis obliterans.



    5.5 Increased Reactivity to Allergens



  While taking beta-blockers, patients with a history of atopy or a history of severe anaphylactic reactions to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated accidental, diagnostic, or therapeutic challenge with such allergens. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat anaphylactic reactions.



    5.6 Potentiation of Muscle Weakness



  Beta-adrenergic blockade has been reported to potentiate muscle weakness consistent with certain myasthenic symptoms (e.g., diplopia, ptosis, and generalized weakness). Timolol has been reported rarely to increase muscle weakness in some patients with myasthenia gravis or myasthenic symptoms.



    5.7 Masking of Hypoglycemic Symptoms in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus



  Beta-adrenergic blocking agents should be administered with caution in patients subject to spontaneous hypoglycemia or to diabetic patients (especially those with labile diabetes) who are receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents. Beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agents may mask the signs and symptoms of acute hypoglycemia.



    5.8 Masking of Thyrotoxicosis



  Beta-adrenergic blocking agents may mask certain clinical signs (e.g., tachycardia) of hyperthyroidism. Patients suspected of developing thyrotoxicosis should be managed carefully to avoid abrupt withdrawal of beta-adrenergic blocking agents that might precipitate a thyroid storm.



    5.9 Contamination of Topical Ophthalmic Products After Use



  There have been reports of bacterial keratitis associated with the use of multiple-dose containers of topical ophthalmic products. These containers had been inadvertently contaminated by patients who, in most cases, had a concurrent corneal disease or a disruption of the ocular epithelial surface (see PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION  ,  17  ).



    5.10 Impairment of Beta-adrenergically Mediated Reflexes During Surgery



  The necessity or desirability of withdrawal of beta-adrenergic blocking agents prior to major surgery is controversial. Beta-adrenergic receptor blockade impairs the ability of the heart to respond to beta-adrenergically mediated reflex stimuli. This may augment the risk of general anesthesia in surgical procedures. Some patients receiving beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agents have experienced protracted severe hypotension during anesthesia. Difficulty in restarting and maintaining the heartbeat has also been reported. For these reasons, in patients undergoing elective surgery, some authorities recommend gradual withdrawal of beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agents.



 If necessary during surgery, the effects of beta-adrenergic blocking agents may be reversed by sufficient doses of adrenergic agonists.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
