<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cometriq" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the label:



 *  Perforations and Fistula [ see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  Hemorrhage [ see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Thromboembolic Events [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Wound Complications [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  ) ] 
 *  Hypertension [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.5  ) ] 
 *  Osteonecrosis of the Jaw [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.6  ) ] 
 *  Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.7  ) ] 
 *  Proteinuria [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.8  ) ] 
 *  Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome [ see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.9  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse drug reactions (&gt;=25%) are diarrhea, stomatitis, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES), decreased weight, decreased appetite, nausea, fatigue, oral pain, hair color changes, dysgeusia, hypertension, abdominal pain, and constipation. The most common laboratory abnormalities (&gt;=25%) are increased AST, increased ALT, lymphopenia, increased alkaline phosphatase, hypocalcemia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, hypophosphatemia, and hyperbilirubinemia. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Exelixis, Inc. at 1-855-500-3935 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of COMETRIQ was evaluated in 330 patients with progressive metastatic medullary thyroid cancer randomized to receive 140 mg COMETRIQ (n = 214) or placebo (n = 109) administered daily until disease progression or intolerable toxicity in a randomized, doubleblind, controlled trial. [  See  Clinical Studies  (  14)    .] The data described below reflect a median exposure to COMETRIQ for 204 days. The population exposed to COMETRIQ was 70% male, 90% white, and had a median age of 55 years.



 Adverse reactions which occurred in &gt;= 25% of COMETRIQ-treated patients occurring more frequently in the COMETRIQ arm with a between-arm difference of &gt;= 5% included, in order of decreasing frequency: diarrhea, stomatitis, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES), decreased weight, decreased appetite, nausea, fatigue, oral pain, hair color changes, dysgeusia, hypertension, abdominal pain, and constipation. The most common laboratory abnormalities (&gt;25%) were increased AST, increased ALT, lymphopenia, increased ALP, hypocalcemia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, hypophosphatemia, and hyperbilirubinemia. Grade 3-4 adverse reactions and laboratory abnormalities which occurred in &gt;= 5% of COMETRIQ-treated patients occurring more frequently in the COMETRIQ arm with a between-arm difference of &gt;= 2% included, in order of decreasing frequency; diarrhea, PPES, lymphopenia, hypocalcemia, fatigue, hypertension, asthenia, increased ALT, decreased weight, stomatitis, and decreased appetite (see  Table 1  ,  Table 2  ).



 Fatal adverse reactions occurred in 6% of patients receiving COMETRIQ and resulted from hemorrhage, pneumonia, septicemia, fistulas, cardiac arrest, respiratory failure, and unspecified death. Fatal adverse reactions occurred in 5% of patients receiving placebo and resulted from septicemia, pneumonia, and general deterioration.



 The dose was reduced in 79% of patients receiving COMETRIQ compared to 9% of patients receiving placebo. The median number of dosing delays was one in patients receiving COMETRIQ compared to none in patients receiving placebo. Adverse reactions led to study treatment discontinuation in 16% of patients receiving COMETRIQ and in 8% of patients receiving placebo. The most frequent adverse reactions leading to permanent discontinuation in patients treated with COMETRIQ were: hypocalcemia, increased lipase, PPES, diarrhea, fatigue, hypertension, nausea, pancreatitis, tracheal fistula formation and vomiting.



 Increased levels of thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) were observed in 57% of patients receiving COMETRIQ after the first dose compared to 19% of patients receiving placebo (regardless of baseline value). Ninety-two percent (92%) of patients on the COMETRIQ arm had a prior thyroidectomy, and 89% were taking thyroid hormone replacement prior to the first dose.



 Table 1 Per-Patient Incidence of Selected Adverse Reactions in Protocol XL184-301 Occurring at a Higher Incidence in COMETRIQ-Treated Patients [Between Arm Difference of &gt;= 5% (All Grades)National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Version 3.0 or &gt;= 2% (Grades 3-4)] 
    MedDRA System Organ Class/Preferred Terms        COMETRIQ(n=214)  Placebo(n=109)   
 AllGrades                                            Grades3-4     AllGrades     Grades3-4     
  
    GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                        
         Diarrhea                                         63            16            33            2         
         Stomatitis                                       51            5             6             0         
         Nausea                                           43            1             21            0         
         Oral pain                                        36            2             6             0         
         Constipation                                     27            0             6             0         
         Abdominal pain                                   27            3             13            1         
         Vomiting                                         24            2             2             1         
         Dysphagia                                        13            4             6             1         
         Dyspepsia                                        11            0             0             0         
         Hemorrhoids                                      9             0             3             0         
    GENERAL DISORDERS AND   ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS   
         Fatigue                                          41            9             28            3         
         Asthenia                                         21            6             15            1         
    INVESTIGATIONS                                    
         Decreased weight                                 48            5             10            0         
    METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS                
         Decreased appetite                               46            5             16            1         
         Dehydration                                      7             2             2             1         
    MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE   TISSUE DISORDERS   
         Arthralgia                                       14            1             7             0         
         Muscle spasms                                    12            0             5             0         
         Musculoskeletal chest pain                       9             1             4             0         
    NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                          
         Dysgeusia                                        34            0             6             0         
         Headache                                         18            0             8             0         
         Dizziness                                        14            0             7             0         
         Paresthesia                                      7             0             2             0         
         Peripheral sensory neuropathy                    7             0             0             0         
         Peripheral neuropathy                            5             0             0             0         
    PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                             
         Anxiety                                          9             0             2             0         
    RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND   MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS   
         Dysphonia                                        20            0             9             0         
    SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE   DISORDERS          
         PPES                                             50            13            2             0         
         Hair color changes/        depigmentation, graying       34            0             1             0         
         Rash                                             19            1             10            0         
         Dry skin                                         19            0             3             0         
         Alopecia                                         16            0             2             0         
         Erythema                                         11            1             2             0         
         Hyperkeratosis                                   7             0             0             0         
    VASCULAR DISORDERS                                
         Hypertension                                     33            8             4             0         
         Hypotension                                      7             1             0             0         
          Table 2 Percent-Patient Incidence of Laboratory Abnormalities Occurring at a Higher Incidence in COMETRIQ-Treated Patients in Protocol XL184-301 [Between Arm Difference of &gt;= 5% (All Grades) or &gt;= 2% (Grades 3-4)] 
    Adverse Event                                    COMETRIQ(n=214)  Placebo(N=109)   
                                                      AllGrades      Grade3-4     AllGrades      Grade3-4     
  
    Chemistries                                                                                               
         Increased AST                                    86            3             35            2         
         Increased ALT                                    86            6             41            2         
         Increased ALP                                    52            3             35            3         
         Hypocalcemia                                     52            12            27            3         
         Hypophosphatemia                                 28            3             10            1         
         Hyperbilirubinemia                               25            2             14            5         
         Hypomagnesemia                                   19            1             4             0         
         Hypokalemia                                      18            4             9             3         
         Hyponatremia                                     10            2             5             0         
    Hematologic                                                                                               
         Lymphopenia                                      53            16            51            11        
         Neutropenia                                      35            3             15            2         
         Thrombocytopenia                                 35            0             4             3         
                                                      
    ALT, alanine aminotransferase; ALP, alkaline phosphatase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase     
           Nearly all COMETRIQ-treated patients (96% vs. 84% placebo) experienced elevated blood pressure and there was a doubling in the incidence of overt hypertension in COMETRIQ-treated patients over placebo-treated patients (61% vs. 30%) according to modified Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure (JNC) staging criteria. No patients developed malignant hypertension.
 

 Table 3 Per-Patient Incidence of Hypertension in Protocol XL184-301 
    Hypertension, JNCStage                                                    COMETRIQN=211(%)  PlaceboN=107(%)   
    Normal: Grade 0: Systolic &lt; 120 mmHg and Diastolic &lt; 80 mmHg                   4             15        
    Pre-hypertension: Systolic &gt;= 120 mmHg or Diastolic &gt;= 80 mmHg                 34            54        
    Stage 1: Systolic &gt;= 140 mmHg or Diastolic &gt;= 90 mmHg                          46            25        
    Stage 2: Systolic &gt;= 160 mmHg or Diastolic &gt;= 100 mmHg                         15            5         
    Malignant: Diastolic &gt;= 120 mmHg                                               0             0         
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: PERFORATIONS AND FISTULAS, and HEMORRHAGE

  WARNING: PERFORATIONS AND FISTULAS, and HEMORRHAGE

    Perforations and fistulas: Gastrointestinal perforations occurred in 3% and fistula formation in 1% of COMETRIQTM-treated patients. Discontinue COMETRIQ for perforation or for fistula formation [See       Warnings and Precautions       (  5.1  )].  



   Hemorrhage: Severe, sometimes fatal, hemorrhage including hemoptysis and gastrointestinal hemorrhage occurred in 3% of COMETRIQ-treated patients. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of bleeding. Do not administer COMETRIQ to patients with severe hemorrhage [See       Warnings and Precautions       (  5.2  )].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: PERFORATIONS AND FISTULAS, andHEMORRHAGE  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Perforations and Fistulas: Gastrointestinal perforations occurred in 3% and fistula formation in 1% of COMETRIQ-treated patients. Discontinue COMETRIQ in patients with perforation or fistula. (5.1) 
 *  Hemorrhage: Severe, sometimes fatal, hemorrhage including hemoptysis and gastrointestinal hemorrhage occurred in 3% of COMETRIQ-treated patients. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of bleeding. Do not administer COMETRIQ to patients with severe hemorrhage. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Thrombotic Events: Discontinue COMETRIQ for myocardial infarction, cerebral infarction, or other serious arterial thromboembolic events. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Wound Complications: Withhold COMETRIQ for dehiscence or complications requiring medical intervention. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hypertension: Monitor blood pressure regularly. Discontinue COMETRIQ for hypertensive crisis. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Osteonecrosis of the jaw: Discontinue COMETRIQ. (  5.6  ). 
 *  Palmar-plantar Erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES): Interrupt COMETRIQ, decrease dose. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Proteinuria: Monitor urine protein. Discontinue for nephrotic syndrome. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS): Discontinue COMETRIQ. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Embryofetal toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise women of potential risk to a fetus. (  5.11  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Perforations and Fistulas



  Gastrointestinal (GI) perforations and fistulas were reported in 3% and 1% of COMETRIQ-treated patients, respectively. All were serious and one GI fistula was fatal (&lt; 1%). Non-GI fistulas including tracheal/esophageal were reported in 4% of COMETRIQ-treated patients. Two (1%) of these were fatal.



 Monitor patients for symptoms of perforations and fistulas. Discontinue COMETRIQ in patients who experience a perforation or a fistula.



    5.2 Hemorrhage



  Serious and sometimes fatal hemorrhage occurred with COMETRIQ. The incidence of Grade &gt;=3 hemorrhagic events was higher in COMETRIQ-treated patients compared with placebo (3% vs. 1%).



 Do not administer COMETRIQ to patients with a recent history of hemorrhage or hemoptysis.



    5.3 Thrombotic Events



  COMETRIQ treatment results in an increased incidence of thrombotic events (venous thromboembolism: 6% vs. 3% and arterial thromboembolism: 2% vs. 0% in COMETRIQ-treated and placebo-treated patients, respectively).



 Discontinue COMETRIQ in patients who develop an acute myocardial infarction or any other clinically significant arterial thromboembolic complication.



    5.4 Wound Complications



  Wound complications have been reported with COMETRIQ. Stop treatment with COMETRIQ at least 28 days prior to scheduled surgery. Resume COMETRIQ therapy after surgery based on clinical judgment of adequate wound healing. Withhold COMETRIQ in patients with dehiscence or wound healing complications requiring medical intervention.



    5.5 Hypertension



  COMETRIQ treatment results in an increased incidence of treatment-emergent hypertension with Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure (modified JNC criteria) stage 1 or 2 hypertension identified in 61% in COMETRIQ-treated patients compared with 30% of placebo-treated patients in the randomized trial. Monitor blood pressure prior to initiation and regularly during COMETRIQ treatment. Withhold COMETRIQ for hypertension that is not adequately controlled with medical management; when controlled, resume COMETRIQ at a reduced dose. Discontinue COMETRIQ for severe hypertension that cannot be controlled with anti-hypertensive therapy.



    5.6 Osteonecrosis of the Jaw



  Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ) occurred in 1% of COMETRIQ-treated patients. ONJ can manifest as jaw pain, osteomyelitis, osteitis, bone erosion, tooth or periodontal infection, toothache, gingival ulceration or erosion, persistent jaw pain or slow healing of the mouth or jaw after dental surgery. Perform an oral examination prior to initiation of COMETRIQ and periodically during COMETRIQ therapy. Advise patients regarding good oral hygiene practices. For invasive dental procedures, withhold COMETRIQ treatment for at least 28 days prior to scheduled surgery, if possible.



    5.7 Palmar-Plantar Erythrodysesthesia Syndrome



  Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (PPES) occurred in 50% of patients treated with COMETRIQ and was severe (&gt;= Grade 3) in 13% of patients. Withhold COMETRIQ in patients who develop intolerable Grade 2 PPES or Grade 3-4 PPES until improvement to Grade 1; resume COMETRIQ at a reduced dose.



    5.8 Proteinuria



  Proteinuria was observed in 4 (2%) of patients receiving COMETRIQ, including one with nephrotic syndrome, as compared to none of the patients receiving placebo. Monitor urine protein regularly during COMETRIQ treatment. Discontinue COMETRIQ in patients who develop nephrotic syndrome.



    5.9 Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome



  Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS), a syndrome of subcortical vasogenic edema diagnosed by characteristic finding on MRI, occurred in one (&lt;1%) patient. Perform an evaluation for RPLS in any patient presenting with seizures, headache, visual disturbances, confusion or altered mental function. Discontinue COMETRIQ in patients who develop RPLS.



    5.10 Drug Interactions



  Avoid administration of COMETRIQ with agents that are strong CYP3A4 inducers or inhibitors [see   Dosage and Administration   (  2.1  ) and   Drug Interactions   (  7.1  ,  7.2  )].  



    5.11 Hepatic Impairment



  COMETRIQ is not recommended for use in patients with moderate or severe hepatic impairment [ see   Use in Specific Populations   (  8.6  )  ].



    5.12 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  COMETRIQ can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Cabozantinib was embryolethal in rats at exposures below the recommended human dose, with increased incidences of skeletal variations in rats and visceral variations and malformations in rabbits. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [See   Use in Specific Populations   (  8.1  )].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
