<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="copaxone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    In controlled studies of COPAXONE 20 mg/mL, most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10% and &gt;=1.5 times higher than placebo) were: injection site reactions, vasodilatation, rash, dyspnea, and chest pain (  6.1  ) 
 *    In a controlled study of COPAXONE 40 mg/mL, most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10% and &gt;=1.5 times higher than placebo) were: injection site reactions (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact TEVA at 1-800-221-4026 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials  



   COPAXONE 20 mg per mL per day  



 Among 563 patients treated with COPAXONE in blinded placebo-controlled trials, approximately 5% of the subjects discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were: injection site reactions, dyspnea, urticaria, vasodilatation, and hypersensitivity. The most common adverse reactions were: injection site reactions, vasodilatation, rash, dyspnea, and chest pain.



 Table 1 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with COPAXONE 20 mg per mL in the placebo-controlled trials. These signs and symptoms were numerically more common in patients treated with COPAXONE than in patients treated with placebo. Adverse reactions were usually mild in intensity.



 Table 1: Adverse reactions in controlled clinical trials with an incidence &gt;=2% of patients and more frequent with COPAXONE (20 mg per mL daily) than with placebo 
                                                                                COPAXONE  20 mg/mL (n=563)    Placebo  (n=564)    
  Blood And Lymphatic System Disorders                Lymphadenopathy           7%                 3%         
  Cardiac Disorders                                   Palpitations              9%                 4%         
  Tachycardia                                         5%                        2%                 
  Eye Disorders                                       Eye Disorder              3%                 1%         
  Diplopia                                            3%                        2%                 
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                          Nausea                    15%                11%        
  Vomiting                                            7%                        4%                 
  Dysphagia                                           2%                        1%                 
  General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions    Injection Site Erythema    43%                10%        
  Injection Site Pain                                 40%                       20%                
  Injection Site Pruritus                             27%                       4%                 
  Injection Site Mass                                 26%                       6%                 
  Asthenia                                            22%                       21%                
  Pain                                                20%                       17%                
  Injection Site Edema                                19%                       4%                 
  Chest Pain                                          13%                       6%                 
  Injection Site Inflammation                         9%                        1%                 
  Edema                                               8%                        2%                 
  Injection Site Reaction                             8%                        1%                 
  Pyrexia                                             6%                        5%                 
  Injection Site Hypersensitivity                     4%                        0%                 
  Local Reaction                                      3%                        1%                 
  Chills                                              3%                        1%                 
  Face Edema                                          3%                        1%                 
  Edema Peripheral                                    3%                        2%                 
  Injection Site Fibrosis                             2%                        1%                 
  Injection Site Atrophy*                             2%                        0%                 
  Immune System Disorders                             Hypersensitivity          3%                 2%         
  Infections And Infestations                         Infection                 30%                28%        
  Influenza                                           14%                       13%                
  Rhinitis                                            7%                        5%                 
  Bronchitis                                          6%                        5%                 
  Gastroenteritis                                     6%                        4%                 
  Vaginal Candidiasis                                 4%                        2%                 
  Metabolism And Nutrition Disorders                  Weight Increased          3%                 1%         
  Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders     Back Pain                 12%                10%        
  Neoplasms Benign, Malignant And Unspecified (Incl Cysts And Polyps)    Benign Neoplasm of Skin    2%                 1%         
  Nervous System Disorders                            Tremor                    4%                 2%         
  Migraine                                            4%                        2%                 
  Syncope                                             3%                        2%                 
  Speech Disorder                                     2%                        1%                 
  Psychiatric Disorders                               Anxiety                   13%                10%        
  Nervousness                                         2%                        1%                 
  Renal And Urinary Disorders                         Micturition Urgency       5%                 4%         
  Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders     Dyspnea                   14%                4%         
  Cough                                               6%                        5%                 
  Laryngospasm                                        2%                        1%                 
  Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders              Rash                      19%                11%        
  Hyperhidrosis                                       7%                        5%                 
  Pruritus                                            5%                        4%                 
  Urticaria                                           3%                        1%                 
  Skin Disorder                                       3%                        1%                 
  Vascular Disorders                                  Vasodilatation            20%                5%         
          *Injection site atrophy comprises terms relating to localized lipoatrophy at injection site
 

 Adverse reactions which occurred only in 4 to 5 more subjects in the COPAXONE group than in the placebo group (less than 1% difference), but for which a relationship to COPAXONE could not be excluded, were arthralgia and herpes simplex.



 Laboratory analyses were performed on all patients participating in the clinical program for COPAXONE. Clinically-significant laboratory values for hematology, chemistry, and urinalysis were similar for both COPAXONE and placebo groups in blinded clinical trials. In controlled trials one patient discontinued treatment due to thrombocytopenia (16 x10  9  /L), which resolved after discontinuation of treatment.



 Data on adverse reactions occurring in the controlled clinical trials of COPAXONE 20 mg per mL were analyzed to evaluate differences based on sex. No clinically-significant differences were identified. Ninety-six percent of patients in these clinical trials were Caucasian. The majority of patients treated with COPAXONE were between the ages of 18 and 45. Consequently, data are inadequate to perform an analysis of the adverse reaction incidence related to clinically-relevant age subgroups.



   Other Adverse Reactions  



 In the paragraphs that follow, the frequencies of less commonly reported adverse clinical reactions are presented. Because the reports include reactions observed in open and uncontrolled premarketing studies (n= 979), the role of COPAXONE in their causation cannot be reliably determined. Furthermore, variability associated with adverse reaction reporting, the terminology used to describe adverse reactions, etc., limit the value of the quantitative frequency estimates provided. Reaction frequencies are calculated as the number of patients who used COPAXONE and reported a reaction divided by the total number of patients exposed to COPAXONE. All reported reactions are included except those already listed in the previous table, those too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug. Reactions are further classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions:  Frequent  adverse reactions are defined as those occurring in at least 1/100 patients and  infrequent  adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients.



   Body as a Whole:  



   Frequent:  Abscess



   Infrequent:  Injection site hematoma, moon face, cellulitis, hernia, injection site abscess, serum sickness, suicide attempt, injection site hypertrophy, injection site melanosis, lipoma, and photosensitivity reaction.



   Cardiovascular:  



   Frequent:  Hypertension.



   Infrequent:  Hypotension, midsystolic click, systolic murmur, atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, fourth heart sound, postural hypotension, and varicose veins.



   Digestive:  



   Infrequent:  Dry mouth, stomatitis, burning sensation on tongue, cholecystitis, colitis, esophageal ulcer, esophagitis, gastrointestinal carcinoma, gum hemorrhage, hepatomegaly, increased appetite, melena, mouth ulceration, pancreas disorder, pancreatitis, rectal hemorrhage, tenesmus, tongue discoloration, and duodenal ulcer.



   Endocrine:  



   Infrequent:  Goiter, hyperthyroidism, and hypothyroidism.



   Gastrointestinal:  



   Frequent:  Bowel urgency, oral moniliasis, salivary gland enlargement, tooth caries, and ulcerative stomatitis.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  



   Infrequent:  Leukopenia, anemia, cyanosis, eosinophilia, hematemesis, lymphedema, pancytopenia, and splenomegaly.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  



   Infrequent:  Weight loss, alcohol intolerance, Cushing's syndrome, gout, abnormal healing, and xanthoma.



   Musculoskeletal:  



   Infrequent:  Arthritis, muscle atrophy, bone pain, bursitis, kidney pain, muscle disorder, myopathy, osteomyelitis, tendon pain, and tenosynovitis.



   Nervous:  



   Frequent:  Abnormal dreams, emotional lability, and stupor.



   Infrequent:  Aphasia, ataxia, convulsion, circumoral paresthesia, depersonalization, hallucinations, hostility, hypokinesia, coma, concentration disorder, facial paralysis, decreased libido, manic reaction, memory impairment, myoclonus, neuralgia, paranoid reaction, paraplegia, psychotic depression, and transient stupor.



   Respiratory:  



   Frequent:  Hyperventilation and hay fever.



   Infrequent:  Asthma, pneumonia, epistaxis, hypoventilation, and voice alteration.



   Skin and Appendages:  



   Frequent:  Eczema, herpes zoster, pustular rash, skin atrophy, and warts.



   Infrequent:  Dry skin, skin hypertrophy, dermatitis, furunculosis, psoriasis, angioedema, contact dermatitis, erythema nodosum, fungal dermatitis, maculopapular rash, pigmentation, benign skin neoplasm, skin carcinoma, skin striae, and vesiculobullous rash.



   Special Senses  :



   Frequent:  Visual field defect.



   Infrequent:  Dry eyes, otitis externa, ptosis, cataract, corneal ulcer, mydriasis, optic neuritis, photophobia, and taste loss.



   Urogenital:  



   Frequent:  Amenorrhea, hematuria, impotence, menorrhagia, suspicious papanicolaou smear, urinary frequency, and vaginal hemorrhage.



   Infrequent:  Vaginitis, flank pain (kidney), abortion, breast engorgement, breast enlargement, carcinoma  in situ  cervix, fibrocystic breast, kidney calculus, nocturia, ovarian cyst, priapism, pyelonephritis, abnormal sexual function, and urethritis.



   COPAXONE 40 mg per mL three times per week  



 Among 943 patients treated with COPAXONE 40 mg per mL three times per week in a blinded, placebo-controlled trial, approximately 3% of the subjects discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction. The most common adverse reactions were injection site reactions, which were also the most common cause of discontinuation.



 Table 2 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with COPAXONE 40 mg per mL in the blinded, placebo-controlled trial. These signs and symptoms were numerically more common in patients treated with COPAXONE 40 mg per mL than in patients treated with placebo. Adverse reactions were usually mild in intensity.



 Table 2: Adverse reactions in a controlled clinical trial with an incidence &gt;=2% of patients and more frequent with COPAXONE (40 mg per mL three times per week) than with placebo 
                                                    COPAXONE  40 mg/mL  (n=943)    Placebo  (n=461)    
  General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions    Injection Site Erythema        22%             2%         
  Injection Site Pain                               10%                            2%              
  Injection Site Mass                               6%                             0%              
  Injection Site Pruritus                           6%                             0%              
  Injection Site Edema                              6%                             0%              
  Pyrexia                                           3%                             2%              
  Influenza-like Illness                            3%                             2%              
  Injection Site Inflammation                       2%                             0%              
  Chills                                            2%                             0%              
  Chest Pain                                        2%                             1%              
  Infections And Infestations                       Nasopharyngitis                11%             9%         
  Respiratory Tract Infection Viral                 3%                             2%              
  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    Dyspnea                        3%              0%         
  Vascular Disorders                                Vasodilatation                 3%              0%         
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                        Nausea                         2%              1%         
  Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders            Erythema                       2%              0%         
  Rash                                              2%                             1%              
          No new adverse reactions appeared in subjects treated with COPAXONE 40 mg per mL three times per week as compared to subjects treated with COPAXONE 20 mg per mL per day in clinical trials and during postmarketing experience. Data on adverse reactions occurring in the controlled clinical trial of COPAXONE 40 mg per mL were analyzed to evaluate differences based on sex. No clinically significant differences were identified. Ninety-eight percent of patients in this clinical trial were Caucasian and the majority were between the ages of 18 and 50. Consequently, data are inadequate to perform an analysis of the adverse reaction incidence related to clinically-relevant age groups.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events occurring under treatment with COPAXONE 20 mg per mL since market introduction and not mentioned above have been identified during postapproval use of COPAXONE. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole:  sepsis; SLE syndrome; hydrocephalus; enlarged abdomen; allergic reaction; anaphylactoid reaction



   Cardiovascular System:  thrombosis; peripheral vascular disease; pericardial effusion; myocardial infarct; deep thrombophlebitis; coronary occlusion; congestive heart failure; cardiomyopathy; cardiomegaly; arrhythmia; angina pectoris



   Digestive System:  tongue edema; stomach ulcer; hemorrhage; liver function abnormality; liver damage; hepatitis; eructation; cirrhosis of the liver; cholelithiasis



   Hemic and Lymphatic System:  thrombocytopenia; lymphoma-like reaction; acute leukemia



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  hypercholesterolemia



   Musculoskeletal System:  rheumatoid arthritis; generalized spasm



   Nervous System:  myelitis; meningitis; CNS neoplasm; cerebrovascular accident; brain edema; abnormal dreams; aphasia; convulsion; neuralgia



   Respiratory System:  pulmonary embolus; pleural effusion; carcinoma of lung



   Special Senses:  glaucoma; blindness



 Urogenital System: urogenital neoplasm; urine abnormality; ovarian carcinoma; nephrosis; kidney failure; breast carcinoma; bladder carcinoma; urinary frequency
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Immediate Post-Injection Reaction (flushing, chest pain, palpitations, anxiety, dyspnea, throat constriction, and/or urticaria), generally transient and self-limiting (  5.1  ) 
 *    Chest pain, usually transient (  5.2  ) 
 *    Lipoatrophy and skin necrosis may occur. Instruct patients in proper injection technique and to rotate injection sites (  5.3  ) 
 *    COPAXONE can modify immune response (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Immediate Post-Injection Reaction



   Approximately 16% of patients exposed to COPAXONE 20 mg per mL in the 5 placebo-controlled trials compared to 4% of those on placebo, and approximately 2% of patients exposed to COPAXONE 40 mg per mL in a placebo-controlled trial compared to none on placebo, experienced a constellation of symptoms immediately after injection that included at least two of the following: flushing, chest pain, palpitations, anxiety, dyspnea, constriction of the throat, and urticaria. In general, these symptoms have their onset several months after the initiation of treatment, although they may occur earlier, and a given patient may experience one or several episodes of these symptoms. Whether or not any of these symptoms actually represent a specific syndrome is uncertain. Typically, the symptoms were transient and self-limited and did not require treatment; however, there have been reports of patients with similar symptoms who received emergency medical care. Whether an immunologic or nonimmunologic mechanism mediates these episodes, or whether several similar episodes seen in a given patient have identical mechanisms, is unknown.  



    5.2 Chest Pain



   Approximately 13% of COPAXONE 20 mg per mL patients in the 5 placebo-controlled studies compared to 6% of placebo patients, and approximately 2% of patients exposed to COPAXONE 40 mg per mL in a placebo-controlled trial compared to 1% of placebo patients, experienced at least one episode of transient chest pain. While some of these episodes occurred in the context of the Immediate Post-Injection Reaction described above, many did not. The temporal relationship of this chest pain to an injection was not always known. The pain was usually transient, often unassociated with other symptoms, and appeared to have no clinical sequelae. Some patients experienced more than one such episode, and episodes usually began at least 1 month after the initiation of treatment. The pathogenesis of this symptom is unknown  .



    5.3 Lipoatrophy and Skin Necrosis



   At injection sites, localized lipoatrophy and, rarely, injection site skin necrosis may occur. Lipoatrophy occurred in approximately 2% of patients exposed to COPAXONE 20 mg per mL in the 5 placebo-controlled trials compared to none on placebo, and 0.5% of patients exposed to COPAXONE 40 mg per mL in a single placebo-controlled trial and none on placebo. Skin necrosis has only been observed in the post-marketing setting. Lipoatrophy may occur at various times after treatment onset (sometimes after several months) and is thought to be permanent. There is no known therapy for lipoatrophy. To assist in possibly minimizing these events, the patient should be advised to follow proper injection technique and to rotate injection sites with each injection  .



    5.4 Potential Effects on Immune Response



  Because COPAXONE can modify immune response, it may interfere with immune functions. For example, treatment with COPAXONE may interfere with the recognition of foreign antigens in a way that would undermine the body's tumor surveillance and its defenses against infection. There is no evidence that COPAXONE does this, but there has not been a systematic evaluation of this risk. Because COPAXONE is an antigenic material, it is possible that its use may lead to the induction of host responses that are untoward, but systematic surveillance for these effects has not been undertaken.



 Although COPAXONE is intended to minimize the autoimmune response to myelin, there is the possibility that continued alteration of cellular immunity due to chronic treatment with COPAXONE may result in untoward effects.



 Glatiramer acetate-reactive antibodies are formed in most patients receiving glatiramer acetate. Studies in both the rat and monkey have suggested that immune complexes are deposited in the renal glomeruli. Furthermore, in a controlled trial of 125 RRMS patients given COPAXONE 20 mg per mL, subcutaneously every day for 2 years, serum IgG levels reached at least 3 times baseline values in 80% of patients by 3 months of initiation of treatment. By 12 months of treatment, however, 30% of patients still had IgG levels at least 3 times baseline values, and 90% had levels above baseline by 12 months. The antibodies are exclusively of the IgG subtype and predominantly of the IgG-1 subtype. No IgE type antibodies could be detected in any of the 94 sera tested; nevertheless, anaphylaxis can be associated with the administration of most any foreign substance, and therefore, this risk cannot be excluded.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
