<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="coreg0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The safety profile of COREG CR was similar to that observed for immediate-release carvedilol. Most common adverse events seen with immediate-release carvedilol (  6.1  ):



 *    Heart failure and left ventricular dysfunction following myocardial infarction (&gt;=10%): Dizziness, fatigue, hypotension, diarrhea, hyperglycemia, asthenia, bradycardia, weight increase. 
 *    Hypertension (&gt;=5%): Dizziness. 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Carvedilol has been evaluated for safety in subjects with heart failure (mild, moderate, and severe), in subjects with left ventricular dysfunction following myocardial infarction, and in hypertensive subjects. The observed adverse event profile was consistent with the pharmacology of the drug and the health status of the subjects in the clinical trials. Adverse events reported for each of these populations reflecting the use of either COREG CR or immediate-release carvedilol are provided below. Excluded are adverse events considered too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug because they were associated with the condition being treated or are very common in the treated population. Rates of adverse events were generally similar across demographic subsets (men and women, elderly and non-elderly, blacks and non-blacks). COREG CR has been evaluated for safety in a 4-week (2 weeks of immediate-release carvedilol and 2 weeks of COREG CR) clinical trial (n = 187) which included 157 subjects with stable mild, moderate, or severe chronic heart failure and 30 subjects with left ventricular dysfunction following acute myocardial infarction. The profile of adverse events observed with COREG CR in this small, short-term trial was generally similar to that observed with immediate-release carvedilol. Differences in safety would not be expected based on the similarity in plasma levels for COREG CR and immediate-release carvedilol.



       Heart Failure    

  The following information describes the safety experience in heart failure with immediate-release carvedilol.



 Carvedilol has been evaluated for safety in heart failure in more than 4,500 subjects worldwide of whom more than 2,100 participated in placebo-controlled clinical trials. Approximately 60% of the total treated population in placebo-controlled clinical trials received carvedilol for at least 6 months and 30% received carvedilol for at least 12 months. In the COMET trial, 1,511 subjects with mild-to-moderate heart failure were treated with carvedilol for up to 5.9 years (mean: 4.8 years). Both in US clinical trials in mild-to-moderate heart failure that compared carvedilol in daily doses up to 100 mg (n = 765) with placebo (n = 437), and in a multinational clinical trial in severe heart failure (COPERNICUS) that compared carvedilol in daily doses up to 50 mg (n = 1,156) with placebo (n = 1,133), discontinuation rates for adverse experiences were similar in carvedilol and placebo subjects. In placebo-controlled clinical trials, the only cause of discontinuation &gt;1%, and occurring more often on carvedilol was dizziness (1.3% on carvedilol, 0.6% on placebo in the COPERNICUS trial).



 Table 2 shows adverse events reported in subjects with mild-to-moderate heart failure enrolled in US placebo-controlled clinical trials, and with severe heart failure enrolled in the COPERNICUS trial. Shown are adverse events that occurred more frequently in drug-treated subjects than placebo-treated subjects with an incidence of &gt;3% in subjects treated with carvedilol regardless of causality. Median trial medication exposure was 6.3 months for both carvedilol and placebo subjects in the trials of mild-to-moderate heart failure, and 10.4 months in the trial of subjects with severe heart failure. The adverse event profile of carvedilol observed in the long-term COMET trial was generally similar to that observed in the US Heart Failure Trials.



 Table 2. Adverse Events (%) Occurring More Frequently With Immediate-Release Carvedilol Than With Placebo in Subjects With Mild-to-Moderate Heart Failure (HF) Enrolled in US Heart Failure Trials or in Subjects With Severe Heart Failure in the COPERNICUS Trial (Incidence &gt;3% in Subjects Treated With Carvedilol, Regardless of Causality) 
                                           Body System/                           
                                           Adverse Event                            Mild-to-Moderate HF    Severe HF       
  Carvedilol                               Placebo           Carvedilol      Placebo           
  (n = 765)                                (n = 437)         (n = 1,156)     (n = 1,133)       
  Body as a Whole                                                                                                
                                          Asthenia                                
                                                                                    7                 7               11                9                 
                                          Fatigue                                 
                                                                                    24                22              -                 -                 
                                          Digoxin level increased                 
                                                                                    5                 4               2                 1                 
                                          Edema generalized                       
                                                                                    5                 3               6                 5                 
                                          Edema dependent                         
                                                                                    4                 2               -                 -                 
  Cardiovascular                                                                                                 
                                          Bradycardia                             
                                                                                    9                 1               10                3                 
                                          Hypotension                             
                                                                                    9                 3               14                8                 
                                          Syncope                                 
                                                                                    3                 3               8                 5                 
                                          Angina pectoris                         
                                                                                    2                 3               6                 4                 
  Central Nervous System                                                                                         
                                          Dizziness                               
                                                                                    32                19              24                17                
                                          Headache                                
                                                                                    8                 7               5                 3                 
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                               
                                          Diarrhea                                
                                                                                    12                6               5                 3                 
                                          Nausea                                  
                                                                                    9                 5               4                 3                 
                                          Vomiting                                
                                                                                    6                 4               1                 2                 
  Metabolic                                                                                                      
                                          Hyperglycemia                           
                                                                                    12                8               5                 3                 
                                          Weight increase                         
                                                                                    10                7               12                11                
                                          BUN increased                           
                                                                                    6                 5               -                 -                 
                                          NPN increased                           
                                                                                    6                 5               -                 -                 
                                          Hypercholesterolemia                    
                                                                                    4                 3               1                 1                 
                                          Edema peripheral                        
                                                                                    2                 1               7                 6                 
  Musculoskeletal                                                                                                
                                          Arthralgia                              
                                                                                    6                 5               1                 1                 
  Respiratory                                                                                                    
                                          Cough increased                         
                                                                                    8                 9               5                 4                 
                                          Rales                                   
                                                                                    4                 4               4                 2                 
  Vision                                                                                                         
                                          Vision abnormal                         
                                                                                    5                 2               -                 -                 
           Cardiac failure and dyspnea were also reported in these trials, but the rates were equal or greater in subjects who received placebo.
 

 The following adverse events were reported with a frequency of &gt;1% but &lt;=3% and more frequently with carvedilol in either the US placebo-controlled trials in subjects with mild-to-moderate heart failure, or in subjects with severe heart failure in the COPERNICUS trial.



   Incidence &gt;1% to &lt;=3%  



   Body as a Whole:  Allergy, malaise, hypovolemia, fever, leg edema.



   Cardiovascular:  Fluid overload, postural hypotension, aggravated angina pectoris, AV block, palpitation, hypertension.



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  Hypesthesia, vertigo, paresthesia.



   Gastrointestinal:  Melena, periodontitis.



   Liver and Biliary System:  SGPT increased, SGOT increased.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Hyperuricemia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, increased alkaline phosphatase, glycosuria, hypervolemia, diabetes mellitus, GGT increased, weight loss, hyperkalemia, creatinine increased.



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle cramps.



   Platelet, Bleeding, and Clotting:  Prothrombin decreased, purpura, thrombocytopenia.



   Psychiatric:  Somnolence.



   Reproductive, male:  Impotence.



   Special Senses:  Blurred vision.



   Urinary System:  Renal insufficiency, albuminuria, hematuria.



       Left Ventricular Dysfunction Following Myocardial Infarction    

  The following information describes the safety experience in left ventricular dysfunction following acute myocardial infarction with immediate-release carvedilol.



 Carvedilol has been evaluated for safety in survivors of an acute myocardial infarction with left ventricular dysfunction in the CAPRICORN trial which involved 969 subjects who received carvedilol and 980 who received placebo. Approximately 75% of the subjects received carvedilol for at least 6 months and 53% received carvedilol for at least 12 months. Subjects were treated for an average of 12.9 months and 12.8 months with carvedilol and placebo, respectively.



 The most common adverse events reported with carvedilol in the CAPRICORN trial were consistent with the profile of the drug in the US heart failure trials and the COPERNICUS trial. The only additional adverse events reported in CAPRICORN in &gt;3% of the subjects and more commonly on carvedilol were dyspnea, anemia, and lung edema. The following adverse events were reported with a frequency of &gt;1% but &lt;=3% and more frequently with carvedilol: flu syndrome, cerebrovascular accident, peripheral vascular disorder, hypotonia, depression, gastrointestinal pain, arthritis, and gout. The overall rates of discontinuations due to adverse events were similar in both groups of subjects. In this database, the only cause of discontinuation &gt;1%, and occurring more often on carvedilol was hypotension (1.5% on carvedilol, 0.2% on placebo).



       Hypertension    

  COREG CR was evaluated for safety in an 8-week double-blind trial in 337 subjects with essential hypertension. The profile of adverse events observed with COREG CR was generally similar to that observed with immediate-release carvedilol. The overall rates of discontinuations due to adverse events were similar between COREG CR and placebo.



 Table 3. Adverse Events (%) Occurring More Frequently With COREG CR Than With Placebo in Subjects With Hypertension (Incidence &gt;=1% in Subjects Treated With Carvedilol, Regardless of Causality) 
  Adverse Event                                COREG CR  (n = 253)                 Placebo  (n = 84)        
  Nasopharyngitis                              4                                   0                        
  Dizziness                                    2                                   1                        
  Nausea                                       2                                   0                        
  Edema peripheral                             2                                   1                        
  Nasal congestion                             1                                   0                        
  Paresthesia                                  1                                   0                        
  Sinus congestion                             1                                   0                        
  Diarrhea                                     1                                   0                        
  Insomnia                                     1                                   0                        
         The following information describes the safety experience in hypertension with immediate-release carvedilol.
 

 Carvedilol has been evaluated for safety in hypertension in more than 2,193 subjects in US clinical trials and in 2,976 subjects in international clinical trials. Approximately 36% of the total treated population received carvedilol for at least 6 months. In general, carvedilol was well tolerated at doses up to 50 mg daily. Most adverse events reported during carvedilol therapy were of mild to moderate severity. In US controlled clinical trials directly comparing carvedilol monotherapy in doses up to 50 mg (n = 1,142) with placebo (n = 462), 4.9% of carvedilol subjects discontinued for adverse events versus 5.2% of placebo subjects. Although there was no overall difference in discontinuation rates, discontinuations were more common in the carvedilol group for postural hypotension (1% versus 0). The overall incidence of adverse events in US placebo-controlled trials was found to increase with increasing dose of carvedilol. For individual adverse events this could only be distinguished for dizziness, which increased in frequency from 2% to 5% as total daily dose increased from 6.25 mg to 50 mg as single or divided doses.



 Table 4 shows adverse events in US placebo-controlled clinical trials for hypertension that occurred with an incidence of &gt;=1% regardless of causality, and that were more frequent in drug-treated subjects than placebo-treated subjects.



 Table 4. Adverse Events (% Occurrence) in US Placebo-Controlled Hypertension Trials With Immediate-Release Carvedilol (Incidence &gt;=1% in Subjects Treated With Carvedilol, Regardless of Causality)* 
                                                            Adverse Event                                           
                                                                                                                      Carvedilol  (n = 1,142)    Placebo  (n = 462)     
  Cardiovascular                                                                                             
                                                           Bradycardia                                              
                                                                                                                      2                         -                      
                                                           Postural hypotension                                     
                                                                                                                      2                         -                      
                                                           Peripheral edema                                         
                                                                                                                      1                         -                      
  Central Nervous System                                                                                     
                                                           Dizziness                                                
                                                                                                                      6                         5                      
                                                           Insomnia                                                 
                                                                                                                      2                         1                      
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                           
                                                           Diarrhea                                                 
                                                                                                                      2                         1                      
  Hematologic                                                                                                
                                                           Thrombocytopenia                                         
                                                                                                                      1                         -                      
  Metabolic                                                                                                  
                                                           Hypertriglyceridemia                                     
                                                                                                                      1                         -                      
           *    Shown are events with rate &gt;1% rounded to nearest integer.
 

 Dyspnea and fatigue were also reported in these trials, but the rates were equal or greater in subjects who received placebo.



 The following adverse events not described above were reported as possibly or probably related to carvedilol in worldwide open or controlled trials with carvedilol in subjects with hypertension or heart failure.



   Incidence &gt;0.1% to &lt;=1%  



   Cardiovascular:  Peripheral ischemia, tachycardia.



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  Hypokinesia.



   Gastrointestinal:  Bilirubinemia, increased hepatic enzymes (0.2% of hypertension patients and 0.4% of heart failure patients were discontinued from therapy because of increases in hepatic enzymes)  [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .



   Psychiatric:  Nervousness, sleep disorder, aggravated depression, impaired concentration, abnormal thinking, paroniria, emotional lability.



   Respiratory System:  Asthma  [see Contraindications (4)]  .



   Reproductive, male:  Decreased libido.



   Skin and Appendages:  Pruritus, rash erythematous, rash maculopapular, rash psoriaform, photosensitivity reaction.



   Special Senses:  Tinnitus.



   Urinary System:  Micturition frequency increased.



   Autonomic Nervous System:  Dry mouth, sweating increased.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Hypokalemia, hypertriglyceridemia.



   Hematologic:  Anemia, leukopenia.



 The following events were reported in &lt;=0.1% of subjects and are potentially important: complete AV block, bundle branch block, myocardial ischemia, cerebrovascular disorder, convulsions, migraine, neuralgia, paresis, anaphylactoid reaction, alopecia, exfoliative dermatitis, amnesia, GI hemorrhage, bronchospasm, pulmonary edema, decreased hearing, respiratory alkalosis, increased BUN, decreased HDL, pancytopenia, and atypical lymphocytes.



   6.2 Laboratory Abnormalities

  Reversible elevations in serum transaminases (ALT or AST) have been observed during treatment with carvedilol. Rates of transaminase elevations (2 to 3 times the upper limit of normal) observed during controlled clinical trials have generally been similar between subjects treated with carvedilol and those treated with placebo. However, transaminase elevations, confirmed by rechallenge, have been observed with carvedilol. In a long-term, placebo-controlled trial in severe heart failure, subjects treated with carvedilol had lower values for hepatic transaminases than subjects treated with placebo, possibly because carvedilol-induced improvements in cardiac function led to less hepatic congestion and/or improved hepatic blood flow.



 Carvedilol therapy has not been associated with clinically significant changes in serum potassium, total triglycerides, total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, uric acid, blood urea nitrogen, or creatinine. No clinically relevant changes were noted in fasting serum glucose in hypertensive subjects; fasting serum glucose was not evaluated in the heart failure clinical trials.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of COREG  (r)  or COREG CR. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Aplastic anemia.



   Immune System Disorders:  Hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylactic reactions, angioedema, urticaria).



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Urinary incontinence.



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Interstitial pneumonitis.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  In clinical trials of COREG CR in subjects with hypertension (338 subjects) and in subjects with left ventricular dysfunction following a myocardial infarction or heart failure (187 subjects), the profile of adverse events observed with carvedilol phosphate was generally similar to that observed with the administration of immediate-release carvedilol. Therefore, the information included within this section is based on data from controlled clinical trials with COREG CR as well as immediate-release carvedilol.



    EXCERPT:    *    Acute exacerbation of coronary artery disease upon cessation of therapy: Do not abruptly discontinue. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Bradycardia, hypotension, worsening heart failure/fluid retention may occur. Reduce the dose as needed. (  5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
 *    Non-allergic bronchospasm (e.g., chronic bronchitis and emphysema): Avoid beta-blockers. (  4  ) However, if deemed necessary, use with caution and at lowest effective dose. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Diabetes: Monitor glucose as beta-blockers may mask symptoms of hypoglycemia or worsen hyperglycemia. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cessation of Therapy



   Patients with coronary artery disease, who are being treated with COREG CR, should be advised against abrupt discontinuation of therapy. Severe exacerbation of angina and the occurrence of myocardial infarction and ventricular arrhythmias have been reported in angina patients following the abrupt discontinuation of therapy with beta  - blockers. The last 2 complications may occur with or without preceding exacerbation of the angina pectoris. As with other beta  - blockers, when discontinuation of COREG CR is planned, the patients should be carefully observed and advised to limit physical activity to a minimum. COREG CR should be discontinued over 1 to 2 weeks whenever possible. If the angina worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, it is recommended that COREG CR be promptly reinstituted, at least temporarily. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, it may be prudent not to discontinue therapy with COREG CR abruptly even in patients treated only for hypertension or heart failure.  



    5.2 Bradycardia



  In clinical trials with immediate-release carvedilol, bradycardia was reported in about 2% of hypertensive subjects, 9% of heart failure subjects, and 6.5% of myocardial infarction subjects with left ventricular dysfunction. Bradycardia was reported in 0.5% of subjects receiving COREG CR in a trial of heart failure subjects and myocardial infarction subjects with left ventricular dysfunction. There were no reports of bradycardia in the clinical trial of COREG CR in hypertension. However, if pulse rate drops below 55 beats/minute, the dosage of COREG CR should be reduced.



    5.3 Hypotension



  In clinical trials of primarily mild-to-moderate heart failure with immediate-release carvedilol, hypotension and postural hypotension occurred in 9.7% and syncope in 3.4% of subjects receiving carvedilol compared with 3.6% and 2.5% of placebo subjects, respectively. The risk for these events was highest during the first 30 days of dosing, corresponding to the up-titration period and was a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 0.7% of carvedilol subjects, compared with 0.4% of placebo subjects. In a long-term, placebo-controlled trial in severe heart failure (COPERNICUS), hypotension and postural hypotension occurred in 15.1% and syncope in 2.9% of subjects with heart failure receiving carvedilol compared with 8.7% and 2.3% of placebo subjects, respectively. These events were a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 1.1% of carvedilol subjects, compared with 0.8% of placebo subjects.



 In a trial comparing subjects with heart failure switched to COREG CR or maintained on immediate-release carvedilol, there was a 2-fold increase in the combined incidence of hypotension, syncope, or dizziness in elderly subjects (&gt;65 years) switched from the highest dose of carvedilol (25 mg twice daily) to COREG CR 80 mg once daily [see Dosage and Administration (2), Use in Specific Populations (8.5)]  .



 In the clinical trial of COREG CR in hypertensive subjects, syncope was reported in 0.3% of subjects receiving COREG CR compared with 0% of subjects receiving placebo. There were no reports of postural hypotension in this trial. Postural hypotension occurred in 1.8% and syncope in 0.1% of hypertensive subjects receiving immediate-release carvedilol, primarily following the initial dose or at the time of dose increase and was a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 1% of subjects.



 In the CAPRICORN trial of survivors of an acute myocardial infarction with left ventricular dysfunction, hypotension or postural hypotension occurred in 20.2% of subjects receiving carvedilol compared with 12.6% of placebo subjects. Syncope was reported in 3.9% and 1.9% of subjects, respectively. These events were a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 2.5% of subjects receiving carvedilol, compared with 0.2% of placebo subjects.



 Starting with a low dose, administration with food, and gradual up-titration should decrease the likelihood of syncope or excessive hypotension [see Dosage and Administration (2.1, 2.2, 2.3)]  . During initiation of therapy, the patient should be cautioned to avoid situations such as driving or hazardous tasks, where injury could result should syncope occur.



    5.4 Heart Failure/Fluid Retention



  Worsening heart failure or fluid retention may occur during up-titration of carvedilol. If such symptoms occur, diuretics should be increased and the dose of COREG CR should not be advanced until clinical stability resumes [see Dosage and Administration (2)]  . Occasionally it is necessary to lower the dose of COREG CR or temporarily discontinue it. Such episodes do not preclude subsequent successful titration of, or a favorable response to, COREG CR. In a placebo-controlled trial of subjects with severe heart failure, worsening heart failure during the first 3 months was reported to a similar degree with immediate-release carvedilol and with placebo. When treatment was maintained beyond 3 months, worsening heart failure was reported less frequently in subjects treated with carvedilol than with placebo. Worsening heart failure observed during long-term therapy is more likely to be related to the patients' underlying disease than to treatment with carvedilol.



    5.5 Non-allergic Bronchospasm



  Patients with bronchospastic disease (e.g., chronic bronchitis and emphysema) should, in general, not receive beta-blockers. COREG CR may be used with caution, however, in patients who do not respond to, or cannot tolerate, other antihypertensive agents. It is prudent, if COREG CR is used, to use the smallest effective dose, so that inhibition of endogenous or exogenous beta-agonists is minimized.



 In clinical trials of subjects with heart failure, subjects with bronchospastic disease were enrolled if they did not require oral or inhaled medication to treat their bronchospastic disease. In such patients, it is recommended that COREG CR be used with caution. The dosing recommendations should be followed closely and the dose should be lowered if any evidence of bronchospasm is observed during up-titration.



    5.6 Glycemic Control in Type 2 Diabetes



  In general, beta-blockers may mask some of the manifestations of hypoglycemia, particularly tachycardia. Nonselective beta-blockers may potentiate insulin-induced hypoglycemia and delay recovery of serum glucose levels. Patients subject to spontaneous hypoglycemia, or diabetic patients receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents, should be cautioned about these possibilities.



 In heart failure patients with diabetes, carvedilol therapy may lead to worsening hyperglycemia, which responds to intensification of hypoglycemic therapy. It is recommended that blood glucose be monitored when dosing with COREG CR is initiated, adjusted, or discontinued. Trials designed to examine the effects of carvedilol on glycemic control in patients with diabetes and heart failure have not been conducted.



 In a trial designed to examine the effects of immediate-release carvedilol on glycemic control in a population with mild-to-moderate hypertension and well-controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus, carvedilol had no adverse effect on glycemic control, based on HbA1c measurements [see Clinical Studies (14.4)]  .



    5.7 Peripheral Vascular Disease



  beta-blockers can precipitate or aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency in patients with peripheral vascular disease. Caution should be exercised in such individuals.



    5.8 Deterioration of Renal Function



  Rarely, use of carvedilol in patients with heart failure has resulted in deterioration of renal function. Patients at risk appear to be those with low blood pressure (systolic blood pressure &lt;100 mm Hg), ischemic heart disease and diffuse vascular disease, and/or underlying renal insufficiency. Renal function has returned to baseline when carvedilol was stopped. In patients with these risk factors it is recommended that renal function be monitored during up-titration of COREG CR and the drug discontinued or dosage reduced if worsening of renal function occurs.



    5.9 Major Surgery



  Chronically administered beta-blocking therapy should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery; however, the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures.



    5.10 Thyrotoxicosis



  beta-adrenergic blockade may mask clinical signs of hyperthyroidism, such as tachycardia. Abrupt withdrawal of beta-blockade may be followed by an exacerbation of the symptoms of hyperthyroidism or may precipitate thyroid storm.



    5.11 Pheochromocytoma



  In patients with pheochromocytoma, an alpha-blocking agent should be initiated prior to the use of any beta-blocking agent. Although carvedilol has both alpha- and beta-blocking pharmacologic activities, there has been no experience with its use in this condition. Therefore, caution should be taken in the administration of carvedilol to patients suspected of having pheochromocytoma.



    5.12 Prinzmetal's Variant Angina



  Agents with non-selective beta-blocking activity may provoke chest pain in patients with Prinzmetal's variant angina. There has been no clinical experience with carvedilol in these patients although the alpha-blocking activity may prevent such symptoms. However, caution should be taken in the administration of COREG CR to patients suspected of having Prinzmetal's variant angina.



    5.13 Risk of Anaphylactic Reaction



  While taking beta-blockers, patients with a history of severe anaphylactic reaction to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated challenge, either accidental, diagnostic, or therapeutic. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reaction.



    5.14 Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome



  Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients treated with alpha-1 blockers (COREG CR is an alpha/beta blocker). This variant of small pupil syndrome is characterized by the combination of a flaccid iris that billows in response to intraoperative irrigation currents, progressive intraoperative miosis despite preoperative dilation with standard mydriatic drugs, and potential prolapse of the iris toward the phacoemulsification incisions. The patient's ophthalmologist should be prepared for possible modifications to the surgical technique, such as utilization of iris hooks, iris dilator rings, or viscoelastic substances. There does not appear to be a benefit of stopping alpha-1 blocker therapy prior to cataract surgery.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
