<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="corzide" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Nadolol

  Most adverse effects have been mild and transient and have rarely required withdrawal of therapy.



   Cardiovascular  -Bradycardia with heart rates of less than 60 beats per minute occurs commonly, and heart rates below 40 beats per minute and/or symptomatic bradycardia were seen in about 2 of 100 patients. Symptoms of peripheral vascular insufficiency, usually of the Raynaud type, have occurred in approximately 2 of 100 patients. Cardiac failure, hypotension, and rhythm/conduction disturbances have each occurred in about 1 of 100 patients. Single instances of first degree and third degree heart block have been reported; intensification of AV block is a known effect of beta-blockers (see also    CONTRAINDICATIONS    ,    WARNINGS    , and    PRECAUTIONS    ).



   Central Nervous System  -Dizziness or fatigue has been reported in approximately 2 of 100 patients; paresthesias, sedation, and change in behavior have each been reported in approximately 6 of 1000 patients.



   Respiratory  -Bronchospasm has been reported in approximately 1 of 1000 patients (see    CONTRAINDICATIONS    and    WARNINGS    ).



   Gastrointestinal  -Nausea, diarrhea, abdominal discomfort, constipation, vomiting, indigestion, anorexia, bloating, and flatulence have been reported in 1 to 5 of 1000 patients.



   Miscellaneous  -Each of the following has been reported in 1 to 5 of 1000 patients: rash; pruritus; headache; dry mouth, eyes, or skin; impotence or decreased libido; facial swelling; weight gain; slurred speech; cough; nasal stuffiness; sweating; tinnitus; blurred vision. Reversible alopecia has been reported infrequently.



 The following adverse reactions have been reported in patients taking nadolol and/or other beta-adrenergic blocking agents, but no causal relationship to nadolol has been established.



   Central Nervous System  -Reversible mental depression progressing to catatonia; visual disturbances; hallucinations; an acute reversible syndrome characterized by disorientation for time and place, short-term memory loss, emotional lability with slightly clouded sensorium, and decreased performance on neuropsychometrics.



   Gastrointestinal  -Mesenteric arterial thrombosis; ischemic colitis; elevated liver enzymes.



   Hematologic  -Agranulocytosis; thrombocytopenic or nonthrombocytopenic purpura.



   Allergic  -Fever combined with aching and sore throat; laryngospasm; respiratory distress.



   Miscellaneous  -Pemphigoid rash; hypertensive reaction in patients with pheochromocytoma; sleep disturbances; Peyronie's disease.



 The oculomucocutaneous syndrome associated with the beta-blocker practolol has not been reported with nadolol.



   Bendroflumethiazide

    Gastrointestinal  -Nausea, vomiting, cramping and anorexia are not uncommon; diarrhea, constipation, gastric irritation, abdominal bloating, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice), hepatitis, and sialadenitis occasionally occur; and pancreatitis has been reported.



   Central Nervous System  -Dizziness, vertigo, paresthesia, headache, and xanthopsia occasionally occur.



   Hematologic  -Leukopenia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia, hemolytic anemia, and aplastic anemia have been reported.



   Dermatologic-Hypersensitivity  -Purpura, exfoliative dermatitis, pruritus, ecchymosis, urticaria, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis, cutaneous vasculitis), respiratory distress including pneumonitis, fever, and anaphylactic reactions occasionally occur; photosensitivity and rash have been reported.



   Cardiovascular  -Orthostatic hypotension may occur and may be potentiated by coadministration with certain other drugs (e.g., alcohol, barbiturates, narcotics, other antihypertensive medications, etc.; see    PRECAUTIONS, Drug Interactions    ).



   Other  -Muscle spasm, weakness, or restlessness is not uncommon; hyperglycemia, glycosuria, metabolic acidosis in diabetic patients, hyperuricemia, allergic glomerulonephritis, and transient blurred vision occasionally occur.



 Whenever adverse reactions are moderate or severe, thiazide dosage should be reduced or therapy withdrawn.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
