<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cosopt" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  COSOPT was evaluated for safety in 1035 patients with elevated intraocular pressure treated for open-angle glaucoma or ocular hypertension. Approximately 5% of all patients discontinued therapy with COSOPT because of adverse reactions. The most frequently reported adverse events were taste perversion (bitter, sour, or unusual taste) or ocular burning and/or stinging in up to 30% of patients. Conjunctival hyperemia, blurred vision, superficial punctate keratitis or eye itching were reported between 5-15% of patients. The following adverse events were reported in 1-5% of patients: abdominal pain, back pain, blepharitis, bronchitis, cloudy vision, conjunctival discharge, conjunctival edema, conjunctival follicles, conjunctival injection, conjunctivitis, corneal erosion, corneal staining, cortical lens opacity, cough, dizziness, dryness of eyes, dyspepsia, eye debris, eye discharge, eye pain, eye tearing, eyelid edema, eyelid erythema, eyelid exudate/scales, eyelid pain or discomfort, foreign body sensation, glaucomatous cupping, headache, hypertension, influenza, lens nucleus coloration, lens opacity, nausea, nuclear lens opacity, pharyngitis, post-subcapsular cataract, sinusitis, upper respiratory infection, urinary tract infection, visual field defect, vitreous detachment.



 The following adverse events have occurred either at low incidence (&lt;1%) during clinical trials or have been reported during the use of COSOPT in clinical practice where these events were reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size and frequency of occurrence cannot be determined precisely. They have been chosen for inclusion based on factors such as seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to COSOPT, or a combination of these factors: bradycardia, cardiac failure, cerebral vascular accident, chest pain, choroidal detachment following filtration surgery (see  PRECAUTIONS, General  ), depression, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspnea, heart block, hypotension, iridocyclitis, myocardial infarction, nasal congestion, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, paresthesia, photophobia, respiratory failure, skin rashes, urolithiasis, and vomiting.



 Other adverse reactions that have been reported with the individual components are listed below:



   Dorzolamide - Allergic/Hypersensitivity:  Signs and symptoms of local reactions including palpebral reactions and systemic allergic reactions including angioedema, bronchospasm, pruritus, urticaria;  Body as a Whole:  Asthenia/fatigue;  Skin/Mucous Membranes:  Contact dermatitis, epistaxis, throat irritation;  Special Senses:  Eyelid crusting, signs and symptoms of ocular allergic reaction, and transient myopia.



   Timolol (ocular administration) - Body as a Whole:  Asthenia/fatigue;  Cardiovascular:  Arrhythmia, syncope, cerebral ischemia, worsening of angina pectoris, palpitation, cardiac arrest, pulmonary edema, edema, claudication, Raynaud's phenomenon, and cold hands and feet;  Digestive:  Anorexia;  Immunologic:  Systemic lupus erythematosus;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Increase in signs and symptoms of myasthenia gravis, somnolence, insomnia, nightmares, behavioral changes and psychic disturbances including confusion, hallucinations, anxiety, disorientation, nervousness, and memory loss;  Skin:  Alopecia, psoriasiform rash or exacerbation of psoriasis;  Hypersensitivity:  Signs and symptoms of systemic allergic reactions, including anaphylaxis, angioedema, urticaria, and localized and generalized rash;  Respiratory:  Bronchospasm (predominantly in patients with pre-existing bronchospastic disease);  Endocrine:  Masked symptoms of hypoglycemia in diabetic patients (see  WARNINGS  );  Special Senses:  Ptosis, decreased corneal sensitivity, cystoid macular edema, visual disturbances including refractive changes and diplopia, pseudopemphigoid, and tinnitus;  Urogenital:  Retroperitoneal fibrosis, decreased libido, impotence, and Peyronie's disease.



 The following additional adverse effects have been reported in clinical experience with ORAL timolol maleate or other ORAL beta-blocking agents and may be considered potential effects of ophthalmic timolol maleate:  Allergic:  Erythematous rash, fever combined with aching and sore throat, laryngospasm with respiratory distress;  Body as a Whole:  Extremity pain, decreased exercise tolerance, weight loss;  Cardiovascular:  Worsening of arterial insufficiency, vasodilatation;  Digestive:  Gastrointestinal pain, hepatomegaly, mesenteric arterial thrombosis, ischemic colitis;  Hematologic:  Nonthrombocytopenic purpura; thrombocytopenic purpura, agranulocytosis;  Endocrine:  Hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia;  Skin:  Pruritus, skin irritation, increased pigmentation, sweating;  Musculoskeletal:  Arthralgia;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Vertigo, local weakness, diminished concentration, reversible mental depression progressing to catatonia, an acute reversible syndrome characterized by disorientation for time and place, emotional lability, slightly clouded sensorium, and decreased performance on neuropsychometrics;  Respiratory:  Rales, bronchial obstruction;  Urogenital:  Urination difficulties.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
