<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cozaar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Hypertension

  COZAAR has been evaluated for safety in more than 3300 adult patients treated for essential hypertension and 4058 patients/subjects overall. Over 1200 patients were treated for over 6 months and more than 800 for over one year. In general, treatment with COZAAR was well-tolerated. The overall incidence of adverse experiences reported with COZAAR was similar to placebo.



 In controlled clinical trials, discontinuation of therapy due to clinical adverse experiences was required in 2.3 percent of patients treated with COZAAR and 3.7 percent of patients given placebo.



 The following table of adverse events is based on four 6- to 12-week, placebo-controlled trials involving over 1000 patients on various doses (10-150 mg) of losartan and over 300 patients given placebo. All doses of losartan are grouped because none of the adverse events appeared to have a dose-related frequency. The adverse experiences reported in &gt;=1% of patients treated with COZAAR and more commonly than placebo are shown in the table below.




                                  Losartan(n=1075)Incidence%          Placebo(n=334)Incidence%             
  
   Musculoskeletal     Cramp, muscle   Pain, back   Pain, leg  121                                 010                                  
   Nervous System/Psychiatric     Dizziness  3                                   2                                    
   Respiratory     Congestion, nasal   Infection, upper respiratory   Sinusitis  281                                 170                                  
         The following adverse events were also reported at a rate of 1% or greater in patients treated with losartan, but were as, or more frequent, in the placebo group: asthenia/fatigue, edema/swelling, abdominal pain, chest pain, nausea, headache, pharyngitis, diarrhea, dyspepsia, myalgia, insomnia, cough, sinus disorder.
 

 Adverse events occurred at about the same rates in men and women, older and younger patients, and Black and non-Black patients.



 A patient with known hypersensitivity to aspirin and penicillin, when treated with COZAAR, was withdrawn from study due to swelling of the lips and eyelids and facial rash, reported as angioedema, which returned to normal 5 days after therapy was discontinued.



 Superficial peeling of palms and hemolysis were reported in one subject.



 In addition to the adverse events above, potentially important events that occurred in at least two patients/subjects exposed to losartan or other adverse events that occurred in &lt;1% of patients in clinical studies are listed below. It cannot be determined whether these events were causally related to losartan:  Body as a Whole:  facial edema, fever, orthostatic effects, syncope;  Cardiovascular:  angina pectoris, second degree AV block, CVA, hypotension, myocardial infarction, arrhythmias including atrial fibrillation, palpitation, sinus bradycardia, tachycardia, ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation;  Digestive:  anorexia, constipation, dental pain, dry mouth, flatulence, gastritis, vomiting;  Hematologic:  anemia;  Metabolic:  gout;  Musculoskeletal:  arm pain, hip pain, joint swelling, knee pain, musculoskeletal pain, shoulder pain, stiffness, arthralgia, arthritis, fibromyalgia, muscle weakness;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  anxiety, anxiety disorder, ataxia, confusion, depression, dream abnormality, hypesthesia, decreased libido, memory impairment, migraine, nervousness, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, panic disorder, sleep disorder, somnolence, tremor, vertigo;  Respiratory:  dyspnea, bronchitis, pharyngeal discomfort, epistaxis, rhinitis, respiratory congestion;  Skin:  alopecia, dermatitis, dry skin, ecchymosis, erythema, flushing, photosensitivity, pruritus, rash, sweating, urticaria;  Special Senses:  blurred vision, burning/stinging in the eye, conjunctivitis, taste perversion, tinnitus, decrease in visual acuity;  Urogenital:  impotence, nocturia, urinary frequency, urinary tract infection.



 Persistent dry cough (with an incidence of a few percent) has been associated with ACE-inhibitor use and in practice can be a cause of discontinuation of ACE-inhibitor therapy. Two prospective, parallel-group, double-blind, randomized, controlled trials were conducted to assess the effects of losartan on the incidence of cough in hypertensive patients who had experienced cough while receiving ACE-inhibitor therapy. Patients who had typical ACE-inhibitor cough when challenged with lisinopril, whose cough disappeared on placebo, were randomized to losartan 50 mg, lisinopril 20 mg, or either placebo (one study, n=97) or 25 mg hydrochlorothiazide (n=135). The double-blind treatment period lasted up to 8 weeks. The incidence of cough is shown below.




 Study 1          HCTZ             Losartan         Lisinopril        
 Cough            25%              17%              69%               
                                                                      
 Study 2          Placebo          Losartan         Lisinopril        
 Cough            35%              29%              62%               
          These studies demonstrate that the incidence of cough associated with losartan therapy, in a population that all had cough associated with ACE-inhibitor therapy, is similar to that associated with hydrochlorothiazide or placebo therapy.
 

 Cases of cough, including positive re-challenges, have been reported with the use of losartan in post-marketing experience.



   Pediatric Patients:  No relevant differences between the adverse experience profile for pediatric patients and that previously reported for adult patients were identified.



   Hypertensive Patients with Left Ventricular Hypertrophy

  In the LIFE study, adverse events with COZAAR were similar to those reported previously for patients with hypertension.



   Nephropathy in Type 2 Diabetic Patients

  In the RENAAL study involving 1513 patients treated with COZAAR or placebo, the overall incidences of reported adverse experiences were similar for the two groups. COZAAR was generally well tolerated as evidenced by a similar incidence of discontinuations due to side effects compared to placebo (19% for COZAAR, 24% for placebo). The adverse experiences, regardless of drug relationship, reported with an incidence of &gt;=4% of patients treated with COZAAR and occurring more commonly than placebo, on a background of conventional antihypertensive therapy, are shown in the table below.




                                      Losartanand ConventionalAntihypertensiveTherapyIncidence%(n=751)  Placeboand ConventionalAntihypertensiveTherapyIncidence%(n=762)   
  
   Body as a Whole     Asthenia/Fatigue   Chest Pain   Fever   Infection   Influenza-like disease   Trauma  141245104                         1083493                            
   Cardiovascular     Hypotension   Orthostatic hypotension  74                                31                                 
   Digestive     Diarrhea   Dyspepsia   Gastritis  1545                              1034                               
   Endocrine     Diabetic neuropathy   Diabetic vascular disease  410                               39                                 
   Eyes, Ears, Nose and Throat       Cataract   Sinusitis  76                                55                                 
   Hemic     Anemia                   14                                11                                 
   Metabolic and Nutrition     Hyperkalemia   Hypoglycemia   Weight gain  7144                              3103                               
   Musculoskeletal     Back pain   Leg pain   Knee pain   Muscular weakness  12557                             10444                              
   Nervous System     Hypesthesia     5                                 4                                  
   Respiratory     Bronchitis   Cough  1011                              910                                
   Skin     Cellulitis                7                                 6                                  
   Urogenital     Urinary tract infection  16                                13                                 
           Post-Marketing Experience
   The following additional adverse reactions have been reported in post-marketing experience:



   Digestive:  Hepatitis (reported rarely).



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Malaise.



   Hemic:  Thrombocytopenia (reported rarely).



   Hypersensitivity:  Angioedema, including swelling of the larynx and glottis, causing airway obstruction and/or swelling of the face, lips, pharynx, and/or tongue has been reported rarely in patients treated with losartan; some of these patients previously experienced angioedema with other drugs including ACE inhibitors. Vasculitis, including Henoch-Schonlein purpura, has been reported. Anaphylactic reactions have been reported.



   Metabolic and Nutrition:  Hyperkalemia, hyponatremia have been reported with losartan.



   Musculoskeletal:  Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers.



   Nervous system disorders:  Dysgeusia.



   Respiratory:  Dry cough (see above).



   Skin:  Erythroderma.



   Laboratory Test Findings

  In controlled clinical trials, clinically important changes in standard laboratory parameters were rarely associated with administration of COZAAR.



   Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen:  Minor increases in blood urea nitrogen (BUN) or serum creatinine were observed in less than 0.1 percent of patients with essential hypertension treated with COZAAR alone (see  PRECAUTIONS, Impaired Renal Function    ).  



   Hemoglobin and Hematocrit:  Small decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit (mean decreases of approximately 0.11 grams percent and 0.09 volume percent, respectively) occurred frequently in patients treated with COZAAR alone, but were rarely of clinical importance. No patients were discontinued due to anemia.



   Liver Function Tests:  Occasional elevations of liver enzymes and/or serum bilirubin have occurred. In patients with essential hypertension treated with COZAAR alone, one patient (&lt;0.1%) was discontinued due to these laboratory adverse experiences.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: USE IN PREGNANCY

  USE IN PREGNANCY

    When used in pregnancy during the second and third trimesters, drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus.   When pregnancy is detected, COZAAR  (r)   should be discontinued as soon as possible. See   WARNINGS, Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
