<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cresemba" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Hepatic Adverse Drug Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.1  )]  
 *    Infusion-Related Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.2  )]  
 *    Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.3  )]  
 *    Embryo-Fetal Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  )]  
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of CRESEMBA cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

   EXCERPT:   Most frequent adverse reactions: nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, headache, elevated liver chemistry tests, hypokalemia, constipation, dyspnea, cough, peripheral edema, and back pain (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Astellas Pharma US, Inc. at 1-800-727-7003 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  A total of 403 patients were exposed to CRESEMBA in two clinical trials. The most frequently reported adverse reactions among CRESEMBA-treated patients were nausea (26%), vomiting (25%), diarrhea (22%), headache (17%), elevated liver chemistry tests (16%), hypokalemia (14%), constipation (13%), dyspnea (12%), cough (12%), peripheral edema (11%), and back pain (10%). Serious adverse reactions occurred in 223/403 (55%) of patients and 56/403 (14%) of patients permanently discontinued treatment with CRESEMBA due to an adverse reaction in the two trials. The adverse reactions which most often led to permanent discontinuation of CRESEMBA therapy during the clinical trials were: confusional state (0.7%), acute renal failure (0.7%), increased blood bilirubin (0.5%), convulsion (0.5%), dyspnea (0.5%), epilepsy (0.5%), respiratory failure (0.5%), and vomiting (0.5%).



 Patients in the clinical trials were immunocompromised with underlying conditions including hematological malignancy, neutropenia post-chemotherapy, graft-versus-host disease, and hematopoietic stem cell transplant. The patient population was 61% male, had a mean age of 51 years (range 17-92, including 85 patients aged greater than 65 years), and was 79% white and 3% black. One hundred forty-four (144) patients had a duration of CRESEMBA therapy of greater than 12 weeks, with 52 patients receiving CRESEMBA for over six months.



 In Trial 1, a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled clinical trial for treatment of invasive aspergillosis, treatment-emergent adverse reactions occurred in 247/257 (96%), and 255/259 (99%) patients in the CRESEMBA and voriconazole treatment groups, respectively. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions resulting in permanent discontinuation were reported in 37 (14%) CRESEMBA-treated patients and 59 (23%) voriconazole-treated patients.  Table 2   includes selected treatment-emergent adverse reactions which were reported at an incidence of &gt;= 5% during CRESEMBA therapy in Trial 1.



 In Trial 2, an open-label, non-comparative trial of CRESEMBA in patients with invasive aspergillosis and renal impairment or invasive mucormycosis, treatment-emergent adverse reactions occurred in 139/146 (95%) of patients in the CRESEMBA treatment group. Adverse reactions resulting in permanent discontinuation were reported in 19 (13%) CRESEMBA-treated patients. The frequencies and types of adverse reactions observed in CRESEMBA-treated patients were similar between Trial 1 and Trial 2.



 Table 2. Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions with Rates of 5% or Greater in CRESEMBA-treated Patients in Trial 1 
  System Organ Class                                                             
     Preferred Term                                   Trial 1                    
                                                       CRESEMBA    (N=257)    n (%)      Voriconazole    (N=259)    n (%)     
  
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                
     Nausea                                           71 (27.6)                  78 (30.1)                  
     Vomiting                                         64 (24.9)                  73 (28.2)                  
     Diarrhea                                         61 (23.7)                  60 (23.2)                  
     Abdominal pain                                   43 (16.7)                  59 (22.8)                  
     Constipation                                     36 (14.0)                  54 (20.8)                  
     Dyspepsia                                        16 (6.2)                   14 (5.4)                   
  General disorders and administration site conditions                                                          
     Edema peripheral                                 39 (15.2)                  46 (17.8)                  
     Fatigue                                          27 (10.5)                  18 (6.9)                   
     Chest pain                                       23 (8.9)                   16 (6.2)                   
     Injection site reaction                          16 (6.2)                   4 (1.5)                    
  Hepatobiliary disorders                                                                                   
     Elevated liver laboratory testsa                 44 (17.1)                  63 (24.3)                  
  Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                        
     Hypokalemia                                      49 (19.1)                  58 (22.4)                  
     Decreased appetite                               22 (8.6)                   28 (10.8)                  
     Hypomagnesemia                                   14 (5.4)                   27 (10.4)                  
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                           
     Back pain                                        26 (10.1)                  19 (7.3)                   
  Nervous system disorders                                                                                  
     Headache                                         43 (16.7)                  38 (14.7)                  
  Psychiatric disorders                                                                                     
     Insomnia                                         27 (10.5)                  25 (9.7)                   
     Deliriumb                                        22 (8.6)                   30 (11.6)                  
     Anxiety                                          21 (8.2)                   18 (6.9)                   
  Renal and urinary disorders                                                                               
     Renal failure                                    26 (10.1)                  21 (8.1)                   
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                           
     Dyspnea                                          44 (17.1)                  35 (13.5)                  
     Acute respiratory failure                        19 (7.4)                   22 (8.5)                   
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                    
     Rash                                             22 (8.6)                   36 (13.9)                  
     Pruritus                                         21 (8.2)                   15 (5.8)                   
  Vascular disorders                                                                                        
     Hypotension                                      21 (8.2)                   28 (10.8)                  
 a                                                   Elevated liver laboratory tests include reactions of increased alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, blood alkaline phosphatase, blood bilirubin, and gamma-glutamyltransferase. 
 b                                                   Delirium includes adverse reactions of agitation, confusional state, delirium, disorientation, and mental status changes. 
                                                                                                          
         The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 5% of all CRESEMBA-treated patients in Trial 1 or 2. The list does not include reactions presented in  Table 2  . This listing includes adverse reactions where a causal relationship to isavuconazole cannot be ruled out or those which may help the physician in managing the risks to the patients.
 

   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  agranulocytosis, leukopenia, pancytopenia



   Cardiac disorders:  atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, bradycardia, reduced QT interval on electrocardiogram, palpitations, supraventricular extrasystoles, supraventricular tachycardia, ventricular extrasystoles, cardiac arrest



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  tinnitus, vertigo



   Eye disorders:  optic neuropathy



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal distension, gastritis, gingivitis, stomatitis



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  catheter thrombosis, malaise, chills



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  cholecystitis, cholelithiasis, hepatitis, hepatomegaly, hepatic failure



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications:  fall



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  hypoalbuminemia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  myositis, bone pain, neck pain



   Nervous system disorders:  convulsion, dysgeusia, encephalopathy, hypoesthesia, migraine, peripheral neuropathy, paraesthesia, somnolence, stupor, syncope, tremor



   Psychiatric disorders:  confusion, hallucination, depression



   Renal and urinary disorders:  hematuria, proteinuria



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  bronchospasm, tachypnea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  alopecia, dermatitis, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema, petechiae, urticaria



   Vascular disorders:  thrombophlebitis



     Laboratory effects    In Trial 1, elevated liver transaminases (alanine aminotransferase or aspartate aminotransferase) greater than three times the upper limit of normal were reported at the end of study treatment in 4.4% of patients who received CRESEMBA. Elevations of liver transaminases greater than ten times the upper limit of normal developed in 1.2% of patients who received CRESEMBA.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hepatic Adverse Drug Reactions: Serious hepatic reactions have been reported. Evaluate liver-related laboratory tests at the start and during the course of CRESEMBA therapy (  5.1  ). 
 *    Infusion-related reactions were reported during intravenous administration of CRESEMBA. Discontinue the infusion if these reactions occur (  5.2  ). 
 *    Hypersensitivity Reactions: Serious hypersensitivity and severe skin reactions, such as anaphylaxis or Stevens Johnson syndrome, have been reported during treatment with other azole antifungal agents. Discontinue CRESEMBA for exfoliative cutaneous reactions (  5.3  ). 
 *    Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Do not administer to pregnant women unless the benefit to the mother outweighs the risk to the fetus. Inform pregnant patients of the hazard (  5.4  ). 
 *    Drug Interactions: Review patient's concomitant medications. Several drugs may significantly alter isavuconazole concentrations. Isavuconazole may alter concentrations of several drugs (  5.5  ,  7  ,  12.3  ). 
 *    Drug Particulates: Intravenous formulation may form insoluble particulates following reconstitution. Administer CRESEMBA through an in-line filter (  2.4  ,  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatic Adverse Drug Reactions



  Hepatic adverse drug reactions (e.g., elevations in alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase, total bilirubin) have been reported in clinical trials. The elevations in liver-related laboratory tests were generally reversible and did not require discontinuation of CRESEMBA. Cases of more severe hepatic adverse drug reactions including hepatitis, cholestasis or hepatic failure including death have been reported in patients with serious underlying medical conditions (e.g., hematologic malignancy) during treatment with azole antifungal agents, including CRESEMBA.



 Evaluate liver-related laboratory tests at the start and during the course of CRESEMBA therapy. Monitor patients who develop abnormal liver-related laboratory tests during CRESEMBA therapy for the development of more severe hepatic injury. Discontinue CRESEMBA if clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop that may be attributable to CRESEMBA [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )]  .



    5.2 Infusion-Related Reactions



  Infusion-related reactions including hypotension, dyspnea, chills, dizziness, paresthesia, and hypoesthesia were reported during intravenous administration of CRESEMBA. Discontinue the infusion if these reactions occur [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )]  .



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious hypersensitivity and severe skin reactions, such as anaphylaxis or Stevens Johnson syndrome, have been reported during treatment with other azole antifungal agents. Discontinue CRESEMBA if a patient develops a severe cutaneous adverse reaction. There is no information regarding cross-sensitivity between CRESEMBA and other azole antifungal agents. Caution should be used when prescribing CRESEMBA to patients with hypersensitivity to other azoles.



    5.4 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  CRESEMBA may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. CRESEMBA should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit to the patient outweighs the risk to the fetus. Women who become pregnant while receiving CRESEMBA are encouraged to contact their physician [see  Use in Specific Populations  (  8.1  )].  



 Perinatal mortality was significantly increased in the offspring of pregnant rats dosed orally with isavuconazonium sulfate at 90 mg/kg/day (less than half the maintenance human dose based on AUC comparisons) during pregnancy through the weaning period.



 Isavuconazonium chloride administration was associated with dose-related increases in the incidences of rudimentary cervical ribs in rats and rabbits at 30 and 45 mg/kg, respectively, doses equivalent to about one fifth and one tenth of the clinical exposures based on AUC comparisons. In rats, dose-related increases in the incidences of zygomatic arch fusion and supernumerary ribs/rudimentary supernumerary ribs were also noted at 30 mg/kg and above, equivalent to one fifth the clinical dose based on AUC comparisons [see  Nonclinical Toxicology  (  13.1  )]  .



    5.5 Drug Interactions



  Coadministration of CRESEMBA with strong CYP3A4 inhibitors such as ketoconazole or high-dose ritonavir and strong CYP3A4 inducers such as rifampin, carbamazepine, St. John's wort, or long acting barbiturates is contraindicated [see  Contraindications  (  4  ) and  Drug Interactions  (  7  )]  .



    5.6 Drug Particulates



  Following dilution, CRESEMBA intravenous formulation may form precipitate from the insoluble isavuconazole. Administer CRESEMBA through an in-line filter [see  Dosage and Administration  (  2.4  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
