<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="crixivan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinical Trials in Adults

  Nephrolithiasis/urolithiasis, including flank pain with or without hematuria (including microscopic hematuria), has been reported in approximately 12.4% (301/2429; range across individual trials: 4.7% to 34.4%) of patients receiving CRIXIVAN at the recommended dose in clinical trials with a median follow-up of 47 weeks (range: 1 day to 242 weeks; 2238 patient-years follow-up). The cumulative frequency of nephrolithiasis events increases with duration of exposure to CRIXIVAN; however, the risk over time remains relatively constant. Of the patients treated with CRIXIVAN who developed nephrolithiasis/urolithiasis in clinical trials during the double-blind phase, 2.8% (7/246) were reported to develop hydronephrosis and 4.5% (11/246) underwent stent placement. Following the acute episode, 4.9% (12/246) of patients discontinued therapy. (See  WARNINGS  and  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION, Nephrolithiasis/Urolithiasis  .)



 Asymptomatic hyperbilirubinemia (total bilirubin &gt;=2.5 mg/dL), reported predominantly as elevated indirect bilirubin, has occurred in approximately 14% of patients treated with CRIXIVAN. In &lt;1% this was associated with elevations in ALT or AST.



 Hyperbilirubinemia and nephrolithiasis/urolithiasis occurred more frequently at doses exceeding 2.4 g/day compared to doses &lt;=2.4 g/day.



 Clinical adverse experiences reported in &gt;=2% of patients treated with CRIXIVAN alone, CRIXIVAN in combination with zidovudine or zidovudine plus lamivudine, zidovudine alone, or zidovudine plus lamivudine are presented in Table 10.



 Table 10: Clinical Adverse Experiences Reported in &gt;=2% of Patients 
          Study 028Considered Drug-Related and of Moderate or Severe Intensity  Study ACTG 320of Unknown Drug Relationship and of Severe or Life-threatening Intensity   
          CRIXIVAN                 CRIXIVANplusZidovudine  Zidovudine    CRIXIVAN plusZidovudine plus Lamivudine  ZidovudineplusLamivudine   
 Adverse Experience  Percent(n=332)           Percent(n=332)  Percent(n=332)  Percent(n=571)  Percent(n=575)    
  
   Body as a Whole     
      Abdominal pain  16.6                     16.0          12.0          1.9           0.7               
      Asthenia/fatigue  2.1                      4.2           3.6           2.4           4.5               
      Fever  1.5                      1.5           2.1           3.8           3.0               
      Malaise  2.1                      2.7           1.8           0             0                 
   Digestive System     
      Nausea  11.7                     31.9          19.6          2.8           1.4               
      Diarrhea  3.3                      3.0           2.4           0.9           1.2               
      Vomiting  8.4                      17.8          9.0           1.4           1.4               
      Acid regurgitation  2.7                      5.4           1.8           0.4           0                 
      Anorexia  2.7                      5.4           3.0           0.5           0.2               
      Appetite increase  2.1                      1.5           1.2           0             0                 
      Dyspepsia  1.5                      2.7           0.9           0             0                 
      Jaundice  1.5                      2.1           0.3           0             0                 
   Hemic and Lymphatic System     
      Anemia  0.6                      1.2           2.1           2.4           3.5               
   Musculoskeletal System     
      Back pain  8.4                      4.5           1.5           0.9           0.7               
   Nervous System/Psychiatric     
      Headache  5.4                      9.6           6.0           2.4           2.8               
      Dizziness  3.0                      3.9           0.9           0.5           0.7               
      Somnolence  2.4                      3.3           3.3           0             0                 
   Skin and Skin Appendage     
      Pruritus  4.2                      2.4           1.8           0.5           0                 
      Rash  1.2                      0.6           2.4           1.1           0.5               
   Respiratory System     
      Cough  1.5                      0.3           0.6           1.6           1.0               
      Difficulty breathing/     dyspnea/     shortness of breath  0                        0.6           0.3           1.8           1.0               
   Urogenital System     
      Nephrolithiasis/urolithiasis  8.7                      7.8           2.1           2.6           0.3               
      Dysuria  1.5                      2.4           0.3           0.4           0.2               
   Special Senses     
      Taste perversion  2.7                      8.4           1.2           0.2           0                 
             In Phase I and II controlled trials, the following adverse events were reported significantly more frequently by those randomized to the arms containing CRIXIVAN than by those randomized to nucleoside analogues: rash, upper respiratory infection, dry skin, pharyngitis, taste perversion.
 

 Selected laboratory abnormalities of severe or life-threatening intensity reported in patients treated with CRIXIVAN alone, CRIXIVAN in combination with zidovudine or zidovudine plus lamivudine, zidovudine alone, or zidovudine plus lamivudine are presented in Table 11.



 Table 11: Selected Laboratory Abnormalities of Severe or Life-threatening Intensity Reported in Studies 028 and ACTG 320 
                                   Study 028   Study ACTG 320   
                                   CRIXIVAN    CRIXIVANplusZidovudine   Zidovudine   CRIXIVAN plusZidovudineplusLamivudine  ZidovudineplusLamivudine   
                                  Percent(n=329)  Percent(n=320)  Percent(n=330)   Percent(n=571)    Percent(n=575)    
  
   Hematology                                                                                                  
 Decreased hemoglobin     &lt;7.0 g/dL      0.6          0.9          3.3             2.4               3.5          
 Decreased platelet count     &lt;50 THS/mm  3        0.9          0.9          1.8             0.2               0.9          
 Decreased neutrophils     &lt;0.75 THS/mm  3        2.4          2.2          6.7             5.1               14.6         
                                                                                                               
   Blood chemistry                                                                                             
 Increased ALT     &gt;500% ULN          4.9          4.1          3.0             2.6               2.6          
 Increased AST     &gt;500% ULN          3.7          2.8          2.7             3.3               2.8          
 Total serum bilirubin     &gt;250% ULN     11.9          9.7          0.6             6.1               1.4          
 Increased serum amylase     &gt;200% ULN      2.1          1.9          1.8             0.9               0.3          
 Increased glucose     &gt;250 mg/dL      0.9          0.9          0.6             1.6               1.9          
 Increased creatinine     &gt;300% ULN       0            0           0.6             0.2                0           
              Post-Marketing Experience
     Body As A Whole:  redistribution/accumulation of body fat (see  PRECAUTIONS, Fat Redistribution  ).



   Cardiovascular System:  cardiovascular disorders including myocardial infarction and angina pectoris; cerebrovascular disorder.



   Digestive System:  liver function abnormalities; hepatitis including reports of hepatic failure (see  WARNINGS  ); pancreatitis; jaundice; abdominal distention; dyspepsia.



   Hematologic:  increased spontaneous bleeding in patients with hemophilia (see  PRECAUTIONS  ); acute hemolytic anemia (see  WARNINGS  ).



   Endocrine/Metabolic:  new onset diabetes mellitus, exacerbation of pre-existing diabetes mellitus, hyperglycemia (see  WARNINGS  ).



   Hypersensitivity:  anaphylactoid reactions; urticaria; vasculitis.



   Musculoskeletal System:  arthralgia.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric:  oral paresthesia; depression.



   Skin and Skin Appendage:  rash including erythema multiforme and Stevens-Johnson syndrome; hyperpigmentation; alopecia; ingrown toenails and/or paronychia; pruritus.



   Urogenital System:  nephrolithiasis/urolithiasis, in some cases resulting in renal insufficiency or acute renal failure, pyelonephritis with or without bacteremia (see  WARNINGS  ); interstitial nephritis sometimes with indinavir crystal deposits; in some patients, the interstitial nephritis did not resolve following discontinuation of CRIXIVAN; renal insufficiency; renal failure; leukocyturia (see  PRECAUTIONS  ), crystalluria; dysuria.



   Laboratory Abnormalities

  Increased serum triglycerides; increased serum cholesterol.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
