<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="crofab" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   The most common adverse events reported in clinical studies were mild or moderate reactions involving the skin and appendages (primarily urticaria, rash or pruritus), which occurred in 14 out of 42 patients. Three patients experienced a serious adverse event. Two patients had a severe allergic reaction (severe hives and a severe rash and pruritus) following treatment. One patient had a recurrent coagulopathy due to envenomation, which required re-hospitalization and additional antivenin administration. One patient discontinued CroFab  (r)  therapy due to an allergic reaction. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact 1-877-377-3784 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trails of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 *  The most common adverse events reported in the clinical studies were urticaria and rash. Adverse events involving the skin and appendages (primarily rash, urticaria, and pruritus) were reported in 14 of the 42 patients (  Table 1  ). 
 *  *  The 1 patient who experienced a serious adverse event had a recurrent coagulopathy due to envenomation, which required re-hospitalization and additional antivenin administration. This patient eventually made a complete recovery. 
 *  The other 2 had severe adverse reactions that consisted of 1 patient who developed severe hives following treatment and 1 patient who developed a severe rash and pruritus several days following treatment. Both patients recovered following treatment with antihistamines and prednisone. 
   Of the 25 patients who experienced adverse reactions, 3 patients experienced severe or serious adverse reactions. 
   *  One patient discontinued CroFab  (r)  therapy due to an allergic reaction. 
   Table 1 Incidence of Clinical Adverse Events in Studies of CroFab (r) by Body System 
   *  Of the 42 patients receiving CroFab  (r)  in the clinical studies, 25 experienced an adverse event. A total of 40 adverse events was experienced by these 25 patients.   
     Allergic reaction consisted of urticaria, dyspnea and wheezing in 1 patient.   
  
   Adverse Events                                           n=42  *  Number of Events                     
   Body as a Whole                                                                                        
 Back pain                                                2                                               
 Chest pain                                               1                                               
 Cellulitis                                               1                                               
 Wound infection                                          1                                               
 Chills                                                   1                                               
 Allergic reaction                                        1                                               
 Serum sickness                                           1                                               
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                    
 Urticaria                                                7                                               
 Rash                                                     5                                               
 Pruritus                                                 3                                               
 Subcutaneous nodule                                      1                                               
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                  
 Hypotension                                              1                                               
   Respiratory System                                                                                     
 Asthma                                                   1                                               
 Cough                                                    1                                               
 Increased sputum                                         1                                               
   Digestive System                                                                                       
 Nausea                                                   3                                               
 Anorexia                                                 1                                               
   Hematologic/Lymphatic                                                                                  
 Coagulation disorder                                     3                                               
 Ecchymosis                                               1                                               
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                        
 Myalgia                                                  1                                               
   Nervous System                                                                                         
 Circumoral paresthesia                                   1                                               
 General paresthesia                                      1                                               
 Nervousness                                              1                                               
         In the 42 patients treated with CroFab  (r)  for minimal or moderate crotalid envenomations, there were 7 events classified as early serum reactions and 5 events classified as late serum reactions, and none were serious (  Table 2  ). In the clinical studies, serum reactions consisted mainly of urticaria and rash, and all patients recovered without sequelae.
 

 Table 2 Incidence of Early and Late Serum Reactions (Reactions Associated with CroFab (r) Infusion) 
   *  6 of 42 patients experienced an adverse event associated with an early serum reaction and 4 experienced an adverse event associated with a late serum reaction. Two additional patients were considered to have a late serum reaction by the investigator, although no associated adverse event was reported.   
   **  Allergic reaction consisted of urticaria, dyspnea and wheezing in 1 patient.   
     Serum sickness consisted of severe rash and pruritus in 1 patient.   
  
                              n=42  *  Number of Events     
   Early Serum Reactions                                
 Urticaria                  5                           
 Cough                      1                           
 Allergic reaction  **      1                           
   Late Serum Reactions                                 
 Rash                       2                           
 Pruritus                   1                           
 Urticaria                  1                           
 Serum sickness             1                           
        6.2 Post-marketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during the post approval use of CroFab  (r)  . Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to product exposure:



 *  Acute allergic reactions including anaphylaxis or anaphylactoid type reactions during or shortly following CroFab  (r)  infusion, manifested by one or more of the following: anxiety, bronchospasm, chills, edema, fever, hypotension, pruritis, rash, urticaria, voice alteration, and/or wheezing 
 *  Delayed allergic reaction manifested by fever, pruritis and/or rash 
 *  Delayed or recurrent coagulopathy or thrombocytopenia 
 *  Failure to achieve initial control 
 *  Recurrent swelling refractory to treatment 
 *  Thrombocytopenia refractory to treatment 
 *  Prolonged hospitalization 
 *  Bleeding 
 *  Nausea 
 *  Tremor 
 *  Worsening eye sight 
 *  Treatment failure resulting in death 
    A retrospective study of data collected by the Rocky Mountain Poison and Drug Center for post-marketing use of CroFab  (r)  was conducted (  14.2  ).
 

 *  *  There were 11 immediate serious adverse events related to CroFab  (r)  administration reported in four patients. The events included two episodes each of hypotension and tongue swelling, and one episode each of chest discomfort, angioedema, bronchospasm, wheezing, tracheal edema, dyspnea, and lip swelling. 
 *  There were 22 immediate non-serious adverse events related to CroFab  (r)  administration reported in 12 patients. The events included four episodes each of rash and pruritis, three episodes of urticaria, and one episode each of tachycardia, tachypnea, erythema, swelling, hyperhidrosis, dizziness, headache, musculoskeletal chest pain, chills, feeling cold, and nervousness. 
   There were a total of 36 immediate adverse drug reactions reported in 6.1% (15/247) of patients in the post-marketing retrospective study, including one patient in the severely envenomated group (3.6%, n = 28) and 13 patients in the mild/moderate severity group (7.2%, n = 181) (not significantly different rates). 
 *  Delayed hypersensitivity reactions were reported for two patients. In one patient the symptoms occurred 6 days post-dosing, were not serious, and described as hives, itching and epigastric pressure. In the second patient symptoms were not described in the medical records and were therefore not captured in this study. 
 *  Recurrent coagulopathy developed in 5 severely envenomated patients and in 6 mild/moderate envenomated patients. In addition, 7 mild/moderate patients experienced delayed-onset coagulopathy. One severely envenomated patient with recurrent coagulopathy experienced medically significant bleeding. 
      Additional Published Clinical Studies Experience  From a literature review of nine publications on CroFab  (r)  containing patient exposure data, 15 of 313 (4.8%) patients receiving CroFab  (r)  experienced acute hypersensitivity reactions.
 

 The most common signs and symptoms associated with these reactions were rash (10 patients) and wheezing (3 patients). Most reactions were mild, resolved after antihistamine therapy, and did not require discontinuation of antivenom therapy. No patient developed a life-threatening hypersensitivity reaction, required intubation, suffered lasting ill-effect, or died as a result of CroFab  (r)  administration.



 Follow up data (minimum of six days after treatment) were available in 94 of the 313 patients and delayed hypersensitivity reactions were reported in 10 cases. The most common signs and symptoms of delayed hypersensitivity were rash (9 patients) and fever (3 patients). Most were mild and treated with antihistamines and steroids.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Patients who experience coagulopathy due to snakebite should be monitored for recurrent coagulopathy for up to 1 week or longer. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Anaphylaxis and hypersensitivity reactions can occur and patients should be monitored closely during treatment. Patients with allergies to papain, chymopapain, other papaya extracts, or the pineapple enzyme bromelain may also be at risk for an allergic reaction to CroFab  (r)  . (  5.2  ) 
 *  CroFab  (r)  contains mercury in the form of ethyl mercury from thimerosal. The final product contains up to 30 mcg or approximately 0.03 mg of mercury per vial, which amounts to no more than 0.6 mg of mercury per dose (based on the maximum dose of 18 vials studied in clinical trials of CroFab  (r)  ). (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Coagulopathy



  Coagulopathy is a complication noted in many victims of viper envenomation that arises due to the ability of the snake venom to interfere with the blood coagulation cascade [  4  ,  8  ,  9  ], and is seen more frequently in severely envenomated patients. In clinical trials with CroFab  (r)  , recurrent coagulopathy (the return of a coagulation abnormality after it has been successfully treated with antivenin), characterized by decreased fibrinogen, decreased platelets, and elevated prothrombin time, occurred in approximately half of patients studied. The clinical significance of these recurrent abnormalities is not known. Recurrent coagulation abnormalities were observed only in patients who experienced coagulation abnormalities during their initial hospitalization, although coagulopathy can initially appear at any time before, during or after treatment. Optimal dosing to completely prevent recurrent coagulopathy has not been determined. Because CroFab  (r)  has a shorter persistence in the blood than crotalid venoms that can leak from depot sites over a prolonged period of time, repeat dosing to prevent or treat such recurrence may be necessary ( see Dosage and Administration (  2  )  ).



 Recurrent coagulopathy may persist for 1 to 2 weeks or more. Patients who experience coagulopathy due to snakebite during hospitalization for initial treatment should be monitored for signs and symptoms of recurrent coagulopathy for up to 1 week or longer at the physician's discretion. During this period, the physician should carefully assess the need for re-treatment with CroFab  (r)  and use of any type of anticoagulant or anti-platelet drug.



 Because snake envenomation can cause coagulation abnormalities, the following conditions, which are also associated with coagulation defects, should be considered: cancer, collagen disease, congestive heart failure, diarrhea, elevated temperature, hepatic disorders, hyperthyroidism, poor nutritional state, steatorrhea, vitamin K deficiency.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur with CroFab  (r)  . In case of acute hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis and anaphylactoid reactions, discontinue infusion and institute appropriated emergency treatment.



 CroFab  (r)  contains purified immunoglobulin fragments from the blood of sheep that have been immunized with snake venoms (see  11 Description  ). Injection of heterologous animal proteins can cause severe acute and delayed hypersensitivity reactions (late serum reaction or serum sickness) and a possible febrile response to immune complexes formed by animal antibodies and neutralized venom components [  10  ].



 Papain is used to cleave antibodies into fragments during the processing of CroFab  (r)  , and trace amounts of papain or inactivated papain residues may be present. Patients allergic to papain, chymopapain, other papaya extracts, or the pineapple enzyme bromelain may also have an allergic reaction to CroFab  (r)  . Some dust mite allergens and some latex allergens share antigenic structures with papain and patients with these allergies may be allergic to papain.



 The following precautions should be used to manage hypersensitivity reactions:



 Emergency medical care (e.g., epinephrine, intravenous antihistamines and/or albuterol) should be readily available.



 Carefully monitored patients for signs and symptoms of an acute allergic reaction (e.g., urticaria, pruritus, erythema, angioedema, bronchospasm with wheezing or cough, stridor, laryngeal edema, hypotension, tachycardia).



 Follow-up all patients for signs and symptoms of delayed allergic reactions or serum sickness (e.g., rash, fever, myalgia, arthralgia).



 It has been noted in the literature with the use of other antibody therapies, that reactions during the infusion, such as fever, low back pain, wheezing and nausea are often related to the rate of infusion and can be controlled by decreasing the rate of administration of the solution [  11  ].



 Patients who receive a course of treatment with a foreign protein such as CroFab  (r)  may become sensitized to it. Therefore, caution should be used when administering a repeat course of treatment with CroFab  (r)  for a subsequent envenomation episode.



 Skin testing has not been used in clinical trials of CroFab  (r)  and is not required.



    5.3 Mercury Toxicity



  The final product contains up to 30 mcg or approximately 0.03 mg of mercury per vial, which amounts to no more than 0.6 mg of mercury per dose (based on the maximum dose of 18 vials studied in clinical trials of CroFab  (r)  ). While there are no definitive data on the toxicity of ethyl mercury, literature suggests that information related to methyl mercury toxicities may be applicable.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
