<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cubicin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described, or described in greater detail, in other sections:



 *  Anaphylaxis/hypersensitivity reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Myopathy and rhabdomyolysis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Eosinophilic pneumonia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Peripheral neuropathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Increased International Normalized Ratio (INR)/prolonged prothrombin time [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  and  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

   EXCERPT:   The most clinically significant adverse reactions observed with CUBICIN 4 mg/kg (cSSSI trials) and 6 mg/kg (  S. aureus  bacteremia/endocarditis trial) were abnormal liver function tests, elevated CPK, and dyspnea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Clinical trials enrolled 1,864 patients treated with CUBICIN and 1,416 treated with comparator.



     Complicated Skin and Skin Structure Infection Trials  



 In Phase 3 complicated skin and skin structure infection (cSSSI) trials, CUBICIN was discontinued in 15/534 (2.8%) patients due to an adverse reaction, while comparator was discontinued in 17/558 (3.0%) patients.



 The rates of the most common adverse reactions, organized by body system, observed in cSSSI (4 mg/kg CUBICIN) patients are displayed in Table 5.



 Table 5: Incidence of Adverse Reactions that Occurred in &gt;=2% of Patients in the CUBICIN Treatment Group and &gt;= the Comparator Treatment Group in Phase 3 cSSSI Trials 
 Adverse Reaction                              Patients (%)              
 CUBICIN 4 mg/kg(N=534)                      Comparator(N=558)           
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
   Diarrhea                                         5.2                                4.3                  
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
   Headache                                         5.4                                5.4                  
   Dizziness                                        2.2                                2.0                  
   Skin/subcutaneous disorders                                                                              
   Rash                                             4.3                                3.8                  
   Diagnostic investigations                                                                                
   Abnormal liver function tests                    3.0                                1.6                  
   Elevated CPK                                     2.8                                1.8                  
   Infections                                                                                               
   Urinary tract infections                         2.4                                0.5                  
   Vascular disorders                                                                                       
   Hypotension                                      2.4                                1.4                  
   Respiratory disorders                                                                                    
   Dyspnea                                          2.1                                1.6                  
         Drug-related adverse reactions (possibly or probably drug-related) that occurred in &lt;1% of patients receiving CUBICIN in the cSSSI trials are as follows:
 

   Body as a Whole:  fatigue, weakness, rigors, flushing, hypersensitivity



   Blood/Lymphatic System:  leukocytosis, thrombocytopenia, thrombocytosis, eosinophilia, increased International Normalized Ratio (INR)



   Cardiovascular System:  supraventricular arrhythmia



   Dermatologic System:  eczema



   Digestive System:  abdominal distension, stomatitis, jaundice, increased serum lactate dehydrogenase



   Metabolic/Nutritional System:  hypomagnesemia, increased serum bicarbonate, electrolyte disturbance



   Musculoskeletal System:  myalgia, muscle cramps, muscle weakness, arthralgia



   Nervous System:  vertigo, mental status change, paresthesia



   Special Senses:  taste disturbance, eye irritation



       S. aureus  Bacteremia/Endocarditis Trial  



 In the  S. aureus  bacteremia/endocarditis trial, CUBICIN was discontinued in 20/120 (16.7%) patients due to an adverse reaction, while comparator was discontinued in 21/116 (18.1%) patients.



 Serious Gram-negative infections (including bloodstream infections) were reported in 10/120 (8.3%) CUBICIN-treated patients and 0/115 comparator-treated patients. Comparator-treated patients received dual therapy that included initial gentamicin for 4 days. Infections were reported during treatment and during early and late follow-up. Gram-negative infections included cholangitis, alcoholic pancreatitis, sternal osteomyelitis/mediastinitis, bowel infarction, recurrent Crohn's disease, recurrent line sepsis, and recurrent urosepsis caused by a number of different Gram-negative bacteria.



 The rates of the most common adverse reactions, organized by System Organ Class (SOC), observed in  S. aureus  bacteremia/endocarditis (6 mg/kg CUBICIN) patients are displayed in Table 6.



 Table 6: Incidence of Adverse Reactions that Occurred in &gt;=5% of Patients in the CUBICIN Treatment Group and &gt;= the Comparator Treatment Group in the S. aureus Bacteremia/Endocarditis Trial 
 Adverse Reaction                              Patientsn (%)             
 CUBICIN 6 mg/kg(N=120)                      Comparator(N=116)           
  
   Infections and infestations                                                                              
   Sepsis NOS                                     6 (5%)                             3 (3%)                 
   Bacteremia                                     6 (5%)                             0 (0%)                 
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
   Abdominal pain NOS                             7 (6%)                             4 (3%)                 
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                           
   Chest pain                                     8 (7%)                             7 (6%)                 
   Edema NOS                                      8 (7%)                             5 (4%)                 
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                           
   Pharyngolaryngeal pain                         10 (8%)                            2 (2%)                 
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                           
   Pruritus                                       7 (6%)                             6 (5%)                 
   Sweating increased                             6 (5%)                             0 (0%)                 
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                       11 (9%)                            8 (7%)                 
   Investigations                                                                                           
   Blood creatine phosphokinase increased               8 (7%)                             1 (1%)                 
   Vascular disorders                                                                                       
   Hypertension NOS                               7 (6%)                             3 (3%)                 
         The following reactions, not included above, were reported as possibly or probably drug-related in the CUBICIN-treated group:
 

   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  eosinophilia, lymphadenopathy, thrombocythemia, thrombocytopenia



   Cardiac Disorders:  atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, cardiac arrest



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  tinnitus



   Eye Disorders:  vision blurred



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  dry mouth, epigastric discomfort, gingival pain, hypoesthesia oral



   Infections and Infestations:  candidal infection NOS, vaginal candidiasis, fungemia, oral candidiasis, urinary tract infection fungal



   Investigations:  blood phosphorous increased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, INR increased, liver function test abnormal, alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, prothrombin time prolonged



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  appetite decreased NOS



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  myalgia



   Nervous System Disorders:  dyskinesia, paresthesia



   Psychiatric Disorders:  hallucination NOS



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  proteinuria, renal impairment NOS



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  pruritus generalized, rash vesicular



     Other Trials  



 In Phase 3 trials of community-acquired pneumonia (CAP), the death rate and rates of serious cardiorespiratory adverse events were higher in CUBICIN-treated patients than in comparator-treated patients. These differences were due to lack of therapeutic effectiveness of CUBICIN in the treatment of CAP in patients experiencing these adverse events  [see  Indications and Usage (1.3)  ].  



     Laboratory Changes  



     Complicated Skin and Skin Structure Infection Trials  



 In Phase 3 cSSSI trials of CUBICIN at a dose of 4 mg/kg, elevations in CPK were reported as clinical adverse events in 15/534 (2.8%) CUBICIN-treated patients, compared with 10/558 (1.8%) comparator-treated patients. Of the 534 patients treated with CUBICIN, 1 (0.2%) had symptoms of muscle pain or weakness associated with CPK elevations to greater than 4 times the upper limit of normal (ULN). The symptoms resolved within 3 days and CPK returned to normal within 7 to 10 days after treatment was discontinued  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  Table 7 summarizes the CPK shifts from Baseline through End of Therapy in the cSSSI trials.



 Table 7: Incidence of CPK Elevations from Baseline during Therapy in Either the CUBICIN Treatment Group or the Comparator Treatment Group in Phase 3 cSSSI Trials 
 Change in CPK             All Patients  Patients with Normal CPK at Baseline   
 CUBICIN4 mg/kg(N=430)   Comparator(N=459)  CUBICIN4 mg/kg(N=374)  Comparator(N=392)   
 %                                    n  %         n         %         n         %         n          
  
 Note: Elevations in CPK observed in patients treated with CUBICIN or comparator were not clinically or statistically significantly different.   
  
 No Increase                             90.7      390       91.1      418       91.2      341       91.1      357        
 Maximum Value                  &gt;1* ULN  9.3       40        8.9       41        8.8       33        8.9       35         
                                &gt;2* ULN  4.9       21        4.8       22        3.7       14        3.1       12         
                                &gt;4* ULN  1.4       6         1.5       7         1.1       4         1.0       4          
                                &gt;5* ULN  1.4       6         0.4       2         1.1       4         0.0       0          
                               &gt;10* ULN  0.5       2         0.2       1         0.2       1         0.0       0          
                    S. aureus Bacteremia/Endocarditis Trial  
 

 In the  S. aureus  bacteremia/endocarditis trial, at a dose of 6 mg/kg, 11/120 (9.2%) CUBICIN-treated patients, including two patients with baseline CPK levels &gt;500 U/L, had CPK elevations to levels &gt;500 U/L, compared with 1/116 (0.9%) comparator-treated patients. Of the 11 CUBICIN-treated patients, 4 had prior or concomitant treatment with an HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor. Three of these 11 CUBICIN-treated patients discontinued therapy due to CPK elevation, while the one comparator-treated patient did not discontinue therapy  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of CUBICIN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  anemia



   General and administration site conditions:  pyrexia



   Immune System Disorders:  anaphylaxis; hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema, drug rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), pruritus, hives, shortness of breath, difficulty swallowing, truncal erythema, and pulmonary eosinophilia  [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



   Infections and Infestations: Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  



   Musculoskeletal Disorders:  myoglobin increased; rhabdomyolysis (some reports involved patients treated concurrently with CUBICIN and HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ,  Drug Interactions (7.1)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  cough, eosinophilic pneumonia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  



   Nervous System Disorders:  peripheral neuropathy  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  serious skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and vesiculobullous rash (with or without mucous membrane involvement), acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  nausea, vomiting



   Renal and urinary disorders:  acute kidney injury, renal insufficiency, and renal failure



   Special Senses:  visual disturbances
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Anaphylaxis/hypersensitivity reactions (including life-threatening): Discontinue CUBICIN RF and treat signs/symptoms. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Myopathy and rhabdomyolysis: Monitor CPK levels and follow muscle pain or weakness; if elevated CPK or myopathy occurs, consider discontinuation of CUBICIN RF. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Eosinophilic pneumonia: Discontinue CUBICIN RF and consider treatment with systemic steroids. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Peripheral neuropathy: Monitor for neuropathy and consider discontinuation. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Potential nervous system and/or muscular system effects in pediatric patients younger than 12 months: Avoid use of CUBICIN RF in this age group. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile- associated diarrhea: Evaluate patients if diarrhea occurs. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Persisting or relapsing S. aureus bacteremia/endocarditis: Perform susceptibility testing and rule out sequestered foci of infection. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Decreased efficacy was observed in patients with moderate baseline renal impairment. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylaxis/Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Anaphylaxis/hypersensitivity reactions have been reported with the use of antibacterial agents, including CUBICIN, and may be life-threatening. If an allergic reaction to CUBICIN RF occurs, discontinue the drug and institute appropriate therapy [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.2 Myopathy and Rhabdomyolysis



  Myopathy, defined as muscle aching or muscle weakness in conjunction with increases in creatine phosphokinase (CPK) values to greater than 10 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), has been reported with the use of CUBICIN. Rhabdomyolysis, with or without acute renal failure, has been reported [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  .



 Patients receiving CUBICIN RF should be monitored for the development of muscle pain or weakness, particularly of the distal extremities. In patients who receive CUBICIN RF, CPK levels should be monitored weekly, and more frequently in patients who received recent prior or concomitant therapy with an HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor or in whom elevations in CPK occur during treatment with CUBICIN RF.



 In patients with renal impairment, both renal function and CPK should be monitored more frequently than once weekly [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



 In Phase 1 studies and Phase 2 clinical trials, CPK elevations appeared to be more frequent when CUBICIN was dosed more than once daily. Therefore, CUBICIN RF should not be dosed more frequently than once a day.



 CUBICIN RF should be discontinued in patients with unexplained signs and symptoms of myopathy in conjunction with CPK elevations to levels &gt;1,000 U/L (~5* ULN), and in patients without reported symptoms who have marked elevations in CPK, with levels &gt;2,000 U/L (&gt;=10* ULN). In addition, consideration should be given to suspending agents associated with rhabdomyolysis, such as HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors, temporarily in patients receiving CUBICIN RF [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ].  



    5.3 Eosinophilic Pneumonia



  Eosinophilic pneumonia has been reported in patients receiving CUBICIN [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  In reported cases associated with CUBICIN, patients developed fever, dyspnea with hypoxic respiratory insufficiency, and diffuse pulmonary infiltrates. In general, patients developed eosinophilic pneumonia 2 to 4 weeks after starting CUBICIN and improved when CUBICIN was discontinued and steroid therapy was initiated. Recurrence of eosinophilic pneumonia upon re-exposure has been reported. Patients who develop these signs and symptoms while receiving CUBICIN RF should undergo prompt medical evaluation, and CUBICIN RF should be discontinued immediately. Treatment with systemic steroids is recommended.



    5.4 Peripheral Neuropathy



  Cases of peripheral neuropathy have been reported during the CUBICIN postmarketing experience [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  Therefore, physicians should be alert to signs and symptoms of peripheral neuropathy in patients receiving CUBICIN RF.



    5.5 Potential Nervous System and/or Muscular System Effects in Pediatric Patients Younger than 12 Months



  Avoid use of CUBICIN RF in pediatric patients younger than 12 months due to the risk of potential effects on muscular, neuromuscular, and/or nervous systems (either peripheral and/or central) observed in neonatal dogs with intravenous daptomycin [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2)  ].  



    5.6 Clostridium difficile  -Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with the use of nearly all systemic antibacterial agents, including CUBICIN, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon, leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B, which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin-producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, since these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial use. Careful medical history is necessary because CDAD has been reported to occur more than 2 months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibacterial use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.7 Persisting or Relapsing S. aureus  Bacteremia/Endocarditis



  Patients with persisting or relapsing S. aureus  bacteremia/endocarditis or poor clinical response should have repeat blood cultures. If a blood culture is positive for S. aureus  , minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) susceptibility testing of the isolate should be performed using a standardized procedure, and diagnostic evaluation of the patient should be performed to rule out sequestered foci of infection. Appropriate surgical intervention (e.g., debridement, removal of prosthetic devices, valve replacement surgery) and/or consideration of a change in antibacterial regimen may be required.



 Failure of treatment due to persisting or relapsing S. aureus  bacteremia/endocarditis may be due to reduced daptomycin susceptibility (as evidenced by increasing MIC of the S. aureus  isolate) [see  Clinical Trials (14.2)  ].  



    5.8 Decreased Efficacy in Patients with Moderate Baseline Renal Impairment



  Limited data are available from the two Phase 3 complicated skin and skin structure infection (cSSSI) trials regarding clinical efficacy of CUBICIN treatment in patients with creatinine clearance (CLCR) &lt;50 mL/min; only 31/534 (6%) patients treated with CUBICIN in the intent-to-treat (ITT) population had a baseline CLCR&lt;50 mL/min. Table 3 shows the number of patients by renal function and treatment group who were clinical successes in the Phase 3 cSSSI trials.



 Table 3: Clinical Success Rates by Renal Function and Treatment Group in Phase 3 cSSSI Trials (Population: ITT) 
 CLCR                                       Success Raten/N (%)          
 CUBICIN4 mg/kg q24h                            Comparator               
  
 50-70 mL/min                                   25/38 (66%)                        30/48 (63%)              
 30-&lt;50 mL/min                                  7/15 (47%)                         20/35 (57%)              
         In a subgroup analysis of the ITT population in the Phase 3 S. aureus  bacteremia/endocarditis trial, clinical success rates, as determined by a treatment-blinded Adjudication Committee [see  Clinical Trials (14.2)  ]  , in the CUBICIN-treated patients were lower in patients with baseline CLCR&lt;50 mL/min (see  Table 4  ). A decrease of the magnitude shown in Table 4 was not observed in comparator-treated patients.
 

 Table 4: Adjudication Committee Clinical Success Rates at Test of Cure by Baseline Creatinine Clearance and Treatment Subgroup in the S. aureus Bacteremia/Endocarditis Trial (Population: ITT) 
 Baseline CLCR         Success Raten/N (%)    
 CUBICIN6 mg/kg q24h        Comparator        
 Bacteremia            Right-SidedInfective Endocarditis       Bacteremia       Right-SidedInfective Endocarditis   
  
 &gt;80 mL/min                30/50 (60%)            7/14 (50%)           19/42 (45%)            5/11 (46%)        
 50-80 mL/min              12/26 (46%)            1/4 (25%)            13/31 (42%)            1/2 (50%)         
 30-&lt;50 mL/min              2/14 (14%)             0/1 (0%)             7/17 (41%)            1/1 (100%)        
           Consider these data when selecting antibacterial therapy for use in patients with baseline moderate to severe renal impairment.
 

    5.9 Drug-Laboratory Test Interactions



  Clinically relevant plasma concentrations of daptomycin have been observed to cause a significant concentration-dependent false prolongation of prothrombin time (PT) and elevation of International Normalized Ratio (INR) when certain recombinant thromboplastin reagents are utilized for the assay [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



    5.10 Non-Susceptible Microorganisms



  The use of antibacterials may promote the overgrowth of non-susceptible microorganisms. If superinfection occurs during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.



 Prescribing CUBICIN RF in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
