<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cyanokit" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions with hydroxocobalamin include allergic reactions and increases in blood pressure  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ,  5.3  )].  



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) include transient chromaturia, erythema, rash, increased blood pressure, nausea, headache, and injection site reactions. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS contact Meridian Medical Technologies    TM    , Inc. at 1-800-776-3637, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials were conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Experience in Healthy Subjects  



 A double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, single-ascending-dose (2.5, 5, 7.5, and 10 g) study was conducted to assess the safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of hydroxocobalamin in 136 healthy adult subjects. Because of the dark red color of hydroxocobalamin, the two most frequently occurring adverse reactions were chromaturia (red-colored urine) which was reported in all subjects receiving a 5 g dose or greater; and erythema (skin redness), which occurred in most subjects receiving a 5 g dose or greater. Adverse reactions reported in at least 5% of the 5 g dose group and corresponding rates in the 10 g and placebo groups are shown in  Table 3  .



 Table 3 Incidence of Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;5% of Subjects in 5 g Dose Group and Corresponding Incidence in 10 g Dose Group and Placebo 
  * Rashes were predominantly acneiform    
  
                                5 g Dose Group         10 g Dose Group     
   ADR                          Hydroxocobalamin    N=66    n (%)      Placebo    N=22    n (%)      Hydroxocobalamin    N=18    n (%)      Placebo N=6    n (%)     
 Chromaturia (red colored urine)  66 (100)               0               18 (100)                0               
 Erythema                     62 (94)                0               18 (100)                0               
 Rash*                        13 (20)                0               8 (44)                  0               
 Blood pressure increased     12 (18)                0               5 (28)                  0               
 Nausea                       4 (6)                  1 (5)           2 (11)                  0               
 Headache                     4 (6)                  1 (5)           6 (33)                  0               
 Lymphocyte percent decreased  5 (8)                  0               3 (17)                  0               
 Infusion site reaction       4 (6)                  0               7 (39)                  0               
           In this study, the following adverse reactions were reported to have occurred in a dose-dependent fashion and with greater frequency than observed in placebo-treated cohorts: increased blood pressure (particularly diastolic blood pressure), rash, nausea, headache and infusion site reactions. All were mild to moderate in severity and resolved spontaneously when the infusion was terminated or with standard supportive therapies.
 

 Other adverse reactions reported in this study and considered clinically relevant were:



 *   Eye disorders: swelling, irritation, redness 
 *   Gastrointestinal disorders: dysphagia, abdominal discomfort, vomiting, diarrhea, dyspepsia, hematochezia 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions: peripheral edema, chest discomfort 
 *   Immune system disorders: allergic reaction 
 *   Nervous system disorders: memory impairment, dizziness 
 *   Psychiatric disorders: restlessness 
 *   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders: dyspnea, throat tightness, dry throat 
 *   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders: urticaria, pruritus 
 *   Vascular disorders: hot flush 
        Experience in Known or Suspected Cyanide Poisoning Victims  
 

 Four open-label, uncontrolled, clinical studies (one of which was prospective and three of which were retrospective) were conducted in known or suspected cyanide-poisoning victims. A total of 245 patients received hydroxocobalamin treatment in these studies. Systematic collection of adverse events was not done in all of these studies and interpretation of causality is limited due to the lack of a control group and due to circumstances of administration (e.g., use in fire victims). Adverse reactions reported in these studies listed by system organ class included:



 *   Cardiac disorders: ventricular extrasystoles 
 *   Investigations: electrocardiogram repolarization abnormality, heart rate increased 
 *   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders: pleural effusion 
    Adverse reactions common to both the studies in known or suspected cyanide poisoning victims and the study in healthy volunteers are listed in the healthy volunteer section only and are not duplicated in this list.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Use caution in the management of patients with known anaphylactic reactions to hydroxocobalamin or cyanocobalamin. Consideration should be given to use of alternative therapies, if available. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Allergic reactions may include: anaphylaxis, chest tightness, edema, urticaria, pruritus, dyspnea, and rash. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Blood pressure increase: Substantial increases in blood pressure may occur following Cyanokit therapy. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Emergency Patient Management



  In addition to Cyanokit, treatment of cyanide poisoning must include immediate attention to airway patency, adequacy of oxygenation and hydration, cardiovascular support, and management of any seizure activity. Consideration should be given to decontamination measures based on the route of exposure.



    5.2 Allergic Reactions



  Use caution in the management of patients with known anaphylactic reactions to hydroxocobalamin or cyanocobalamin. Consideration should be given to use of alternative therapies, if available.



 Allergic reactions may include: anaphylaxis, chest tightness, edema, urticaria, pruritus, dyspnea, and rash.



 Allergic reactions including angioneurotic edema have also been reported in postmarketing experience.



    5.3 Blood Pressure Increase



  Many patients with cyanide poisoning will be hypotensive; however, elevations in blood pressure have also been observed in known or suspected cyanide poisoning victims.



 Elevations in blood pressure (&gt;= 180 mmHg systolic or &gt;= 110 mmHg diastolic) were observed in approximately 18% of healthy subjects (not exposed to cyanide) receiving hydroxocobalamin 5 g and 28% of subjects receiving 10 g. Increases in blood pressure were noted shortly after the infusions were started; the maximal increase in blood pressure was observed toward the end of the infusion. These elevations were generally transient and returned to baseline levels within 4 hours of dosing.



    5.4 Use of Blood Cyanide Assay



  While determination of blood cyanide concentration is not required for management of cyanide poisoning and should not delay treatment with Cyanokit, collecting a pretreatment blood sample may be useful for documenting cyanide poisoning as sampling post-Cyanokit use may be inaccurate.



    5.5 Interference with Clinical Laboratory Evaluations and Clinical Methods



   Clinical Laboratory Evaluations  



 Because of its deep red color, hydroxocobalamin has been found to interfere with colorimetric determination of certain laboratory parameters (e.g., clinical chemistry, hematology, coagulation, and urine parameters). In-vitro  tests indicated that the extent and duration of the interference are dependent on numerous factors such as the dose of hydroxocobalamin, analyte, methodology, analyzer, hydroxocobalamin concentration, and partially on the time between sampling and measurement.



 Based on in-vitro studies and pharmacokinetic data obtained in healthy volunteers, the following table (  Table 2  ) describes laboratory interference that may be observed following a 5 g dose of hydroxocobalamin. Interference following a 10 g dose can be expected to last up to an additional 24 hours. The extent and duration of interference in cyanide-poisoned patients may differ. Results may vary substantially from one analyzer to another; therefore, caution should be used when reporting and interpreting laboratory results.



 Table 2 Laboratory Interference Observed with In-Vitro Samples of Hydroxocobalamin 
 Laboratory        No Interference    Artificially       Artificially     Un-predictable   Duration of        
 Parameter         Observed           Increased *        Decreased *                       Interference       
  
  * &gt;=10% interference observed on at least 1 analyzer    
  Analyzers used: ACL Futura (Instrumentation Laboratory), AxSYM(r)/ArchitectTM (Abbott), BM Coasys110 (Boehringer Mannheim), CellDyn 3700(r) (Abbott), Clinitek(r) 500 (Bayer), Cobas Integra(r) 700, 400 (Roche), Gen-S Coultronics, Hitachi 917, STA(r) Compact, Vitros(r) 950 (Ortho Diagnostics)    
  
  Clinical         Calcium            Creatinine         ALT              Phosphate        24 hours with the exception of bilirubin (up to 4 days)   
  Chemistry        Sodium             Bilirubin          Amylase          Uric Acid         
                   Potassium          Triglycerides                       AST               
                   Chloride           Cholesterol                         CK                
                   Urea               Total protein                       CKMB              
                   GGT                Glucose Albumin Alkaline phosphatase                   LDH               
  Hematology       erythrocytesHematocritMCVLeukocytesLymphocytesMonocytesEosinophilsNeutrophilsPlatelets  HemoglobinMCHMCHCBasophils                                    12 - 16 hours      
  Coagulation                                                             aPTTPT (Quick or INR)  24 - 48 hours      
  Urinalysis                          pH (with all doses)  pH (with equivalent doses of &lt;5 g)                   48 hours up to 8 days; color changes may persist up to 28 days   
                                      Glucose                              
                                      ProteinErythrocytesLeukocytesKetonesBilirubinUrobilinogenNitrite                    
               Clinical Methods  
 

    Because of its deep red color, hydroxocobalamin may cause hemodialysis machines to shut down due to an erroneous detection of a "blood leak". This should be considered before hemodialysis is initiated in patients treated with hydroxocobalamin.



    5.6 Photosensitivity



  Hydroxocobalamin absorbs visible light in the UV spectrum. It therefore has potential to cause photosensitivity. While it is not known if the skin redness predisposes to photosensitivity, patients should be advised to avoid direct sun while their skin remains discolored.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
