<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cystaran" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Clinical Studies Experience  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety data described below reflect exposure in controlled clinical trials of six months to 19 years duration in approximately 300 patients.



 The most frequently reported ocular adverse reactions occuring in &gt;=10% of patients were sensitivity to light, redness, and eye pain/irritation, headache and visual field defects.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence approximately 10% or greater) are sensitivity to light, redness, eye pain/irritation, headache and visual field defects. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sigma-Tau Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-888-393-4584 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   To minimize the risk of contamination, do not touch the dropper tip to any surface. Keep bottle tightly closed when not in use. (  5.1  )



 



   5.1 Contamination of Tip and Solution



  To minimize contaminating the dropper tip and solution, care should be taken not to touch the eyelids or surrounding areas with the dropper tip of the bottle. Keep bottle tightly closed when not in use.



    5.2 Benign Intracranial Hypertension



  There have been reports of benign intracranial hypertension (or pseudotumor cerebri) associated with oral cysteamine treatment that has resolved with the addition of diuretic therapy.



 There have also been reports associated with ophthalmic use of cysteamine; however, all of these patients were on concurrent oral cysteamine.



    5.3 Use with Contact Lenses



  CYSTARAN contains benzalkonium chloride, which may be absorbed by soft contact lenses. Contact lenses should be removed prior to application of solution and may be reinserted 15 minutes following its administration [see Patient Counseling Information(  17.3  )]  .



    5.4 Topical Ophthalmic Use Only



  CYSTARAN is for topical ophthalmic use only.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
