<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cystagon" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In three clinical trials, cysteamine or phosphocysteamine have been administered to 246 children with cystinosis. Causality of side effects is sometimes difficult to determine because adverse effects may result from the underlying disease.



 The most frequent adverse reactions seen involve the gastrointestinal and central nervous systems. These are especially prominent at the initiation of cysteamine therapy. Temporarily suspending treatment, then gradual re-introduction may be effective in improving tolerance.



 Adverse reactions were not collected systematically in the NCCS, but were often listed by investigators. The following rates may therefore be underestimated. The most common events (&gt; 5%) were vomiting 35%, anorexia 31%, fever 22%, diarrhea 16%, lethargy 11%, and rash 7%.



 Less common adverse events are:



   Body as a whole:  Dehydration.



   Cardiovascular:  Hypertension.



   Digestive:  Nausea, bad breath, abdominal pain, dyspepsia, constipation, gastroenteritis, duodenitis, gastrointestinal ulceration and bleeding.



   Central Nervous System:  Somnolence, encephalopathy, headache, seizures, ataxia, confusion, tremor, hyperkinesia, decreasing hearing, dizziness, jitteriness.



   Psychiatric:  Nervousness, abnormal thinking, depression, emotional lability, hallucinations, nightmares.



   Integumentary:  Urticaria.



   Urogenital:  Interstitial nephritis, renal failure (see  WARNINGS  ).



   Clinical Laboratory:  Abnormal liver function, anemia, leukopenia.



 Adverse reactions or intolerance leading to cessation of treatment occurred in 8% of patients in the U.S. Studies.



 Withdrawals due to intolerance, vomiting associated with medication, anorexia, lethargy, and fever appeared dose related, occurring more frequently in those patients receiving 1.95 grams/m  2  /day as compared to 1.30 grams/m  2  /day.




                                                                      Dose in Grams/m  2  /day     
                                                                      1.30(  n = 42  )%      1.95(  n = 51  )%     
  
 Vomiting Considered Related to Medicine                                   31                67           
 Anorexia                                                                  33                51           
 Lethargy                                                                  17                27           
 Diarrhea                                                                  31                31           
 Fever                                                                     28                45           
         Sudden deaths have been reported in this disease state.
 

   Post-marketing surveillance

  Benign intracranial hypertension (or pseudotumor cerebri; PTC) with papilledema; skin lesions, molluscoid pseudotumors, skin striae, skin fragility; joint hyperextension, leg pain, genu valgum, osteopenia, compression fracture and scoliosis have been reported (see  PRECAUTIONS  ).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
