<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="cytotec" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following have been reported as adverse events in subjects receiving Cytotec:



   Gastrointestinal

  In subjects receiving Cytotec 400 or 800 mcg daily in clinical trials, the most frequent gastrointestinal adverse events were diarrhea and abdominal pain. The incidence of diarrhea at 800 mcg in controlled trials in patients on NSAIDs ranged from 14-40% and in all studies (over 5,000 patients) averaged 13%. Abdominal pain occurred in 13-20% of patients in NSAID trials and about 7% in all studies, but there was no consistent difference from placebo.



 Diarrhea was dose related and usually developed early in the course of therapy (after 13 days), usually was self-limiting (often resolving after 8 days), but sometimes required discontinuation of Cytotec (2% of the patients). Rare instances of profound diarrhea leading to severe dehydration have been reported. Patients with an underlying condition such as inflammatory bowel disease, or those in whom dehydration, were it to occur, would be dangerous, should be monitored carefully if Cytotec is prescribed. The incidence of diarrhea can be minimized by administering after meals and at bedtime, and by avoiding coadministration of Cytotec with magnesium-containing antacids.



   Gynecological

  Women who received Cytotec during clinical trials reported the following gynecological disorders: spotting (0.7%), cramps (0.6%), hypermenorrhea (0.5%), menstrual disorder (0.3%) and dysmenorrhea (0.1%). Postmenopausal vaginal bleeding may be related to Cytotec administration. If it occurs, diagnostic workup should be undertaken to rule out gynecological pathology. (See boxed    WARNINGS  .  )



   Elderly

  There were no significant differences in the safety profile of Cytotec in approximately 500 ulcer patients who were 65 years of age or older compared with younger patients.



 Additional adverse events which were reported are categorized as follows:



   Incidence greater than 1%

  In clinical trials, the following adverse reactions were reported by more than 1% of the subjects receiving Cytotec and may be causally related to the drug: nausea (3.2%), flatulence (2.9%), headache (2.4%), dyspepsia (2.0%), vomiting (1.3%), and constipation (1.1%). However, there were no significant differences between the incidences of these events for Cytotec and placebo.



   Causal relationship unknown

  The following adverse events were infrequently reported. Causal relationships between Cytotec and these events have not been established but cannot be excluded:



   Body as a whole:  aches/pains, asthenia, fatigue, fever, chills, rigors, weight changes.



   Skin:  rash, dermatitis, alopecia, pallor, breast pain.



   Special senses:  abnormal taste, abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, deafness, tinnitus, earache.



   Respiratory:  upper respiratory tract infection, bronchitis, bronchospasm, dyspnea, pneumonia, epistaxis.



   Cardiovascular:  chest pain, edema, diaphoresis, hypotension, hypertension, arrhythmia, phlebitis, increased cardiac enzymes, syncope, myocardial infarction (some fatal), thromboembolic events (e.g., pulmonary embolism, arterial thrombosis, and CVA).



   Gastrointestinal:  GI bleeding, GI inflammation/infection, rectal disorder, abnormal hepatobiliary function, gingivitis, reflux, dysphagia, amylase increase.



   Hypersensitivity:  anaphylactic reaction



   Metabolic:  glycosuria, gout, increased nitrogen, increased alkaline phosphatase.



   Genitourinary:  polyuria, dysuria, hematuria, urinary tract infection.



   Nervous system/Psychiatric:  anxiety, change in appetite, depression, drowsiness, dizziness, thirst, impotence, loss of libido, sweating increase, neuropathy, neurosis, confusion.



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, myalgia, muscle cramps, stiffness, back pain.



   Blood/Coagulation:  anemia, abnormal differential, thrombocytopenia, purpura, ESR increased.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS

  WARNINGS

  CYTOTEC (MISOPROSTOL) ADMINISTRATION TO WOMEN WHO ARE PREGNANT CAN CAUSE BIRTH DEFECTS, ABORTION, OR PREMATURE BIRTH. UTERINE RUPTURE HAS BEEN REPORTED WHEN CYTOTEC WAS ADMINISTERED IN PREGNANT WOMEN TO INDUCE LABOR OR TO INDUCE ABORTION BEYOND THE EIGHTH WEEK OF PREGNANCY (see also     PRECAUTIONS     and     LABOR AND DELIVERY    ). CYTOTEC SHOULD NOT BE TAKEN BY PREGNANT WOMEN TO REDUCE THE RISK OF ULCERS INDUCED BY NONSTEROIDAL ANTI-INFLAMMATORY DRUGS (NSAIDs) (see     CONTRAINDICATIONS    ,     WARNINGS    , and     PRECAUTIONS    ).



 PATIENTS MUST BE ADVISED OF THE ABORTIFACIENT PROPERTY AND WARNED NOT TO GIVE THE DRUG TO OTHERS.



 Cytotec should not be used for reducing the risk of NSAID-induced ulcers in women of childbearing potential unless the patient is at high risk of complications from gastric ulcers associated with use of the NSAID, or is at high risk of developing gastric ulceration. In such patients, Cytotec may be prescribed if the patient



 *  has had a negative serum pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to beginning therapy. 
 *  is capable of complying with effective contraceptive measures. 
 *  has received both oral and written warnings of the hazards of misoprostol, the risk of possible contraception failure, and the danger to other women of childbearing potential should the drug be taken by mistake. 
 *  will begin Cytotec only on the second or third day of the next normal menstrual period. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
