<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dacogen" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt; 50%) are neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, and pyrexia. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eisai, Inc. at 1-888-274-2378 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

      Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Most Commonly Occurring Adverse Reactions:    neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, fatigue, pyrexia, nausea, cough, petechiae, constipation, diarrhea, and hyperglycemia.



   Adverse Reactions Most Frequently  (&gt;= 1%)   Resulting in Clinical Intervention in the Phase 3 Trials in the Dacogen Arm:  



 *  Discontinuation:  thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, pneumonia, Mycobacterium avium complex infection, cardio-respiratory arrest, increased blood bilirubin, intracranial hemorrhage, abnormal liver function tests. 
 *  Dose Delayed:  neutropenia, pulmonary edema, atrial fibrillation, central line infection, febrile neutropenia. 
 *  Dose Reduced:  neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, lethargy, edema, tachycardia, depression, pharyngitis. 
      Discussion of Adverse Reactions Information      Dacogen was studied in 3 single-arm studies (N = 66, N = 98, N = 99) and 1 controlled supportive care study (N = 83 Dacogen, N = 81 supportive care ).  The data described below reflect exposure to Dacogen in 83 patients in the MDS trial.  In the trial, patients received 15 mg/m  2  intravenously every 8 hours for 3 days every 6 weeks.  The median number of Dacogen cycles was 3 (range 0 to 9).
 

 Table 1 presents all adverse events regardless of causality occurring in at least 5% of patients in the Dacogen group and at a rate greater than supportive care.



 Table 1 Adverse Events Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients in the Dacogen Group and at a Rate Greater than Supportive Care in Phase 3 MDS Trial 
                  DacogenN = 83 (%)  Supportive CareN = 81 (%)   
  
    Blood and lymphatic system disorders     
       Neutropenia    75 (90)          58 (72)         
       Thrombocytopenia    74 (89)          64 (79)         
       Anemia NOS    68 (82)          60 (74)         
       Febrile neutropenia    24 (29)          5 (6)           
       Leukopenia NOS    23 (28)          11 (14)         
       Lymphadenopathy    10 (12)          6 (7)           
       Thrombocythemia   4 (5)            1 (1)            
    Cardiac disorders     
       Pulmonary edema NOS   5 (6)           0 (0)             
    Eye disorders     
       Vision blurred   5 (6)            0 (0)            
    Gastrointestinal disorders     
       Nausea       35 (42)        13 (16)           
       Constipation    29 (35)        11 (14)           
       Diarrhea NOS    28 (34)        13 (16)           
       Vomiting NOS    21 (25)        7 (9)             
       Abdominal pain NOS    12 (14)        5 (6)             
       Oral mucosal petechiae    11 (13)        4 (5)             
       Stomatitis    10 (12)        5 (6)             
       Dyspepsia    10 (12)        1 (1)             
       Ascites      8 (10)         2 (2)             
       Gingival bleeding   7 (8)           5 (6)             
       Hemorrhoids   7 (8)           3 (4)             
       Loose stools   6 (7)           3 (4)             
       Tongue ulceration   6 (7)           2 (2)             
       Dysphagia   5 (6)           2 (2)             
       Oral soft tissue disorder NOS   5 (6)           1 (1)             
       Lip ulceration   4 (5)           3 (4)             
       Abdominal distension   4 (5)           1 (1)             
       Abdominal pain upper   4 (5)           1 (1)             
       Gastro-esophageal reflux disease   4 (5)           0 (0)             
       Glossodynia   4 (5)           0 (0)             
    General disorders and administrative site disorders     
       Pyrexia      44 (53)        23 (28)           
       Edema peripheral    21 (25)        13 (16)           
       Rigors       18 (22)        14 (17)           
       Edema NOS    15 (18)        5 (6)             
       Pain NOS     11 (13)        5 (6)             
       Lethargy     10 (12)        3 (4)             
       Tenderness NOS    9 (11)         0 (0)             
       Fall       7 (8)            3 (4)             
       Chest discomfort  6 (7)            3 (4)             
       Intermittent pyrexia  5 (6)            3 (4)             
       Malaise    4 (5)            1 (1)             
       Crepitations NOS  4 (5)            1 (1)             
       Catheter site erythema  4 (5)            1 (1)             
       Catheter site pain  4 (5)            0 (0)             
       Injection site swelling  4 (5)            0 (0)             
    Hepatobiliary disorders     
       Hyperbilirubinemia    12 (14)          4 (5)           
    Infections and infestations     
       Pneumonia NOS    18 (22)          11 (14)         
       Cellulitis    10 (12)          6 (7)           
       Candidal infection NOS    8 (10)           1 (1)           
       Catheter related infection  7 (8)            0 (0)             
       Urinary tract infection NOS  6 (7)            1 (1)             
       Staphylococcal infection  6 (7)            0 (0)             
       Oral candidiasis  5 (6)            2 (2)             
       Sinusitis NOS  4 (5)            2 (2)             
       Bacteremia  4 (5)            0 (0)             
    Injury, poisoning and procedural complications     
       Transfusion reaction  6 (7)            3 (4)             
       Abrasion NOS  4 (5)            1 (1)             
    Investigations     
       Cardiac murmur NOS    13 (16)          9 (11)          
       Blood alkaline phosphatase NOS increased     9 (11)           7 (9)           
       Aspartate aminotransferase increased    8 (10)           7 (9)           
       Blood urea increased    8 (10)           1 (1)           
       Blood lactate dehydrogenase increased  7 (8)            5 (6)             
       Blood albumin decreased  6 (7)            0 (0)             
       Blood bicarbonate increased  5 (6)            1 (1)             
       Blood chloride decreased  5 (6)            1 (1)             
       Protein total decreased  4 (5)            3 (4)             
       Blood bicarbonate decreased  4 (5)            1 (1)             
       Blood bilirubin decreased  4 (5)            1 (1)             
    Metabolism and nutrition disorders     
       Hyperglycemia NOS    27 (33)        16 (20)           
       Hypoalbuminemia    20 (24)        14 (17)           
       Hypomagnesemia    20 (24)        6 (7)             
       Hypokalemia    18 (22)        10 (12)           
       Hyponatremia    16 (19)        13 (16)           
       Appetite decreased NOS    13 (16)        12 (15)           
       Anorexia     13 (16)        8 (10)            
       Hyperkalemia    11 (13)        3 (4)             
       Dehydration  5 (6)            4 (5)             
    Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
       Arthralgia    17 (20)          8 (10)          
       Pain in limb    16 (19)          8 (10)          
       Back pain    14 (17)          5 (6)           
       Chest wall pain  6 (7)            1 (1)             
       Musculoskeletal discomfort  5 (6)            0 (0)             
       Myalgia    4 (5)            1 (1)             
    Nervous system disorders     
       Headache     23 (28)          11 (14)         
       Dizziness    15 (18)          10 (12)         
       Hypoesthesia    9 (11)           1 (1)           
    Psychiatric disorders     
       Insomnia     23 (28)          11 (14)         
       Confusional state    10 (12)          3 (4)           
       Anxiety      9 (11)           8 (10)          
    Renal and urinary disorders     
       Dysuria    5 (6)            3 (4)             
       Urinary frequency  4 (5)            1 (1)             
    Respiratory, thoracic and Mediastinal disorders     
       Cough        33 (40)        25 (31)           
       Pharyngitis    13 (16)        6 (7)             
       Crackles lung    12 (14)        1 (1)             
       Breath sounds decreased    8 (10)         7 (9)             
       Hypoxia      8 (10)         4 (5)             
       Rales      7 (8)            2 (2)             
       Postnasal drip  4 (5)            2 (2)             
    Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders     
       Ecchymosis    18 (22)          12 (15)         
       Rash NOS     16 (19)          7 (9)           
       Erythema     12 (14)          5 (6)           
       Skin lesion NOS    9 (11)           3 (4)           
       Pruritis     9 (11)           2 (2)           
       Alopecia   7 (8)            1 (1)             
       Urticaria NOS  5 (6)            1 (1)             
       Swelling face  5 (6)            0 (0)             
    Vascular disorders     
       Petechiae    32 (39)          13 (16)         
       Pallor       19 (23)          10 (12)         
       Hypotension NOS  5 (6)            4 (5)             
       Hematoma NOS  4 (5)            3 (4)             
                 Discussion of Clinically Important Adverse Reactions        In the controlled trial using Dacogen dosed at 15 mg/m  2  , administered by continuous intravenous infusion over 3 hours repeated every 8 hours for 3 days, the highest incidence of Grade 3 or Grade 4 adverse events in the Dacogen arm were neutropenia (87%), thrombocytopenia (85%), febrile neutropenia (23%) and leukopenia (22%).  Bone marrow suppression was the most frequent cause of dose reduction, delay and discontinuation.  Six patients had fatal events associated with their underlying disease and myelosuppression (anemia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia) that were considered at least possibly related to drug treatment [See  Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ]. Of the 83 Dacogen-treated patients, 8 permanently discontinued therapy for adverse events; compared to 1 of 81 patients in the supportive care arm.
 

     In a single-arm MDS study (N=99) Dacogen was dosed at 20 mg/m  2  intravenous, infused over one hour daily for 5 consecutive days of a 4 week cycle. Table 2 presents all adverse events regardless of causality occurring in at least 5% of patients.



 Table 2 Adverse Events Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients in a Single-arm Study* 
                  DacogenN = 99 (%)   
  
    Blood and lymphatic system disorders     
       Anemia     31 (31%)          
       Febrile neutropenia  20 (20%)          
       Leukopenia  6 (6% )           
       Neutropenia  38 (38% )         
       Pancytopenia  5 (5% )           
       Thrombocythemia  5 (5% )           
       Thrombocytopenia  27 (27%)          
    Cardiac disorders     
       Cardiac failure congestive  5 (5% )           
       Tachycardia  8 (8% )           
    Ear and labyrinth disorders     
       Ear pain   6 (6% )           
    Gastrointestinal disorders     
       Abdominal pain    14 (14%)        
       Abdominal pain upper  6 (6% )           
       Constipation    30 (30%)        
       Diarrhea     28 (28%)        
       Dyspepsia    10 (10%)        
       Dysphagia  5 (5% )           
       Gastro-esophageal reflux disease  5 (5% )           
       Nausea       40 (40%)        
       Oral pain  5 (5% )           
       Stomatitis    11 (11%)        
       Toothache  6 (6% )           
       Vomiting     16 (16%)        
    General disorders and administration site conditions     
       Asthenia     15 (15%)        
       Chest pain  6 (6% )           
       Chills       16 (16%)        
       Fatigue      46 (46%)        
       Mucosal inflammation  9 (9% )           
       Edema      5 (5% )           
       Edema peripheral    27 (27%)        
       Pain       5 (5% )           
       Pyrexia      36 (36%)        
    Infections and infestations     
       Cellulitis  9 (9% )           
       Oral candidiasis  6 (6% )           
       Pneumonia    20 (20%)        
       Sinusitis  6 (6% )           
       Staphylococcal bacteremia  8 (8% )           
       Tooth abscess  5 (5% )           
       Upper respiratory tract infection    10 (10%)        
       Urinary tract infection  7 (7% )           
    Injury, poisoning and procedural complications     
       Contusion  9 (9% )           
    Investigations     
       Blood bilirubin increased  6 (6% )           
       Breath sounds abnormal  5 (5% )           
       Weight decreased  9 (9% )           
    Metabolism and nutrition disorders     
       Anorexia   23 (23%)          
       Decreased appetite  8 (8% )           
       Dehydration  8 (8% )           
       Hyperglycemia  6 (6% )           
       Hypokalemia  12 (12%)          
       Hypomagnesemia  5 (5% )           
    Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
       Arthralgia    17 (17%)        
       Back pain    18 (18%)        
       Bone pain  6 (6% )           
       Muscle spasms  7 (7% )           
       Muscular weakness  5 (5% )           
       Musculoskeletal pain  5 (5% )           
       Myalgia    9 (9% )           
       Pain in extremity    18 (18%)        
    Nervous system disorders     
       Dizziness    21 (21%)        
       Headache     23 (23%)        
    Psychiatric disorders     
       Anxiety    9 (9% )           
       Confusional state  8 (8% )           
       Depression  9 (9% )           
       Insomnia     14 (14%)        
    Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
       Cough        27 (27%)        
       Dyspnea      29 (29%)        
       Epistaxis    13 (13%)        
       Pharyngolaryngeal pain  8 (8% )           
       Pleural effusion  5 (5% )           
       Sinus congestion  5 (5% )           
    Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders     
       Dry skin   8 (8% )           
       Ecchymosis  9 (9% )           
       Erythema   5 (5% )           
       Night sweats  5 (5% )           
       Petechiae    12 (12%)        
       Pruritus   9 (9% )           
       Rash         11 (11%)        
       Skin lesion  5 (5% )           
    Vascular disorders     
       Hypertension  6 (6% )           
       Hypotension    11 (11%)        
  * In this single arm study, investigators reported adverse events based on clinical signs and symptoms ratherthan predefined laboratory abnormalities. Thus not all laboratory abnormalities were recorded as adverse events.   
              Discussion of Clinically Important Adverse Reactions      In the single-arm study (N=99) when Dacogen was dosed at 20 mg/m  2  intravenous, infused over one hour daily for 5 consecutive days, the highest incidence of Grade 3 or Grade 4 adverse events were neutropenia (37%), thrombocytopenia (24%) and anemia (22%).  Seventy-eight percent of patients had dose delays, the median duration of this delay was 7 days and the largest percentage of delays were due to hematologic toxicities.  Hematologic toxicities and infections were the most frequent causes of dose delays and discontinuation.  Eight patients had fatal events due to infection and/or bleeding (seven of which occurred in the clinical setting of myelosuppression) that were considered at least possibly related to drug treatment.  Nineteen of 99 patients permanently discontinued therapy for adverse events.
 

     No overall difference in safety was detected between patients &gt; 65 years of age and younger patients in these myelodysplasia trials.  No significant gender differences in safety or efficacy were detected.  Patients with renal or hepatic dysfunction were not studied.  Insufficient numbers of non-white patients were available to draw conclusions in these clinical trials.



     Serious Adverse Events that occurred in patients receiving Dacogen regardless of causality, not previously reported in    Tables 1 and 2    include:



 *  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  myelosuppression, splenomegaly. 
 *  Cardiac Disorders:  myocardial infarction, cardio-respiratory arrest, cardiomyopathy, atrial fibrillation, supraventricular tachycardia. 
 *  Gastrointestinal Disorders:  gingival pain, upper gastrointestinal hemorrhage. 
 *  General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions:  chest pain, catheter site hemorrhage. 
 *  Hepatobiliary Disorders:  cholecystitis. 
 *  Infections and Infestations:  fungal infection, sepsis, bronchopulmonary aspergillosis, peridiverticular abscess, respiratory tract infection, pseudomonal lung infection, Mycobacterium avium complex infection. 
 *  Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  post procedural pain, post procedural hemorrhage. 
 *  Nervous System Disorders:  intracranial hemorrhage. 
 *  Psychiatric Disorders:  mental status changes. 
 *  Renal and Urinary Disorders:  renal failure, urethral hemorrhage. 
 *  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  hemoptysis, lung infiltration, pulmonary embolism, respiratory arrest, pulmonary mass. 
 *  Allergic Reaction:  Hypersensitivity (anaphylactic reaction) to Dacogen has been reported in a Phase 2 trial. 
      6.2 Post-marketing Experience
       The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Dacogen.  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Cases of Sweet's Syndrome (acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis) have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Neutropenia and thrombocytopenia: Perform complete blood counts and platelet counts. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Pregnancy: Can cause fetal harm. Advise women of potential risk to the fetus (  5.2  ,  8.1  ) 
 *  Women of childbearing potential and men with female partners of childbearing potential should use effective contraception and avoid pregnancy (  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Neutropenia and Thrombocytopenia



      Treatment with Dacogen is associated with neutropenia and thrombocytopenia.  Complete blood and platelet counts should be performed as needed to monitor response and toxicity, but at a minimum, prior to each dosing cycle.  After administration of the recommended dosage for the first cycle, treatment for subsequent cycles should be adjusted [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  ,  2.2  )].   Clinicians should consider the need for early institution of growth factors and/or antimicrobial agents for the prevention or treatment of infections in patients with MDS.  Myelosuppression and worsening neutropenia may occur more frequently in the first or second treatment cycles, and may not necessarily indicate progression of underlying MDS.



    5.2 Use in Pregnancy



      Dacogen can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.  Based on its mechanism of action, Dacogen is expected to result in adverse reproductive effects.  In preclinical studies in mice and rats, decitabine was teratogenic, fetotoxic, and embryotoxic. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of Dacogen in pregnant women.  If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if a patient becomes pregnant while receiving this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.  Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while taking Dacogen [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  



    5.3 Use in Women of Childbearing Potential



      Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving Dacogen and for 1 month following completion of treatment. Women of childbearing potential should be counseled to use effective contraception during this time [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  . Based on its mechanism of action, Dacogen can cause fetal harm if used during pregnancy.



    5.4 Use in Men



      Men should be advised not to father a child while receiving treatment with Dacogen, and for 2 months following completion of treatment [see Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.1  )]  . Men with female partners of childbearing potential should use effective contraception during this time. Based on its mechanism of action, Dacogen alters DNA synthesis and can cause fetal harm.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
