<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dantrium" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  There have been occasional reports of death following malignant hyperthermia crisis even when treated with intravenous dantrolene; incidence figures are not available (the pre-dantrolene mortality of malignant hyperthermia crisis was approximately 50%). Most of these deaths can be accounted for by late recognition, delayed treatment, inadequate dosage, lack of supportive therapy, intercurrent disease and/or the development of delayed complications such as renal failure or disseminated intravascular coagulopathy. In some cases there are insufficient data to completely rule out therapeutic failure of dantrolene.



 There are reports of fatality in malignant hyperthermia crisis, despite initial satisfactory response to i.v. dantrolene, which involve patients who could not be weaned from dantrolene after initial treatment.



 The administration of intravenous  Dantrium  to human volunteers is associated with loss of grip strength and weakness in the legs, as well as drowsiness and dizziness.



 The following adverse reactions are in approximate order of severity:



 *     There are rare reports of pulmonary edema developing during the treatment of malignant hyperthermia crisis in which the diluent volume and mannitol needed to deliver i.v. dantrolene possibly contributed. 
 *     There have been reports of thrombophlebitis following administration of intravenous dantrolene; actual incidence figures are not available. Tissue necrosis secondary to extravasation has been reported. 
 *     There have been rare reports of urticaria and erythema possibly associated with the administration of i.v. Dantrium . There has been one case of anaphylaxis. 
 *     Injection site reactions (pain, erythema, swelling), commonly due to extravasation, have been reported. 
    None of the serious reactions occasionally reported with long-term oral  Dantrium  use, such as hepatitis, seizures, and pleural effusion with pericarditis, have been reasonably associated with short-term  Dantrium Intravenous  therapy.
 

 The following events have been reported in patients receiving oral dantrolene: aplastic anemia, leukopenia, lymphocytic lymphoma, and heart failure. (See package insert for  Dantrium  (dantrolene sodium)  Capsules  for a complete listing of adverse reactions.)



 The published literature has included some reports of  Dantrium  use in patients with Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS).  Dantrium Intravenous  is not indicated for the treatment of NMS and patients may expire despite treatment with  Dantrium Intravenous  .



 For medical advice about adverse reactions contact your medical professional. To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact JHP at 1-866-923-2547 or MEDWATCH at 1-800-FDA-1088 (1-800-332-1088) or http://www.fda.gov/medwatch/.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
