<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="daptacel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Rates of adverse reactions varied by dose number, with systemic reactions most frequent following doses 1-3 and injection site reactions most frequent following doses 4 and 5. Systemic reactions that occurred in &gt;50% of subjects following any dose included fussiness/irritability, inconsolable crying, and decreased activity/lethargy. Fever &gt;=38.0 degrees C occurred in 6-16% of US subjects, depending on dose number. Injection site reactions that occurred in &gt;30% of subjects following any dose included tenderness, redness and increase in arm circumference. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sanofi Pasteur Inc., at 1-800-822-2463 (1-800-VACCINE) or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 and  http://vaers.hhs.gov.
 

 

  6.1 Data from Clinical Studies

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to vaccine use and for approximating rates of those events.



 Approximately 18,000 doses of DAPTACEL vaccine have been administered to infants and children in 9 clinical studies. Of these, 3 doses of DAPTACEL vaccine were administered to 4,998 children, 4 doses of DAPTACEL vaccine were administered to 1,725 children, and 5 doses of DAPTACEL vaccine were administered to 485 children. A total of 989 children received 1 dose of DAPTACEL vaccine following 4 prior doses of Pentacel vaccine.



 In a randomized, double-blinded pertussis vaccine efficacy trial, the Sweden I Efficacy Trial, conducted in Sweden during 1992-1995, the safety of DAPTACEL vaccine was compared with DT and a whole-cell pertussis DTP vaccine. A standard diary card was kept for 14 days after each dose and follow-up telephone calls were made 1 and 14 days after each injection. Telephone calls were made monthly to monitor the occurrence of severe events and/or hospitalizations for the 2 months after the last injection. There were fewer of the solicited common local and systemic reactions following DAPTACEL vaccine than following the whole-cell pertussis DTP vaccine. As shown in Table 1, the 2,587 infants who received DAPTACEL vaccine at 2, 4 and 6 months of age had similar rates of reactions within 24 hours as recipients of DT and significantly lower rates than infants receiving whole-cell pertussis DTP.



 Table 1: Percentage of Infants from Sweden I Efficacy Trial with Local or Systemic Reactions within 24 Hours Post-Dose 1, 2 and 3 of DAPTACEL vaccine compared with DT and Whole-Cell Pertussis DTP Vaccines 
             Dose 1(2 MONTHS)  Dose 2(4 MONTHS)  Dose 3(6 MONTHS)   
 EVENT       DAPTACEL vaccineN = 2,587  DTN = 2,574  DTPN = 2,102  DAPTACEL vaccineN = 2,563  DTN = 2,555  DTPN = 2,040  DAPTACEL vaccineN = 2,549  DTN = 2,538  DTPN = 2,001   
  
 DT: Swedish National Biologics LaboratoriesDTP: whole-cell pertussis DTP, Sanofi Pasteur Inc.N = Number of evaluable subjects   
  
   Local                                                                                                                  
 Tenderness  (Any)     8.0         8.4         59.5        10.1        10.3        60.2        10.8        10.0        50.0      
 Redness  &gt;=2 cm     0.3         0.3         6.0         1.0         0.8         5.1         3.7         2.4         6.4       
 Swelling  &gt;=2 cm     0.9         0.7         10.6        1.6         2.0         10.0        6.3         3.9         10.5      
   Systemic                                                                                                                 
 Fever&gt;=38 degrees C (100.4 degrees F)     7.8         7.6         72.3        19.1        18.4        74.3        23.6        22.1        65.1      
 Fretfulness     32.3        33.0        82.1        39.6        39.8        85.4        35.9        37.7        73.0      
 Anorexia       11.2        10.3        39.2        9.1         8.1         25.6        8.4         7.7         17.5      
 Drowsiness     32.7        32.0        56.9        25.9        25.6        50.6        18.9        20.6        37.6      
 Crying&gt;=1 hour     1.7         1.6         11.8        2.5         2.7         9.3         1.2         1.0         3.3       
 Vomiting       6.9         6.3         9.5         5.2         5.8         7.4         4.3         5.2         5.5       
                The incidence of serious and less common selected systemic events in the Sweden I Efficacy Trial is summarized in Table 2.
 

 Table 2: Selected Systemic Events: Rates Per 1,000 Doses after Vaccination at 2, 4 and 6 Months of Age in Sweden I Efficacy Trial 
 EVENT             Dose 1(2 MONTHS)  Dose 2(4 MONTHS)  Dose 3(6 MONTHS)   
 DAPTACEL vaccineN = 2,587  DTN = 2,574  DTPN = 2,102  DAPTACEL vaccineN = 2,565  DTN = 2,556  DTPN = 2,040  DAPTACEL vaccineN = 2,551  DTN = 2,539  DTPN = 2,002   
  
 DT: Swedish National Biologics LaboratoriesDTP: whole-cell pertussis DTP, Sanofi Pasteur Inc.N = Number of evaluable subjects   
  
 Rectal temperature &gt;=40 degrees C (104 degrees F) within 48 hours of vaccination     0.39       0.78       3.33         0         0.78       3.43        0.39       1.18       6.99      
                                                                                                                          
 Hypotonic-hypo-responsive episode within 24 hours of vaccination      0           0         1.9         0           0        0.49        0.39         0          0       
                                                                                                                          
 Persistent crying &gt;=3 hours within 24 hours of vaccination     1.16         0        8.09        0.39       0.39       1.96         0           0         1.0      
                                                                                                                          
 Seizures within 72 hours of vaccination      0         0.39         0          0         0.39       0.49         0         0.39         0       
                In the Sweden I Efficacy Trial, one case of whole limb swelling and generalized symptoms, with resolution within 24 hours, was observed following dose 2 of DAPTACEL vaccine. No episodes of anaphylaxis or encephalopathy were observed. No seizures were reported within 3 days of vaccination with DAPTACEL vaccine. Over the entire study period, 6 seizures were reported in the DAPTACEL vaccine group, 9 in the DT group and 3 in the whole-cell pertussis DTP group, for overall rates of 2.3, 3.5 and 1.4 per 1,000 vaccinees, respectively. One case of infantile spasms was reported in the DAPTACEL vaccine group. There were no instances of invasive bacterial infection or death.
 

 In a US study, children received 4 doses of DAPTACEL vaccine at 2, 4, 6 and 15-17 months of age. A total of 1,454 children received DAPTACEL vaccine and were included in the safety analyses. Of these, 51.7% were female, 77.2% Caucasian, 6.3% Black, 6.5% Hispanic, 0.9% Asian and 9.1% other races. The use of DAPTACEL vaccine as a fifth dose of DTaP vaccine was evaluated in 2 subsequent US clinical studies. In one study, a total of 485 children received DAPTACEL vaccine at 4-6 years of age following 4 prior doses of DAPTACEL vaccine in infancy (DAPTACEL-primed). In a separate study, a total of 989 children received DAPTACEL vaccine at 4-6 years of age following 4 prior doses of Pentacel vaccine in infancy (Pentacel-primed). The children included in these fifth dose studies were non-random subsets of participants from previous DAPTACEL or Pentacel studies. The subsets were representative of all children who received 4 doses of DAPTACEL or Pentacel vaccine in the earlier studies with regard to frequencies of solicited local and systemic adverse events following the fourth dose.



 In the US 4-dose DAPTACEL study, at 2, 4, and 6 months of age, DAPTACEL vaccine was administered concomitantly with  Haemophilus influenzae  type b (Hib) conjugate vaccine (tetanus toxoid conjugate) (Sanofi Pasteur SA), inactivated poliovirus vaccine (IPV) (Sanofi Pasteur SA), and 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.). Infants had received the first dose of hepatitis B vaccine at 0 months of age. At 2 and 6 months of age, hepatitis B vaccine (recombinant) (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.) was also administered concomitantly with DAPTACEL vaccine. Based on random assignment, the fourth dose of DAPTACEL vaccine was administered either alone; concomitantly with Hib conjugate (tetanus toxoid conjugate) vaccine; or concomitantly with Hib conjugate (tetanus toxoid conjugate) vaccine, 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine, measles, mumps, rubella (MMR) vaccine (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.), and varicella vaccine (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.). In the fifth dose studies, DAPTACEL vaccine was administered concomitantly with IPV (all DAPTACEL-primed subjects and 47% of Pentacel-primed subjects) and MMR vaccine.



 In the US studies, the occurrence of solicited local and systemic adverse events listed in Table 3 was recorded daily by parents or guardians for Days 0-7 following vaccination. For Days 0 and 1 following the first three doses of DAPTACEL vaccine, signs and symptoms of HHE also were solicited. Periodic telephone calls were made to inquire about adverse events. Serious adverse events were monitored during the three studies, through 6 months following the last dose of DAPTACEL vaccine.



 The incidence and severity of selected solicited local and systemic adverse events that occurred within 3 days following each dose of DAPTACEL vaccine are shown in Table 3. The incidence of redness, tenderness and swelling at the DAPTACEL injection site increased with the fourth and fifth doses, with the highest rates reported after the fifth dose. The incidence of redness, tenderness and swelling at the DAPTACEL injection site was similarly increased when DAPTACEL vaccine was given as a fifth dose of DTaP vaccine in Pentacel-primed children.



 Table 3: Number (Percentage) of Children from US Studies with Selected Solicited Local and Systemic Adverse Events by Severity Occurring Between 0 to 3 Days after Each Dose of DAPTACEL Vaccine 
                           Dose 1           Dose 2           Dose 3           Dose 4         Dose 5     
                                                                          DAPTACEL-primed  Pentacel-primed   
 N = 1390-1406%        N = 1346-1360%   N = 1301-1312%   N = 1118-1144%    N = 473-481%    N = 936-981%   
  
   Injection Site Reactions (DAPTACEL vaccine injection site)                                                                                                 
   Redness                                                                                                          
   &gt;5 mm                     6.2              7.1              9.6             17.3           35.8        20.2      
   25 - 50 mm                0.6              0.5              1.9              6.3           10.4        6.8       
   &gt;50 mm                    0.4              0.1              0.0              3.1           15.8        6.6       
   Swelling                                                                                                         
   &gt;5 mm                     4.0              4.0              6.5             11.7           23.9        12.0      
   25 - 50 mm                1.2              0.6              1.0              3.2           5.8         4.1       
   &gt;50 mm                    0.4              0.1              0.1              1.6           7.7         2.9       
   Tenderness                                                                                                       
   Any                      48.8             38.2             40.9             49.5           61.5        50.0      
   Moderate                 16.5              9.9             10.6             12.3           11.2        7.4       
   Severe                    4.1              2.3              1.7              2.2           1.7         0.3       
   Increase in Arm Circumference                                                                                                 
   &gt;5 mm                      -                -                -              30.1           38.3        28.6      
   20 - 40 mm                7.0             14.0              7.6         
   &gt;40 mm                    0.4              1.5              1.2         
   Interference with Normal Activity of the Arm                                                                                                 
   Any                        -                -                -                -            20.4        8.8       
   Moderate                  5.6              1.7         
   Severe                    0.4              0.0         
   Systemic Reactions                                                                                                 
   Fever                                                                                                            
   &gt;=38.0 degrees C          9.3             16.1             15.8             10.5           6.1         4.6       
   &gt;38.5-39.5 degrees C        1.5              3.9              4.8              2.7           2.1         2.0       
   &gt;39.5 degrees C           0.1              0.4              0.3              0.7           0.2         0.2       
   Decreased Activity/Lethargy                                                                                                 
   Any                      51.1             37.4             33.2             25.3           21.0        12.6      
   Moderate                 23.0             14.4             12.1              8.2           5.8         3.6       
   Severe                    1.2              1.4              0.6              1.0           0.8         0.4       
   Inconsolable Crying                                                                                                 
   Any                      58.5             51.4             47.9             37.1           14.1        7.2       
   Moderate                 14.2             12.6             10.8              7.7           3.5         1.9       
   Severe                    2.2              3.4              1.4              1.5           0.4         0.3       
   Fussiness/Irritability                                                                                                 
   Any                      75.8             70.7             67.1             54.4           34.9        22.9      
   Moderate                 27.7             25.0             22.0             16.3           7.5         5.3       
   Severe                    5.6              5.5              4.3              3.9           0.4         0.5       
             In the US study in which children received 4 doses of DAPTACEL vaccine, of 1,454 subjects who received DAPTACEL vaccine, 5 (0.3%) subjects experienced a seizure within 60 days following any dose of DAPTACEL vaccine. One seizure occurred within 7 days post-vaccination: an infant who experienced an afebrile seizure with apnea on the day of the first vaccination. Three other cases of seizures occurred between 8 and 30 days post-vaccination. Of the seizures that occurred within 60 days post-vaccination, 3 were associated with fever. In this study, there were no reported cases of HHE following DAPTACEL vaccine. There was one death due to aspiration 222 days post-vaccination in a subject with ependymoma. Within 30 days following any dose of DAPTACEL vaccine, 57 (3.9%) subjects reported at least one serious adverse event. During this period, the most frequently reported serious adverse event was bronchiolitis, reported in 28 (1.9%) subjects. Other serious adverse events that occurred within 30 days following DAPTACEL vaccine include three cases of pneumonia, two cases of meningitis and one case each of sepsis, pertussis (post-dose 1), irritability and unresponsiveness.
 

 In the US study in which DAPTACEL vaccine was administered as a fifth DTaP dose in DAPTACEL-primed subjects, within 30 days following the fifth consecutive dose of DAPTACEL vaccine, 1 (0.2%) subject reported 2 serious adverse events (bronchospasm and hypoxia). In the US study in which DAPTACEL vaccine was administered as a fifth DTaP dose in Pentacel-primed subjects, within 30 days following DAPTACEL, 4 (0.4%) subjects reported one or more serious adverse events (asthma and pneumonia; idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura; vomiting; cellulitis not at the injection site). In these two studies, there were no reports of seizures within 30 days following DAPTACEL vaccine in either the DAPTACEL-primed subjects or Pentacel-primed subjects.



 In another study (Sweden II Efficacy Trial), 3 DTaP vaccines and a whole-cell pertussis DTP vaccine, none of which are licensed in the US, were evaluated to assess relative safety and efficacy. This study included HCPDT, a vaccine made of the same components as DAPTACEL vaccine but containing twice the amount of detoxified PT and four times the amount of FHA (20 mcg detoxified PT and 20 mcg FHA). HHE was observed following 29 (0.047%) of 61,220 doses of HCPDT; 16 (0.026%) of 61,219 doses of an acellular pertussis vaccine made by another manufacturer; and 34 (0.056%) of 60,792 doses of a whole-cell pertussis DTP vaccine. There were 4 additional cases of HHE in other studies using HCPDT vaccine for an overall rate of 33 (0.047%) in 69,525 doses.



   6.2 Data from Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during the post-marketing use of DAPTACEL vaccine in the US and other countries. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it may not be possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure.



 The following adverse events were included based on one or more of the following factors: severity, frequency of reporting, or strength of evidence for a causal relationship to DAPTACEL vaccine.



 *   Blood and lymphatic disorders Lymphadenopathy 
 *   Cardiac disorders Cyanosis 
 *   Gastro-intestinal disorders Nausea, diarrhea 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions Local reactions: injection site pain, injection site rash, injection site nodule, injection site mass, extensive swelling of injected limb (including swelling that involves adjacent joints). 
 *   Infections and infestations Injection site cellulitis, cellulitis, injection site abscess 
 *   Immune system disorders Hypersensitivity, allergic reaction, anaphylactic reaction (edema, face edema, swelling face, pruritus, rash generalized) and other types of rash (erythematous, macular, maculo-papular) 
 *   Nervous system disorders Convulsions: febrile convulsion, grand mal convulsion, partial seizuresHHE, hypotonia, somnolence, syncope 
 *   Psychiatric disorders Screaming 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  *  -  fever &gt;=40.5 degrees C (105 degrees F), hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode (HHE) or persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours within 48 hours after a previous pertussis-containing vaccine. (  5.2  ) 
 *  -  seizures within 3 days after a previous pertussis-containing vaccine. (  5.2  ) 
 *  -  If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk for Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following DAPTACEL. (  5.3  ) 
   Carefully consider benefits and risks before administering DAPTACEL to persons with a history of: 
 *  For infants and children with a history of previous seizures, an antipyretic may be administered (in the dosage recommended in its prescribing information) at the time of vaccination with DAPTACEL and for the next 24 hours. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including DAPTACEL, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Syncope (fainting) has been reported following vaccination with DAPTACEL. Procedures should be in place to prevent falling injury and manage syncopal reactions. 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Acute Allergic Reactions



  Epinephrine hydrochloride solution (1:1,000) and other appropriate agents and equipment must be available for immediate use in case an anaphylactic or acute hypersensitivity reaction occurs.



    5.2 Adverse Reactions Following Prior Pertussis Vaccination



  If any of the following events occur within the specified period after administration of a whole-cell pertussis vaccine or a vaccine containing an acellular pertussis component, the decision to administer DAPTACEL vaccine should be based on careful consideration of potential benefits and possible risks. [See   Dosage and Administration (2.1)  .  ]



 *  Temperature of &gt;=40.5 degrees C (105 degrees F) within 48 hours, not attributable to another identifiable cause. 
 *  Collapse or shock-like state (hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode (HHE)) within 48 hours. 
 *  Persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours within 48 hours. 
 *  Seizures with or without fever within 3 days. 
       5.3 Guillain-Barre Syndrome and Brachial Neuritis
 

  A review by the Institute of Medicine found evidence for a causal relation between tetanus toxoid and both brachial neuritis and Guillain-Barre syndrome. (  1  ) If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk for Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following DAPTACEL vaccine.



    5.4 Infants and Children with a History of Previous Seizures



  For infants or children with a history of previous seizures, an appropriate antipyretic may be administered (in the dosage recommended in its prescribing information) at the time of vaccination with a vaccine containing an acellular pertussis component (including DAPTACEL vaccine) and for the following 24 hours, to reduce the possibility of post-vaccination fever.



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with DAPTACEL vaccine may not protect all individuals.



    5.6 Altered Immunocompetence



  If DAPTACEL vaccine is administered to immunocompromised persons, including persons receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained. [See   Immunosuppressive Treatments (7.2)  .  ]



    5.7 Apnea in Premature Infants



  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including DAPTACEL, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination.



    5.8 Syncope



   Syncope (fainting) has been reported following vaccination with DAPTACEL. Procedures should be in place to prevent falling injury and manage syncopal reactions.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
