<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="daranide" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions include gastrointestinal disturbances (anorexia, nausea, and vomiting), drowsiness and paresthesias.



 Certain adverse reactions characteristic of carbonic anhydrase inhibitors may result with DARANIDE  (r)  (dichlorphenamide tablets USP), particularly with increasing doses. The following are adverse reactions which have been reported with systemic carbonic anhydrase inhibitors. The pharmacological similarities among the carbonic anhydrase inhibitors make it advisable to consider the following reactions when dichlorphenamide is administered: agranulocytosis, ataxia, confusion, constipation, depression, disorientation, dizziness, electrolyte imbalance (hypokalemia, hyperchloremia), fever, globus hystericus, headache, hepatic insufficiency, hyperuricemia, kidney stones, lassitude, leucopenia, metabolic acidosis, nervousness, phosphaturia, pruritus, renal colic, skin eruptions, thrombocytopenia, tinnitus, tremor, urinary frequency, weakness, and weight loss.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions include gastrointestinal disturbances (anorexia, nausea, and vomiting), drowsiness and paresthesias. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, call the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Potassium excretion is increased by DARANIDE   (r)   (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypokalemia may develop with brisk diuresis (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypokalemia



  Potassium excretion is increased by DARANIDE   (r)    (dichlorphenamide tablets USP) and hypokalemia may develop.



 Interference with adequate oral electrolyte intake will also contribute to hypokalemia. Hypokalemia can sensitize or exaggerate the response of the heart to the toxic effects of digitalis (e.g., increased ventricular irritability). Hypokalemia may be avoided or treated by use of potassium supplements such as foods with a high potassium content.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
