<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="darifenacin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6         ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   The most frequently reported adverse reactions (greater than 3%) for Darifenacin are: constipation, dry mouth, headache, dyspepsia, nausea, urinary tract infection, accidental injury, and flu symptoms (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Actavis at 1-800-272-5525-or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6.1    Clinical    Trials    Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of Darifenacin was evaluated in controlled clinical trials in a total of 8,830 patients, 6,001 of whom were treated with Darifenacin. Of this total, 1,069 patients participated in three, 12-week, randomized, placebo-controlled, fixed-dose efficacy and safety studies (Studies 1, 2 and 3). Of this total, 337 and 334 patients received Darifenacin 7.5 mg daily and 15 mg daily, respectively. In all long-term trials combined, 1,216 and 672 patients received treatment with Darifenacin for at least 24 and 52 weeks, respectively.



 In Studies 1, 2 and 3 combined, the serious adverse reactions to Darifenacin were urinary retention and constipation.



 In Studies 1, 2 and 3 combined, dry mouth leading to study discontinuation occurred in 0%, 0.9%, and 0% of patients treated with Darifenacin 7.5 mg daily, Darifenacin 15 mg daily and placebo, respectively. Constipation leading to study discontinuation occurred in 0.6%, 1.2%, and 0.3% of patients treated with Darifenacin 7.5 mg daily, Darifenacin 15 mg daily and placebo, respectively.



 Table 1 lists the rates of identified adverse reactions, derived from all reported adverse events in 2% or more of patients treated with 7.5 mg or 15 mg Darifenacin, and greater than placebo in Studies 1, 2 and 3. In these studies, the most frequently reported adverse reactions were dry mouth and constipation. The majority of the adverse reactions were mild or moderate in severity and most occurred during the first two weeks of treatment.



 Table 1: Incidence of Identified Adverse Reactions, Derived from All Adverse Events Reported in greater than or equal to 2% of Patients Treated with Darifenacin Extended-Release Tablets and More Frequent with Darifenacin than with Placebo in Studies 1, 2, and 3 
   Body System      Adverse    Reaction      %    of Subjects     
                                     Darifenacin    7.5 mg    N         =         337      Darifenacin    15 mg    N         =         334      Placebo    N         =         388     
   Digestive      Dry MouthConstipationDyspepsiaAbdominal PainNauseaDiarrhea  20.214.82.72.42.72.1  35.321.38.43.91.50.9  8.26.22.60.51.51.8   
   Urogenital     Urinary Tract Infection  4.7              4.5              2.6               
                                                                                       
                                                                                       
   Nervous        Dizziness        0.9              2.1              1.3               
   Body as a Whole    Asthenia         1.5              2.7              1.3               
   Eye            Dry Eyes         1.5              2.1              0.5               
           Other adverse reactions reported by 1% to 2% of Darifenacin-treated patients include: abnormal vision, accidental injury, back pain, dry skin, flu syndrome, hypertension, vomiting, peripheral edema, weight gain, arthralgia, bronchitis, pharyngitis, rhinitis, sinusitis, rash, pruritus, urinary tract disorder and vaginitis.
 

 Study 4 was a randomized, 12-week, placebo-controlled, dose-titration regimen study in which Darifenacin was administered in accordance with dosing recommendations  [see       Dosage and Administration (2)      ]  . All patients initially received placebo or Darifenacin 7.5 mg daily, and after two weeks, patients and physicians were allowed to adjust upward to Darifenacin 15 mg if needed. In this study, the most commonly reported adverse reactions were also constipation and dry mouth. Table 2 lists the identified adverse reactions, derived from all adverse events reported in greater than 3% of patients treated with Darifenacin and greater than placebo.



 Table 2: Number (%) of Adverse Reactions, Derived from All Adverse Events Reported in greater than 3% of Patients Treated with Darifenacin Extended-Release Tablets, and More Frequent with Darifenacin than Placebo, in Study 4 
   Adverse    Reaction           Darifenacin         7.5 mg/15 mg    N         =         268      Placebo    N         =         127     
 ConstipationDry MouthHeadacheDyspepsiaNauseaUrinary Tract InfectionAccidental InjuryFlu Syndrome  56 (20.9%)50 (18.7%)18 (6.7%)12 (4.5%)11 (4.1%)10 (3.7%)8 (3.0%)8 (3.0%)  10 (7.9%)11 (8.7%)7 (5.5%)2 (1.6%)2 (1.6%)4 (3.1%)3 (2.4%)3 (2.4%)   
             6.2    Post Marketing    Experience  
   The following adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of Darifenacin extended-release tablets. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Dermatologic:  erythema multiforme, interstitial granuloma annulare



   General:  hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema with airway obstruction and anaphylactic reaction



   Central Nervous:  confusion, hallucinations and somnolence



   Cardiovascular:  palpitations and syncope
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5        WARNINGS AND   PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Darifenacin should be administered with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outflow obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention (  5.1  ) 
 *  Darifenacin should be administered with caution to patients with gastrointestinal obstructive disorders because of the risk of gastric retention (  5.2  ) 
 *  Darifenacin should be used with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma and only where the potential benefits outweigh the risks (  5.3  ) 
 *  Central Nervous System Effects: Somnolence has been reported with Darifenacin. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how Darifenacin affects them (  5.5  ) 
    
 

    5.1   Risk of Urinary Retention  



  Darifenacin should be administered with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outflow obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention.



     5.2   Decreased Gastrointestinal Motility  



  Darifenacin should be administered with caution to patients with gastrointestinal obstructive disorders because of the risk of gastric retention. Darifenacin, like other anticholinergic drugs, may decrease gastrointestinal motility and should be used with caution in patients with conditions such as severe constipation, ulcerative colitis, and myasthenia gravis.



     5.3   Controlled Narrow   -Angle Glaucoma  



  Darifenacin should be used with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma and only where the potential benefits outweigh the risks.



     5.   4       Angioedema  



  Angioedema of the face, lips, tongue, and/or larynx have been reported with darifenacin. In some cases angioedema occurred after the first dose. Angioedema associated with upper airway swelling may be life threatening. If involvement of the tongue, hypopharynx, or larynx occurs, darifenacin should be promptly discontinued and appropriate therapy and/or measures necessary to ensure a patent airway should be promptly provided.



     5.5   Central Nervous System Effects  



  Darifenacin is associated with anticholinergic central nervous system (CNS) effects [see     Adverse Reactions (6.2)     ]  . A variety of CNS anticholinergic effects have been reported, including headache, confusion, hallucinations and somnolence. Patients should be monitored for signs of anticholinergic CNS effects, particularly after beginning treatment or increasing the dose. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how Darifenacin affects them. If a patient experiences anticholinergic CNS effects, dose reduction or drug discontinuation should be considered.



     5.   6       Patients with Hepatic Impairment  



  The daily dose of Darifenacin should not exceed 7.5 mg for patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh B). Darifenacin has not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh C) and therefore is not recommended for use in this patient population [see     Dosage and Administration (2)           Use In Specific Populations (8.6)             and         Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)     ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
