<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="depoprovera0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    See  PRECAUTIONS  for possible adverse effects on the fetus  



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders

    *  -  breakthrough bleeding 
 *  -  spotting 
 *  -  change in menstrual flow 
 *  -  amenorrhea 
 *  -  changes in cervical erosion and cervical secretions 
 *  -  breast tenderness and galactorrhea 
 *  -  erectile dysfunction 
      Nervous System Disorders
     *  -  headache 
 *  -  dizziness 
 *  -  somnolence 
 *  -  convulsions 
      Psychiatric Disorders
     *  -  nervousness 
 *  -  euphoria 
 *  -  mental depression 
 *  -  insomnia 
      General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions
     *  -  edema 
 *  -  pyrexia 
 *  -  fatigue 
 *  -  malaise 
      Investigations
     *  -  change in weight (increase or decrease) 
      Hepatobiliary Disorders
     *  -  cholestatic jaundice, including neonatal jaundice 
      Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders
     *  -  skin sensitivity reactions consisting of urticaria, pruritus, edema and generalized rash 
 *  -  acne, alopecia and hirsutism 
 *  -  rash (allergic) with and without pruritis 
      Immune System Disorders
     *  -  anaphylactoid reactions and anaphylaxis 
 *  -  angioedema 
      Gastrointestinal Disorders
     *  -  nausea 
      Endocrine Disorders
     *  -  corticoid-like effects (e.g., Cushingoid syndrome) 
      Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders
     *  -  hypercalcemia 
      In a few instances there have been undesirable sequelae at the site of injection, such as residual lump, change in color of skin, or sterile abscess.
 

 A statistically significant association has been demonstrated between use of estrogen-pro-gestin combination drugs and pulmonary embolism and cerebral thrombosis and embolism. For this reason patients on progestin therapy should be carefully observed. There is also evidence suggestive of an association with neuro-ocular lesions, e.g. retinal thrombosis and optic neuritis.



 The following adverse reactions have been observed in patients receiving estrogen-progestin combination drugs:



 *  -  rise in blood pressure in susceptible individuals 
 *  -  premenstrual syndrome 
 *  -  changes in libido 
 *  -  changes in appetite 
 *  -  cystitis-like syndrome 
 *  -  headache 
 *  -  nervousness 
 *  -  fatigue 
 *  -  backache 
 *  -  hirsutism 
 *  -  loss of scalp hair 
 *  -  erythema multiforma 
 *  -  erythema nodosum 
 *  -  hemorrhagic eruption 
 *  -  itching 
 *  -  dizziness 
    The following laboratory results may be altered by the use of estrogen-progestin combination drugs:
 

 *  -  increased sulfobromophthalein retention and other hepatic function tests 
 *  -  coagulation tests: increase in prothrombin factors VII, VIII, IX, and X 
 *  -  metyrapone test 
 *  -  pregnanediol determinations 
 *  -  thyroid function: increase in PBI, and butanol extractable protein bound iodine and decrease in T3uptake values 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
