<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="deposubq" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In five clinical studies of depo-subQ provera 104 involving 2,325 women (282 treated for up to 6 months, 1,780 treated for up to 1 year and 263 treated for up to 2 years), 9% of women discontinued treatment for adverse reactions. Among these 212 women, the most common reasons for discontinuation were:



 *  Uterine bleeding irregularities (35%, n=75) 
 *  Increased weight (18%, n=39) 
 *  Decreased libido (11%, n=23) 
 *  Acne (10%, n=21) 
 *  Injection site reactions (6%, n=12) 
    Adverse reactions reported by 5% or more of all women in these clinical trials included:
 

 *  Headache (9%) 
 *  Intermenstrual bleeding (7%) 
 *  Increased weight (6%) 
 *  Amenorrhea (6%) 
 *  Injection site reactions (5%) 
    Adverse reactions reported by 1% to &lt;5% of all women in these clinical trials included:
 

   General disorders:  fatigue, injection site pain



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal distention, abdominal pain, diarrhea, nausea



   Infections:  bronchitis, influenza, nasopharyngitis, pharyngitis, sinusitis, upper respiratory tract infection, urinary tract infection, vaginal candidiasis, vaginitis, vaginitis bacterial



   Investigations:  abnormal cervix smear



   Musculoskeletal, connective tissue, and bone disorders:  arthralgia, back pain, limb pain



   Nervous system disorders:  dizziness, insomnia



   Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety, depression, irritability, decreased libido



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  breast pain, breast tenderness, dysmenorrhea, menometrorrhagia, menorrhagia, menstruation irregular, uterine hemorrhage, vaginal hemorrhage



   Skin disorders:  acne



   Vascular disorders:  hot flushes



   Postmarketing Experience

  There have been rare cases of osteoporosis including osteoporotic fractures reported postmarketing in patients taking DEPO-PROVERA Contraceptive Injection. In addition, infrequent voluntary reports of anaphylaxis and anaphylactoid reaction have been received associated with use of Depo-Provera CI (150 mg).



 The following additional reactions have been reported with Depo-Provera Contraceptive Injection and may occur with use of depo-subQ provera 104:



   General disorders:  asthenia, axillary swelling, chills, chest pain, fever, excessive thirst



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  anemia, blood dyscrasia



   Cardiac disorders:  tachycardia



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  gastrointestinal disturbances, rectal bleeding



   Hepato-biliary disorders:  jaundice



   Immune system disorders:  allergic reaction



   Infections:  genitourinary infections



   Investigations:  decreased glucose tolerance



   Musculoskeletal, connective tissue, and bone disorders:  loss of bone mineral density, scleroderma



   Neoplasms:  breast cancer, cervical cancer



   Nervous system disorders:  convulsions, facial palsy, fainting, paralysis, paresthesia, somnolence



   Psychiatric disorders:  increased libido, nervousness



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  breast lumps, galactorrhea, nipple discharge or bleeding, oligomenorrhea, prevention of lactation, prolonged anovulation, unexpected pregnancy, uterine hyperplasia, vaginal cyst



   Respiratory disorders:  asthma, dyspnea, hoarseness



   Skin disorders:  angioedema, dry skin, increased body odor, melasma, pruritus, urticaria



   Vascular disorders:  deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolus, thrombophlebitis
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LOSS OF BONE MINERAL DENSITY

    WARNING: LOSS OF BONE MINERAL DENSITY  

    Women who use depo-subQ provera 104 may lose significant bone mineral density.  Bone loss is greater with increasing duration of use and may not be completely reversible.  



   It is unknown if use of depo-subQ provera 104 during adolescence or early adulthood, a critical period of bone accretion, will reduce peak bone mass and increase the risk for osteoporotic fracture in later life.   



   depo-subQ provera 104 should not be used as a long-term birth control method (i.e., longer than 2 years) unless other birth control methods are considered inadequate (see   WARNINGS, section 1  ).  



   Patients should be counseled that this product does not protect against HIV infection (AIDS) and other sexually transmitted diseases.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
