<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="depoprovera1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following important adverse reactions observed with the use of Depo-Provera CI are discussed in greater detail in the  Warnings and Precautions  section (  5  ):



 *  Loss of Bone Mineral Density [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Thromboembolic disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Breast Cancer [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Anaphylaxis and Anaphylactoid Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Bleeding Irregularities [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Weight Gain [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;5%) are: menstrual irregularities (bleeding or spotting) 57% at 12 months, 32% at 24 months, abdominal pain/discomfort 11%, weight gain &gt; 10 lbs at 24 months 38%, dizziness 6%, headache 17%, nervousness 11%, decreased libido 6%. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In the two clinical trials with Depo-Provera CI, over 3,900 women, who were treated for up to 7 years, reported the following adverse reactions, which may or may not be related to the use of Depo-Provera CI. The population studied ranges in age from 15 to 51 years, of which 46% were White, 50% Non-White, and 4.9% Unknown race. The patients received 150 mg Depo-Provera CI every 3-months (90 days). The median study duration was 13 months with a range of 1-84 months. Fifty eight percent of patients remained in the study after 13 months and 34% after 24 months.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions that Were Reported by More than 5% of Subjects 
 Body System                Adverse Reactions [Incidence (%)]                                             
  
   Body as a Whole          Headache (16.5%)Abdominal pain/discomfort (11.2%)                             
   Metabolic/Nutritional    Increased weight&gt; 10lbs at 24 months (37.7%)                                  
   Nervous                  Nervousness (10.8%)Dizziness (5.6%)Libido decreased (5.5%)                    
   Urogenital               Menstrual irregularities:(bleeding (57.3% at 12 months, 32.1% at 24 months)amenorrhea (55% at 12 months, 68% at 24 months)   
       Table 2 Adverse Reactions that Were Reported by between 1 and 5% of Subjects 
 Body System                Adverse Reactions [Incidence (%)]                                             
  
   Body as a Whole          Asthenia/fatigue (4.2%)Backache (2.2%)Dysmenorrhea (1.7%)Hot flashes (1.0%)   
   Digestive                Nausea (3.3%)Bloating (2.3%)                                                  
   Metabolic/Nutritional    Edema (2.2%)                                                                  
   Musculoskeletal          Leg cramps (3.7%)Arthralgia (1.0%)                                            
   Nervous                  Depression (1.5%)Insomnia (1.0%)                                              
   Skin and Appendages      Acne (1.2%)No hair growth/alopecia (1.1%)Rash (1.1%)                          
   Urogenital               Leukorrhea (2.9%)Breast pain (2.8%)Vaginitis (1.2%)                           
          Adverse reactions leading to study discontinuation in &gt;= 2% of subjects:  bleeding (8.2%), amenorrhea (2.1%), weight gain (2.0%)
 

   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Depo-Provera CI. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 There have been cases of osteoporosis including osteoporotic fractures reported post-marketing in patients taking Depo-Provera CI.



 Table 3 Adverse Reactions Reported during Post-Marketing Experience 
 Body System                     Adverse Reactions                                                        
  
   Body as a Whole               Chest pain, Allergic reactions including angioedema, Fever, Pain at injection site, Chills, Axillary swelling   
   Cardiovascular                Syncope, Tachycardia, Thrombophlebitis, Deep vein thrombosis, Pulmonary embolus, Varicose veins   
   Digestive                     Changes in appetite, Gastrointestinal disturbances, Jaundice, Excessive thirst, Rectal bleeding   
   Hematologic and Lymphatic     Anemia, Blood dyscrasia                                                  
   Musculoskeletal               Osteoporosis                                                             
   Neoplasms                     Cervical cancer, Breast cancer                                           
   Nervous                       Paralysis, Facial palsy, Paresthesia, Drowsiness                         
   Respiratory                   Dyspnea and asthma, Hoarseness                                           
   Skin and Appendages           Hirsutism, Excessive sweating and body odor, Dry skin, Scleroderma       
   Urogenital                    Lack of return to fertility, Unexpected pregnancy, Prevention of lactation, Changes in breast size, Breast lumps or nipple bleeding, Galactorrhea, Melasma, Chloasma, Increased libido, Uterine hyperplasia, Genitourinary infections, Vaginal cysts, Dyspareunia   
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LOSS OF BONE MINERAL DENSITY

    WARNING: LOSS OF BONE MINERAL DENSITY  

    Women who use Depo-Provera Contraceptive Injection may lose significant bone mineral density. Bone loss is greater with increasing duration of use and may not be completely reversible.  



   It is unknown if use of Depo-Provera Contraceptive Injection during adolescence or early adulthood, a critical period of bone accretion, will reduce peak bone mass and increase the risk for osteoporotic fracture in later life.  



   Depo-Provera Contraceptive Injection should not be used as a long-term birth control method (i.e., longer than 2 years) unless other birth control methods are considered inadequate [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LOSS OF BONE MINERAL DENSITY  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    .  



 *  Women who use Depo-Provera Contraceptive Injection (Depo-Provera CI) may lose significant bone mineral density. Bone loss is greater with increasing duration of use and may not be completely reversible. (5.1) 
 *  It is unknown if use of Depo-Provera Contraceptive Injection during adolescence or early adulthood, a critical period of bone accretion, will reduce peak bone mass and increase the risk for osteoporotic fracture in later life. (5.1) 
 *  Depo-Provera Contraceptive Injection should not be used as a long-term birth control method (i.e., longer than 2 years) unless other birth control methods are considered inadequate. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Thromboembolic Disorders: Discontinue Depo-Provera CI in patients who develop thrombosis. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cancer Risks: Monitor women with a strong family history of breast cancer carefully. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Ectopic Pregnancy: Consider ectopic pregnancy if a woman using Depo-Provera CI becomes pregnant or complains of severe abdominal pain. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Anaphylaxis and Anaphylactoid Reactions: Provide emergency medical treatment. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Liver Function: Discontinue Depo-Provera CI if jaundice or disturbances of liver function develop. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Carbohydrate Metabolism: Monitor diabetic patients carefully. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Loss of Bone Mineral Density



  Use of Depo-Provera CI reduces serum estrogen levels and is associated with significant loss of bone mineral density (BMD). This loss of BMD is of particular concern during adolescence and early adulthood, a critical period of bone accretion. It is unknown if use of Depo-Provera CI by younger women will reduce peak bone mass and increase the risk for osteoporotic fracture in later life.



 After discontinuing Depo-Provera CI in adolescents, mean BMD loss at total hip and femoral neck did not fully recover by 60 months (240 weeks) post-treatment [   see     Clinical Studies (14.3)  ].  Similarly, in adults, there was only partial recovery of mean BMD at total hip, femoral neck and lumbar spine towards baseline by 24 months post-treatment. [See  Clinical Studies (14.2)  .]  



 Depo-Provera CI should not be used as a long-term birth control method (i.e., longer than 2 years) unless other birth control methods are considered inadequate. BMD should be evaluated when a woman needs to continue to use Depo-Provera CI long-term. In adolescents, interpretation of BMD results should take into account patient age and skeletal maturity.



 Other birth control methods should be considered in the risk/benefit analysis for the use of Depo-Provera CI in women with osteoporosis risk factors. Depo-Provera CI can pose an additional risk in patients with risk factors for osteoporosis (e.g., metabolic bone disease, chronic alcohol and/or tobacco use, anorexia nervosa, strong family history of osteoporosis or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass such as anticonvulsants or corticosteroids). Although there are no studies addressing whether calcium and Vitamin-D may lessen BMD loss in women using Depo-Provera CI, all patients should have adequate calcium and Vitamin D intake.



    5.2 Thromboembolic Disorders



  There have been reports of serious thrombotic events in women using Depo-Provera CI (150 mg). However, Depo-Provera CI has not been causally associated with the induction of thrombotic or thromboembolic disorders. Any patient who develops thrombosis while undergoing therapy with Depo-Provera CI should discontinue treatment unless she has no other acceptable options for birth control.



 Do not re-administer Depo-Provera CI pending examination if there is a sudden partial or complete loss of vision or if there is a sudden onset of proptosis, diplopia, or migraine. Do not re-administer if examination reveals papilledema or retinal vascular lesions.



    5.3 Cancer Risks



   Breast Cancer  



  Women who have or have had a history of breast cancer should not use hormonal contraceptives, including Depo-Provera CI, because breast cancer may be hormonally sensitive [see  Contraindications (4)  ].  Women with a strong family history of breast cancer should be monitored with particular care.  



  The results of five large case-control studies  1, 2, 3, 4, 5  assessing the association between depo-medroxyprogesterone acetate (DMPA) use and the risk of breast cancer are summarized in Figure 1. Three of the studies suggest a slightly increased risk of breast cancer in the overall population of users; these increased risks were statistically significant in one study. One recent US study  1  evaluated the recency and duration of use and found a statistically significantly increased risk of breast cancer in recent users (defined as last use within the past five years) who used DMPA for 12 months or longer; this is consistent with results of a previous study  4  .  



  Figure 1 Risk estimates for breast cancer in DMPA users  




 Odds ratio estimates were adjusted for the following covariates:                                       
 Lee et al. (1987): age, parity, and socioeconomic status.                                              
 Paul et al. (1989): age, parity, ethnic group, and year of interview.                                  
 WHO (1991): age, center, and age at first live birth.                                                  
 Shapiro et al. (2000): age, ethnic group, socioeconomic status, and any combined estrogen/progestogen oral contraceptive use.   
 Li et al. (2012): age, year, BMI, duration of OC use, number of full-term pregnancies, family history of breast cancer, and history of screening mammography.   
  
                                                                                                        
       Based on the published SEER-18 2011 incidence rate (age-adjusted to the 2000 US Standard Population ) of breast cancer for US women, all races, age 20 to 49 years  6  , a doubling of risk would increase the incidence of breast cancer in women who use Depo-Provera CI from about 72 to about 144 cases per 100,000 women.
 

  Figure 1    Cervical Cancer  



 A statistically nonsignificant increase in RR estimates of invasive squamous-cell cervical cancer has been associated with the use of Depo-Provera CI in women who were first exposed before the age of 35 years (RR 1.22 to 1.28 and 95% CI 0.93 to 1.70). The overall, nonsignificant relative rate of invasive squamous-cell cervical cancer in women who ever used Depo-Provera CI was estimated to be 1.11 (95% CI 0.96 to 1.29). No trends in risk with duration of use or times since initial or most recent exposure were observed.



    Other Cancers  



 Long-term case-controlled surveillance of users of Depo-Provera CI found no overall increased risk of ovarian or liver cancer.



    5.4 Ectopic Pregnancy



  Be alert to the possibility of an ectopic pregnancy among women using Depo-Provera CI who become pregnant or complain of severe abdominal pain.



    5.5 Anaphylaxis and Anaphylactoid Reaction



  Anaphylaxis and anaphylactoid reaction have been reported with the use of Depo-Provera CI. Institute emergency medical treatment if an anaphylactic reaction occurs.



    5.6 Liver Function



  Discontinue Depo-Provera CI use if jaundice or acute or chronic disturbances of liver function develop. Do not resume use until markers of liver function return to normal and Depo-Provera CI causation has been excluded.



    5.7 Convulsions



  There have been a few reported cases of convulsions in patients who were treated with Depo-Provera CI. Association with drug use or pre-existing conditions is not clear.



    5.8 Depression



  Monitor patients who have a history of depression and do not readminister Depo-Provera CI if depression recurs.



    5.9 Bleeding Irregularities



  Most women using Depo-Provera CI experience disruption of menstrual bleeding patterns. Altered menstrual bleeding patterns include amenorrhea, irregular or unpredictable bleeding or spotting, prolonged spotting or bleeding, and heavy bleeding. Rule out the possibility of organic pathology if abnormal bleeding persists or is severe, and institute appropriate treatment.



 As women continue using Depo-Provera CI, fewer experience irregular bleeding and more experience amenorrhea. In clinical studies of Depo-Provera CI, by month 12 amenorrhea was reported by 55% of women, and by month 24, amenorrhea was reported by 68% of women using Depo-Provera CI.



    5.10 Weight Gain



  Women tend to gain weight while on therapy with Depo-Provera CI. From an initial average body weight of 136 lb, women who completed 1 year of therapy with Depo-Provera CI gained an average of 5.4 lb. Women who completed 2 years of therapy gained an average of 8.1 lb. Women who completed 4 years gained an average of 13.8 lb. Women who completed 6 years gained an average of 16.5 lb. Two percent of women withdrew from a large-scale clinical trial because of excessive weight gain.



    5.11 Carbohydrate Metabolism



  A decrease in glucose tolerance has been observed in some patients on Depo-Provera CI treatment. Monitor diabetic patients carefully while receiving Depo-Provera CI.



    5.12 Lactation



  Detectable amounts of drug have been identified in the milk of mothers receiving Depo-Provera CI. In nursing mothers treated with Depo-Provera CI, milk composition, quality, and amount are not adversely affected. Neonates and infants exposed to medroxyprogesterone from breast milk have been studied for developmental and behavioral effects through puberty. No adverse effects have been noted.



    5.13 Fluid Retention



  Because progestational drugs including Depo-Provera CI may cause some degree of fluid retention, monitor patients with conditions that might be influenced by this condition, such as epilepsy, migraine, asthma, and cardiac or renal dysfunction.



    5.14 Return of Fertility



  Return to ovulation and fertility is likely to be delayed after stopping Depo-Provera CI. In a large US study of women who discontinued use of Depo-Provera CI to become pregnant, data are available for 61% of them. Of the 188 women who discontinued the study to become pregnant, 114 became pregnant. Based on Life-Table analysis of these data, it is expected that 68% of women who do become pregnant may conceive within 12 months, 83% may conceive within 15 months, and 93% may conceive within 18 months from the last injection. The median time to conception for those who do conceive is 10 months following the last injection with a range of 4 to 31 months, and is unrelated to the duration of use. No data are available for 39% of the patients who discontinued Depo-Provera CI to become pregnant and who were lost to follow-up or changed their mind.



    5.15 Sexually Transmitted Diseases



  Patients should be counseled that Depo-Provera CI does not protect against HIV infection (AIDS) and other sexually transmitted diseases.



    5.16 Pregnancy



  Although Depo-Provera CI should not be used during pregnancy, there appears to be little or no increased risk of birth defects in women who have inadvertently been exposed to medroxyprogesterone acetate injections in early pregnancy. Neonates exposed to medroxyprogesterone acetate in-utero and followed to adolescence showed no evidence of any adverse effects on their health including their physical, intellectual, sexual or social development.



    5.17 Monitoring



  A woman who is taking hormonal contraceptive should have a yearly visit with her healthcare provider for a blood pressure check and for other indicated healthcare.



    5.18 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  The use of Depo-Provera CI may change the results of some laboratory tests, such as coagulation factors, lipids, glucose tolerance, and binding proteins. [See  Drug Interactions (7.2)  .]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
