<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="desferal" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following adverse reactions have been observed, but there are not enough data to support an estimate of their frequency.



   At the Injection Site:       Localized irritation, pain, burning, swelling, induration, infiltration, pruritus, erythema, wheal formation, eschar, crust, vesicles, local edema. Injection site reactions may be associated with systemic allergic reactions (see Body as a Whole, below).



   Hypersensitivity Reactions and Systemic Allergic Reactions:       Generalized rash, urticaria, anaphylactic reaction with or without shock, angioedema. 



   Body as a Whole:   Local injection site reactions may be accompanied by systemic reactions like arthralgia, fever, headache, myalgia, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, or asthma.



 Infections with  Yersinia   and  Mucormycosis   have been reported in association with Desferal use (see PRECAUTIONS).



   Cardiovascular:       Tachycardia, hypotension, shock.



   Digestive:       Abdominal discomfort, diarrhea, nausea, vomiting.



   Hematologic:   Blood dyscrasia (thrombocytopenia, leucopenia).



   Hepatic:   Increased transaminases, hepatic dysfunction.



   Musculoskeletal:       Muscle spasms. Growth retardation and bone changes (e.g., metaphyseal dysplasia) are common in chelated patients given doses above 60 mg/kg, especially those who begin iron chelation in the first three years of life. If doses are kept to 40 mg/kg or below, the risk may be reduced (see WARNINGS, PRECAUTIONS/Pediatric Use).



   Nervous    S    ystem:       Neurological disturbances including dizziness, peripheral sensory, motor, or mixed neuropathy, paresthesias, seizures; exacerbation or precipitation of aluminum-related dialysis encephalopathy (see PRECAUTIONS/Information for Patients).



   Special Senses:   High-frequency sensorineural hearing loss and/or tinnitus are uncommon if dosage guidelines are not exceeded and if dose is reduced when ferritin levels decline. Visual disturbances are rare if dosage guidelines are not exceeded. These may include decreased acuity, blurred vision, loss of vision, dyschromatopsia, night blindness, visual field defects, scotoma, retinopathy (pigmentary degeneration), optic neuritis, and cataracts (see WARNINGS).



   Respiratory:   Acute respiratory distress syndrome (with dyspnea, cyanosis, and/or interstitial infiltrates) (see WARNINGS).



   Skin:   Very rare generalized rash.



   Urogenital:       Dysuria, acute renal failure, increased serum creatinine and renal tubular disorders (see CONTRAINDICATIONS and WARNINGS).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
