<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dexilant0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=2%): diarrhea, abdominal pain, nausea, upper respiratory tract infection, vomiting, and flatulence. (  6.1  )



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Takeda Pharmaceuticals America, Inc. at 1-877-TAKEDA-7 (1-877-825-3327) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of DEXILANT was evaluated in 4548 patients in controlled and uncontrolled clinical studies, including 863 patients treated for at least six months and 203 patients treated for one year. Patients ranged in age from 18 to 90 years (median age 48 years), with 54% female, 85% Caucasian, 8% Black, 4% Asian, and 3% other races. Six randomized controlled clinical trials were conducted for the treatment of EE, maintenance of healed EE, and symptomatic GERD, which included 896 patients on placebo, 455 patients on DEXILANT 30 mg, 2218 patients on DEXILANT 60 mg, and 1363 patients on lansoprazole 30 mg once daily.



     Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions  



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) that occurred at a higher incidence for DEXILANT than placebo in the controlled studies are presented in Table 2.




  Table 2. Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Controlled Studies    
  Adverse Reaction                  Placebo  (N=896)%    DEXILANT30 mg  (N=455)%    DEXILANT60 mg  (N=2218)%    DEXILANTTotal  (N=2621)%    Lansoprazole30 mg  (N=1363)%    
  Diarrhea                          2.9         5.1             4.7             4.8             3.2              
  Abdominal Pain                    3.5         3.5             4.0             4.0             2.6              
  Nausea                            2.6         3.3             2.8             2.9             1.8              
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection    0.8         2.9             1.7             1.9             0.8              
  Vomiting                          0.8         2.2             1.4             1.6             1.1              
  Flatulence                        0.6         2.6             1.4             1.6             1.2              
                Adverse Reactions Resulting in Discontinuation  
 

 In controlled clinical studies, the most common adverse reaction leading to discontinuation from DEXILANT therapy was diarrhea (0.7%).



     Other Adverse Reactions  



 Other adverse reactions that were reported in controlled studies at an incidence of less than 2% are listed below by body system:



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  anemia, lymphadenopathy



   Cardiac Disorders:  angina, arrhythmia, bradycardia, chest pain, edema, myocardial infarction, palpitation, tachycardia



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  ear pain, tinnitus, vertigo



   Endocrine Disorders:  goiter



   Eye Disorders:  eye irritation, eye swelling



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  abdominal discomfort, abdominal tenderness, abnormal feces, anal discomfort, Barrett's esophagus, bezoar, bowel sounds abnormal, breath odor, colitis microscopic, colonic polyp, constipation, dry mouth, duodenitis, dyspepsia, dysphagia, enteritis, eructation, esophagitis, gastric polyp, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal disorders, gastrointestinal hypermotility disorders, GERD, GI ulcers and perforation, hematemesis, hematochezia, hemorrhoids, impaired gastric emptying, irritable bowel syndrome, mucus stools, oral mucosal blistering, painful defecation, proctitis, paresthesia oral, rectal hemorrhage, retching



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  adverse drug reaction, asthenia, chest pain, chills, feeling abnormal, inflammation, mucosal inflammation, nodule, pain, pyrexia



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  biliary colic, cholelithiasis, hepatomegaly



   Immune System Disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Infections and Infestations:  candida infections, influenza, nasopharyngitis, oral herpes, pharyngitis, sinusitis, viral infection, vulvo-vaginal infection



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  falls, fractures, joint sprains, overdose, procedural pain, sunburn



   Laboratory Investigations:  ALP increased, ALT increased, AST increased, bilirubin decreased/increased, blood creatinine increased, blood gastrin increased, blood glucose increased, blood potassium increased, liver function test abnormal, platelet count decreased, total protein increased, weight increase



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  appetite changes, hypercalcemia, hypokalemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  arthralgia, arthritis, muscle cramps, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia



   Nervous System Disorders:  altered taste, convulsion, dizziness, headaches, migraine, memory impairment, paresthesia, psychomotor hyperactivity, tremor, trigeminal neuralgia



   Psychiatric Disorders:  abnormal dreams, anxiety, depression, insomnia, libido changes



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  dysuria, micturition urgency



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  dysmenorrhea, dyspareunia, menorrhagia, menstrual disorder



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  aspiration, asthma, bronchitis, cough, dyspnoea, hiccups, hyperventilation, respiratory tract congestion, sore throat



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  acne, dermatitis, erythema, pruritis, rash, skin lesion, urticaria



   Vascular Disorders:  deep vein thrombosis, hot flush, hypertension



 Additional adverse reactions that were reported in a long-term uncontrolled study and were considered related to DEXILANT by the treating physician included: anaphylaxis, auditory hallucination, B-cell lymphoma, bursitis, central obesity, cholecystitis acute, dehydration, diabetes mellitus, dysphonia, epistaxis, folliculitis, gout, herpes zoster, hyperlipidemia, hypothyroidism, increased neutrophils, MCHC decrease, neutropenia, rectal tenesmus, restless legs syndrome, somnolence, tonsillitis.



 Other adverse reactions not observed with DEXILANT, but occurring with the racemate lansoprazole can be found in the lansoprazole prescribing information, ADVERSE REACTIONS section.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval of DEXILANT. As these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  autoimmune hemolytic anemia, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  deafness



   Eye Disorders:  blurred vision



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  oral edema, pancreatitis



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  facial edema



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  drug-induced hepatitis



   Immune System Disorders:  anaphylactic shock (requiring emergency intervention), exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis (some fatal)



   Infections and Infestations: Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  hypomagnesemia, hyponatremia



   Musculoskeletal System Disorders:  bone fracture



   Nervous System Disorders:  cerebrovascular accident, transient ischemic attack



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  acute renal failure



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  pharyngeal edema, throat tightness



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  generalized rash, leukocytoclastic vasculitis
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Gastric Malignancy : Symptomatic response with DEXILANT does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs. (  5.2  ) 
 *     Cyanocobalamin (vitamin B12) Deficiency : Daily long-term use (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption or a deficiency of cyanocobalamin. (5.3) 
 *      Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea: PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea. (  5.4  ) 
 *     Bone Fracture: Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine. (  5.5  ) 
 *     Hypomagnesemia : Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Gastric Malignancy



  Symptomatic response with DEXILANT does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



    5.2 Acute Interstitial Nephritis



   Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including lansoprazole. Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue DEXILANT if acute interstitial nephritis develops[     see Contraindications (4)     ] .    



    5.3 Cyanocobalamin (vitamin B12) Deficiency



   Daily treatment with any acid-suppressing medications over a long period of time (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption of cyanocobalamin (vitamin B12) caused by hypo- or achlorhydria. Rare reports of cyanocobalamin deficiency occurring with acid-suppressing therapy have been reported in the literature. This diagnosis should be considered if clinical symptoms consistent with cyanocobalamin deficiency are observed.  



    5.4 Clostridium difficile  Associated Diarrhea



  Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like DEXILANT may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve   [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]    .



 Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.



    5.5 Bone Fracture



  Several published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the conditions being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)  ].  



    5.6 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), health care professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.7 Concomitant Use of DEXILANT with Methotrexate



  Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients [see  Drug Interactions (7.5)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
