<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dexmethylphenidate" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The premarketing development program for dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets included exposures in a total of 696 participants in clinical trials (684 patients, 12 healthy adult subjects). These participants received dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets 5, 10, or 20 mg/day. The 684 ADHD patients (ages 6 to 17 years) were evaluated in 2 controlled clinical studies, 2 clinical pharmacology studies, and 2 uncontrolled long-term safety studies. Safety data on all patients are included in the discussion that follows. Adverse reactions were assessed by collecting adverse events, and results of physical examinations, vital sign and body weight measurements, and laboratory analyses.



 Adverse events during exposure were primarily obtained by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of events into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and tabulations that follow, standard COSTART dictionary terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events.



 The stated frequencies of adverse events represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



   Adverse Findings in Clinical Trials with Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride Tablets

      Adverse Events Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment    

  No dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride-treated patients discontinued due to adverse events in 2 placebo-controlled trials. Overall, 50 of 684 children treated with dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets (7.3%) experienced an adverse event that resulted in discontinuation. The most common reasons for discontinuation were twitching (described as motor or vocal tics), anorexia, insomnia, and tachycardia (approximately 1% each).



   Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 5% or More Among Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride-Treated Patients

  Table 1 enumerates treatment-emergent adverse events for 2, placebo-controlled, parallel group trials in children with ADHD at dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride doses of 5, 10, and 20 mg/day. The table includes only those events that occurred in 5% or more of patients treated with dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets where the incidence in patients treated with dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets was at least twice the incidence in placebo-treated patients. The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events1 Occurring During Double-Blind Treatment in Clinical Trials of Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride Tablets 
                                               Dexmethylphenidate  Hydrochloride Tablets    Placebo     
  Body System           Preferred Term         (n=79)                                  (n=82)      
  Body as a Whole                                                                                  
                        Abdominal Pain         15%                                     6%          
                        Fever                  5%                                      1%          
  Digestive System                                                                                 
                        Anorexia               6%                                      1%          
                        Nausea                 9%                                      1%          
            1  Events, regardless of causality, for which the incidence for patients treated with dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets were at least 5% and twice the incidence among placebo-treated patients. Incidence has been rounded to the nearest whole number.
 

   Adverse Events from Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride extended-release capsules. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency:



     Immune System Disorders:    hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema and anaphylaxis



   Adverse Events with Other Methylphenidate HCl Products

  Nervousness and insomnia are the most common adverse reactions reported with other methylphenidate products. In children, loss of appetite, abdominal pain, weight loss during prolonged therapy, insomnia, and tachycardia may occur more frequently; however, any of the other adverse reactions listed below may also occur.



   Other reactions include:

      Cardiac:    angina, arrhythmia, palpitations, pulse increased or decreased, tachycardia



     Gastrointestinal:    nausea



     Immune:    hypersensitivity reactions including skin rash, urticaria, fever, arthralgia, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme with histopathological findings of necrotizing vasculitis, and thrombocytopenic purpura



     Nervous System:    dizziness, drowsiness, dyskinesia, headache, rare reports of Tourette's syndrome, toxic psychosis



     Vascular:    blood pressure increased or decreased, cerebral arteritis and/or occlusion



 Although a definite causal relationship has not been established, the following have been reported in patients taking methylphenidate:



     Blood/lymphatic:    leukopenia and/or anemia



     Hepatobiliary:    abnormal liver function, ranging from transaminase elevation to hepatic coma



     Psychiatric:    transient depressed mood, aggressive behavior, libido changes



     Skin/subcutaneous:    scalp hair loss



     Urogenital System:    priapism



 Very rare reports of neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS) have been received, and, in most of these, patients were concurrently receiving therapies associated with NMS. In a single report, a 10-year-old boy who had been taking methylphenidate for approximately 18 months experienced an NMS-like event within 45 minutes of ingesting his first dose of venlafaxine. It is uncertain whether this case represented a drug-drug interaction, a response to either drug alone, or some other cause.



 In children, loss of appetite, abdominal pain, weight loss during prolonged therapy, insomnia, and tachycardia may occur more frequently; however, any of the other adverse reactions listed above may also occur.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: MEDICATION GUIDE Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride Tablets, CII(dex-meth-ill-FEN-ih-date)  

  MEDICATION GUIDE Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride Tablets, CII(dex-meth-ill-FEN-ih-date)  

  Read the Medication Guide that comes with dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets before you or your child starts taking it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your doctor about your or your child's treatment with dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets.



   

    What is the most important information I should know about     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets?  



   The following have been reported with use of     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride and other stimulant medicines.  



     1. Heart-related problems:    



 *  sudden death in patients who have heart problems or heart defects 
 *  stroke and heart attack in adults 
 *  increased blood pressure and heart rate 
    Tell your doctor if you or your child have any heart problems, heart defects, high blood pressure, or a family history of these problems. 
 

 Your doctor should check you or your child carefully for heart problems before starting dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets. 



 Your doctor should check your or your child's blood pressure and heart rate regularly during treatment with dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets. 



   Call your doctor right away if you or your child has any signs of heart problems such as chest pain, shortness of breath, or fainting while taking     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets.  



     2. Mental (Psychiatric) problems:    



   All Patients  



 *  new or worse behavior and thought problems 
 *  new or worse bipolar illness 
 *  new or worse aggressive behavior or hostility 
      Children and Teenagers  
 

 *  new psychotic symptoms (such as hearing voices, believing things that are not true, are suspicious) or new manic symptoms 
    Tell your doctor about any mental problems you or your child have, or about a family history of suicide, bipolar illness, or depression. 
 

   Call your doctor right away if you or your     child have     any new or worsening mental symptoms or problems while taking     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets, especially seeing or hearing things that are not real, believing things that are not real, or are suspicious.  



     3. Circulation problems in fingers and toes     [Peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon]: fingers or toes may feel numb, cool, painful, and/or may change color from pale, to blue, to red 



 *  Tell your doctor if you have or your child has numbness, pain, skin color change, or sensitivity to temperature in the fingers or toes. 
 *  Call your doctor right away if you have or your child has any signs of unexplained wounds appearing on fingers or toes while taking dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets 
      What are dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets?
   Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets are a central nervous system stimulant prescription medicine.   They are used for the treatment of attention deficit and hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).   Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets may help increase attention and decrease impulsiveness and hyperactivity in patients with ADHD. 



 Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets should be used as a part of a total treatment program for ADHD that may include counseling or other therapies.




 Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride is a federally controlled substance (CII) because it can be abused or lead to dependence. Keep dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets in a safe place to prevent misuse and abuse. Selling or giving away dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets may harm others, and is against the law.Tell your doctor if you or your child have (or have a family history of) ever abused or been dependent on alcohol, prescription medicines or street drugs.   
         Who should not take     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets?  
 

   Dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets should not be taken if you or your child:  



 *  are very anxious, tense, or agitated 
 *  have an eye problem called glaucoma 
 *  have tics or Tourette's syndrome, or a family history of Tourette's syndrome. Tics are hard to control repeated movements or sounds. 
 *  are taking or have taken within the past 14 days an anti-depression medicine called a monoamine oxidase inhibitor or MAOI. 
 *  are allergic to anything in dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients. 
    Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride should not be used in children less than 6 years old because it has not been studied in this age group. 
 

   Dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets may not be right for you or your child. Before starting     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets tell your or your child's doctor about all health conditions (or a family history of) including:  



 *  heart problems, heart defects, high blood pressure 
 *  mental problems including psychosis, mania, bipolar illness, or depression 
 *  tics or Tourette's syndrome 
 *  seizures or have had an abnormal brain wave test (EEG) 
 *  circulation problems in fingers or toes 
    Tell your doctor if you or your child is pregnant, planning to become pregnant, or breastfeeding. 
 

   Can     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets be taken with other medicines?  



   Tell your doctor about all of the medicines that you or your child takes including prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements.   Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride and some medicines may interact with each other and cause serious side effects. Sometimes the doses of other medicines will need to be adjusted while taking dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets. 



 Your doctor will decide whether dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets can be taken with other medicines. 



   Especially tell your doctor if you or your child takes:  



 *  anti-depression medicines including MAOIs 
 *  seizure medicines 
 *  blood thinner medicines 
 *  blood pressure medicines 
 *  cold or allergy medicines that contain decongestants 
    Know the medicines that you or your child takes. Keep a list of your medicines with you to show your doctor and pharmacist. 
 

   Do not start any new medicine while taking     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets without talking to your doctor first.  



   How should     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets be taken?  



 *  Take dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets exactly as prescribed. Your doctor may adjust the dose until it is right for you or your child. 
 *  Take dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets twice a day, at least 4 hours apart. 
 *  Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets can be taken with or without food. 
 *  From time to time, your doctor may stop dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets treatment for a while to check ADHD symptoms. 
 *  Your doctor may do regular checks of the blood, heart, and blood pressure while taking dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets. Children should have their height and weight checked often while taking dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets. Dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets treatment may be stopped if a problem is found during these check-ups. 
 *  If you or your child takes too many dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets or overdoses, call your doctor or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What are possible side effects of     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets?  
 

 See   "What is the most important information I should know about     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets?"   for information on reported heart and mental problems. 



   Other serious side effects include:  



 *  serious allergic reactions (symptoms can be difficulty breathing, swelling of the face, neck and throat, rashes and hives, fever) 
 *  slowing of growth (height and weight) in children 
 *  seizures, mainly in patients with a history of seizures 
 *  eyesight changes or blurred vision 
 *  painful and prolonged erections (priapism) have occurred with methylphenidate. If you or your child develop priapism, seek medical help right away. Because of the potential for lasting damage, priapism should be evaluated by a doctor immediately. 
      Common side effects include:  
 

 *  stomach ache 
 *  decreased appetite 
 *  nausea 
 *  fever 
    Talk to your doctor if you or your child has side effects that are bothersome or do not go away. 
 

 This is not a complete list of possible side effects. Ask your doctor or pharmacist for more information. 



   How should I store     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets?  



 *  Store dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets in a safe place at room temperature, 59 degrees F to 86 degrees F (15 degrees C to 30 degrees C). 
 *  Keep dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets and all medicines out of the reach of children. 
      General information about     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets for a condition for which it was not prescribed. Do not give dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets to other people, even if they have the same condition. It  may harm them and it is against the law. 



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets. If you would like more information, talk with your doctor. You can ask your doctor or pharmacist for information about dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets that was written for healthcare professionals. For more information about dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride tablets call 1-800-525-8747. 



   What are the ingredients in     dexmethylphenidate     hydrochloride tablets?  



   Active Ingredient:   dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride 



   Inactive Ingredients:   pregelatinized starch, lactose monohydrate, sodium starch glycolate, microcrystalline cellulose, magnesium stearate, and FD&amp;C Blue No.1 #5516 aluminum lake (2.5 mg tablets), D&amp;C Yellow Lake #10 (5 mg tablets); the 10 mg tablet contains no dye.



   Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.  



   This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.  



 Manufactured by:



 Mikart, Inc.Atlanta, GA 30318 forSandoz Inc.Princeton, NJ 08540



 T2014-60/T2014-61 December 2013/December 2013



 5004418
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
