<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dexmedetomidine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Bradycardia and sinus arrest [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Transient hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than 2%) were hypotension, respiratory depression, and bradycardia. (6.1)
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact WG Critical Care at 1-866-562-4708 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or     www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reaction information is derived from the two trials for procedural sedation in which 318 adult patients received dexmedetomidine HCl (Studies 1 and 2)  [see Clinical Studies (14)]  . The mean total dose was 1.6 mcg/kg (range: 0.5 mcg/kg to 6.7 mcg/kg), mean dosage per hour was 1.3 mcg/kg/hour (range: 0.3 mcg/kg/hour to 6.1 mcg/kg/hour) and the mean duration of infusion was 1.5 hours (range: 0.1 hour to 6.2 hours). The population was between 18 to 93 years of age, 30% greater than or equal to 65 years of age, 52% male and 61% Caucasian.



 Adverse reactions that occurred at an incidence of greater than 2% of patients receiving dexmedetomidine HCl and at an incidence greater than placebo are provided in Table 2. Pre-specified criteria for the vital signs to be reported as adverse reactions are footnoted below the table. The decrease in respiratory rate and hypoxia was similar between dexmedetomidine HCl and comparator groups in both studies.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions* in Clinical Trials of Dexmedetomidine HCl for Adult Procedural Sedation 
  Adverse Reaction                         Dexmedetomidine HCl(N = 318) (%)            Placebo (N = 113) (%)    
  Hypotension1                             54%                                         30%                  
  Respiratory Depression2                  37%                                         32%                  
  Bradycardia3                             14%                                         4%                   
  Nausea                                   3%                                          2%                   
  Dry Mouth                                3%                                          1%                   
  * Adverse reactions that occurred at an incidence of greater than 2% of patients receiving dexmedetomidine HCl and at an incidence greater than placebo  1 Hypotension was defined in absolute and relative terms as systolic blood pressure of less than 80 mmHg or less than or equal to 30% lower than pre-study drug infusion value, or diastolic blood pressure of less than 50 mmHg.  2 Respiratory depression was defined in absolute and relative terms as respiratory rate (RR) less than 8 beats per minute or greater than 25% decrease from baseline.  3 Bradycardia was defined in absolute and relative terms as less than 40 beats per minute or less than or equal to 30% lower than pre-study drug infusion value.    
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions, which do not appear elsewhere in this section, have been identified during post-approval use of dexmedetomidine HCl. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Hypotension and bradycardia were the most common adverse reactions associated with the use of dexmedetomidine HCl during post approval use.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Experienced During Post-approval Use of Dexmedetomidine HCl 
  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    Anemia                                                              
  Cardiac Disorders                   Arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, atrioventricular block, cardiac arrest, cardiac disorder, extrasystoles, myocardial infarction, supraventricular tachycardia, tachycardia, ventricular arrhythmia, ventricular tachycardia    
  Eye Disorders                       Photopsia, visual impairment                                        
  Gastrointestinal Disorders          Abdominal pain, diarrhea, vomiting                                  
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    Chills, hyperpyrexia, pain, pyrexia, thirst                         
  Hepatobiliary Disorders             Hepatic function abnormal, hyperbilirubinemia                       
  Investigations                      Alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, blood urea increased, electrocardiogram T wave inversion, gammaglutamyltransferase increased, Electrocardiogram QT prolonged    
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders    Acidosis, hyperkalemia, hypoglycemia, hypovolemia, hypernatremia    
  Nervous System Disorders            Convulsion, dizziness, headache, neuralgia, neuritis, speech disorder    
  Psychiatric Disorders               Agitation, confusional state, delirium, hallucination, illusion     
  Renal and Urinary Disorders         Oliguria, polyuria                                                  
  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    Apnea, bronchospasm, dyspnea, hypercapnia, hypoventilation, hypoxia, pulmonary congestion, respiratory acidosis    
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    Hyperhidrosis, pruritus, rash, urticaria                            
  Surgical and Medical Procedures     Light anesthesia                                                    
  Vascular Disorders                  Blood pressure fluctuation, hemorrhage, hypertension                
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   



 *     Bradycardia and Sinus Arrest: Consider decreasing or stopping dexmedetomidine HCl infusion; decreasing or stopping other medications that depress sinus node function; administering anticholinergic agents (e.g., glycopyrrolate, atropine); and/or administering pressor agents. (5.1) 
 *     Hypotension: Consider decreasing or stopping dexmedetomidine HCl infusion; increasing rate of intravenous fluid administration; elevating lower extremities, and/or administering pressor agents. (5.2) 
 *     Transient Hypertension: Observed primarily during administration of loading dose. Consider reducing loading infusion rate. (5.3) 
 *     Arousability: Patients can become aroused/alert with stimulation; this alone should not be considered as lack of efficacy. (5.4) 
 *    Prolonged exposure to dexmedetomidine beyond 24 hours may be associated with tolerance and tachyphylaxis and a dose-related increase in adverse events. (5.6) 
    
 

   5.1 Bradycardia and Sinus Arrest



  Bradycardia and sinus arrest have been reported following administration of dexmedetomidine HCl to young, healthy adult volunteers with high vagal tone or following rapid intravenous or bolus administration of dexmedetomidine HCl. Bradycardia has also been reported in association with intravenous infusion of dexmedetomidine HCl. Some of these cases have resulted in fatalities. Dexmedetomidine HCl decreases sympathetic nervous system activity and has the potential to augment bradycardia induced by vagal stimuli. Elderly patients and patients with advanced heart block, severe ventricular dysfunction, hypovolemia, diabetes mellitus, and/or chronic hypertension are at increased risk of bradycardia following administration of dexmedetomidine HCl. Closely monitor heart rate and other hemodynamic parameters during administration of dexmedetomidine HCl. In patients who develop bradycardia, consider decreasing or stopping the dexmedetomidine HCl infusion; decreasing or stopping other medications that depress the sinus node function; administering anticholinergic agents (e.g., glycopyrrolate, atropine) to modify vagal tone; and/or administering pressor agents. In patients with significant cardiovascular dysfunction, more advanced resuscitative measures may be required.



    5.2 Hypotension



  Hypotension has been reported in association with intravenous infusion of dexmedetomidine HCl. Some of these cases have resulted in fatalities. Elderly patients [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5)]  and patients with advanced heart block, severe ventricular dysfunction, hypovolemia, diabetes mellitus, and/or chronic hypertension are at increased risk of hypotension following administration of dexmedetomidine HCl. Closely monitor blood pressure and other hemodynamic parameters during administration of dexmedetomidine HCl. If hypotension occurs, consider decreasing or stopping the dexmedetomidine HCl infusion; increasing the rate of intravenous fluid administration; elevating the lower extremities; and/or administering pressor agents.



    5.3 Transient Hypertension



   5.4 Arousability



  Some patients receiving dexmedetomidine HCl have been observed to be arousable and alert when stimulated. This alone should not be considered as evidence of lack of efficacy in the absence of other clinical signs and symptoms.



    5.5 Withdrawal Adverse Reactions



  In adult subjects, withdrawal symptoms were not seen after discontinuation of infusions of dexmedetomidine HCl less than 6 hours in duration.



    5.6 Tolerance and Tachyphylaxis
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
