<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dextroamphetamine0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



    EXCERPT:    *  Children (ages 6 to 12): Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and with a higher incidence than on placebo) were loss of appetite, insomnia, abdominal pain, emotional lability, vomiting, nervousness, nausea, and fever. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adolescents (ages 13 to 17): Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and with a higher incidence than on placebo) were loss of appetite, insomnia, abdominal pain, weight loss, and nervousness. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adults: Most common adverse reactions &gt;=5% and with a higher incidence than on placebo were dry mouth, loss of appetite, insomnia, headache, weight loss, nausea, anxiety, agitation, dizziness, tachycardia, diarrhea, asthenia, and urinary tract infections. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact IMPAX Laboratories Inc., at 1-800-934-6729 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  The premarketing development program for MAS-ER Capsules included exposures in a total of 1315 participants in clinical trials (635 pediatric patients, 350 adolescent patients, 248 adult patients, and 82 healthy adult subjects). Of these, 635 patients (ages 6 to 12) were evaluated in two controlled clinical studies, one open-label clinical study, and two single-dose clinical pharmacology studies (N= 40). Safety data on all patients are included in the discussion that follows. Adverse reactions were assessed by collecting adverse reactions, results of physical examinations, vital signs, weights, laboratory analyses, and ECGs.



 Adverse reactions during exposure were obtained primarily by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse reactions without first grouping similar types of reactions into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and listings that follow, COSTART terminology has been used to classify reported adverse reactions.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed.



   

    Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment  



 In two placebo-controlled studies of up to 5 weeks duration among children with ADHD, 2.4% (10/425) of MAS-ER Capsules-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions (including 3 patients with loss of appetite, one of whom also reported insomnia) compared to 2.7% (7/259) receiving placebo.



 The most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of MAS-ER Capsules in controlled and uncontrolled, multiple-dose clinical trials of children (N=595) were anorexia (loss of appetite) (2.9%), insomnia (1.5%), weight loss (1.2%), emotional lability (1%), and depression (0.7%). Over half of these patients were exposed to MAS-ER Capsules for 12 months or more.



 In a separate placebo-controlled 4-week study in adolescents with ADHD, five patients (2.1%) discontinued treatment due to adverse events among MAS-ER Capsules-treated patients (N=233) compared to none who received placebo (N=54). The most frequent adverse event leading to discontinuation and considered to be drug-related (i.e. leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of MAS-ER Capsules-treated patients and at a rate at least twice that of placebo) was insomnia (1.3%, n=3).



 In one placebo-controlled 4-week study among adults with ADHD with doses 20 mg to 60 mg, 23 patients (12.0% ) discontinued treatment due to adverse events among MAS-ER Capsules-treated patients (N=191) compared to one patient (1.6%) who received placebo (N=64). The most frequent adverse events leading to discontinuation and considered to be drug-related (i.e. leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of MAS-ER Capsules-treated patients and at a rate at least twice that of placebo) were insomnia (5.2%, n=10), anxiety (2.1%, n=4), nervousness (1.6%, n=3), dry mouth (1.6%, n=3), anorexia (1.6%, n=3), tachycardia (1.6%, n=3), headache (1.6%, n=3), and asthenia (1.0%, n=2).



   

    Adverse Reactions Occurring in Controlled Trials  



 Adverse reactions reported in a 3-week clinical trial of children and a 4-week clinical trial in adolescents and adults, respectively, treated with MAS-ER Capsules or placebo are presented in the tables below.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Reported by 2% or More of Children (6-12 Years Old) Receiving MAS-ER Capsules with Higher Incidence Than on Placebo in a 584-Patient Clinical Study 
 Body System      Preferred Term    MAS-ER(n=374)   Placebo(n=210)    
  
    General        Abdominal Pain (stomachache)        14%              10%         
                   Fever                  5%               2%         
                   Infection              4%               2%         
                   Accidental Injury         3%               2%         
                   Asthenia (fatigue)         2%               0%         
    Digestive System     Loss of Appetite        22%               2%         
                   Vomiting               7%               4%         
                   Nausea                 5%               3%         
                   Dyspepsia              2%               1%         
    Nervous System     Insomnia              17%               2%         
                   Emotional Lability         9%               2%         
                   Nervousness            6%               2%         
                   Dizziness              2%               0%         
    Metabolic/Nutritional     Weight Loss            4%               0%         
         Table 2 Adverse Reactions Reported by 5% or More of Adolescents (13-17 Years Old) Weighing &lt;= 75 kg/165 lbs Receiving MAS-ER Capsules with Higher Incidence Than Placebo in a 287 Patient Clinical Forced Weekly-Dose Titration StudyIncluded doses up to 40 mg 
 Body System      Preferred Term    MAS-ER(n=233)    Placebo(n=54)    
  
 Note: The following reactions did not meet the criterion for inclusion in Table 2 but were reported by 2% to 4% of adolescent patients receiving MAS-ER Capsules with a higher incidence than patients receiving placebo in this study: accidental injury, asthenia (fatigue), dry mouth, dyspepsia, emotional lability, nausea, somnolence, and vomiting.   
  
    General        Abdominal Pain (stomachache)        11%               2%         
    Digestive System     Loss of Appetite        36%               2%         
    Nervous System     Insomnia              12%               4%         
                   Nervousness            6%               6%         
    Metabolic/Nutritional     Weight Loss            9%               0%         
         Table 3 Adverse Reactions Reported by 5% or More of Adults Receiving MAS-ER Capsules with Higher Incidence Than on Placebo in a 255 Patient Clinical Forced Weekly-Dose Titration Study* 
 Body System      Preferred Term    MAS-ER(n=191)    Placebo(n=64)    
  
  Note: The following reactions did not meet the criterion for inclusion in Table 3 but were reported by 2% to 4% of adult patients receiving MAS-ER Capsules with a higher incidence than patients receiving placebo in this study: infection, photosensitivity reaction, constipation, tooth disorder (e.g., teeth clenching, tooth infection), emotional lability, libido decreased, somnolence, speech disorder (e.g., stuttering, excessive speech), palpitation, twitching, dyspnea, sweating, dysmenorrhea, and impotence.* Included doses up to 60 mg.? Appears the same due to rounding    
  
    General        Headache              26%              13%         
                   Asthenia               6%               5%         
    Digestive System     Dry Mouth             35%               5%         
                   Loss of Appetite        33%               3%         
                   Nausea                 8%               3%         
                   Diarrhea               6%               0%         
    Nervous System     Insomnia              27%              13%         
                   Agitation              8%               5%         
                   Anxiety                8%               5%         
                   Dizziness              7%               0%         
                   Nervousness           13%            13%  ?        
    Cardiovascular System     Tachycardia            6%               3%         
    Metabolic/Nutritional     Weight Loss           10%               0%         
    Urogenital System     Urinary Tract Infection         5%               0%         
            
     Hypertension    [see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)  ]  



 In a controlled 4-week outpatient clinical study of adolescents with ADHD, isolated systolic blood pressure elevations &gt;=15 mmHg were observed in 7/64 (11%) placebo-treated patients and 7/100 (7%) patients receiving MAS-ER Capsules 10 or 20 mg. Isolated elevations in diastolic blood pressure &gt;= 8 mmHg were observed in 16/64 (25%) placebo-treated patients and 22/100 (22%) MAS-ER Capsule-treated patients. Similar results were observed at higher doses  .  



 In a single-dose pharmacokinetic study in 23 adolescents with ADHD, isolated increases in systolic blood pressure (above the upper 95% CI for age, gender, and stature) were observed in 2/17 (12%) and 8/23 (35%), subjects administered 10 mg and 20 mg MAS-ER Capsules, respectively. Higher single doses were associated with a greater increase in systolic blood pressure. All increases were transient, appeared maximal at 2 to 4 hours post dose and not associated with symptoms.



   6.2 Adverse Reactions Associated with the Use of Amphetamine, MAS-ER Capsules, or ADDERALL  (r)  

  The following adverse reactions have been associated with the use of amphetamine, MAS-ER Capsules, or ADDERALL  (r)  :



   

    Cardiovascular  



 Palpitations. There have been isolated reports of cardiomyopathy associated with chronic amphetamine use.



   

    Central Nervous System  



 Psychotic episodes at recommended doses, overstimulation, restlessness, irritability, euphoria, dyskinesia, dysphoria, depression, tremor, tics, aggression, anger, logorrhea, dermatillomania, paresthesia (including formication), and bruxism.



   

    Eye Disorders  



 Vision blurred, mydriasis.



   

    Gastrointestinal  



 Unpleasant taste, constipation, other gastrointestinal disturbances.



   

    Allergic  



 Urticaria, rash, hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema and anaphylaxis. Serious skin rashes, including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis have been reported.



   

    Endocrine  



 Impotence, changes in libido, frequent or prolonged erections.



   

    Skin  



 Alopecia.



   Vascular Disorders  



 Raynaud's phenomenon.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  



 Rhabdomyolysis
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: POTENTIAL FOR ABUSE

  WARNING: POTENTIAL FOR ABUSE

    Amphetamines have a high potential for abuse. Administration of amphetamines for prolonged periods of time may lead to drug dependence. Pay particular attention to the possibility of subjects obtaining amphetamines for non-therapeutic use or distribution to others and the drugs should be prescribed or dispensed sparingly   [see   DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE (9)  ]  .  



   Misuse of amphetamine may cause sudden death and serious cardiovascular adverse reactions.  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  POTENTIAL FOR ABUSE



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Amphetamines have a high potential for abuse; prolonged administration may lead to dependence. (9) 
 *  Misuse of amphetamines may cause sudden death and serious cardiovascular adverse reactions. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious Cardiovascular Events: Sudden death has been reported with usual doses of CNS stimulants in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems; sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults taking CNS stimulants at usual doses. Stimulant drugs should not be used in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, coronary artery disease, or other serious heart problems. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Increase in Blood Pressure: Monitor blood pressure and pulse at appropriate intervals. Use with caution in patients for whom blood pressure increases may be problematic. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Events: Stimulants may cause treatment-emergent psychotic or manic symptoms in patients with no prior history, or exacerbation of symptoms in patients with pre-existing psychosis. Evaluate for bipolar disorder prior to stimulant use. Monitor for aggressive behavior. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Long-term Suppression of Growth: Monitor height and weight at appropriate intervals. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Seizures: May lower the convulsive threshold. Discontinue in the presence of seizures. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon:  Stimulants used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon.  Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Visual Disturbance: Difficulties with accommodation and blurring of vision have been reported with stimulant treatment. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Tics: May exacerbate tics. Evaluate for tics and Tourette's syndrome prior to stimulant administration. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Cardiovascular Events



   



   Sudden Death and Pre-existing Structural Cardiac Abnormalities or Other Serious Heart Problems  



    



   Children and Adolescents  



 Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at usual doses in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. Although some serious heart problems alone carry an increased risk of sudden death, stimulant products generally should not be used in children or adolescents with known serious structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, or other serious cardiac problems that may place them at increased vulnerability to the sympathomimetic effects of a stimulant drug [see  CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)  ].  



    



   Adults  



 Sudden deaths, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults taking stimulant drugs at usual doses for ADHD. Although the role of stimulants in these adult cases is also unknown, adults have a greater likelihood than children of having serious structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, coronary artery disease, or other serious cardiac problems. Adults with such abnormalities should also generally not be treated with stimulant drugs [see  CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)  ].  



    



   Hypertension and Other Cardiovascular Conditions  



 Stimulant medications cause a modest increase in average blood pressure (about 2-4 mmHg) and average heart rate (about 3-6 bpm), and individuals may have larger increases. While the mean changes alone would not be expected to have short-term consequences, all patients should be monitored for larger changes in heart rate and blood pressure. Caution is indicated in treating patients whose underlying medical conditions might be compromised by increases in blood pressure or heart rate, e.g., those with pre-existing hypertension, heart failure, recent myocardial infarction, or ventricular arrhythmia [see  CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)  and  ADVERSE REACTIONS (6)  ].  



    



   Assessing Cardiovascular Status in Patients being Treated with Stimulant Medications  



 Children, adolescents, or adults who are being considered for treatment with stimulant medications should have a careful history (including assessment for a family history of sudden death or ventricular arrhythmia) and physical exam to assess for the presence of cardiac disease, and should receive further cardiac evaluation if findings suggest such disease (e.g. electrocardiogram and echocardiogram). Patients who develop symptoms such as exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or other symptoms suggestive of cardiac disease during stimulant treatment should undergo a prompt cardiac evaluation.



    5.2 Psychiatric Adverse Events



   



   Pre-Existing Psychosis  



 Administration of stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with pre-existing psychotic disorder.



    



   Bipolar Illness  



 Particular care should be taken in using stimulants to treat ADHD patients with comorbid bipolar disorder because of concern for possible induction of mixed/manic episode in such patients. Prior to initiating treatment with a stimulant, patients with comorbid depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression.



    



   Emergence of New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms  



 Treatment-emergent psychotic or manic symptoms, e.g., hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania in children and adolescents without prior history of psychotic illness or mania can be caused by stimulants at usual doses. If such symptoms occur, consideration should be given to a possible causal role of the stimulant, and discontinuation of treatment may be appropriate. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies, such symptoms occurred in about 0.1% (4 patients with events out of 3482 exposed to methylphenidate or amphetamine for several weeks at usual doses) of stimulant-treated patients compared to 0 in placebo-treated patients.



    



   Aggression  



 Aggressive behavior or hostility is often observed in children and adolescents with ADHD, and has been reported in clinical trials and the postmarketing experience of some medications indicated for the treatment of ADHD. Although there is no systematic evidence that stimulants cause aggressive behavior or hostility, patients beginning treatment for ADHD should be monitored for the appearance of or worsening of aggressive behavior or hostility.



    5.3 Long-Term Suppression of Growth



  Monitor growth in children during treatment with stimulants. Patients who are not growing or gaining weight as expected may need to have their treatment interrupted.



 Careful follow-up of weight and height in children ages 7 to 10 years who were randomized to either methylphenidate or non-medication treatment groups over 14 months, as well as in naturalistic subgroups of newly methylphenidate-treated and non-medication treated children over 36 months (to the ages of 10 to 13 years), suggests that consistently medicated children (i.e., treatment for 7 days per week throughout the year) have a temporary slowing in growth rate (on average, a total of about 2 cm less growth in height and 2.7 kg less growth in weight over 3 years), without evidence of growth rebound during this period of development.



 In a controlled trial of MAS-ER Capsules in adolescents, mean weight change from baseline within the initial 4 weeks of therapy was -1.1 lbs. and -2.8 lbs., respectively, for patients receiving 10 mg and 20 mg MAS-ER Capsules. Higher doses were associated with greater weight loss within the initial 4 weeks of treatment. Chronic use of amphetamines can be expected to cause a similar suppression of growth.



    5.4 Seizures



  There is some clinical evidence that stimulants may lower the convulsive threshold in patients with prior history of seizures, in patients with prior EEG abnormalities in the absence of seizures, and very rarely, in patients without a history of seizures and no prior EEG evidence of seizures. In the presence of seizures, MAS-ER Capsules should be discontinued.



    5.5 Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon



   Stimulants, including MAS-ER Capsules, used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon.  Signs and symptoms are usually intermittent and mild; however, very rare sequelae include digital ulceration and/or soft tissue breakdown.  Effects of peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon, were observed in post-marketing reports at different times and at therapeutic doses in all age groups throughout the course of treatment.  Signs and symptoms generally improve after reduction in dose or discontinuation of drug.  Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants.  Further clinical evaluation (e.g., rheumatology referral) may be appropriate for certain patients.  



    5.6 Visual Disturbance



  Difficulties with accommodation and blurring of vision have been reported with stimulant treatment.



    5.7 Tics



  Amphetamines have been reported to exacerbate motor and phonic tics and Tourette's syndrome. Therefore, clinical evaluation for tics and Tourette's syndrome in patients and their families should precede use of stimulant medications.



    5.8 Prescribing and Dispensing



  The least amount of amphetamine feasible should be prescribed or dispensed at one time in order to minimize the possibility of overdosage. MAS-ER Capsules should be used with caution in patients who use other sympathomimetic drugs.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
