<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dextroamphetamine1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Cardiovascular  

  Palpitations, tachycardia, elevation of blood pressure. There have been isolated reports of cardiomyopathy associated with chronic amphetamine use.



     Central Nervous System  

  Psychotic episodes at recommended doses (rare), overstimulation, restlessness, dizziness, insomnia, euphoria, dyskinesia, dysphoria, tremor, headache, exacerbation of motor and phonic tics, and Tourette's syndrome.



     Gastrointestinal  

  Dryness of the mouth, unpleasant taste, diarrhea, constipation, other gastrointestinal disturbances. Anorexia and weight loss may occur as undesirable effects.



     Allergic  

  Urticaria.



     Endocrine  

  Impotence, changes in libido, frequent or prolonged erections.



     Musculoskeletal  

  Rhabdomyolysis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: MEDICATION GUIDECIIDextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules

    MEDICATION GUIDECIIDextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules  

  Read the Medication Guide that comes

                            with Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                            Capsules before you or your child starts taking it and each

                            time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication

                            Guide does not take the place of talking to your doctor about your or

                            your child's treatment with Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                            Extended-Release Capsules.



   

    What is the most important information

                                        I should know about Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                        Extended-Release Capsules? The following have been

                                        reported with use of Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                        Extended-Release Capsules and other stimulant

                                    medicines.  



   1.   Heart-related problems:    



 *  Sudden death in patients who have heart problems or heart defects 
 *  Stroke and heart attack in adults 
 *  Increased blood pressure and heart rate 
    Tell your doctor if you or your child have any heart
                                     problems, heart defects, high blood pressure, or a family

                                    history of these problems.Your doctor should check you or

                                    your child carefully for heart problems before starting

                                    Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules.Your

                                    doctor should check your or your child's blood pressure

                                    and heart rate regularly during treatment with Dextroamphetamine

                                    Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules.



   Call your doctor right away if you or

                                        your child has any signs of heart problems such as chest

                                        pain, shortness of breath, or fainting while taking

                                        Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules.  



   2.   Mental (Psychiatric) problems:    



   All Patients  



 *  new or worse behavior and thought problems 
 *  new or worse bipolar illness 
 *  new or worse aggressive behavior or hostility 
      Children and Teenagers  
 

 *  new psychotic symptoms (such as hearing voices, believing things that are not true, are suspicious) or new manic symptoms 
    Tell your doctor about any mental problems you or your
                                     child have, or about a family history of suicide, bipolar

                                    illness, or depression.



   Call your doctor right away if you or

                                        your child have any new or worsening mental symptoms or

                                        problems while taking Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                        Extended-Release Capsules, especially seeing or hearing

                                        things that are not real, believing things that are not

                                        real, or are suspicious.  



   3.   Circulation problems in fingers and toes       [Peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon]:  



 *  fingers or toes may feel numb, cool, painful 
 *  fingers or toes may change color from pale, to blue, to red 
    Tell your doctor if you have or your child has numbness, pain, skin color change, or sensitivity to temperature in your fingers or toes.
 

 Call your doctor right away if you have or your child has any signs of unexplained wounds appearing on fingers or toes while taking dextroamphetamine sulfate.



     What are Dextroamphetamine

                                    Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules?  

  Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules are a central nervous system stimulant

                                    prescription medicine.   It is used for

                                        the treatment of Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder

                                        (ADHD).  Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                    Extended-Release Capsules may help increase attention

                                    and decrease impulsiveness and hyperactivity in patients with

                                    ADHD.Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules should be used as a part of a total treatment

                                    program for ADHD that may include counseling or other

                                    therapies.Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules are also used in the treatment of a sleep

                                    disorder called narcolepsy.



   

    Dextroamphetamine

                                                Sulfate is a federally controlled substance

                                                (CII) because it can be abused or lead to

                                                dependence. Keep Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                                Extended-Release Capsules in a safe place to prevent

                                                misuse and abuse. Selling or giving

                                                away Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                                Extended-Release Capsules may harm others and is

                                                against the law.  



 Tell your doctor if you or your child have (or

                                            have a family history of) ever abused or been dependent

                                            on alcohol, prescription medicines or street

                                        drugs.



   

    Who should not take Dextroamphetamine

                                        Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules?Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                        Extended-Release Capsules should not be taken if you or your

                                        child:  



 *  Have heart disease or hardening of the arteries 
 *  Have moderate to severe high blood pressure 
 *  Have hyperthyroidism 
 *  Have an eye problem called glaucoma 
 *  Are very anxious, tense, or agitated 
 *  Have a history of drug abuse 
 *  Are taking or have taken within the past 14 days an antidepression medicine called a monoamine oxidase inhibitor or MAOI 
 *  Is sensitive to, allergic to, or had a reaction to other stimulant medicines 
    Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release
                                     Capsules are not recommended for use in children

                                    younger than 6 years old.



   Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                        Extended-Release Capsules may not be right for you or your

                                        child. Before starting Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                        Extended-Release Capsules tell your or your

                                        child's doctor about all health conditions (or a

                                        family history of) including:  



 *  Heart problems, heart defects, high blood pressure 
 *  Mental problems including psychosis, mania, bipolar illness, or depression 
 *  Tics or Tourette's syndrome 
 *  Thyroid problems 
 *  Seizures or have had an abnormal brain wave test (EEG) 
 *  Circulation problems in fingers and toes 
    Tell your doctor if you or your child is pregnant,
                                     planning to become pregnant, or breastfeeding.



   Can Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                        Extended-Release Capsules be taken with other

                                    medicines?  



   Tell your doctor about all of the

                                    medicines that you or your child take including prescription

                                    and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal

                                    supplements.   Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules and

                                    some medicines may interact with each other and cause serious

                                    side effects. Sometimes the doses of other medicines will need

                                    to be adjusted while taking Dextroamphetamine Sulfate

                                    Extended-Release Capsules.



 Your doctor will decide

                                    whether Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules can be taken with other medicines.



   Especially tell your doctor if you or

                                        your child takes:  



 *  Anti-depression medicines including MAOIs 
 *  Blood pressure medicines 
 *  Antacids 
 *  Seizure medicines 
    Know the medicines that you or your child takes. Keep a
                                     list of your medicines with you to show your doctor and

                                    pharmacist.



   Do not start any new medicine while

                                        taking Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                        Capsules without talking to your doctor first.  



   How should Dextroamphetamine

                                        Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules be taken?  



 *  Take Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules exactly as prescribed. Your doctor may adjust the dose until it is right for you or your child. 
 *  Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules comes as a capsule. 
 *  Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules are usually taken once a day in the morning. Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules are extended release capsules. It releases medicine into your body throughout the day. 
 *  From time to time, your doctor may stop treatment with Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules for a while to check ADHD symptoms. 
 *  Your doctor may do regular checks of the blood, heart, and blood pressure while taking Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules. Children should have their height and weight checked often while taking Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules. Treatment with Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules may be stopped if a problem is found during these check-ups. 
 *  If you or your child takes too much Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules or overdoses, call your doctor or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What are possible side effects of
                                         Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules?  See     "What is the most

                                        important information I should know about Dextroamphetamine

                                        Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules?"     for

                                    information on reported heart and mental problems. 



   Other serious side effects

                                    include:  



 *  Slowing of growth (height and weight) in children 
 *  Seizures, mainly in patients with a history of seizures 
 *  Eyesight changes or blurred vision 
      Common side effects include:
                                       



 *  Fast heartbeat 
 *  Decreased appetite 
 *  Tremors 
 *  Headache 
 *  Trouble sleeping 
 *  Dizziness 
 *  Stomach upset 
 *  Weight loss 
 *  Dry mouth 
    Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release
                                     Capsules may affect your or your child's

                                    ability to drive or do other dangerous activities.



 Talk to your doctor if you or your child has side effects

                                    that are bothersome or do not go away. This is not a complete list of possible side effects. Ask

                                    your doctor or pharmacist for more information. Call you doctor

                                    for medical advice about side effects.  You may report

                                    side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.



   How should I store Dextroamphetamine

                                        Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules?   



 *  Store Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules in a safe place at room temperature, 68 degrees  to 77 degrees F (20 degrees  to 25 degrees C). [See USP]. Protect from light. 
 *  Keep Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules and all medicines out of the reach of children. 
    
 

   General information about

                                    Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules  Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other

                                    than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not

                                    use Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules

                                    for a condition for which it was not prescribed. Do not

                                    give Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules to other people, even if they have the same condition.

                                    It may harm them and it is against the law.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important

                                    information about Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules. If you would like more information, talk with your

                                    doctor. You can ask your doctor or pharmacist for information

                                    about Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules that was written for healthcare professionals. For more information about Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release Capsules, please contact Lineage Therapeutics at 1-888-894-6528 or visit www.lineagetherapeutics.com.



   What are the ingredients in

                                        Dextroamphetamine Sulfate Extended-Release

                                    Capsules?  



   Active Ingredient:  

                                    Dextroamphetamine sulfate 



   Inactive

                                        Ingredients:    Cetyl alcohol,

                                    D&amp;C Yellow No. 10, dibutyl sebacate, ethylcellulose,

                                    FD&amp;C Red No. 40, FD&amp;C Yellow No. 6, gelatin,

                                    hypromellose, polyethylene glycol, povidone, sodium lauryl sulfate, and sugar spheres and trace amounts of

                                    other inactive ingredients.



 This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food

                                    and Drug Administration.



 Manufactured by Catalent Pharma

                                    SolutionsWinchester, KY 40391



 forLineage Therapeutics Inc.Horsham, PA 19044LB# 823-04                          Rev. October, 2013



 For additional copies of the printed patient information/medication guide, please visit

                                    www.lineagetherapeutics.com or contact us at 1-888-894-6528.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
