<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="diabeta" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Hypoglycemia:  See  PRECAUTIONS  and  OVERDOSAGE  Sections.



   Gastrointestinal Reactions:  Cholestatic jaundice and hepatitis may occur rarely which may progress to liver failure; Diabetaeta should be discontinued if this occurs. Liver function abnormalities, including isolated transaminase elevations, have been reported. Gastrointestinal disturbances, e.g., nausea, epigastric fullness, and heartburn, are the most common reactions and occur in 1.8% of treated patients. They tend to be dose-related and may disappear when dosage is reduced.



   Dermatologic Reactions:  Allergic skin reactions, e.g., pruritus, erythema, urticaria, and morbilliform or maculopapular eruptions, occur in 1.5% of treated patients. These may be transient and may disappear despite continued use of Diabetaeta; if skin reactions persist, the drug should be discontinued.



 Porphyria cutanea tarda and photosensitivity reactions have been reported with sulfonylureas.



   Hematologic Reactions:  Leukopenia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia, which occasionally may present as purpura, hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia, and pancytopenia have been reported with sulfonylureas.



   Metabolic Reactions:  Hepatic porphyria reactions have been reported with sulfonylureas; however, these have not been reported with Diabetaeta. Disulfiram-like reactions have been reported very rarely with Diabetaeta. Cases of hyponatremia have been reported with glyburide and all other sulfonylureas, most often in patients who are on other medications or have medical conditions known to cause hyponatremia or increase release of antidiuretic hormone. The syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone (SIADH) secretion has been reported with certain other sulfonylureas, and it has been suggested that these sulfonylureas may augment the peripheral (antidiuretic) action of ADH and/or increase release of ADH.



   Other Reactions:  Changes in accommodation and/or blurred vision have been reported with glyburide and other sulfonylureas. These are thought to be related to fluctuation in glucose levels.



 In addition to dermatologic reactions, allergic reactions such as angioedema, arthralgia, myalgia and vasculitis have been reported.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
