<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="diclofenac" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Of the 423 patients evaluable for safety in adequate and well-controlled trials, 211 were treated with Diclofenac Sodium Gel drug product and 212 were treated with a vehicle gel. Eighty-seven percent (87%) of the Diclofenac Sodium Gel treated patients (183 patients) and 84% of the vehicle-treated patients (178 patients) experienced one or more adverse events (AEs) during the studies. The majority of these reactions were mild to moderate in severity and resolved upon discontinuation of therapy.



 Of the 211 patients treated with Diclofenac Sodium Gel, 172 (82%) experienced AEs involving skin and the application site compared to 160 (75%) vehicle-treated patients. Application site reactions (ASRs) were the most frequent AEs in both Diclofenac Sodium Gel and vehicle-treated groups. Of note, four reactions,  contact dermatitis, rash, dry skin and exfoliation  (scaling) were significantly more prevalent in the Diclofenac Sodium Gel group than in the vehicle-treated patients.



 Eighteen percent of Diclofenac Sodium Gel treated patients and 4% of vehicle-treated patients discontinued from the clinical trials due to adverse events (whether considered related to treatment or not). These discontinuations were mainly due to skin irritation or related cutaneous adverse reactions.



   Table 1  below presents the AEs reported at an incidence of &gt;1% for patients treated with either Diclofenac Sodium Gel or vehicle (60- and 90-day treatment groups) during the phase 3 studies.



 Table 1. Adverse Events Reported (&gt;1% in Any Treatment Group) During Diclofenac Sodium Gel Phase 3 Clinical Trials Incidences for 60-Day and 90-Day Treatments 
                                60-day Treatment      90-day Treatment   
                                Diclofenac Sodium Gel (%)  Gel Vehicle (%)  Diclofenac Sodium Gel (%)  Gel Vehicle (%)   
                                N=48                  N=49            N=114                   N=114           
   BODY AS A WHOLE                21                    20              20                      18            
 Abdominal Pain                 2                     0               1                       0               
 Accidental Injury              0                     0               4                       2               
 Allergic Reaction              0                     0               1                       3               
 Asthenia                       0                     0               2                       0               
 Back Pain                      4                     0               2                       2               
 Chest Pain                     2                     0               1                       0               
 Chills                         0                     2               0                       0               
 Flu Syndrome                   10                    6               1                       4               
 Headache                       0                     6               7                       6               
 Infection                      4                     6               4                       5               
 Neck Pain                      0                     0               2                       0               
 Pain                           2                     0               2                       2               
   CARDIOVASCULAR SYSTEM          2                     4               3                       1             
 Hypertension                   2                     0               1                       0               
 Migraine                       0                     2               1                       0               
 Phlebitis                      0                     2               0                       0               
   DIGESTIVE SYSTEM               4                     0               6                       8             
 Constipation                   0                     0               0                       2               
 Diarrhea                       2                     0               2                       3               
 Dyspepsia                      2                     0               3                       4               
   METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL DISORDERS      2                     8               7                       2             
 Creatine Phosphokinase Increased  0                     0               4                       1               
 Creatinine Increased           2                     2               0                       1               
 Edema                          0                     2               0                       0               
 Hypercholesteremia             0                     2               1                       0               
 Hyperglycemia                  0                     2               1                       0               
 SGOT Increased                 0                     0               3                       0               
 SGPT Increased                 0                     0               2                       0               
   MUSCULOSKELETAL SYSTEM         4                     0               3                       4             
 Arthralgia                     2                     0               0                       2               
 Arthrosis                      2                     0               0                       0               
 Myalgia                        2                     0               3                       1               
   NERVOUS SYSTEM                 2                     2               2                       5             
 Anxiety                        0                     2               0                       1               
 Dizziness                      0                     0               0                       4               
 Hypokinesia                    2                     0               0                       0               
   RESPIRATORY SYSTEM             8                     8               7                       6             
 Asthma                         2                     0               0                       0               
 Dyspnea                        2                     0               2                       0               
 Pharyngitis                    2                     8               2                       4               
 Pneumonia                      2                     0               0                       1               
 Rhinitis                       2                     2               2                       2               
 Sinusitis                      0                     0               2                       0               
   SKIN AND APPENDAGES            75                    86              86                      71            
 Acne                           0                     2               0                       1               
 Application Site Reaction      75                    71              84                      70              
     Acne                       0                     4               1                       0               
     Alopecia                   2                     0               1                       1               
     Contact Dermatitis         19                    4               33                      4               
     Dry Skin                   27                    12              25                      17              
     Edema                      4                     0               3                       0               
     Exfoliation                6                     4               24                      13              
     Hyperesthesia              0                     0               3                       1               
     Pain                       15                    22              26                      30              
     Paresthesia                8                     4               20                      20              
     Photosensitivity Reaction  0                     2               3                       0               
     Pruritus                   31                    59              52                      45              
     Rash                       35                    20              46                      17              
     Vesiculobullous Rash       0                     0               4                       1               
 Contact Dermatitis             2                     0               0                       0               
 Dry Skin                       0                     4               3                       0               
 Herpes Simplex                 0                     2               0                       0               
 Maculopapular Rash             0                     2               0                       0               
 Pain                           2                     2               1                       0               
 Pruritus                       4                     6               4                       1               
 Rash                           2                     10              4                       0               
 Skin Carcinoma                 0                     6               2                       2               
 Skin Nodule                    0                     2               0                       0               
 Skin Ulcer                     2                     0               1                       0               
   SPECIAL SENSES                 2                     0               4                       2             
 Conjunctivitis                 2                     0               4                       1               
 Eye Pain                       0                     2               2                       0               
   UROGENITAL SYSTEM              0                     0               4                       5             
 Hematuria                      0                     0               2                       1               
   OTHER                          0                     0               0                       3             
 Procedure                      0                     0               0                       3               
             Skin and Appendages Adverse Events Reported for Diclofenac Sodium Gel    at Less Than 1% Incidence in the Phase 3 Studies:  skin hypertrophy, paresthesia, seborrhea, urticaria, application site reactions (skin carcinoma, hypertonia, skin hypertrophy lacrimation disorder, maculopapular rash, purpuric rash, vasodilation).
 

   Adverse Reactions Reported for    Oral    Diclofenac Dosage Form (not topical Diclofenac Sodium Gel    ):  *Incidence greater than 1% marked with asterisk.



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain or cramps*, headache*, fluid retention*, abdominal distention*, malaise, swelling of lips and tongue, photosensitivity, anaphylaxis, anaphylactoid reactions, chest pain.



   Cardiovascular:  hypertension, congestive heart failure, palpitations, flushing, tachycardia, premature ventricular contractions, myocardial infarction, hypotension.



   Digestive:  diarrhea*, indigestion*, nausea*, constipation*, flatulence*, liver test abnormalities*, PUB*, i.e., peptic ulcer, with or without bleeding and/or perforation, or bleeding without ulcer, vomiting, jaundice, melena, esophageal lesions, aphthous stomatitis, dry mouth and mucous membranes, bloody diarrhea, hepatitis, hepatic necrosis, cirrhosis, hepatorenal syndrome, appetite change, pancreatitis with or without concomitant hepatitis, colitis, intestinal perforation.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  hemoglobin decrease, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, eosinophilia, hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, purpura, allergic purpura, bruising.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  azotemia, hypoglycemia, weight loss.



   Nervous System:  dizziness*, insomnia, drowsiness, depression, diplopia, anxiety, irritability, aseptic meningitis, convulsions, paresthesia, memory disturbance, nightmares, tremor, tic, abnormal coordination, disorientation, psychotic reaction.



   Respiratory:  epistaxis, asthma, laryngeal edema, dyspnea, hyperventilation, edema of pharynx.



   Skin and Appendages:  rash*, pruritus*, alopecia, urticaria, eczema, dermatitis, bullous eruption, erythema multiforme major, angioedema, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, excess perspiration, exfoliative dermatitis.



   Special Senses:  tinnitus*, blurred vision, taste disorder, reversible and irreversible hearing loss, scotoma, vitreous floaters, night blindness, amblyopia.



   Urogenital:  nephrotic syndrome, proteinuria, oliguria, interstitial nephritis, papillary necrosis, acute renal failure, urinary frequency, nocturia, hematuria, impotence, vaginal bleeding.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
