<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="differin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Dry skin of mild to moderate severity was the most frequently reported (&gt;= 1%) treatment related adverse vent. Erythema, scaling, dryness, burning/stinging were also seen during treatment.  (6)  



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Galderma Laboratories, L.P. at 1-866-735-4137 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 2141 subjects with acne vulgaris, 12 years and older, were treated once daily for 12 weeks. Of these, 1068 were exposed to DIFFERIN Lotion during the clinical trials. A total of 1057 subjects completed at least one post treatment evaluation.



 Related adverse reactions that were reported in at least 1% of patients treated with DIFFERIN Lotion or with the Vehicle Lotion are presented in  Table 1  .



 The majority of cases was transient, mild to moderate in severity and was managed with moisturizers.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials by At Least 1% of Patients 
 SystemTerm  Organ       Class/Preferred     Adapalene Lotion 0.1%  N = 1068         Vehicle Lotion  N = 1073          
  
   Subjects with Related AR(s)    10.2%       4.6%         
     Dry Skin  7.7%        3.0%         
     Skin Irriitation  1.5%        0.7%         
     Skin burning/skin discomfort  0.9%        0.0%         
     Sunburn  0.6%        0.6%         
      Local tolerability evaluations, presented in  Table 2  , were conducted at each study visit in clinical trials. Erythema, scaling, dryness, burning/stinging were assessed:
 

 Table 2: Incidence of Local Cutaneous Irritation, for Subjects Whose Irritation Score was Higher than at Baseline, in Controlled Clinical Studies Adverse Reactions (DIFFERIN Lotion Group N = 1057 ) 
 Combined Study 1and Study 2  Maximum SeverityDuring Treatment (N = 1057)  Week 12 Treatment Severity(N = 950)   
  
 Local CutaneousIrritation (skin irritation)  Mild             Moderate         Severe           Mild             Moderate         Severe            
 Erythema         21.8%            8.0%             0.2%             7.9%             2.6%             0.2%              
 Scaling          25.3%            6.5%             0.1%             5.3%             1.1%             0                 
 Dryness          36.1%            7.3%             0.3%             7.6%             2.0%             0                 
 Stinging/burning  22.1%            7.0%             0.9%             4.6%             1.0%             0.4%              
      Local tolerability scores for erythema, scaling, dryness, burning/stinging rose during the first two weeks of treatment and generally decreased thereafter.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    EXCERPT:   Ultraviolet Light and Environmental Exposure: Avoid exposure to sunlight and sunlamps. Wear sunscreen when sun exposure cannot be avoided.  (5.1)  .



  



 Erythema, scaling, dryness, and stinging/ burning may occur with use of DIFFERIN Lotion.  (5.2)  



 



   5.1 Ultraviolet Light and Environmental Exposure



  Exposure to sunlight, including sunlamps, should be avoided during the use of DIFFERIN Lotion. Patients with high levels of sun exposure and those with inherent sensitivity to sun should be warned to exercise caution. Use of sunscreen products and protective apparel (e.g. hat) are recommended when exposure cannot be avoided. Weather extremes, such as wind or cold, may be irritating to patients under treatment with DIFFERIN Lotion.



    5.2 Local Cutaneous Reactions



  Signs and symptoms of local skin irritation (such as erythema, scaling, dryness, stinging/burning) may be experienced with use of DIFFERIN Lotion. These are most likely to occur during the first 2 weeks of treatment, are mostly mild to moderate in severity, and usually lessen with continued use of DIFFERIN Lotion. Depending upon the severity of these side effects, patients should be instructed to use a moisturizer, reduce the frequency of the application of DIFFERIN Lotion 0.1%, or discontinue use.



 DIFFERIN Lotion should not be applied to cuts, abrasions, eczematous or sunburned skin. As with other retinoids, use of "waxing" as a depilatory method should be avoided on skin treated with DIFFERIN Lotion.



 Avoid concomitant use of other potentially irritating topical products (abrasive soaps and cleansers, soaps and cosmetics that have strong skin-drying effect and products with high concentrations of alcohol, astringents, spices, or limes).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
