<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dinoprostone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Dinoprostone Vaginal Insert is well tolerated. In placebo-controlled trials in which 658 women were entered and 320 received active therapy (218 without retrieval system, 102 with retrieval system), the following events were reported.



 Table 1 Total Dinoprostone Vaginal Insert - Treated Related Adverse Events 
                                          Controlled Studies             
                                                  Active                             Placebo                
 Uterine hyperstimulation with fetal distress                2.8%                               0.3%                  
 Uterine hyperstimulation without fetal distress                4.7%                                0%                   
 Fetal Distress without uterine hyperstimulation                3.8%                               1.2%                  
 N                                                  320                                338                  
                                               STUDY 101-801             
                                                  Active                             Placebo                
 Uterine hyperstimulation with fetal distress                2.9%                                0%                   
 Uterine hyperstimulation without fetal distress                2.0%                                0%                   
 Fetal Distress without uterine hyperstimulation                2.9%                               1.0%                  
 N                                                  102                                104                  
         Drug related fever, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and abdominal pain were noted in less than 1% of patients who received Dinoprostone Vaginal Insert.
 

 In study 101-801 (with the retrieval system) cases of hyperstimulation reversed within 2 to 13 minutes of removal of the product. Tocolytics were required in one of the five cases.



 In cases of fetal distress, when product removal was thought advisable there was a return to normal rhythm and no neonatal sequelae.



 Five minute Apgar scores were 7 or above in 98.2% (646/658) of studied neonates whose mothers received Dinoprostone Vaginal Insert. In a report of a 3 year pediatric follow-up study in 121 infants, 51 of whose mothers received Dinoprostone Vaginal Insert, there were no deleterious effects on physical examination or psychomotor evaluation (18).



   Post-marketing surveillance

  Immune System Disorders: Hypersensitivity



 Blood and lymphatic system disorders: Disseminated Intravascular Coagulation (See    Warnings    Section)



 Reproductive system: Reports of uterine rupture have been reported in association with use of Dinoprostone Vaginal Insert some required a hysterectomy and some resulted in subsequent fetal or neonatal death.



 Vascular Disorders: Hypotension



 Pregnancy, Puerperium and Perinatal Conditions: Amniotic fluid embolism
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
