<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="diovan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are headache, dizziness, viral infection, fatigue and abdominal pain ( )  Hypertension:    6.1  



 Most common adverse reactions are dizziness, hypotension, diarrhea, arthralgia, back pain, fatigue and hyperkalemia ( )  Heart Failure:    6.1  



 Most common adverse reactions which caused patients to discontinue therapy are hypotension, cough and increased blood creatinine ( )   Post-Myocardial Infarction:    6.1  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or .  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1     Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adult    Hypertension  



 Diovan (valsartan) has been evaluated for safety in more than 4,000 patients, including over 400 treated for over 6 months, and more than 160 for over 1 year. Adverse reactions have generally been mild and transient in nature and have only infrequently required discontinuation of therapy. The overall incidence of adverse reactions with Diovan was similar to placebo.



 The overall frequency of adverse reactions was neither dose-related nor related to gender, age, race, or regimen. Discontinuation of therapy due to side effects was required in 2.3% of valsartan patients and 2.0% of placebo patients. The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy with Diovan were headache and dizziness.



 The adverse reactions that occurred in placebo-controlled clinical trials in at least 1% of patients treated with Diovan and at a higher incidence in valsartan (n=2,316) than placebo (n=888) patients included viral infection (3% vs. 2%), fatigue (2% vs. 1%), and abdominal pain (2% vs. 1%).



 Headache, dizziness, upper respiratory infection, cough, diarrhea, rhinitis, sinusitis, nausea, pharyngitis, edema, and arthralgia occurred at a more than 1% rate but at about the same incidence in placebo and valsartan patients.



 In trials in which valsartan was compared to an ACE inhibitor with or without placebo, the incidence of dry cough was significantly greater in the ACE-inhibitor group (7.9%) than in the groups who received valsartan (2.6%) or placebo (1.5%). In a 129-patient trial limited to patients who had had dry cough when they had previously received ACE inhibitors, the incidences of cough in patients who received valsartan, HCTZ, or lisinopril were 20%, 19%, and 69% respectively (p &lt;0.001).



 Dose-related orthostatic effects were seen in less than 1% of patients. An increase in the incidence of dizziness was observed in patients treated with Diovan 320 mg (8%) compared to 10 to 160 mg (2% to 4%).



 Diovan has been used concomitantly with hydrochlorothiazide without evidence of clinically important adverse interactions.



 Other adverse reactions that occurred in controlled clinical trials of patients treated with Diovan (&gt;0.2% of valsartan patients) are listed below. It cannot be determined whether these events were causally related to Diovan.



 Allergic reaction and asthenia  Body as a Whole:  



 Palpitations  Cardiovascular:  



 Pruritus and rash  Dermatologic:  



 Constipation, dry mouth, dyspepsia, and flatulence  Digestive:  



 Back pain, muscle cramps, and myalgia  Musculoskeletal:  



 Anxiety, insomnia, paresthesia, and somnolence  Neurologic and Psychiatric:  



 Dyspnea  Respiratory:  



 Vertigo  Special Senses:  



 Impotence  Urogenital:  



 Other reported events seen less frequently in clinical trials included chest pain, syncope, anorexia, vomiting, and angioedema.



   Pediatric Hypertension  



 Diovan has been evaluated for safety in over 400 pediatric patients aged 6 to 17 years and more than 160 pediatric patients aged 6 months to 5 years. No relevant differences were identified between the adverse experience profile for pediatric patients aged 6 to 16 years and that previously reported for adult patients. Headache and hyperkalemia were the most common adverse events suspected to be study drug-related in older children (6 to 17 years old) and younger children (6 months to 5 years old), respectively. Hyperkalemia was mainly observed in children with underlying renal disease. Neurocognitive and developmental assessment of pediatric patients aged 6 to 16 years revealed no overall clinically relevant adverse impact after treatment with Diovan for up to 1 year.



 Diovan is not recommended for pediatric patients under 6 years of age. In a study (n=90) of pediatric patients (1 to 5 years), two deaths and three cases of on-treatment transaminase elevations were seen in the one-year open-label extension phase. These 5 events occurred in a study population in which patients frequently had significant co-morbidities. A causal relationship to Diovan has not been established. In a second study in which 75 children aged 1 to 6 years were randomized, no deaths and one case of marked liver transaminase elevations occurred during a 1 year open-label extension.



   Heart Failure  



 The adverse experience profile of Diovan in heart failure patients was consistent with the pharmacology of the drug and the health status of the patients. In the Valsartan Heart Failure Trial, comparing valsartan in total daily doses up to 320 mg (n=2,506) to placebo (n=2,494), 10% of valsartan patients discontinued for adverse reactions vs. 7% of placebo patients.



 The table shows adverse reactions in double-blind short-term heart failure trials, including the first 4 months of the Valsartan Heart Failure Trial, with an incidence of at least 2% that were more frequent in valsartan-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients. All patients received standard drug therapy for heart failure, frequently as multiple medications, which could include diuretics, digitalis, beta-blockers. About 93% of patients received concomitant ACE inhibitors.




                    Valsartan (n=3,282)      Placebo (n=2,740)     
 Dizziness        17%              9%                
 Hypotension      7%               2%                
 Diarrhea         5%               4%                
 Arthralgia       3%               2%                
 Fatigue          3%               2%                
 Back Pain        3%               2%                
 Dizziness, postural  2%               1%                
 Hyperkalemia     2%               1%                
 Hypotension, postural  2%               1%                
         Discontinuations occurred in 0.5% of valsartan-treated patients and 0.1% of placebo patients for each of the following: elevations in creatinine and elevations in potassium.
 

 Other adverse reactions with an incidence greater than 1% and greater than placebo included headache NOS, nausea, renal impairment NOS, syncope, blurred vision, upper abdominal pain and vertigo. (NOS = not otherwise specified).



 From the long-term data in the Valsartan Heart Failure Trial, there did not appear to be any significant adverse reactions not previously identified.



   Post-Myocardial Infarction  



 The safety profile of Diovan was consistent with the pharmacology of the drug and the background diseases, cardiovascular risk factors, and clinical course of patients treated in the post-myocardial infarction setting. The table shows the percentage of patients discontinued in the valsartan and captopril-treated groups in the Valsartan in Acute Myocardial Infarction Trial (VALIANT) with a rate of at least 0.5% in either of the treatment groups.



 Discontinuations due to renal dysfunction occurred in 1.1% of valsartan-treated patients and 0.8% of captopril-treated patients.




                    Valsartan (n=4,885)      Captopril (n=4,879)     
 Discontinuation for adverse reaction  5.8%             7.7%              
 Adverse reactions                                     
       Hypotension NOS  1.4%             0.8%              
       Cough      0.6%             2.5%              
       Blood creatinine increased  0.6%             0.4%              
       Rash NOS   0.2%             0.6%              
           6.2     Postmarketing Experience
   The following additional adverse reactions have been reported in postmarketing experience:



 There are rare reports of angioedema. Some of these patients previously experienced angioedema with other drugs including ACE inhibitors. Diovan should not be re-administered to patients who have had angioedema.  Hypersensitivity:  



 Elevated liver enzymes and very rare reports of hepatitis  Digestive:  



 Impaired renal function, renal failure  Renal:  



 Hyperkalemia  Clinical Laboratory Tests:  



 Alopecia, bullous dermatitis  Dermatologic:  



 There are very rare reports of thrombocytopenia  Blood and Lymphatic:  



 Vasculitis  Vascular:  



 Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Diovan as soon as possible. (5.1) 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. (5.1) 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Diovan as soon as possible. ( ) 5.1 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. ( ) 5.1 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension ( )  5.2   
 *  Monitor renal function and potassium in susceptible patients ( , )  5.3    5.4   
    
 

   5.1     Fetal Toxicity



   Pregnancy Category D  



 Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Diovan as soon as possible . [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  



    5.2     Hypotension



  Excessive hypotension was rarely seen (0.1%) in patients with uncomplicated hypertension treated with Diovan alone. In patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- and/or salt-depleted patients receiving high doses of diuretics, symptomatic hypotension may occur. This condition should be corrected prior to administration of Diovan, or the treatment should start under close medical supervision.



 Caution should be observed when initiating therapy in patients with heart failure or post-myocardial infarction patients. Patients with heart failure or post-myocardial infarction patients given Diovan commonly have some reduction in blood pressure, but discontinuation of therapy because of continuing symptomatic hypotension usually is not necessary when dosing instructions are followed. In controlled trials in heart failure patients, the incidence of hypotension in valsartan-treated patients was 5.5% compared to 1.8% in placebo-treated patients. In the Valsartan in Acute Myocardial Infarction Trial (VALIANT), hypotension in post-myocardial infarction patients led to permanent discontinuation of therapy in 1.4% of valsartan-treated patients and 0.8% of captopril-treated patients.



 If excessive hypotension occurs, the patient should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.



    5.3     Impaired Renal Function



  Changes in renal function including acute renal failure can be caused by drugs that inhibit the renin-angiotensin system and by diuretics. Patients whose renal function may depend in part on the activity of the renin-angiotensin system (e.g., patients with renal artery stenosis, chronic kidney disease, severe congestive heart failure, or volume depletion) may be at particular risk of developing acute renal failure on Diovan. Monitor renal function periodically in these patients. Consider withholding or discontinuing therapy in patients who develop a clinically significant decrease in renal function on Diovan . [see Drug Interactions (7)]  



    5.4     Hyperkalemia



  Some patients with heart failure have developed increases in potassium. These effects are usually minor and transient, and they are more likely to occur in patients with pre-existing renal impairment. Dosage reduction and/or discontinuation of Diovan may be required . [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
