<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dipentum" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Olsalazine has been evaluated in ulcerative colitis patients in remission, as well as those with acute disease. Both sulfasalazine-tolerant and intolerant patients have been studied in controlled clinical trials. Overall, 10.4% of patients discontinued olsalazine because of an adverse experience compared with 6.7% of placebo patients. The most commonly reported adverse reactions leading to treatment withdrawal were diarrhea or loose stools (olsalazine 5.9%; placebo 4.8%), abdominal pain, and rash or itching (slightly more than 1% of patients receiving olsalazine). Other adverse reactions to olsalazine leading to withdrawal occurred in fewer than 1% of patients ( ).  Table 1  



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Resulting In Withdrawal From Controlled Studies Total 
                                                Olsalazine (N = 441)             Placebo (N = 208)          
  
 Diarrhea/Loose Stools                              26 (5.9%)                        10 (4.8 %)             
 Nausea                                            3                               2                        
 Abdominal Pain                                       5 (1.1%)                     0                        
 Rash/Itching                                         5 (1.1%)                     0                        
 Headache                                          3                               0                        
 Heartburn                                         2                               0                        
 Rectal Bleeding                                   1                               0                        
 Insomnia                                          1                               0                        
 Dizziness                                         1                               0                        
 Anorexia                                          1                               0                        
 Light Headedness                                  1                               0                        
 Depression                                        1                               0                        
 Miscellaneous                                        4 (0.9%)                        3 (1.4%)              
 Total Number of Patients Withdrawn                  46 (10.4%)                      14 (6.7 %)             
         For those controlled studies, the comparative incidences of adverse reactions reported in 1% or more patients treated with olsalazine or placebo are provided in Table 2.
 

 Table 2 Comparative Incidence (%) of Adverse Effects Reported By One Percent Or More of Ulcerative Colitis Patients Treated With Olsalazine Or Placebo in Double Blind Controlled Studies 
 Adverse Event                                        Olsalazine (N = 441) %       Placebo (N = 208) %      
  
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                         
 Diarrhea                                                      11.1                        6.7              
 Abdominal Pain/Cramps                                         10.1                        7.2              
 Nausea                                                         5.0                        3.9              
 Dyspepsia                                                      4.0                        4.3              
 Bloating                                                       1.5                        1.4              
 Vomiting                                                       1.0                         -               
 Stomatitis                                                     1.0                         -               
 Increased Blood in Stool                                        -                         3.4              
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                 
 Anorexia                                                       1.3                        1.9              
   Nervous System Disorders                           
 Headache                                                       5.0                        4.8              
 Insomnia                                                        -                         2.4              
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions     
 Fatigue/Drowsiness/Lethargy                                    1.8                        2.9              
   Psychiatric Disorders                              
 Depression                                                     1.5                         -               
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                        
 Vertigo/Dizziness                                              1.0                         -               
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders             
 Rash                                                           2.3                        1.4              
 Itching                                                        1.3                         -               
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
 Arthralgia/Joint Pain                                          4.0                        2.9              
   Infections and Infestations                        
 Upper Respiratory Infection                                    1.5                         -               
         Over 2,500 patients have been treated with olsalazine in various controlled and uncontrolled clinical studies. In these as well as in post-marketing experience, olsalazine was administered mainly to patients intolerant to sulfasalazine. There have been rare reports of the following adverse effects in patients receiving olsalazine. These were often difficult to distinguish from possible symptoms of the underlying disease or from the effects of prior and/or concomitant therapy. A causal relationship to the drug has not been demonstrated for some of these reactions.
 

 Anemia, Eosinophilia, Hemolytic anemia, Interstitial pulmonary disease, Leukopenia, Lymphopenia, Neutropenia, Reticulocytosis, Thrombocytopenia  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  



 Chest pains, Heart block second degree, Myocarditis, Palpitations, Pericarditis, Peripheral edema, Shortness of breath, Tachycardia  Cardiac Disorders:  



 A patient who developed thyroid disease 9 days after starting DIPENTUM was given propranolol and radioactive iodine and subsequently developed shortness of breath and nausea. The patient died 5 days later with signs and symptoms of acute diffuse myocarditis.



 Tinnitus  Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  



 Dry eyes, Vision blurred, Watery eyes  Eye Disorders:  



 Abdominal pain (upper), Diarrhea with dehydration, Dry mouth, Epigastric discomfort, Flare in symptoms, Flatulence, Increased blood in stool, Pancreatitis, Rectal bleeding, Rectal discomfort  Gastrointestinal Disorders:  



 In a double-blind, placebo-controlled study, increased frequency and severity of diarrhea were reported in patients randomized to olsalazine 500 mg B.I.D. with concomitant pelvic radiation.



 Rare cases of granulomatous hepatitis and nonspecific, reactive hepatitis have been reported in patients receiving olsalazine. Additionally, a patient developed mild cholestatic hepatitis during treatment with sulfasalazine and experienced the same symptoms two weeks later after the treatment was changed to olsalazine. Withdrawal of olsalazine led to complete recovery in these cases.



 Fever chills, Hot flashes, Irritability, Rigors  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  



 Bronchospasm, Erythema nodosum  Immune System Disorders:  



 ALT (SGPT) or AST (SGOT) elevated beyond the normal range.  Laboratory:  



 Muscle cramps  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  



 Insomnia, Paraesthesia, Tremors  Nervous System Disorders:  



 Mood swings  Psychiatric Disorders:  



 Dysuria, Hematuria, Interstitial nephritis, Nephrotic syndrome, Proteinuria, Urinary frequency  Renal and Urinary Disorders:  



 Impotence, Menorrhagia  Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  



 Alopecia, Erythema, Photosensitivity reaction  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  



 Hypertension, Orthostatic hypotension  Vascular Disorders:  



   Postmarketing

  The following events have been identified during post-approval use of products that contain (or are metabolized to) mesalamine in clinical practice. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to mesalamine:



 Aplastic anemia, Pancytopenia  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  



 Pyrexia  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  



 Hepatic enzyme increased, Hepatitis, Increased bilirubin  Hepatobiliary Disorders:  



 Reports of hepatotoxicity, including elevated liver function tests (SGOT/AST, SGPT/ALT, GGT, LDH, alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin), jaundice, cholestatic jaundice, cirrhosis, and possible hepatocellular damage including liver necrosis and liver failure. Some of these cases were fatal. One case of Kawasaki-like syndrome, which included hepatic function changes, was also reported.



 Myalgia  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  



 Dyspnoea, Interstitial lung disease  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  



 Angioneurotic oedema  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  



 Paraesthesia, Peripheral neuropathy  Nervous System Disorders:  



 Interstitial nephritis  Renal and Urinary Disorders:  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
