<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="diphtheria" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) were crying, fever, and loss of appetite.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) were crying, fever, and loss of appetite. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sanofi Pasteur Inc., at 1-800-822-2463 (1-800-VACCINE) or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 and http://vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to vaccine use and for approximating rates of those events.



 In a clinical trial in Baltimore, 163 infants received Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed at 2, 4 and 6 months of age. The results of this trial are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1: Percentage of Children Experiencing Local and Systemic Reactions at 24 Hours Following Immunization 
 Reaction                                    BALTIMORE(N=163)     
 Dose 1(%)(n = 155)                         Dose 2(%)(n = 145)    Dose 3(%)(n = 136)    
  
   Systemic Reactions                       
 Fever &gt;=38 degrees C &lt;39 degrees C (&gt;=100.4 degrees F &lt;102.2 degrees F)          0.7                   0.8                   6.6            
 Fever &gt;=39 degrees C (&gt;=102.2 degrees F )           0                     0                     0             
 Crying                                            13.6                  15.2                  13.0           
 Loss of Appetite                                  3.9                   6.2                   2.9            
   Injection Site Reactions                 
 Redness &gt;=2.5 cm                                  0.7                    0                    3.6            
 Slight Pain                                       2.6                   2.8                   2.2            
 Moderate Pain                                     0.7                   1.4                    0             
 Hardness &gt;=2.5 cm                                 1.3                   1.4                   3.6            
          Two clinical trials were conducted in Canada. In the first clinical trial, 52 children aged 17-22 months who had previously received 3 doses of whole-cell DTP Adsorbed vaccine (not licensed in US), received Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed with either an acellular pertussis (n = 25) or a whole cell pertussis (n = 27) vaccine (neither licensed in US) given concurrently but at a separate site. The only reported local reaction was slight pain at the Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed injection site in 11% of children.
 

 In a second clinical trial conducted in Canada, 99 children aged 4 to 6 years old who were eligible for the preschool (fifth) dose of DTP received Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed in one arm and a whole-cell Monovalent Pertussis vaccine (not licensed in US) in the other. The following local reactions at the Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed injection site were reported: redness &gt;=50 mm - 9%, swelling &gt;50 mm - 51%, tenderness, moderate or severe - 17%, arm mobility "too sore to move" - 9%. (2)



 Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed evaluated in clinical trials contained thimerosal.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during the postmarketing use of a Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur Limited that contained thimerosal. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure.



 The following adverse events were included based on severity, frequency of reporting or the strength of causal association with Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed:



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders  



 *     Lymphadenopathy 
      Gastrointestinal disorders  
 

 *     Nausea 
      General disorders and administration site conditions  
 

 *     Injection site inflammation 
 *     Injection site hypersensitivity 
 *     Pain 
      Nervous system disorders  
 

 *     Convulsion 
 *     Somnolence 
 *     Syncope 
 *     Headache 
      Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  
 

 *     Rash 
 *     Urticaria 
      Vascular disorders  
 

 *     Pallor 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk for Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed vaccine. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Syncope (fainting) has been reported following vaccination with Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed vaccine. Procedures should be in place to prevent falling injury and manage syncopal reactions. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Acute Allergic Reactions



  Epinephrine Injection (1:1000) and other appropriate agents and equipment must be available for immediate use in case an anaphylactic or acute hypersensitivity reaction occurs.



    5.2 Guillain-Barre Syndrome and Brachial Neuritis



  A review by the Institute of Medicine (IOM) found evidence for a causal relation between tetanus toxoid and both brachial neuritis and Guillain-Barre syndrome. (1) If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk for Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed vaccine.



    5.3 Limitation of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed may not protect all individuals.



    5.4 Altered Immunocompetence



  If Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed vaccine is administered to immunocompromised persons, including persons receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained. [See   Immunosuppressive Treatments (7.3)    .]



    5.5 Apnea in Premature Infants



   Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination.  



    5.6 Syncope



   Syncope (fainting) has been reported following vaccination with Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids Adsorbed vaccine. Procedures should be in place to prevent falling injury and manage syncopal reactions.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
