<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="diprivan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    Adverse Reactions

  Adverse event information is derived from controlled clinical trials and worldwide marketing experience.  In the description below, rates of the more common events represent US/Canadian clinical study results.  Less frequent events are also derived from publications and marketing experience in over 8 million patients; there are insufficient data to support an accurate estimate of their incidence rates.  These studies were conducted using a variety of premedicants, varying lengths of surgical/diagnostic procedures, and various other anesthetic/sedative agents.  Most adverse events were mild and transient.



            Anesthesia and MAC Sedation in Adults The following estimates of adverse events for DIPRIVAN Injectable Emulsion include data from clinical trials in general anesthesia/MAC sedation (N=2889 adult patients).  The adverse events listed below as probably causally related are those events in which the actual incidence rate in patients treated with DIPRIVAN Injectable Emulsion was greater than the comparator incidence rate in these trials.  Therefore, incidence rates for anesthesia and MAC sedation in adults generally represent estimates of the percentage of clinical trial patients which appeared to have probable causal relationship.



 The adverse experience profile from reports of 150 patients in the MAC sedation clinical trials is similar to the profile established with DIPRIVAN Injectable Emulsion during anesthesia (see below).  During MAC sedation clinical trials, significant respiratory events included cough, upper airway obstruction, apnea, hypoventilation, and dyspnea.



            Anesthesia in Pediatric Patients Generally the adverse experience profile from reports of 506 DIPRIVAN Injectable Emulsion pediatric patients from 6 days through 16 years of age in the US/Canadian anesthesia clinical trials is similar to the profile established with DIPRIVAN Injectable Emulsion during anesthesia in adults (see Pediatric percentages [Peds %] below).  Although not reported as an adverse event in clinical trials, apnea is frequently observed in pediatric patients.



            ICU Sedation in Adults The following estimates of adverse events include data from clinical trials in ICU sedation (N=159 adult patients).  Probably related incidence rates for ICU sedation were determined by individual case report form review.  Probable causality was based upon an apparent dose response relationship and/or positive responses to rechallenge.  In many instances the presence of concomitant disease and concomitant therapy made the causal relationship unknown.  Therefore, incidence rates for ICU sedation generally represent estimates of the percentage of clinical trial patients which appeared to have a probable causal relationship.



     Incidence greater than 1% - Probably Causally Related    




                            Anesthesia/MAC Sedation    ICU Sedations               
 Cardiovascular             BradycardiaArrhythmia (Peds: 1.2%)Tachycardia Nodal (Peds: 1.6%)Hypotension* (Peds: 17%)(see also CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGYHypertension (Peds: 8%)  Bradycardia                 
 Central Nervous System     Movement* (Peds:17%)                                   
 Injection Site             Burning/Stinging or Pain,17.6% (Peds: 10%)                              
 Metabolic/Nutritional                                 Hyperlipemia*               
 Respiratory                Apnea(see also CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY  Respiratory Acidosis DuringWeaning*   
 Skin and Appendages        Rash (Peds: 5%)Pruritus (Peds: 2%)                              
      Events without an * or % had an icidence of 1% to 3%
 

 *Incidence of events 3% to 10%



     Incidence less than 1% - Probably Causally Related    




                            A  nesthesia/Mac Sedation      ICU Sedation              
 Body as a Whole            Anaphylaxis/Anaphylactoid ReactionPerinatal Disorder(Tachycardia)(Bigeminy)(Bradycardia)(Premature Ventricular Contractions)(Hemorrhage)(ECG Abnormal)(Arrhythmia Atrial)(Fever)(Extremities Pain)(Anticholinergic Syndrome)                              
 Cardiovascular             Premature Atrial ContractionsSyncope                              
 Central Nervous System     Hypertonia/Dystonia, Pareshesia  Agitation                   
 Digestive                  (Hypersalivation)(Nausea)                              
 Hemic/Lymphatic            (Leukocytosis)                                         
 Injection Site             (Plebitis)(Pruritus)                                   
 Metabolic                  (Hypomagnesemia)                                       
 Musculoskeletal            Myalgia                                                
 Nervous                    (Dizziness)(Agitation)(Chills)(Somnolence)(Delirium)                              
 Respiratory                Wheezing(Cough)(Laryngospasm)(Hypoxia)  Decreased Lung Function     
 Skin and Appendages        Flushing, Pruritus                                     
 Special Senses             Amblyopia(Vision Abnormal)                              
 Urogenital                 Cloudy Urine               Green Urine                 
      
 

     Incidence less than 1% - Causal Relationship Unknown    



         




                            Anesthesia/MAC Sedation    ICU Sedation                
 Body as a Whole            Asthenia, Awareness, Chest Pain,Extremities Pain, Fever, IncreasedDrug Effect, Neck Rigidity/Stiffness,Trunk Pain  Fever, Sepsis, Trunk Pain, Whole Body Weakness   
 Cardiovascular             Arrhythmia, Atrial Fibrillation,Atrioventricular Heart Block,Bigeminy, Bleeding, Bundle BranchBlock, Cardiac Arrest, ECG Abnormal,Edema, Extrasystole, Heart Block,Hypertension, MyocardialInfarction, Myocardial Ischemia,Premature Ventricular Contractions,ST Segment Depression,Supraventricular Tachycardia,Tachycardia, Ventricular Fibrillation  Arrythmia, Atrial Fibrillation, Bigeminy, CardiacArrest, Extrasystole, Right Heart Failure, VentricularTachycardia   
 Central Nervous System     Abnormal Dreams, Agitation,Amorous Behavior, Anxiety,Bucking/Jerking/Thrashing,Chills/Shivering/Clonic/MyoclonicMovement, Combativeness,Confusion, Delirium, Depression,Dizziness, Emotional Lability,Euphoria, Fatigue, Hallucinations,Headache, Hypotonia, Hysteria,Insomnia, Moaning, Neuropathy,Opisthotonos, Rigidity, Seizures,Somnolence, Tremor, Twitching  Chills/Shivering, Intracranial Hypertension,Seizures, Somnolence, Thinking Abnormal   
 Digestive                  Cramping, Diarrhea, Dry Mouth,Enlarged Parotic, Nausea, Swallowing,Vomiting  Ileus, Liver Function Abnormal   
 Hematologic/Lymphatic      Coagulation Disorder, Leukocytosis                              
 Injection Site             Hives/Itching, Phlebitis,Redness/Discoloration                              
 Metabolic/Nutritional      Hyperkalemia, Hyperlipemia  BUN Increased, Creatinine Increased, Dehydration,Hyperglycemia, Metabolic Acidosis, OsmolalityIncreased   
 Respiratory                Bronchospasm, Burning in Throat,Cough, Dyspnea, Hiccough,Hyperventilation, Hypoventilation,Hypoxia, Laryngospasm, Pharyngitis,Sneezing, Tachypnea, Upper AirwayObstruction  Hypoxia                     
 Skin and Appendages        Conjunctival Hyperemia, Diaphoresis, Urticaria  Rash                        
 Special Senses             Diplopia, Ear Pain, Eye Pain,Nystagmus, Taste Perversion,Tinnitus                              
 Urogenital                 Oliguria, Urine Retention  Kidney Failure              
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
