<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ditropan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse Events with DITROPAN XL  (r)  

  The safety and efficacy of DITROPAN XL  (r)  (oxybutynin chloride) were evaluated in a total of 580 participants who received DITROPAN XL  (r)  in 4 clinical trials (429 patients) and four pharmacokinetic studies (151 healthy volunteers). The 429 patients were treated with 5-30 mg/day for up to 4.5 months. Three of the 4 clinical trials allowed dose adjustments based on efficacy and adverse events and one was a fixed-dose escalation design. Safety information is provided for 429 patients from these three controlled clinical studies and one open-label study in the first column of Table 3 below.



 Adverse events from two additional fixed-dose, active-controlled, 12-week treatment duration, postmarketing studies, in which 576 patients were treated with DITROPAN XL  (r)  10 mg/day, are also listed in Table 3 (second column). The adverse events are reported regardless of causality.



 Table 3 Incidence (%) of Adverse Events Reported by &gt;= 5% of Patients Using DITROPAN XL(r) (5-30 mg/day) and % of Corresponding Adverse Events in Two Fixed-Dose (10 mg/day) Studies 
                                                          DITROPAN XL  (r)           DITROPAN XL  (r)         
 Body System                Adverse Event                 5-30 mg/day(n=429)          10 mg/day(n=576)        
  
 General                    headache                              10                          6               
                            asthenia                               7                          3               
                            pain                                   7                          4               
 Digestive                  dry mouth                             61                         29               
                            constipation                          13                          7               
                            diarrhea                               9                          7               
                            nausea                                 9                          2               
                            dyspepsia                              7                          5               
 Nervous                    somnolence                            12                          2               
                            dizziness                              6                          4               
 Respiratory                rhinitis                               6                          2               
 Special senses             blurred vision                         8                          1               
                            dry eyes                               6                          3               
 Urogenital                 urinary tract infection                5                          5               
          The most common adverse events reported by the 429 patients receiving 5-30 mg/day DITROPAN XL  (r)  were the expected side effects of anticholinergic agents. The incidence of dry mouth was dose-related.
 

 The discontinuation rate for all adverse events was 6.8% in the 429 patients from the 4 studies of efficacy and safety who received 5-30 mg/day. The most frequent adverse event causing early discontinuation of study medication was nausea (1.9%), while discontinuation due to dry mouth was 1.2%.



 In addition, the following adverse events were reported by &gt;= 1 to &lt; 5% of all patients who received DITROPAN XL  (r)  in the 6 adjustable and fixed-dose efficacy and safety studies.  Infections and infestations:  nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, sinusitis, bronchitis, cystitis;  Psychiatric disorders:  insomnia, depression, nervousness, confusional state;  Nervous System Disorders:  dysgeusia;  Cardiac disorders:  palpitations;  Vascular disorders:  hypertension;  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  nasal dryness, cough, pharyngolaryngeal pain, dry throat;  Gastrointestinal Disorders:  gastroesophageal reflux disease, abdominal pain, loose stools, flatulence, vomiting;  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  dry skin, pruritis;  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  back pain, arthralgia, pain in extremity;  Renal and urinary disorders:  urinary retention, urinary hesitation, dysuria;  General disorders and administration site conditions:  fatigue, edema peripheral, asthenia, chest pain;  Investigations:  blood pressure increased.



   Postmarketing Surveillance

  Because postmarketing reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The following additional adverse drug reactions have been reported from worldwide postmarketing experience with DITROPAN XL  (r)  :  Psychiatric Disorders:  psychotic disorder, agitation, hallucinations, memory impairment;  Nervous System Disorders:  convulsions;  Eye Disorders:  glaucoma;  Cardiac Disorders:  arrhythmia, tachycardia, QT interval prolongation;  Vascular Disorders:  flushing;  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  rash;  Renal and Urinary Disorders:  impotence;  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema with airway obstruction, urticaria, and face edema; rare anaphylactic reactions requiring hospitalization for emergency treatment;  Injury, poisoning and procedural complications:  fall.



 Additional adverse events reported with some other oxybutynin chloride formulations include: cycloplegia, mydriasis, and suppression of lactation.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
