<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="divalproex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 Hepatic failure  (5.1)  



 Birth defects  (5.2)  



 Decreased IQ following  in utero  exposure  (5.3)  



 Pancreatitis  (5.5)  



 Thrombocytopenia  (5.9)  



 Hyperammonemic encephalopathy  (5.6  ,  5.10  ,  5.11)  



 Multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions  (5.13)  



 Somnolence in the elderly  (5.15)  



 Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Information on pediatric adverse reactions is presented in section 8.



    EXCERPT:    *  Most common adverse reactions (reported &gt;5%) reported in adult studies are nausea, somnolence, dizziness, vomiting, asthenia, abdominal pain, dyspepsia, rash, diarrhea, increased appetite, tremor, weight gain, back pain, alopecia, headache, fever, anorexia, constipation, diplopia, amblyopia/blurred, ataxia, nystagmus, emotional lability, thinking abnormal, amnesia, flu syndrome, infection, bronchitis, rhinitis, ecchymosis, peripheral edema, insomnia, nervousness, depression, pharyngitis, dyspnea, tinnitus  (6.1  ,  6.2  ,  6.3  ,  6.4)  . 
 *  The safety and tolerability of valproate in pediatric patients were shown to be comparable to those in adults  (8.4)  . 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Zydus Pharmaceuticals USA Inc. at 1-877-993-8779 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Mania

  The incidence of treatment-emergent events has been ascertained based on combined data from two three week placebo-controlled clinical trials of divalproex sodium extended-release tablets in the treatment of manic episodes associated with bipolar disorder.



   Table 3  summarizes those adverse reactions reported for patients in these trials where the incidence rate in the divalproex sodium extended-release tablets-treated group was greater than 5% and greater than the placebo incidence.




   Table 3. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt; 5% of Divalproex Sodium Extended-Release Tablets-Treated Patients During Placebo-Controlled Trials of Acute Mania    1     
   Adverse Event      Divalproex Sodium Extended-Release Tablets(n=338)      Placebo(n=263)     
 Somnolence       26%              14%               
 Dyspepsia        23%              11%               
 Nausea           19%              13%               
 Vomiting         13%              5%                
 Diarrhea         12%              8%                
 Dizziness        12%              7%                
 Pain             11%              10%               
 Abdominal pain   10%              5%                
 Accidental injury  6%               5%                
 Asthenia         6%               5%                
 Pharyngitis      6%               5%                
 1. The following adverse reactions/event occurred at an equal or greater incidence for placebo than for divalproex sodium extended-release tablets: headache   
      The following additional adverse reactions were reported by greater than 1% of the divalproex sodium extended-release tablets-treated patients in controlled clinical trials:
 

   Body as a Whole:  Back Pain, Chills, Chills and Fever, Drug Level Increased, Flu Syndrome, Infection, Infection Fungal, Neck Rigidity.



   Cardiovascular System:  Arrhythmia, Hypertension, Hypotension, Postural Hypotension.



   Digestive System:  Constipation, Dry Mouth, Dysphagia, Fecal Incontinence, Flatulence, Gastroenteritis, Glossitis, Gum Hemorrhage, Mouth Ulceration.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System:  Anemia, Bleeding Time Increased, Ecchymosis, Leucopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  Hypoproteinemia, Peripheral Edema.



   Musculoskeletal System:  Arthrosis, Myalgia.



   Nervous System:  Abnormal Gait, Agitation, Catatonic Reaction, Dysarthria, Hallucinations, Hypertonia, Hypokinesia, Psychosis, Reflexes Increased, Sleep Disorder, Tardive Dyskinesia, Tremor.



   Respiratory System:  Hiccup, Rhinitis.



   Skin and Appendages:  Discoid Lupus Erythematosus, Erythema Nodosum, Furunculosis, Maculopapular Rash, Pruritus, Rash, Seborrhea, Sweating, Vesiculobullous Rash.



   Special Senses:  Conjunctivitis, Dry Eyes, Eye Disorder, Eye Pain, Photophobia, Taste Perversion.



   Urogenital System:  Cystitis, Urinary Tract Infection, Menstrual Disorder, Vaginitis.



   6.2 Epilepsy

  Based on a placebo-controlled trial of adjunctive therapy for treatment of complex partial seizures, divalproex sodium tablets was generally well tolerated with most adverse reactions rated as mild to moderate in severity. Intolerance was the primary reason for discontinuation in the divalproex sodium tablets-treated patients (6%), compared to 1% of placebo-treated patients.



   Table 4  lists treatment-emergent adverse reactions which were reported by &gt;= 5% of divalproex sodium tablets-treated patients and for which the incidence was greater than in the placebo group, in the placebo-controlled trial of adjunctive therapy for treatment of complex partial seizures. Since patients were also treated with other antiepilepsy drugs, it is not possible, in most cases, to determine whether the following adverse reactions can be ascribed to divalproex sodium tablets alone, or the combination of divalproex sodium tablets and other antiepilepsy drugs.




   Table 4. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;= 5% of Patients Treated with Valproate During Placebo-Controlled Trial of Adjunctive Therapy for Complex Partial Seizures     
   Body System/Event                                Divalproex Sodium Tablets (%)(N=77)      Placebo (%)(N=70)     
   Body as a Whole                                 
      Headache                                    31                             21                     
      Asthenia                                    27                             7                      
      Fever                                       6                              4                      
   Gastrointestinal System                         
      Nausea                                      48                             14                     
      Vomiting                                    27                             7                      
      Abdominal pain                              23                             6                      
      Diarrhea                                    13                             6                      
      Anorexia                                    12                             0                      
      Dyspepsia                                   8                              4                      
      Constipation                                5                              1                      
   Nervous System                                  
      Somnolence                                  27                             11                     
      Tremor                                      25                             6                      
      Dizziness                                   25                             13                     
      Diplopia                                    16                             9                      
      Amblyopia/Blurred Vision                    12                             9                      
      Ataxia                                      8                              1                      
      Nystagmus                                   8                              1                      
      Emotional Lability                          6                              4                      
      Thinking Abnormal                           6                              0                      
      Amnesia                                     5                              1                      
   Respiratory System                              
      Flu Syndrome                                12                             9                      
      Infection                                   12                             6                      
      Bronchitis                                  5                              1                      
      Rhinitis                                    5                              4                      
   Other                                           
      Alopecia                                    6                              1                      
      Weight Loss                                 6                              0                      
        Table 5  lists treatment-emergent adverse reactions which were reported by &gt;= 5% of patients in the high dose valproate group, and for which the incidence was greater than in the low dose group, in a controlled trial of divalproex sodium tablets monotherapy treatment of complex partial seizures. Since patients were being titrated off another antiepilepsy drug during the first portion of the trial, it is not possible, in many cases, to determine whether the following adverse reactions can be ascribed to divalproex sodium tablets alone, or the combination of valproate and other antiepilepsy drugs.
 


   Table 5. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;= 5% of Patients in the High Dose Group in the Controlled Trial of Valproate Monotherapy for Complex Partial Seizures    1     
   Body System/Event                                 High Dose (%)(n=131)      Low Dose (%)(n=134)         
   Body as a Whole                                  
      Asthenia                                     21                        10                            
   Digestive System                                 
      Nausea                                       34                        26                            
      Diarrhea                                     23                        19                            
      Vomiting                                     23                        15                            
      Abdominal pain                               12                        9                             
      Anorexia                                     11                        4                             
      Dyspepsia                                    11                        10                            
   Hemic/Lymphatic System                           
      Thrombocytopenia                             24                        1                             
      Ecchymosis                                   5                         4                             
   Metabolic/Nutritional                            
      Weight Gain                                  9                         4                             
      Peripheral Edema                             8                         3                             
   Nervous System                                   
      Tremor                                       57                        19                            
      Somnolence                                   30                        18                            
      Dizziness                                    18                        13                            
      Insomnia                                     15                        9                             
      Nervousness                                  11                        7                             
      Amnesia                                      7                         4                             
      Nystagmus                                    7                         1                             
      Depression                                   5                         4                             
   Respiratory System                               
      Infection                                    20                        13                            
      Pharyngitis                                  8                         2                             
      Dyspnea                                      5                         1                             
   Skin and Appendages                              
      Alopecia                                     24                        13                            
   Special Senses                                   
      Amblyopia/Blurred Vision                     8                         4                             
      Tinnitus                                     7                         1                             
 1.   Headache was the only adverse event that occurred in &gt;=5% of patients in the high dose group and at an equal or greater incidence in the low dose group.   
      The following additional adverse reactions were reported by greater than 1% but less than 5% of the 358 patients treated with valproate in the controlled trials of complex partial seizures:
 

   Body as a Whole:  Back pain, chest pain, malaise.



   Cardiovascular System:  Tachycardia, hypertension, palpitation.



   Digestive System:  Increased appetite, flatulence, hematemesis, eructation, pancreatitis, periodontal abscess.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System:  Petechia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  SGOT increased, SGPT increased.



   Musculoskeletal System:  Myalgia, twitching, arthralgia, leg cramps, myasthenia.



   Nervous System:  Anxiety, confusion, abnormal gait, paresthesia, hypertonia, incoordination, abnormal dreams, personality disorder.



   Respiratory System:  Sinusitis, cough increased, pneumonia, epistaxis.



   Skin and Appendages:  Rash, pruritus, dry skin.



   Special Senses:  Taste perversion, abnormal vision, deafness, otitis media.



   Urogenital System:  Urinary incontinence, vaginitis, dysmenorrhea, amenorrhea, urinary frequency.



   6.3 Migraine

  Based on two placebo-controlled clinical trials and their long term extension, valproate was generally well tolerated with most adverse reactions rated as mild to moderate in severity. Of the 202 patients exposed to valproate in the placebo-controlled trials, 17% discontinued for intolerance. This is compared to a rate of 5% for the 81 placebo patients. Including the long term extension study, the adverse reactions reported as the primary reason for discontinuation by &gt;= 1% of 248 valproate-treated patients were alopecia (6%), nausea and/or vomiting (5%), weight gain (2%), tremor (2%), somnolence (1%), elevated SGOT and/or SGPT (1%), and depression (1%).



   Table 6  includes those adverse reactions reported for patients in the placebo-controlled trial where the incidence rate in the divalproex sodium extended-release tablets-treated group was greater than 5% and was greater than that for placebo patients.




   Table 6. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;5% of Divalproex Sodium Extended-Release Tablets-Treated Patients During the Migraine Placebo-Controlled Trial with a Greater Incidence than Patients Taking Placebo    1     
   Body System    Event                 Divalproex Sodium Extended-Release Tablets(n=122)      Placebo(n=115)                     
   Gastrointestinal System             
      Nausea                          15%                             9%                                   
      Dyspepsia                       7%                              4%                                   
      Diarrhea                        7%                              3%                                   
      Vomiting                        7%                              2%                                   
      Abdominal Pain                  7%                              5%                                   
   Nervous System                      
      Somnolence                      7%                              2%                                   
   Other                               
      Infection                       15%                             14%                                  
 1. The following adverse reactions occurred in greater than 5% of divalproex sodium extended-release tablets-treated patients and at a greater incidence for placebo than for divalproex sodium extended-release tablets: asthenia and flu syndrome.   
      The following additional adverse reactions were reported by greater than 1% but not more than 5% of divalproex sodium extended-release tablets-treated patients and with a greater incidence than placebo in the placebo-controlled clinical trial for migraine prophylaxis:
 

   Body as a Whole:  Accidental injury, viral infection.



   Digestive System:  Increased appetite, tooth disorder.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  Edema, weight gain.



   Nervous System:  Abnormal gait, dizziness, hypertonia, insomnia, nervousness, tremor, vertigo.



   Respiratory System:  Pharyngitis, rhinitis.



   Skin and Appendages:  Rash.



   Special Senses:  Tinnitus.



   Table 7  includes those adverse reactions reported for patients in the placebo-controlled trials where the incidence rate in the valproate-treated group was greater than 5% and was greater than that for placebo patients.




   Table 7. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt; 5% of Valproate-Treated Patients During Migraine Placebo-Controlled Trials with a Greater Incidence than Patients Taking Placebo    1     
   Body System    Reaction                Divalproex Sodium Tablets(n=202)      Placebo(n=81)                  
   Gastrointestinal System               
      Nausea                            31%                             10%                              
      Dyspepsia                         13%                             9%                               
      Diarrhea                          12%                             7%                               
      Vomiting                          11%                             1%                               
      Abdominal pain                    9%                              4%                               
      Increased appetite                6%                              4%                               
   Nervous System                        
      Asthenia                          20%                             9%                               
      Somnolence                        17%                             5%                               
      Dizziness                         12%                             6%                               
      Tremor                            9%                              0%                               
   Other                                 
      Weight gain                       8%                              2%                               
      Back pain                         8%                              6%                               
      Alopecia                          7%                              1%                               
 1. The following adverse reactions occurred in greater than 5% of divalproex sodium tablets-treated patients and at a greater incidence for placebo than for divalproex sodium tablets: flu syndrome and pharyngitis.   
      The following additional adverse reactions were reported by greater than 1% but not more than 5% of the 202 valproate-treated patients in the controlled clinical trials:
 

   Body as a Whole:  Chest pain.



   Cardiovascular System:  Vasodilatation.



   Digestive System:  Constipation, dry mouth, flatulence, and stomatitis.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System:  Ecchymosis.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  Peripheral edema.



   Musculoskeletal System:  Leg cramps.



   Nervous System:  Abnormal dreams, confusion, paresthesia, speech disorder, and thinking abnormalities.



   Respiratory System:  Dyspnea, and sinusitis.



   Skin and Appendages:  Pruritus.



   Urogenital System:  Metrorrhagia.



   6.4 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Depakote. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Dermatologic  : Photosensitivity, erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and Stevens-Johnson syndrome.



   Psychiatric  : Emotional upset, psychosis, aggression, hyperactivity, hostility, and behavioral deterioration.



   Musculoskeletal  : Fractures, decreased bone mineral density, osteopenia, osteoporosis, and weakness.



   Hematologic  : Relative lymphocytosis, macrocytosis, hypofibrinogenemia, leukopenia, eosinophilia, anemia including macrocytic with or without folate deficiency, bone marrow suppression, pancytopenia, aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, and acute intermittent porphyria.



   Endocrine  : Irregular menses, secondary amenorrhea, breast enlargement, galactorrhea, parotid gland swelling, polycystic ovary disease, decrease carnitine concentrations, hyponatremia, hyperglycinemia, and inappropriate ADH secretion.



   Genitourinary  : Enuresis and urinary tract infection.



   Special Senses  : Hearing loss.



   Other  : Allergic reaction, anaphylaxis, developmental delay, bone pain, bradycardia, and cutaneous vasculitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LIFE THREATENING ADVERSE REACTIONS

  WARNING: LIFE THREATENING ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Hepatotoxicity  



     General Population:   Hepatic failure resulting in fatalities has occurred in patients receiving valproate and its derivatives. These incidents usually have occurred during the first six months of treatment. Serious or fatal hepatotoxicity may be preceded by non-specific symptoms such as malaise, weakness, lethargy, facial edema, anorexia, and vomiting. In patients with epilepsy, a loss of seizure control may also occur. Patients should be monitored closely for appearance of these symptoms. Serum liver tests should be performed prior to therapy and at frequent intervals thereafter, especially during the first six months   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.1)  ]  .  



   Children under the age of two years are at a considerably increased risk of developing fatal hepatotoxicity, especially those on multiple anticonvulsants, those with congenital metabolic disorders, those with severe seizure disorders accompanied by mental retardation, and those with organic brain disease. When divalproex sodium extended-release tablets are used in this patient group, it should be used with extreme caution and as a sole agent. The benefits of therapy should be weighed against the risks. The incidence of fatal hepatotoxicity decreases considerably in progressively older patient groups.  



     Patients with Mitochondrial Disease:   There is an increased risk of valproate-induced acute liver failure and resultant deaths in patients with hereditary neurometabolic syndromes caused by DNA mutations of the mitochondrial DNA Polymerase gamma (POLG) gene (e.g. Alpers Huttenlocher Syndrome). Divalproex sodium extended-release tablets are contraindicated in patients known to have mitochondrial disorders caused by POLG mutations and children under two years of age who are clinically suspected of having a mitochondrial disorder   [see Contraindications   (4)  ]  . In patients over two years of age who are clinically suspected of having a hereditary mitochondrial disease, divalproex sodium extended-release tablets should only be used after other anticonvulsants have failed.  This older group of patients should be closely monitored during treatment with divalproex sodium extended-release tablets for the development of acute liver injury with regular clinical assessments and serum liver testing.  POLG mutation screening should be performed in accordance with current clinical practice   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.1)  ]  .  



   Fetal Risk  



   Valproate can cause major congenital malformations, particularly neural tube defects (e.g., spina bifida). In addition, valproate can cause decreased IQ scores following   in utero   exposure.  



   Valproate is therefore contraindicated in pregnant women treated for prophylaxis of migraine   [see Contraindications   (4)  ]  . Valproate should only be used to treat pregnant women with epilepsy or bipolar disorder if other medications have failed to control their symptoms or are otherwise unacceptable.  



   Valproate should not be administered to a woman of childbearing potential unless the drug is essential to the management of her medical condition. This is especially important when valproate use is considered for a condition not usually associated with permanent injury or death (e.g., migraine). Women should use effective contraception while using valproate   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.2  ,    5.3  ,   5.4)  ]  .  



   A Medication Guide describing the risks of valproate is available for patients   [see Patient Counseling Information   (17)  ]  .  



   Pancreatitis  



   Cases of life-threatening pancreatitis have been reported in both children and adults receiving valproate. Some of the cases have been described as hemorrhagic with a rapid progression from initial symptoms to death. Cases have been reported shortly after initial use as well as after several years of use. Patients and guardians should be warned that abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting and/or anorexia can be symptoms of pancreatitis that require prompt medical evaluation. If pancreatitis is diagnosed, valproate should ordinarily be discontinued. Alternative treatment for the underlying medical condition should be initiated as clinically indicated   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.5)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LIFE THREATENING ADVERSE REACTIONS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .  



 *  Hepatotoxicity, including fatalities, usually during first 6 months of treatment. Children under the age of two years and patients with mitochondrial disorders are at higher risk. Monitor patients closely, and perform serum liver testing prior to therapy and at frequent intervals thereafter (5.1) 
 *  Fetal Risk, particularly neural tube defects, other major malformations, and decreased IQ (5.2, 5.3, 5.4) 
 *  Pancreatitis, including fatal hemorrhagic cases (5.5) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    



   EXCERPT:    *  Hepatotoxicity; evaluate high risk populations and monitor serum liver tests  (5.1)   
 *  Birth defects and decreased IQ following in utero exposure; only use to treat pregnant women with epilepsy or bipolar disorder if other medications are unacceptable; should not be administered to a woman of childbearing potential unless essential  (5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.4)   
 *  Pancreatitis; divalproex sodium extended-release tablets should ordinarily be discontinued  (5.5)   
 *  Brain Atrophy; evaluate for continued use in the presence of suspected or apparent signs of reversible or irreversible cerebral and cerebellar atrophy  (5.7)   
 *  Suicidal behavior or ideation; Antiepileptic drugs, including divalproex sodium extended-release tablets, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior  (5.8)   
 *  Thrombocytopenia; monitor platelet counts and coagulation tests  (5.9)   
 *  Hyperammonemia and hyperammonemic encephalopathy; measure ammonia level if unexplained lethargy and vomiting or changes in mental status, and also with concomitant topiramate use; consider discontinuation of valproate therapy  (5.6  ,  5.10  ,  5.11)   
 *  Hypothermia; Hypothermia has been reported during valproate therapy with or without associated hyperammonemia. This adverse reaction can also occur in patients using concomitant topiramate  (5.12)   
 *  Multi-organ hypersensitivity reaction; discontinue divalproex sodium extended-release tablets  (5.13)   
 *  Somnolence in the elderly can occur. Divalproex sodium extended-release tablets dosage should be increased slowly and with regular monitoring for fluid and nutritional intake  (5.15)   
    
 

   5.1 Hepatotoxicity



   General Information on Hepatotoxicity  



 Hepatic failure resulting in fatalities has occurred in patients receiving valproate. These incidents usually have occurred during the first six months of treatment. Serious or fatal hepatotoxicity may be preceded by non-specific symptoms such as malaise, weakness, lethargy, facial edema, anorexia, and vomiting. In patients with epilepsy, a loss of seizure control may also occur. Patients should be monitored closely for appearance of these symptoms. Serum liver tests should be performed prior to therapy and at frequent intervals thereafter, especially during the first six months. However, healthcare providers should not rely totally on serum biochemistry since these tests may not be abnormal in all instances, but should also consider the results of careful interim medical history and physical examination.



 Caution should be observed when administering valproate products to patients with a prior history of hepatic disease. Patients on multiple anticonvulsants, children, those with congenital metabolic disorders, those with severe seizure disorders accompanied by mental retardation, and those with organic brain disease may be at particular risk. See below, "Patients with Known or Suspected Mitochondrial Disease."



 Experience has indicated that children under the age of two years are at a considerably increased risk of developing fatal hepatotoxicity, especially those with the aforementioned conditions. When divalproex sodium extended-release tablets are used in this patient group, it should be used with extreme caution and as a sole agent. The benefits of therapy should be weighed against the risks. In progressively older patient groups experience in epilepsy has indicated that the incidence of fatal hepatotoxicity decreases considerably.



  Patients with Known or Suspected Mitochondrial Disease  



 Divalproex sodium extended-release tablets are contraindicated in patients known to have mitochondrial disorders caused by POLG mutations and children under two years of age who are clinically suspected of having a mitochondrial disorder [see Contraindications  (4)  ]  . Valproate-induced acute liver failure and liver-related deaths have been reported in patients with hereditary neurometabolic syndromes caused by mutations in the gene for mitochondrial DNA polymerase gamma (POLG) (e.g., Alpers-Huttenlocher Syndrome) at a higher rate than those without these syndromes. Most of the reported cases of liver failure in patients with these syndromes have been identified in children and adolescents.



 POLG-related disorders should be suspected in patients with a family history or suggestive symptoms of a POLG-related disorder, including but not limited to unexplained encephalopathy, refractory epilepsy (focal, myoclonic), status epilepticus at presentation, developmental delays, psychomotor regression, axonal sensorimotor neuropathy, myopathy cerebellar ataxia, opthalmoplegia, or complicated migraine with occipital aura. POLG mutation testing should be performed in accordance with current clinical practice for the diagnostic evaluation of such disorders. The A467T and W748S mutations are present in approximately 2/3 of patients with autosomal recessive POLG-related disorders.



 In patients over two years of age who are clinically suspected of having a hereditary mitochondrial disease, divalproex sodium extended-release tablets should only be used after other anticonvulsants have failed. This older group of patients should be closely monitored during treatment with divalproex sodium extended-release tablets for the development of acute liver injury with regular clinical assessments and serum liver test monitoring.



 The drug should be discontinued immediately in the presence of significant hepatic dysfunction, suspected or apparent. In some cases, hepatic dysfunction has progressed in spite of discontinuation of drug [see  Boxed Warning  and Contraindications  (4)  ]  .



    5.2 Birth Defects



  Valproate can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Pregnancy registry data show that maternal valproate use can cause neural tube defects and other structural abnormalities (e.g., craniofacial defects, cardiovascular malformations and malformations involving various body systems). The rate of congenital malformations among babies born to mothers using valproate is about four times higher than the rate among babies born to epileptic mothers using other anti-seizure monotherapies. Evidence suggests that folic acid supplementation prior to conception and during the first trimester of pregnancy decreases the risk for congenital neural tube defects in the general population.



    5.3 Decreased IQ Following in utero  Exposure



  Valproate can cause decreased IQ scores following in utero  exposure. Published epidemiological studies have indicated that children exposed to valproate in utero  have lower cognitive test scores than children exposed in utero  to either another antiepileptic drug or to no antiepileptic drugs. The largest of these studies  1  is a prospective cohort study conducted in the United States and United Kingdom that found that children with prenatal exposure to valproate (n=62) had lower IQ scores at age 6 (97 [95% C.I. 94-101]) than children with prenatal exposure to the other antiepileptic drug monotherapy treatments evaluated: lamotrigine (108 [95% C.I. 105-110]), carbamazepine (105 [95% C.I. 102-108]), and phenytoin (108 [95% C.I. 104-112]). It is not known when during pregnancy cognitive effects in valproate-exposed children occur. Because the women in this study were exposed to antiepileptic drugs throughout pregnancy, whether the risk for decreased IQ was related to a particular time period during pregnancy could not be assessed.



 Although all of the available studies have methodological limitations, the weight of the evidence supports the conclusion that valproate exposure in utero  can cause decreased IQ in children.



 In animal studies, offspring with prenatal exposure to valproate had malformations similar to those seen in humans and demonstrated neurobehavioral deficits [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  ]  .



 Valproate use is contraindicated during pregnancy in women being treated for prophylaxis of migraine headaches. Women with epilepsy or bipolar disorder who are pregnant or who plan to become pregnant should not be treated with valproate unless other treatments have failed to provide adequate symptom control or are otherwise unacceptable. In such women, the benefits of treatment with valproate during pregnancy may still outweigh the risks.



    5.4 Use in Women of Childbearing Potential



  Because of the risk to the fetus of decreased IQ and major congenital malformations (including neural tube defects), which may occur very early in pregnancy, valproate should not be administered to a woman of childbearing potential unless the drug is essential to the management of her medical condition. This is especially important when valproate use is considered for a condition not usually associated with permanent injury or death (e.g., migraine). Women should use effective contraception while using valproate. Women who are planning a pregnancy should be counseled regarding the relative risks and benefits of valproate use during pregnancy, and alternative therapeutic options should be considered for these patients [see  Boxed Warning  and Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  ]  .



 To prevent major seizures, valproate should not be discontinued abruptly, as this can precipitate status epilepticus with resulting maternal and fetal hypoxia and threat to life.



 Evidence suggests that folic acid supplementation prior to conception and during the first trimester of pregnancy decreases the risk for congenital neural tube defects in the general population. It is not known whether the risk of neural tube defects or decreased IQ in the offspring of women receiving valproate is reduced by folic acid supplementation. Dietary folic acid supplementation both prior to conception and during pregnancy should be routinely recommended for patients using valproate.



    5.5 Pancreatitis



  Cases of life-threatening pancreatitis have been reported in both children and adults receiving valproate. Some of the cases have been described as hemorrhagic with rapid progression from initial symptoms to death. Some cases have occurred shortly after initial use as well as after several years of use. The rate based upon the reported cases exceeds that expected in the general population and there have been cases in which pancreatitis recurred after rechallenge with valproate. In clinical trials, there were 2 cases of pancreatitis without alternative etiology in 2416 patients, representing 1044 patient-years experience. Patients and guardians should be warned that abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, and/or anorexia can be symptoms of pancreatitis that require prompt medical evaluation. If pancreatitis is diagnosed, divalproex sodium extended-release tablets should ordinarily be discontinued. Alternative treatment for the underlying medical condition should be initiated as clinically indicated [see  Boxed Warning  ]  .



    5.6 Urea Cycle Disorders



  Divalproex sodium extended-release tablets are contraindicated in patients with known urea cycle disorders (UCD). Hyperammonemic encephalopathy, sometimes fatal, has been reported following initiation of valproate therapy in patients with urea cycle disorders, a group of uncommon genetic abnormalities, particularly ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency. Prior to the initiation of divalproex sodium extended-release tablets therapy, evaluation for UCD should be considered in the following patients: 1) those with a history of unexplained encephalopathy or coma, encephalopathy associated with a protein load, pregnancy-related or postpartum encephalopathy, unexplained mental retardation, or history of elevated plasma ammonia or glutamine; 2) those with cyclical vomiting and lethargy, episodic extreme irritability, ataxia, low BUN, or protein avoidance; 3) those with a family history of UCD or a family history of unexplained infant deaths (particularly males); 4) those with other signs or symptoms of UCD. Patients who develop symptoms of unexplained hyperammonemic encephalopathy while receiving valproate therapy should receive prompt treatment (including discontinuation of valproate therapy) and be evaluated for underlying urea cycle disorders [see Contraindications  (4)  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.11)  ]  .



    5.7 Brain Atrophy



  There have been postmarketing reports of reversible and irreversible cerebral and cerebellar atrophy temporally associated with the use of valproate products; in some cases, patients recovered with permanent sequelae. The motor and cognitive functions of patients on valproate should be routinely monitored and drug should be evaluated for continued use in the presence of suspected or apparent signs of brain atrophy.



 Reports of cerebral atrophy have also been reported in children who were exposed in utero  to valproate products [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  ]  .



    5.8 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including divalproex sodium extended-release tablets, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.



   Table 2  shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.




  Table 2. Risk by indication for antiepileptic drugs in the pooled analysis     
  Indication       Placebo Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients     Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients     Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients     Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients     
 Epilepsy         1.0              3.4              3.5              2.4               
 Psychiatric      5.7              8.5              1.5              2.9               
 Other            1.0              1.8              1.9              0.9               
 Total            2.4              4.3              1.8              1.9               
      The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing divalproex sodium extended-release tablets or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.9 Thrombocytopenia



  The frequency of adverse effects (particularly elevated liver enzymes and thrombocytopenia) may be dose-related. In a clinical trial of valproate as monotherapy in patients with epilepsy, 34/126 patients (27%) receiving approximately 50 mg/kg/day on average, had at least one value of platelets &lt;= 75 x 10  9  /L. Approximately half of these patients had treatment discontinued, with return of platelet counts to normal. In the remaining patients, platelet counts normalized with continued treatment. In this study, the probability of thrombocytopenia appeared to increase significantly at total valproate concentrations of &gt;= 110 mcg/mL (females) or &gt;= 135 mcg/mL (males). The therapeutic benefit which may accompany the higher doses should therefore be weighed against the possibility of a greater incidence of adverse effects.



 Because of reports of thrombocytopenia, inhibition of the secondary phase of platelet aggregation, and abnormal coagulation parameters, (e.g., low fibrinogen), platelet counts and coagulation tests are recommended before initiating therapy and at periodic intervals. It is recommended that patients receiving divalproex sodium extended-release tablets be monitored for platelet count and coagulation parameters prior to planned surgery. Evidence of hemorrhage, bruising, or a disorder of hemostasis/coagulation is an indication for reduction of the dosage or withdrawal of therapy.



    5.10 Hyperammonemia



  Hyperammonemia has been reported in association with valproate therapy and may be present despite normal liver function tests. In patients who develop unexplained lethargy and vomiting or changes in mental status, hyperammonemic encephalopathy should be considered and an ammonia level should be measured. Hyperammonemia should also be considered in patients who present with hypothermia [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.12)  ]  . If ammonia is increased, valproate therapy should be discontinued. Appropriate interventions for treatment of hyperammonemia should be initiated, and such patients should undergo investigation for underlying urea cycle disorders [see Contraindications  (4)  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.6  ,  5.10)  ]  .



 During the placebo controlled pediatric mania trial, one (1) in twenty (20) adolescents (5%) treated with valproate developed increased plasma ammonia levels compared to no (0) patients treated with placebo.



 Asymptomatic elevations of ammonia are more common and when present, require close monitoring of plasma ammonia levels. If the elevation persists, discontinuation of valproate therapy should be considered.



    5.11 Hyperammonemia and Encephalopathy associated with Concomitant Topiramate Use



  Concomitant administration of topiramate and valproate has been associated with hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy in patients who have tolerated either drug alone. Clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting. Hypothermia can also be a manifestation of hyperammonemia [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.12)  ]  . In most cases, symptoms and signs abated with discontinuation of either drug. This adverse event is not due to a pharmacokinetic interaction. It is not known if topiramate monotherapy is associated with hyperammonemia. Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced hepatic mitochondrial activity may be at an increased risk for hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy. Although not studied, an interaction of topiramate and valproate may exacerbate existing defects or unmask deficiencies in susceptible persons. In patients who develop unexplained lethargy, vomiting, or changes in mental status, hyperammonemic encephalopathy should be considered and an ammonia level should be measured [see Contraindications  (4)  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.6  ,  5.10)  ]  .



    5.12 Hypothermia



  Hypothermia, defined as an unintentional drop in body core temperature to &lt; 35 degrees C (95 degrees F), has been reported in association with valproate therapy both in conjunction with and in the absence of hyperammonemia. This adverse reaction can also occur in patients using concomitant topiramate with valproate after starting topiramate treatment or after increasing the daily dose of topiramate [see Drug Interactions  (7.3)  ]  . Consideration should be given to stopping valproate in patients who develop hypothermia, which may be manifested by a variety of clinical abnormalities including lethargy, confusion, coma, and significant alterations in other major organ systems such as the cardiovascular and respiratory systems. Clinical management and assessment should include examination of blood ammonia levels.



    5.13 Multi-Organ Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions have been rarely reported in close temporal association to the initiation of valproate therapy in adult and pediatric patients (median time to detection 21 days: range 1 to 40 days). Although there have been a limited number of reports, many of these cases resulted in hospitalization and at least one death has been reported. Signs and symptoms of this disorder were diverse; however, patients typically, although not exclusively, presented with fever and rash associated with other organ system involvement. Other associated manifestations may include lymphadenopathy, hepatitis, liver function test abnormalities, hematological abnormalities (e.g., eosinophilia, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia), pruritus, nephritis, oliguria, hepato-renal syndrome, arthralgia, and asthenia. Because the disorder is variable in its expression, other organ system symptoms and signs, not noted here, may occur. If this reaction is suspected, valproate should be discontinued and an alternative treatment started. Although the existence of cross sensitivity with other drugs that produce this syndrome is unclear, the experience amongst drugs associated with multi-organ hypersensitivity would indicate this to be a possibility.



    5.14 Interaction with Carbapenem Antibiotics



  Carbapenem antibiotics (for example, ertapenem, imipenem, meropenem; this is not a complete list) may reduce serum valproate concentrations to subtherapeutic levels, resulting in loss of seizure control. Serum valproate concentrations should be monitored frequently after initiating carbapenem therapy. Alternative antibacterial or anticonvulsant therapy should be considered if serum valproate concentrations drop significantly or seizure control deteriorates [see Drug Interactions  (7.1)  ]  .



    5.15 Somnolence in the Elderly



  In a double-blind, multicenter trial of valproate in elderly patients with dementia (mean age = 83 years), doses were increased by 125 mg/day to a target dose of 20 mg/kg/day. A significantly higher proportion of valproate patients had somnolence compared to placebo, and although not statistically significant, there was a higher proportion of patients with dehydration. Discontinuations for somnolence were also significantly higher than with placebo. In some patients with somnolence (approximately one-half), there was associated reduced nutritional intake and weight loss. There was a trend for the patients who experienced these events to have a lower baseline albumin concentration, lower valproate clearance, and a higher BUN. In elderly patients, dosage should be increased more slowly and with regular monitoring for fluid and nutritional intake, dehydration, somnolence, and other adverse reactions. Dose reductions or discontinuation of valproate should be considered in patients with decreased food or fluid intake and in patients with excessive somnolence [see Dosage and Administration  (2.4)  ]  .



    5.16 Monitoring: Drug Plasma Concentration



  Since valproate may interact with concurrently administered drugs which are capable of enzyme induction, periodic plasma concentration determinations of valproate and concomitant drugs are recommended during the early course of therapy [see Drug Interactions  (7)  ]  .



    5.17 Effect on Ketone and Thyroid Function Tests



  Valproate is partially eliminated in the urine as a keto-metabolite which may lead to a false interpretation of the urine ketone test.



 There have been reports of altered thyroid function tests associated with valproate. The clinical significance of these is unknown.



    5.18 Effect on HIV and CMV Viruses Replication



  There are in vitro  studies that suggest valproate stimulates the replication of the HIV and CMV viruses under certain experimental conditions. The clinical consequence, if any, is not known. Additionally, the relevance of these in vitro  findings is uncertain for patients receiving maximally suppressive antiretroviral therapy. Nevertheless, these data should be borne in mind when interpreting the results from regular monitoring of the viral load in HIV infected patients receiving valproate or when following CMV infected patients clinically.



    5.19 Medication Residue in the Stool



  There have been rare reports of medication residue in the stool. Some patients have had anatomic (including ileostomy or colostomy) or functional gastrointestinal disorders with shortened GI transit times. In some reports, medication residues have occurred in the context of diarrhea. It is recommended that plasma valproate levels be checked in patients who experience medication residue in the stool, and patients' clinical condition should be monitored. If clinically indicated, alternative treatment may be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
