<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="divigel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  See    BOXED WARNINGS  ,  WARNINGS     and     PRECAUTIONS    .



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



 Divigel  (r)  was studied at doses of 0.25, 0.5 and 1.0 g/day in a 12-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled study that included a total of 495 postmenopausal women (86.5% Caucasian). The adverse events that occurred at a rate greater than 5% in any of the treatment groups are summarized in  Table 5  .



 Table 5: Number (%) of Subjects with Common Adverse Events* in a 12-Week Placebo- Controlled Study of Divigel(r) 
  *     Adverse events reported by &gt;=5% of patients in any treatment group.    
  
                                             Divigel    (r)      Placebo        
                                             0.25 g/day       0.5 g/day       1.0 g/day                       
   SYSTEM ORGAN CLASS                        N=122            N=123           N=125            N=125          
        Preferred Term                       n (%)            n (%)           n (%)            n (%)          
   INFECTIONS &amp; INFESTATIONS                                                                                  
      Nasopharyngitis                      7 (5.7)          5 (4.1)         6 (4.8)          5 (4.0)          
      Upper Respiratory Tract Infection    7 (5.7)          3 (2.4)         2 (1.6)          2 (1.6)          
      Vaginal mycosis                      1 (0.8)          3 (2.4)         8 (6.4)          4(3.2)           
   REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM &amp; BREAST DISORDERS                                                                       
      Breast Tenderness                    3 (2.5)          7 (5.7)         11 (8.8)         2 (1.6)          
      Metrorrhagia                         5 (4.1)          7 (5.7)         12 (9.6)         2 (1.6)          
           In a 12-week placebo-controlled study of Divigel  (r)  , application site reactions were seen in &lt;1% of subjects.
 

 The following additional adverse reactions have been reported with estrogen and/or progestin therapy.



 *   Genitourinary system: Changes in vaginal bleeding pattern and abnormal withdrawal bleeding or flow; breakthrough bleeding; spotting; dysmenorrhea; increase in size of uterine leiomyomata; vaginitis, including vaginal candidiasis; change in amount of cervical secretion; changes in cervical ectropion; ovarian cancer; endometrial hyperplasia; endometrial cancer; vaginal discharge. 
 *   Breasts: Tenderness; enlargement, pain, nipple discharge, galactorrhea, fibrocystic breast changes; breast cancer; nipple pain. 
 *   Cardiovascular: Deep and superficial venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolism; thrombophlebitis; myocardial infarction; stroke; increase in blood pressure. 
 *   Gastrointestinal: Nausea; vomiting; abdominal cramps; bloating; cholestatic jaundice; increased incidence of gallbladder disease; pancreatitis; enlargement of hepatic hemangiomas; abdominal pain. 
 *   Skin: Chloasma or melasma, which may persist when drug is discontinued; erythema multiforme; erythema nodosum; hemorrhagic eruption; loss of scalp hair; hirsutism; pruritus; rash. 
 *   Eyes: Retinal vascular thrombosis, intolerance to contact lenses. 
 *   Central Nervous System: Headache; migraine; dizziness; mental depression; chorea; nervousness; mood disturbances; irritability; exacerbation of epilepsy; dementia. 
 *   Miscellaneous: Increase or decrease in weight; reduced carbohydrate tolerance; aggravation of porphyria; edema; arthralgias; leg cramps; changes in libido; urticaria; angioedema; anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions; hypocalcemia; exacerbation of asthma; increased triglycerides; muscle cramps. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  ESTROGENS INCREASE THE RISK OF ENDOMETRIAL CANCER 

  Close clinical surveillance of all women taking estrogens is important.  Adequate diagnostic measures, including endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in all cases of undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal vaginal bleeding.  There is no evidence that the use of "natural" estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens at equivalent estrogen doses.  (See     WARNINGS, Malignant neoplasms  ,   Endometrial cancer    .) 



   CARDIOVASCULAR AND OTHER RISKS 

  Estrogens with or without progestins should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia.  (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Dementia    .) 



 The estrogen-alone substudy of the Women's Health Initiative (WHI) reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 6.8 years and 7.1 years, respectively, of treatment with oral conjugated estrogens (CE 0.625 mg) alone per day, relative to placebo.  (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders    .) 



 The estrogen-plus-progestin substudy of the WHI reported increased risk of myocardial infarction, stroke, invasive breast cancer, pulmonary emboli, and deep vein thrombosis in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with oral conjugated estrogens (CE 0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA 2.5 mg) per day, relative to placebo.  (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Malignant neoplasms  ,       Breast cancer    .  )  



 The Women's Health Initiative Memory Study (WHIMS), a substudy of the WHI, reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with CE 0.625 mg alone and during 4 years of treatment with CE 0.625 mg combined with MPA 2.5 mg, relative to placebo.  It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women.  (See     CLINICAL STUDIES  ,   WARNINGS, Dementia  ,   and     PRECAUTIONS, Geriatric Use    .) 



 Other doses of oral conjugated estrogens with medroxyprogesterone acetate, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins were not studied in the WHI clinical trials and, in the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar.  Because of these risks, estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
