<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="docetaxel0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reactions from docetaxel are:



 *  Toxic Deaths  [see  Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]   
 *  Hepatotoxicity  [see  Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]   
 *  Neutropenia  [see  Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]   
 *  Hypersensitivity  [see  Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]   
 *  Fluid Retention  [see  Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]   
    The most common adverse reactions across all docetaxel indications are infections, neutropenia, anemia, febrile neutropenia, hypersensitivity, thrombocytopenia, neuropathy, dysgeusia, dyspnea, constipation, anorexia, nail disorders, fluid retention, asthenia, pain, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, mucositis, alopecia, skin reactions, and myalgia. Incidence varies depending on the indication.
 

 Adverse reactions are described according to indication. Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Responding patients may not experience an improvement in performance status on therapy and may experience worsening. The relationship between changes in performance status, response to therapy, and treatment-related side effects has not been established.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions across all docetaxel indications are infections, neutropenia, anemia, febrile neutropenia, hypersensitivity, thrombocytopenia, neuropathy, dysgeusia, dyspnea, constipation, anorexia, nail disorders, fluid retention, asthenia, pain, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, mucositis, alopecia, skin reactions, myalgia(  6  )



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Northstar RxLLC at 1-800-206-7821 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch      



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  

      Breast Cancer    



   

    Monotherapy with docetaxel for locally advanced or metastatic breast cancer after failure of prior chemotherapy  



 Docetaxel 100 mg/m  2  : Adverse drug reactions occurring in at least 5% of patients are compared for three populations who received docetaxel administered at 100 mg/m  2  as a 1-hour infusion every 3 weeks: 2045 patients with various tumor types and normal baseline liver function tests; the subset of 965 patients with locally advanced or metastatic breast cancer, both previously treated and untreated with chemotherapy, who had normal baseline liver function tests; and an additional 61 patients with various tumor types who had abnormal liver function tests at baseline. These reactions were described using COSTART terms and were considered possibly or probably related to docetaxel. At least 95% of these patients did not receive hematopoietic support. The safety profile is generally similar in patients receiving docetaxel for the treatment of breast cancer and in patients with other tumor types (See  Table 4  ).



 Table 4 - Summary of Adverse Reactions in Patients Receiving Docetaxel at 100 mg/m 2 
 Adverse Reaction    All Tumor TypesNormal LFTsn=2045%  All Tumor TypesElevated LFTsn=61%  Breast CancerNormal LFTsn=965%   
  
   Hematologic                                                                   
 Neutropenia                                                                     
   &lt;2000 cells/mm  3            96                  96                 99           
   &lt;500 cells/mm  3            75                  88                 86           
 Leukopenia                                                                      
   &lt;4000 cells/mm  3            96                  98                 99           
   &lt;1000 cells/mm  3            32                  47                 44           
 Thrombocytopenia                                                                
   &lt;100,000 cells/mm  3            8                   25                  9           
 Anemia                                                                          
   &lt;11 g/dL                  90                  92                 94           
   &lt;8 g/dL                   9                   31                  8           
 Febrile Neutropenia          11                  26                 12           
   Septic Death              2                   5                   1           
   Non-Septic Death            1                   7                   1           
   Infections                                                                    
   Any                       22                  33                 22           
   Severe                    6                   16                  6           
   Fever in Absence of Infection                                                                
   Any                       31                  41                 35           
   Severe                    2                   8                   2           
   Hypersensitivity Reactions                                                                
 Regardless of Premedication                                                              
   Any                       21                  20                 18           
   Severe                    4                   10                  3           
 With 3-day Premedication         n=92                n=3                n=92          
                                                                                 
   Any                       15                  33                 15           
   Severe                    2                   0                   2           
   Fluid Retention                                                                
 Regardless of Premedication                                                              
   Any                       47                  39                 60           
   Severe                    7                   8                   9           
 With 3-day Premedication         n=92                n=3                n=92          
   Any                       64                  67                 64           
   Severe                    7                   33                  7           
   Neurosensory                                                                  
   Any                       49                  34                 58           
   Severe                    4                   0                   6           
   Cutaneous                                                                     
                                                                                 
   Any                       48                  54                 47           
   Severe                    5                   10                  5           
   Nail Changes                                                                  
   Any                       31                  23                 41           
   Severe                    3                   5                   4           
   Gastrointestinal                                                                
 Nausea                      39                  38                 42           
 Vomiting                    22                  23                 23           
 Diarrhea                    39                  33                 43           
   Severe                    5                   5                   6           
   Stomatitis                                                                    
   Any                       42                  49                 52           
   Severe                    6                   13                  7           
   Alopecia                  76                  62                 74           
   Asthenia                                                                      
   Any                       62                  53                 66           
   Severe                    13                  25                 15           
   Myalgia                                                                       
   Any                       19                  16                 21           
   Severe                    2                   2                   2           
   Arthralgia                9                   7                   8           
   Infusion Site Reactions            4                   3                   4           
            
     Hematologic Reactions  



 Reversible marrow suppression was the major dose-limiting toxicity of docetaxel  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  The median time to nadir was 7 days, while the median duration of severe neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  ) was 7 days. Among 2045 patients with solid tumors and normal baseline LFTs, severe neutropenia occurred in 75.4% and lasted for more than 7 days in 2.9% of cycles.



 Febrile neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  with fever &gt;38 degrees C with intravenous antibiotics and/or hospitalization) occurred in 11% of patients with solid tumors, in 12.3% of patients with metastatic breast cancer, and in 9.8% of 92 breast cancer patients premedicated with 3-day corticosteroids.



 Severe infectious episodes occurred in 6.1% of patients with solid tumors, in 6.4% of patients with metastatic breast cancer, and in 5.4% of 92 breast cancer patients premedicated with 3-day corticosteroids. Thrombocytopenia (&lt;100,000 cells/mm3) associated with fatal gastrointestinal hemorrhage has been reported.



   

    Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 Severe hypersensitivity reactions have been reported    [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]    . Minor events, including flushing, rash with or without pruritus, chest tightness, back pain, dyspnea, drug fever, or chills, have been reported and resolved after discontinuing the infusion and instituting appropriate therapy.



   

    Fluid Retention  



 Fluid retention can occur with the use of docetaxel    [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Dosage and Administration (2.6)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].    



   

    Cutaneous Reactions  



 Severe skin toxicity is discussed elsewhere in the label    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ].    Reversible cutaneous reactions characterized by a rash including localized eruptions, mainly on the feet and/or hands, but also on the arms, face, or thorax, usually associated with pruritus, have been observed. Eruptions generally occurred within 1 week after docetaxel infusion, recovered before the next infusion, and were not disabling.



 Severe nail disorders were characterized by hypo- or hyperpigmentation, and occasionally by onycholysis (in 0.8% of patients with solid tumors) and pain.



   

    Neurologic Reactions  



 Neurologic reactions are discussed elsewhere in the label    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)      ].



   

    Gastrointestinal Reactions  



 Nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea were generally mild to moderate. Severe reactions occurred in 3 to 5% of patients with solid tumors and to a similar extent among metastatic breast cancer patients. The incidence of severe reactions was 1% or less for the 92 breast cancer patients premedicated with 3-day corticosteroids.



 Severe stomatitis occurred in 5.5% of patients with solid tumors, in 7.4% of patients with metastatic breast cancer, and in 1.1% of the 92 breast cancer patients premedicated with 3-day corticosteroids.



   

    Cardiovascular Reactions  



 Hypotension occurred in 2.8% of patients with solid tumors; 1.2% required treatment. Clinically meaningful events such as heart failure, sinus tachycardia, atrial flutter, dysrhythmia, unstable angina, pulmonary edema, and hypertension occurred rarely. Seven of 86 (8.1%) of metastatic breast cancer patients receiving docetaxel 100 mg/m  2  in a randomized trial and who had serial left ventricular ejection fractions assessed developed deterioration of LVEF by &gt;=10% associated with a drop below the institutional lower limit of normal.



   

    Infusion Site Reactions  



 Infusion site reactions were generally mild and consisted of hyperpigmentation, inflammation, redness or dryness of the skin, phlebitis, extravasation, or swelling of the vein.



   

    Hepatic Reactions  



 In patients with normal LFTs at baseline, bilirubin values &gt; the ULN occurred in 8.9% of patients. Increases in AST or ALT &gt;1.5 times the ULN, or alkaline phosphatase &gt;2.5 times ULN, were observed in 18.9% and 7.3% of patients, respectively. While on docetaxel, increases in AST and/or ALT &gt;1.5 times ULN concomitant with alkaline phosphatase &gt;2.5 times ULN occurred in 4.3% of patients with normal LFTs at baseline. Whether these changes were related to the drug or underlying disease has not been established.



   

    Hematologic and Other Toxicity: Relation to dose and baseline liver chemistry abnormalities  



 Hematologic and other toxicity is increased at higher doses and in patients with elevated baseline liver function tests (LFTs). In the following tables, adverse drug reactions are compared for three populations: 730 patients with normal LFTs given docetaxel at 100 mg/m  2  in the randomized and single arm studies of metastatic breast cancer after failure of previous chemotherapy; 18 patients in these studies who had abnormal baseline LFTs (defined as AST and/or ALT &gt;1.5 times ULN concurrent with alkaline phosphatase &gt;2.5 times ULN); and 174 patients in Japanese studies given docetaxel at 60 mg/m  2  who had normal LFTs (see  Tables 5  and  6  ).



 Table 5 - Hematologic Adverse Reactions in Breast Cancer Patients Previously Treated with Chemotherapy Treated at Docetaxel 100 mg/m 2 with Normal or Elevated Liver Function Tests or 60 mg/m 2 with Normal Liver Function Tests 
                                           Docetaxel100 mg/m  2    Docetaxel60 mg/m  2     
                                               Normal LFTs          Elevated LFTs          Normal LFTs        
 Adverse Reaction                                 n=730                  n=18                 n=174           
                                                    %                     %                     %             
  
   Neutropenia                                                                                                
   Any         &lt;2000 cells/mm  3                    98                   100                    95            
   Grade 4   &lt;500 cells/mm  3                       84                    94                    75            
   Thrombocytopenia                                                                                           
   Any        &lt;100,000 cells/mm  3                  11                    44                    14            
   Grade 4  &lt;20,000 cells/mm  3                     1                     17                    1             
   Anemia     &lt;11 g/dL                              95                    94                    65            
   Infection                                                                                                  
   Any                                              23                    39                    1             
   Grade 3 and 4                                    7                     33                    0             
   Febrile Neutropenia                                                                                        
   By Patient                                       12                    33                    0             
   By Course                                        2                     9                     0             
   Septic Death                                     2                     6                     1             
   Non-Septic Death                                 1                     11                    0             
         Table 6 - Non-Hematologic Adverse Reactions in Breast Cancer Patients Previously Treated with Chemotherapy Treated at Docetaxel 100 mg/m 2 with Normal or Elevated Liver Function Tests or 60 mg/m 2 with Normal Liver Function Tests 
                                           Docetaxel100 mg/m  2    Docetaxel60 mg/m  2     
                                               Normal LFTs          Elevated LFTs          Normal LFTs        
 Adverse Reaction                                 n=730                  n=18                 n=174           
                                                    %                     %                     %             
  
 NA = not available                         
  
   Acute Hypersensitivity  Reaction Regardless of Premedication                                                                       
     Any                                            13                    6                     1             
     Severe                                         1                     0                     0             
   Fluid Retention  Regardless of Premedication                                                                       
     Any                                            56                    61                    13            
     Severe                                         8                     17                    0             
   Neurosensory                                                                                               
     Any                                            57                    50                    20            
     Severe                                         6                     0                     0             
   Myalgia                                          23                    33                    3             
   Cutaneous                                                                                                  
     Any                                            45                    61                    31            
     Severe                                         5                     17                    0             
   Asthenia                                                                                                   
     Any                                            65                    44                    66            
     Severe                                         17                    22                    0             
   Diarrhea                                                                                                   
     Any                                            42                    28                    NA            
     Severe                                         6                     11                                  
   Stomatitis                                                                                                 
     Any                                            53                    67                    19            
     Severe                                         8                     39                    1             
          In the three-arm monotherapy trial, TAX313, which compared docetaxel 60 mg/m  2  , 75 mg/m  2  and 100 mg/m  2  in advanced breast cancer, grade 3/4 or severe adverse reactions occurred in 49.0% of patients treated with docetaxel 60 mg/m  2  compared to 55.3% and 65.9% treated with 75 mg/m  2  and 100 mg/m  2  respectively. Discontinuation due to adverse reactions was reported in 5.3% of patients treated with 60 mg/m  2  vs. 6.9% and 16.5% for patients treated at 75 mg/m  2  and 100 mg/m  2  respectively. Deaths within 30 days of last treatment occurred in 4.0% of patients treated with 60 mg/m  2  compared to 5.3% and 1.6% for patients treated at 75 mg/m  2  and 100 mg/m  2  respectively.
 

 The following adverse reactions were associated with increasing docetaxel doses: fluid retention (26%, 38%, and 46% at 60 mg/m  2  , 75 mg/m  2  , and 100 mg/m  2  respectively), thrombocytopenia (7%, 11% and 12% respectively), neutropenia (92%, 94%, and 97% respectively), febrile neutropenia (5%, 7%, and 14% respectively), treatment-related grade 3/4 infection (2%, 3%, and 7% respectively) and anemia (87%, 94%, and 97% respectively).



   

    Combination therapy with docetaxel in the adjuvant treatment of breast cancer  



 The following table presents treatment emergent adverse reactions observed in 744 patients, who were treated with docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  every 3 weeks in combination with doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide (see  Table 7  ).



 Table 7- Clinically Important Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions Regardless of Causal Relationship in Patients Receiving Docetaxel in Combination with Doxorubicin and Cyclophosphamide (TAX316). 
                                           Docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  + Doxorubicin 50 mg/m  2  + Cyclophosphamide 500 mg/m  2  (TAC)n=744%  Fluorouracil 500 mg/m  2  +Doxorubicin 50 mg/m  2  + Cyclophosphamide 500 mg/m  2  (FAC)n=736%   
 Adverse Reaction                                Any           Grade 3/4           Any           Grade 3/4      
  
   Anemia                                        92                4               72                2          
   Neutropenia                                   71               66               82               49          
   Fever in absence of infection                 47                1               17                0          
   Infection                                     39                4               36                2          
   Thrombocytopenia                              39                2               28                1          
   Febrile neutropenia                           25               N/A               3               N/A         
   Neutropenic infection                         12               N/A               6               N/A         
   Hypersensitivity reactions                    13                1                4                0          
   Lymphedema                                     4                0                1                0          
   Fluid Retention                               35                1               15                0          
 Peripheral edema                                27                0                7                0          
 Weight gain                                     13                0                9                0          
   Neuropathy sensory                            26                0               10                0          
   Neuro-cortical                                 5                1                6                1          
   Neuropathy motor                               4                0                2                0          
   Neuro-cerebellar                               2                0                2                0          
   Syncope                                        2                1                1                0          
   Alopecia                                      98               N/A              97               N/A         
   Skin toxicity                                 27                1               18                0          
   Nail disorders                                19                0               14                0          
   Nausea                                        81                5               88               10          
   Stomatitis                                    69                7               53                2          
   Vomiting                                      45                4               59                7          
   Diarrhea                                      35                4               28                2          
   Constipation                                  34                1               32                1          
   Taste perversion                              28                1               15                0          
   Anorexia                                      22                2               18                1          
   Abdominal Pain                                11                1                5                0          
   Amenorrhea                                    62               N/A              52               N/A         
   Cough                                         14                0               10                0          
   Cardiac dysrhythmias                           8                0                6                0          
   Vasodilatation                                27                1               21                1          
   Hypotension                                    2                0                1                0          
   Phlebitis                                      1                0                1                0          
   Asthenia                                      81               11               71                6          
   Myalgia                                       27                1               10                0          
   Arthralgia                                    19                1                9                0          
   Lacrimation disorder                          11                0                7                0          
   Conjunctivitis                                 5                0                7                0          
           Of the 744 patients treated with TAC, 36.3% experienced severe treatment emergent adverse reactions compared to 26.6% of the 736 patients treated with FAC. Dose reductions due to hematologic toxicity occurred in 1% of cycles in the TAC arm versus 0.1% of cycles in the FAC arm. Six percent of patients treated with TAC discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions, compared to 1.1% treated with FAC; fever in the absence of infection and allergy being the most common reasons for withdrawal among TAC-treated patients. Two patients died in each arm within 30 days of their last study treatment; 1 death per arm was attributed to study drugs.
 

   

    Fever and Infection  



 Fever in the absence of infection was seen in 46.5% of TAC-treated patients and in 17.1% of FAC-treated patients. Grade 3/4 fever in the absence of infection was seen in 1.3% and 0% of TAC- and FAC-treated patients respectively. Infection was seen in 39.4% of TAC-treated patients compared to 36.3% of FAC-treated patients. Grade 3/4 infection was seen in 3.9% and 2.2% of TAC-treated and FAC-treated patients respectively. There were no septic deaths in either treatment arm.



   

    Gastrointestinal Reactions  



 In addition to gastrointestinal reactions reflected in the table above, 7 patients in the TAC arm were reported to have colitis/enteritis/large intestine perforation vs. one patient in the FAC arm. Five of the 7 TAC-treated patients required treatment discontinuation; no deaths due to these events occurred.



   

    Cardiovascular Reactions  



 More cardiovascular reactions were reported in the TAC arm vs. the FAC arm; dysrhythmias, all grades (7.9% vs. 6.0%), hypotension, all grades (2.6% vs. 1.1%) and CHF (2.3% vs. 0.9%, at 70 months median follow-up). One patient in each arm died due to heart failure.



   

    Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)  



 Treatment-related acute myeloid leukemia or myelodysplasia is known to occur in patients treated with anthracyclines and/or cyclophosphamide, including use in adjuvant therapy for breast cancer. AML occurs at a higher frequency when these agents are given in combination with radiation therapy. AML occurred in the adjuvant breast cancer trial (TAX316). The cumulative risk of developing treatment-related AML at 5 years in TAX316 was 0.4% for TAC treated patients and 0.1% for FAC-treated patients. This risk of AML is comparable to the risk observed for other anthracyclines/cyclophosphamide containing adjuvant breast chemotherapy regimens.



   

    Lung Cancer  



   

    Monotherapy with docetaxel for unresectable, locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC previously treated with platinum-based chemotherapy  



 Docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  : Treatment emergent adverse drug reactions are shown in  Table 8  . Included in this table are safety data for a total of 176 patients with non-small cell lung carcinoma and a history of prior treatment with platinum-based chemotherapy who were treated in two randomized, controlled trials. These reactions were described using NCI Common Toxicity Criteria regardless of relationship to study treatment, except for the hematologic toxicities or where otherwise noted.



 Table 8 - Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Treatment in Patients Receiving Docetaxel as Monotherapy for Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Previously Treated with Platinum-Based Chemotherapy Normal Baseline LFTs: Transaminases &lt;=1.5 times ULN or alkaline phosphatase &lt;=2.5 times ULN or isolated elevations of transaminases or alkaline phosphatase up to 5 times ULN 
 Adverse Reaction                    Docetaxel75 mg/m  2  n=176%  Best Supportive Caren=49%  Vinorelbine/Ifosfamiden=119%   
  
   Neutropenia                                                                                                
   Any                                         84                      14                      83             
   Grade 3/4                                   65                      12                      57             
   Leukopenia                                                                                                 
   Any                                         84                      6                       89             
   Grade 3/4                                   49                      0                       43             
   Thrombocytopenia                                                                                           
   Any                                         8                       0                       8              
   Grade 3/4                                   3                       0                       2              
   Anemia                                                                                                     
   Any                                         91                      55                      91             
   Grade 3/4                                   9                       12                      14             
   Febrile Neutropenia                         6                       NA                      1              
   Infection                                                                                                  
   Any                                         34                      29                      30             
   Grade 3/4                                   10                      6                       9              
   Treatment Related Mortality                 3                       NA                      3              
   Hypersensitivity Reactions                                                                                 
   Any                                         6                       0                       1              
   Grade 3/4                                   3                       0                       0              
   Fluid Retention                                                                                            
   Any                                         3                       ND                      23             
   Severe                                      3                                               3              
   Neurosensory                                                                                               
   Any                                         23                      14                      29             
   Grade 3/4                                   2                       6                       5              
   Neuromotor                                                                                                 
   Any                                         16                      8                       10             
   Grade 3/4                                   5                       6                       3              
   Skin                                                                                                       
   Any                                         20                      6                       17             
   Grade 3/4                                   1                       2                       1              
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                           
   Nausea                                                                                                     
     Any                                       34                      31                      31             
     Grade 3/4                                 5                       4                       8              
   Vomiting                                                                                                   
     Any                                       22                      27                      22             
     Grade 3/4                                 3                       2                       6              
   Diarrhea                                                                                                   
     Any                                       23                      6                       12             
 Grade 3/4                                     3                       0                       4              
   Alopecia                                    56                      35                      50             
   Asthenia                                                                                                   
   Any                                         53                      57                      54             
   Severe                                      18                      39                      23             
   Stomatitis                                                                                                 
   Any                                         26                      6                       8              
   Grade 3/4                                   2                       0                       1              
   Pulmonary                                                                                                  
   Any                                         41                      49                      45             
   Grade 3/4                                   21                      29                      19             
   Nail Disorder                                                                                              
   Any                                         11                      0                       2              
   Severe                                      1                       0                       0              
   Myalgia                                                                                                    
   Any                                         6                       0                       3              
   Severe                                      0                       0                       0              
   Arthralgia                                                                                                 
   Any                                         3                       2                       2              
   Severe                                      0                       0                       1              
   Taste Perversion                                                                                           
   Any                                         6                       0                       0              
   Severe                                      1                       0                       0              
            
     Combination therapy with docetaxel in chemotherapy-naive advanced unresectable or metastatic NSCLC  



   Table 9  presents safety data from two arms of an open label, randomized controlled trial (TAX326) that enrolled patients with unresectable stage IIIB or IV non-small cell lung cancer and no history of prior chemotherapy. Adverse reactions were described using the NCI Common Toxicity Criteria except where otherwise noted.



 Table 9 - Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Treatment in Chemotherapy- Naive Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Patients Receiving Docetaxel in Combination with Cisplatin 
 Adverse Reaction                                    Docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  + Cisplatin75 mg/m  2  n=406%  Vinorelbine 25 mg/m  2  + Cisplatin 100 mg/m  2  n=396%   
  
   Neutropenia                                                                                              
   Any                                                          91                         90               
   Grade 3/4                                                    74                         78               
   Febrile Neutropenia                                           5                          5               
   Thrombocytopenia                                                                                         
   Any                                                          15                         15               
   Grade 3/4                                                     3                          4               
   Anemia                                                                                                   
   Any                                                          89                         94               
   Grade 3/4                                                     7                         25               
   Infection                                                                                                
   Any                                                          35                         37               
   Grade 3/4                                                     8                          8               
   Fever in absence of infection                                                                            
   Any                                                          33                         29               
   Grade 3/4                                                    &lt; 1                         1               
   Hypersensitivity Reaction                                                                                
   Any                                                          12                          4               
   Grade 3/4                                                     3                         &lt; 1              
   Fluid Retention                                                                                          
   Any                                                          54                         42               
   All severe or life-threatening events                         2                          2               
 Pleural effusion                                                                                           
   Any                                                          23                         22               
   All severe or life-threatening events                         2                          2               
 Peripheral edema                                                                                           
   Any                                                          34                         18               
   All severe or life-threatening events                        &lt;1                         &lt;1               
 Weight gain                                                                                                
   Any                                                          15                          9               
   All severe or life-threatening events                        &lt;1                         &lt;1               
   Neurosensory                                                                                             
   Any                                                          47                         42               
   Grade 3/4                                                     4                          4               
   Neuromotor                                                                                               
   Any                                                          19                         17               
   Grade 3/4                                                     3                          6               
   Skin                                                                                                     
   Any                                                          16                         14               
   Grade 3/4                                                    &lt;1                          1               
   Nausea                                                                                                   
   Any                                                          72                         76               
   Grade 3/4                                                    10                         17               
   Vomiting                                                                                                 
   Any                                                          55                         61               
   Grade 3/4                                                     8                         16               
   Diarrhea                                                                                                 
   Any                                                          47                         25               
   Grade 3/4                                                     7                          3               
   Anorexia                                                                                                 
   Any                                                          42                         40               
   All severe or life-threatening events                         5                          5               
   Stomatitis                                                                                               
   Any                                                          24                         21               
   Grade 3/4                                                     2                          1               
   Alopecia                                                                                                 
   Any                                                          75                         42               
   Grade 3                                                      &lt;1                          0               
   Asthenia                                                                                                 
   Any                                                          74                         75               
   All severe or life-threatening events                        12                         14               
   Nail Disorder                                                                                            
   Any                                                          14                         &lt;1               
   All severe events                                            &lt;1                          0               
   Myalgia                                                                                                  
   Any                                                          18                         12               
   All severe events                                            &lt;1                         &lt;1               
         Deaths within 30 days of last study treatment occurred in 31 patients (7.6%) in the docetaxel+cisplatin arm and 37 patients (9.3%) in the vinorelbine+cisplatin arm. Deaths within 30 days of last study treatment attributed to study drug occurred in 9 patients (2.2%) in the docetaxel+cisplatin arm and 8 patients (2.0%) in the vinorelbine+cisplatin arm.
 

 The second comparison in the study, vinorelbine+cisplatin versus docetaxel + carboplatin (which did not demonstrate a superior survival associated with docetaxel,    [see  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]    ) demonstrated a higher incidence of thrombocytopenia, diarrhea, fluid retention, hypersensitivity reactions, skin toxicity, alopecia and nail changes on the docetaxel + carboplatin arm, while a higher incidence of anemia, neurosensory toxicity, nausea, vomiting, anorexia and asthenia was observed on the vinorelbine+cisplatin arm.



   

      Prostate Cancer    



   

    Combination therapy with docetaxel in patients with prostate cancer  



 The following data are based on the experience of 332 patients, who were treated with docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  every 3 weeks in combination with prednisone 5 mg orally twice daily (see  Table 10  ).



 Table 10 - Clinically Important Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions (Regardless of Relationship) in Patients with Prostate Cancer who Received Docetaxel in Combination with Prednisone (TAX327) 
                                           Docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  every 3 weeks + prednisone 5 mg twice dailyn=332%  Mitoxantrone 12 mg/m  2  every 3 weeks + prednisone 5 mg twice dailyn=335%   
 Adverse Reaction                                Any           Grade 3/4           Any           Grade 3/4      
  
   Anemia                                        67                5               58                2          
   Neutropenia                                   41               32               48               22          
   Thrombocytopenia                               3                1                8                1          
   Febrile neutropenia                            3               N/A               2               N/A         
   Infection                                     32                6               20                4          
   Epistaxis                                      6                0                2                0          
   Allergic Reactions                             8                1                1                0          
   Fluid Retention                               24                1                5                0          
 Weight Gain                                      8                0                3                0          
 Peripheral Edema                                18                0                2                0          
   Neuropathy Sensory                            30                2                7                0          
   Neuropathy Motor                               7                2                3                1          
   Rash/Desquamation                              6                0                3                1          
   Alopecia                                      65               N/A              13               N/A         
   Nail Changes                                  30                0                8                0          
   Nausea                                        41                3               36                2          
   Diarrhea                                      32                2               10                1          
   Stomatitis/Pharyngitis                        20                1                8                0          
   Taste Disturbance                             18                0                7                0          
   Vomiting                                      17                2               14                2          
   Anorexia                                      17                1               14                0          
   Cough                                         12                0                8                0          
   Dyspnea                                       15                3                9                1          
   Cardiac left ventricular function             10                0               22                1          
   Fatigue                                       53                5               35                5          
   Myalgia                                       15                0               13                1          
   Tearing                                       10                1                2                0          
   Arthralgia                                     8                1                5                1          
             
     Gastric Cancer  



   

    Combination therapy with docetaxel in gastric adenocarcinoma  



 Data in the following table are based on the experience of 221 patients with advanced gastric adenocarcinoma and no history of prior chemotherapy for advanced disease, who were treated with docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  in combination with cisplatin and fluorouracil (see  Table 11  ).



 Table 11 - Clinically Important Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Treatment in the Gastric Cancer Study 
                                           Docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  +cisplatin 75 mg/m  2  +fluorouracil 750 mg/m  2  n=221  Cisplatin 100 mg/m  2  +fluorouracil 1000 mg/m  2  n=224   
 Adverse Reaction                               Any%          Grade 3/4%          Any%          Grade 3/4%      
  
 Clinically important treatment emergent adverse reactions were determined based upon frequency, severity, and clinical impact of the adverse reaction.   
  
   Anemia                                        97               18               93               26          
   Neutropenia                                   96               82               83               57          
   Fever in the absence of infection             36                2               23                1          
   Thrombocytopenia                              26                8               39               14          
   Infection                                     29               16               23               10          
   Febrile neutropenia                           16               N/A               5               N/A         
   Neutropenic infection                         16               N/A              10               N/A         
   Allergic reactions                            10                2                6                0          
   Fluid retention                               15                0                4                0          
   Edema                                         13                0                3                0          
   Lethargy                                      63               21               58               18          
   Neurosensory                                  38                8               25                3          
   Neuromotor                                     9                3                8                3          
   Dizziness                                     16                5                8                2          
   Alopecia                                      67                5               41                1          
   Rash/itch                                     12                1                9                0          
   Nail changes                                   8                0                0                0          
   Skin desquamation                              2                0                0                0          
   Nausea                                        73               16               76               19          
   Vomiting                                      67               15               73               19          
   Anorexia                                      51               13               54               12          
   Stomatitis                                    59               21               61               27          
   Diarrhea                                      78               20               50                8          
   Constipation                                  25                2               34                3          
   Esophagitis/dysphagia/odynophagia             16                2               14                5          
   Gastrointestinal pain/cramping                11                2                7                3          
   Cardiac dysrhythmias                           5                2                2                1          
   Myocardial ischemia                            1                0                3                2          
   Tearing                                        8                0                2                0          
   Altered hearing                                6                0               13                2          
             
     Head and Neck Cancer  



   

    Combination therapy with docetaxel in head and neck cancer  



   Table 12  summarizes the safety data obtained from patients that received induction chemotherapy with docetaxel 75 mg/m  2  in combination with cisplatin and fluorouracil followed by radiotherapy (TAX323; 174 patients) or chemoradiotherapy (TAX324; 251 patients). The treatment regimens are described in Section 14.6.



 Table 12 - Clinically Important Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions (Regardless of Relationship) in Patients with SCCHN Receiving Induction Chemotherapy with Docetaxel in Combination with cisplatin and fluorouracil followed by radiotherapy (TAX323) or chemoradiotherapy (TAX324) 
                       TAX323(n=355)  TAX324(n=494)   
 Docetaxel arm (n=174)  Comparator arm (n=181)  Docetaxel arm (n=251)  Comparator arm (n=243)   
 Adverse Reaction(by Body System)     Any%     Grade3/4%      Any%     Grade3/4%      Any%     Grade3/4%      Any%     Grade3/4%    
  
 Clinically important treatment emergent adverse reactions based upon frequency, severity, and clinical impact.   
  
   Neutropenia             93          76          87          53          95          84          84          56       
   Anemia                  89          9           88          14          90          12          86          10       
   Thrombocytopenia        24          5           47          18          28          4           31          11       
   Infection               27          9           26          8           23          6           28          5        
   Febrile neutropenia        5          N/A          2          N/A          12         N/A          7          N/A       
   Neutropenic infection        14         N/A          8          N/A          12         N/A          8          N/A       
   Cancer pain             21          5           16          3           17          9           20          11       
   Lethargy                41          3           38          3           61          5           56          10       
   Fever in the absence of infection        32          1           37          0           30          4           28          3        
   Myalgia                 10          1           7           0           7           0           7           2        
   Weight loss             21          1           27          1           14          2           14          2        
   Allergy                 6           0           3           0           2           0           0           0        
   Fluid retention         20          0           14          1           13          1           7           2        
   Edema only              13          0           7           0           12          1           6           1        
   Weight gain only        6           0           6           0           0           0           1           0        
   Dizziness               2           0           5           1           16          4           15          2        
   Neurosensory            18          1           11          1           14          1           14          0        
   Altered hearing         6           0           10          3           13          1           19          3        
   Neuromotor              2           1           4           1           9           0           10          2        
   Alopecia                81          11          43          0           68          4           44          1        
   Rash/itch               12          0           6           0           20          0           16          1        
   Dry skin                6           0           2           0           5           0           3           0        
   Desquamation            4           1           6           0           2           0           5           0        
   Nausea                  47          1           51          7           77          14          80          14       
   Stomatitis              43          4           47          11          66          21          68          27       
   Vomiting                26          1           39          5           56          8           63          10       
   Diarrhea                33          3           24          4           48          7           40          3        
   Constipation            17          1           16          1           27          1           38          1        
   Anorexia                16          1           25          3           40          12          34          12       
   Esophagitis/dysphagia/    Odynophagia        13          1           18          3           25          13          26          10       
   Taste, sense of smell altered        10          0           5           0           20          0           17          1        
   Gastrointestinal pain/cramping        8           1           9           1           15          5           10          2        
   Heartburn               6           0           6           0           13          2           13          1        
   Gastrointestinal bleeding        4           2           0           0           5           1           2           1        
   Cardiac dysrhythmia        2           2           2           1           6           3           5           3        
   Venous                  3           2           6           2           4           2           5           4        
   Ischemia myocardial        2           2           1           0           2           1           1           1        
   Tearing                 2           0           1           0           2           0           2           0        
   Conjunctivitis          1           0           1           0           1           0          0.4          0        
                 6.2 Post-Marketing Experiences
   The following adverse reactions have been identified from clinical trials and/or post-marketing surveillance. Because they are reported from a population of unknown size, precise estimates of frequency cannot be made.



   Body as a whole  : diffuse pain, chest pain, radiation recall phenomenon.



   Cardiovascular  : atrial fibrillation, deep vein thrombosis, ECG abnormalities, thrombophlebitis, pulmonary embolism, syncope, tachycardia, myocardial infarction.



   Cutaneous  : very rare cases of cutaneous lupus erythematosus and rare cases of bullous eruptions such as erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and Scleroderma-like changes usually preceded by peripheral lymphedema. In some cases multiple factors may have contributed to the development of these effects. Severe hand and foot syndrome has been reported.



   Gastrointestinal  : abdominal pain, anorexia, constipation, duodenal ulcer, esophagitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastrointestinal perforation, ischemic colitis, colitis, intestinal obstruction, ileus, neutropenic enterocolitis and dehydration as a consequence to gastrointestinal events have been reported.



   Hematologic  : bleeding episodes. Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), often in association with sepsis or multiorgan failure, has been reported. Cases of acute myeloid leukemia and myelodysplasic syndrome have been reported in association with docetaxel when used in combination with other chemotherapy agents and/or radiotherapy.



   Hypersensitivity  : rare cases of anaphylactic shock have been reported. Very rarely these cases resulted in a fatal outcome in patients who received premedication.



   Hepatic  : rare cases of hepatitis, sometimes fatal primarily in patients with pre-existing liver disorders, have been reported.



   Neurologic  : confusion, rare cases of seizures or transient loss of consciousness have been observed, sometimes appearing during the infusion of the drug.



   Ophthalmologic  :conjunctivitis, lacrimation or lacrimation with or without conjunctivitis. Excessive tearing which may be attributable to lacrimal duct obstruction has been reported. Rare cases of transient visual disturbances (flashes, flashing lights, scotomata) typically occurring during drug infusion and in association with hypersensitivity reactions have been reported. These were reversible upon discontinuation of the infusion. Cases of cystoid macular edema (CME) have been reported in patients treated with Docetaxel Injection.



   Hearing  : rare cases of ototoxicity, hearing disorders and/or hearing loss have been reported, including cases associated with other ototoxic drugs.



   Respiratory  : dyspnea, acute pulmonary edema, acute respiratory distress syndrome/pneumonitis, interstitial lung disease, interstitial pneumonia, respiratory failure, and pulmonary fibrosis have rarely been reported and may be associated with fatal outcome. Rare cases of radiation pneumonitis have been reported in patients receiving concomitant radiotherapy.



   Renal  : renal insufficiency and renal failure have been reported, the majority of these cases were associated with concomitant nephrotoxic drugs.



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders  : cases of hyponatremia have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:TOXIC DEATHS, HEPATOTOXICITY, NEUTROPENIA,

      



  HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, AND FLUID RETENTION

     



  WARNING:TOXIC DEATHS, HEPATOTOXICITY, NEUTROPENIA,

      



  HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, AND FLUID RETENTION

     



  The incidence of treatment-related mortality associated with docetaxel therapy is increased in patients with abnormal liver function, in patients receiving higher doses, and in patients with non-small   cell   lung   carcinoma   and   a   history   of   prior   treatment   with   platinum-based chemotherapy who receive docetaxel as a single agent at a dose of 100 mg/m

       

 

    2      [see 

        

   

      Warnings and

Precautions (5.1)  ].

       

  

       



 Docetaxel Injection  should not

be given to patients with bilirubin &gt; upper limit of normal (ULN),

or to patients with AST and/or ALT &gt;1.5 * ULN concomitant with

alkaline phosphatase &gt;2.5 * ULN. Patients with elevations of

bilirubin or abnormalities of transaminase concurrent with alkaline

phosphatase are at increased risk for the development of grade 4 neutropenia,

febrile neutropenia, infections, severe thrombocytopenia, severe stomatitis,

severe skin toxicity, and toxic death. Patients with isolated elevations

of transaminase &gt;1.5 * ULN also had a higher rate of febrile

neutropenia grade 4 but did not have an increased incidence of toxic

death. Bilirubin, AST or ALT, and alkaline phosphatase values should

be obtained prior to each cycle of Docetaxel Injection  therapy



       

 

      

[see

        

   

       Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  

       

  

       



 Docetaxel Injection  therapy should not be given to patients with neutrophil

counts of &lt;1500 cells/mm

       

 

    3  . In order to monitor the occurrence

of neutropenia, which may be severe and result in infection, frequent

blood cell counts should be performed on all patients receiving Docetaxel Injection .



       

 

      

[see

        

   

       Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  

       

  

       



 Severe hypersensitivity reactions

characterized by generalized rash/erythema, hypotension and/or bronchospasm,

or very rarely fatal anaphylaxis, have been reported in patients who

received a 3-day dexamethasone premedication. Hypersensitivity

reactions require immediate discontinuation of the Docetaxel Injection  infusion

and administration of appropriate therapy 

       

 

      [see 

        

   

      Warnings and

Precautions (5.4)  ]

       

  

       . Docetaxel Injection  must not be given

to patients who have a history of severe hypersensitivity reactions

to docetaxel or to other drugs formulated with polysorbate 80 

       

 

      [see 

        

   

      Contraindications

(4)  ]

       

  

       .

      



 



 Severe fluid retention occurred in 6.5% (6/92) of patients despite

use of a 3-day dexamethasone premedication regimen. It was characterized

by one or more of the following events: poorly tolerated peripheral

edema, generalized edema, pleural effusion requiring urgent drainage,

dyspnea at rest, cardiac tamponade, or pronounced abdominal distention

(due to ascites) 

       

 

      [see 

        

   

      Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].

       

  

       



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:TOXIC DEATHS, HEPATOTOXICITY, NEUTROPENIA, HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, AND FLUID RETENTION   



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Treatment-related mortality increases with abnormal liver function, at higher doses, and in patients with NSCLC and prior platinum-based therapy receiving docetaxel at 100 mg/m 2 ( 5.1) 
 *  Should not be given if bilirubin &gt; ULN, or if AST and/or ALT &gt; 1.5 * ULN concomitant with alkaline phosphatase &gt; 2.5 * ULN. LFT elevations increase risk of severe or life-threatening complications. Obtain LFTs before each treatment cycle ( 8.6) 
 *  Should not be given if neutrophil counts are &lt; 1500 cells/mm 3. Obtain frequent blood counts to monitor for neutropenia ( 4) 
 *  Severe hypersensitivity, including very rare fatal anaphylaxis, has been reported in patients who received dexamethasone premedication. Severe reactions require immediate discontinuation of Docetaxel Injection and administration of appropriate therapy ( 5.4) 
 *  Contraindicated if history of severe hypersensitivity reactions to docetaxel or to drugs formulated with polysorbate 80 ( 4) 
 *  Severe fluid retention may occur despite dexamethasone ( 5.5) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute myeloid leukemia: In patients who received docetaxel, doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide, monitor for delayed myelodysplasia or myeloid leukemia (  5.6  ) 
 *  Cutaneous reactions: Reactions including erythema of the extremities with edema followed by desquamation may occur. Severe skin toxicity may require dose adjustment (  5.7  ) 
 *  Neurologic reactions: Reactions including. paresthesia, dysesthesia, and pain may occur. Severe neurosensory symptoms require dose adjustment or discontinuation if persistent. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Eye disorders: Cystoid macular edema (CME) has been reported and requires treatment discontinuation. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Asthenia: Severe asthenia may occur and may require treatment discontinuation. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Pregnancy: Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women of childbearing potential should be advised not to become pregnant when receiving Docetaxel Injection (  5.11  ,  8.1  ) 
 *  Alcohol content: The alcohol content in a dose of Docetaxel Injection may affect the central nervous system. This may include impairment of a patient's ability to drive or use machines immediately after infusion. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Toxic Deaths



   



   Breast Cancer  



 Docetaxel administered at 100 mg/m  2  was associated with deaths considered possibly or probably related to treatment in 2.0% (19/965) of metastatic breast cancer patients, both previously treated and untreated, with normal baseline liver function and in 11.5% (7/61) of patients with various tumor types who had abnormal baseline liver function (AST and/or ALT &gt;1.5 times ULN together with AP &gt;2.5 times ULN). Among patients dosed at 60 mg/m  2  , mortality related to treatment occurred in 0.6% (3/481) of patients with normal liver function, and in 3 of 7 patients with abnormal liver function. Approximately half of these deaths occurred during the first cycle. Sepsis accounted for the majority of the deaths.



    



   Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer  



 Docetaxel administered at a dose of 100 mg/m  2  in patients with locally advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer who had a history of prior platinum-based chemotherapy was associated with increased treatment-related mortality (14% and 5% in two randomized, controlled studies). There were 2.8% treatment-related deaths among the 176 patients treated at the 75 mg/m  2  dose in the randomized trials. Among patients who experienced treatment-related mortality at the 75 mg/m  2  dose level, 3 of 5 patients had an ECOG PS of 2 at study entry  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ,  Clinical Studies (14)  ].    



    5.2 Hepatic Impairment



  Patients with combined abnormalities of transaminases and alkaline phosphatase should not be treated with Docetaxel Injection  [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ,  Clinical studies (14)  ].    



    5.3 Hematologic Effects



  Perform frequent peripheral blood cell counts on all patients receiving Docetaxel Injection. Patients should not be retreated with subsequent cycles of Docetaxel Injection until neutrophils recover to a level &gt;1500 cells/mm  3  and platelets recover to a level &gt;100,000 cells/mm  3  .



 A 25% reduction in the dose of Docetaxel Injection is recommended during subsequent cycles following severe neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  ) lasting 7 days or more, febrile neutropenia, or a grade 4 infection in a Docetaxel Injection cycle  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.7)  ].    



 Neutropenia (&lt;2000 neutrophils/mm  3  ) occurs in virtually all patients given 60 mg/m  2  to 100 mg/m  2  of docetaxel and grade 4 neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  ) occurs in 85% of patients given 100 mg/m  2  and 75% of patients given 60 mg/m  2  . Frequent monitoring of blood counts is, therefore, essential so that dose can be adjusted. Docetaxel Injection should not be administered to patients with neutrophils &lt;1500 cells/mm  3  .



 Febrile neutropenia occurred in about 12% of patients given 100 mg/m  2  but was very uncommon in patients given 60 mg/m  2  . Hematologic responses, febrile reactions and infections, and rates of septic death for different regimens are dose related  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1),    Clinical Studies (14)  ].    



 Three breast cancer patients with severe liver impairment (bilirubin &gt;1.7 times ULN) developed fatal gastrointestinal bleeding associated with severe drug-induced thrombocytopenia. In gastric cancer patients treated with docetaxel in combination with cisplatin and fluorouracil (TCF), febrile neutropenia and/or neutropenic infection occurred in 12% of patients receiving G-CSF compared to 28% who did not. Patients receiving TCF should be closely monitored during the first and subsequent cycles for febrile neutropenia and neutropenic infection  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.7)  ,  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]    



    5.4 Hypersensitivity reaction



  Patients should be observed closely for hypersensitivity reactions, especially during the first and second infusions. Severe hypersensitivity reactions characterized by generalized rash/erythema, hypotension and/or bronchospasm, or very rarely fatal anaphylaxis, have been reported in patients premedicated with 3 days of corticosteroids. Severe hypersensitivity reactions require immediate discontinuation of the Docetaxel Injection infusion and aggressive therapy. Patients with a history of severe hypersensitivity reactions should not be rechallenged with Docetaxel Injection.



 Hypersensitivity reactions may occur within a few minutes following initiation of a Docetaxel Injection infusion. If minor reactions such as flushing or localized skin reactions occur, interruption of therapy is not required. All patients should be premedicated with an oral corticosteroid prior to the initiation of the infusion of Docetaxel Injection  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.6)  ]    



    5.5 Fluid Retention



  Severe fluid retention has been reported following docetaxel therapy. Patients should be premedicated with oral corticosteroids prior to each Docetaxel Injection administration to reduce the incidence and severity of fluid retention  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.6)  ].    Patients with pre-existing effusions should be closely monitored from the first dose for the possible exacerbation of the effusions.



 When fluid retention occurs, peripheral edema usually starts in the lower extremities and may become generalized with a median weight gain of 2 kg.



 Among 92 breast cancer patients premedicated with 3-day corticosteroids, moderate fluid retention occurred in 27.2% and severe fluid retention in 6.5%. The median cumulative dose to onset of moderate or severe fluid retention was 819 mg/m  2  . Nine of 92 patients (9.8%) of patients discontinued treatment due to fluid retention: 4 patients discontinued with severe fluid retention; the remaining 5 had mild or moderate fluid retention. The median cumulative dose to treatment discontinuation due to fluid retention was 1021 mg/m  2  . Fluid retention was completely, but sometimes slowly, reversible with a median of 16 weeks from the last infusion of docetaxel to resolution (range: 0 to 42+ weeks). Patients developing peripheral edema may be treated with standard measures, e.g., salt restriction, oral diuretic(s).



    5.6 Acute Myeloid Leukemia



  Treatment-related acute myeloid leukemia (AML) or myelodysplasia has occurred in patients given anthracyclines and/or cyclophosphamide, including use in adjuvant therapy for breast cancer. In the adjuvant breast cancer trial (TAX316) AML occurred in 3 of 744 patients who received docetaxel, doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide (TAC) and in 1 of 736 patients who received fluorouracil, doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].    In TAC-treated patients, the risk of delayed myelodysplasia or myeloid leukemia requires hematological follow-up.



    5.7 Cutaneous Reactions



     



  Localized erythema of the extremities with edema followed by desquamation has been observed. In case of severe skin toxicity, an adjustment in dosage is recommended  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.7)  ].    The discontinuation rate due to skin toxicity was 1.6% (15/965) for metastatic breast cancer patients. Among 92 breast cancer patients premedicated with 3-day corticosteroids, there were no cases of severe skin toxicity reported and no patient discontinued docetaxel due to skin toxicity.



    5.8 Neurologic Reactions



  Severe neurosensory symptoms (e.g. paresthesia, dysesthesia, pain) were observed in 5.5% (53/965) of metastatic breast cancer patients, and resulted in treatment discontinuation in 6.1%. When these symptoms occur, dosage must be adjusted. If symptoms persist, treatment should be discontinued  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.7)  ].    Patients who experienced neurotoxicity in clinical trials and for whom follow-up information on the complete resolution of the event was available had spontaneous reversal of symptoms with a median of 9 weeks from onset (range: 0 to 106 weeks). Severe peripheral motor neuropathy mainly manifested as distal extremity weakness occurred in 4.4% (42/965).



    5.9 Eye Disorders



   Cystoid macular edema (CME) has been reported in patients treated with Docetaxel Injection. Patients with impaired vision should undergo a prompt and comprehensive ophthalmologic examination. If CME is diagnosed, Docetaxel Injection treatment should be discontinued and appropriate treatment initiated. Alternative non-taxane cancer treatment should be considered.  



    5.10 Asthenia



  Severe asthenia has been reported in 14.9% (144/965) of metastatic breast cancer patients but has led to treatment discontinuation in only 1.8%. Symptoms of fatigue and weakness may last a few days up to several weeks and may be associated with deterioration of performance status in patients with progressive disease.



    5.11 Use in Pregnancy



  Docetaxel Injection can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Docetaxel caused embryofetal toxicities including intrauterine mortality when administered to pregnant rats and rabbits during the period of organogenesis. Embryofetal effects in animals occurred at doses as low as 1/50 and 1/300 the recommended human dose on a body surface area basis.



 There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women using Docetaxel Injection. If Docetaxel Injection is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while receiving this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant during therapy with Docetaxel Injection  [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].    



    5.12 Alcohol Content



   Cases of intoxication have been reported with some formulations of docetaxel due to the alcohol content. The alcohol content in a dose of Docetaxel Injection may affect the central nervous system and should be taken into account for patients in whom alcohol intake should be avoided or minimized. Consideration should be given to the alcohol content in Docetaxel Injection on the ability to drive or use machines immediately after the infusion.  



   For One-vial formulation (Injection Concentrate)  Each administration of Docetaxel Injection at 100 mg/m  2  delivers 1.975 g/m  2  of ethanol. For a patient with a BSA of 2.0 m  2  , this would deliver 3.95 grams of ethanol [ see  Description (11)    ]. Other docetaxel products may have a different amount of alcohol.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
