<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dolophine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Heroin Withdrawal

  During the induction phase of methadone maintenance treatment, patients are being withdrawn from heroin and may therefore show typical withdrawal symptoms, which should be differentiated from methadone-induced side effects. They may exhibit some or all of the following signs and symptoms associated with acute withdrawal from heroin or other opiates: lacrimation, rhinorrhea, sneezing, yawning, excessive perspiration, goose-flesh, fever, chilliness alternating with flushing, restlessness, irritability, weakness, anxiety, depression, dilated pupils, tremors, tachycardia, abdominal cramps, body aches, involuntary twitching and kicking movements, anorexia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, intestinal spasms, and weight loss.



   Initial Administration

  The initial methadone dose should be carefully titrated to the individual. Too rapid titration for the patient's sensitivity is more likely to produce adverse effects.



     The major hazards of methadone are respiratory depression and, to a lesser degree, systemic hypotension. Respiratory arrest, shock, cardiac arrest, and death have occurred.    



 The  most frequently observed adverse reactions  include lightheadedness, dizziness, sedation, nausea, vomiting, and sweating. These effects seem to be more prominent in ambulatory patients and in those who are not suffering severe pain. In such individuals, lower doses are advisable.



 Other adverse reactions include the following:



   Body as a Whole

  asthenia (weakness), edema, headache



 Cardiovascular arrhythmias, bigeminal rhythms, bradycardia, cardiomyopathy, ECG abnormalities, extrasystoles, flushing, heart failure, hypotension, palpitations, phlebitis, QT interval prolongation, syncope, T-wave inversion, tachycardia, torsade de pointes, ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia



   Digestive

  abdominal pain, anorexia, biliary tract spasm, constipation, dry mouth, glossitis



   Hematologic and Lymphatic

  reversible thrombocytopenia has been described in opioid addicts with chronic hepatitis



   Metabolic and Nutritional

  hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, weight gain



   Nervous

  agitation, confusion, disorientation, dysphoria, euphoria, insomnia, seizures



   Respiratory

  pulmonary edema, respiratory depression



   Skin and Appendages

  pruritis, urticaria, other skin rashes, and rarely, hemorrhagic urticaria



   Special Senses

  hallucinations, visual disturbances



   Urogenital

  amenorrhea, antidiuretic effect, reduced libido and/or potency, urinary retention or hesitancy



   Maintenance on a Stabilized Dose

  During prolonged administration of methadone, as in a methadone maintenance treatment program, there is usually a gradual, yet progressive, disappearance of side effects over a period of several weeks. However, constipation and sweating often persist.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

      Rx Only    



       Deaths, cardiac and respiratory, have been reported during initiation and conversion of pain patients to methadone treatment from treatment with other opioid agonists. It is critical to understand the pharmacokinetics of methadone when converting patients from other opioids (see   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ). Particular vigilance is necessary during treatment initiation, during conversion from one opioid to another, and during dose titration.    



     Respiratory depression is the chief hazard associated with methadone hydrochloride administration. Methadone's peak respiratory depressant effects typically occur later, and persist longer than its peak analgesic effects, particularly in the early dosing period. These characteristics can contribute to cases of iatrogenic overdose, particularly during treatment initiation and dose titration.    



     In addition, cases of QT interval prolongation and serious arrhythmia (torsades de pointes) have been observed during treatment with methadone. Most cases involve patients being treated for pain with large, multiple daily doses of methadone, although cases have been reported in patients receiving doses commonly used for maintenance treatment of opioid addiction.    



     Methadone treatment for analgesic therapy in patients with acute or chronic pain should only be initiated if the potential analgesic or palliative care benefit of treatment with methadone is considered and outweighs the risks.    



     Conditions For Distribution And Use Of Methadone Products For The Treatment Of Opioid Addiction    



 Code of Federal Regulations, Title 42, Sec 8



 Methadone products when used for the treatment of opioid addiction in detoxification or maintenance programs, shall be dispensed only by opioid treatment programs (and agencies, practitioners or institutions by formal agreement with the program sponsor) certified by the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration and approved by the designated state authority. Certified treatment programs shall dispense and use methadone in oral form only and according to the treatment requirements stipulated in the Federal Opioid Treatment Standards (42 CFR 8.12). See below for important regulatory exceptions to the general requirement for certification to provide opioid agonist treatment.



 Failure to abide by the requirements in these regulations may result in criminal prosecution, seizure of the drug supply, revocation of the program approval, and injunction precluding operation of the program.



   Regulatory Exceptions To The General Requirement For Certification To Provide Opioid Agonist Treatment:



 *  During inpatient care, when the patient was admitted for any condition other than concurrent opioid addiction (pursuant to 21CFR 1306.07(c)), to facilitate the treatment of the primary admitting diagnosis). 
 *  During an emergency period of no longer than 3 days while definitive care for the addiction is being sought in an appropriately licensed facility (pursuant to 21CFR 1306.07(b)). 
    
 



    BOXED WARNING: DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION

  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION

  Methadone differs from many other opioid agonists in several important ways. Methadone's pharmacokinetic properties, coupled with high interpatient variability in its absorption, metabolism, and relative analgesic potency, necessitate a cautious and highly individualized approach to prescribing.     Particular vigilance is necessary during treatment initiation, during conversion from one opioid to another, and during dose titration.    



 While methadone's duration of analgesic action (typically 4 to 8 hours) in the setting of single-dose studies approximates that of morphine, methadone's plasma elimination half-life is substantially longer than that of morphine (typically 8 to 59 hours vs. 1 to 5 hours).     Methadone's peak respiratory depressant effects typicallyoccur later, and persist longer than its peak analgesic effects.     Also, with repeated dosing, methadone may be retained in the liver and then slowly released, prolonging the duration of action despite low plasma concentrations. For these reasons, steady-state plasma concentrations, and full analgesic effects, are usually not attained until 3 to 5 days of dosing. Additionally, incomplete cross-tolerance between mu-opioid agonists makes determination of dosing during opioid conversion complex.



 The complexities associated with methadone dosing can contribute to cases of iatrogenic overdose, particularly during treatment initiation and dose titration.     A high degree of "opioid tolerance" does not eliminate the possibility of methadone overdose, iatrogenic or otherwise. Deaths have been reported during conversion to methadone from chronic, high-dose treatment with other opioid agonists and during initiation of methadone treatment of addiction in subjects previously abusing high doses of other agonists.    



   Treatment of Pain

  Optimal methadone initiation and dose titration strategies for the treatment of pain have not been determined. Published equianalgesic conversion ratios between methadone and other opioids are   imprecise  , providing at best, only population averages that cannot be applied consistently to all patients. It should be noted that many commonly cited equianalgesia tables only present relative analgesic potencies of single opioid doses in non-tolerant patients, thus greatly underestimating methadone's analgesic potency, and its potential for adverse effects in repeated-dose settings. Regardless of the dose determination strategy employed, methadone is most safely initiated and titrated using small initial doses and gradual dose adjustments.



 As with all opioid drugs, it is necessary to adjust the dosing regimen for each patient individually, taking into account the patient's prior analgesic treatment experience. The following dosing recommendations should only be considered as suggested approaches to what is actually a series of clinical decisions over time in the management of the pain of each individual patient. Prescribers should always follow appropriate pain management principles of careful assessment and ongoing monitoring.



 In the selection of an initial dose of DOLOPHINE, attention should be given to the following:



 *  The total daily dose, potency and specific characteristics of the opioid the patient had been taking previously, if any; 
 *  The relative potency estimate used to calculate an equianalgesic starting methadone dose, in particular, whether it is intended for use in acute or chronic methadone dosing; 
 *  The patient's degree of opioid tolerance; 
 *  The age, general condition and medical status of the patient; 
 *  Concurrent medications, particularly other CNS and respiratory depressants; 
 *  The type, severity and expected duration of the patient's pain; 
 *  The acceptable balance between pain control and adverse side effects. 
      Initiation of Therapy in Opioid Non-Tolerant Patients
   When oral methadone is used as the first analgesic in patients who are not already being treated with, and tolerant to, opioids, the usual oral methadone starting dose is 2.5 mg to 10 mg every 8 to 12 hours, slowly titrated to effect. More frequent administration may be required during methadone initiation in order to maintain adequate analgesia, and extreme caution is necessary to avoid overdosage, taking into account methadone's long elimination half-life. 



   Conversion from Parenteral Methadone to Oral Methadone

  Conversion from parenteral methadone to oral methadone should initially use a 1:2 dose ratio (e.g., 5 mg parenteral methadone to 10 mg oral methadone). 



   Switching Patients to Methadone from other Chronic Opioids

  Switching a patient from another chronically administered opioid to methadone requires caution due to the uncertainty of dose conversion ratios and incomplete cross-tolerance.     Deaths have occurred in opioid tolerant patients during conversion to methadone.     



 Conversion ratios in many commonly used equianalgesic dosing tables do not apply in the setting of repeated methadone dosing. Although with single-dose administration the onset and duration of analgesic action, as well as the analgesic potency of methadone and morphine, are similar methadone's potency increases over time with repeated dosing. Furthermore, the conversion ratio between methadone and other opiates varies dramatically depending on baseline opiate (morphine equivalent) use as shown in the table below. 



 The dose conversion scheme below is derived from various consensus guidelines for converting chronic pain patients to methadone from morphine. Clinicians should consult published conversion guidelines to determine the equivalent morphine dose for patients converting from other opioids.



   Table 1

    Oral Morphine to Oral Methadone Conversion for Chronic Administration 
 Total Daily Baseline OralMorphine Dose           Estimated Daily Oral Methadone Requirement as Percent of Total Daily Morphine Dose   
 &lt; 100 mg                                         20% to 30%                                             
 100 to 300 mg                                    10% to 20%                                             
 300 to 600 mg                                    8% to 12%                                              
 600 mg to 1000 mg                                5% to 10%                                              
 &gt; 1000 mg                                        &lt; 5 %                                                  
        The total daily methadone dose derived from the table above may then be divided to reflect the intended dosing schedule (i.e., for administration every 8 hours, divide total daily methadone dose by 3).
 

   Note  : Equianalgesic methadone dosing varies not only between patients, but also within the same patient, depending on baseline morphine (or other opioid) dose.   Table 1   has been included in order to illustrate this concept and to provide a safe starting point for opioid conversion. Methadone dosing should not be based solely on these tables. Methadone conversion and dose titration methods should always be individualized to account for the patient's prior opioid exposure, general medical condition, concomitant medication, and anticipated breakthrough medication use. The endpoint of titration is achievement of adequate pain relief, balanced against tolerability of opioid side effects. If a patient develops intolerable opioid related side effects, the methadone dose, or dosing interval, may need to be adjusted.



   Dosage Adjustment During Pregnancy

  Methadone clearance may be increased during pregnancy. Several small studies have demonstrated significantly lower trough methadone plasma concentrations and shorter methadone half-lives in women during their pregnancy compared to after their delivery. During pregnancy a woman's methadone dose may need to be increased, or their dosing interval decreased. Methadone should be used in pregnancy only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk to the fetus.



   For detoxification and maintenance of opiate dependence methadone should be administered in accordance with the treatment standards cited in 42 CFR Section 8.12, including limitations on unsupervised administration



   Induction/Initial Dosing

  The initial methadone dose should be administered, under supervision, when there are no signs of sedation or intoxication, and the patient shows symptoms of withdrawal. Initially, a single dose of 20 to 30 mg of methadone will often be sufficient to suppress withdrawal symptoms. The initial dose should not exceed 30 mg. If same-day dosing adjustments are to be made, the patient should be asked to wait 2 to 4 hours for further evaluation, when peak levels have been reached. An additional 5 to 10 mg of methadone may be provided if withdrawal symptoms have not been suppressed or if symptoms reappear. The total daily dose of methadone on the first day of treatment should not ordinarily exceed 40 mg. Dose adjustments should be made over the first week of treatment based on control of withdrawal symptoms at the time of expected peak activity (e.g., 2 to 4 hours after dosing). Dose adjustment should be cautious; deaths have occurred in early treatment due to the cumulative effects of the first several days' dosing. Patients should be reminded that the dose will "hold" for a longer period of time as tissue stores of methadone accumulate.



 Initial doses should be lower for patients whose tolerance is expected to be low at treatment entry. Loss of tolerance should be considered in any patient who has not taken opioids for more than 5 days. Initial doses should not be determined by previous treatment episodes or dollars spent per day on illicit drug use.



   For Short-term Detoxification

  For patients preferring a brief course of stabilization followed by a period of medically supervised withdrawal, it is generally recommended that the patient be titrated to a total daily dose of about 40 mg in divided doses to achieve an adequate stabilizing level. Stabilization can be continued for 2 to 3 days, after which the dose of methadone should be gradually decreased. The rate at which methadone is decreased should be determined separately for each patient.



 The dose of methadone can be decreased on a daily basis or at 2-day intervals, but the amount of intake should remain sufficient to keep withdrawal symptoms at a tolerable level. In hospitalized patients, a daily reduction of 20% of the total daily dose may be tolerated. In ambulatory patients, a somewhat slower schedule may be needed.



   For Maintenance Treatment

  Patients in maintenance treatment should be titrated to a dose at which opioid symptoms are prevented for 24 hours, drug hunger or craving is reduced, the euphoric effects of self-administered opioids are blocked or attenuated, and the patient is tolerant to the sedative effects of methadone. Most commonly, clinical stability is achieved at doses between 80 to 120 mg/day.



   For Medically Supervised Withdrawal After a Period of Maintenance Treatment

  There is considerable variability in the appropriate rate of methadone taper in patients choosing medically supervised withdrawal from methadone treatment. It is generally suggested that dose reductions should be less than 10% of the established tolerance or maintenance dose, and that 10 to 14-day intervals should elapse between dose reductions. Patients should be apprised of the high risk of relapse to illicit drug use associated with discontinuation of methadone maintenance treatment.



 





    BOXED WARNING: PATIENT INFORMATION

  PATIENT INFORMATION

      DOLOPHINE(r) HYDROCHLORIDE CII    



     (Methadone Hydrochloride Tablets, USP), 5 mg and 10 mg    



       WARNINGS:     



     Keep DOLOPHINE out of the reach of children. Accidental overdose by a child is a medical emergency and can result in death. If a child accidentally takes DOLOPHINE, get emergency help right away.    



       Do not take a higher dose of DOLOPHINE or take it more often than prescribed. This can lead to an overdose and possible death.      



   Read the Patient Information that comes with DOLOPHINE before you take it and each time you get a new prescription. There may be new information. This leaflet does not take the place of talking with your doctor about your medical condition or your treatment. Share the important information in this leaflet with members of your household. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
