<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="doryx" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions observed in patients receiving tetracyclines include anorexia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, rash, photosensitivity, urticaria, and hemolytic anemia. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Warner Chilcott at 1-800-521-8813 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  The safety and efficacy of DORYX Tablets, 200 mg as a single daily dose was evaluated in a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, active-controlled study. DORYX Tablets, 200 mg was given orally once-a-day for 7 days and compared to doxycycline hyclate capsules 100 mg given orally twice daily for 7 days for the treatment of men and women with uncomplicated urogenital  C. trachomatis  infection.



 Adverse events in the Safety Population were reported by 99 (40.2 %) subjects in the DORYX Tablets, 200 mg treatment group and 132 (53.2 %) subjects in the doxycycline hyclate capsules reference treatment group. Most AEs were mild in intensity. The most commonly reported adverse events in both treatment groups were nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and bacterial vaginitis,  Table 1  .



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Greater than or Equal to 2% of Subjects 
               DORYX Tablets,  200 mgN = 246               
  Preferred Term   n (%)                                        
  Subjects with any AE   99 (40.2)                                    
              Nausea                                      33 (13.4)                                       
              Vomiting                                    20 (8.1)                                        
              Headache                                    5 (2.0)                                         
              Diarrhea                                    8 (3.3)                                         
              Abdominal Pain Upper                        5 (2.0)                                         
              Vaginitis Bacterial                         8 (3.3)                                         
              Vulvovaginal Mycotic Infection              5 (2.0)                                         
         Because clinical trials are conducted under prescribed conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trial may not always reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Due to oral doxycycline's virtually complete absorption, side effects to the lower bowel, particularly diarrhea, have been infrequent. The following adverse reactions have been observed in patients receiving tetracyclines:



   Gastrointestinal  : Anorexia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, glossitis, dysphagia, enterocolitis, and inflammatory lesions (with monilial overgrowth) in the anogenital region. Hepatotoxicity has been reported. These reactions have been caused by both the oral and parenteral administration of tetracyclines. Esophagitis and esophageal ulcerations have been reported in patients receiving capsule and tablet forms of drugs in the tetracycline-class. Most of these patients took medications immediately before going to bed [  see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )  ].



   Skin  : Maculopapular and erythematous rashes, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, exfoliative dermatitis,  and erythema multiforme have been reported. Photosensitivity is discussed above [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )  ].



   Renal  : Rise in BUN has been reported and is apparently dose-related [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )  ].



   Hypersensitivity reactions  : Urticaria, angioneurotic edema, anaphylaxis, anaphylactoid purpura, serum sickness, pericarditis, and exacerbation of systemic lupus erythematosus.



   Blood  : Hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, and eosinophilia have been reported.



   Benign Intracranial Hypertension  



 Bulging fontanels in infants and benign intracranial hypertension in adults [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )  ].



   Thyroid Gland Changes  : When given over prolonged periods, tetracyclines have been reported to produce brown-black microscopic discoloration of thyroid glands. No abnormalities of thyroid function are known to occur.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  The use of drugs of the tetracycline-class during tooth development (last half of pregnancy, infancy and childhood to the age of 8 years) may cause permanent discoloration of the teeth (yellow-gray-brown). (  5.1  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea: Evaluate patients if diarrhea occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Photosensitivity manifested by an exaggerated sunburn reaction has been observed in some individuals taking tetracyclines. Limit sun exposure. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Overgrowth of non-susceptible organisms, including fungi, may occur. Re-evaluate therapy if superinfection occurs. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Tooth Development



  The use of drugs of the tetracycline-class during tooth development (last half of pregnancy, infancy and childhood to the age of 8 years) may cause permanent discoloration of the teeth (yellow-gray-brown). This adverse reaction is more common during long-term use of the drugs but it has been observed following repeated short-term courses. Enamel hypoplasia has also been reported. Doxycycline should not be used in this age group, except for anthrax, including inhalational anthrax (post-exposure), unless other drugs are not likely to be effective or are contraindicated.



    5.2 Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including DORYX Tablets, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibacterial use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.3 Photosensitivity



  Photosensitivity manifested by an exaggerated sunburn reaction has been observed in some individuals taking tetracyclines. Patients apt to be exposed to direct sunlight or ultraviolet light should be advised that this reaction can occur with tetracycline drugs, and treatment should be discontinued at the first evidence of skin erythema.



    5.4 Superinfection



  As with other antibacterial preparations, use of DORYX may result in overgrowth of non-susceptible organisms, including fungi. If superinfection occurs, the antibacterial should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted.



    5.5 Benign Intracranial Hypertension



  Bulging fontanels in infants and benign intracranial hypertension in adults have been reported in individuals receiving tetracyclines. These conditions disappeared when the drug was discontinued.



    5.6 Skeletal Development



  All tetracyclines form a stable calcium complex in any bone-forming tissue. A decrease in fibula growth rate has been observed in prematures given oral tetracycline in doses of 25 mg/kg every six hours. This reaction was shown to be reversible when the drug was discontinued.



 Results of animal studies indicate that tetracyclines cross the placenta, are found in fetal tissues, and can have toxic effects on the developing fetus (often related to retardation of skeletal development). Evidence of embryotoxicity also has been noted in animals treated early in pregnancy. If any tetracycline is used during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking these drugs, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.



    5.7 Antianabolic Action



  The antianabolic action of the tetracyclines may cause an increase in BUN. Studies to date indicate that this does not occur with the use of doxycycline in patients with impaired renal function.



    5.8 Malaria



  Doxycycline offers substantial but not complete suppression of the asexual blood stages of Plasmodium  strains.



 Doxycycline does not suppress P. falciparum's  sexual blood stage gametocytes. Subjects completing this prophylactic regimen may still transmit the infection to mosquitoes outside endemic areas.



    5.9 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing DORYX in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.



    5.10 Laboratory Monitoring for Long-Term Therapy



  In long-term therapy, periodic laboratory evaluation of organ systems, including hematopoietic, renal, and hepatic studies should be performed.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
