<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="doxepin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Controlled Clinical Trials  

    Systemic Adverse Effects:  In controlled clinical trials of patients treated with Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5%, the most common systemic adverse event reported was drowsiness. Drowsiness occurred in 71 of 330 (22%) of patients treated with Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5% compared to 7 of 334 (2%) of patients treated with vehicle cream. Drowsiness resulted in the premature discontinuation of the drug in approximately 5% of patients treated with Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5% in controlled clinical trials.



   Local Site Adverse Effects:  In controlled clinical trials of patients treated with Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5%, the most common local site adverse event reported was burning and/or stinging at the site of application. These occurred in 76 of 330 (23%) of patients treated with Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5% compared to 54 of 334 (16%) of patients treated with vehicle cream. Most of these reactions were categorized as "mild"; however, approximately 25% of patients who reported burning and/or stinging reported the reaction as "severe". Four patients treated with Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5% withdrew from the study because of the burning and/or stinging.



 The table below presents the adverse events reported at an incidence of &gt;= 1% in either Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5% or vehicle cream treatment groups during the trials:




   Adverse Event      Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5% N=330      Vehicle    N=334     
 Burning/Stinging  76 (23.0%)       54 (16.2%)        
 Drowsiness       71 (21.5%)       7 (2.1%)          
 Dry Mouth  1     32 (9.7%)        4 (1.2%)          
 Pruritus  2      13 (3.9%)        20 (6.0%)         
 Fatigue/Tiredness  10 (3.0%)        5 (1.5%)          
 Exacerbated Eczema  10 (3.0%)        8 (2.4%)          
 Other Application Site Reaction  3    10 (3.0%)        16 (4.8%)         
 Dizziness  4     7 (2.1%)         3 (0.9%)          
 Mental/Emotional Changes  6 (1.8%)         1 (0.3%)          
 Taste Perversion  5    5 (1.5%)         1 (0.3%)          
 Edema            4 (1.2%)         1 (0.3%)          
 Headache         3 (0.9%)         14 (4.2%)         
         1 Includes reports of "dry lips", "dry throat", and "thirst"2 Includes reports of "pruritus exacerbated"3 Includes report of "increased irritation at application site"4 Includes reports of "lightheadedness" and "dizziness/vertigo"5 Includes reports of "bitter taste" and "metallic taste in mouth"
 

 Adverse events occurring in 0.5% to &lt; 1.0% of Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5% treated patients in the controlled clinical trials included: nervousness/anxiety, tongue numbness, fever, and nausea.



     Post-Marketing    Experience  

  Twenty-six cases of allergic contact dermatitis have been reported in patients using Doxepin Hydrochloride Cream, 5%, twenty of which were documented by positive patch test to doxepin 5% cream.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
