<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="doxercalciferol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  

      Dialysis:    Doxercalciferol Capsules have been evaluated for safety in clinical studies in 165 patients with chronic kidney disease on hemodialysis. In two placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter studies, discontinuation of therapy due to any adverse event occurred in 2.9% of 138 patients treated with Doxercalciferol Capsules for four to six months (dosage titrated to achieve target iPTH levels, see      CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY/Clinical Studies      ) and in 3.3% of 61 patients treated with placebo for two months. Adverse events occurring in the Doxercalciferol Capsules group at a frequency of 2% or greater and more frequently than in the placebo group are presented in      Table 3      below:



 Table 3: Adverse Events Reported by &gt;= 2% of Doxercalciferol Capsules Treated Patients and More Frequently Than Placebo During the Double-blind Phase of Two Clinical Studies 
 Adverse Event              Doxercalciferol Capsules(n=61)%  Placebo(n=61)%              
  
     Body as a Whole                                                               
 Abscess                    3.3                        0.0                         
 Headache                   27.9                       18.0                        
 Malaise                    27.9                       19.7                        
     Cardiovascular System                                                             
 Bradycardia                6.6                        4.9                         
     Digestive System                                                              
 Anorexia                   4.9                        3.3                         
 Constipation               3.3                        3.3                         
 Dyspepsia                  4.9                        1.6                         
 Nausea/Vomiting            21.3                       19.7                        
     Musculoskeletal System                                                             
 Arthralgia                 4.9                        0.0                         
     Metabolic and Nutritional                                                             
 Edema                      34.4                       21.3                        
 Weight increase            4.9                        0.0                         
     Nervous System                                                                
 Dizziness                  11.5                       9.8                         
 Sleep disorder             3.3                        0.0                         
     Respiratory System                                                             
 Dyspnea                    11.5                       6.6                         
     Skin                                                                          
 Pruritus                   8.2                        6.6                         
 A patient who reported the same medical term more than once was counted only once for that medical term.   
        
       Pre-dialysis:    Doxercalciferol Capsules have been evaluated for safety in clinical studies in 55 patients (27 active and 28 placebo) with chronic kidney disease, Stages 3 or 4. In two placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter studies, discontinuation of therapy due to any adverse event occurred in one (3.7%) of 27 patients treated with Doxercalciferol Capsules for 24 weeks (dosage titrated to achieve target iPTH levels, see      CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY/Clinical Studies      ) and in three (10.7%) of 28 patients treated with placebo for 24 weeks. Adverse events occurring in the Doxercalciferol Capsules group at a frequency of 5% or greater and more frequently than in the placebo group are as follows:    Body as a Whole    - Infection, Chest Pain;    Digestive System    - Constipation, Dyspepsia;    Hematologic and Lymphatic    - Anemia;    Metabolic and Nutritional    - Dehydration;    Nervous System    - Depression, Hypertonia, Insomnia, Paresthesia;    Respiratory System    - Cough increased, Dyspnea, Rhinitis.



 Potential adverse effects of Doxercalciferol are, in general, similar to those encountered with excessive vitamin D intake. The early and late signs and symptoms of vitamin D intoxication associated with hypercalcemia include:



   

      Early    



 Weakness, headache, somnolence, nausea, vomiting, dry mouth, constipation, muscle pain, bone pain, metallic taste, and anorexia.



   

      Late    



 Polyuria, polydipsia, anorexia, weight loss, nocturia, conjunctivitis (calcific), pancreatitis, photophobia, rhinorrhea, pruritus, hyperthermia, decreased libido, elevated blood urea nitrogen (BUN), albuminuria, hypercholesterolemia, elevated serum aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT), ectopic calcification, hypertension, cardiac arrhythmias, sensory disturbances, dehydration, apathy, arrested growth, urinary tract infections, and, rarely, overt psychosis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
