<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="doxycycline0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  Due to oral doxycycline's virtually complete absorption, side effects to the lower bowel, particularly diarrhea, have been infrequent. The following adverse reactions have been observed in patients receiving tetracyclines.



   Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, glossitis, dysphagia, enterocolitis, and inflammatory lesions (with monilial overgrowth) in the anogenital region. Hepatotoxicity has been reported. These reactions have been caused by both the oral and parenteral administration of tetracyclines. Rare instances of esophagitis and esophageal ulcerations have been reported in patients receiving capsule and tablet forms of drugs in the tetracycline class. Most of these patients took medications immediately before going to bed. (See  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  .)



   Skin:  Maculopapular and erythematous rashes, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and erythema multiforme have been reported. Exfoliative dermatitis has been reported but is uncommon. Photosensitivity is discussed above. (See  WARNINGS  .)



   Renal Toxicity:  Rise in BUN has been reported and is apparently dose related. (See  WARNINGS  .)



   Hypersensitivity Reactions:  Urticaria, angioneurotic edema, anaphylaxis, anaphylactoid purpura, serum sickness, pericarditis, and exacerbation of systemic lupus erythematosus.



   Blood:  Hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, and eosinophilia have been reported with tetracyclines.



   Other:  Intracranial hypertension (IH, pseudotumor cerebri) has been associated with the use of tetracyclines. (See  PRECAUTIONS-General  .)



 When given over prolonged periods, tetracyclines have been reported to produce brown-black microscopic discoloration of the thyroid gland. No abnormalities of thyroid function are known to occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
