<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="duexis" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular events [ see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Gastrointestinal effects [ see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Renal injury [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Seizures [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *  Anaphylaxis [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *  Skin reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *  Corticosteroid treatment [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.17)   ] 
 *  Masking of inflammation and fever [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.18)   ] 
 *  Hepatic injury [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)   ] 
 *  Hematological effects [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)   ] 
 *  Pre-existing asthma [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)   ] 
 *  Aseptic meningitis [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.16)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=1% and greater than ibuprofen alone) are nausea, diarrhea, constipation, upper abdominal pain, and headache. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Horizon Pharma USA, Inc. at (1-866-479-6742) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of DUEXIS was evaluated in 1022 patients in controlled clinical studies, including 508 patients treated for at least 6 months and 107 patients treated for approximately 1 year. Patients treated with DUEXIS ranged in age from 39 to 80 years (median age 55 years), with 67% female, 79% Caucasian, 18% African-American, and 3% other races. Two randomized, active-controlled clinical studies (Study 301 and Study 303) were conducted for the reduction of the risk of development of ibuprofen-associated, upper gastrointestinal ulcers in patients who required use of ibuprofen, which included 1022 patients on DUEXIS and 511 patients on ibuprofen alone. Approximately 15% of patients were on low-dose aspirin. Patients were assigned randomly, in a 2:1 ratio, to treatment with either DUEXIS or ibuprofen 800 mg three times a day for 24 consecutive weeks



 Three serious cases of acute renal failure were observed in patients treated with DUEXIS in the two controlled clinical trials. All three patients recovered to baseline levels after discontinuation of DUEXIS. Additionally, increases in serum creatinine were observed in both treatment arms in the two clinical studies. Many of these patients were taking concomitant diuretics and/or angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, or angiotensin receptor blockers. There were patients with a normal baseline serum creatinine level who developed abnormal values in the controlled trials as presented in Table 1.



 Table 1: Shift table of serum creatinine, normalserum creatinine normal range is 0.5 - 1.4 mg/dL or 44-124 micromol/L to abnormalserum creatinine &gt;1.4 mg/dL in controlled studies 
                                           Study 301          Study 303       
     Baseline         Post-Baseline    DUEXISN=414% (n)   IbuprofenN=207% (n)  DUEXISN=598% (n)  IbuprofenN=296% (n)   
  
      Normal            Abnormal            4% (17)            2% (4)             2%(15)           4% (12)        
                Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions  
 

 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%), from pooled data from the two controlled studies are presented in Table 2.



 Table 2: Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Controlled Studies 
                                                                   DUEXISN=1022         IbuprofenN=511      
 %                                                                      %             
  
 DUEXIS (ibuprofen and famotidine) tablets 800 mg/26.6 mg administered orally three times per day.   
 Ibuprofen 800 mg administered orally three times per day.      
  
 Blood and lymphatic system disorders                                                                       
   Anemia                                                               2                     1             
 Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                 
   Nausea                                                               6                     5             
   Dyspepsia                                                            5                     8             
   Diarrhea                                                             5                     4             
   Constipation                                                         4                     4             
   Abdominal pain upper                                                 3                     3             
   Gastroesophageal reflux disease                                      2                     3             
   Vomiting                                                             2                     2             
   Stomach discomfort                                                   2                     2             
   Abdominal pain                                                       2                     2             
 General disorders and administration site conditions                                                       
   Edema peripheral                                                     2                     2             
 Infections and infestations                                                                                
   Upper respiratory tract infection                                    4                     4             
   Nasopharyngitis                                                      2                     3             
   Sinusitis                                                            2                     3             
   Bronchitis                                                           2                     1             
   Urinary tract infection                                              2                     2             
   Influenza                                                            2                     2             
 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                            
   Arthralgia                                                           1                     2             
   Back pain                                                            2                     1             
 Nervous system disorders                                                                                   
   Headache                                                             3                     3             
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                            
   Cough                                                                2                     2             
   Pharyngolaryngeal pain                                               2                     1             
 Vascular disorders                                                                                         
   Hypertension                                                         3                     2             
         In controlled clinical studies, the discontinuation rate due to adverse events for patients receiving DUEXIS and ibuprofen alone were similar. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation from DUEXIS therapy were nausea (0.9%) and upper abdominal pain (0.9%).
 

 There were no differences in types of related adverse reactions seen during maintenance treatment up to 12 months compared to short-term treatment.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Ibuprofen  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ibuprofen. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These reports are listed below by body system:



 Cardiac disorders: myocardial infarction



 Gastrointestinal disorders: nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain



 General disorders and administration site conditions: pyrexia, pain, fatigue, asthenia, chest pain, drug ineffective, edema peripheral



 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders: arthralgia



 Nervous system disorders: headache, dizziness



 Psychiatric disorders: depression, anxiety



 Renal and urinary disorders: renal failure acute



 Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders: dyspnea



 Vascular disorders: hypertension



     Famotidine  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of famotidine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These reports are listed below by body system:



 Blood and lymphatic system disorders: anemia, thrombocytopenia



 Gastrointestinal disorders: nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, abdominal pain



 General disorders and administration site conditions: pyrexia, condition aggravated, asthenia, drug ineffective, chest pain, fatigue, pain, edema peripheral



 Hepatobiliary disorders: hepatic function abnormal



 Infections and infestations: pneumonia, sepsis



 Investigations: platelet count decreased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, alanine aminotransferase increased, hemoglobin decreased



 Metabolism and nutrition disorders: decreased appetite



 Nervous system disorders: dizziness, headache



 Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders: dyspnea



 Vascular disorders: hypotension
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS

    WARNING:  RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS  

  EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .         



 *  Ibuprofen, a component of DUEXIS, may increase the risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. Risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. (5.1) 
 *  DUEXIS is contraindicated for the treatment of perioperative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4, 5.1) 
 *  NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, a component of DUEXIS, increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse reactions including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. Reactions can occur at any time without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk. (5.4) 
    
 

    Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  NSAIDs, including DUEXIS, are contraindicated for treatment of perioperative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
        Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse reactions including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These reactions can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypertension: Hypertension can occur with NSAID treatment; monitor blood pressure closely during treatment with DUEXIS. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Congestive heart failure and edema: Fluid retention and edema can occur with NSAID treatment; use DUEXIS with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Active Bleeding: Active and clinically significant bleeding from any source can occur; discontinue DUEXIS if active bleeding occurs (  5.5  ) 
 *  Renal Injury: Long-term administration of NSAIDs can result in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury; use DUEXIS with caution in patients at risk (e.g., the elderly, those with renal impairment, heart failure, liver impairment, and those taking diuretics or ACE inhibitors). (  5.6  ) 
 *  Anaphylaxis: Anaphylaxis may occur in patients with the aspirin triad or in patients without prior exposure to DUEXIS; discontinue DUEXIS immediately if an anaphylactoid reaction occurs. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Serious skin reactions: Includes exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which can be fatal; discontinue DUEXIS if rash or other signs of local skin reaction occur. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Hepatic Injury: Hepatic injury ranging from transaminase elevations to liver failure can occur; discontinue DUEXIS immediately if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, if clinical signs and symptoms of liver disease develop or if systemic manifestations occur. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS tablets, of up to 3 years duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Patients should be informed about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID does increase the risk of serious GI events [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)    ].



 Two large, controlled clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10-14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.2 Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS tablets, can lead to onset of new hypertension or worsening of pre-existing hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. Patients taking thiazides or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs. NSAIDs, including DUEXIS, should be used with caution in patients with hypertension. Blood pressure (BP) should be monitored closely during the initiation of NSAID treatment and throughout the course of therapy [ see  Drug Interactions (7.1  ,  7.4  )  ].



    5.3 Congestive Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention and edema have been observed in some patients taking NSAIDs. DUEXIS should be used with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure.



    5.4 Risk of Gastrointestinal Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS tablets, can cause serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse reactions including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse reactions can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs occur in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3-6 months, and in about 2-4% of patients treated for 1 year. These trends continue with longer duration of use, increasing the likelihood of developing a serious GI event at some time during the course of therapy. However, even short-term therapy is not without risk. NSAIDs, including DUEXIS, should be prescribed with extreme caution in those with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or GI bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing a GI bleed compared to patients treated with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk of GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs, including DUEXIS, include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids, anticoagulants, antiplatelet drugs (including low-dose aspirin), longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most spontaneous reports of fatal GI reactions are in elderly or debilitated patients, and, therefore, special care should be taken in treating this population with DUEXIS.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI reaction in patients treated with an NSAID, the shortest possible duration should be used. Patients and physicians should remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulcers and bleeding during NSAID therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI adverse reaction is suspected. This should include discontinuation of the NSAID until a serious GI adverse reaction is ruled out. For high-risk patients, alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs should be considered.



 Epidemiological studies of the case-control and cohort design have demonstrated an association between use of psychotropic drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of upper gastrointestinal bleeding. In two studies, concurrent use of an NSAID, COX-2 inhibitor, or aspirin potentiated the risk of bleeding [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2  ,  7.7  )  ]. Although these studies focused on upper gastrointestinal bleeding, bleeding at other sites cannot be ruled out.



 NSAIDs should be given with care to patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease) as their condition may be exacerbated.



 Because serious GI tract ulcers and bleeding can occur without warning symptoms, physicians should monitor for signs or symptoms of GI bleeding. Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs should have their complete blood count (CBC) and chemistry profile checked periodically.



 Symptomatic response to therapy with DUEXIS does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



    5.5 Active Bleeding



  When active and clinically significant bleeding from any source occurs in patients receiving DUEXIS, the treatment should be withdrawn. Patients with initial hemoglobin values of 10 g or less who are to receive long-term therapy should have hemoglobin values determined periodically.



    5.6 Renal Injury



  Long-term administration of NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS tablets, has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of an NSAID may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics and angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, and the elderly. If clinical signs (e.g., azotemia, hypertension, and/or proteinuria) and symptoms consistent with renal disease develop, DUEXIS should be discontinued. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ]  .



    5.7 Seizures



  Central nervous system (CNS) adverse effects including seizures, delirium, and coma have been reported with famotidine in patients with moderate (creatinine clearance &lt;50 mL/min) and severe renal insufficiency (creatinine clearance &lt;10 mL/min), and the dosage of the famotidine component in DUEXIS is fixed. Therefore, DUEXIS is not recommended in patients with creatinine clearance &lt; 50 mL/min.



    5.8 Anaphylaxis



  Anaphylaxis may occur in patients without known prior exposure to ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS tablets. DUEXIS should not be given to patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [ see  Contraindications(4)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)    ]. Emergency help should be sought in cases where anaphylaxis, which may have a fatal outcome, occurs.



    5.9 Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS tablets, can cause serious skin adverse reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Patients should be informed about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations and use of the drug should be discontinued at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  .



    5.10 Pregnancy



  Starting at 30 weeks gestation, DUEXIS should be avoided by pregnant women because it may cause premature closure of the ductus arteriosus [ see  Contraindications (4)  and  Use in Specific Population (8.1)    ].



    5.11 Hepatic Injury



  Borderline elevations of one or more liver tests may occur in up to 15% of patients taking NSAIDs, including ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS tablets. These laboratory abnormalities may progress, may remain unchanged, or may be transient with continuing therapy. Notable elevations of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (approximately three or more times the upper limit of normal) have been reported in approximately 1% of patients in clinical trials with NSAIDs. In addition, rare cases of severe hepatic reactions, including jaundice, fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis, and hepatic failure, some of them with fatal outcomes have been reported.



 A patient with symptoms and/or signs suggesting liver dysfunction, or with abnormal liver test values, should be evaluated for evidence of the development of a more severe hepatic reaction while on therapy with DUEXIS. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.), DUEXIS should be discontinued.



    5.12 Anemia



  Anemia is sometimes seen in patients receiving NSAIDs, including ibuprofen which is a component of DUEXIS tablets. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs, including DUEXIS, should have their hemoglobin or hematocrit checked if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia.



    5.13 Inhibition of Platelet Aggregation



  NSAIDs inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effect on platelet function is quantitatively less, of shorter duration, and reversible. Patients receiving DUEXIS who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants, should be carefully monitored.



    5.14 Pre-existing Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm, which can be fatal. Since cross reactivity, including bronchospasm, between aspirin and NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, DUEXIS should not be administered to patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and should be used with caution in patients with pre-existing asthma.



    5.15 Concomitant NSAID Use



  DUEXIS contains ibuprofen as one of its active ingredients. It should not be used with other ibuprofen-containing products.



 The concomitant use of NSAIDs, including aspirin, with DUEXIS may increase the risk of adverse events [ see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ,  Drug Interactions (7.2)  , and  Clinical Studies (14)  ].  



    5.16 Aseptic Meningitis



  Aseptic meningitis with fever and coma has been observed on rare occasions in patients on ibuprofen, which is a component of DUEXIS. Although it is probably more likely to occur in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) and related connective tissue diseases, it has been reported in patients who do not have an underlying chronic disease. If signs or symptoms of meningitis develop in a patient on DUEXIS, the possibility of its being related to ibuprofen should be considered.



    5.17 Corticosteroid Treatment



  DUEXIS cannot be expected to substitute for corticosteroids or to treat corticosteroid insufficiency. Abrupt discontinuation of corticosteroids may lead to disease exacerbation. Patients on prolonged corticosteroid therapy should have their therapy tapered slowly if a decision is made to discontinue corticosteroids and the patient should be observed closely for any evidence of adverse effects, including adrenal insufficiency and exacerbation of symptoms of arthritis.



    5.18 Masking of Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of DUEXIS in reducing fever and inflammation may diminish the utility of these diagnostic signs in detecting complications of presumed noninfectious, noninflammatory painful conditions.



    5.19 Visual Disturbances



  Blurred and/or diminished vision, scotomata, and/or changes in color vision have been reported. If a patient develops such complaints while receiving DUEXIS, the drug should be discontinued, and the patient should have an ophthalmologic examination which includes central visual fields and color vision testing.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
