<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="duopa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed below and elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Gastrointestinal and Gastrointestinal Procedure-Related Risks [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  
 *  Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)  ]  
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hallucinations/Psychosis/Confusion [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)  ]  
 *  Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.5)  ]  
 *  Depression and Suicidality [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)  ]  
 *  Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.7)  ]  
 *  Dyskinesia [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)  ]  
 *  Neuropathy [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.9)  ]  
 *  Cardiovascular Ischemic Events [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.10)  ]  
 *  Melanoma [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.11)  ]  
 *  Laboratory Test Abnormalities [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.12)  ]  
 *  Glaucoma [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.13)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions for DUOPA (DUOPA incidence at least 7% greater than oral carbidopa-levodopa incidence) were: complication of device insertion, nausea, depression, peripheral edema, hypertension, upper respiratory tract infection, oropharyngeal pain, atelectasis, and incision site erythema.  (6.1)  
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AbbVie Inc. at 1-800-633-9110 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are run under widely varying conditions, the incidence of adverse reactions observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical studies, 416 patients with advanced Parkinson's disease received DUOPA. 338 patients were treated with DUOPA for more than 1 year, 233 patients were treated with DUOPA for more than 2 years, and 162 patients were treated with DUOPA for more than 3 years.



 In a 12-week, active-controlled clinical trial (Study 1), a total of 71 patients with advanced Parkinson's disease were enrolled and had a PEG-J procedure. Of these, 37 patients received DUOPA and 34 received oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa.



 The most common adverse reactions for DUOPA (incidence at least 7% greater than oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa) were: complication of device insertion, nausea, depression, peripheral edema, hypertension, upper respiratory tract infection, oropharyngeal pain, atelectasis, and incision site erythema.



 Table 3 lists the incidence of adverse reactions occurring in the DUOPA-treated group (requiring at least 2 patients in this group) in Study 1 when the incidence was numerically greater than that for oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions in Study 1 for DUOPA in Patients with Advanced Parkinson's disease 
   Preferred Term      DUOPA    (n = 37)    %      Oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa  a      (n = 34)    %     
  
 Complication of device insertion        57               44          
 Nausea                 30               21          
 Constipation           22               21          
 Incision site erythema        19               12          
 Dyskinesia             14               12          
 Depression             11                3          
 Post procedural discharge        11                9          
 Peripheral edema         8                0          
 Hypertension            8                0          
 Upper respiratory tract infection         8                0          
 Oropharyngeal pain         8                0          
 Atelectasis             8                0          
 Confusional state         8                3          
 Anxiety                 8                3          
 Dizziness               8                6          
 Hiatal hernia           8                6          
 Postoperative ileus         5                0          
 Sleep disorder          5                0          
 Pyrexia                 5                0          
 Excessive granulation tissue         5                0          
 Rash                    5                0          
 Bacteriuria             5                0          
 White blood cells urine positive         5                0          
 Hallucination           5                3          
 Psychotic disorder         5                3          
 Diarrhea                5                3          
 Dyspepsia               5                3          
   a  All patients in the clinical trial regardless of treatment arm received a PEG-J.   
        Procedure and Device- Related Adverse Reactions  
 

 The most common adverse reactions associated with complications due to naso-jejunal (NJ) insertion were: oropharyngeal pain, abdominal distention, abdominal pain, abdominal discomfort, pain, throat irritation, gastrointestinal injury, esophageal hemorrhage, anxiety, dysphagia, and vomiting.



 The most common adverse reactions associated with complications due to PEG-J insertion were: abdominal pain, abdominal discomfort, abdominal distension, flatulence, or pneumoperitoneum.



 Additional adverse reactions that were co-reported with complication of naso-jejunal and PEG-J insertion included upper abdominal pain, duodenal ulcer, duodenal ulcer hemorrhage, erosive duodenitis, erosive gastritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, peritonitis, post-operative abscess, and small intestine ulcer.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Gastrointestinal procedure-related complications may result in serious outcomes, such as need for surgery or death  (5.1)   
 *  May cause falling asleep during activities of daily living  (5.2)   
 *  Monitor patients for orthostatic hypotension, especially after starting DUOPA or increasing the dose  (5.3)   
 *  Hallucinations/Psychosis/Confusion: May respond to dose reduction in levodopa  (5.4)   
 *  Impulse Control Disorders: Consider dose reductions or stopping DUOPA  (5.5)   
 *  Monitor patients for depression and suicidality  (5.6)   
 *  Avoid sudden discontinuation or rapid dose reduction to reduce the risk of withdrawal-emergent hyperpyrexia and confusion  (5.7)   
 *  May cause or exacerbate dyskinesia: Consider dose reduction  (5.8)   
 *  Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of peripheral neuropathy  (5.9)   
    
 

   5.1 Gastrointestinal and Gastrointestinal Procedure-Related Risks



  Because DUOPA is administered using a PEG-J or naso-jejunal tube, gastrointestinal complications can occur.



 These complications include bezoar, ileus, implant site erosion/ulcer, intestinal hemorrhage, intestinal ischemia, intestinal obstruction, intestinal perforation, pancreatitis, peritonitis, pneumoperitoneum, and post-operative wound infection. These complications may result in serious outcomes, such as the need for surgery or death.



 Instruct patients to notify their healthcare provider immediately if they experience abdominal pain, prolonged constipation, nausea, vomiting, fever, or melanotic stool [see Patient Counseling Information  (17)  ]  .



    5.2 Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence



  Patients treated with levodopa, a component of DUOPA, have reported falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, which sometimes resulted in accidents. Although many of these patients reported somnolence while on levodopa, some perceived that they had no warning signs (sleep attack), such as excessive drowsiness, and believed that they were alert immediately prior to the event. Some of these events have been reported more than one year after initiation of treatment.



 Falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living usually occurs in patients experiencing preexisting somnolence, although patients may not give such a history. For this reason, prescribers should reassess patients for drowsiness or sleepiness in DUOPA-treated patients, especially since some of the events occur well after the start of treatment. Prescribers should be aware that patients may not acknowledge drowsiness or sleepiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities. Patients who have already experienced somnolence or an episode of sudden sleep onset should not participate in these activities while taking DUOPA.



 Before initiating treatment with DUOPA, advise patients about the potential to develop drowsiness and specifically ask about factors that may increase the risk for somnolence with DUOPA such as the use of concomitant sedating medications or the presence of sleep disorders. Consider discontinuing DUOPA in patients who report significant daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require active participation (e.g., conversations, eating). If DUOPA is continued, they should be advised to avoid driving and other potentially dangerous activities that might result in harm if the patient becomes somnolent.



    5.3 Orthostatic Hypotension



  DUOPA-treated patients were more likely to experience a decline in orthostatic blood pressure than patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa in the controlled clinical study. Orthostatic systolic hypotension (&gt;=30 mm Hg decrease) occurred in 73% of DUOPA-treated patients compared to 68% of patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa in the controlled clinical study. Orthostatic diastolic hypotension (&gt;=20 mm Hg decrease) occurred in 70% of DUOPA-treated patients compared to 62% of patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa. Inform patients about the risk for hypotension and syncope. Monitor patients for orthostatic hypotension, especially after starting DUOPA or increasing the dose.



    5.4 Hallucinations/Psychosis/Confusion



  There is an increased risk for hallucinations and psychosis in patients taking DUOPA. In the controlled clinical trial, hallucinations occurred in 5% of DUOPA-treated patients compared to 3% of patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa. Confusion occurred in 8% of DUOPA-treated patients compared to 3% of patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa, and psychotic disorder occurred in 5% of DUOPA-treated patients compared to 3% of patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa.



 Hallucinations associated with levodopa may present shortly after the initiation of therapy and may be responsive to dose reduction in levodopa. Confusion, insomnia, and excessive dreaming may accompany hallucinations. Abnormal thinking and behavior may present with one or more symptoms, including paranoid ideation, delusions, hallucinations, confusion, psychosis, disorientation, aggressive behavior, agitation, and delirium.



 Because of the risk of exacerbating psychosis, patients with a major psychotic disorder should not be treated with DUOPA. In addition, medications that antagonize the effects of dopamine used to treat psychosis may exacerbate the symptoms of Parkinson's disease and may decrease the effectiveness of DUOPA [see Drug Interactions  (7.3)  ]  .



    5.5 Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors



  Patients may experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money, binge or compulsive eating, and/or other intense urges, and the inability to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications, including DUOPA, that increase central dopaminergic tone and that are generally used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease. In some cases, although not all, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose was reduced or the medication was discontinued.



 Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal, it is important for prescribers to ask patients or their caregivers specifically about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending, binge or compulsive eating, or other urges while being treated with DUOPA. Consider reducing the dose or discontinuing DUOPA if a patient develops such urges.



    5.6 Depression and Suicidality



  In the controlled clinical trial, 11% of DUOPA-treated patients developed depression compared to 3% of oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa-treated patients.



 Monitor patients for the development of depression and concomitant suicidal tendencies.



    5.7 Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion



  A symptom complex that resembles neuroleptic malignant syndrome (characterized by elevated temperature, muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, and autonomic instability), with no other obvious etiology, has been reported in association with rapid dose reduction, withdrawal of, or changes in dopaminergic therapy. Avoid sudden discontinuation or rapid dose reduction in patients taking DUOPA. If DUOPA is discontinued, the dose should be tapered to reduce the risk of hyperpyrexia and confusion [see Dosage and Administration  (2.4)  ]  .



    5.8 Dyskinesia



  DUOPA may cause or exacerbate dyskinesias. In the controlled clinical trial, dyskinesia occurred in 14% of DUOPA-treated patients compared to 12% of patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa. The occurrence of dyskinesias may require a dosage reduction of DUOPA or other medications used to treat Parkinson's disease.



    5.9 Neuropathy



  In clinical studies, 19 of 412 (5%) patients treated with DUOPA developed a generalized polyneuropathy. The onset of neuropathy could be determined in 13 of 19 patients. Most cases (12/19) were classified as subacute or chronic in onset. The neuropathy was most often characterized as sensory or sensorimotor. Electrodiagnostic testing performed in 16 patients was most often (15/16) consistent with an axonal polyneuropathy, and one patient was classified as having a demyelinating neuropathy. There was insufficient information to determine the potential role of vitamin deficiencies in the etiology of neuropathy associated with DUOPA.



 Patients should have clinical assessments for the signs and symptoms of peripheral neuropathy before starting DUOPA. Monitor patients periodically for signs of neuropathy after starting DUOPA, especially in patients with pre-existing neuropathy and in patients taking medications or those who have medical conditions that are also associated with neuropathy.



    5.10 Cardiovascular Ischemic Events



  In clinical studies, myocardial infarction and arrhythmia were reported in patients taking carbidopa-levodopa. Ask patients about symptoms of ischemic heart disease and arrhythmia, especially those with a history of myocardial infarction or cardiac arrhythmias.



    5.11 Melanoma



  Epidemiological studies have shown that patients with Parkinson's disease have a higher risk (2 to approximately 6-fold higher) of developing melanoma than the general population. Whether the increased risk observed was due to Parkinson's disease or other factors, such as drugs used to treat Parkinson's disease, is unclear. In the clinical studies, 2 of 416 (0.5%) DUOPA-treated patients developed melanoma.



 Appropriately qualified health care providers (e.g., dermatologists) should perform periodic skin examinations to monitor for melanoma in patients receiving DUOPA.



    5.12 Laboratory Test Abnormalities



  DUOPA may increase the risk for elevated (above the upper limit of normal for the reference range) blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and creatine phosphokinase (CPK). In the controlled clinical trial, the shift from a low or normal value at baseline to an increased BUN value was greater for DUOPA-treated patients (13%) than for patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa (4%). The shift from a low or normal value at baseline to an increased CPK value was greater for DUOPA-treated patients (17%) than for patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa (7%). The incidence of patients with a markedly increased BUN (&gt;=10 mmol/L; &gt;=28 mg/dL) was greater for patients treated with DUOPA (11%) than that for patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa (0%). The incidence of patients with an increased CPK (&gt;3 times the upper limit of normal) was greater for patients treated with DUOPA (9%) than that for patients treated with oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa (0%).



 Patients taking levodopa or carbidopa-levodopa may have increased levels of catecholamines and their metabolites in plasma and urine giving false positive results suggesting the diagnosis of pheochromocytoma in patients on levodopa and carbidopa-levodopa.



    5.13 Glaucoma



  Carbidopa-levodopa may cause increased intraocular pressure in patients with glaucoma. Monitor intraocular pressure in patients with glaucoma after starting DUOPA.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
