<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dyanavel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6.         ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Drug Dependence [see      Boxed Warning    , Warnings and Precautions (    5.1    ), and Drug Abuse and Dependence (    9.2    ,    9.3    ) ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity to amphetamine, or other components of DYANAVEL     XR [see Contraindications     (    4    ) ] 
 *  Hypertensive Crisis When Used Concomitantly with Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors [see Contraindications (    4    ) and Drug Interactions (    7.1    ) ] 
 *  Serious Cardiovascular Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions   (    5.2    ) ] 
 *  Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases [see Warnings and Precautions   (    5.3    ) ] 
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions   (    5.4    ) ] 
 *  Long-Term Suppression of Growth [see Warnings and Precautions   (    5.5    ) ] 
 *  Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.6    ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions observed with amphetamine products: dry mouth, anorexia, weight loss, abdominal pain, nausea, insomnia, restlessness, emotional lability, dizziness, tachycardia (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Tris Pharma, Inc. 1-732-940-0358 and www.trispharma.com or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6.1         Clinical Trial Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Clinical Trials Experience with Other Amphetamine Products in    Pediatric Patients    and Adults with ADHD  



 Cardiovascular: Palpitations, tachycardia, elevation of blood pressure, sudden death, myocardial infarction. There have been isolated reports of cardiomyopathy associated with chronic amphetamine use.



 Central Nervous System: Psychotic episodes at recommended doses, overstimulation, restlessness, irritability, euphoria, dyskinesia, dysphoria, depression, tremor, tics, aggression, anger, logorrhea.



 Eye Disorders: Vision blurred, mydriasis.



 Gastrointestinal: Dryness of the mouth, unpleasant taste, diarrhea, constipation, other gastrointestinal disturbances. Anorexia and weight loss may occur as undesirable effects.



 Allergic: Urticaria, rash, hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema and anaphylaxis. Serious skin rashes, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis have been reported.



 Endocrine: Impotence, changes in libido.



 Skin: Alopecia.



   Clinical Trials Experience with  DYANAVEL     XR   in    Pediatric Patients    with ADHD  



 There is limited experience with DYANAVEL     XR in controlled trials. Based on this limited experience, the adverse reaction profile of DYANAVEL     XR appears similar to other amphetamine extended-release products. The most common (&gt;=2% in the DYANAVEL     XR group and greater than placebo) adverse reactions reported in the Phase 3 controlled study conducted in 108 patients with ADHD (aged 6-12 years) were: epistaxis, allergic rhinitis and upper abdominal pain.



 Table 1.  Common adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=2% of Subjects on DYANAVEL XR and greater than Placebo during the double blind phase. 
   Preferred Term      DYANAVEL             XR    (N=    52    )      Placebo    (N=    48    )     
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
    Epistaxis     3.8%             0%                
    Rhinitis allergic  3.8%             0%                
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
    Abdominal pain upper  3.8%             2.1%              
             6.2          Postmarketing Experience  
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of other amphetamine products. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Endocrine: frequent or prolonged erections.



 Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue, and Bone Disorders: rhabdomyolysis.



 Psychiatric Disorders: dermatillomania.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE

    WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE  

    CNS stimulants    , including DYANAVEL XR,         other     amphetamine    -containing product    s    ,         and methylphenidate    ,         have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy     [    see         Warnings and Precautions (      5.1      ,       9.3      )    , and         Drug Abuse and Dependence (      9.2      ,           9.3      )    ].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE  



   See full     prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  CNS stimulants, including DYANAVEL XR, other amphetamine-containing products, and methylphenidate, have a high potential for abuse and dependence (5.1, 9.3) 
 *  Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy (9.2, 9.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5.        WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *   Serious Cardiovascular Reactions: Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at recommended doses in pediatric patients with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. In adults, sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmia, or coronary artery disease (  5.2  ) 
 *   Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases: Monitor blood pressure and pulse. Consider benefits and risks before use in patients for whom blood pressure increases may be problematic (  5.3  ) 
 *   Psychiatric Adverse Reactions: May cause psychotic or manic symptoms in patients with no prior history, or exacerbation of symptoms in patients with pre-existing psychosis. Evaluate for bipolar disorder prior to stimulant use (  5.4  ) 
 *   Long-Term  Suppression  of Growth: Monitor height and weight in pediatric patients during treatment (  5.5  ) 
 *   Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon: Stimulants used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants (  5.6  ) 
    
 

    5.1        Potential for Abuse and Dependence  



  CNS stimulants, including DYANAVEL XR, other amphetamine-containing products, and methylphenidate, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy [see   Boxed Warning     ,   Drug Abuse and Dependence   (     9.2     ,         9.3     )  ].



     5.2        Serious Cardiovascular Reactions  



  Sudden death, stroke and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults with CNS stimulant treatment at recommended doses. Sudden death has been reported in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities and other serious heart problems taking CNS stimulants at recommended doses for ADHD. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmia, coronary artery disease, and other serious heart problems. Further evaluate patients who develop exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or arrhythmias during DYANAVEL     XR treatment.



     5.3        Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases  



  CNS stimulants cause an increase in blood pressure (mean increase about 2-4 mm Hg) and heart rate (mean increase about 3-6 bpm). Monitor all patients for potential tachycardia and hypertension.



     5.4        Psychiatric Adverse Reactions  



   Exacerbation of Preexisting Psychosis  



 CNS stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with a preexisting psychotic disorder.



  Induction of a Manic Episode in Patients with Bipolar Illness  



 CNS stimulants may induce a mixed or manic episode in patients with bipolar disorder. Prior to initiating treatment, screen patients for risk factors for developing a manic episode (e.g., comorbid or history of depressive symptoms or a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, or depression).



  New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms  



 CNS stimulants, at recommended doses, may cause psychotic or manic symptoms, e.g., hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania in patients without prior history of psychotic illness or mania. If such symptoms occur, consider discontinuing DYANAVEL XR. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies of CNS stimulants, psychotic or manic symptoms occurred in 0.1% of CNS stimulant-treated patients compared to 0% in placebo-treated patients.



     5.5        Long-Term   Suppression of Growth  



  CNS stimulants have been associated with weight loss and slowing of growth rate in pediatric patients. Closely monitor growth (weight and height) in pediatric patients treated with CNS stimulants, including DYANAVEL     XR.



     5.6        Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon  



  Stimulants, including DYANAVEL XR, used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Signs and symptoms are usually intermittent and mild; however, very rare sequelae include digital ulceration and/or soft tissue breakdown. Effects of peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon, were observed in post-marketing reports at different times and at therapeutic doses in all age groups throughout the course of treatment. Signs and symptoms generally improve after reduction in dose or discontinuation of drug. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. Further clinical evaluation (e.g., rheumatology referral) may be appropriate for certain patients.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
