<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="dyloject" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Cardiovascular thrombotic events [ see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *    Gastrointestinal effects [ see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *    Renal effects [ see  Contraindications (4)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *    Hepatic effects [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *    Hypertension [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *    Congestive heart failure and edema [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *    Anaphylactoid reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *    Serious skin reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
        Adverse reactions from clinical studies of Dyloject    
 

 Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During clinical development, 1,156 patients were exposed to Dyloject in multiple-dose, controlled and open-label studies. Dyloject was administered post-surgically every 6 hours for up to 5 days. The incidence rates of adverse reactions listed in the following table are derived from multicenter, controlled clinical studies in post-operative patients comparing Dyloject to placebo in patients who may have also received morphine rescue medication.



 Table 1: Proportion of Patients Experiencing Common Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Studies in Patients with Acute Moderate-to-Severe Postoperative Pain occurring in greater than or equal to 3% in patients treated with DylojectIntravenous morphine was permitted as rescue medication for pain management. 
  MedDRA Preferred Term              Placebo  N=126                     Dyloject  N=187                    
  Any Reaction                       104 (83%)                          146 (78%)                          
  Nausea  Constipation  Headache  Infusion Site Pain  Dizziness  Flatulence  Vomiting  Insomnia  Pruritus  Hypotension  Pyrexia  Anemia  Infusion Site Extravasation    50 (40%)  14 (11%)  20 (16%)  10 (8%)  2 (2%)  20 (16%)  23 (18%)  12 (10%)  10 (8%)  6 (5%)  13 (10%)  9 (7%)  1 (1%)    45 (24%)  25 (13%)  19 (10%)  19 (10%)  15 (8%)  15 (8%)  12 (6%)  11 (6%)  9 (5%)  9 (5%)  8 (4%)  8 (4%)  6 (3%)    
             Adverse reactions from clinical studies or spontaneous reports for other formulations of diclofenac and other NSAIDs    
 

 In patients taking diclofenac or other NSAIDs, the most frequently reported adverse reactions occurring in approximately 1%-10% of patients are:



 Gastrointestinal experiences including abdominal pain, constipation, diarrhea, dyspepsia, flatulence, gross bleeding/perforation, heartburn, nausea, GI ulcers (gastric/duodenal) and vomiting.



 Abnormal renal function, anemia, dizziness, edema, elevated liver enzymes, headaches, increased bleeding time, pruritus, rashes and tinnitus.



 Additional adverse reactions reported occasionally include:



     Body as a Whole:    fever, infection, sepsis



     Cardiovascular System:    congestive heart failure, hypertension, tachycardia, syncope



     Digestive System:    esophagitis, gastric/peptic ulcers, gastritis, gastrointestinal bleeding, glossitis, hematemesis, hepatitis, jaundice



     Hemic and Lymphatic System:    ecchymosis, eosinophilia, leukopenia, melena, purpura, rectal bleeding, stomatitis, thrombocytopenia



     Metabolic and Nutritional:    weight changes



     Nervous System:    anxiety, asthenia, confusion, depression, dream abnormalities, drowsiness, insomnia, malaise, nervousness, paresthesia, somnolence, tremors, vertigo



     Respiratory System:    asthma, dyspnea



     Skin and Appendages:    alopecia, photosensitivity, sweating increased



     Special Senses:    blurred vision



     Urogenital System:    cystitis, dysuria, hematuria, interstitial nephritis, oliguria/polyuria, proteinuria, renal failure



 Other adverse reactions, which occur rarely are:



     Body as a Whole:    anaphylactic reactions, appetite changes, death



     Cardiovascular System:    arrhythmia, hypotension, myocardial infarction, palpitations, vasculitis



     Digestive System:    colitis, eructation, fulminant hepatitis with and without jaundice, liver failure, liver necrosis, pancreatitis



     Hemic and Lymphatic System:    agranulocytosis, hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia



     Metabolic and Nutritional:    hyperglycemia



     Nervous System:    convulsions, coma, hallucinations, meningitis



     Respiratory System:    respiratory depression, pneumonia



     Skin and Appendages:    angioedema, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, urticaria



     Special Senses:    conjunctivitis, hearing impairment



       Adverse reactions of special interest      



 Based on the analysis of the pooled data from the multi-dose, controlled clinical trials, post-operative patients treated with Dyloject had more adverse reactions related to wound healing (7.5%) compared to patients treated with placebo (4%).



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) in controlled clinical trials include nausea, constipation, headache, infusion site pain, dizziness, flatulence, vomiting, and insomnia. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Hospira, Inc. at 1-800-441-4100 or electronically at ProductComplaintsPP@hospira.com, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS

  WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS

    Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may increase the risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Dyloject is contraindicated for the treatment of perioperative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery [see Contraindications (4)]. 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may increase the risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. Risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. (5.1) 
 *  Dyloject is contraindicated for the treatment of perioperative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4) 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. Events can occur at any time without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Serious and potentially fatal cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke: Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. Use for the shortest possible duration. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation, which can be fatal: Use for the shortest possible duration. Use with caution in patients with prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury with long-term administration of NSAIDs: Use Dyloject with caution in patients at greatest risk for this reaction, including the elderly; those with impaired renal function, heart failure, or liver impairment; and those taking diuretics or ACE inhibitors. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Elevation of one or more liver tests and severe hepatic reactions: Discontinue Dyloject immediately if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen. (  5.4  ) 
 *    New onset or worsening of hypertension: Monitor blood pressure closely during treatment with Dyloject. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Fluid retention and edema: Use Dyloject with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Anaphylactic reactions in patients with the aspirin triad or in patients without prior exposure to Dyloject: Discontinue Dyloject immediately if an anaphylactic reaction occurs. (  5.7  ,  5.13  ) 
 *    Serious skin reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. Discontinue Dyloject if rash or other signs of local skin reaction occur. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Patients should be informed about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 Two large, controlled clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10-14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID does increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) events [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].



    5.2 Gastrointestinal Effects: Risk of Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including Dyloject, can cause serious GI adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs occur in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3-6 months and in about 2-4% of patients treated for one year. These trends continue with longer duration of use, increasing the likelihood of developing a serious GI event at some time during the course of therapy. Dyloject is administered by intravenous injection and is intended for acute short term use. However, even short-term therapy is not without risk. 



 Prescribe NSAIDs, including Dyloject, with extreme caution in those with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or GI bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing a GI bleed compared to treated patients with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk for GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants, longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most reports of spontaneous fatal GI events are in elderly or debilitated patients, and therefore special care should be taken in treating this population.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest possible duration. Patients and physicians should remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulcerations and bleeding during NSAID therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI event is suspected. This should include discontinuation of the NSAID until a serious GI adverse event is ruled out. For high risk patients, alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs should be considered.



    5.3 Renal Effects



  Use caution when initiating treatment with Dyloject in patients with considerable dehydration. Dyloject is not recommended in patients with moderate to severe renal insufficiency and is contraindicated in patients with moderate to severe renal insufficiency in the perioperative period and who are at risk for volume depletion. Acute renal decompensation was observed in 4% out of 68 patients enrolled with renal impairment and treated with Dyloject in clinical trials in the perioperative period.



 Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of an NSAID may cause a dose dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics and ACE inhibitors, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



    5.4 Hepatic Effects



  Elevations of one or more liver tests may occur during therapy with Dyloject. These laboratory abnormalities may progress, may remain unchanged, or may be transient with continued therapy. Borderline elevations (i.e., less than 3 times the ULN [ULN = the upper limit of the normal range]) or greater elevations of transaminases occurred in about 15% of diclofenac-treated patients in clinical trials of indications other than acute pain. Of the markers of hepatic function, ALT (SGPT) is recommended for the monitoring of liver injury.



 In clinical trials of oral diclofenac, meaningful elevations (i.e., more than 3 times the ULN) of AST (SGOT) occurred in about 2% of approximately 5,700 patients at some time during diclofenac treatment (ALT was not measured in all studies).



 In a large, open-label, controlled trial of 3,700 patients treated for 2-6 months, patients were monitored first at 8 weeks and 1,200 patients were monitored again at 24 weeks. Meaningful elevations of ALT and/or AST occurred in about 4% of the 3,700 patients and included marked elevations (i.e., more than 8 times the ULN) in about 1% of the 3,700 patients. In this open-label study, a higher incidence of borderline (less than 3 times the ULN), moderate (3-8 times the ULN), and marked (greater than 8 times the ULN) elevations of ALT or AST was observed in patients receiving diclofenac when compared to other NSAIDs. Elevations in transaminases were seen more frequently in patients with osteoarthritis than in those with rheumatoid arthritis. Almost all meaningful elevations in transaminases were detected before patients became symptomatic. Abnormal tests occurred during the first 2 months of therapy with diclofenac in 42 of the 51 patients in all trials who developed marked transaminase elevations.



 In postmarketing reports, cases of drug-induced hepatotoxicity have been reported in the first month, and in some cases, the first 2 months of therapy, but can occur at any time during treatment with diclofenac. Postmarketing surveillance has reported cases of severe hepatic reactions, including liver necrosis, jaundice, fulminant hepatitis with and without jaundice, and liver failure. Some of these reported cases resulted in fatalities or liver transplantation.



 Measure transaminases (ALT and AST) periodically in patients receiving long-term therapy with diclofenac, because severe hepatotoxicity may develop without a prodrome of distinguishing symptoms. The optimum times for making the first and subsequent transaminase measurements are not known. Based on clinical trial data and postmarketing experiences, transaminases should be monitored within 4 to 8 weeks after initiating treatment with diclofenac. Dyloject is not indicated for long-term treatment. However, severe hepatic reactions can occur at any time during treatment with diclofenac.



 If abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, if clinical signs and/or symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g. eosinophilia, rash, abdominal pain, diarrhea, dark urine, etc.), discontinue Dyloject immediately. To minimize the possibility that hepatic injury will become severe between transaminase measurements, inform patients of the warning signs and symptoms of hepatotoxicity (e.g., nausea, fatigue, lethargy, diarrhea, pruritus, jaundice, right upper quadrant tenderness, and "flu-like" symptoms), and the appropriate action patients should take if these signs and symptoms appear. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse liver-related event in patients treated with diclofenac, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. Exercise caution when prescribing Dyloject with concomitant drugs that are known to be potentially hepatotoxic (e.g., acetaminophen, certain antibiotics, anti-epileptics).



    5.5 Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including Dyloject, can lead to onset of new hypertension or worsening of pre-existing hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. Use NSAIDs, including Dyloject, with caution in patients with hypertension. Monitor blood pressure closely during the initiation of NSAID treatment and throughout the course of therapy.



 Patients taking ACE inhibitors, thiazides or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs.



    5.6 Congestive Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention and edema have been observed in some patients taking NSAIDs. Use Dyloject with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure.



    5.7 Anaphylactic Reactions



  As with other NSAIDs, anaphylactic reactions may occur in patients without known prior exposure to Dyloject. Dyloject is contraindicated in patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.8 Serious Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs, including Dyloject, can cause serious skin adverse reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations, and discontinue Dyloject at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.9 Pregnancy



  Starting at 30 weeks gestation, Dyloject and other NSAIDs, should be avoided by pregnant women as premature closure of the ductus arteriosus in the fetus may occur. If this drug is used during this time period in pregnancy, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].



    5.10 Corticosteroid Treatment



  Dyloject cannot be expected to substitute for corticosteroids or to treat corticosteroid insufficiency. Abrupt discontinuation of corticosteroids may lead to exacerbation of corticosteroid-responsive illness. Patients on prolonged corticosteroid therapy should have their therapy tapered slowly if a decision is made to discontinue corticosteroids.



    5.11 Masking Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of Dyloject in reducing inflammation, and possibly fever, may diminish the utility of these diagnostic signs in detecting infectious complications of presumed noninfectious, painful conditions.



    5.12 Hematological Effects



  Anemia may occur in patients receiving NSAIDs, including Dyloject. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. In patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs, including diclofenac, check hemoglobin or hematocrit if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia or blood loss. Dyloject is not indicated for long-term treatment.



 NSAIDs inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effect on platelet function is quantitatively less, of shorter duration, and reversible. Carefully monitor patients who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants .  



    5.13 Pre-existing Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm, which can be fatal. Since cross-reactivity between aspirin and NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, including bronchospasm, Dyloject is contraindicated in patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and should be used with caution in all patients with pre-existing asthma [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.14 Monitoring



  Because serious GI tract ulcerations and bleeding can occur without warning symptoms, monitor for signs or symptoms of GI bleeding.



 For patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs, periodically check a CBC and chemistry profile, including liver function tests. Discontinue Dyloject if clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver or renal disease develop, systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash), or abnormal liver tests persist or worsen. Dyloject is not indicated for long-term treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
