<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="econazole" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   During clinical trials with Econazole Nitrate Topical Foam, 1%, the most common adverse reactions were application site reactions which occurred in less than 1% of subjects in both the Econazole Nitrate Topical Foam, 1% and vehicle arms. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Xiromed, LLC. at 844-XIROMED (844-947-6633) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In two double-blind, vehicle-controlled clinical trials, 495 subjects were exposed to Econazole Nitrate Topical Foam, 1% or vehicle (246 subjects were exposed to Econazole Nitrate Topical Foam, 1% and 249 were exposed to vehicle). Subjects with interdigital tinea pedis applied foam or vehicle once daily for approximately 28 days. During clinical trials with Econazole Nitrate Topical Foam, 1%, the most common adverse reactions were application site reactions which occurred in less than 1% of subjects in both the Econazole Nitrate Topical Foam, 1% and vehicle arms. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Contents are flammable. Instruct the patient to avoid heat, flame, and/or smoking during and immediately following application. (  5.1  )



 



   5.1 Flammability



  Econazole Nitrate Topical Foam, 1% is flammable. Avoid heat, flame, and smoking during and immediately following application. Contents under pressure. Do not puncture and/or incinerate the containers. Do not expose containers to heat and/or store at temperatures above 120 degrees F (49 degrees C) even when empty. Do not store in direct sunlight.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
