<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="edex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  edex  (r)  , administered by intracavernous injection in doses ranging from 1 to 40 mcg per injection for periods up to 24 months, has been evaluated in clinical trials for safety in over 1,065 patients with erectile dysfunction. Discontinuation of therapy due to a side effect in clinical trials was required in approximately 9% of patients treated with edex  (r)  and in &lt;1% of patients treated with placebo.



   Local Adverse Reactions

  The following local adverse reactions were reported in studies including 1,065 patients treated with edex  (r)  for up to two years.



   Penile Pain

  With use of up to 24 months, penile pain was reported at least once by 29% of patients during injection, 35% of patients during erection, and by 30% of patients after erection. On a per injection basis, 15% of injections were associated with penile pain. Penile pain was judged by patients to be mild in intensity for 80% of painful injections, moderate in intensity for 16% of painful injections, and severe in intensity for 4% of painful injections. The frequency of penile pain reports decreased over time; forty-one percent of the patients experienced pain during the first 2 months and 3% of the patients experienced pain during months 21-24. In placebo-controlled studies, penile pain was reported by 31% of patients after edex  (r)  and by 9% of patients after placebo injection.



   Prolonged Erection/Priapism

  Prolonged erections greater than four hours in duration occurred in 4% of all patients treated up to 24 months. In placebo-controlled studies, 3% of patients treated with edex  (r)  and &lt;1% of patients treated with placebo reported prolonged erections greater than four hours. The incidence of priapism (erections greater than 6 hours in duration) was &lt;1% with long-term use for up to 24 months. In the majority of cases, spontaneous detumescence occurred. A higher incidence of prolonged erections was found in younger patients (&lt;40 years), non-diabetic patients, and patients with psychogenic etiology of erectile dysfunction. (See  WARNINGS  .)



   Hematoma/Ecchymosis

  In patients treated with edex  (r)  for up to 24 months, local bleeding, hematoma and ecchymosis were observed in 15%, 5% and 4% of patients, respectively. In placebo-controlled studies, the frequency of local bleeding was 6% with injection of edex  (r)  and 3% with injection of placebo. In most cases, these reactions were attributed to faulty injection technique.



 Local Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=1% of Patients All Study PeriodsProtocol Numbers KU-620-001, KU-620-002, KU-620-003, F-8653. 
   Local Reaction                         edex  (r)          Local Reaction                 edex  (r)       
                                         N = 1065n (%)                                      N = 1065n (%)     
  
 Penile pain during injection              305 (29)        Ecchymosis                         44 (4)        
 Penile pain during erection               368 (35)        Penile angulation                  72 (7)        
 Penile pain after erection                317 (30)        Penile fibrosis                    52 (5)        
 Penile pain (other)                       116 (11)        Cavernous body fibrosis            20 (2)        
 Prolonged erection                                        Peyronie's disease                 11 (1)        
   &gt; 4 &lt;= 6 Hours                           44 (4)         Faulty injection technique         59 (6)        
   &gt; 6 Hours                                6 (&lt;1)         Penis disorder                     28 (3)        
 Bleeding                                  158 (15)        Erythema                           17 (2)        
 Hematoma                                   56 (5)                                                          
            Systemic Adverse Experiences
   The following systemic adverse experiences were reported in controlled and uncontrolled studies in &gt;=1% of patients treated for up to 24 months with edex  (r)  .



 Systemic Adverse Experiences Reported by &gt;=1% of PatientsProtocol Numbers KU-620-001, KU-620-002, KU-620-003, F-8653. 
   BODY SYSTEMAdverse Experience      edex  (r)  N = 1065n (%)      BODY SYSTEMAdverse Experience      edex  (r)  N = 1065n (%)      BODY SYSTEMAdverse Experience      edex  (r)  N = 1065n (%)     
  
 RESPIRATORY                       CARDIOVASCULAR                         UROGENITAL                             
 Upper respiratory tract               Hypertension               17 (2)      Prostate disorder         15 (1)       
 infection              58 (5)     Myocardial infarction      13 (1)      Testicular pain           13 (1)       
 Sinusitis              14 (1)     Abnormal ECG               12 (1)      Inguinal hernia           11 (1)       
 BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                                 
 Influenza-like symptoms    35 (3)     METABOLIC/NURITIONAL                   DERMATOLOGIC                           
 Headache               20 (2)     Hypertriglyceridemia       17 (2)      Skin disorder             14 (1)       
 Infection              18 (2)     Hypercholesterolemia       12 (1)      SPECIAL SENSES                         
 Pain                   16 (2)     Hyperglycemia              12 (1)      Abnormal vision           11 (1)       
 MUSCULOSKELETAL                                                                                                 
 Back pain              23 (2)                                                                                   
 Leg pain               13 (1)                                                                                   
            Hemodynamic changes, manifested as increases or decreases in blood pressure and pulse rate, were observed during clinical studies but did not appear to be dose-dependent. Four patients (&lt;1%) reported clinical symptoms of hypotension such as dizziness or syncope.
 

 edex  (r)  had no clinically important effect on serum or urine laboratory tests.



   Post-Marketing Adverse Experiences

  Needle breakage.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
