<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="eldepryl" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Introduction

  The number of patients who received selegiline in prospectively monitored pre-marketing studies is limited. While other sources of information about the use of selegiline are available (e.g., literature reports, foreign post-marketing reports, etc.) they do not provide the kind of information necessary to estimate the incidence of adverse events. Thus, overall incidence figures for adverse reactions associated with the use of selegiline cannot be provided. Many of the adverse reactions seen have also been reported as symptoms of dopamine excess.



 Moreover, the importance and severity of various reactions reported often cannot be ascertained. One index of relative importance, however, is whether or not a reaction caused treatment discontinuation. In prospective pre-marketing studies, the following events led, in decreasing order of frequency, to discontinuation of treatment with selegiline: nausea, hallucinations, confusion, depression, loss of balance, insomnia, orthostatic hypotension, increased akinetic involuntary movements, agitation, arrhythmia, bradykinesia, chorea, delusions, hypertension, new or increased angina pectoris, and syncope. Events reported only once as a cause of discontinuation are ankle edema, anxiety, burning lips/mouth, constipation, drowsiness/lethargy, dystonia, excess perspiration, increased freezing, gastrointestinal bleeding, hair loss, increased tremor, nervousness, weakness, and weight loss.



 Experience with ELDEPRYL obtained in parallel, placebo controlled, randomized studies provides only a limited basis for estimates of adverse reaction rates. The following reactions that occurred with greater frequency among the 49 patients assigned to selegiline as compared to the 50 patients assigned to placebo in the only parallel, placebo controlled trial performed in patients with Parkinson's disease are shown in the following Table. None of these adverse reactions led to a discontinuation of treatment.



 INCIDENCE OF TREATMENT-EMERGENT ADVERSE EXPERIENCES IN THE PLACEBO-CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIAL 
   Adverse Event      Number of Patients Reporting Events     
                  selegiline hydrochlorideN = 49  PlaceboN = 50     
 Nausea           10               3                 
 Dizziness/Lightheaded/Fainting  7                1                 
 Abdominal Pain   4                2                 
 Confusion        3                0                 
 Hallucinations   3                1                 
 Dry mouth        3                1                 
 Vivid Dreams     2                0                 
 Dyskinesias      2                5                 
 Headache         2                1                 
   The following events were reported once in either or both groups:     
 Ache, generalized  1                0                 
 Anxiety/Tension  1                1                 
 Anemia           0                1                 
 Diarrhea         1                0                 
 Hair Loss        0                1                 
 Insomnia         1                1                 
 Lethargy         1                0                 
 Leg pain         1                0                 
 Low back pain    1                0                 
 Malaise          0                1                 
 Palpitations     1                0                 
 Urinary Retention  1                0                 
 Weight Loss      1                0                 
         In all prospectively monitored clinical investigations, enrolling approximately 920 patients, the following adverse events, classified by body system, were reported.
 

   Central Nervous System

  Motor/Coordination/Extrapyramidal

  increased tremor, chorea, loss of balance, restlessness, blepharospasm, increased bradykinesia, facial grimace, falling down, heavy leg, muscle twitch  *  , myoclonic jerks  *  , stiff neck, tardive dyskinesia, dystonic symptoms, dyskinesia, involuntary movements, freezing, festination, increased apraxia, muscle cramps.



   Mental Status/Behavioral/Psychiatric

  hallucinations, dizziness, confusion, anxiety, depression, drowsiness, behavior/mood change, dreams/nightmares, tiredness, delusions, disorientation, lightheadedness, impaired memory  *  , increased energy  *  , transient high  *  , hollow feeling, lethargy/malaise, apathy, overstimulation, vertigo, personality change, sleep disturbance, restlessness, weakness, transient irritability.



   Pain/Altered Sensation

  headache, back pain, leg pain, tinnitus, migraine, supraorbital pain, throat burning, generalized ache, chills, numbness of toes/fingers, taste disturbance.



   Autonomic Nervous System

  dry mouth, blurred vision, sexual dysfunction.



   Cardiovascular

  orthostatic hypotension, hypertension, arrhythmia, palpitations, new or increased angina pectoris, hypotension, tachycardia, peripheral edema, sinus bradycardia, syncope.



   Gastrointestinal

  nausea/vomiting, constipation, weight loss, anorexia, poor appetite, dysphagia, diarrhea, heartburn, rectal bleeding, bruxism  *  , gastrointestinal bleeding (exacerbation of preexisting ulcer disease).



   Genitourinary/Gynecologic/Endocrine

  slow urination, transient anorgasmia  *  , nocturia, prostatic hypertrophy, urinary hesitancy, urinary retention, decreased penile sensation  *  , urinary frequency.



   Skin and Appendages

  increased sweating, diaphoresis, facial hair, hair loss, hematoma, rash, photosensitivity.



   Miscellaneous

  asthma, diplopia, shortness of breath, speech affected.



   Post-marketing Reports

  The following experiences were described in spontaneous post-marketing reports. These reports do not provide sufficient information to establish a clear causal relationship with the use of ELDEPRYL.



   CNS

  Seizure in dialyzed chronic renal failure patient on concomitant medications.



 * indicates events reported only at doses greater than 10 mg/day.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
