<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="elestrin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular Disorders [see  Boxed Warning  , and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Malignant Neoplasms [see  Boxed Warning  , and Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
      EXCERPT:   In a placebo-controlled trial that included a total of 484 postmenopausal women, the most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5 percent) are breast tenderness, metrorrhagia, nasopharyngitis, and upper respiratory tract infections. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Azur at 1-800-890-3098 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 ELESTRIN was studied in a placebo-controlled trial that included a total of 484 postmenopausal women. The adverse reactions that occurred at a rate greater than 5 percent in any of the treatment groups are summarized in Table 1.



 TABLE 1 - Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 5 Percent of Subjects 
   Body System / Signs and Symptoms      Number (%) of Subjects     
   Placebo   (n = 137)                     ELESTRIN 0.87 g/day   (n = 136)         ELESTRIN 1.7 g/day   (n = 142)     
  
 Reproductive system &amp; breast disorders                                                                         
   Breast tenderness                  5 (3.6)               9 (6.6)                  11 (7.7)                
   Metrorrhagia                       3 (2.2)               6 (4.4)                  13 (9.2)                
 Respiratory, thoracic &amp; mediastinal disorders                                                                            
   Nasopharyngitis                    10 (7.3)              14 (10.3)                12 (8.5)                
   Upper respiratory tract infection  5 (3.6)               8 (5.9)                  5 (3.5)                 
            6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ELESTRIN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Genitourinary System  



 Changes in vaginal bleeding pattern and abnormal withdrawal bleeding or flow; breakthrough bleeding; spotting; dysmenorrhea; increase in size of uterine leiomyomata; vaginitis, including vaginal candidiasis; change in amount of cervical secretion; changes in cervical ectropion; ovarian cancer; endometrial hyperplasia; endometrial cancer.



   Breasts  



 Tenderness; enlargement, pain, nipple discharge, galactorrhea; fibrocystic breast changes; breast cancer.



   Cardiovascular  



 Deep and superficial venous thrombosis; pulmonary embolism; thrombophlebitis; myocardial infarction; stroke; increase in blood pressure.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Nausea, vomiting; abdominal cramps, bloating; cholestatic jaundice; increased incidence of gallbladder disease; pancreatitis, enlargement of hepatic hemangiomas.



   Skin  



 Chloasma or melasma that may persist when drug is discontinued; erythema multiforme; erythema nodosum; hemorrhagic eruption; loss of scalp hair; hirsutism; pruritus, rash.



   Eyes  



 Retinal vascular thrombosis, intolerance to contact lenses.



   Central Nervous System  



 Headache; migraine; dizziness; mental depression; chorea; nervousness; mood disturbances; irritability; exacerbation of epilepsy, dementia.



   Miscellaneous  



 Increase or decrease in weight; reduced carbohydrate tolerance; aggravation of porphyria; edema; arthralgias; leg cramps; changes in libido; urticaria, angioedema, anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions; hypocalcemia; exacerbation of asthma; increased triglycerides.



 Additional postmarketing adverse reactions have been reported in women receiving other forms of hormone therapy.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA

  WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA

      Estrogen-Alone Therapy    



   Endometrial Cancer  



   There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed, persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    



   Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,   5.3  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  ,   14.3  )].    



   The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg]-alone, relative to placebo   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].    



   The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )].    



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and other dosage forms of estrogens.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.  



     Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy    



   Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,   5.3  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  ,   14.3  )].    



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].    



   The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )].    



   Breast Cancer  



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].    



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual women.   



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



     Estrogen-Alone Therapy    



 *  There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens (5.2) 
 *  Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.1, 5.3) 
 *  The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) (5.1) 
 *  The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.3) 
        Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy    
 

 *  Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.1, 5.3) 
 *  The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of stroke, DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), and myocardial infarction (MI) (5.1) 
 *  The WHI estrogen plus progestin study reported increased risks of invasive breast cancer (5.2) 
 *  The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.3) 
    
 







    BOXED WARNING: FDA-Approved Patient Labeling

  FDA-Approved Patient Labeling

    ELESTRINTM     (estradiol gel)  



 Read this PATIENT INFORMATION before you start using ELESTRIN and read what you get each time you refill your ELESTRIN prescription. There may be new information. This information does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your menopausal symptoms or your treatment.



     What is the most important information I should know about ELESTRIN (an estrogen hormone)?  



 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb) 
    Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are using ELESTRIN. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause.
 

 *  Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes, or dementia (decline in brain function) 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting strokes or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older 
 *  Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older 
 *  You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with ELESTRIN 
        What is ELESTRIN?  
 

 ELESTRIN is a medicine in a colorless gel that contains an estrogen hormone (estradiol) which is absorbed through the skin into the bloodstream.



   What is ELESTRIN used for?  



 ELESTRIN is used after menopause to:



 *  Reduce moderate to severe hot flashes 
    Estrogens are hormones made by a woman's ovaries. The ovaries normally stop making estrogens when a woman is between 45 to 55 years old. This drop in body estrogen levels causes the "change of life" or menopause (the end of monthly menstrual periods). Sometimes, both ovaries are removed during an operation before natural menopause takes place. The sudden drop in estrogen levels causes "surgical menopause."
 

 When the estrogen levels begin dropping, some women develop very uncomfortable symptoms, such as feelings of warmth in the face, neck, and chest, or sudden strong feelings of heat and sweating ("hot flashes" or "hot flushes"). In some women, the symptoms are mild, and they will not need estrogens. In other women, symptoms can be more severe. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with ELESTRIN.



   Who should not use ELESTRIN?  



 Do not start using ELESTRIN if you:



 *  Have unusual vaginal bleeding 
 *  Currently have or have had certain cancersEstrogens may increase the chance of getting certain types of cancers, including cancer of the breast or uterus. If you have or have had cancer, talk with your healthcare provider about whether you should use ELESTRIN. 
 *  Had a stroke or heart attack 
 *  Currently have or have had blood clots 
 *  Currently have or have had liver problems 
 *  Have been diagnosed with a bleeding disorder 
 *  Are allergic to ELESTRIN or any of its ingredientsSee the list of ingredients in ELESTRIN at the end of this leaflet 
 *  Think you may be pregnant 
      Tell your healthcare provider:  
 

 *  If you have any unusual vaginal bleedingVaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  About all of your medical problems Your healthcare provider may need to check you more carefully if you have certain conditions, such as asthma (wheezing), epilepsy (seizures), diabetes, migraine, endometriosis, lupus, or problems with your heart, liver, thyroid, kidneys, or have high calcium levels in your blood. 
 *  About all the medicines you take This includes prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Some medicines may affect how ELESTRIN works. ELESTRIN may also affect how your other medicines work. 
 *  If you are going to have surgery or will be on bed rest You may need to stop using ELESTRIN. 
 *  If you are breastfeedingThe hormone in ELESTRIN can pass into your breast milk. 
      How should I use ELESTRIN?  
 

 *  Start at the lowest dose and talk to your healthcare provider about how well that dose is working for you. 
 *  ELESTRIN should be used at the lowest dose possible for your treatment and only as long as needed. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly (for example, every 3 to 6 months) about the dose you are taking and whether you still need treatment with ELESTRIN. 
    ELESTRIN comes in a metered-dose pump. One dose of ELESTRIN is released each time the pump is depressed (pressed down).
 

 Use ELESTRIN exactly how your healthcare provider tells you.



 The ELESTRIN pump contains enough of the medicine to let you prime the pump before you use it the first time (ten depressions) and then use the pump a total of 100 times (100 depressions) as prescribed by your healthcare provider. 



 After you have initially primed the pump with ten pump depressions and have used a total of 100 doses of ELESTRIN, you will need to throw the pump away and use a new one. The correct amount of medicine in each dose cannot be assured after 100 doses have been used, even though the pump container is not completely empty.



   Important things to remember when using ELESTRIN  



        Wash your hands with soap and water after applying the gel to reduce the chance that the medicine will be spread from your hands to other people.  



      Allow the gel to dry for five minutes or more before dressing. Try to keep the area dry for as long as possible.



      Do not allow others to come in contact with the area of skin where you applied the gel for at least two hours after you apply ELESTRIN.



        Always move the spout into locked position and place the cap over the top of the pump after each use.  



        Never apply ELESTRIN to the breast. Never apply ELESTRIN in or around the vagina.  



      Do not allow others to apply the gel for you.



        Do not apply sunscreen to the area where the gel was applied for at least 25 minutes.  



        Do not apply sunscreen to the area where the gel was applied for 7 or more consecutive days.  



        Avoid fire, flame or smoking until the gel has dried. ELESTRIN contains alcohol. Alcohol based gels are flammable.  



   It is important that you read and follow the detailed "Patient Instructions for Use" at the end of this leaflet on how to use the ELESTRIN pump and apply the dose.  



   What should I do if someone else is exposed to ELESTRIN?  



 If someone else is exposed to ELESTRIN by direct contact with the gel, that person should wash the area of contact with soap and water as soon as possible. The longer the gel is in contact with the skin before washing, the greater is the chance that the other person will absorb some of the estrogen hormone. This is especially important for men and children.



   What should I do if I get ELESTRIN in my eyes?  



 If you get ELESTRIN in your eyes, rinse your eyes right away with warm clean water to flush out any ELESTRIN. Seek medical attention if needed.



   What should I do if I miss a dose?  



 If you miss a dose, do not double the dose on the next day to catch up. If your next dose is less than 12 hours away, it is best just to wait and apply your normal dose the next day. If it is more than 12 hours until the next dose, apply the dose you missed and resume your normal dosing the next day.



   What are the possible side effects of ELESTRIN?  



   Side effects are grouped by how serious they are and how often they happen when you are treated.  



   Serious, but less common side effects include:  



 *  Heart attack 
 *  Stroke 
 *  Blood clots 
 *  Dementia 
 *  Breast cancer 
 *  Cancer of the lining of the uterus (womb) 
 *  Cancer of the ovary 
 *  High blood pressure 
 *  High blood sugar 
 *  Gallbladder disease 
 *  Liver problems 
 *  Enlargement of benign tumors of the uterus ("fibroids") 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you get any of the following warning signs or any other unusual symptoms that concern you:  
 

 *  New breast lumps 
 *  Unusual vaginal bleeding 
 *  Changes in vision or speech 
 *  Sudden new severe headaches 
 *  Severe pains in your chest or legs with or without shortness of breath, weakness and fatigue 
      Less serious, but common side effects include:  
 

 *  Headache 
 *  Breast pain 
 *  Irregular vaginal bleeding or spotting 
 *  Stomach or abdominal cramps, bloating 
 *  Nausea and vomiting 
 *  Hair loss 
 *  Fluid retention 
 *  Vaginal yeast infection 
    These are not all the possible side effects of ELESTRIN. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for advice about side effects. You may report side effects to Azur Pharma at 1-800-890-3098 or to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.
 

   What can I do to lower my chances of a serious side effect with ELESTRIN?   



 *  Talk with your healthcare provider regularly about whether you should continue using ELESTRIN 
 *  If you have a uterus, talk to your healthcare provider about whether the addition of a progestin is right for you The addition of a progestin is generally recommended for a woman with a uterus to reduce the chance of getting cancer of the uterus. See your healthcare provider right away if you get vaginal bleeding while using ELESTRIN. 
 *  Have a pelvic exam, breast exam and mammogram (breast X-ray) every year unless your healthcare provider tells you something else If members of your family have had breast cancer or if you have ever had breast lumps or an abnormal mammogram, you may need to have breast exams more often. 
 *  If you have high blood pressure, high cholesterol (fat in the blood), diabetes, are overweight, or if you use tobacco, you may have a higher chance for getting heart disease Ask your healthcare provider for ways to lower your chances of getting heart disease. 
      General information about the safe and effective use of ELESTRIN  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for conditions that are not mentioned in patient information leaflets. Do not use ELESTRIN for conditions for which it was not prescribed. Do not give ELESTRIN to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them.



   Keep ELESTRIN out of the reach of children   



 This leaflet provides a summary of the most important information about ELESTRIN. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider or pharmacist. You can ask for information about ELESTRIN that is written for health professionals. You can get more information by calling   1-800-890-3098   (toll free).



 Patient Instructions for Use.



   1. Remove the cap.  



   2. Activate the pump.  



 *  Unlock the pump by turning the spout on top of the bottle a quarter turn to the left or the right 
      3. Prime the pump before using the pump for the first time.  
 

 *  Prime the pump by fully depressing the spout ten times 
 *  Throw away the unused gel by placing it in the trash to avoid another person or pet from accidental contact with the gel or, eating or drinking it 
 *  After priming, the pump is ready to use 
 *  One complete pump depression will dispense the same amount of ELESTRIN each time. After each daily dose, return the spout to the locked position and replace the cap before you put it away 
      4. Apply ELESTRIN.  
 

 *  Dry skin completely before applying ELESTRINYou should apply your daily dose of gel to clean, dry, unbroken skin. If you take a bath or shower or use a sauna, apply ELESTRIN after your bath, shower, or sauna. If you go swimming, try to leave as much time as possible, at least 2 hours, between applying your ELESTRIN dose and going into the water. 
 *  Apply ELESTRIN at the same time each day 
      Figure 1  To apply the dose, hold the pump with the tip facing the application area of the arm. For each pump depression needed, press the pump firmly and fully with a continuous motion without hesitation.
 

   Figure 2  Gently spread the gel using only 2 fingers. Spread and gently rub in the gel over the entire area of your upper arm and shoulder area, as illustrated.



   5. Wash your hands with soap and water.  



 ELESTRIN should not be used after the date printed on the container (expiration date).



   What are the ingredients in ELESTRIN?   



 Active ingredient: estradiol.



 Inactive ingredients: purified water, ethanol, propylene glycol, diethylene glycol monoethyl ether, carbomer 940, triethanolamine, and edetate disodium.



 ELESTRINTM is a trademark of Azur Pharma International II Limited



 Distributed by:



 1818 Market Street, Suite 2350, Philadelphia, PA 19103  www.azurpharma.com



 Manufactured by:



   DPT Laboratories, Ltd.  318 McCulloughSan Antonio, TX 78215



 U.S. Pat. No. 7,198,801 and U.S. Pat. No. 7,470,433



  Figure 1 -- Image for Applying Elestrin  Figure 2 -- Image for Spreading Elestrin  Azur Pharma Logo 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Estrogens increase the risk of gallbladder disease (  5.4  ) 
 *  Discontinue estrogen if severe hypercalcemia, loss of vision, severe hypertriglyceridemia or cholestatic jaundice occurs (  5.5  ,  5.6  ,  5.9  ,  5.10  ) 
 *  Monitor thyroid function in women on thyroid replacement therapy (  5.11  ,  5.21  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Disorders



  An increased risk of stroke and DVT has been reported with estrogen-alone therapy.



 An increased risk of PE, DVT, stroke and MI has been reported with estrogen plus progestin therapy. Should any of these occur or be suspected, estrogen with or without progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 Risk factors for arterial vascular disease (for example, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, tobacco use, hypercholesterolemia, and obesity) and/or venous thromboembolism (VTE) (for example, personal history or family history of VTE, obesity, and systemic lupus erythematosus) should be managed appropriately.



  Stroke  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (45 versus 33 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in risk was demonstrated in year 1 and persisted [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  . Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest no increased risk of stroke for those women receiving CE (0.625 mg)-alone versus those receiving placebo (18 versus 21 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (33 versus 25 per 10,000 women-years) [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  . The increase in risk was demonstrated after the first year and persisted.  1  Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



  Coronary Heart Disease  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, no overall effect on coronary heart disease (CHD) events (defined as nonfatal MI, silent MI and CHD death) was reported in women receiving estrogen-alone compared to placebo  2    [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  .



 Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest a statistically non-significant reduction in CHD events (CE [0.625 mg]-alone compared to placebo) in women with less than 10 years since menopause (8 versus 16 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, there was a statistically non-significant increased risk of CHD events reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (41 versus 34 per 10,000 women-years).  1  An increase in relative risk was demonstrated in year 1, and a trend toward decreasing relative risk was reported in years 2 through 5 [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  .



 In postmenopausal women with documented heart disease (n = 2,763, average 66.7 years of age), in a controlled clinical trial of secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease (Heart and Estrogen/Progestin Replacement Study [HERS]), treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) demonstrated no cardiovascular benefit. During an average follow-up of 4.1 years, treatment with CE plus MPA did not reduce the overall rate of CHD events in postmenopausal women with established coronary heart disease. There were more CHD events in the CE plus MPA-treated group than in the placebo group in year 1, but not during the subsequent years. Two thousand, three hundred and twenty-one (2,321) women from the original HERS trial agreed to participate in an open label extension of HERS, HERS II. Average follow-up in HERS II was an additional 2.7 years, for a total of 6.8 years overall. Rates of CHD events were comparable among women in the CE plus MPA group and the placebo group in HERS, HERS II, and overall.



  Venous Thromboembolism  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, the risk of VTE (DVT and PE) was increased for women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to placebo (30 versus 22 per 10,000 women-years), although only the increased risk of DVT reached statistical significance (23 versus 15 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first 2 years  3    [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  . Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant 2-fold greater rate of VTE was reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (35 versus 17 per 10,000 women-years). Statistically significant increases in risk for both DVT (26 versus 13 per 10,000 women-years) and PE (18 versus 8 per 10,000 women-years) were also demonstrated. The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first year and persisted  4    [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  . Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 If feasible, estrogens should be discontinued at least 4 to 6 weeks before surgery of the type associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, or during periods of prolonged immobilization.



    5.2 Malignant Neoplasms



   Endometrial Cancer  



 An increased risk of endometrial cancer has been reported with the use of unopposed estrogen therapy in a woman with a uterus. The reported endometrial cancer risk among unopposed estrogen users is about 2 to 12 times greater than in non-users, and appears dependent on duration of treatment and on estrogen dose. Most studies show no significant increased risk associated with use of estrogens for less than 1 year. The greatest risk appears associated with prolonged use, with an increased risk of 15- to 24-fold for 5 to 10 years or more. This risk has been shown to persist for at least 8 to 15 years after estrogen therapy is discontinued.



 Clinical surveillance of all women using estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy is important. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding.



 There is no evidence that the use of natural estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens of equivalent estrogen dose. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



 In a 12-week clinical trial, one case of complex hyperplasia with atypia was reported in the ELESTRIN 1.7 g per day dose.



  Breast Cancer  



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen-alone users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone. In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, after an average of follow-up of 7.1 years, daily CE-alone was not associated with an increased risk of invasive breast cancer [relative risk (RR) 0.80]  5      [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  .



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen plus progestin users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg). After a mean follow-up of 5.6 years, the estrogen plus progestin substudy reported an increased risk of invasive breast cancer in women who took daily CE plus MPA.



 In this substudy, prior use of estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy was reported by 26 percent of the women. The relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.24, and the absolute risk was 41 versus 33 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.86, and the absolute risk was 46 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported no prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.09, and the absolute risk was 40 versus 36 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. In the same substudy, invasive breast cancers were larger, were more likely to be node positive, and were diagnosed at a more advanced stage in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group compared with the placebo group. Metastatic disease was rare, with no apparent difference between the two groups. Other prognostic factors such as histologic subtype, grade and hormone receptor status did not differ between the groups.  6    [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  .



 Consistent with the WHI clinical trial, observational studies have also reported an increased risk of breast cancer for estrogen plus progestin therapy, and a smaller increased risk for estrogen-alone therapy, after several years of use. The risk increased with duration of use, and appeared to return to baseline over about 5 years after stopping treatment (only the observational studies have substantial data on risk after stopping). Observational studies also suggest that the risk of breast cancer was greater, and became apparent earlier, with estrogen plus progestin therapy as compared to estrogen-alone therapy. However, these studies have not generally found significant variation in the risk of breast cancer among different estrogen plus progestin combinations, doses, or routes of administration.



 The use of estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin has been reported to result in an increase in abnormal mammograms requiring further evaluation.



 All women should receive yearly breast examinations by a healthcare provider and perform monthly self-examinations. In addition, mammography examinations should be scheduled based on patient age, risk factors, and prior mammogram results.



  Ovarian Cancer  



 The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported a statistically non-significant increased risk of ovarian cancer. After an average follow-up of 5.6 years, the relative risk for ovarian cancer for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 1.58 [95 percent CI, 0.77-3.24]. The absolute risk for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 4 versus 3 cases per 10,000 women-years.  7  In some epidemiological studies, the use of estrogen plus progestin and estrogen-only products, in particular for 5 or more years, has been associated with an increased risk of ovarian cancer. However, the duration of exposure associated with increased risk is not consistent across all epidemiologic studies, and some report no association.



    5.3 Probable Dementia



  In the WHIMS estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI, a population of 2,947 hysterectomized women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone or placebo.



 After an average follow-up of 5.2 years, 28 women in the estrogen-alone group and 19 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 1.49 (95 percent CI, 0.83-2.66). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 37 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years  8    [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  .



 In the WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study, a population of 4,532 postmenopausal women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) or placebo.



 After an average follow-up of 4 years, 40 women in the CE plus MPA group and 21 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 2.05 (95 percent CI, 1.21-3.48). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 45 versus 22 cases per 10,000 women-years  8    [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  .



 When data from the two populations in the WHIMS estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin ancillary studies were pooled as planned in the WHIMS protocol, the reported overall relative risk for probable dementia was 1.76 (95 percent CI, 1.19-2.60). Since both ancillary studies were conducted in women 65 to 79 years of age, it is unknown whether these findings apply to younger postmenopausal women  8    [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  .



    5.4 Gallbladder Disease



  A 2- to 4-fold increase in the risk of gallbladder disease requiring surgery in postmenopausal women receiving estrogens has been reported.



    5.5 Hypercalcemia



  Estrogen administration may lead to severe hypercalcemia in women with breast cancer and bone metastases. If hypercalcemia occurs, use of the drug should be stopped and appropriate measures taken to reduce the serum calcium level.



    5.6 Visual Abnormalities



  Retinal vascular thrombosis has been reported in women receiving estrogens. Discontinue medication pending examination if there is sudden partial or complete loss of vision, or a sudden onset of proptosis, diplopia, or migraine. If examination reveals papilledema or retinal vascular lesions, estrogens should be permanently discontinued.



    5.7 Addition of a Progestin When a Woman Has Not Had a Hysterectomy



  Studies of the addition of a progestin for 10 or more days of a cycle of estrogen administration, or daily with estrogen in a continuous regimen, have reported a lowered incidence of endometrial hyperplasia than would be induced by estrogen treatment alone. Endometrial hyperplasia may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



 There are, however, possible risks that may be associated with the use of progestins with estrogens compared to estrogen-alone regimens. These include an increased risk of breast cancer.



    5.8 Elevated Blood Pressure



  In a small number of case reports, substantial increases in blood pressure have been attributed to idiosyncratic reactions to estrogens. In a large, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial, a generalized effect of estrogens on blood pressure was not seen.



    5.9 Hypertriglyceridemia



  In women with pre-existing hypertriglyceridemia, estrogen therapy may be associated with elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis. Consider discontinuation of treatment if pancreatitis occurs.



    5.10 Hepatic Impairment and/or Past History of Cholestatic Jaundice



  Estrogens may be poorly metabolized in women with impaired liver function. For women with a history of cholestatic jaundice associated with past estrogen use or with pregnancy, caution should be exercised, and in the case of recurrence, medication should be discontinued.



    5.11 Hypothyroidism



  Estrogen administration leads to increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels. Women with normal thyroid function can compensate for the increased TBG by making more thyroid hormone, thus maintaining free T4and T3serum concentrations in the normal range. Women dependent on thyroid hormone replacement therapy who are also receiving estrogens may require increased doses of their thyroid replacement therapy. These women should have their thyroid function monitored to maintain their free thyroid hormone levels in an acceptable range.



    5.12 Fluid Retention



  Estrogens may cause some degree of fluid retention. Women with conditions that might be influenced by this factor, such as a cardiac or renal dysfunction, warrant careful observation when estrogen-alone is prescribed.



    5.13 Hypocalcemia



  Estrogen therapy should be used with caution in women with hypoparathyroidism as estrogen-induced hypocalcemia may occur.



    5.14 Exacerbation of Endometriosis



  A few cases of malignant transformation of residual endometrial implants have been reported in women treated post-hysterectomy with estrogen-alone therapy. For women known to have residual endometriosis post-hysterectomy, the addition of progestin should be considered.



     5.15 Hereditary Angioedema  



   Exogenous estrogens may exacerbate symptoms of angioedema in women with hereditary angioedema.  



    5.16 Exacerbation of Other Conditions



  Estrogen therapy may cause an exacerbation of asthma, diabetes mellitus, epilepsy, migraine, porphyria, systemic lupus erythematosus, and hepatic hemangiomas and should be used with caution in women with these conditions.



    5.17 Photosensitivity or Photoallergy



  Increased sensitivity to direct exposure to the sun on areas of ELESTRIN application has not been evaluated.



    5.18 Sunscreen Application



  Estradiol absorption was increased when sunscreen was applied 10 minutes before ELESTRIN application. Sunscreen should not be applied to the same site until at least 25 minutes after the application of ELESTRIN.



 Concomitant application of sunscreen and ELESTRIN to the same application site for 7 or more days may increase estradiol absorption. Avoid applying sunscreen to the area of ELESTRIN application for an extended period of 7 or more days [see Clinical Pharmacology,  Pharmacokinetics (  12.3  )]  .



    5.19 Miscellaneous



  Alcohol based gels potentially are flammable. Avoid fire, flame, or smoking until the gel has dried.



    5.20 Laboratory Tests



  Serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels have not been shown to be useful in the management of moderate to severe vasomotor symptoms.



    5.21 Drug-Laboratory Test Interactions



  Accelerated prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet aggregation time; increased platelet count; increased factors II, VII antigen, VIII antigen, VIII coagulant activity, IX, X, XII, VII-X complex, II-VII-X complex, and beta-thromboglobulin; decreased levels of anti-factor Xa and antithrombin III, decreased antithrombin III activity; increased levels of fibrinogen and fibrinogen activity; increased plasminogen antigen and activity.



 Increased thyroid binding globulin (TBG) levels leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone levels as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T4levels (by column or by radioimmunoassay) or T3levels by radioimmunoassay. T3resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG. Free T4and free T3concentrations are unaltered. Women on thyroid replacement therapy may require higher doses of thyroid hormone.



 Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum, for example, corticosteroid binding globulin (CBG), sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), leading to increased total circulating corticosteroids and sex steroids, respectively. Free hormone concentrations, such as testosterone and estradiol, may be decreased. Other plasma proteins may be increased (angiotensinogen/renin substrate, alpha-1-antitrypsin, ceruloplasmin).



 Increased plasma high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and HDL2cholesterol subfraction concentrations, reduced low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol concentration, increased triglycerides levels.



 Impaired glucose tolerance.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
