<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="elestat" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common ocular adverse reactions (incidence occurring in approximately 1% - 10% of  ELESTAT    (r)  treated eyes were burning sensation in the eye, folliculosis, hyperemia, and pruritus. The most common non-ocular adverse reactions, occurring in 10% of  ELESTAT    (r)  treated eyes, were infection (cold symptoms and upper respiratory infections). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Allergan at 1-800-433-8871 or the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most frequently reported ocular adverse reactions occurring in approximately 1-10% of patients were burning sensation in the eye, folliculosis, hyperemia, and pruritus.



 The most frequently reported non-ocular adverse reactions were infection (cold symptoms and upper respiratory infections), seen in approximately 10% of patients, and headache, rhinitis, sinusitis, increased cough, and pharyngitis, seen in approximately 1 - 3% of patients.



 Some of these reactions were similar to the underlying disease being studied.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of  ELESTAT    (r)  in clinical practice. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. The reactions, which have been chosen for inclusion due to either their seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to  ELESTAT    (r)  , or a combination of these factors, include: lacrimation increased.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  To minimize the risk of contamination, do not touch dropper tip to any surface. Keep bottle tightly closed when not in use. (  5.1  ) 
 *   ELESTAT   (r)  should not be used to treat contact lens-related irritation. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Remove contact lenses prior to instillation of ELESTAT   (r)  . (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Contamination of Tip and Solution



  Patients should be instructed to avoid allowing the tip of the dispensing container to contact the eye, surrounding structures, fingers, or any other surface in order to avoid contamination of the solution by common bacteria known to cause ocular infections. Serious damage to the eye and subsequent loss of vision may result from using contaminated solutions.



 Bottle should be kept tightly closed when not in use.



    5.2 Use with Contact Lenses



  Patients should be advised not to wear a contact lens if their eye is red. ELESTAT    (r)  ophthalmic solution should not be used to treat contact lens-related irritation.



 The preservative in ELESTAT    (r)  , benzalkonium chloride, may be absorbed by soft contact lenses. Contact lenses should be removed prior to instillation of ELESTAT    (r)  ophthalmic solution and may be reinserted after 10 minutes following its administration.



    5.3 Topical Ophthalmic Use Only



   ELESTAT    (r)  is for topical ophthalmic use only and not for injection or oral use.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
