<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="eloxatin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Anaphylaxis and Allergic reactions [See   Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   .] 
 *  Neuropathy [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   .] 
 *  Pulmonary Toxicities [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   .] 
 *  Hepatotoxicity [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   .] 
   *  Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 40%) were peripheral sensory neuropathy, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, nausea, increase in transaminases and alkaline phosphatase, diarrhea, emesis, fatigue and stomatitis. Other adverse reactions, including serious adverse reactions, have been reported. (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi-aventis U.S. LLC at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 More than 1100 patients with stage II or III colon cancer and more than 4,000 patients with advanced colorectal cancer have been treated in clinical studies with ELOXATIN. The most common adverse reactions in patients with stage II or III colon cancer receiving adjuvant therapy were peripheral sensory neuropathy, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, nausea, increase in transaminases and alkaline phosphatase, diarrhea, emesis, fatigue and stomatitis. The most common adverse reactions in previously untreated and treated patients were peripheral sensory neuropathies, fatigue, neutropenia, nausea, emesis, and diarrhea  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5)  ].  



   

    Combination Adjuvant Therapy with ELOXATIN and Infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin in Patients with Colon Cancer  



 One thousand one hundred and eight patients with stage II or III colon cancer, who had undergone complete resection of the primary tumor, have been treated in a clinical study with ELOXATIN in combination with infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ].  The incidence of grade 3 or 4 adverse reactions was 70% on the ELOXATIN combination arm, and 31% on the infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm. The adverse reactions in this trial are shown in the tables below. Discontinuation of treatment due to adverse reactions occurred in 15% of the patients receiving ELOXATIN and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin. Both 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin and ELOXATIN are associated with gastrointestinal or hematologic adverse reactions. When ELOXATIN is administered in combination with infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, the incidence of these events is increased.



 The incidence of death within 28 days of last treatment, regardless of causality, was 0.5% (n=6) in both the ELOXATIN combination and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arms, respectively. Deaths within 60 days from initiation of therapy were 0.3% (n=3) in both the ELOXATIN combination and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arms, respectively. On the ELOXATIN combination arm, 3 deaths were due to sepsis/neutropenic sepsis, 2 from intracerebral bleeding and one from eosinophilic pneumonia. On the 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm, one death was due to suicide, 2 from Steven-Johnson Syndrome (1 patient also had sepsis), 1 unknown cause, 1 anoxic cerebral infarction and 1 probable abdominal aorta rupture.



 The following table provides adverse reactions reported in the adjuvant therapy colon cancer clinical trial  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  by body system and decreasing order of frequency in the ELOXATIN and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm for events with overall incidences &gt;= 5% and for NCI grade 3/4 events with incidences &gt;= 1%.



 Table 3 - Adverse Reactions Reported in Patients with Colon Cancer receiving Adjuvant Treatment (&gt;=5% of all patients and with &gt;=1% NCI Grade 3/4 events) 
                           ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LVN=1108     5-FU/LVN=1111      
 Adverse reaction(WHO/Pref)     All Grades(%)        Grade 3/4(%)         All Grades(%)        Grade 3/4(%)       
  
 Any Event                         100                  70                   99                   31            
   Allergy/Immunology       
 Allergic Reaction                 10                    3                    2                   &lt;1            
   Constitutional Symptoms/Pain     
 Fatigue                           44                    4                   38                    1            
 Abdominal Pain                    18                    1                   17                    2            
   Dermatology/Skin         
 Skin Disorder                     32                    2                   36                    2            
 Injection Site Reaction           11                    3                   10                    3            
   Gastrointestinal         
 Nausea                            74                    5                   61                    2            
 Diarrhea                          56                   11                   48                    7            
 Vomiting                          47                    6                   24                    1            
 Stomatitis                        42                    3                   40                    2            
 Anorexia                          13                    1                    8                   &lt;1            
   Fever/Infection          
 Fever                             27                    1                   12                    1            
 Infection                         25                    4                   25                    3            
   Neurology                
 Overall Peripheral Sensory Neuropathy          92                   12                   16                   &lt;1            
           The following table provides adverse reactions reported in the adjuvant therapy colon cancer clinical trial  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  by body system and decreasing order of frequency in the ELOXATIN and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm for events with overall incidences &gt;= 5% but with incidences &lt;1% NCI grade 3/4 events.
 

 Table 4 - Adverse Reactions Reported in Patients with Colon Cancer receiving Adjuvant Treatment (&gt;= 5% of all patients, but with &lt;1% NCI Grade 3/4 events) 
                                         Eloxatin + 5-FU/LVN=1108                 5-FU/LVN=1111             
 Adverse reaction(WHO/Pref)                   All Grades (%)                     All Grades (%)             
  
   Allergy/Immunology                 
 Rhinitis                                            6                                  8                   
   Constitutional Symptoms/Pain/Ocular/Visual     
 Epistaxis                                          16                                 12                   
 Weight Increase                                    10                                 10                   
 Conjunctivitis                                      9                                 15                   
 Headache                                            7                                  5                   
 Dyspnea                                             5                                  3                   
 Pain                                                5                                  5                   
 Lacrimation Abnormal                                4                                 12                   
   Dermatology/Skin                   
 Alopecia                                           30                                 28                   
   Gastrointestinal                   
 Constipation                                       22                                 19                   
 Taste Perversion                                   12                                  8                   
 Dyspepsia                                           8                                  5                   
   Metabolic                          
 Phosphate Alkaline increased                       42                                 20                   
   Neurology                          
 Sensory Disturbance                                 8                                  1                   
         Although specific events can vary, the overall frequency of adverse reactions was similar in men and women and in patients &lt;65 and &gt;=65 years. However, the following grade 3/4 events were more common in females: diarrhea, fatigue, granulocytopenia, nausea and vomiting. In patients &gt;=65 years old, the incidence of grade 3/4 diarrhea and granulocytopenia was higher than in younger patients. Insufficient subgroup sizes prevented analysis of safety by race. The following additional adverse reactions, were reported in &gt;=2% and &lt;5% of the patients in the ELOXATIN and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm (listed in decreasing order of frequency): pain, leukopenia, weight decrease, coughing.
 

 The number of patients who developed secondary malignancies was similar; 62 in the ELOXATIN combination arm and 68 in the infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm. An exploratory analysis showed that the number of deaths due to secondary malignancies was 1.96% in the ELOXATIN combination arm and 0.98% in infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm. In addition, the number of cardiovascular deaths was 1.4% in the ELOXATIN combination arm as compared to 0.7% in the infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm. Clinical significance of these findings is unknown.



   

    Patients Previously Untreated for Advanced Colorectal Cancer  



 Two hundred and fifty-nine patients were treated in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm of the randomized trial in patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . The adverse reaction profile in this study was similar to that seen in other studies and the adverse reactions in this trial are shown in the tables below.Both 5-fluorouracil and ELOXATIN are associated with gastrointestinal and hematologic adverse reactions. When ELOXATIN is administered in combination with 5-fluorouracil, the incidence of these events is increased.



 The incidence of death within 30 days of treatment in the previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer study, regardless of causality, was 3% with the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination, 5% with irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, and 3% with ELOXATIN plus irinotecan. Deaths within 60 days from initiation of therapy were 2.3% with the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination, 5.1% with irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, and 3.1% with ELOXATIN plus irinotecan.The following table provides adverse reactions reported in the previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer study  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  by body system and decreasing order of frequency in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm for events with overall incidences &gt;=5% and for grade 3/4 events with incidences &gt;=1%.



 Table 5 - Adverse Reactions Reported in Patients Previously Untreated for Advanced Colorectal Cancer Clinical Trial (&gt;=5% of all patients and with &gt;=1% NCI Grade 3/4 events) 
                         ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LVN=259  irinotecan + 5-FU/LVN=256  ELOXATIN + irinotecanN=258   
 Adverse reaction(WHO/Pref)  All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)    
  
 Any Event                    99             82             98             70             99             76         
   Allergy/Immunology     
 Hypersensitivity             12              2              5              0              6              1         
   Cardiovascular         
 Thrombosis                    6              5              6              6              3              3         
 Hypotension                   5              3              6              3              4              3         
   Constitutional Symptoms/Pain/Ocular/Visual     
 Fatigue                      70              7             58             11             66             16         
 Abdominal Pain               29              8             31              7             39             10         
 Myalgia                      14              2              6              0              9              2         
 Pain                          7              1              5              1              6              1         
 Vision abnormal               5              0              2              1              6              1         
 Neuralgia                     5              0              0              0              2              1         
   Dermatology/Skin       
 Skin reaction - hand/foot        7              1              2              1              1              0         
 Injection site reaction        6              0              1              0              4              1         
   Gastrointestinal       
 Nausea                       71              6             67             15             83             19         
 Diarrhea                     56             12             65             29             76             25         
 Vomiting                     41              4             43             13             64             23         
 Stomatitis                   38              0             25              1             19              1         
 Anorexia                     35              2             25              4             27              5         
 Constipation                 32              4             27              2             21              2         
 Diarrhea-colostomy           13              2             16              7             16              3         
 Gastrointestinal NOS          5              2              4              2              3              2         
   Hematology/Infection     
 Infection normal ANC         10              4              5              1              7              2         
 Infection low ANC             8              8             12             11              9              8         
 Lymphopenia                   6              2              4              1              5              2         
 Febrile neutropenia           4              4             15             14             12             11         
   Hepatic/Metabolic/Laboratory/Renal     
 Hyperglycemia                14              2             11              3             12              3         
 Hypokalemia                  11              3              7              4              6              2         
 Dehydration                   9              5             16             11             14              7         
 Hypoalbuminemia               8              0              5              2              9              1         
 Hyponatremia                  8              2              7              4              4              1         
 Urinary frequency             5              1              2              1              3              1         
   Neurology              
 Overall Neuropathy           82             19             18              2             69              7         
 Paresthesias                 77             18             16              2             62              6         
 Pharyngo-laryngeal dysesthesias       38              2              1              0             28              1         
 Neuro-sensory                12              1              2              0              9              1         
 Neuro NOS                     1              0              1              0              1              0         
   Pulmonary              
 Cough                        35              1             25              2             17              1         
 Dyspnea                      18              7             14              3             11              2         
 Hiccups                       5              1              2              0              3              2         
             The following table provides adverse reactions reported in the previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer study  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  by body system and decreasing order of frequency in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm for events with overall incidences &gt;=5% but with incidences &lt;1% NCI Grade 3/4 events.
 

 Table 6 - Adverse Reactions Reported in Patients Previously Untreated for Advanced Colorectal Cancer Clinical Trial (&gt;=5% of all patients but with &lt; 1% NCI Grade 3/4 events) 
                             ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LVN=259   irinotecan + 5-FU/LVN=256  ELOXATIN + irinotecanN=258   
 Adverse reaction(WHO/Pref)        All Grades(%)              All Grades(%)              All Grades(%)         
  
   Allergy/Immunology        
 Rash                                  11                          4                          7               
 Rhinitis allergic                     10                          6                          6               
   Cardiovascular            
 Edema                                 15                         13                         10               
   Constitutional    Symptoms/Pain/Ocular/Visual     
 Headache                              13                          6                          9               
 Weight loss                           11                          9                         11               
 Epistaxis                             10                          2                          2               
 Tearing                                9                          1                          2               
 Rigors                                 8                          2                          7               
 Dysphasia                              5                          3                          3               
 Sweating                               5                          6                         12               
 Arthralgia                             5                          5                          8               
   Dermatology/Skin          
 Alopecia                              38                         44                         67               
 Flushing                               7                          2                          5               
 Pruritis                               6                          4                          2               
 Dry Skin                               6                          2                          5               
   Gastrointestinal          
 Taste perversion                      14                          6                          8               
 Dyspepsia                             12                          7                          5               
 Flatulence                             9                          6                          5               
 Mouth Dryness                          5                          2                          3               
   Hematology/Infection      
 Fever normal ANC                      16                          9                          9               
   Hepatic/Metabolic/Laboratory/Renal     
 Hypocalcemia                           7                          5                          4               
 Elevated Creatinine                    4                          4                          5               
   Neurology                 
 Insomnia                              13                          9                         11               
 Depression                             9                          5                          7               
 Dizziness                              8                          6                         10               
 Anxiety                                5                          2                          6               
          Adverse reactions were similar in men and women and in patients &lt;65 and  &gt;=  65 years, but older patients may have been more susceptible to diarrhea, dehydration, hypokalemia, leukopenia, fatigue and syncope. The following additional adverse reactions, at least possibly related to treatment and potentially important, were reported in  &gt;=  2% and &lt;5% of the patients in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm (listed in decreasing order of frequency): metabolic, pneumonitis, catheter infection, vertigo, prothrombin time, pulmonary, rectal bleeding, dysuria, nail changes, chest pain, rectal pain, syncope, hypertension, hypoxia, unknown infection, bone pain, pigmentation changes, and urticaria.
 

   

    Previously Treated Patients with Advanced Colorectal Cancer  



 Four hundred and fifty patients (about 150 receiving the combination of ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin) were studied in a randomized trial in patients with refractory and relapsed colorectal cancer  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . The adverse reaction profile in this study was similar to that seen in other studies and the adverse reactions in this trial are shown in the tables below.Thirteen percent of patients in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm and 18% in the 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm of the previously treated study had to discontinue treatment because of adverse effects related to gastrointestinal, or hematologic adverse reactions, or neuropathies. Both 5-fluorouracil and ELOXATIN are associated with gastrointestinal and hematologic adverse reactions. When ELOXATIN is administered in combination with 5-fluorouracil, the incidence of these events is increased.



 The incidence of death within 30 days of treatment in the previously treated study, regardless of causality, was 5% with the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination, 8% with ELOXATIN alone, and 7% with 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin. Of the 7 deaths that occurred on the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm within 30 days of stopping treatment, 3 may have been treatment related, associated with gastrointestinal bleeding or dehydration.



 The following table provides adverse reactions reported in the previously treated study  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  by body system and in decreasing order of frequency in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm for events with overall incidences  &gt;=  5% and for grade 3/4 events with incidences &gt;=1%. This table does not include hematologic and blood chemistry abnormalities; these are shown separately below.



 Table 7 - Adverse Reactions Reported In Previously Treated Colorectal Cancer Clinical Trial (&gt;=5% of all patients and with &gt;=1% NCI Grade 3/4 events) 
                         5-FU/LV(N = 142)  ELOXATIN(N = 153)  ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LV(N = 150)   
 Adverse reaction(WHO/Pref)  All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)    
  
 Any Event                    98             41             100            46             99             73         
   Cardiovascular         
 Dyspnea                      11              2             13              7             20              4         
 Coughing                      9              0             11              0             19              1         
 Edema                        13              1             10              1             15              1         
 Thromboembolism               4              2              2              1              9              8         
 Chest Pain                    4              1              5              1              8              1         
   Constitutional Symptoms/Pain     
 Fatigue                      52              6             61              9             68              7         
 Back Pain                    16              4             11              0             19              3         
 Pain                          9              3             14              3             15              2         
   Dermatology/Skin       
 Injection Site Reaction        5              1              9              0             10              3         
   Gastrointestinal       
 Diarrhea                     44              3             46              4             67             11         
 Nausea                       59              4             64              4             65             11         
 Vomiting                     27              4             37              4             40              9         
 Stomatitis                   32              3             14              0             37              3         
 Abdominal Pain               31              5             31              7             33              4         
 Anorexia                     20              1             20              2             29              3         
 Gastroesophageal Reflux        3              0              1              0              5              2         
   Hematology/Infection     
 Fever                        23              1             25              1             29              1         
 Febrile Neutropenia           1              1              0              0              6              6         
   Hepatic/Metabolic/Laboratory/Renal     
 Hypokalemia                   3              1              3              2              9              4         
 Dehydration                   6              4              5              3              8              3         
   Neurology              
 Neuropathy                   17              0             76              7             74              7         
   Acute                      10              0             65              5             56              2         
   Persistent                  9              0             43              3             48              6         
             The following table provides adverse reactions reported in the previously treated study  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  by body system and in decreasing order of frequency in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm for events with overall incidences &gt;=5% but with incidences &lt;1% NCI Grade 3/4 events.
 

 Table 8 - Adverse Reactions Reported In Previously Treated Colorectal Cancer Clinical Trial (&gt;=5% of all patients but with &lt; 1% NCI Grade 3/4 events) 
                                5-FU/LV(N = 142)           ELOXATIN(N = 153)      ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LV(N = 150)   
 Adverse reaction(WHO/Pref)        All Grades(%)              All Grades(%)              All Grades(%)         
  
   Allergy/Immunology        
 Rhinitis                               4                          6                         15               
 Allergic Reaction                      1                          3                         10               
 Rash                                   5                          5                          9               
   Cardiovascular            
 Peripheral Edema                      11                          5                         10               
   Constitutional Symptoms/Pain/Ocular/Visual     
 Headache                               8                         13                         17               
 Arthralgia                            10                          7                         10               
 Epistaxis                              1                          2                          9               
 Abnormal Lacrimation                   6                          1                          7               
 Rigors                                 6                          9                          7               
   Dermatology/Skin          
 Hand-Foot Syndrome                    13                          1                         11               
 Flushing                               2                          3                         10               
 Alopecia                               3                          3                          7               
   Gastrointestinal          
 Constipation                          23                         31                         32               
 Dyspepsia                             10                          7                         14               
 Taste Perversion                       1                          5                         13               
 Mucositis                             10                          2                          7               
 Flatulence                             6                          3                          5               
   Hepatic/Metabolic/Laboratory/Renal     
 Hematuria                              4                          0                          6               
 Dysuria                                1                          1                          6               
   Neurology                 
 Dizziness                              8                          7                         13               
 Insomnia                               4                         11                          9               
   Pulmonary                 
 Upper Resp Tract Infection              4                          7                         10               
 Pharyngitis                           10                          2                          9               
 Hiccup                                 0                          2                          5               
          Adverse reactions were similar in men and women and in patients &lt;65 and &gt;=65 years, but older patients may have been more susceptible to dehydration, diarrhea, hypokalemia and fatigue. The following additional adverse reactions, at least possibly related to treatment and potentially important, were reported in &gt;=2% and &lt;5% of the patients in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm (listed in decreasing order of frequency): anxiety, myalgia, erythematous rash, increased sweating, conjunctivitis, weight decrease, dry mouth, rectal hemorrhage, depression, ataxia, ascites, hemorrhoids, muscle weakness, nervousness, tachycardia, abnormal micturition frequency, dry skin, pruritus, hemoptysis, purpura, vaginal hemorrhage, melena, somnolence, pneumonia, proctitis, involuntary muscle contractions, intestinal obstruction, gingivitis, tenesmus, hot flashes, enlarged abdomen, urinary incontinence.
 

   

    Hematologic Changes  



 The following tables list the hematologic changes occurring in &gt;=5% of patients, based on laboratory values and NCI grade, with the exception of those events occurring in adjuvant patients and anemia in the patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer, respectively, which are based on AE reporting and NCI grade alone.



 Table 9 - Adverse Hematologic Reactions in Patients with Colon Cancer Receiving Adjuvant Therapy (&gt;=5% of patients) 
                               ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LV(N=1108)   5-FU/LV(N=1111)     
 Hematology Parameter            All Grades(%)        Grade 3/4(%)       All Grades(%)        Grade 3/4(%)      
  
 Anemia                                76                  1                   67                  &lt;1           
 Neutropenia                           79                  41                  40                  5            
 Thrombocytopenia                      77                  2                   19                  &lt;1           
          Table 10 - Adverse Hematologic Reactions in Patients Previously Untreated for Advanced Colorectal Cancer (&gt;=5% of patients) 
                         ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LVN=259  Irinotecan+ 5-FU/LVN=256  ELOXATIN + irinotecanN=258   
 Hematology Parameter    All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)    
  
 Anemia                       27              3             28              4             25              3         
 Leukopenia                   85             20             84             23             76             24         
 Neutropenia                  81             53             77             44             71             36         
 Thrombocytopenia             71              5             26              2             44              4         
            Table 11 - Adverse Hematologic Reactions in Previously Treated Patients (&gt;=5% of patients) 
                         5-FU/LV(N=142)  ELOXATIN(N=153)  ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LV(N=150)   
 Hematology Parameter    All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)    
  
 Anemia                       68              2             64              1             81              2         
 Leukopenia                   34              1             13              0             76             19         
 Neutropenia                  25              5              7              0             73             44         
 Thrombocytopenia             20              0             30              3             64              4         
               
     Thrombocytopenia and Bleeding  



 Thrombocytopenia was frequently reported with the combination of ELOXATIN and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin. The incidence of all hemorrhagic events in the adjuvant and previously treated patients was higher on the ELOXATIN combination arm compared to the infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm. These events included gastrointestinal bleeding, hematuria, and epistaxis. In the adjuvant trial, two patients died from intracerebral hemorrhages.



 The incidence of Grade 3/4 thrombocytopenia was 2% in adjuvant patients with colon cancer. In patients treated for advanced colorectal cancer the incidence of Grade 3/4 thrombocytopenia was 3-5%, and the incidence of these events was greater for the combination of ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin over the irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin or 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin control groups. Grade 3/4 gastrointestinal bleeding was reported in 0.2% of adjuvant patients receiving ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin. In the previously untreated patients, the incidence of epistaxis was 10% in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm, and 2% and 1%, respectively, in the irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin or irinotecan plus ELOXATIN arms.



   

    Neutropenia  



 Neutropenia was frequently observed with the combination of ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, with Grade 3 and 4 events reported in 29% and 12% of adjuvant patients with colon cancer, respectively. In the adjuvant trial, 3 patients died from sepsis/neutropenic sepsis. Grade 3 and 4 events were reported in 35% and 18% of the patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer, respectively. Grade 3 and 4 events were reported in 27% and 17% of previously treated patients, respectively. In adjuvant patients the incidence of either febrile neutropenia (0.7%) or documented infection with concomitant grade 3/4 neutropenia (1.1%) was 1.8% in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm. The incidence of febrile neutropenia in the patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer was 15% (3% of cycles) in the irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm and 4% (less than 1% of cycles) in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm. Additionally, in this same population, infection with grade 3 or 4 neutropenia was 12% in the irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, and 8% in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination. The incidence of febrile neutropenia in the previously treated patients was 1% in the 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm and 6% (less than 1% of cycles) in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm.



   

    Gastrointestinal  



 In patients receiving the combination of ELOXATIN plus infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin for adjuvant treatment for colon cancer the incidence of Grade 3/4 nausea and vomiting was greater than those receiving infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin alone (see table). In patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer receiving the combination of ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, the incidence of Grade 3 and 4 vomiting and diarrhea was less compared to irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin controls (see table). In previously treated patients receiving the combination of ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, the incidence of Grade 3 and 4 nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and mucositis/stomatitis increased compared to 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin controls (see table).



 The incidence of gastrointestinal adverse reactions in the previously untreated and previously treated patients appears to be similar across cycles. Premedication with antiemetics, including 5-HT3blockers, is recommended. Diarrhea and mucositis may be exacerbated by the addition of ELOXATIN to 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin, and should be managed with appropriate supportive care. Since cold temperature can exacerbate acute neurological symptoms, ice (mucositis prophylaxis) should be avoided during the infusion of ELOXATIN.



   

    Dermatologic  



 ELOXATIN did not increase the incidence of alopecia compared to 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin alone. No complete alopecia was reported. The incidence of Grade 3/4 skin disorders was 2% in both the ELOXATIN plus infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin and the infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin alone arms in the adjuvant colon cancer patients. The incidence of hand-foot syndrome in patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer was 2% in the irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm and 7% in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm. The incidence of hand-foot syndrome in previously treated patients was 13% in the 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm and 11% in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm.



   

    Intravenous Site Reactions  



 Extravasation, in some cases including necrosis, has been reported.Injection site reaction, including redness, swelling, and pain, has been reported.



   

    Anticoagulation and Hemorrhage  



 There have been reports while on study and from post-marketing surveillance of prolonged prothrombin time and INR occasionally associated with hemorrhage in patients who received ELOXATIN plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin while on anticoagulants. Patients receiving ELOXATIN plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin and requiring oral anticoagulants may require closer monitoring.



   

    Renal  



 About 5-10% of patients in all groups had some degree of elevation of serum creatinine. The incidence of Grade 3/4 elevations in serum creatinine in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm was 1% in the previously treated patients. Serum creatinine measurements were not reported in the adjuvant trial.



   

    Hepatic  



 Hepatotoxicity (defined as elevation of liver enzymes) appears to be related to ELOXATIN combination therapy  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  . The following tables list the clinical chemistry changes associated with hepatic toxicity occurring in &gt;=5% of patients, based on adverse reactions reported and NCI CTC grade for adjuvant patients and patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer, laboratory values and NCI CTC grade for previously treated patients.



 Table 12 - Adverse Hepatic Reactions in Patients with Stage II or III Colon Cancer Receiving Adjuvant Therapy (&gt;=5% of patients) 
                               ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LV(N=1108)   5-FU/LV(N=1111)     
 Hepatic Parameter               All Grades(%)        Grade 3/4(%)       All Grades(%)        Grade 3/4(%)      
  
 Increase in transaminases             57                  2                   34                  1            
 ALP increased                         42                  &lt;1                  20                  &lt;1           
 Bilirubinaemia                        20                  4                   20                  5            
          Table 13 - Adverse Hepatic - Clinical Chemistry Abnormalities in Patients Previously Untreated for Advanced Colorectal Cancer (&gt;=5% of patients) 
                         ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LVN=259  irinotecan + 5-FU/LVN=256  ELOXATIN + irinotecanN=258   
 Clinical Chemistry      All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)    
  
 ALT(SGPT-ALAT)                6              1              2              0              5              2         
 AST(SGOT-ASAT)               17              1              2              1             11              1         
 Alkaline Phosphatase         16              0              8              0             14              2         
 Total Bilirubin               6              1              3              1              3              2         
            Table 14 - Adverse Hepatic - Clinical Chemistry Abnormalities in Previously Treated Patients (&gt;=5% of patients) 
                         5-FU/LV(N=142)  ELOXATIN(N=153)  ELOXATIN + 5-FU/LV(N=150)   
 Clinical Chemistry      All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)   All Grades(%)  Grade 3/4(%)    
  
 ALT(SGPT-ALAT)               28              3             36              1             31              0         
 AST(SGOT-ASAT)               39              2             54              4             47              0         
 Total Bilirubin              22              6             13              5             13              1         
               
     Thromboembolism  



 The incidence of thromboembolic events in adjuvant patients with colon cancer was 6% (1.8% grade 3/4) in the infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm and 6% (1.2% grade 3/4) in the ELOXATIN and infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combined arm, respectively. The incidence was 6 and 9% of the patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer and previously treated patients in the ELOXATIN and 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm, respectively.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ELOXATIN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a whole:  angioedema, anaphylactic shock



   Central and peripheral nervous system disorders:  loss of deep tendon reflexes, dysarthria, Lhermitte's sign, cranial nerve palsies, fasciculations, convulsion, Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS, also known as PRES).



   Hearing and vestibular system disorders:  deafness



   Infusion reactions/hypersensitivity:  laryngospasm



   Liver and Gastrointestinal system disorders:  severe diarrhea/vomiting resulting in hypokalemia, colitis (including  Clostridium difficile  diarrhea), metabolic acidosis; ileus; intestinal obstruction, pancreatitis; veno-occlusive disease of liver also known as sinusoidal obstruction syndrome, and perisinusoidal fibrosis which rarely may progress.



   Platelet, bleeding, and clotting disorders:  immuno-allergic thrombocytopeniaprolongation of prothrombin time and of INR in patients receiving anticoagulants



   Red Blood Cell disorders:  hemolytic uremic syndrome, immuno-allergic hemolytic anemia



   Renal disorders:  Acute tubular necrosis, acute interstitial nephritis and acute renal failure.



   Respiratory system disorders:  pulmonary fibrosis, and other interstitial lung diseases (sometimes fatal)



   Vision disorders:  decrease of visual acuity, visual field disturbance, optic neuritis and transient vision loss (reversible following therapy discontinuation)
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ANAPHYLACTIC REACTIONS

  WARNING: ANAPHYLACTIC REACTIONS

    Anaphylactic reactions to ELOXATIN have been reported, and may occur within minutes of ELOXATIN administration.  Epinephrine, corticosteroids, and antihistamines have been employed to alleviate symptoms of anaphylaxis   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ANAPHYLACTIC REACTIONS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Anaphylactic reactions to ELOXATIN have been reported, and may occur within minutes of ELOXATIN administration. Epinephrine, corticosteroids, and antihistamines have been employed to alleviate symptoms. (  5.1  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Allergic Reactions: Monitor for development of rash, urticaria, erythema, pruritis, bronchospasm, and hypotension. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Neuropathy: Reduce the dose or discontinue ELOXATIN if necessary. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Pulmonary Toxicity: May need to discontinue ELOXATIN until interstitial lung disease or pulmonary fibrosis are excluded. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Monitor liver function tests. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Pregnancy. Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be apprised of the potential harm to the fetus. (  5.5  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Allergic Reactions



  See  boxed warning  



 Grade 3/4 hypersensitivity, including anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions, to ELOXATIN has been observed in 2-3% of colon cancer patients. These allergic reactions which can be fatal, can occur within minutes of administration and at any cycle, and were similar in nature and severity to those reported with other platinum-containing compounds, such as rash, urticaria, erythema, pruritus, and, rarely, bronchospasm and hypotension. The symptoms associated with hypersensitivity reactions reported in the previously untreated patients were urticaria, pruritus, flushing of the face, diarrhea associated with oxaliplatin infusion, shortness of breath, bronchospasm, diaphoresis, chest pains, hypotension, disorientation and syncope. These reactions are usually managed with standard epinephrine, corticosteroid, antihistamine therapy, and require discontinuation of therapy. Rechallenge is contraindicated in these patients [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . Drug-related deaths associated with platinum compounds from anaphylaxis have been reported.



    5.2 Neurologic Toxicity



   Neuropathy  



 ELOXATIN is associated with two types of neuropathy:



  An acute, reversible, primarily peripheral, sensory neuropathy that is of early onset, occurring within hours or one to two days of dosing, that resolves within 14 days, and that frequently recurs with further dosing.  The symptoms may be precipitated or exacerbated by exposure to cold temperature or cold objects and they usually present as transient paresthesia, dysesthesia and hypoesthesia in the hands, feet, perioral area, or throat. Jaw spasm, abnormal tongue sensation, dysarthria, eye pain, and a feeling of chest pressure have also been observed. The acute, reversible pattern of sensory neuropathy was observed in about 56% of study patients who received ELOXATIN with 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin. In any individual cycle acute neurotoxicity was observed in approximately 30% of patients. In adjuvant patients the median cycle of onset for grade 3 peripheral sensory neuropathy was 9 in the previously treated patients the median number of cycles administered on the ELOXATIN with 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin combination arm was 6.



 An acute syndrome of pharyngolaryngeal dysesthesia seen in 1-2% (grade 3/4) of patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer, and the previously treated patients, is characterized by subjective sensations of dysphagia or dyspnea, without any laryngospasm or bronchospasm (no stridor or wheezing). Ice (mucositis prophylaxis) should be avoided during the infusion of ELOXATIN because cold temperature can exacerbate acute neurological symptoms.



  A persistent (&gt;14 days), primarily peripheral, sensory neuropathy that is usually characterized by paresthesias, dysesthesias, hypoesthesias, but may also include deficits in proprioception that can interfere with daily activities (e.g., writing, buttoning, swallowing, and difficulty walking from impaired proprioception).  These forms of neuropathy occurred in 48% of the study patients receiving ELOXATIN with 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin. Persistent neuropathy can occur without any prior acute neuropathy event. The majority of the patients (80%) who developed grade 3 persistent neuropathy progressed from prior Grade 1 or 2 events. These symptoms may improve in some patients upon discontinuation of ELOXATIN.



 In the adjuvant colon cancer trial, neuropathy was graded using a prelisted module derived from the Neuro-Sensory section of the National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (NCI CTC) scale, Version 1, as follows:



 Table 1 - NCI CTC Grading for Neuropathy in Adjuvant Patients 
 Grade                           Definition                                                               
  
 Grade 0                         No change or none                                                        
 Grade 1                         Mild paresthesias, loss of deep tendon reflexes                          
 Grade 2                         Mild or moderate objective sensory loss, moderate paresthesias           
 Grade 3                         Severe objective sensory loss or paresthesias that interfere with function   
 Grade 4                         Not applicable                                                           
        Peripheral sensory neuropathy was reported in adjuvant patients treated with the ELOXATIN combination with a frequency of 92% (all grades) and 13% (grade 3). At the 28-day follow-up after the last treatment cycle, 60% of all patients had any grade (Grade 1=40%, Grade 2=16%, Grade 3=5%) peripheral sensory neuropathy decreasing to 39% at 6 months follow-up (Grade 1=31%, Grade 2=7%, Grade 3=1%) and 21% at 18 months of follow-up (Grade 1=17%, Grade 2=3%, Grade 3=1%).
 

 In the advanced colorectal cancer studies, neuropathy was graded using a study-specific neurotoxicity scale, which was different from the NCI CTC scale, Version 2.0 (see below).



 Table 2 - Grading Scale for Paresthesias/Dysesthesias in Advanced Colorectal Cancer Patients 
 Grade                      Definition                                                                    
  
 Grade 1                    Resolved and did not interfere with functioning                               
 Grade 2                    Interfered with function but not daily activities                             
 Grade 3                    Pain or functional impairment that interfered with daily activities           
 Grade 4                    Persistent impairment that is disabling or life-threatening                   
        Overall, neuropathy was reported in patients previously untreated for advanced colorectal cancer in 82% (all grades) and 19% (grade 3/4), and in the previously treated patients in 74% (all grades) and 7% (grade 3/4) events. Information regarding reversibility of neuropathy was not available from the trial for patients who had not been previously treated for colorectal cancer.
 

    Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome  



 Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS, also known as PRES, Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome) has been observed in clinical trials (&lt; 0.1%) and postmarketing experience. Signs and symptoms of RPLS could be headache, altered mental functioning, seizures, abnormal vision from blurriness to blindness, associated or not with hypertension [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . Diagnosis of RPLS is based upon confirmation by brain imaging.



    5.3 Pulmonary Toxicity



  ELOXATIN has been associated with pulmonary fibrosis (&lt;1% of study patients), which may be fatal. The combined incidence of cough and dyspnea was 7.4% (any grade) and &lt;1% (grade 3) with no grade 4 events in the ELOXATIN plus infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm compared to 4.5% (any grade) and no grade 3 and 0.1% grade 4 events in the infusional 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin alone arm in adjuvant colon cancer patients. In this study, one patient died from eosinophilic pneumonia in the ELOXATIN combination arm. The combined incidence of cough, dyspnea and hypoxia was 43% (any grade) and 7% (grade 3 and 4) in the ELOXATIN plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm compared to 32% (any grade) and 5% (grade 3 and 4) in the irinotecan plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin arm of unknown duration for patients with previously untreated colorectal cancer. In case of unexplained respiratory symptoms such as non-productive cough, dyspnea, crackles, or radiological pulmonary infiltrates, ELOXATIN should be discontinued until further pulmonary investigation excludes interstitial lung disease or pulmonary fibrosis.



    5.4 Hepatotoxicity



  Hepatotoxicity as evidenced in the adjuvant study, by increase in transaminases (57% vs. 34%) and alkaline phosphatase (42% vs. 20%) was observed more commonly in the ELOXATIN combination arm than in the control arm. The incidence of increased bilirubin was similar on both arms. Changes noted on liver biopsies include: peliosis, nodular regenerative hyperplasia or sinusoidal alterations, perisinusoidal fibrosis, and veno-occlusive lesions. Hepatic vascular disorders should be considered, and if appropriate, should be investigated in case of abnormal liver function test results or portal hypertension, which cannot be explained by liver metastases [see  Clinical Trials Experience (6.1)  ]  .



    5.5 Use in Pregnancy



  Pregnancy Category D



 ELOXATIN may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of ELOXATIN in pregnant women. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving treatment with ELOXATIN. [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].  



    5.6 Recommended Laboratory Tests



  Standard monitoring of the white blood cell count with differential, hemoglobin, platelet count, and blood chemistries (including ALT, AST, bilirubin and creatinine) is recommended before each ELOXATIN cycle [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ].  



 There have been reports while on study and from post-marketing surveillance of prolonged prothrombin time and INR occasionally associated with hemorrhage in patients who received ELOXATIN plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin while on anticoagulants. Patients receiving ELOXATIN plus 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin and requiring oral anticoagulants may require closer monitoring.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
