<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="embeda" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Life Threatening Respiratory Depression [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Interactions with Other CNS Depressants [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Hypotensive Effect [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *  Gastrointestinal Effects [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *  Seizures [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)   ] 
    In the randomized study, the most common adverse reactions with EMBEDA therapy were constipation, nausea, and somnolence. The most common adverse reactions leading to study discontinuation were nausea, constipation (sometimes severe), vomiting, fatigue, dizziness, pruritus, and somnolence.
 

   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;10%): constipation, nausea, and somnolence. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Short-Term Randomized Study  



 This study utilized an enriched enrollment with a randomized withdrawal design in which subjects were titrated to effect on open-label EMBEDA for up to 45 days. Once their pain was controlled, 344 of 547 subjects were randomized to either an active treatment with EMBEDA or were tapered off EMBEDA using a double-dummy design and placed on placebo. The maintenance Period was 12 weeks. Adverse reactions, reported in &gt;=2% of subjects in either the titration or maintenance phase of the 12-week study are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=2% of Subjects in the Randomized Study 
                                         Titration               Maintenance         
 Adverse Reaction                   EMBEDA(N=547)n (%)       EMBEDA(N=171)n (%)       Placebo(N=173)n (%)     
  
 Constipation                            165 (30%)                 12 (7%)                  7 (4%)            
 Nausea                                  106 (19%)                19 (11%)                  11 (6%)           
 Somnolence                              76 (14%)                  2 (1%)                   5 (3%)            
 Vomiting                                 46 (8%)                  7 (4%)                   2 (1%)            
 Dizziness                                42 (8%)                  2 (1%)                   2 (1%)            
 Pruritus                                 34 (6%)                     0                     1 (1%)            
 Dry mouth                                31 (6%)                  3 (2%)                   2 (1%)            
 Headache                                 22 (4%)                  4 (2%)                   2 (1%)            
 Fatigue                                  16 (3%)                  1 (1%)                   2 (1%)            
 Insomnia                                 7 (1%)                   5 (3%)                   4 (2%)            
 Diarrhea                                 6 (1%)                   12 (7%)                  12 (7%)           
 Abdominal pain upper                     6 (1%)                   4 (2%)                   3 (2%)            
 Flushing                                    0                     4 (2%)                   1 (1%)            
              Long-Term Open-Label Safety Study  
 

 In the long-term open-label safety study, 465 patients with chronic non-malignant pain were enrolled and 124 patients were treated for up to 1 year. The distributions of adverse events were similar to that of the randomized, controlled studies, and were consistent with the most common opioid-related adverse reactions. Adverse reactions reported in &gt;= 2.0% of subjects are presented in Table 2.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;= 2.0% of Subjects in Long-Term Safety Study 
 Adverse Reaction                                                              EMBEDA(N=465)n (%)         
  
 Constipation                                                                      145 (31%)              
 Nausea                                                                            103 (22%)              
 Vomiting                                                                           37 (8%)               
 Somnolence                                                                         34 (7%)               
 Headache                                                                           32 (7%)               
 Pruritus                                                                           26 (6%)               
 Fatigue                                                                            19 (4%)               
 Dizziness                                                                          19 (4%)               
 Dry mouth                                                                          17 (4%)               
 Hyperhidrosis                                                                      16 (3%)               
 Insomnia                                                                           13 (3%)               
 Diarrhea                                                                           10 (2%)               
 Anxiety                                                                            10 (2%)               
            Adverse Reactions Observed in the Phase 2/3 Studies  
 

 Most common (&gt;=10%): constipation, nausea, somnolence



 Common (&gt;=1% to &lt;10%): vomiting, headache, dizziness, pruritus, dry mouth, diarrhea, fatigue, insomnia, hyperhidrosis, anxiety, chills, abdominal pain, lethargy, edema peripheral, dyspepsia, anorexia, muscle spasms, depression, flatulence, restlessness, decreased appetite, irritability, stomach discomfort, tremor, arthralgia, hot flush, sedation



 Less Common (&lt;1%):



   Eye disorders  : vision blurred, orthostatic hypotension



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : abdominal distension, pancreatitis, abdominal discomfort, fecaloma, abdominal pain lower, abdominal tenderness



   General disorders and administration site conditions  : malaise, asthenia, feeling jittery, drug withdrawal syndrome



   Hepatobiliary disorders  : cholecystitis



   Investigations  : alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  : myalgia, muscular weakness



   Nervous system disorders  : depressed level of consciousness, mental impairment, memory impairment, disturbance in attention, stupor, paresthesia, coordination abnormal



   Psychiatric disorders  : disorientation, thinking abnormal, mental status changes, confusional state, euphoric mood, hallucination, abnormal dreams, mood swings, nervousness



   Renal and urinary disorders  : urinary retention, dysuria



   Reproductive system and breast disorders  : erectile dysfunction



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  : dyspnea, rhinorrhea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : rash, piloerection, cold sweat, night sweats



   Vascular disorders  : hypotension, flushing



 Anaphylaxis has been reported with ingredients contained in EMBEDA. Advise patients how to recognize such a reaction and when to seek medical attention.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and INTERACTION WITH ALCOHOL

    WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and INTERACTION WITH ALCOHOL  

    EXCERPT:   WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and INTERACTION WITH ALCOHOL



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .



 *  EMBEDA exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors or conditions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients to swallow EMBEDA capsules whole to avoid exposure to a potentially fatal dose of morphine. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental ingestion of EMBEDA, especially in children, can result in fatal overdose of morphine. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of EMBEDA during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available (5.3). 
 *  Instruct patients not to consume alcohol or any products containing alcohol while taking EMBEDA because co-ingestion can result in fatal plasma morphine levels. (5.4) 
    
 

  

    Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse  



     EMBEDA  (r)   exposes patients and other users to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing EMBEDA, and monitor all patients regularly for the development of these behaviors or conditions [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1  )  ]  .      



     Life-threatening Respiratory Depression  



   Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of EMBEDA. Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of EMBEDA or following a dose increase  .    Instruct patients to swallow EMBEDA capsules whole, or to sprinkle the contents of the capsule on applesauce and swallow immediately without chewing. Crushing, chewing, or dissolving EMBEDA can cause rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of morphine [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].  



     Accidental Ingestion  



   Accidental ingestion of even one dose of EMBEDA, especially by children, can result in a fatal overdose of morphine [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].  



   

    Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome  



   Prolonged use of EMBEDA during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ].  



   

    Interaction with Alcohol  



   Instruct patients not to consume alcoholic beverages or use prescription or non-prescription products that contain alcohol while taking EMBEDA. The co-ingestion of alcohol with EMBEDA may result in increased plasma level and a potentially fatal overdose of morphine [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ].  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Interactions with CNS depressants: Concomitant use may cause profound sedation, respiratory depression, and death. If coadministration is required, consider dose reduction of one or both drugs because of additive pharmacological effects. (  5.4  ,  7.2  ) 
 *  Elderly, cachectic, debilitated patients, and those with chronic pulmonary disease: Monitor closely because of increased risk for life-threatening respiratory depression. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypotensive effect: Monitor during dose initiation and titration. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Patients with head injury or increased intracranial pressure: Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression. Avoid use of EMBEDA in patients with impaired consciousness or coma susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



   EMBEDA contains morphine, a Schedule II controlled substance. As an opioid, EMBEDA exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse [ see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)    ] .  As modified-release products such as EMBEDA deliver the opioid over an extended period of time, there is a greater risk for overdose and death due to the larger amount of morphine present.  



  Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed EMBEDA and in those who obtain the drug illicitly. Addiction can occur at recommended doses and if the drug is misused or abused.  



  Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing EMBEDA, and monitor all patients receiving EMBEDA for the development of these behaviors or conditions. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol addiction or abuse) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the prescribing of EMBEDA for the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed modified-release opioid formulations such as EMBEDA, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks and proper use of EMBEDA along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, and misuse.  



  Abuse or misuse of EMBEDA by crushing, chewing, snorting, or injecting the dissolved product will result in the uncontrolled delivery of the morphine and can result in overdose and death [ see  Overdosage (10)    ]. Misuse or abuse of EMBEDA by these methods may also release sufficient naltrexone to precipitate withdrawal in opioid-dependent individuals [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)    ].  



  Opioid agonists such as EMBEDA are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing EMBEDA. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper disposal of unused drug [ see  Patient Counseling Information (17)    ]. Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.  



    5.2 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



   Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of modified-release opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression from opioid use, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [ see  Overdosage (10)    ]. Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.  



 While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of EMBEDA, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dose increase. Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression when initiating therapy with EMBEDA and following dose increases.



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of EMBEDA are essential [ see  Dosage and Administration (2)    ]. Overestimating the EMBEDA dose when converting patients from another opioid product can result in fatal overdose with the first dose.



  Accidental ingestion of even one dose of EMBEDA, especially by children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of morphine.  



    5.3 Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



   Prolonged use of EMBEDA during pregnancy can result in withdrawal signs in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available.  



  Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome presents as irritability, hyperactivity and abnormal sleep pattern, high pitched cry, tremor, vomiting, diarrhea and failure to gain weight. The onset, duration, and severity of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome vary based on the specific opioid used, duration of use, timing and amount of last maternal use, and rate of drug elimination by the newborn.  



    5.4 Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



   Patients must not consume alcoholic beverages or prescription or non-prescription products containing alcohol while on EMBEDA therapy. The co-ingestion of alcohol with EMBEDA may result in increased plasma levels and a potentially fatal overdose of morphine. [ see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ] .    



  Hypotension, profound sedation, coma, respiratory depression, and death may result if EMBEDA is used concomitantly with alcohol or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids).  



  When considering the use of EMBEDA in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration of use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin EMBEDA is made, start with EMBEDA 20 mg/0.8 mg every 24 hours, monitor patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, and consider using a lower dose of the concomitant CNS depressant [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2)    ].  



    5.5 Use in Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



   Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating EMBEDA and when EMBEDA is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].  



    5.6 Use in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Monitor patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression for respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy and titrating with EMBEDA, as in these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of EMBEDA may decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]. Consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients if possible.



    5.7 Hypotensive Effect



  EMBEDA may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is an increased risk in patients whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a reduced blood volume or concurrent administration of certain CNS depressant drugs (e.g., phenothiazines or general anesthetics) [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2)    ]. Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dose of EMBEDA. In patients with circulatory shock, EMBEDA may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. Avoid the use of EMBEDA in patients with circulatory shock.



    5.8 Use in Patients with Head Injury or Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Monitor patients taking EMBEDA who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors) for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with EMBEDA. EMBEDA may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2retention can further increase intracranial pressure .  Opioids may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury.



 Avoid the use of EMBEDA in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.9 Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  EMBEDA is contraindicated in patients with paralytic ileus. Avoid the use of EMBEDA in patients with other GI obstruction.



 The morphine in EMBEDA may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, for worsening symptoms. Opioids may cause increases in serum amylase.



    5.10 Use in Patients with Convulsive or Seizure Disorders



  The morphine in EMBEDA may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings. Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during EMBEDA therapy.



    5.11 Avoidance of Withdrawal



   Avoid the use of mixed agonist/antagonist (i.e., pentazocine, nalbuphine, and butorphanol) or partial agonist (buprenorphine) analgesics in patients who have received or are receiving a course of therapy with a full opioid agonist analgesic, including EMBEDA. In these patients, mixed agonists/antagonist and partial agonist analgesics may reduce the analgesic effect and/or may precipitate withdrawal symptoms.  



 Consuming EMBEDA capsules that have been altered by crushing, chewing, or dissolving the pellets can release sufficient naltrexone to precipitate withdrawal in opioid-dependent individuals. Symptoms of withdrawal usually appear within five minutes of ingestion of naltrexone and can last for up to 48 hours. Mental status changes can include restlessness, lacrimation, rhinorrhea, yawning, perspiration, chills, myalgia, and mydriasis. Significant fluid losses from vomiting and diarrhea can require intravenous (IV) fluid administration.



 When discontinuing EMBEDA, gradually taper the dose [ see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)    ]. Do not abruptly discontinue EMBEDA.



    5.12 Driving and Operating Machinery



  EMBEDA may impair the mental or physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to the effects of EMBEDA and know how they will react to the medication.



    5.13 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  Naltrexone does not interfere with thin-layer, gas-liquid, and high performance liquid chromatographic methods which may be used for the separation and detection of morphine, methadone, or quinine in the urine. Naltrexone may or may not interfere with enzymatic methods for the detection of opioids depending on the specificity of the test. Consult the test manufacturer for specific details.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
