<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="emend1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are (  6.1  ):



   Prevention of Chemotherapy Induced Nausea    and    Vomiting (CINV)  



 *  Adults (&gt;=3%): fatigue, diarrhea, asthenia, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, hiccups, white blood cell count decreased, dehydration, and alanine aminotransferase increased. 
 *  Pediatrics (&gt;=3%): neutropenia, headache, diarrhea, decreased appetite, cough, fatigue, hemoglobin decreased, dizziness, and hiccups. 
      PONV  
 

 *  Adults (&gt;=3%): constipation and hypotension. 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The overall safety of EMEND was evaluated in approximately 6500 individuals.



     Adverse Reactions in Adults in the Prevention of Nausea and Vomiting Associated with HEC and MEC  



 In 2 active-controlled, double-blind clinical trials in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy (HEC) (Studies 1 and 2), EMEND in combination with ondansetron and dexamethasone (EMEND regimen) was compared to ondansetron and dexamethasone alone (standard therapy)  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  .



 In 2 active-controlled clinical trials in patients receiving moderately emetogenic chemotherapy (MEC) (Studies 3 and 4), EMEND in combination with ondansetron and dexamethasone (EMEND regimen) was compared to ondansetron and dexamethasone alone (standard therapy)  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  The most common adverse reaction reported in patients who received MEC in pooled Studies 3 and 4 was dyspepsia (6% versus 4%).



 Across these 4 studies there were 1412 patients treated with the EMEND regimen during Cycle 1 of chemotherapy and 1099 of these patients continued into the Multiple-Cycle extension for up to 6 cycles of chemotherapy. The most common adverse reactions reported in patients who received HEC and MEC in pooled Studies 1, 2, 3 and 4 are listed in Table 3.



 Table 3: Most Common Adverse Reactions in Patients Receiving HEC and MEC from a Pooled Analysis of HEC and MEC StudiesReported in &gt;= 3% of patients treated with the EMEND regimen and at a greater incidence than standard therapy. 
                                      EMEND, ondansetron, and dexamethasone(N=1412)  Ondansetron and dexamethasone(N=1396)   
  
 fatigue                                              13%                               12%                 
 diarrhea                                             9%                                 8%                 
 asthenia                                             7%                                 6%                 
 dyspepsia                                            7%                                 5%                 
 abdominal pain                                       6%                                 5%                 
 hiccups                                              5%                                 3%                 
 white blood cell count decreased                     4%                                 3%                 
 dehydration                                          3%                                 2%                 
 alanine aminotransferase increased                   3%                                 2%                 
         In a pooled analysis of the HEC and MEC studies, less common adverse reactions reported in patients treated with the EMEND regimen are listed in Table 4.
 

 Table 4: Less Common Adverse Reactions in EMEND-Treated Patients from a Pooled Analysis of HEC and MEC StudiesReported in &gt; 0.5% of patients treated with the EMEND regimen, at a greater incidence than standard therapy and not previously described in Table 3. 
   Infection and Infestations              oral candidiasis, pharyngitis                                  
   Blood and the Lymphatic System Disorders    anemia, febrile neutropenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia     
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders      decreased appetite, hypokalemia                                
   Psychiatric Disorders                   anxiety                                                        
   Nervous System Disorders                dizziness, dysgeusia, peripheral neuropathy                    
   Cardiac Disorders                       palpitations                                                   
   Vascular Disorders                      flushing, hot flush                                            
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    cough, dyspnea, oropharyngeal pain                             
   Gastrointestinal Disorders              dry mouth, eructation, flatulence, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux disease, nausea, vomiting   
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    alopecia, hyperhidrosis, rash                                  
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    musculoskeletal pain                                           
   General Disorders and Administration Site Condition    edema peripheral, malaise                                      
   Investigations                          aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, blood sodium decreased, blood urea increased, proteinuria, weight decreased   
        In an additional active-controlled clinical study in 1169 patients receiving EMEND and HEC, the adverse reactions were generally similar to that seen in the other HEC studies with EMEND.
 

 In another CINV study, Stevens-Johnson syndrome was reported as a serious adverse reaction in a patient receiving the EMEND regimen with cancer chemotherapy.



 Adverse reactions in the Multiple-Cycle extensions of HEC and MEC studies for up to 6 cycles of chemotherapy were generally similar to that observed in Cycle 1.



     Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients in the Prevention of Nausea and Vomiting Associated with HEC or MEC  



 There is no commercially available dosage formulation appropriate for patients less than 12 years of age and weighing less than 30 kg  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ].  



 In a pooled analysis of 2 active-controlled clinical trials in pediatric patients aged 6 months to 17 years who received highly or moderately emetogenic cancer chemotherapy (Study 5 and a safety study, Study 6), EMEND in combination with ondansetron with or without dexamethasone (EMEND regimen) was compared to ondansetron with or without dexamethasone (control regimen).



 There were 184 patients treated with the EMEND regimen during Cycle 1 and 215 patients received open-label EMEND for up to 9 additional cycles of chemotherapy.



 In Cycle 1, the most common adverse reactions reported in pediatric patients treated with the EMEND regimen in pooled Studies 5 and 6 are listed in Table 5.



 Table 5: Most Common Adverse Reactions in EMEND-Treated Pediatric Patients in HEC and MEC Pooled Studies 5 and 6Reported in &gt;=3% of patients treated with the EMEND regimen and at a greater incidence than control regimen. 
                                         EMEND and ondansetron(N=184)            Ondansetron(N=168)         
  
 neutropenia                                          13%                               11%                 
 headache                                             9%                                 5%                 
 diarrhea                                             6%                                 5%                 
 decreased appetite                                   5%                                 4%                 
 cough                                                5%                                 3%                 
 fatigue                                              5%                                 2%                 
 hemoglobin decreased                                 5%                                 4%                 
 dizziness                                            5%                                 1%                 
 hiccups                                              4%                                 1%                 
         Forty-nine patients were treated with ifosfamide chemotherapy in each arm. Two of the patients treated with ifosfamide in the aprepitant arm developed behavioral changes (agitation = 1; abnormal behavior = 1), whereas no patient treated with ifosfamide in the control arm developed behavioral changes. Aprepitant has the potential for increasing ifosfamide-mediated neurotoxicity through induction of CYP3A4  [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .
 

     Adverse Reactions in Adult Patients in the Prevention of PONV  



 In 2 active-controlled, double-blind clinical studies in patients receiving general anesthesia (Studies 7 and 8), 40-mg oral EMEND was compared to 4-mg intravenous ondansetron  [see  Clinical Studies (14.4)  ].  



 There were 564 patients treated with EMEND and 538 patients treated with ondansetron.



 The most common adverse reactions reported in patients treated with EMEND for PONV in pooled Studies 7 and 8 are listed in Table 6.



 Table 6: Most Common Adverse Reactions in EMEND-Treated Patients in a Pooled Analysis of PONV StudiesReported in &gt;= 3% of patients treated with the EMEND 40 mg and at a greater incidence than ondansetron. 
                                        EMEND 40 mg(N = 564)                 Ondansetron(N = 538)           
  
 constipation                                    9%                                   8%                    
 hypotension                                     6%                                   5%                    
         In a pooled analysis of PONV studies, less common adverse reactions reported in patients treated with EMEND are listed in Table 7.
 

 Table 7: Less Common Adverse Reactions in EMEND-Treated Patients in a Pooled Analysis of PONV StudiesReported in &gt; 0.5% of patients treated with EMEND and at a greater incidence than ondansetron 
   Infections and Infestations                       postoperative infection                              
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                hypokalemia, hypovolemia                             
   Nervous System Disorders                          dizziness, hypoesthesia, syncope                     
   Cardiac Disorders                                 bradycardia                                          
   Vascular Disorders                                hematoma                                             
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    dyspnea, hypoxia, respiratory depression             
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                        abdominal pain, dry mouth, dyspepsia                 
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders            urticaria                                            
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    hypothermia                                          
   Investigations                                    blood albumin decreased, bilirubin increased, blood glucose increased, blood potassium decreased   
   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications    operative hemorrhage, wound dehiscence               
        In addition, two serious adverse reactions were reported in PONV clinical studies in patients taking a higher than recommended dose of EMEND: one case of constipation, and one case of sub-ileus.
 

     Other Studies  



 Angioedema and urticaria were reported as serious adverse reactions in a patient receiving EMEND in a non-CINV/non-PONV study (EMEND is only approved in the CINV and PONV populations).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of EMEND. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  pruritus, rash, urticaria, Stevens-Johnson syndrome/toxic epidermal necrolysis.



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic reactions  [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



   Nervous system disorders:  ifosfamide-induced neurotoxicity reported after EMEND and ifosfamide coadministration.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   CYP3A4 Interactions : Aprepitant is a substrate, weak-to-moderate inhibitor and inducer of CYP3A4; See Full Prescribing Information for recommendations regarding contraindications, risk of adverse reactions, and dosage adjustments of EMEND and concomitant drugs. (  4  ,  5.1  ,  7.1  ,  7.2  ) 
 *   Warfarin  (a CYP2C9 substrate  ) : Risk of decreased INR of prothrombin time; monitor INR in 2-week period, particularly at 7 to 10 days, following initiation of EMEND. (  5.2  ,  7.1  ) 
 *   Hormonal Contraceptives : Efficacy of contraceptives may be reduced during administration of and for 28 days following the last dose of EMEND. Use alternative or back-up methods of contraception. (  5.3  ,  7.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Clinically Significant CYP3A4 Drug Interactions



  Aprepitant is a substrate, a weak-to-moderate (dose-dependent) inhibitor, and an inducer of CYP3A4.



 *  *  Use of pimozide with EMEND is contraindicated due to the risk of significantly increased plasma concentrations of pimozide, potentially resulting in prolongation of the QT interval, a known adverse reaction of pimozide [see  Contraindications (4)  ].  
   Use of EMEND with other drugs that are CYP3A4 substrates, may result in increased plasma concentration of the concomitant drug. 
 *  Use of EMEND with strong or moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ketoconazole, diltiazem) may increase plasma concentrations of aprepitant and result in an increased risk of adverse reactions related to EMEND. 
 *  Use of EMEND with strong CYP3A4 inducers (e.g., rifampin) may result in a reduction in aprepitant plasma concentrations and decreased efficacy of EMEND. 
    See  Table 8  and  Table 9  for a listing of potentially significant drug interactions [see  Drug Interactions (7.1  ,  7.2)  ].  
 

    5.2 Decrease in INR with Concomitant Warfarin



  Coadministration of EMEND with warfarin, a CYP2C9 substrate, may result in a clinically significant decrease in International Normalized Ratio (INR) of prothrombin time [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . Monitor the INR in patients on chronic warfarin therapy in the 2-week period, particularly at 7 to 10 days, following initiation of the 3-day regimen of EMEND with each chemotherapy cycle, or following administration of a single 40-mg dose of EMEND for the prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .



    5.3 Risk of Reduced Efficacy of Hormonal Contraceptives



  Upon coadministration with EMEND, the efficacy of hormonal contraceptives may be reduced during administration of and for 28 days following the last dose of EMEND [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . Advise patients to use alternative or back-up methods of contraception during treatment with EMEND and for 1 month following the last dose of EMEND [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
