<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="emend0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Adverse reactions for the CINV oral aprepitant regimen in conjunction with highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy (incidence &gt;=1% and greater than standard therapy) are: hiccups, asthenia/fatigue, AST/ALT increased, headache, constipation, anorexia, dyspepsia, diarrhea, eructation. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adverse reactions reported for EMEND for Injection were generally similar to that seen in prior HEC studies with oral aprepitant. In addition, infusion site reactions (3%) occurred with EMEND for Injection. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Since EMEND for Injection is converted to aprepitant, those adverse reactions associated with aprepitant might also be expected to occur with EMEND for Injection.



 The overall safety of fosaprepitant was evaluated in approximately 1100 individuals and the overall safety of aprepitant was evaluated in approximately 6500 individuals.



   Oral Aprepitant  



   Highly Emetogenic Chemotherapy (HEC)  



 In 2 well-controlled clinical trials in patients receiving highly emetogenic cancer chemotherapy, 544 patients were treated with aprepitant during Cycle 1 of chemotherapy and 413 of these patients continued into the Multiple-Cycle extension for up to 6 cycles of chemotherapy. Oral aprepitant was given in combination with ondansetron and dexamethasone.



 In Cycle 1, adverse reactions were reported in approximately 17% of patients treated with the aprepitant regimen compared with approximately 13% of patients treated with standard therapy. Treatment was discontinued due to adverse reactions in 0.6% of patients treated with the aprepitant regimen compared with 0.4% of patients treated with standard therapy.



 The most common adverse reactions reported in patients treated with the aprepitant regimen with an incidence &gt;=1% and greater than standard therapy are listed in Table 5.



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions (incidence &gt;=1%) in patients receiving HEC with a greater incidence in the Aprepitant Regimen relative to Standard Therapy 
                                          Aprepitant Regimen   (N=544)     Standard Therapy   (N=550)        
     Respiratory System                                                                                    
 hiccups                                 4.6                            2.9                                
     Body as a Whole/Site Unspecified                                                                        
 asthenia/fatigue                        2.9                            1.6                                
     Investigations                                                                                        
 ALT increased                           2.8                            1.5                                
 AST increased                           1.1                            0.9                                
     Digestive System                                                                                      
 constipation                            2.2                            2.0                                
 dyspepsia                               1.5                            0.7                                
 diarrhea                                1.1                            0.9                                
     Nervous System                                                                                        
 headache                                2.2                            1.8                                
     Metabolism and Nutrition                                                                              
 anorexia                                2.0                            0.5                                
         A listing of adverse reactions in the aprepitant regimen (incidence &lt;1%) that occurred at a greater incidence than standard therapy are presented in the  Less Common Adverse Reactions  subsection below.
 

 In an additional active-controlled clinical study in 1169 patients receiving aprepitant and highly emetogenic chemotherapy, the adverse experience profile was generally similar to that seen in the other HEC studies with aprepitant.



   Moderately Emetogenic Chemotherapy (MEC)  



 In 2 well-controlled clinical trials in patients receiving moderately emetogenic cancer chemotherapy, 868 patients were treated with the aprepitant regimen during Cycle 1 of chemotherapy and 686 of these patients continued into extensions for up to 4 cycles of chemotherapy. In both studies, oral aprepitant was given in combination with ondansetron and dexamethasone (aprepitant regimen).



 In the combined analysis of Cycle 1 data for these 2 studies, adverse reactions were reported in approximately 14% of patients treated with the aprepitant regimen compared with approximately 15% of patients treated with standard therapy. Treatment was discontinued due to adverse reactions in 0.7% of patients treated with the aprepitant regimen compared with 0.2% of patients treated with standard therapy.



 The most common adverse reactions reported in patients treated with the aprepitant regimen with an incidence &gt;=1% and greater than standard therapy are listed in Table 6.



 Table 6: Adverse Reactions (incidence &gt;=1%) in patients receiving MEC with a greater incidence in the Aprepitant Regimen relative to Standard Therapy 
                                          Aprepitant Regimen   (N=868)     Standard Therapy   (N=846)       
     Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                            
 eructation                              1.0                             0.1                               
     General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                        
 fatigue                                 1.4                             0.9                               
         A listing of adverse reactions in the aprepitant regimen (incidence &lt;1%) that occurred at a greater incidence than standard therapy are presented in the  Less Common Adverse Reactions  subsection below.
 

   Less Common Adverse Reactions  



 Adverse reactions reported in either HEC or MEC studies in patients treated with the aprepitant regimen with an incidence &lt;1% and greater than standard therapy are listed in Table 7.



 Table 7: Adverse Reactions (incidence &lt;1%) in patients observed in either HEC or MEC Studies with a greater incidence in the Aprepitant Regimen relative to Standard Therapy 
   Infection and infestations             candidiasis, staphylococcal infection                          
   Blood and the lymphatic system disorders    anemia, febrile neutropenia                                    
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders     weight gain, polydipsia                                        
   Psychiatric disorders                  disorientation, euphoria, anxiety                              
   Nervous system disorders               dizziness, dream abnormality, cognitive disorder, lethargy, somnolence   
   Eye disorders                          conjunctivitis                                                 
   Ear and labyrinth disorders            tinnitus                                                       
   Cardiac disorders                      bradycardia, cardiovascular disorder, palpitations             
   Vascular disorders                     hot flush, flushing                                            
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders    pharyngitis, sneezing, cough, postnasal drip, throat irritation   
   Gastrointestinal disorders             nausea, acid reflux, dysgeusia, epigastric discomfort, obstipation, gastroesophageal reflux disease, perforating duodenal ulcer, vomiting, abdominal pain, dry mouth, abdominal distension, faeces hard, neutropenic colitis, flatulence, stomatitis   
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders    rash, acne, photosensitivity, hyperhidrosis, oily skin, pruritus, skin lesion   
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders    muscle cramp, myalgia, muscular weakness                       
   Renal and urinary disorders            polyuria, dysuria, pollakiuria                                 
   General disorders and administration site condition    edema, chest discomfort, malaise, thirst, chills, gait disturbance   
   Investigations                         alkaline phosphatase increased, hyperglycemia, microscopic hematuria, hyponatremia, weight decreased, neutrophil count decreased   
        In another chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting (CINV) study, Stevens-Johnson syndrome was reported as a serious adverse reaction in a patient receiving aprepitant with cancer chemotherapy.
 

 The adverse experience profiles in the Multiple-Cycle extensions of HEC and MEC studies for up to 6 cycles of chemotherapy were similar to that observed in Cycle 1.



   Fosaprepitant  



 In an active-controlled clinical study in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy, safety was evaluated for 1143 patients receiving the 1-day regimen of EMEND for Injection 150 mg compared to 1169 patients receiving the 3-day regimen of EMEND (aprepitant). The safety profile was generally similar to that seen in prior HEC studies with aprepitant. However, infusion-site reactions occurred at a higher incidence in patients in the fosaprepitant group (3.0%) compared to those in the aprepitant group (0.5%). The reported infusion-site reactions included infusion-site erythema, infusion-site pruritus, infusion-site pain, infusion-site induration, and infusion-site thrombophlebitis.



 The following additional adverse reactions occurred with fosaprepitant 150 mg and were not reported with the oral aprepitant regimen in the corresponding section above.



 Table 8: Adverse Reactions (incidence &gt;0.1%) in patients receiving Fosaprepitant 150 mg and not reported above for the Oral Aprepitant Regimen 
   General disorders and administration site conditions    infusion site erythema, infusion site pruritus, infusion site induration, infusion site pain   
   Investigations                                  blood pressure increased                              
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders          erythema                                              
   Vascular disorders                              thrombophlebitis (predominantly, infusion-site thrombophlebitis)   
          Other Studies with Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting  
 

 In well-controlled clinical studies in patients receiving general balanced anesthesia, 564 patients were administered 40-mg aprepitant orally and 538 patients were administered 4-mg ondansetron intravenously.



 Adverse reactions were reported in approximately 4% of patients treated with 40-mg aprepitant compared with approximately 6% of patients treated with 4-mg ondansetron intravenously.



 In patients treated with aprepitant, increased ALT (1.1%) was seen at a greater incidence than with ondansetron (1.0%). The following additional adverse reactions were observed in patients treated with aprepitant at an incidence &lt;1% and greater than with ondansetron.



 Table 9: Adverse Reactions (incidence &lt;1%) in patients receiving Aprepitant 40 mg with a greater incidence in the Aprepitant group relative to ondansetron 
   Psychiatric disorders                           insomnia                                              
   Nervous system disorders                        dysarthria, hypoesthesia, sensory disturbance         
   Eye disorders                                   miosis, visual acuity reduced                         
   Cardiac disorders                               bradycardia                                           
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders    dyspnea, wheezing                                     
   Gastrointestinal disorders                      abdominal pain upper, bowel sounds abnormal, dry mouth, nausea, stomach discomfort   
        In addition, two serious adverse reactions were reported in postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) clinical studies in patients taking a higher dose of aprepitant: one case of constipation, and one case of subileus.
 

   Other Studies  



 Angioedema and urticaria were reported as serious adverse reactions in a patient receiving aprepitant in a non-CINV/non-PONV study.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of fosaprepitant and aprepitant. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  pruritus, rash, urticaria, rarely Stevens-Johnson syndrome/toxic epidermal necrolysis.



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic reactions.



   Nervous system disorders:  Events of ifosfamide-induced neurotoxicity have been reported after aprepitant and ifosfamide coadministration.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Fosaprepitant should be used with caution in patients receiving concomitant medications that are primarily metabolized through CYP3A4. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Immediate hypersensitivity reactions may occur during infusion. Patients have generally responded to discontinuation. It is not recommended to reinitiate the infusion. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Coadministration of fosaprepitant or aprepitant with warfarin (a CYP2C9 substrate) may result in a clinically significant decrease in International Normalized Ratio (INR) of prothrombin time. (  5.3  ) 
 *  The efficacy of hormonal contraceptives during and for 28 days following the last dose of fosaprepitant or aprepitant may be reduced. Alternative or back-up methods of contraception should be used. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 CYP3A4 Interactions



  Fosaprepitant is rapidly converted to aprepitant, which is a moderate inhibitor of CYP3A4 when administered as a 3-day antiemetic dosing regimen for CINV. Fosaprepitant should be used with caution in patients receiving concomitant medications that are primarily metabolized through CYP3A4. Inhibition of CYP3A4 by aprepitant or fosaprepitant could result in elevated plasma concentrations of these concomitant medications. When fosaprepitant is used concomitantly with another CYP3A4 inhibitor, aprepitant plasma concentrations could be elevated. When aprepitant is used concomitantly with medications that induce CYP3A4 activity, aprepitant plasma concentrations could be reduced, and this may result in decreased efficacy of aprepitant [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .



 Chemotherapy agents that are known to be metabolized by CYP3A4 include docetaxel, paclitaxel, etoposide, irinotecan, ifosfamide, imatinib, vinorelbine, vinblastine and vincristine. In clinical studies, the oral aprepitant regimen was administered commonly with etoposide, vinorelbine, or paclitaxel. The doses of these agents were not adjusted to account for potential drug interactions.



 In separate pharmacokinetic studies, no clinically significant change in docetaxel or vinorelbine pharmacokinetics was observed when the oral aprepitant regimen was coadministered.



 Due to the small number of patients in clinical studies who received the CYP3A4 substrates vinblastine, vincristine, or ifosfamide, particular caution and careful monitoring are advised in patients receiving these agents or other chemotherapy agents metabolized primarily by CYP3A4 that were not studied [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Isolated reports of immediate hypersensitivity reactions including flushing, erythema, dyspnea, and anaphylaxis have occurred during infusion of fosaprepitant. These hypersensitivity reactions have generally responded to discontinuation of the infusion and administration of appropriate therapy. Reinitiation of the infusion is not recommended in patients who experience these symptoms during first-time use.



    5.3 Coadministration with Warfarin (a CYP2C9 substrate)



  Coadministration of fosaprepitant or aprepitant with warfarin may result in a clinically significant decrease in International Normalized Ratio (INR) of prothrombin time. In patients on chronic warfarin therapy, the INR should be closely monitored in the 2-week period, particularly at 7 to 10 days, following initiation of fosaprepitant with each chemotherapy cycle [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .



    5.4 Coadministration with Hormonal Contraceptives



  Upon coadministration with fosaprepitant or aprepitant, the efficacy of hormonal contraceptives may be reduced during and for 28 days following the last dose of either fosaprepitant or aprepitant. Alternative or back-up methods of contraception should be used during treatment with and for 1 month following the last dose of fosaprepitant or aprepitant [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .



    5.5 Chronic Continuous Use



  Chronic continuous use of EMEND for Injection for prevention of nausea and vomiting is not recommended because it has not been studied; and because the drug interaction profile may change during chronic continuous use.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
