<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="emsam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label.



 *    Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ] . 
 *    Serotonin Syndrome [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] . 
 *    Blood Pressure Elevation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] . 
 *    Activation of Mania/Hypomania [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ] . 
   *    Adverse Reactions occurring at an incidence of 2% or More Among EMSAM-Treated Patients and greater than placebo: Application site reaction, headache, insomnia, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, rash, pharyngitis, sinusitis (  6.1  ). 
      EXCERPT:   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Mylan Specialty L.P. at 1-877-4-INFO-RX (877-446-3679) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



       Patient Exposure    

  The premarketing development program for EMSAM included selegiline exposures in patients and/or normal subjects from two different groups of studies: 702 healthy subjects in clinical pharmacology/pharmacokinetics studies and 2,036 exposures from patients in controlled and uncontrolled major depressive disorder clinical trials. The conditions and duration of treatment with EMSAM varied and included double-blind, open-label, fixed-dose, and dose titration studies of short-term and longer-term exposures. Safety was assessed by monitoring adverse reactions, physical examinations, vital signs, body weights, laboratory analyses, and ECGs.



 Adverse reactions during exposure were obtained primarily by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators. In the tables and tabulations that follow, standard COSTART terminology has been used to classify reported adverse reactions. The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse reaction of the type listed. A reaction was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



       Adverse Reactions Leading To Discontinuation of Treatment    

  Among 817 MDD patients treated with EMSAM at doses of either 3 mg per 24 hours (151 patients), 6 mg per 24 hours (550 patients) or 6 mg per 24 hours, 9 mg per 24 hours, and 12 mg per 24 hours (116 patients) in placebo-controlled trials of up to 8 weeks in duration, 7.1% discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction as compared with 3.6% of 668 patients receiving placebo. The only adverse reaction associated with discontinuation, in at least 1% of EMSAM-treated patients at a rate at least twice that of placebo, was application site reaction (2% EMSAM vs. 0% placebo).



       Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More Among EMSAM-Treated Patients    

  Table 2 enumerates adverse reactions that occurred at an incidence of 2% or more (rounded to the nearest percent) among 817 MDD patients treated with EMSAM in doses ranging from 3 to 12 mg per 24 hours in placebo-controlled trials of up to 8 weeks in duration. Reactions included are those occurring in 2% or more of patients treated with EMSAM and for which the incidence in patients treated with EMSAM was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 One adverse reaction was associated with a reporting of at least 5% in the EMSAM group, and a rate at least twice that in the placebo group, in the pool of short-term, placebo-controlled studies: application site reactions (  see  Application Site Reactions  , below  ). In one such study which utilized higher mean doses of EMSAM than that in the entire study pool, the following reactions met these criteria: application site reactions, insomnia, diarrhea, and pharyngitis.



 Table 2. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials for Major Depressive Disorder with EMSAMReactions reported by at least 2% of patients treated with EMSAM are included, except the following reactions, which had an incidence on placebo treatment greater than or equal to EMSAM: infection, nausea, dizziness, pain, abdominal pain, nervousness, back pain, asthenia, anxiety, flu syndrome, accidental injury, somnolence, rhinitis, and palpitations. 
  Body System/Preferred Term                      EMSAM  (N = 817)            Placebo  (N = 668)           
                                                  (% of Patients Reporting Reaction)    
  Body as a Whole                                                                                          
     Headache                                     18                          17                           
  Digestive                                                                                                
     Diarrhea                                     9                           7                            
     Dyspepsia                                    4                           3                            
  Nervous                                                                                                  
     Insomnia                                     12                          7                            
     Dry Mouth                                    8                           6                            
  Respiratory                                                                                              
     Pharyngitis                                  3                           2                            
     Sinusitis                                    3                           1                            
  Skin                                                                                                     
     Application Site Reaction                    24                          12                           
     Rash                                         4                           2                            
               Application Site Reactions    
   In the pool of short-term, placebo-controlled major depressive disorder studies, application site reactions (ASRs) were reported in 24% of EMSAM-treated patients and 12% of placebo-treated patients. Most ASRs were mild or moderate in severity. ASRs led to dropout in 2% of EMSAM-treated patients and no placebo-treated patients.



 In one such study which utilized higher mean doses of EMSAM, ASRs were reported in 40% of EMSAM-treated patients and 20% of placebo-treated patients. Most of the ASRs in this study were described as erythema and most resolved spontaneously, requiring no treatment. When treatment was administered, it most commonly consisted of dermatological preparations of corticosteroids.



       Sexual Dysfunction    

  Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment.



 Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling are likely to underestimate their actual incidence. Table 3 shows that the incidence rates of sexual side effects in patients with major depressive disorder are comparable to the placebo rates in placebo-controlled trials.



 Table 3. Incidence of Sexual Side Effects in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials with EMSAM 
  Adverse Reaction                      EMSAM                             Placebo                           
                                        IN MALES ONLY                     
                                        (N = 304)                         (N = 256)                         
  Abnormal Ejaculation                  1.0%                              0.0%                              
  Decreased Libido                      0.7%                              0.0%                              
  Impotence                             0.7%                              0.4%                              
  Anorgasmia                            0.2%                              0.0%                              
                                        IN FEMALES ONLY                   
                                        (N = 513)                         (N = 412)                         
  Decreased Libido                      0.0%                              0.2%                              
         There are no adequately designed studies examining sexual dysfunction with EMSAM treatment.
 

       Vital Sign Changes    

  EMSAM and placebo groups were compared with respect to (1) mean change from baseline in vital signs (pulse, systolic blood pressure, and diastolic blood pressure), and (2) the incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially clinically significant changes from baseline in these variables. In the pool of short-term, placebo-controlled major depressive disorder studies, 3.0% of EMSAM-treated patients and 1.5% of placebo-treated patients experienced a low systolic blood pressure, defined as a reading less than or equal to 90 mmHg with a change from baseline of at least 20 mmHg. In one study which utilized higher mean doses of EMSAM, 6.2% of EMSAM-treated patients and no placebo-treated patients experienced a low standing systolic blood pressure by these criteria.



 In the pool of short-term major depressive disorder trials, 9.8% of EMSAM-treated patients and 6.7% of placebo-treated patients experienced a notable orthostatic change in blood pressure, defined as a decrease of at least 10 mmHg in mean blood pressure with postural change.



       Weight Changes    

  In placebo-controlled studies (6 to 8 weeks), the incidence of patients who experienced at least 5% weight gain or weight loss is shown in Table 4.



 Table 4. Incidence of Weight Gain and Weight Loss in Placebo-Controlled Trials with EMSAM 
  Weight Change                            EMSAM                              Placebo                       
                                           (N = 757)                          (N = 614)                     
  Gained at least 5%                       2.1%                               2.4%                          
  Lost at least 5%                         5.0%                               2.8%                          
         In these trials, the mean change in body weight among EMSAM-treated patients was a 1.2 lbs loss compared to 0.3 lbs gain in placebo-treated patients.
 

       Laboratory Changes    

  EMSAM and placebo groups were compared with respect to (1) mean change from baseline in various serum chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis variables, and (2) the incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially clinically significant changes from baseline in these variables. These analyses revealed no clinically important changes in laboratory test parameters associated with EMSAM.



       Electrocardiogram Changes    

  Electrocardiograms (ECGs) from EMSAM (N = 817) and placebo (N = 668) groups in controlled studies were compared with respect to (1) mean change from baseline in various ECG parameters, and (2) the incidence of patients meeting criteria for clinically significant changes from baseline in these variables.



 No clinically meaningful changes in ECG parameters from baseline to final visit were observed for patients in controlled studies.



       Other Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of EMSAM    

  The following listing does not include reactions: 1) already listed elsewhere in labeling, 2) for which a causal relationship to drug was remote, 3) which were so general as to be uninformative, 4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or 5) which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo.



   Cardiovascular System:       Tachycardia.



   Digestive System:       Anorexia.



   Nervous System:       Agitation, amnesia, tremor, twitching.



   Skin and Appendages:       Pruritus.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of EMSAM.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Nervous System:    Convulsion and hypoesthesia.



     Psychiatric System:    Disorientation, hallucination (visual), and tension.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS

  WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS

    Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies. These studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressant use in patients over age 24; there was a trend toward reduced risk with antidepressant use in patients aged 65 and older   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .         



   In patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy, monitor closely for worsening and for emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .        



   EMSAM is contraindicated in patients less than 12 years of age because of an increased risk of hypertensive crisis   [see   Contraindications (4)   and   Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behaviors in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants (5.1). 
 *  Monitor for worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors (5.1). 
 *  EMSAM is contraindicated in patients less than 12 years of age (4) and (8.4). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Tyramine-Induced Hypertensive Crisis: Patients receiving EMSAM 9 mg per 24 hours and 12 mg per 24 hours should follow the recommended dietary modifications (  5.3  ). 
 *    Blood Pressure Elevation Related to Concomitant Medication: monitor blood pressure if EMSAM is used with any of the following drugs: buspirone, amphetamines, or cold products or weight-reducing preparations that contain sympathomimetic amines (e.g., pseudoephedrine, phenylephrine, phenylpropanolamine, and ephedrine) (  5.3  ). 
 *    Activation of Mania/Hypomania: Use cautiously in patients with a history of mania (  5.4  ). 
 *    External Heat: Avoid exposing the EMSAM application site to external sources of direct heat, such as heating pads or electric blankets, heat lamps, saunas, hot tubs, heated water beds, and prolonged direct sunlight (  5.5  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [SSRIs] and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18 to 24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a trend toward risk reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorders (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of nine antidepressant drugs in over 4,400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of two months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1,000 patients treated) are provided in Table 1.



 Table 1. Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated 
  Age Range                                                                                               
  Increases Compared to Placebo                     
  &lt; 18                                              14 additional cases                                   
  18 to 24                                          5 additional cases                                    
  Decreases Compared to Placebo                     
  25 to 64                                          1 fewer case                                          
  &gt;= 65                                             6 fewer cases                                         
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials.    There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



 The following symptoms anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to healthcare providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers.  



      Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder    



  A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described above represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It should be noted that EMSAM is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with concomitant use of MAOIs, such as EMSAM, with serotonergic drugs. These reactions have also been reported in patients who have discontinued serotonergic drugs and then subsequently started an MAOI [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular changes (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea).



 Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome. Treatment with EMSAM and any concomitant serotonergic agents should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Blood Pressure Elevation



     Tyramine-Induced Hypertensive Crisis    



  EMSAM inhibits the catabolism of dietary amines, such as tyramine, and has the potential to produce a hypertensive crisis following the ingestion of tyramine-rich foods or beverages [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .



 Hypertensive crises, which in some cases may be fatal, are characterized by some or all of the following symptoms: occipital headache which may radiate frontally, palpitation, neck stiffness or soreness, nausea, vomiting, sweating (sometimes with fever and sometimes with cold, clammy skin), dilated pupils, and photophobia. Either tachycardia or bradycardia may be present and can be associated with constricting chest pain. Intracranial bleeding has been reported in association with the increase in blood pressure. Patients should be instructed as to the signs and symptoms of severe hypertension and advised to seek immediate medical attention if these signs or symptoms are present.



 If a hypertensive crisis occurs, EMSAM should be discontinued immediately and therapy to lower blood pressure should be instituted immediately. Fever should be managed by means of external cooling. Patients must be closely monitored until symptoms have stabilized.



 To prevent a hypertensive crisis, patients receiving treatment with EMSAM 9 mg per 24 hours or EMSAM 12 mg per 24 hours should follow the advice regarding a low tyramine diet described in Table 5 under Dietary Modifications Required for Patients Taking EMSAM 9 mg per 24 hours and 12 mg per 24 hours [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



      Blood Pressure Elevation Related to Concomitant Medication    



  Carbamazepine is contraindicated with EMSAM because carbamazepine has been shown to significantly elevate selegiline levels, which may increase the risk of a hypertensive crisis [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.4)  ]  .



 The use of EMSAM with adrenergic drugs or buspirone may produce substantial increases in blood pressure. Therefore, monitor blood pressure if EMSAM is used with any of the following drugs: buspirone, amphetamines, or cold products or weight-reducing preparations that contain sympathomimetic amines (e.g., pseudoephedrine, phenylephrine, phenylpropanolamine, and ephedrine).



    5.4 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



  During Phase III trials, a manic reaction occurred in 8 out of 2,036 (0.4%) patients treated with EMSAM. Activation of mania/hypomania can occur in a small proportion of patients with major depressive disorder treated with antidepressants. EMSAM should be used cautiously in patients with a history of mania.



    5.5 External Heat



  The effect of direct heat applied to the EMSAM patch on the bioavailability of selegiline has not been studied. However, in theory, heat may result in an increase in the amount of selegiline absorbed from the EMSAM patch and produce elevated serum levels of selegiline. Patients should be advised to avoid exposing the EMSAM application site to external sources of direct heat, such as heating pads or electric blankets, heat lamps, saunas, hot tubs, heated water beds, and prolonged direct sunlight.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
