<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="emtriva1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Lactic acidosis/severe hepatomegaly with steatosis [See  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  
 *  Severe acute exacerbations of Hepatitis B [See  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  
 *  Immune reconstitution syndrome [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ].  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=10%) are headache, diarrhea, nausea, fatigue, dizziness, depression, insomnia, abnormal dreams, rash, abdominal pain, asthenia, increased cough, and rhinitis. Skin hyperpigmentation was very common (&gt;=10%) in pediatric patients. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc. at 1-800-GILEAD-5 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Adverse Reactions from Clinical Trials Experience

    Clinical Trials in Adult Subjects  



 More than 2,000 adult subjects with HIV-1 infection have been treated with EMTRIVA alone or in combination with other antiretroviral agents for periods of 10 days to 200 weeks in clinical trials.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 10%, any severity) identified from any of the 3 large controlled clinical trials include headache, diarrhea nausea, fatigue, dizziness, depression, insomnia, abnormal dreams, rash, abdominal pain, asthenia, increased cough, and rhinitis.



     Studies 301A and 303 - Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions:  The most common adverse reactions that occurred in subjects receiving EMTRIVA with other antiretroviral agents in clinical trials 301A and 303 were headache, diarrhea, nausea, and rash, which were generally of mild to moderate severity. Approximately 1% of subjects discontinued participation in the clinical trials due to these events. All adverse reactions were reported with similar frequency in EMTRIVA and control treatment groups with the exception of skin discoloration which was reported with higher frequency in the EMTRIVA treated group.



 Skin discoloration, manifested by hyperpigmentation on the palms and/or soles was generally mild and asymptomatic. The mechanism and clinical significance are unknown.



 A summary of EMTRIVA treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions in Studies 301A and 303 is provided in Table 2.



 Table 2 Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions (All Grades, Regardless of Causality) Reported in &gt;=3% of EMTRIVA-Treated Subjects in Either Study 301A or 303 (0-48 Weeks) 
                                                 303             301A         
 EMTRIVA+ ZDV/d4T+ NNRTI/PI(N=294)         Lamivudine+ ZDV/d4T+ NNRTI/PI(N=146)  EMTRIVA+ didanosine + efavirenz(N=286)  Stavudine+ didanosine+ efavirenz(N=285)   
  
 Body as a Whole                                                                                                
   Abdominal pain                                8%               11%              14%              17%         
   Asthenia                                      16%              10%              12%              17%         
   Headache                                      13%              6%               22%              25%         
 Digestive System                                                                                               
   Diarrhea                                      23%              18%              23%              32%         
   Dyspepsia                                     4%               5%               8%               12%         
   Nausea                                        18%              12%              13%              23%         
   Vomiting                                      9%               7%               9%               12%         
 Musculoskeletal                                                                                                
   Arthralgia                                    3%               4%               5%               6%          
   Myalgia                                       4%               4%               6%               3%          
 Nervous System                                                                                                 
   Abnormal dreams                               2%               &lt;1%              11%              19%         
   Depressive disorders                          6%               10%              9%               13%         
   Dizziness                                     4%               5%               25%              26%         
   Insomnia                                      7%               3%               16%              21%         
   Neuropathy/peripheral neuritis                4%               3%               4%               13%         
   Paresthesia                                   5%               7%               6%               12%         
 Respiratory                                                                                                    
   Increased cough                               14%              11%              14%              8%          
   Rhinitis                                      18%              12%              12%              10%         
 Skin                                                                                                           
   Rash event                                    17%              14%              30%              33%         
               Studies 301A and 303 - Laboratory Abnormalities  :    Laboratory abnormalities in these trials occurred with similar frequency in the EMTRIVA and comparator groups. A summary of Grades 3-4 laboratory abnormalities is provided in Table 3 below.
 

 Table 3 Treatment-Emergent Grades 3-4 Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=1% of EMTRIVA-Treated Subjects in Either Study 301A or 303 
                                                 303             301A         
 EMTRIVA+ ZDV/d4T+ NNRTI/PI(N=294)         Lamivudine+ ZDV/d4T+ NNRTI/PI(N=146)  EMTRIVA+ Didanosine+ Efavirenz(N=286)  Stavudine+ Didanosine+ Efavirenz(N=285)   
  
 Percentage with grade 3 or grade 4 laboratory abnormality        31%              28%              34%              38%         
 ALT (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                                2%               1%               5%               6%          
 AST (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                                3%               &lt;1%              6%               9%          
 Bilirubin (&gt;2.5 * ULN)                          1%               2%               &lt;1%              &lt;1%         
 Creatine kinase(&gt;4.0 * ULN)                     11%              14%              12%              11%         
 Neutrophils (&lt;750 mm  3  )                      5%               3%               5%               7%          
 Pancreatic amylase(&gt;2.0 * ULN)                  2%               2%               &lt;1%              1%          
 Serum amylase(&gt;2.0 * ULN)                       2%               2%               5%               10%         
 Serum glucose&lt;40 or &gt;250 mg/dL)                 3%               3%               2%               3%          
 Serum lipase(&gt;2.0 * ULN)                        &lt;1%              &lt;1%              1%               2%          
 Triglycerides(&gt;750 mg/dL)                       10%              8%               9%               6%          
               Study 934 - Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions:  In Study 934, 511 antiretroviral-naive subjects received either VIREAD  (r)  + EMTRIVA administered in combination with efavirenz (N=257) or zidovudine/lamivudine administered in combination with efavirenz (N=254). Adverse reactions observed in this trial were generally consistent with those seen in previous trials in treatment-experienced or treatment-naive subjects (Table 4).
 

 Table 4 Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse ReactionsFrequencies of adverse reactions are based on all treatment-emergent adverse events, regardless of relationship to study drug. (Grades 2-4) Reported in &gt;=5% in Any Treatment Group in Study 934 (0-144 Weeks) 
                                                 TDF+ EMTRIVA + EFV                AZT/3TC + EFV            
                                                       N=257                           N=254                
  
 Gastrointestinal Disorder                                                                                  
   Diarrhea                                              9%                              5%                 
   Nausea                                                9%                              7%                 
   Vomiting                                              2%                              5%                 
 General Disorders and Administration Site Condition                                                                   
   Fatigue                                               9%                              8%                 
 Infections and Infestations                                                                                
   Sinusitis                                             8%                              4%                 
   Upper respiratory tract infections                    8%                              5%                 
   Nasopharyngitis                                       5%                              3%                 
 Nervous System Disorders                                                                                   
   Headache                                              6%                              5%                 
   Dizziness                                             8%                              7%                 
 Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                      
   Depression                                            9%                              7%                 
   Insomnia                                              5%                              7%                 
 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                     
   Rash event                                            7%                              9%                 
             Study 934 - Laboratory Abnormalities:  Significant laboratory abnormalities observed in this trial are shown in Table 5.
 

 Table 5 Significant Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=1% of Subjects in Any Treatment Group in Study 934 (0-144 Weeks) 
                                                 TDF+ EMTRIVA + EFV                AZT/3TC + EFV            
                                                       N=257                           N=254                
  
 Any &gt;= Grade 3 Laboratory Abnormality                  30%                             26%                 
 Fasting Cholesterol (&gt;240 mg/dL)                       22%                             24%                 
 Creatine Kinase(M: &gt;990 U/L)(F: &gt;845 U/L)                9%                              7%                 
 Serum Amylase (&gt;175 U/L)                                8%                              4%                 
 Alkaline Phosphatase (&gt;550 U/L)                         1%                              0%                 
 AST(M: &gt;180 U/L)(F: &gt;170 U/L)                           3%                              3%                 
 ALT(M: &gt;215 U/L)(F: &gt;170 U/L)                           2%                              3%                 
 Hemoglobin (&lt;8.0 mg/dL)                                 0%                              4%                 
 Hyperglycemia (&gt;250 mg/dL)                              2%                              1%                 
 Hematuria (&gt;75 RBC/HPF)                                 3%                              2%                 
 Glycosuria (3+)                                        &lt;1%                              1%                 
 Neutrophils (&lt;750/mm  3  )                              3%                              5%                 
 Fasting Triglycerides (&gt;750 mg/dL)                      4%                              2%                 
             Clinical Trials in Pediatric Subjects  
 

 Assessment of adverse reactions is based on data from Study 203, an open label, uncontrolled trial of 116 HIV-1-infected pediatric subjects who received emtricitabine through 48 weeks. The adverse reaction profile in pediatric subjects was generally comparable to that observed in clinical trials of EMTRIVA in adult subjects  [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Hyperpigmentation was more frequent in children. Additional adverse reactions identified from this trial include anemia.



 Selected treatment-emergent adverse events, regardless of causality, reported in subjects during 48 weeks of treatment were the following: infection (44%), hyperpigmentation (32%), increased cough (28%), vomiting (23%), otitis media (23%), rash (21%), rhinitis (20%), diarrhea (20%), fever (18%), pneumonia (15%), gastroenteritis (11%), abdominal pain (10%), and anemia (7%). Treatment-emergent grades 3-4 laboratory abnormalities were experienced by 9% of pediatric subjects, including elevated amylase (&gt;2.0 * ULN) (n=4), decreased neutrophils (&lt;750/mm  3  ) (n=3), elevated ALT (&gt;5 * ULN) (n=2), elevated CPK (&gt;4 * ULN) (n=2) and one subject each with elevated bilirubin (&gt;3.0 * ULN), elevated GGT (&gt;10 * ULN), elevated lipase (&gt;2.5 * ULN), decreased hemoglobin (&lt;7 g/dL), and decreased glucose (&lt;40 mg/dL).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B

    WARNING:  LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B  

    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs alone or in combination with other antiretrovirals   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].    



   EMTRIVA is not approved for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection and the safety and efficacy of EMTRIVA have not been established in patients coinfected with HBV and HIV-1. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who have discontinued EMTRIVA. Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and discontinue EMTRIVA. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning      .  



 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs. (5.1) 
 *  Emtriva is not approved for the treatment of chronic Hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. Severe acute exacerbations of Hepatitis B have been reported in patients who have discontinued EMTRIVA. Hepatic function should be monitored closely in patients coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV. If appropriate, initiation of anti-Hepatitis B therapy may be warranted. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Products with same active ingredient: Do not use with other emtricitabine-containing products (e.g., ATRIPLA, COMPLERA, STRIBILD, and TRUVADA). (  5.3  ) 
 *  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat: Observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Immune reconstitution syndrome: May necessitate further evaluation and treatment. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs alone or in combination, including emtricitabine and other antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged nucleoside exposure may be risk factors. Particular caution should be exercised when administering nucleoside analogs to any patient with known risk factors for liver diseases; however, cases have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors. Treatment with EMTRIVA should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.2 Patients Coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV



  It is recommended that all patients with HIV-1 be tested for the presence of chronic Hepatitis B virus (HBV) before initiating antiretroviral therapy. EMTRIVA is not approved for the treatment of chronic HBV infection and the safety and efficacy of EMTRIVA have not been established in patients coinfected with HBV and HIV-1. Severe acute exacerbations of Hepatitis B have been reported in patients after the discontinuation of EMTRIVA. In some patients infected with HBV and treated with EMTRIVA, the exacerbations of hepatitis B were associated with liver decompensation and liver failure. Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and discontinue EMTRIVA. If appropriate, initiation of anti-Hepatitis B therapy may be warranted.



    5.3 Coadministration with Related Products



   EMTRIVA is a component of ATRIPLA (a fixed-dose combination of efavirenz, emtricitabine, and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate), COMPLERA (a fixed-dose combination of emtricitabine, rilpivirine, and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate), STRIBILD (a fixed-dose combination of elvitegravir, cobicistat, emtricitabine, and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate), and TRUVADA (a fixed-dose combination of emtricitabine and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate). EMTRIVA should not be coadministered with ATRIPLA, COMPLERA, STRIBILD, or TRUVADA. Due to similarities between emtricitabine and lamivudine, EMTRIVA should not be coadministered with other drugs containing lamivudine, including Combivir (lamivudine/zidovudine), Epivir or Epivir-HBV (lamivudine), Epzicom (abacavir sulfate/lamivudine), or Trizivir (abacavir sulfate/lamivudine/zidovudine).  



    5.4 New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment



  Emtricitabine is principally eliminated by the kidney. Reduction of the dosage of EMTRIVA is recommended for patients with impaired renal function [See  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.5 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.6 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including EMTRIVA. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections [such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia (PCP), or tuberculosis], which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



  Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
