<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="endometrin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions reported (greater than 2%) were post-oocyte retrieval pain, abdominal pain, nausea, and ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (  6  )



   This leaflet summarizes the most important information about Endometrin. To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ferring at 1-888-FERRING (1-888-337-7464) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety data reflect exposure to Endometrin in 808 infertile women (74.9% White, 10.3% Hispanic, 5.4% Black, 5% Asian, and 4.6% Other) in a single Assisted Reproductive Technology 10 week clinical study conducted in the U.S. Endometrin was studied at doses of 100 mg twice daily and 100 mg three times daily. The adverse reactions that occurred at a rate greater than or equal to 2% in either Endometrin group are summarized in Table 1.



 Table 1: Number and Frequency of Reported Adverse Reactions in Women Treated with Endometrin in an Assisted Reproductive Technology Study FULL PRESCRIBING INFORMATION 
 Body System                         Endometrin100 mg twice daily(N=404)  Endometrin100 mg three times daily(N=404)   
   Preferred Term                     
  
   Gastrointestinal Disorders         
   Abdominal pain                                50 (12%)                           50 (12%)                
   Nausea                                         32 (8%)                            29 (7%)                
   Abdominal distension                           18 (4%)                            17 (4%)                
   Constipation                                   9 (2%)                             14 (3%)                
   Vomiting                                       13 (3%)                            9 (2%)                 
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions     
   Fatigue                                        7 (2%)                             12 (3%)                
   Infections and Infestations        
   Urinary tract infection                        9 (2%)                             4 (1%)                 
   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications     
   Post-oocyte retrieval pain                    115 (28%)                          102 (25%)               
   Nervous System Disorders           
   Headache                                       15 (4%)                            13 (3%)                
   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders     
   Ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome               30 (7%)                            27 (7%)                
   Uterine spasm                                  15 (4%)                            11 (3%)                
   Vaginal bleeding                               13 (3%)                            14 (3%)                
         Other less common reported adverse reactions included vaginal irritation, itching, burning, discomfort, urticaria, and peripheral edema.
 

   6.2 Expected Adverse Reaction Profile Seen with Progesterone

  Endometrin is also expected to have adverse reactions similar to other drugs containing progesterone that may include breast tenderness, bloating, mood swings, irritability, and drowsiness.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Life-threatening arterial or venous thromboembolic disorders may occur during hormone treatment, including treatment with Endometrin. Discontinue Endometrin if any of these are suspected (  5.1  ) 
 *  Observe patients with a history of depression closely. Consider discontinuation if symptoms worsen (  5.2  ) 
 *  Endometrin is not recommended for use with other vaginal products (such as antifungal products) as this may alter progesterone release and absorption from the vaginal insert (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular or Cerebrovascular Disorders



  The physician should be alert to earliest signs of myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular disorders, arterial or venous thromboembolism (venous thromboembolism or pulmonary embolism), thrombophlebitis, or retinal thrombosis. Endometrin should be discontinued if any of these are suspected.



    5.2 Depression



  Patients with a history of depression need to be closely observed. Consider discontinuation if symptoms worsen.



    5.3 Use of Other Vaginal Products



  Endometrin should not be recommended for use with other vaginal products (such as antifungal products as this may alter progesterone release and absorption from the vaginal insert [ see  Drug Interactions (7)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
