<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="endodan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions that may be associated with ENDODAN tablet use include respiratory depression, apnea, respiratory arrest, circulatory depression, hypotension, and shock (see  OVERDOSAGE  ).



 The most frequently observed non-serious adverse reactions include lightheadedness, dizziness, drowsiness or sedation, nausea, and vomiting. These effects seem to be more prominent in ambulatory than in nonambulatory patients, and some of these adverse reactions may be alleviated if the patient lies down. Other adverse reactions include euphoria, dysphoria, constipation and pruritus.



 Aspirin may increase the likelihood of hemorrhage due to its effect on the gastric mucosa and platelet function. Furthermore, aspirin has the potential to cause anaphylaxis in hypersensitive patients as well as angioedema especially in patients with chronic urticaria. Other adverse reactions due to aspirin use include anorexia, reversible hepatotoxicity, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, purpura, decreased plasma iron concentration, and shortened erythrocyte survival time.



 Other adverse reactions obtained from postmarketing experiences with ENDODAN tablets are listed by organ system and in decreasing order of severity and/or frequency as follows:



   Body as a Whole  



 allergic reaction, malaise, asthenia, headache, anaphylaxis, fever, hypothermia, thirst, increased sweating, accident, accidental overdose, non-accidental overdose.



   Cardiovascular  



 tachycardia, dysrhythmias, hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, bradycardia, palpitations



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System  



 stupor, paresthesia, agitation, cerebral edema, coma, confusion, dizziness, headache, subdural or intracranial hemorrhage, lethargy, seizures, anxiety, mental impairment



   Fluid and Electrolyte  



 dehydration, hyperkalemia, metabolic acidosis, respiratory alkalosis



   Gastrointestinal  



 hemorrhagic gastric/duodenal ulcer, gastric/peptic ulcer, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, diarrhea, eructation, dry mouth, gastrointestinal bleeding, intestinal perforation, nausea, vomiting, transient elevations of hepatic enzymes, hepatitis, Reye syndrome, pancreatitis, intestinal obstruction, ileus



   Hearing and Vestibular  



 hearing loss, tinnitus. Patients with high frequency loss may have difficulty perceiving tinnitus. In these patients, tinnitus cannot be used as a clinical indicator of salicylism.



   Hematologic  



 unspecified hemorrhage, purpura, reticulocytosis, prolongation of prothrombin time, disseminated intravascular coagulation, ecchymosis, thrombocytopenia.



   Hypersensitivity  



 acute anaphylaxis, angioedema, asthma, bronchospasm, laryngeal edema, urticaria, anaphylactoid reaction



   Metabolic and Nutritional  



 hypoglycemia, hyperglycemia, acidosis, alkalosis



   Musculoskeletal  



 rhabdomyolysis



   Ocular  



 miosis, visual disturbances, red eye.



   Psychiatric  



 drug dependence, drug abuse, somnolence, depression, nervousness, hallucination



   Reproductive  



 prolonged pregnancy and labor, stillbirths, lower birth weight infants, antepartum and postpartum bleeding, closure of patent ductus arteriosis



   Respiratory System  



 bronchospasm, dyspnea, hyperpnea, pulmonary edema, tachypnea, aspiration, hypoventilation, laryngeal edema



   Skin and Appendages  



 urticaria, rash, flushing



   Urogenital  



 interstitial nephritis, papillary necrosis, proteinuria, renal insufficiency and failure, urinary retention
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
