<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="enoxaparin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;1%) were bleeding, anemia, thrombocytopenia, elevation of serum aminotransferase, diarrhea, and nausea (  6.1  )



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi-aventis at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  The following serious adverse reactions are also discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Spinal/epidural hematoma [see   Boxed Warning   and   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Increased Risk of Hemorrhage [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Thrombocytopenia [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.
 

 During clinical development for the approved indications, 15,918 patients were exposed to enoxaparin sodium. These included 1,228 for prophylaxis of deep vein thrombosis following abdominal surgery in patients at risk for thromboembolic complications, 1,368 for prophylaxis of deep vein thrombosis following hip or knee replacement surgery, 711 for prophylaxis of deep vein thrombosis in medical patients with severely restricted mobility during acute illness, 1,578 for prophylaxis of ischemic complications in unstable angina and non-Q-wave myocardial infarction, 10,176 for treatment of acute ST-elevation myocardial infarction, and 857 for treatment of deep vein thrombosis with or without pulmonary embolism. Enoxaparin sodium doses in the clinical trials for prophylaxis of deep vein thrombosis following abdominal or hip or knee replacement surgery or in medical patients with severely restricted mobility during acute illness ranged from 40 mg SC once daily to 30 mg SC twice daily. In the clinical studies for prophylaxis of ischemic complications of unstable angina and non-Q-wave myocardial infarction doses were 1 mg/kg every 12 hours and in the clinical studies for treatment of acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction enoxaparin sodium doses were a 30 mg IV bolus followed by 1 mg/kg every 12 hours SC.



   

    Hemorrhage  



 The incidence of major hemorrhagic complications during enoxaparin sodium treatment has been low.



 The following rates of major bleeding events have been reported during clinical trials with enoxaparin sodium [see Tables 2 to 7].



 Table 2 Major Bleeding Episodes Following Abdominal and Colorectal SurgeryBleeding complications were considered major: (1) if the hemorrhage caused a significant clinical event, or (2) if accompanied by a hemoglobin decrease &gt;= 2 g/dL or transfusion of 2 or more units of blood products. Retroperitoneal, intraocular, and intracranial hemorrhages were always considered major. 
                                              Dosing Regimen             
 Indications                           Enoxaparin Sodium  40 mg q.d. SC        Heparin  5000 U q8h SC        
  
   Abdominal Surgery                          n = 55523 (4%)                     n = 56016 (3%)             
   Colorectal Surgery                         n = 67328 (4%)                     n = 67421 (3%)             
        Table 3 Major Bleeding Episodes Following Hip or Knee Replacement SurgeryBleeding complications were considered major: (1) if the hemorrhage caused a significant clinical event, or (2) if accompanied by a hemoglobin decrease &gt;= 2 g/dL or transfusion of 2 or more units of blood products. Retroperitoneal and intracranial hemorrhages were always considered major. In the knee replacement surgery trials, intraocular hemorrhages were also considered major hemorrhages. 
                                         Dosing Regimen       
 Indications                           Enoxaparin Sodium  40 mg q.d. SC    Enoxaparin Sodium  30 mg q12h SC    Heparin  15,000 U/24h SC   
  
   Hip Replacement Surgery without Extended Prophylaxis                                n = 78631 (4%)          n = 54132 (6%)       
   Hip Replacement Surgery with Extended Prophylaxis                                                                             
 Peri-operative Period                   n = 2884 (2%)                                                        
 Extended Prophylaxis Period             n = 2210 (0%)                                                        
   Knee Replacement Surgery without Extended Prophylaxis                                n = 2943 (1%)           n = 2253 (1%)        
          NOTE: At no time point were the 40 mg once a day pre-operative and the 30 mg every 12 hours post-operative hip replacement surgery prophylactic regimens compared in clinical trials.
 

 Injection site hematomas during the extended prophylaxis period after hip replacement surgery occurred in 9% of the enoxaparin patients versus 1.8% of the placebo patients.



 Table 4 Major Bleeding Episodes in Medical Patients with Severely Restricted Mobility During Acute IllnessBleeding complications were considered major: (1) if the hemorrhage caused a significant clinical event, (2) if the hemorrhage caused a decrease in hemoglobin of &gt;= 2 g/dL or transfusion of 2 or more units of blood products. Retroperitoneal and intracranial hemorrhages were always considered major although none were reported during the trial. 
 Indications                     Dosing Regimen         
   Enoxaparin Sodium  20 mg q.d. SC    Enoxaparin Sodium  40 mg q.d. SC           Placebo            
  
   Medical Patients During Acute Illness         n = 3511 (&lt;1%)             n = 3603 (&lt;1%)             n = 3622 (&lt;1%)         
         Table 5 Major Bleeding Episodes in Deep Vein Thrombosis with or without Pulmonary Embolism Treatment Bleeding complications were considered major: (1) if the hemorrhage caused a significant clinical event, or (2) if accompanied by a hemoglobin decrease &gt;= 2 g/dL or transfusion of 2 or more units of blood products. Retroperitoneal, intraocular, and intracranial hemorrhages were always considered major. 
                                 Dosing Regimen         
 Indication                   Enoxaparin Sodium  1.5 mg/kg q.d. SC    Enoxaparin Sodium  1 mg/kg q12h SC    Heparin  aPTT Adjusted IV Therapy   
  
   Treatment of DVT and PE          n = 2985 (2%)              n = 5599 (2%)              n = 5549 (2%)         
         Table 6 Major Bleeding Episodes in Unstable Angina and Non-Q-Wave Myocardial Infarction 
 Indication                                   Dosing Regimen             
   Enoxaparin Sodium  1 mg/kg q12h SC    Heparin  aPTT Adjusted IV Therapy   
  
   Unstable Angina and Non-Q-Wave MI  ,               n = 157817 (1%)                     n = 152918 (1%)            
        Table 7 Major Bleeding Episodes in Acute ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction 
                                              Dosing Regimen             
 Indication                            Enoxaparin Sodium  Initial 30 mg IV bolus followed by 1 mg/kg q12h SC    Heparin  aPTT Adjusted IV Therapy   
  
   Acute ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction             n = 10176n (%)                     n = 10151n (%)             
 - Major bleeding (including ICH)                211 (2.1)                          138 (1.4)               
 - Intracranial hemorrhages (ICH)                84 (0.8)                           66 (0.7)                
           
     Elevations of Serum Aminotransferases  



 Asymptomatic increases in aspartate (AST [SGOT]) and alanine (ALT [SGPT]) aminotransferase levels greater than three times the upper limit of normal of the laboratory reference range have been reported in up to 6.1% and 5.9% of patients, respectively, during treatment with enoxaparin sodium. Similar significant increases in aminotransferase levels have also been observed in patients and healthy volunteers treated with heparin and other low molecular weight heparins. Such elevations are fully reversible and are rarely associated with increases in bilirubin.



 Since aminotransferase determinations are important in the differential diagnosis of myocardial infarction, liver disease, and pulmonary emboli, elevations that might be caused by drugs like enoxaparin sodium should be interpreted with caution.



   

    Local Reactions  



 Mild local irritation, pain, hematoma, ecchymosis, and erythema may follow SC injection of enoxaparin sodium.



   

    Adverse Reactions in Patients Receiving Enoxaparin Sodium for Prophylaxis or Treatment of DVT, PE:  



 Other adverse reactions that were thought to be possibly or probably related to treatment with enoxaparin sodium, heparin, or placebo in clinical trials with patients undergoing hip or knee replacement surgery, abdominal or colorectal surgery, or treatment for DVT and that occurred at a rate of at least 2% in the enoxaparin group, are provided below [see Tables 8 to 11].



 Table 8 Adverse Reactions Occurring at &gt;=2% Incidence in Enoxaparin-Treated Patients Undergoing Abdominal or Colorectal Surgery 
 Adverse Reaction                 Dosing Regimen     
   Enoxaparin Sodium  40 mg q.d. SCn = 1228%    Heparin  5000 U q8h SCn = 1234%   
 Severe                                Total             Severe              Total         
  
 Hemorrhage                             &lt;1                  7                 &lt;1                  6           
 Anemia                                 &lt;1                  3                 &lt;1                  3           
 Ecchymosis                              0                  3                  0                  3           
          Table 9 Adverse Reactions Occurring at &gt;=2% Incidence in Enoxaparin-Treated Patients Undergoing Hip or Knee Replacement Surgery 
 Adverse Reaction  Dosing Regimen   
   Enoxaparin Sodium  40 mg q.d. SC    Enoxaparin Sodium  30 mg q12h SC    Heparin  15,000 U/24h SC    Placebo  q12h SC   
 Peri-operative Periodn = 288%  Extended Prophylaxis Periodn = 131%  n = 1080%  n = 766%   n = 115%    
 Severe Total     Severe Total  Severe Total  Severe Total  Severe Total   
  
 Fever                0          8          0          0         &lt;1         5         &lt;1        4         0         3       
 Hemorrhage          &lt;1         13          0          5         &lt;1         4         1         4         0         3       
 Nausea                                                          &lt;1         3         &lt;1        2         0         2       
 Anemia               0         16          0         &lt;2         &lt;1         2         2         5         &lt;1        7       
 Edema                                                           &lt;1         2         &lt;1        2         0         2       
 Peripheral edema      0          6          0          0         &lt;1         3         &lt;1        4         0         3       
                Table 10 Adverse Reactions Occurring at &gt;=2% Incidence in Enoxaparin-Treated Medical Patients with Severely Restricted Mobility During Acute Illness 
 Adverse Reaction                             Dosing Regimen             
   Enoxaparin Sodium  40 mg q.d. SCn = 360%       Placebo  q.d. SCn = 362%       
  
 Dyspnea                                            3.3                                5.2                  
 Thrombocytopenia                                   2.8                                2.8                  
 Confusion                                          2.2                                1.1                  
 Diarrhea                                           2.2                                1.7                  
 Nausea                                             2.5                                1.7                  
        Table 11 Adverse Reactions Occurring at &gt;=2% Incidence in Enoxaparin-Treated Patients Undergoing Treatment of Deep Vein Thrombosis with or without Pulmonary Embolism 
 Adverse Reaction           Dosing Regimen   
   Enoxaparin Sodium  1.5 mg/kg q.d. SCn = 298%    Enoxaparin Sodium  1 mg/kg q12h SCn = 559%    Heparin  aPTT Adjusted IV Therapyn = 544%   
 Severe                        Total         Severe        Total         Severe        Total       
  
 Injection Site Hemorrhage       0             5             0             3             &lt;1            &lt;1        
 Injection Site Pain             0             2             0             2             0             0         
 Hematuria                       0             2             0             &lt;1            &lt;1            2         
               
     Adverse Events in Enoxaparin-Treated Patients with Unstable Angina or Non-Q-Wave Myocardial Infarction:  



 Non-hemorrhagic clinical events reported to be related to enoxaparin sodium therapy occurred at an incidence of &lt;=1%.



 Non-major hemorrhagic events, primarily injection site ecchymoses and hematomas, were more frequently reported in patients treated with SC enoxaparin sodium than in patients treated with IV heparin.



 Serious adverse events with enoxaparin sodium or heparin in a clinical trial in patients with unstable angina or non-Q-wave myocardial infarction that occurred at a rate of at least 0.5% in the enoxaparin group are provided below [see  Table 12  ].



 Table 12 Serious Adverse Events Occurring at &gt;=0.5% Incidence in Enoxaparin-Treated Patients with Unstable Angina or Non-Q-Wave Myocardial Infarction 
 Adverse Event                                Dosing Regimen             
   Enoxaparin Sodium  1 mg/kg q12h SCn = 1578n (%)    Heparin  aPTT Adjusted IV Therapyn = 1529n (%)   
  
 Atrial fibrillation                            11 (0.70)                           3 (0.20)                
 Heart failure                                  15 (0.95)                           11 (0.72)               
 Lung edema                                     11 (0.70)                           11 (0.72)               
 Pneumonia                                      13 (0.82)                           9 (0.59)                
           
     Adverse Reactions in Enoxaparin-Treated Patients with Acute ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction:  



 In a clinical trial in patients with acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction, the only adverse reaction that occurred at a rate of at least 0.5% in the enoxaparin group was thrombocytopenia (1.5%).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of enoxaparin sodium. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 There have been reports of epidural or spinal hematoma formation with concurrent use of enoxaparin sodium and spinal/epidural anesthesia or spinal puncture. The majority of patients had a post-operative indwelling epidural catheter placed for analgesia or received additional drugs affecting hemostasis such as NSAIDs. Many of the epidural or spinal hematomas caused neurologic injury, including long-term or permanent paralysis.



 Local reactions at the injection site (  e.g.  nodules, inflammation, oozing), systemic allergic reactions (  e.g.  pruritus, urticaria  ,  anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions including shock), vesiculobullous rash, rare cases of hypersensitivity cutaneous vasculitis, purpura, skin necrosis (occurring at either the injection site or distant from the injection site), thrombocytosis, and thrombocytopenia with thrombosis [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ] have been reported.



 Cases of hyperkalemia have been reported. Most of these reports occurred in patients who also had conditions that tend toward the development of hyperkalemia (  e.g.,  renal dysfunction, concomitant potassium-sparing drugs, administration of potassium, hematoma in body tissues). Very rare cases of hyperlipidemia have also been reported, with one case of hyperlipidemia, with marked hypertriglyceridemia, reported in a diabetic pregnant woman; causality has not been determined.



 Cases of headache, hemorrhagic anemia, eosinophilia, alopecia, hepatocellular and cholestatic liver injury have been reported. Osteoporosis has also been reported following long-term therapy.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMAS

    WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMAS  

    Epidural or spinal hematomas may occur in patients who are anticoagulated with low molecular weight heparins (LMWH) or heparinoids and are receiving neuraxial anesthesia or undergoing spinal puncture. These hematomas may result in long-term or permanent paralysis. Consider these risks when scheduling patients for spinal procedures. Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include:  



 *  Use of indwelling epidural catheters 
 *  Concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, other anticoagulants. 
 *  A history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal punctures 
 *  A history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery 
 *  Optimal timing between the administration of enoxaparin sodium and neuraxial procedures is not known. 
        Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurological impairment. If neurological compromise is noted, urgent treatment is necessary.    
 

     Consider the benefits and risks before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or to be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)     and     Drug Interactions (7)    ].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMA



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Epidural or spinal hematomas may occur in patients who are anticoagulated with low molecular weight heparins (LMWH) or heparinoids and are receiving neuraxial anesthesia or undergoing spinal puncture. These hematomas may result in long-term or permanent paralysis. Consider these risks when scheduling patients for spinal procedures. Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include:  



 *  Use of indwelling epidural catheters 
 *  Concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, other anticoagulants 
 *  A history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal punctures 
 *  A history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery 
 *  Optimal timing between the administration of enoxaparin sodium and neuraxial procedures is not known. 
      Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurological impairment. If neurological compromise is noted, urgent treatment is necessary[see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)     and     Drug Interactions (7)    ].  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Increased risk of hemorrhage: Use with caution in patients at risk (  5.1  ) 
 *  Percutaneous coronary revascularization: Obtain hemostasis at the puncture site before sheath removal (  5.2  ) 
 *  Concomitant medical conditions: Use with caution in patients with bleeding diathesis, uncontrolled arterial hypertension or history of recent gastrointestinal ulceration, diabetic retinopathy, renal dysfunction, or hemorrhage (  5.3  ) 
 *  History of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia: Use with caution (  5.4  ) 
 *  Thrombocytopenia: Monitor thrombocytopenia closely (  5.5  ) 
 *  Interchangeability with other heparins: Do not exchange with heparin or other LMWHs (  5.6  ) 
 *  Pregnant women with mechanical prosthetic heart valves and their fetuses, may be at increased risk and may need more frequent monitoring and dosage adjustment (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Risk of Hemorrhage



   Cases of epidural or spinal hemorrhage and subsequent hematomas have been reported with the use of enoxaparin sodium and epidural or spinal anesthesia/analgesia or spinal puncture procedures, resulting in long-term or permanent paralysis. The risk of these events is higher with the use of post-operative indwelling epidural catheters, with the concomitant use of additional drugs affecting hemostasis such as NSAIDs, with traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal puncture, or in patients with a history of spinal surgery or spinal deformity [see   Boxed Warning  ,  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    and   Drug Interactions (7)    ].  



  To reduce the potential risk of bleeding associated with the concurrent use of enoxaparin sodium and epidural or spinal anesthesia/analgesia or spinal puncture, consider the pharmacokinetic profile of enoxaparin [see   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ]. Placement or removal of an epidural catheter or lumbar puncture is best performed when the anticoagulant effect of enoxaparin is low; however, the exact timing to reach a sufficiently low anticoagulant effect in each patient is not known.  



  Placement or removal of a catheter should be delayed for at least 12 hours after administration of lower doses (30 mg once or twice daily or 40 mg once daily) of enoxaparin sodium and at least 24 hours after the administration of higher doses (0.75 mg/kg twice daily, 1 mg/kg twice daily, or 1.5 mg/kg once daily) of enoxaparin sodium. Anti-Xa levels are still detectable at these time points, and these delays are not a guarantee that neuraxial hematoma will be avoided. Patients receiving the 0.75 mg/kg twice daily dose or the1mg/kg twice daily dose should not receive the second enoxaparin sodium dose in the twice daily regimen to allow a longer delay before catheter placement or removal. Likewise, although a specific recommendation for timing of a subsequent enoxaparin sodium dose after catheter removal cannot be made, consider delaying this next dose for at least four hours, based on a benefit-risk assessment considering both the risk for thrombosis and the risk for bleeding in the context of the procedure and patient risk factors. For patients with creatinine clearance &lt;30mL/minute, additional considerations are necessary because elimination of enoxaparin is more prolonged; consider doubling the timing of removal of a catheter, at least 24 hours for the lower prescribed dose of enoxaparin sodium (30 mg once daily) and at least 48 hours for the higher dose (1 mg/kg/day) [see   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].  



  Should the physician decide to administer anticoagulation in the context of epidural or spinal anesthesia/analgesia or lumbar puncture, frequent monitoring must be exercised to detect any signs and symptoms of neurological impairment such as midline back pain, sensory and motor deficits (numbness or weakness in lower limbs), bowel and/or bladder dysfunction. Instruct patients to report immediately if they experience any of the above signs or symptoms. If signs or symptoms of spinal hematoma are suspected, initiate urgent diagnosis and treatment including consideration for spinal cord decompression even though such treatment may not prevent or reverse neurological sequelae.  



 Enoxaparin sodium should be used with extreme caution in conditions with increased risk of hemorrhage, such as bacterial endocarditis, congenital or acquired bleeding disorders, active ulcerative and angiodysplastic gastrointestinal disease, hemorrhagic stroke, or shortly after brain, spinal, or ophthalmological surgery, or in patients treated concomitantly with platelet inhibitors.



 Major hemorrhages including retroperitoneal and intracranial bleeding have been reported. Some of these cases have been fatal.



 Bleeding can occur at any site during therapy with enoxaparin sodium. An unexplained fall in hematocrit or blood pressure should lead to a search for a bleeding site.



    5.2 Percutaneous Coronary Revascularization Procedures



  To minimize the risk of bleeding following the vascular instrumentation during the treatment of unstable angina, non-Q-wave myocardial infarction and acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction, adhere precisely to the intervals recommended between enoxaparin sodium doses. It is important to achieve hemostasis at the puncture site after PCI. In case a closure device is used, the sheath can be removed immediately. If a manual compression method is used, sheath should be removed 6 hours after the last IV/SC enoxaparin sodium. If the treatment with enoxaparin sodium is to be continued, the next scheduled dose should be given no sooner than 6 to 8 hours after sheath removal. The site of the procedure should be observed for signs of bleeding or hematoma formation [see   Dosage and Administration (2.1)    ].



    5.3 Use of Enoxaparin sodium with Concomitant Medical Conditions



  Enoxaparin sodium should be used with care in patients with a bleeding diathesis, uncontrolled arterial hypertension or a history of recent gastrointestinal ulceration, diabetic retinopathy, renal dysfunction and hemorrhage.



    5.4 History of Heparin-Induced Thrombocytopenia



  Enoxaparin sodium should be used with extreme caution in patients with a history of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia.



    5.5 Thrombocytopenia



  Thrombocytopenia can occur with the administration of enoxaparin sodium.



 Moderate thrombocytopenia (platelet counts between 100,000/mm  3  and 50,000/mm  3  ) occurred at a rate of 1.3% in patients given enoxaparin sodium, 1.2% in patients given heparin, and 0.7% in patients given placebo in clinical trials.



 Platelet counts less than 50,000/mm  3  occurred at a rate of 0.1% in patients given enoxaparin sodium, in 0.2% of patients given heparin, and 0.4% of patients given placebo in the same trials.



 Thrombocytopenia of any degree should be monitored closely. If the platelet count falls below 100,000/mm  3  , enoxaparin sodium should be discontinued. Cases of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia with thrombosis have also been observed in clinical practice. Some of these cases were complicated by organ infarction, limb ischemia, or death [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ].



    5.6 Interchangeability with Other Heparins



  Enoxaparin sodium cannot be used interchangeably (unit for unit) with heparin or other low molecular weight heparins as they differ in manufacturing process, molecular weight distribution, anti-Xa and anti-IIa activities, units, and dosage. Each of these medicines has its own instructions for use.



    5.7 Pregnant Women with Mechanical Prosthetic Heart Valves



  The use of enoxaparin sodium for thromboprophylaxis in pregnant women with mechanical prosthetic heart valves has not been adequately studied. In a clinical study of pregnant women with mechanical prosthetic heart valves given enoxaparin (1 mg/kg twice daily) to reduce the risk of thromboembolism, 2 of 8 women developed clots resulting in blockage of the valve and leading to maternal and fetal death. Although a causal relationship has not been established these deaths may have been due to therapeutic failure or inadequate anticoagulation. No patients in the heparin/warfarin group (0 of 4 women) died. There also have been isolated postmarketing reports of valve thrombosis in pregnant women with mechanical prosthetic heart valves while receiving enoxaparin for thromboprophylaxis. Women with mechanical prosthetic heart valves may be at higher risk for thromboembolism during pregnancy, and, when pregnant, have a higher rate of fetal loss from stillbirth, spontaneous abortion and premature delivery. Therefore, frequent monitoring of peak and trough anti-Factor Xa levels, and adjusting of dosage may be needed [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.6)    ].



    5.8 Benzyl Alcohol



  Enoxaparin sodium multiple-dose vials contain benzyl alcohol as a preservative. The administration of medications containing benzyl alcohol as a preservative to premature neonates has been associated with a fatal "gasping syndrome". Because benzyl alcohol may cross the placenta, enoxaparin sodium multiple-dose vials, preserved with benzyl alcohol, should be used with caution in pregnant women and only if clearly needed [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].



    5.9 Laboratory Tests



  Periodic complete blood counts, including platelet count, and stool occult blood tests are recommended during the course of treatment with enoxaparin sodium. When administered at recommended prophylaxis doses, routine coagulation tests such as Prothrombin Time (PT) and Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) are relatively insensitive measures of enoxaparin activity and, therefore, unsuitable for monitoring. Anti-Factor Xa may be used to monitor the anticoagulant effect of enoxaparin sodium in patients with significant renal impairment. If during enoxaparin sodium therapy abnormal coagulation parameters or bleeding should occur, anti-Factor Xa levels may be used to monitor the anticoagulant effects of enoxaparin sodium [see   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
