<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="enstilar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions reported in &lt; 1% of subjects included application site irritation, application site pruritus, folliculitis, skin hypopigmentation, hypercalcemia, urticaria, and exacerabation of psoriasis. (  6.1  )



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact LEO Pharma Inc. at 1-877-494-4536 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/ medwatch.  



 



 



 



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The rates of adverse reactions given below were derived from three randomized, multicenter, prospective vehicle and/or active-controlled clinical trials in subjects with plaque psoriasis. Subjects applied study product once daily for 4 weeks, and the median weekly dose of Enstilar  (r)  Foam was 24.8 g.



 Adverse reactions reported in &lt;1% of subjects treated with Enstilar  (r)  Foam included: application site irritation, application site pruritus, folliculitis, skin hypopigmentation, hypercalcemia, urticaria, and exacerbation of psoriasis.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because adverse reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Postmarketing reports for local adverse reactions to topical steroids include atrophy, striae, telangiectasia, dryness, perioral dermatitis, secondary infection and miliaria.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  The propellants in Enstilar  (r)   Foam are flammable. Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame, and smoking during and immediately following application.  (5.1)   
 *  Hypercalcemia and hypercalciuria have been observed with use of Enstilar  (r)  Foam. If hypercalcaemia or hypercalciuria develop, discontinue treatment until parameters of calcium metabolism have normalized.  (5.2)   
 *   Topical corticosteroids can produce reversible hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis suppression with the potential for glucocorticosteroid insufficiency during and after withdrawal of treatment. Risk factors include the use of high-potency topical corticosteroids, use over a large surface area or to areas under occlusion, prolonged use, altered skin barrier, liver failure, and use in pediatric patients. Modify use should HPA axis suppression develop. (  5.3  ,  8.4  )



 
    
 

   5.1 Flammability



  The propellants in Enstilar  (r)   Foam are flammable. Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame, and smoking during and immediately following application.



    5.2 Hypercalcemia and Hypercalciuria



  Hypercalcemia and hypercalciuria have been observed with use of Enstilar  (r)  Foam [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  . If hypercalcaemia or hypercalciuria develop, discontinue treatment until parameters of calcium metabolism have normalized. The incidence of hypercalcemia and hypercalciuria following Enstilar  (r)  Foam treatment of more than 4 weeks has not been evaluated.



    5.3 Effects on Endocrine System



  Systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids can produce reversible hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis suppression with the potential for clinical glucocorticosteroid insufficiency. This may occur during treatment or upon withdrawal of the topical corticosteroid. Factors that predispose a patient to HPA axis suppression include the use of high-potency steroids, large treatment surface areas, prolonged use, use of occlusive dressings, altered skin barrier, liver failure, and young age. Evaluation for HPA axis suppression may be done by using the adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) stimulation test.



 If HPA axis suppression is documented, gradually withdraw the drug, reduce the frequency of application, or substitute with a less potent corticosteroid.



 Systemic effects of topical corticosteroids may also include Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and glucosuria.



 Pediatric patients may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity due to their larger skin surface to body mass ratios [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.3  )]  .



 Use of more than one corticosteroid-containing product at the same time may increase total systemic corticosteroid exposure.



    5.4 Allergic Contact Dermatitis



  Allergic contact dermatitis has been observed with topical calcipotriene and topical corticosteroids. Allergic contact dermatitis to a topical corticosteroid is usually diagnosed by observing a failure to heal rather than a clinical exacerbation. Corroborate such an observation with appropriate diagnostic patch testing.



    5.5 Risks of Ultraviolet Light Exposures



  Patients who apply Enstilar  (r)  Foam to exposed skin should avoid excessive exposure to either natural or artificial sunlight, including tanning booths, sun lamps, etc.



 Physicians may wish to limit or avoid use of phototherapy in patients who use Enstilar  (r)  Foam.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
