<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="entocort" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following clinically significant adverse reactions are described elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Hypercorticism and adrenal axis suppression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Symptoms of steroid withdrawal in those patients transferred from other systemic corticosteroids [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Increased risk of infection [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Other corticosteroid effects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) in adults are: headache, respiratory infection, nausea, back pain, dyspepsia, dizziness, abdominal pain, flatulence, vomiting, fatigue, and pain. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Perrigo at 1-866-634-9120 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adults  



 The data described below reflect exposure to ENTOCORT EC in 520 patients with Crohn's disease, including 520 exposed to 9 mg per day (total daily dose) for 8 weeks and 145 exposed to 6 mg per day for one year in placebo controlled clinical trials. Of the 520 patients, 38% were males and the age range was 17 to 74 years.



     Treatment of Mild to Moderate Active Crohn's Disease  



 The safety of ENTOCORT EC was evaluated in 651 adult patients in five clinical trials of 8 weeks duration in patients with active mild to moderate Crohn's disease. The most common adverse reactions, occurring in greater than or equal to 5% of the patients, are listed in Table 1.



 Table 1: Common Adverse ReactionsOccurring in greater than or equal to 5% of the patients in any treated group. in 8-Week Treatment Clinical Trials 
 Adverse Reaction          ENTOCORT EC9 mgn=520Number (%)  Placebon=107Number (%)  Prednisolone40 mgn=145Number (%)  Comparatorn=88Number (%)   
  
 Headache                        107(21)              19(18)               31(21)               11(13)          
 Respiratory Infection           55 (11)               7(7)                20(14)                5(6)           
 Nausea                          57(11)                10(9)               18(12)                7(8)           
 Back Pain                        36(7)                10(9)               17(12)                5(6)           
 Dyspepsia                        31(6)                4(4)                17(12)                3(3)           
 Dizziness                        38(7)                5(5)                18(12)                5(6)           
 Abdominal Pain                   32(6)               18(17)                6(4)                10(11)          
 Flatulence                       30(6)                6(6)                 12(8)                5(6)           
 Vomiting                         29(6)                6(6)                 6(4)                 6(7)           
 Fatigue                          25(5)                8(7)                 11(8)                0(0)           
 Pain                             24(5)                8(7)                17(12)                2(2)           
           The incidence of signs and symptoms of hypercorticism reported by active questioning of patients in 4 of the 5 short-term clinical trials are displayed in Table 2.
 

 Table 2: Summary and Incidence of Signs/Symptoms of Hypercorticism in 8-Week Treatment Clinical Trials 
 Signs/Symptom              ENTOCORT EC9 mgn=427Number (%)   Placebon=107Number (%)    Prednisolone40 mgn=145Number (%)   
  
 Total                              145 (34%)                  29 (27%)                   69 (48%)            
 Acne                                63 (15)                    14 (13)                    33 (23)            
 Bruising Easily                     63 (15)                    12 (11)                    13 (9)             
 Moon Face                           46 (11)                     4 (4)                     53 (37)            
 Swollen Ankles                      32 (7)                      6 (6)                     13 (9)             
 Hirsutism                           22 (5)                      2 (2)                      5 (3)             
 Buffalo Hump                         6 (1)                      2 (2)                      5 (3)             
 Skin Striae                          4 (1)                      2 (2)                      0 (0)             
              Maintenance of Clinical Remission of Mild to Moderate Crohn's Disease  
 

 The safety of ENTOCORT EC was evaluated in 233 adult patients in four long-term clinical trials (52 weeks) of maintenance of clinical remission in patients with mild to moderate Crohn's disease. A total of 145 patients were treated with ENTOCORT EC 6 mg once daily.



 The adverse reaction profile of ENTOCORT EC 6 mg once daily in maintenance of Crohn's disease was similar to that of short-term treatment with ENTOCORT EC 9 mg once daily in active Crohn's disease. In the long-term clinical trials, the following adverse reactions occurred in greater than or equal to 5% and are not listed in Table 1: diarrhea (10%); sinusitis (8%); infection viral (6%); and arthralgia (5%).



 Signs/symptoms of hypercorticism reported by active questioning of patients in the long-term maintenance clinical trials are displayed in Table 3.



 Table 3: Summary and Incidence of Signs/Symptoms of Hypercorticism in Long-Term Clinical Trials 
 Signs/Symptom              ENTOCORT EC3 mgn=88Number (%)  ENTOCORT EC6 mgn=145Number (%)   Placebon=143Number (%)     
  
 Bruising easily                      4(5)                      15(10)                      5(4)              
 Acne                                 4(5)                      14(10)                      3(2)              
 Moon face                            3(3)                       6(4)                         0               
 Hirsutism                            2(2)                       5(3)                       1(1)              
 Swollen ankles                       2(2)                       3(2)                       3(2)              
 Buffalo hump                         1(1)                       1(1)                         0               
 Skin striae                          2(2)                         0                          0               
          The incidence of signs/symptoms of hypercorticism as described above in long-term maintenance clinical trials was similar to that seen in the short-term treatment clinical trials.
 

     Less Common Adverse Reactions in Treatment and Maintenance Clinical Trials  



 Less common adverse reactions (less than 5%), occurring in adult patients treated with ENTOCORT EC 9 mg (total daily dose) in short-term treatment clinical studies and/or ENTOCORT EC 6 mg (total daily dose) in long-term maintenance clinical trials, with an incidence are listed below by system organ class:



   Cardiac disorders:  palpitation, tachycardia



   Eye disorders:  eye abnormality, vision abnormal



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  asthenia, chest pain, dependent edema, face edema, flu-like disorder, malaise, fever



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  anus disorder, enteritis, epigastric pain, gastrointestinal fistula, glossitis, hemorrhoids, intestinal obstruction, tongue edema, tooth disorder



   Infections and infestations:  Ear infection - not otherwise specified, bronchitis, abscess, rhinitis, urinary tract infection, thrush



   Investigations:  weight increased



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  appetite increased



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  arthritis, cramps, myalgia



   Nervous system disorders:  hyperkinesia, parasthesia, tremor, vertigo, somnolence, amnesia



   Psychiatric disorders:  agitation, confusion, insomnia, nervousness, sleep disorder



   Renal and urinary disorders:  dysuria, micturition frequency, nocturia



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  intermenstrual bleeding, menstrual disorder



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  dyspnea, pharynx disorder



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  alopecia, dermatitis, eczema, skin disorder, sweating increased, purpura



   Vascular disorders:  flushing, hypertension



     Bone Mineral Density  



 A randomized, open, parallel-group multicenter safety clinical trial specifically compared the effect of ENTOCORT EC (less than 9 mg per day) and prednisolone (less than 40 mg per day) on bone mineral density over 2 years when used at doses adjusted to disease severity. Bone mineral density decreased significantly less with ENTOCORT EC than with prednisolone in steroid-naive patients, whereas no difference could be detected between treatment groups for steroid-dependent patients and previous steroid users. The incidence of symptoms associated with hypercorticism was significantly higher with prednisolone treatment.



     Clinical Laboratory Test Findings  



 The following potentially clinically significant laboratory changes in clinical trials, irrespective of relationship to ENTOCORT EC, were reported in greater than or equal to 1% of patients: hypokalemia, leukocytosis, anemia, hematuria, pyuria, erythrocyte sedimentation rate increased, alkaline phosphatase increased, atypical neutrophils, c-reactive protein increased and adrenal insufficiency.



     Pediatrics -- Treatment of Mild to Moderate Active Crohn's Disease  



 Adverse reactions reported in pediatric patients 8 to 17 years of age, who weigh more than 25 kg, were similar to those reactions described above in adult patients.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of ENTOCORT EC. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Immune System Disorders:  Anaphylactic reactions



   Nervous System Disorders:  Benign intracranial hypertension



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Mood swings
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hypercorticism and Adrenal Axis Suppression: Follow general warnings concerning corticosteroids; pediatrics and patients with hepatic impairment may be at increased risk. (  2.4  ,  5.1  ,  8.4  ,  8.6  ) 
 *   Symptoms of Steroid Withdrawal in Patients Transferred from Other Systemic Corticosteroids: Taper slowly from corticosteroids with high systemic effects; monitor for withdrawal symptoms and unmasking of allergies (rhinitis, eczema). (  5.2  ) 
 *   Increased Risk of Infection, including Serious and Fatal Chicken Pox and Measles: Monitor patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection, untreated fungal, bacterial, systemic viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Other Corticosteroid Effects: Monitor patients with concomitant conditions where corticosteroids may have unwanted effects (e.g., hypertension, diabetes mellitus). (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypercorticism and Adrenal Axis Suppression



  When corticosteroids are used chronically, systemic effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal axis suppression may occur. Corticosteroids can reduce the response of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis to stress. In situations where patients are subject to surgery or other stress situations, supplementation with a systemic corticosteroid is recommended. Since ENTOCORT EC contains a corticosteroid, general warnings concerning corticosteroids should be followed [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ,  (5.3)  ,  (5.4)  ]  .



  Pediatric patients with Crohn's disease have a slightly higher systemic exposure of budesonide and increased cortisol suppression than adults with Crohn's disease [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  . Patients with moderate to severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B and C respectively) could be at an increased risk of hypercorticism and adrenal axis suppression due to an increased systemic exposure of oral budesonide. Avoid use in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C). Monitor for increased signs and/or symptoms of hypercorticism and consider reducing the dosage in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B) [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .  



    5.2 Symptoms of Steroid Withdrawal in Patients Transferred from Other Systemic Corticosteroids



  Monitor patients who are transferred from corticosteroid treatment with high systemic effects to corticosteroids with lower systemic availability, such as ENTOCORT EC, since symptoms attributed to withdrawal of steroid therapy, including those of acute adrenal axis suppression or benign intracranial hypertension, may develop. Adrenocortical function monitoring may be required in these patients and the dose of corticosteroid treatment with high systemic effects should be reduced cautiously.



 Replacement of systemic corticosteroids with ENTOCORT EC may unmask allergies (e.g., rhinitis and eczema), which were previously controlled by the systemic drug.



    5.3 Increased Risk of Infection



  Patients who are on drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infection than healthy individuals. Chicken pox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible patients or patients on immunosuppressant doses of corticosteroids. In patients who have not had these diseases, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure.



 How the dose, route and duration of corticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If exposed, therapy with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG), as appropriate, may be indicated. If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See prescribing information for VZIG and IG). If chicken pox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.



 Corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection, untreated fungal, bacterial, systemic viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex.



    5.4 Other Corticosteroid Effects



  Monitor patients with hypertension, diabetes mellitus, osteoporosis, peptic ulcer, glaucoma or cataracts, or with a family history of diabetes or glaucoma, or with any other condition where corticosteroids may have unwanted effects.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
