<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="entresto" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  Clinically significant adverse reactions that appear in other sections of the labeling include:



 *  Angioedema [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *  Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *  Impaired Renal Function [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *  Hyperkalemia [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions occurring &gt;=5% are hypotension, hyperkalemia, cough, dizziness, and renal failure. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In the PARADIGM-HF trial, subjects were required to complete sequential enalapril and ENTRESTO run-in periods of (median) 15 and 29 days, respectively, prior to entering the randomized double-blind period comparing ENTRESTO and enalapril. During the enalapril run-in period, 1,102 patients (10.5%) were permanently discontinued from the study, 5.6% because of an adverse event, most commonly renal dysfunction (1.7%), hyperkalemia (1.7%) and hypotension (1.4%). During the ENTRESTO run-in period, an additional 10.4% of patients permanently discontinued treatment, 5.9% because of an adverse event, most commonly renal dysfunction (1.8%), hypotension (1.7%) and hyperkalemia (1.3%). Because of this run-in design, the adverse reaction rates described below are lower than expected in practice.



 In the double-blind period, safety was evaluated in 4,203 patients treated with ENTRESTO and 4,229 treated with enalapril. In PARADIGM-HF, patients randomized to ENTRESTO received treatment for up to 4.3 years, with a median duration of exposure of 24 months; 3,271 patients were treated for more than one year. Discontinuation of therapy because of an adverse event during the double-blind period occurred in 450 (10.7%) of ENTRESTO treated patients and 516 (12.2%) of patients receiving enalapril.



 Adverse reactions occurring at an incidence of &gt;=5% in patients who were treated with ENTRESTO in the double-blind period are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients Treated with ENTRESTO in the Double-Blind Period 
                    ENTRESTO(n = 4,203)%      Enalapril(n = 4,229)%     
 Hypotension      18               12                
 Hyperkalemia     12               14                
 Cough            9                13                
 Dizziness        6                5                 
 Renal failure/acute renal failure  5                5                 
         In the PARADIGM-HF trial, the incidence of angioedema was 0.1% in both the enalapril and ENTRESTO run-in periods. In the double-blind period, the incidence of angioedema was higher in patients treated with ENTRESTO than enalapril (0.5% and 0.2%, respectively). The incidence of angioedema in Black patients was 2.4% with ENTRESTO and 0.5% with enalapril  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .
 

 Orthostasis was reported in 2.1% of patients treated with ENTRESTO compared to 1.1% of patients treated with enalapril during the double-blind period of PARADIGM-HF. Falls were reported in 1.9% of patients treated with ENTRESTO compared to 1.3% of patients treated with enalapril.



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



   Hemoglobin and Hematocrit  



 Decreases in hemoglobin/hematocrit of &gt;20% were observed in approximately 5% of both ENTRESTO- and enalapril-treated patients in the double-blind period in PARADIGM-HF.



   Serum Creatinine  



 Increases in serum creatinine of &gt;50% were observed in 1.4% of patients in the enalapril run-in period and 2.2% of patients in the ENTRESTO run-in period. During the double-blind period, approximately 16% of both ENTRESTO- and enalapril-treated patients had increases in serum creatinine of &gt;50%.



   Serum Potassium  



 Potassium concentrations &gt;5.5 mEq/L were observed in approximately 4% of patients in both the enalapril and ENTRESTO run-in periods. During the double-blind period, approximately 16% of both ENTRESTO- and enalapril-treated patients had potassium concentrations &gt;5.5 mEq/L.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ENTRESTO as soon as possible (5.1) 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1) 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ENTRESTO as soon as possible. (5.1) 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Observe for signs and symptoms of angioedema and hypotension. (  5.2  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  Monitor renal function and potassium in susceptible patients. (  5.4  ,  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Fetal Toxicity



  ENTRESTO can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. When pregnancy is detected, consider alternative drug treatment and discontinue ENTRESTO. However, if there is no appropriate alternative to therapy with drugs affecting the renin-angiotensin system, and if the drug is considered lifesaving for the mother, advise a pregnant woman of the potential risk to the fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  .



    5.2     Angioedema



  ENTRESTO may cause angioedema. In the double-blind period of PARADIGM-HF, 0.5% of patients treated with ENTRESTO and 0.2% of patients treated with enalapril had angioedema [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . If angioedema occurs, discontinue ENTRESTO immediately, provide appropriate therapy, and monitor for airway compromise. ENTRESTO must not be re-administered. In cases of confirmed angioedema where swelling has been confined to the face and lips, the condition has generally resolved without treatment, although antihistamines have been useful in relieving symptoms.



 Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema may be fatal. Where there is involvement of the tongue, glottis or larynx, likely to cause airway obstruction, administer appropriate therapy, e.g., subcutaneous epinephrine/adrenaline solution 1:1000 (0.3 mL to 0.5 mL) and take measures necessary to ensure maintenance of a patent airway.



 ENTRESTO has been associated with a higher rate of angioedema in Black than in non-Black patients.



 Patients with a prior history of angioedema may be at increased risk of angioedema with ENTRESTO [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . ENTRESTO should not be used in patients with a known history of angioedema related to previous ACE inhibitor or ARB therapy [see Contraindications (4)]  .



    5.3     Hypotension



  ENTRESTO lowers blood pressure and may cause symptomatic hypotension. Patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- and/or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics), are at greater risk. In the double-blind period of PARADIGM-HF, 18% of patients treated with ENTRESTO and 12% of patients treated with enalapril reported hypotension as an adverse event [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  , with hypotension reported as a serious adverse event in approximately 1.5% of patients in both treatment arms. Correct volume or salt depletion prior to administration of ENTRESTO or start at a lower dose. If hypotension occurs, consider dose adjustment of diuretics, concomitant antihypertensive drugs, and treatment of other causes of hypotension (e.g., hypovolemia). If hypotension persists despite such measures, reduce the dosage or temporarily discontinue ENTRESTO. Permanent discontinuation of therapy is usually not required.



    5.4     Impaired Renal Function



  As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS), decreases in renal function may be anticipated in susceptible individuals treated with ENTRESTO. In the double-blind period of PARADIGM-HF, 5% of patients in both the ENTRESTO and enalapril groups reported renal failure as an adverse event [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . In patients whose renal function depends upon the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with ACE inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria, progressive azotemia and, rarely, acute renal failure and death. Closely monitor serum creatinine, and down-titrate or interrupt ENTRESTO in patients who develop a clinically significant decrease in renal function [see Use in Specific Populations (8.7) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  .



 As with all drugs that affect the RAAS, ENTRESTO may increase blood urea and serum creatinine levels in patients with bilateral or unilateral renal artery stenosis. In patients with renal artery stenosis, monitor renal function.



    5.5     Hyperkalemia



  Through its actions on the RAAS, hyperkalemia may occur with ENTRESTO. In the double-blind period of PARADIGM-HF, 12% of patients treated with ENTRESTO and 14% of patients treated with enalapril reported hyperkalemia as an adverse event [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Monitor serum potassium periodically and treat appropriately, especially in patients with risk factors for hyperkalemia such as severe renal impairment, diabetes, hypoaldosteronism, or a high potassium diet. Dosage reduction or interruption of ENTRESTO may be required [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
