<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="envarsus" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=10%) include: diarrhea and blood creatinine increased (    6.1    )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Veloxis Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-844-VELOXIS (1-844-835-6947) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. In addition, the clinical studies were not designed to establish comparative differences across study arms with regards to the adverse reactions discussed below.



 In an open label, randomized, multinational conversion study, stable kidney transplant patients on a tacrolimus immediate-release product and concomitant immunosuppressants were randomized to treatment with ENVARSUS XR (N=162) or to continued treatment on the tacrolimus immediate-release product (N=162) and treated for a duration of 12 months  [see    Clinical Studies (14)    ]  .



 The proportion of patients who discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions was 7.4% and 1.2% in the ENVARSUS XR and tacrolimus immediate-release treatment groups, respectively, through 12 months of treatment. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of study drug in the ENVARSUS XR treatment group was cardiac arrest (2 events).



   Infections  



 The overall incidence of infections, serious infections, and infections with identified etiology reported in stable kidney transplant recipients treated with ENVARSUS XR or tacrolimus immediate-release product are shown in    Table 1    .



 Table 1. Percentage of Stable Patients with Infections Through One Year Post- Treatment in the Conversion Study a 
   a  The stable kidney transplant study was not designed to support comparative claims of ENVARSUS XR compared to tacrolimus immediate-release product for the adverse reactions reported in this table.   
   b  BK virus associated nephropathy (BKVAN) occurred in 1.2% (2/162) and 0.6% (1/162) in the ENVARSUS XR and tacrolimus immediate-release treatment groups, respectively.   
  
                                           ENVARSUS XR +/- steroids, MMF/MPS or AZAN=162  Tacrolimus immediate-release product +/- steroids, MMF/MPS or AZAN=162   
   All infections                          46%                             48%                              
        Respiratory Infections             26%                             28%                              
        Urinary Tract Infections           10%                             14%                              
        Bacterial Infections               7%                              5%                               
        Fungal Infections                  4%                              4%                               
        Gastrointestinal Infections        4%                              5%                               
        BK virus  b                        2%                              2%                               
        Cytomegalovirus Infections         2%                              1%                               
   Serious Infections                      8%                              9%                               
           New Onset Diabetes After Transplantation (NODAT)  
 

 New onset diabetes after transplantation (NODAT) was defined by the composite occurrence of fasting plasma glucose values &gt;=126 mg/dL, 2-hour postprandial plasma glucose of at least 200 mg/dL (in oral glucose tolerance test) on 2 or more consecutive occasions post baseline, insulin requirement for &gt;=31 days, an oral hypoglycemic agent use &gt;=31 days, or HbA1c&gt;=6.5% (at least 3 months after randomization) among kidney transplant patients with no medical history of diabetes. The incidence of NODAT for the stable kidney transplant study through one year post-transplant is summarized in    Table 2    below  [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ]  .



 Table 2. Percentage of Stable Patients with NODAT Through 1 Year Post- Treatment in the Conversion Study a 
   a  The stable kidney transplant study was not designed to support comparative claims of ENVARSUS XR compared to tacrolimus immediate-release product for the adverse reactions reported in this table.   
   b  Analyses restricted to patients at risk for NODAT   
  
                                                     ENVARSUS XR +/- steroids , MMF/MPS or AZA(N=90)  Tacrolimus immediate-release product +/- steroids, MMF/MPS or AZA(N=95)   
  Composite NODAT  b                                 10%                        11%                         
      HbA1c&gt;=6.5%                                    3%                         7%                          
      Fasting Plasma Glucose Values &gt;=126 mg/dL     on 2 consecutive occurrences  8%                         6%                          
      Oral hypoglycemic use                          1%                         1%                          
      Insulin Use &gt;=31 days                          1%                         0%                          
           Common Adverse Reactions  
 

 The incidence of adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=5% of ENVARSUS XR-treated patients compared to tacrolimus immediate-release product through one year of treatment in the conversion study is shown by treatment group in    Table 3    .



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions ( &gt;= 5%) in Stable Kidney Transplant Patients Through 1 Year Post- Treatment in the Conversion Studya 
   a  The stable kidney transplant study was not designed to support comparative claims of ENVARSUS XR compared to tacrolimus immediate-release for the adverse reactions reported in this table.   
  
  Adverse Reaction                                   ENVARSUS XRN=162           Tacrolimus immediate-release productN=162   
  Diarrhea                                           14%                        9%                          
  Blood Creatinine Increased                         12%                        9%                          
  Urinary Tract Infection                            9%                         14%                         
  Nasopharyngitis                                    9%                         11%                         
  Headache                                           9%                         7%                          
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                  7%                         9%                          
  Peripheral Edema                                   7%                         6%                          
  Hypertension                                       4%                         6%                          
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been reported from marketing experience with tacrolimus in the U.S. and outside the U.S. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Agranulocytosis, decreased blood fibrinogen, disseminated intravascular coagulation, hemolytic anemia, hemolytic uremic syndrome, pancytopenia, prolonged activated partial thromboplastin time, pure red cell aplasia [  see    Warnings and Precaution (5.12)      ], thrombocytopenic purpura, thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura



   Cardiac Disorders  : Atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, cardiac arrhythmia, cardiac arrest, electrocardiogram T wave abnormal, flushing, myocardial hypertrophy, myocardial infarction, myocardial ischaemia, pericardial effusion, QT prolongation, supraventricular extrasystoles, supraventricular tachycardia, Torsade de Pointes, deep limb venous thrombosis, ventricular fibrillation



   Ear Disorders  : Hearing loss including deafness



   Eye Disorders  : Blindness, photophobia, optic atrophy



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : Colitis, dysphagia, gastrointestinal perforation, impaired gastric emptying, intestinal obstruction, mouth ulceration, peritonitis, stomach ulcer



   Hepatobiliary Disorders  : Bile duct stenosis, cholangitis, cirrhosis, fatty liver, hepatic cytolysis, hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatic steatosis, jaundice, hemorrhagic pancreatitis, necrotizing pancreatitis, venoocclusive liver disease



   Hypersensitivity Reactions  : Hypersensitivity, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, urticaria



   Immune System Disorders  : Graft versus host disease (acute and chronic)



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  : Glycosuria, increased amylase, pancreatitis



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  : Myalgia, polyarthritis, rhabdomyolysis



   Neoplasms  : Lymphoma including EBV-associated lymphoproliferative disorder, PTLD [  see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)      ]; leukemia



   Nervous System Disorders  : Carpal tunnel syndrome, cerebral infarction, coma, dysarthria, flaccid paralysis, hemiparesis, mental disorder, mutism, nerve compression, posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES) [  see    Warnings and Precautions (5.6)      ], progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML) sometimes fatal [  see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)      ], quadriplegia, speech disorder, status epilepticus, syncope



   Renal and Urinary Disorder:  Acute renal failure, hemorrhagic cystitis, hemolytic uremic syndrome, micturition disorder



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  : Acute respiratory distress syndrome, interstitial lung disease, lung infiltration, pulmonary hypertension, respiratory distress, respiratory failure



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  : Hyperpigmentation, photosensitivity
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: MALIGNANCIES AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS

  WARNING: MALIGNANCIES AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS

    Increased risk for developing serious infections and malignancies with ENVARSUS XR or other immunosuppressants that may lead to hospitalization or death   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,   5.2  )  ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: MALIGNANCIES AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS  See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



   Increased risk for developing serious infections and malignancies with ENVARSUS XR or other immunosuppressants that may lead to hospitalization or death (  5.1  ,   5.2  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Graft-rejection and other serious adverse reactions due to medication errors : Instruct patients or caregivers to recognize appearance of ENVARSUS XR tablets (   5.3   ) 
 *   New onset diabetes after transplant : Monitor blood glucose (   5.4   ) 
 *   Nephrotoxicity (acute and/or chronic) due to ENVARSUS XR or concomitant nephrotoxic drugs: Monitor renal function; consider dosage reduction (   5.5   ) 
 *   Neurotoxicity [including risk of posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES)]: Monitor for neurologic abnormalities; reduce dosage or discontinue ENVARSUS XR (   5.6   ) 
 *   Hyperkalemia : Risk may be increased with other agents associated with hyperkalemia; monitor serum potassium levels (   5.7   ) 
 *   Hypertension: May require antihypertensive therapy (   5.8   ) 
 *   QT prolongation : Consider obtaining electrocardiograms and monitoring electrolytes in patients at high risk (   5.10   ) 
 *   Pure red cell aplasia : Consider discontinuation (   5.12   ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lymphoma and Other Malignancies



  Immunosuppressants, including ENVARSUS XR, increase the risk of developing lymphomas and other malignancies, particularly of the skin. The risk appears to be related to the intensity and duration of immunosuppression rather than to the use of any specific agent. Examine patients for skin changes and advise to avoid or limit exposure to sunlight and UV light.



 Post-transplant lymphoproliferative disorder (PTLD), associated with Epstein-Barr Virus (EBV), has been reported in immunosuppressed organ transplant patients. The risk of PTLD appears greatest in those individuals who are EBV seronegative. Monitor EBV serology during treatment.



    5.2 Serious Infections



  Immunosuppressants, including ENVARSUS XR, increase the risk of developing bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections. These infections may lead to serious, including fatal, outcomes. Serious viral infections reported include:



 *  Polyomavirus-associated nephropathy (especially due to BK virus infection), 
 *  JC virus-associated progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), and 
 *  Cytomegalovirus (CMV) infections: CMV seronegative transplant patients who receive an organ from a CMV seropositive donor are at highest risk of CMV viremia and CMV disease. 
    Monitor for the development of infection and adjust the immunosuppressive regimen to balance the risk of rejection with the risk of infection [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]  .
 

    5.3 Graft Rejection and Other Serious Adverse Reactions due to Medication Errors



  Medication errors, including substitution and dispensing errors, between tacrolimus immediate-release products and tacrolimus extended-release products were reported outside the U.S. This led to serious adverse reactions, including graft rejection, or other adverse reactions due to under- or over-exposure to tacrolimus. ENVARSUS XR is not interchangeable or substitutable with tacrolimus immediate-release products or other tacrolimus extended-release products. Instruct patients and caregivers to recognize the appearance of ENVARSUS XR tablet [ see   Dosage Forms and Strengths (3)      ].



    5.4 New Onset Diabetes After Transplant



  ENVARSUS XR caused new onset diabetes after transplant (NODAT) in kidney transplant patients, which may be reversible in some patients. African-American and Hispanic kidney transplant patients are at an increased risk. Monitor blood glucose concentrations and treat appropriately [ see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    and   Use in Specific Populations (8.8)      ].



    5.5 Nephrotoxicity due to ENVARSUS XR and Drug Interactions



  ENVARSUS XR, like other calcineurin-inhibitors, can cause acute or chronic nephrotoxicity. Consider dosage reduction in patients with elevated serum creatinine and tacrolimus whole blood trough concentrations greater than the recommended range. The risk for nephrotoxicity may increase when ENVARSUS XR is concomitantly administered with CYP3A inhibitors (by increasing tacrolimus whole blood concentrations) or drugs associated with nephrotoxicity (e.g., aminoglycosides, ganciclovir, amphotericin B, cisplatin, nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors, protease inhibitors) [see   Drug Interactions (7.2)    ]  . Monitor renal function and consider dosage reduction if nephrotoxicity occurs.



    5.6 Neurotoxicity



  ENVARSUS XR may cause a spectrum of neurotoxicities. The most severe neurotoxicities include posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES), delirium, seizure, and coma; others include tremors, paresthesias, headache, mental status changes, and changes in motor and sensory functions [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1  ,  6.2)    ]  . As symptoms may be associated with tacrolimus whole blood trough concentrations at or above the recommended range, monitor for neurologic symptoms and consider dosage reduction or discontinuation of ENVARSUS XR if neurotoxicity occurs.



    5.7 Hyperkalemia



  Mild to severe hyperkalemia, which may require treatment, has been reported with tacrolimus including ENVARSUS XR. Concomitant use of agents associated with hyperkalemia (e.g., potassium-sparing diuretics, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers) may increase the risk for hyperkalemia [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]  . Monitor serum potassium levels periodically during treatment.



    5.8 Hypertension



  Hypertension is a common adverse reaction of ENVARSUS XR therapy and may require antihypertensive therapy [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]  . Some antihypertensive drugs can increase the risk for hyperkalemia [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ]  . Calcium-channel blocking agents may increase tacrolimus blood concentrations and require dosage reduction of ENVARSUS XR [see   Drug Interactions (7.2)    ]  .



    5.9 Risk of Rejection with Strong CYP3A Inducers and Risk of Serious Adverse Reactions with Strong CYP3A Inhibitors



  The concomitant use of strong CYP3A inducers may increase the metabolism of tacrolimus, leading to lower whole blood trough concentrations and greater risk of rejection. In contrast, the concomitant use of strong CYP3A inhibitors may decrease the metabolism of tacrolimus, leading to higher whole blood trough concentrations and greater risk of serious adverse reactions (e.g., neurotoxicity, QT prolongation) [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6  ,  5.10)    ]  Therefore, adjust ENVARSUS XR dose and monitor tacrolimus whole blood trough concentrations when coadministering ENVARSUS XR with strong CYP3A inhibitors (e.g., telaprevir, boceprevir, ritonavir, ketoconazole, itraconazole, voriconazole, clarithromycin) or strong CYP3A inducers (e.g., rifampin, rifabutin) [see   Dosage and Administration (2.3)    and   Drug Interactions (7.2)    ]  .



    5.10 QT Prolongation



  ENVARSUS XR may prolong the QT/QTc interval and cause Torsade de Pointes. Avoid ENVARSUS XR in patients with congenital long QT syndrome. Consider obtaining electrocardiograms and monitoring electrolytes (magnesium, potassium, calcium) periodically during treatment in patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, those taking certain antiarrhythmic medications or other products that lead to QT prolongation, and those with electrolyte disturbances (e.g., hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, or hypomagnesemia).



 When coadministering ENVARSUS XR with other substrates and/or inhibitors of CYP3A, a reduction in ENVARSUS XR dosage, monitoring of tacrolimus whole blood concentrations, and monitoring for QT prolongation is recommended [see   Drug Interactions (7.2)    ]  .



    5.11 Immunizations



  Whenever possible, administer the complete complement of vaccines before transplantation and treatment with ENVARSUS XR.



 Avoid the use of live attenuated vaccines during treatment with ENVARSUS XR (e.g., intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, BCG, yellow fever, varicella, and TY21a typhoid vaccines).



 Inactivated vaccines noted to be safe for administration after transplantation may not be sufficiently immunogenic during treatment with ENVARSUS XR.



    5.12 Pure Red Cell Aplasia



  Cases of pure red cell aplasia (PRCA) have been reported in patients treated with tacrolimus. All of these patients reported risk factors for PRCA such as parvovirus B19 infection, underlying disease, or concomitant medications associated with PRCA. A mechanism for tacrolimus-induced PRCA has not been elucidated. If PRCA is diagnosed, consider discontinuation of ENVARSUS XR.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
