<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="epclusa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Serious Symptomatic Bradycardia When Sofosbuvir Is Coadministered with Amiodarone and Another HCV Direct-Acting Antiviral [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  
   *  The most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 10%, all grades) observed with treatment with EPCLUSA for 12 weeks are headache and fatigue. (  6.1  ) 
 *  The most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 10%, all grades) observed with treatment with EPCLUSA and ribavirin for 12 weeks in patients with decompensated cirrhosis are fatigue, anemia, nausea, headache, insomnia, and diarrhea. (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc. at 1-800-GILEAD-5 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 If EPCLUSA is administered with ribavirin, refer to the prescribing information for ribavirin for a description of ribavirin-associated adverse reactions.



     Adverse Reactions in Subjects without Cirrhosis or with Compensated Cirrhosis  



 The adverse reactions data for EPCLUSA in patients without cirrhosis or with compensated cirrhosis were derived from three Phase 3 clinical trials (ASTRAL-1, ASTRAL-2, and ASTRAL-3) which evaluated a total of 1035 subjects infected with genotype 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6 HCV, without cirrhosis or with compensated cirrhosis, who received EPCLUSA for 12 weeks. EPCLUSA was studied in placebo- and active-controlled trials  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 The proportion of subjects who permanently discontinued treatment due to adverse events was 0.2% for subjects who received EPCLUSA for 12 weeks.



 The most common adverse reactions (adverse events assessed as causally related by the investigator and at least 10%) were headache and fatigue in subjects treated with EPCLUSA for 12 weeks.



 Adverse reactions, all grades, observed in greater than or equal to 5% of subjects receiving 12 weeks of treatment with EPCLUSA in ASTRAL-1 include headache (22%), fatigue (15%), nausea (9%), asthenia (5%), and insomnia (5%). Of subjects receiving EPCLUSA who experienced these adverse reactions, 79% had an adverse reaction of mild severity (Grade 1). With the exception of asthenia, each of these adverse reactions occurred at a similar frequency or more frequently in subjects treated with placebo compared to subjects treated with EPCLUSA (asthenia: 3% versus 5% for the placebo and EPCLUSA groups, respectively).



 The adverse reactions observed in subjects treated with EPCLUSA in ASTRAL-2 and ASTRAL-3 were consistent with those observed in ASTRAL-1. Irritability was also observed in greater than or equal to 5% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA in ASTRAL-3.



     Adverse Reactions in Subjects with Decompensated Cirrhosis  



 The safety assessment of EPCLUSA in subjects infected with genotype 1, 2, 3, 4, or 6 HCV with decompensated cirrhosis was based on one Phase 3 trial (ASTRAL-4) including 87 subjects who received EPCLUSA with ribavirin for 12 weeks. All 87 subjects had Child-Pugh B cirrhosis at screening. On the first day of treatment with EPCLUSA with ribavirin, 6 subjects and 4 subjects were assessed to have Child-Pugh A and Child-Pugh C cirrhosis, respectively  [see  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .



 The most common adverse reactions (adverse events assessed as causally related by the investigator, all grades with frequency of 10% or greater) in the 87 subjects who received EPCLUSA with ribavirin for 12 weeks were fatigue (32%), anemia (26%), nausea (15%), headache (11%), insomnia (11%), and diarrhea (10%). Of subjects who experienced these adverse reactions, 98% had adverse reactions of mild to moderate severity.



 A total of 4 (5%) subjects permanently discontinued EPCLUSA with ribavirin due to an adverse event; there was no adverse event leading to discontinuation that occurred in more than 1 subject.



 Decreases in hemoglobin to less than 10 g/dL and 8.5 g/dL during treatment were observed in 23% and 7% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA with ribavirin for 12 weeks, respectively. Ribavirin was permanently discontinued in 17% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA with ribavirin for 12 weeks, due to adverse reactions.



     Less Common Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials  



 The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 5% of subjects without cirrhosis or with compensated cirrhosis treated with EPCLUSA for 12 weeks and are included because of a potential causal relationship.



     *      Rash: In the ASTRAL-1 study, rash occurred in 2% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA and in 1% of subjects treated with placebo. No serious adverse reactions of rash occurred and all rashes were mild or moderate in severity. 
   *      Depression: In the ASTRAL-1 study, depressed mood occurred in 1% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA and was not reported by any subject taking placebo. No serious adverse reactions of depressed mood occurred and all events were mild or moderate in severity. 
        The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 10% of subjects with decompensated cirrhosis (ASTRAL-4) treated with EPCLUSA with ribavirin for 12 weeks and are included because of a potential causal relationship.
 

     *      Rash: Rash occurred in 5% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA with ribavirin. No serious adverse reactions of rash occurred and all rashes were mild or moderate in severity. 
        Laboratory Abnormalities  
 

     *      Lipase Elevations: In ASTRAL-1, isolated, asymptomatic lipase elevations of greater than 3*ULN were observed in 3% and 1% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA and placebo for 12 weeks, respectively; and in 6% and 3% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA in ASTRAL-2 and ASTRAL-3, respectively. 
 *      
 *     In the Phase 3 trial of subjects with decompensated cirrhosis (ASTRAL-4), lipase was assessed when amylase values were greater than or equal to 1.5*ULN. Isolated, asymptomatic lipase elevations of greater than 3*ULN were observed in 2% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA with ribavirin for 12 weeks. 
   *      Creatine Kinase: In ASTRAL-1, isolated, asymptomatic creatine kinase elevations greater than or equal to 10*ULN were reported in 1% and 0% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA and placebo for 12 weeks, respectively; and in 2% and 1% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA in ASTRAL-2 and ASTRAL-3, respectively. 
 *      
 *     In the Phase 3 trial with decompensated cirrhosis (ASTRAL-4), isolated, asymptomatic creatine kinase elevations greater than or equal to 10*ULN were reported in 1% of subjects treated with EPCLUSA with ribavirin for 12 weeks. 
   *      Indirect Bilirubin: Increases in indirect bilirubin up to 3 mg/dL above baseline were noted among HIV-1/HCV coinfected subjects treated with EPCLUSA and an atazanavir/ritonavir-based antiretroviral regimen. The elevated indirect bilirubin values were not associated with clinical adverse events and all subjects completed 12 weeks of EPCLUSA without dose adjustment or treatment interruption of either EPCLUSA or HIV antiretroviral agents. 
          6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of sofosbuvir. Because postmarketing reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Cardiac Disorders  



 Serious symptomatic bradycardia has been reported in patients taking amiodarone who initiated treatment with sofosbuvir in combination with another HCV direct-acting antiviral  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  and  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ].  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Bradycardia with amiodarone coadministration: Serious symptomatic bradycardia may occur in patients taking amiodarone, particularly in patients also receiving beta blockers, or those with underlying cardiac comorbidities and/or advanced liver disease. Coadministration of amiodarone with EPCLUSA is not recommended. In patients without alternative viable treatment options, cardiac monitoring is recommended. (  5.1  ,  7.3  )



 



   5.1 Serious Symptomatic Bradycardia When Sofosbuvir Is Coadministered with Amiodarone and Another HCV Direct-Acting Antiviral



  Postmarketing cases of symptomatic bradycardia and cases requiring pacemaker intervention have been reported when amiodarone is coadministered with sofosbuvir in combination with daclatasvir or simeprevir. A fatal cardiac arrest was reported in a patient taking amiodarone who was coadministered a sofosbuvir-containing regimen (HARVONI (ledipasvir/sofosbuvir)). Bradycardia has generally occurred within hours to days, but cases have been observed up to 2 weeks after initiating HCV treatment. Patients also taking beta blockers, or those with underlying cardiac comorbidities and/or advanced liver disease may be at increased risk for symptomatic bradycardia with coadministration of amiodarone. Bradycardia generally resolved after discontinuation of HCV treatment. The mechanism for this effect is unknown.



 Coadministration of amiodarone with EPCLUSA is not recommended. For patients taking amiodarone who have no other alternative viable treatment options and who will be coadministered EPCLUSA:



 *  Counsel patients about the risk of symptomatic bradycardia. 
 *  Cardiac monitoring in an in-patient setting for the first 48 hours of coadministration is recommended, after which outpatient or self-monitoring of the heart rate should occur on a daily basis through at least the first 2 weeks of treatment. 
    Patients who are taking EPCLUSA who need to start amiodarone therapy due to no other alternative viable treatment options should undergo similar cardiac monitoring as outlined above.
 

 Due to amiodarone's long half-life, patients discontinuing amiodarone just prior to starting EPCLUSA should also undergo similar cardiac monitoring as outlined above.



 Patients who develop signs or symptoms of bradycardia should seek medical evaluation immediately. Symptoms may include near-fainting or fainting, dizziness or lightheadedness, malaise, weakness, excessive tiredness, shortness of breath, chest pains, confusion, or memory problems [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  and  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ]  .



    5.2 Risk of Reduced Therapeutic Effect Due to Concomitant Use of EPCLUSA with Inducers of P-gp and/or Moderate to Potent Inducers of CYP



  Drugs that are inducers of P-gp and/or moderate to potent inducers of CYP2B6, CYP2C8, or CYP3A4 (e.g., rifampin, St. John's wort, carbamazepine) may significantly decrease plasma concentrations of sofosbuvir and/or velpatasvir, leading to potentially reduced therapeutic effect of EPCLUSA. The use of these agents with EPCLUSA is not recommended [see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ]  .



    5.3 Risks Associated with Ribavirin and EPCLUSA Combination Treatment



  If EPCLUSA is administered with ribavirin, the warnings and precautions for ribavirin apply to this combination regimen. Refer to the ribavirin prescribing information for a full list of the warnings and precautions for ribavirin [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
