<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="epinephrine1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Due to the lack of randomized, controlled clinical trials of epinephrine for the treatment of anaphylaxis, the true incidence of adverse reactions associated with the systemic use of epinephrine is difficult to determine. Adverse reactions reported in observational trials, case reports, and studies are listed below.



 Common adverse reactions to systemically administered epinephrine include anxiety; apprehensiveness; restlessness; tremor; weakness; dizziness; sweating; palpitations; pallor; nausea and vomiting; headache; and/or respiratory difficulties. These symptoms occur in some persons receiving therapeutic doses of epinephrine, but are more likely to occur in patients with hypertension or hyperthyroidism [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ].



 Arrhythmias, including fatal ventricular fibrillation, have been reported, particularly in patients with underlying cardiac disease or those receiving certain drugs [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  and  Drug Interactions (7)    ].



 Rapid rises in blood pressure have produced cerebral hemorrhage, particularly in elderly patients with cardiovascular disease [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ].



 Angina may occur in patients with coronary artery disease [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ].



 Accidental injection into the digits, hands or feet may result in loss of blood flow to the affected area [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].



 Adverse events experienced as a result of accidental injections may include increased heart rate, local reactions including injection site pallor, coldness and hypoesthesia or injury at the injection site resulting in bruising, bleeding, discoloration, erythema or skeletal injury.



 Lacerations, bent needles, and embedded needles have been reported when epinephrine injection, USP auto-injector has been injected into the thigh of young children who are uncooperative and kick or move during the injection [  see  Warning and Precautions (5.2)    ].



 Injection into the buttock has resulted in cases of gas gangrene [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]  .  



 Rare cases of serious skin and soft tissue infections, including necrotizing fasciitis and myonecrosis caused by Clostridia (gas gangrene), have been reported following epinephrine injection, including epinephrine injection, USP auto-injector, in the thigh [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ].



   EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions to epinephrine include anxiety, apprehensiveness, restlessness, tremor, weakness, dizziness, sweating, palpitations, pallor, nausea and vomiting, headache, and/or respiratory difficulties. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Mylan Specialty, L.P. at 1-877-446-3679 (1-877-4-INFO-RX) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    In conjunction with use, seek immediate medical or hospital care. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Do not inject intravenously, into buttock, or into digits, hands, or feet. (  5.2  ) 
 *    To minimize the risk of injection related injury, instruct caregivers to hold the child's leg firmly in place and limit movement prior to and during injection when administering to young children. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Rare cases of serious skin and soft tissue infections have been reported following epinephrine injection. Advise patients to seek medical care if they develop signs or symptoms of infection. (  5.3  ) 
 *    The presence of a sulfite in this product should not deter use. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Administer with caution in patients with heart disease; may aggravate angina pectoris or produce ventricular arrhythmias. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Emergency Treatment



  Epinephrine injection, USP auto-injectors are intended for immediate administration as emergency supportive therapy and are not intended as a substitute for immediate medical care. In conjunction with the administration of epinephrine, the patient should seek immediate medical or hospital care.  More than two sequential doses of epinephrine should only be administered under direct medical supervision [ see  Indications and Usage (1)  ,  Dosage and Administration (2)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17)    ].



    5.2 Injection-Related Complications



  Epinephrine injection, USP auto-injector should only  be injected into the anterolateral aspect of the thigh [ see  Dosage and Administration (2)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17)    ].



 *     Do not inject intravenously. Large doses or accidental intravenous injection of epinephrine may result in cerebral hemorrhage due to sharp rise in blood pressure. Rapidly acting vasodilators can counteract the marked pressor effects of epinephrine if there is such inadvertent administration. 
 *     Do not inject into buttock. Injection into the buttock may not provide effective treatment of anaphylaxis. Advise the patient to go immediately to the nearest emergency room for further treatment of anaphylaxis. Additionally, injection into the buttock has been associated with Clostridial infections (gas gangrene). Cleansing with alcohol does not kill bacterial spores, and therefore, does not lower this risk. 
 *     Do not inject into digits, hands or feet. Since epinephrine is a strong vasoconstrictor, accidental injection into the digits, hands or feet may result in loss of blood flow to the affected area. Advise the patient to go immediately to the nearest emergency room and to inform the healthcare provider in the emergency room of the location of the accidental injection. Treatment of such inadvertent administration should consist of vasodilation, in addition to further appropriate treatment of anaphylaxis [ see  Adverse Reactions (6)   ]. 
 *     Hold leg firmly during injection. Lacerations, bent needles, and embedded needles have been reported when epinephrine injection, USP auto-injector has been injected into the thigh of young children who are uncooperative and kick or move during an injection. To minimize the risk of injection related injury when administering epinephrine injection, USP auto-injector to young children, instruct caregivers to hold the child's leg firmly in place and limit movement prior to and during injection. 
       5.3 Serious Infections at the Injection Site
 

  Rare cases of serious skin and soft tissue infections, including necrotizing fasciitis and myonecrosis caused by Clostridia (gas gangrene), have been reported at the injection site following epinephrine injection for anaphylaxis. Clostridium  spores can be present on the skin and introduced into the deep tissue with subcutaneous or intramuscular injection. While cleansing with alcohol may reduce presence of bacteria on the skin, alcohol cleansing does not kill Clostridium  spores. To decrease the risk of Clostridium  infection, do not inject epinephrine injection, USP auto-injector into the buttock [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]. Advise patients to seek medical care if they develop signs or symptoms of infection, such as persistent redness, warmth, swelling, or tenderness, at the epinephrine injection site.



    5.4 Allergic Reactions Associated with Sulfite



  The presence of a sulfite in this product should not deter administration of the drug for treatment of serious allergic or other emergency situations even if the patient is sulfite-sensitive.



 Epinephrine is the preferred treatment for serious allergic reactions or other emergency situations even though this product contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfite that may, in other products, cause allergic-type reactions including anaphylactic symptoms or life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in certain susceptible persons.



 The alternatives to using epinephrine in a life-threatening situation may not be satisfactory.



    5.5 Disease Interactions



  Some patients may be at greater risk for developing adverse reactions after epinephrine administration. Despite these concerns, it should be recognized that the presence of these conditions is not a contraindication to epinephrine administration in an acute, life-threatening situation. Therefore, patients with these conditions, and/or any other person who might be in a position to administer epinephrine injection, USP auto-injector to a patient experiencing anaphylaxis should be carefully instructed in regard to the circumstances under which epinephrine should be used.



 *    Patients with Heart Disease 
    Epinephrine should be administered with caution to patients who have heart disease, including patients with cardiac arrhythmias, coronary artery or organic heart disease, or hypertension .  In such patients, or in patients who are on drugs that may sensitize the heart to arrhythmias ,  epinephrine may precipitate or aggravate angina pectoris as well as produce ventricular arrhythmias [ see  Drug Interactions (7)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)    ].
 

 *    Other Patients and Diseases 
    Epinephrine should be administered with caution to patients with hyperthyroidism, diabetes, elderly individuals, and pregnant women. Patients with Parkinson's disease may notice a temporary worsening of symptoms.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
