<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="eplerenone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Hyperkalemia [See  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)  ]  
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

   EXCERPT:     CHF Post-MI  : Most common adverse reactions (&gt;2% and more frequent than with placebo): hyperkalemia and increased creatinine. (  6.1  )



   Hypertension  : Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2% and more frequent than with placebo): dizziness, diarrhea, coughing, fatigue and flu-like symptoms. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Greenstone LLC at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

      Congestive Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction    



 In EPHESUS, safety was evaluated in 3307 patients treated with eplerenone and 3301 placebo-treated patients. The overall incidence of adverse events reported with eplerenone (78.9%) was similar to placebo (79.5%). Adverse events occurred at a similar rate regardless of age, gender, or race. Patients discontinued treatment due to an adverse event at similar rates in either treatment group (4.4% eplerenone vs. 4.3% placebo), with the most common reasons for discontinuation being hyperkalemia, MI, and abnormal renal function.



 Adverse reactions that occurred more frequently in patients treated with eplerenone than placebo were hyperkalemia (3.4% vs. 2.0%) and increased creatinine (2.4% vs. 1.5%). Discontinuations due to hyperkalemia or abnormal renal function were less than 1.0% in both groups. Hypokalemia occurred less frequently in patients treated with eplerenone (0.6% vs. 1.6%).



 The rates of sex hormone-related adverse events are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2. Rates of Sex Hormone-Related Adverse Events in EPHESUS 
                     Rates in Males       Rates in Females     
                      Gynecomastia           Mastodynia           Either         Abnormal Vaginal Bleeding      
  
   Eplerenone             0.4%                  0.1%               0.5%                     0.4%                
     Placebo              0.5%                  0.1%               0.6%                     0.4%                
               Hypertension  
 

 Eplerenone has been evaluated for safety in 3091 patients treated for hypertension. A total of 690 patients were treated for over 6 months and 106 patients were treated for over 1 year.



 In placebo-controlled studies, the overall rates of adverse events were 47% with eplerenone and 45% with placebo. Adverse events occurred at a similar rate regardless of age, gender, or race. Therapy was discontinued due to an adverse event in 3% of patients treated with eplerenone and 3% of patients given placebo. The most common reasons for discontinuation of eplerenone were headache, dizziness, angina pectoris/MI, and increased GGT. The adverse events that were reported at a rate of at least 1% of patients and at a higher rate in patients treated with eplerenone in daily doses of 25 mg to 400 mg versus placebo are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3. Rates (%) of Adverse Events Occurring in Placebo-Controlled Hypertension Studies in &gt;=1% of Patients Treated with Eplerenone (25 mg to 400 mg) and at a More Frequent Rate than in Placebo-Treated Patients 
                                                         Eplerenone(n=945)           Placebo(n=372)         
  
 Note: Adverse events that are too general to be informative or are very common in the treated population are excluded.   
  
   Metabolic                                                                                                
   Hypercholesterolemia                                          1                          0               
   Hypertriglyceridemia                                          1                          0               
   Digestive                                                                                                
   Diarrhea                                                      2                          1               
   Abdominal pain                                                1                          0               
   Urinary                                                                                                  
   Albuminuria                                                   1                          0               
   Respiratory                                                                                              
   Coughing                                                      2                          1               
   Central/Peripheral Nervous System                                                                        
   Dizziness                                                     3                          2               
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Fatigue                                                       2                          1               
   Influenza-like symptoms                                       2                          1               
         Gynecomastia and abnormal vaginal bleeding were reported with eplerenone but not with placebo. The rates of these sex hormone-related adverse events are shown in Table 4. The rates increased slightly with increasing duration of therapy. In females, abnormal vaginal bleeding was also reported in 0.8% of patients on antihypertensive medications (other than spironolactone) in active control arms of the studies with eplerenone.
 

 Table 4. Rates of Sex Hormone-Related Adverse Events with Eplerenone in Hypertension Clinical Studies 
                               Rates in Males       Rates in Females     
 Gynecomastia                    Mastodynia              Either         Abnormal Vaginal Bleeding   
  
 All controlled studies             0.5%                  0.8%               1.0%                0.6%           
 Controlled studies lasting &gt;= 6 months          0.7%                  1.3%               1.6%                0.8%           
 Open-label, long-term study          1.0%                  0.3%               1.0%                2.1%           
             6.2 Clinical Laboratory Test Findings
     Congestive Heart Failure Post-Myocardial Infarction  



   Creatinine:  Increases of more than 0.5 mg/dL were reported for 6.5% of patients administered eplerenone and for 4.9% of placebo-treated patients.



   Potassium:  In EPHESUS  [see  CLINICAL STUDIES (14.1)  ]  , the frequencies of patients with changes in potassium (&lt;3.5 mEq/L or &gt;5.5 mEq/L or &gt;=6.0 mEq/L) receiving eplerenone compared with placebo are displayed in Table 5.



 Table 5. Hypokalemia (&lt;3.5 mEq/L) or Hyperkalemia (&gt;5.5 or &gt;=6.0 mEq/L) in EPHESUS 
 Potassium (mEq/L)                       Eplerenone(N=3251)n (%)              Placebo(N=3237)n (%)          
  
 &lt; 3.5                                          273 (8.4)                          424 (13.1)               
 &gt;5.5                                           508 (15.6)                         363 (11.2)               
 &gt;= 6.0                                         180 (5.5)                           126 (3.9)               
         Table 6 shows the rates of hyperkalemia in EPHESUS as assessed by baseline renal function (creatinine clearance).
 

 Table 6. Rates of Hyperkalemia ( &gt;5.5 mEq/L) in EPHESUS by Baseline Creatinine ClearanceEstimated using the Cockroft-Gault formula. 
 Baseline Creatinine Clearance            Eplerenone(N=508)n (%)               Placebo(N=363)n (%)          
  
 &lt;=30 mL/min                                     160 (32)                            82 (23)                
 31-50 mL/min                                    122 (24)                            46 (13)                
 51-70 mL/min                                    86 (17)                             48 (13)                
 &gt;70 mL/min                                      56 (11)                             32 (9)                 
         Table 7 shows the rates of hyperkalemia in EPHESUS as assessed by two baseline characteristics: presence/absence of proteinuria from baseline urinalysis and presence/absence of diabetes.  [See  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)  .]  
 

 Table 7. Rates of Hyperkalemia ( &gt;5.5 mEq/L) in EPHESUS by Proteinuria and History of DiabetesDiabetes assessed as positive medical history at baseline; proteinuria assessed by positive dipstick urinalysis at baseline. 
                                          Eplerenone(N=508)n (%)               Placebo(N=363)n (%)          
  
 Proteinuria, no Diabetes                        81 (16)                             40 (11)                
 Diabetes, no Proteinuria                        91 (18)                             47 (13)                
 Proteinuria and Diabetes                        132 (26)                            58 (16)                
             Hypertension  
 

   Potassium:  In placebo-controlled fixed-dose studies, the mean increases in serum potassium were dose-related and are shown in Table 8 along with the frequencies of values &gt;5.5 mEq/L.



 Table 8. Increases in Serum Potassium in the Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose Hypertension Studies of Eplerenone 
                       Mean Increase mEq/L            % &gt;5.5 mEq/L            
     Daily Dosage               n                                                                             
  
       Placebo                 194                         0                               1                  
          25                    97                        0.08                             0                  
          50                   245                        0.14                             0                  
         100                   193                        0.09                             1                  
         200                   139                        0.19                             1                  
         400                   104                        0.36                            8.7                 
          Patients with both type 2 diabetes and microalbuminuria are at increased risk of developing persistent hyperkalemia. In a study of such patients taking eplerenone 200 mg, the frequencies of maximum serum potassium levels &gt;5.5 mEq/L were 33% witheplerenone given alone and 38% when eplerenone was given with enalapril.
 

 Rates of hyperkalemia increased with decreasing renal function. In all studies, serum potassium elevations &gt;5.5 mEq/L were observed in 10.4% of patients treated with eplerenone with baseline calculated creatinine clearance &lt;70 mL/min, 5.6% of patients with baseline creatinine clearance of 70 to 100 mL/min, and 2.6% of patients with baseline creatinine clearance of &gt;100 mL/min.  [See  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)  .]  



   Sodium:  Serum sodium decreased in a dose-related manner. Mean decreases ranged from 0.7 mEq/L at 50 mg daily to 1.7 mEq/L at 400 mg daily. Decreases in sodium (&lt;135 mEq/L) were reported for 2.3% of patients administered eplerenone and 0.6% of placebo-treated patients.



   Triglycerides:  Serum triglycerides increased in a dose-related manner. Mean increases ranged from 7.1 mg/dL at 50 mg daily to 26.6 mg/dL at 400 mg daily. Increases in triglycerides (above 252 mg/dL) were reported for 15% of patients administered eplerenone and 12% of placebo-treated patients.



   Cholesterol:  Serum cholesterol increased in a dose-related manner. Mean changes ranged from a decrease of 0.4 mg/dL at 50 mg daily to an increase of 11.6 mg/dL at 400 mg daily. Increases in serum cholesterol values greater than 200 mg/dL were reported for 0.3% of patients administered eplerenone and 0% of placebo-treated patients.



   Liver Function Tests:  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and gamma glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT) increased in a dose-related manner. Mean increases ranged from 0.8 U/L at 50 mg daily to 4.8 U/L at 400 mg daily for ALT and 3.1 U/L at 50 mg daily to 11.3 U/L at 400 mg daily for GGT. Increases in ALT levels greater than 120 U/L (3 times upper limit of normal) were reported for 15/2259 patients administered eplerenone and 1/351 placebo-treated patients. Increases in ALT levels greater than 200 U/L (5 times upper limit of normal) were reported for 5/2259 of patients administered eplerenone and 1/351 placebo-treated patients. Increases of ALT greater than 120 U/L and bilirubin greater than 1.2 mg/dL were reported 1/2259 patients administered eplerenone and 0/351 placebo-treated patients. Hepatic failure was not reported in patients receiving eplerenone.



   BUN/Creatinine:  Serum creatinine increased in a dose-related manner. Mean increases ranged from 0.01 mg/dL at 50 mg daily to 0.03 mg/dL at 400 mg daily. Increases in blood urea nitrogen to greater than 30 mg/dL and serum creatinine to greater than 2 mg/dL were reported for 0.5% and 0.2%, respectively, of patients administered eplerenone and 0% of placebo-treated patients.



   Uric Acid:  Increases in uric acid to greater than 9 mg/dL were reported in 0.3% of patients administered eplerenone and 0% of placebo-treated patients.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of eplerenone. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Skin:  angioneurotic edema, rash
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hyperkalemia: Patients with decreased renal function and diabetics with proteinuria are at increased risk. Proper patient selection and monitoring and avoiding certain concomitant medications can minimize the risk. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hyperkalemia



  Minimize the risk of hyperkalemia with proper patient selection and monitoring, and avoidance of certain concomitant medications [See  CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)  ,  ADVERSE REACTIONS (6.2)  , and  DRUG INTERACTIONS (7)  ]  . Monitor patients for the development of hyperkalemia until the effect of eplerenone is established. Patients who develop hyperkalemia (&gt;5.5 mEq/L) may continue eplerenone therapy with proper dose adjustment. Dose reduction decreases potassium levels. [See  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2.1)  .]  



 The rates of hyperkalemia increase with declining renal function. [See  ADVERSE REACTIONS (6.2)  .]  Patients with hypertension who have serum creatinine levels &gt;2.0 mg/dL (males) or &gt;1.8 mg/dL (females) or creatinine clearance &lt;=50 mL/min should not be treated with eplerenone. [See  CONTRAINDICTIONS (4)  .]  Patients with CHF post-MI who have serum creatinine levels &gt;2.0 mg/dL (males) or &gt;1.8 mg/dL (females) or creatinine clearance &lt;=50mL/min should be treated with eplerenone with caution.



 Diabetic patients with CHF post-MI should also be treated with caution, especially those with proteinuria. The subset of patients in the EPHESUS study with both diabetes and proteinuria on the baseline urinalysis had increased rates of hyperkalemia compared to patients with either diabetes or proteinuria. [See  ADVERSE REACTIONS (6.2)  .]  



 The risk of hyperkalaemia may increase when eplerenone is used in combination with an angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor and/or an angiotensin receptor blocker (ARB). [See  DRUG INTERACTIONS (7.2)  ]  



    5.2 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment did not increase the incidence of hyperkalemia. In 16 subjects with mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment who received 400 mg of eplerenone, no elevations of serum potassium above 5.5 mEq/L were observed. The mean increase in serum potassium was 0.12 mEq/L in patients with hepatic impairment and 0.13 mEq/L in normal controls. The use of eplerenone in patients with severe hepatic impairment has not been evaluated. [See  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY (12.3)  .]  



    5.3 Impaired Renal Function



  Patients with decreased renal function are at increased risk of hyperkalemia. [See  CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)  ,  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5.1)  ,  ADVERSE REACTIONS (6.1)  .]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
