<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="equetro" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Serious dermatologic reactions: Toxic Epidermal Necrolysis and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  
 *  Aplastic anemia/agranulocytosis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms/multiorgan hypersensitivity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Embryofetal Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Abrupt Discontinuation and Seizure Risk [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Hyponatremia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Cognitive and Motor Impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Drug Interaction with Non-Nucleoside Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Hepatic Porphyria [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Anticholinergic Reactions and Increased Intraocular Pressure [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common (&gt;5% and 2 times placebo) adverse reactions were dizziness, somnolence, nausea, vomiting, ataxia, constipation, pruritus, dry mouth, asthenia, rash, blurred vision, and speech disorder (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Validus Pharmaceuticals LLC at 1-866-9VALIDUS or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=5% in the EQUETRO group and at least twice placebo) in the pooled 3-week placebo-controlled trials in patients with acute mania associated with Bipolar I Disorder (Studies 1 and 2) were dizziness, somnolence, nausea, vomiting, ataxia, constipation, pruritus, dry mouth, asthenia, rash, blurred vision, and speech disorder  [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  . The EQUETRO doses used were 400 to 1600 mg per day.



 Table 2. Common Adverse Reactions Reported in Bipolar Disorder Studies 1 and 2 (Incidence &gt;= 2% and greater than placebo) 
   Adverse Reactions                     EQUETRO  (r)      (N = 251)       Placebo    (N = 248)             
 Dizziness                             44%                               12%                                
 Somnolence                            32%                               13%                                
 Nausea                                29%                               10%                                
 Vomiting                              18%                               3%                                 
 Ataxia                                15%                               0.4%                               
 Constipation                          10%                               5%                                 
 Pruritus                              8%                                2%                                 
 Dry Mouth                             8%                                3%                                 
 Asthenia                              8%                                4%                                 
 Rash                                  7%                                4%                                 
 Blurred vision                        6%                                2%                                 
 Speech Disorder                       6%                                0.4%                               
 Hypertension                          3%                                0.4%                               
 Paresthesia                           2%                                1%                                 
 Thinking abnormal                     2%                                0.4%                               
 Tremor                                3%                                1%                                 
 Twitching                             2%                                1%                                 
 Vertigo                               2%                                1%                                 
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of carbamazepine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Nervous System:  confusion, diplopia, oculomotor disturbances, nystagmus, speech disturbances, abnormal involuntary movements, tinnitus.



   Digestive System:  gastric distress, abdominal pain, diarrhea, anorexia.



   Other:  lupus erythematosus-like syndrome



 One case of aseptic meningitis, accompanied by myoclonus and peripheral eosinophilia, has been reported in a patient taking carbamazepine in combination with other medications. The patient was successfully dechallenged, and the meningitis reappeared upon rechallenge with carbamazepine.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

WARNING: SERIOUS DERMATOLOGIC ADVERSE REACTIONS and APLASTIC ANEMIA AND AGRANULOCYTOSIS



  

WARNING: SERIOUS DERMATOLOGIC ADVERSE REACTIONS and APLASTIC ANEMIA AND AGRANULOCYTOSIS



    Serious Dermatologic Reactions and HLA-B*1502 Allelle  



   Serious and sometimes fatal dermatologic reactions, including toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), have occurred in patients treated with carbamazepine. These syndromes may be accompanied by mucous membrane ulcers, fever, or painful rash occur. These reactions are estimated to occur in 1 to 6 per 10,000 new users in countries with mainly Caucasian populations, but the risk in patients of Asian descent is estimated to be about 10 times higher. There is a strong association between the risk of developing SJS/TEN and the presence of HLA-B*1502, an inherited allelic variant of the HLA-B gene that is found almost exclusively in patients with Asian ancestry. Test for HLA-B*1502, prior to initiating EQUETRO in patients with an increased likelihood of carrying this allele. Avoid use of EQUETRO in patients testing positive for the allele unless the benefit clearly outweighs the risk. Discontinue EQUETRO if you suspect that the patient has a serious dermatologic reaction   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  



   Aplastic Anemia and Agranulocytosis  



   Aplastic anemia and agranulocytosis can occur during treatment with EQUETRO. The risk of developing these reactions with EQUETRO is 5-8 times greater than in the general population. However, the overall risk in the general population is low (6 cases in a population of one million per year for agranulocytosis and two cases in a population of one million per year for aplastic anemia). Obtain a complete blood count before beginning treatment with EQUETRO, and monitor CBC periodically. Consider discontinuing if EQUETRO if significant bone marrow depression develops   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: SERIOUS DERMATOLOGIC REACTIONS and APLASTIC ANEMIA AND AGRANULOCYTOSIS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Serious Dermatologic Reactions  



 *  Serious and sometimes fatal dermatologic reactions, including toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), have occurred with EQUETRO (5.1) 
 *  Patients of Asian ancestry have a 10-fold greater risk of TEN/SJS, compared to other populations. In genetically at-risk patients, test for the HLA-B*1502 allele prior to initiating EQUETRO (2.3, 5.1) 
 *  Discontinue EQUETRO if these reactions occur (5.1) 
      Aplastic Anemia and Agranulocytosis   
 

 *  Aplastic anemia and agranulocytosis occurred with EQUETRO (5.2) 
 *  Obtain complete pretreatment hematological testing. Consider discontinuing EQUETRO if significant bone marrow depression develops (2.3, 5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms: Monitor for hypersensitivity. Discontinue if another cause can not be established (  5.3  ) 
 *   Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior (  5.4  ) 
 *   Embryofetal Toxicity: Advise women of child-bearing potential of possible risks to the fetus (  5.4  ,  8.1  ) 
 *   Abrupt Discontinuation and Risk of Seizure: Taper the dose when discontinuing treatment (  5.6  ). 
 *   Hyponatremia: Consider discontinuing EQUETRO in patients with significant symptomatic hyponatremia (  5.7  ). 
 *   Cognitive and Motor Impairment: Advise patients not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on EQUETRO to gauge whether it adversely affects these activities (  5.8  ) 
 *   Hepatic Porphyria: Avoid EQUETRO use in patients with hepatic porphyria: can cause acute episodes of porphyria (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Dermatologic Reactions



  Serious and sometimes fatal dermatologic reactions, including toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) and Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS), have been reported with carbamazepine treatment. These syndromes may be accompanied by mucous membrane ulcers, fever, or painful rash occur. Over 90% of carbamazepine-treated patients who experienced SJS/TEN developed these reactions within the first few months of treatment. The risk of these reactions is estimated to be about 1 to 6 per 10,000 new users in countries with mainly Caucasian populations. However, the risk in some Asian countries is estimated to be about 10 times higher. Discontinue EQUETRO if you suspect that the patient has a serious dermatologic reaction. If signs or symptoms suggest SJS/TEN, do not resume treatment with EQUETRO.



  SJS, TEN, and HLA-B*1502 Allele  



 Retrospective case-control studies have found that in patients of Chinese ancestry there is a strong association between the risk of developing SJS/TEN with carbamazepine treatment and the presence of the HLA-B*1502 allele (an inherited variant of the HLA-B gene). Prior to initiating EQUETRO therapy in patients at higher likelihood for this allele, perform testing for HLA-B*1502. The high resolution genotype test is positive if one or two HLA-B*1502 alleles are present. Avoid use of EQUETRO in patients positive for the HLA-B*1502 allele unless the benefits clearly outweighs the risks of serious dermatologic reactions. Tested patients who are found to be negative for the allele are thought to have a low risk of SJS/TEN associated with carbamazepine treatment.



 The prevalence of the HLA-B*1502 allele may be higher in Asian populations: Hong Kong, Thailand, Malaysia, and parts of the Philippines (&gt; 15%); Taiwan (10%), North China (4%); south Asians, including Indians (2 to 4%); and Japan and Korea (&lt; 1%). HLA-B*1502 is largely absent in individuals not of Asian origin (e.g., Caucasians, African-Americans, Hispanics, and Native Americans). The accuracy of estimated rates of the HLA-B*1502 allele in these populations may be limited by wide variability in rates within ethnic groups, the difficulty in ascertaining ethnic ancestry, and the likelihood of mixed ancestry.



 The HLA-B*1502 allele has not been found to predict risk of less severe adverse cutaneous reactions from carbamazepine, such as maculopapular rash, or to predict Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms hypersensitivity syndrome or non-serious rash (maculopapular eruption [MPE]) or to predict Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .



 Limited evidence suggests that HLA-B*1502 may be a risk factor for the development of SJS/TEN in patients of Chinese ancestry taking other anti-epileptic drugs associated with SJS/TEN, including phenytoin. Consideration should be given to avoiding use of other drugs associated with SJS/TEN in HLA-B*1502 positive patients, when alternative therapies are otherwise equally acceptable.



  Hypersensitivity Reactions and HLA-A*3101 Allele  



 Retrospective case-control studies in patients of European, Korean, and Japanese ancestry have found a moderate association between the risk of developing hypersensitivity reactions and the presence of HLA-A*3101, an inherited allelic variant of the HLA-A gene, in patients using carbamazepine. These hypersensitivity reactions include SJS/TEN, maculopapular eruptions, and Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .



 HLA-A*3101 is expected to be present in the following frequencies: greater than 15% in patients of Japanese and Native American ancestry; up to about 10% in patients of Han Chinese, Korean, European, and Latin American ancestry; and up to about 5% in African-Americans and patients of Indian, Thai, Taiwanese, and Chinese (Hong Kong) ancestry.



 The risks and benefits of carbamazepine therapy should be weighed before considering carbamazepine in patients known to be positive for HLA-A*3101.



  Hypersensitivity and Limitations of HLA Genotyping  



 Application of HLA-B*1502 genotyping as a screening tool has important limitations and must never substitute for appropriate clinical vigilance and patient management. Many HLA-B*1502-positive Asian and HLA-A*3101 positive patients treated with carbamazepine will not develop SJS/TEN or other hypersensitivity reactions, and these reactions can still occur infrequently in HLA-B*1502-negative and HLA-A*3101-negative patients of any ethnicity. The role of other possible factors in the development of, and morbidity from, SJS/TEN and other hypersensitivity reactions, such as AED dose, compliance, concomitant medications, co-morbidities, and the level of dermatologic monitoring have not been studied.



    5.2 Aplastic Anemia and Agranulocytosis



  Aplastic anemia and agranulocytosis have occurred in patients treated with carbamazepine. Data from a population-based case-control study suggest that the risk of developing these reactions is 5-8 times greater than in the general population. However, the overall risk of these reactions in the untreated general population is low, approximately six patients per one million population per year for agranulocytosis and two patients per one million population per year for aplastic anemia.



 Although reports of transient or persistent decreased platelet or white blood cell counts are not uncommon in association with the use of carbamazepine, data are not available to estimate accurately their incidence or outcome. However, the vast majority of the cases of leukopenia have not progressed to the more serious conditions of aplastic anemia or agranulocytosis.



 Because of the very low incidence of agranulocytosis and aplastic anemia, the vast majority of minor hematologic changes observed in monitoring of patients on carbamazepine are unlikely to signal the occurrence of either abnormality. Nonetheless, complete pretreatment hematological testing should be obtained as a baseline. If a patient in the course of treatment exhibits low or decreased white blood cell or platelet counts, the patient should be monitored closely. Consider discontinuing EQUETRO if any evidence of significant bone marrow depression develops. Clinical features can include fever, dyspnea on exertion, fatigue, easy bruising, petechiae, epistaxis, gingival bleeding, and heavy menses.



    5.3 Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms/Multiorgan Hypersensitivity



  Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS), also known as Multiorgan hypersensitivity, have occurred with carbamazepine. Some of these events have been fatal or life-threatening. DRESS typically, although not exclusively, presents with fever, rash, and/or lymphadenopathy, in association with other organ system involvement, such as hepatitis, nephritis, hematologic abnormalities, myocarditis, or myositis sometimes resembling an acute viral infection. Eosinophilia is often present. This disorder is variable in its expression, and other organ systems not noted here may be involved. It is important to note that early manifestations of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may be present even though rash is not evident. If such signs or symptoms are present, the patient should be evaluated immediately. Equetro should be discontinued if an alternative etiology for the signs or symptoms cannot be established.



  Hypersensitivity  



 Hypersensitivity reactions to carbamazepine have been reported in patients who previously experienced this reaction to anticonvulsants including phenytoin, primidone, and phenobarbital. A history of hypersensitivity reactions should be obtained for patients and their immediate family members. If such history is present, benefits and risks should be carefully considered, and, if carbamazepine is initiated, the signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity should be carefully monitored.



 In patients who have exhibited hypersensitivity reactions to carbamazepine, approximately 25 to 30% may experience hypersensitivity reactions with oxcarbazepine.



    5.4 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including EQUETRO, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed. Table 1 presents the absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 1 Risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior (reactions) for antiepileptic drugs by indication in the pooled analysis 
                    Placebo           Antiepileptic Drugs                                                         
 Indication        Reactions Per1000 Patients  Reactions Per 1000Patients  Relative Risk:Incidence of Reactions in AEDGroup/ Incidence of Reactions inPlacebo Group  Risk Difference: Additional DrugPatients with Events Per 1000 Patients   
 EpilepsyPsychiatricOtherTotal  1.05.71.02.4      3.48.51.84.3          3.51.51.91.8              2.42.90.91.9               
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing EQUETRO or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thought or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behaviors and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.5 Embryofetal Toxicity



  EQUETRO is a Category D drug [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



 EQUETRO can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Apprise women of childbearing potential of this risk. Use in pregnancy only if the potential benefits of treatment outweigh the risks



 Epidemiological data suggest that there may be an association between the use of carbamazepine during pregnancy and congenital malformations, including spina bifida. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.



 Retrospective case reviews suggest that, compared with monotherapy, there may be a higher prevalence of teratogenic effects associated with the use of anticonvulsants in combination therapy.



 In humans, transplacental passage of carbamazepine is rapid (30-60 minutes), and the drug is accumulated in the fetal tissues, with higher levels found in liver and kidney than in brain and lung.



 Carbamazepine has been shown to have adverse effects in reproduction studies in rats when given orally in dosages 10-25 times a human daily dosage of 1200 mg on a mg/kg basis or 1.5-4 times the human daily dosage of 1200 mg on a mg/m  2  basis. In rat teratology studies, 2 of 135 offspring showed kinked ribs at 250 mg/kg, and 4 of 119 offspring showed other anomalies at 650 mg/kg (cleft palate, 1; talipes, 1; anophthalmos, 2).



 Tests to detect defects using current accepted procedures should be considered a part of routine prenatal care in childbearing women receiving carbamazepine.



 To provide additional information regarding the effects of in utero exposure to Equetro, physicians are advised to recommend that pregnant patients taking Equetro enroll in the North American Antiepileptic Drug (NAAED) Pregnancy Registry. This can be done by calling the toll-free number 1-888-233-2334, and must be done by patients themselves. Information on the registry can also be found at the website http://www.aedpregnancyregistry.org/



    5.6 Abrupt Discontinuation and Risk of Seizure



  Do not discontinue EQUETRO abruptly, because of the risk of seizure and other withdrawal signs/symptoms. Patients with seizure disorder are at increased risk of developing seizure and status epilepticus with attendant hypoxia and threat to life.



    5.7 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia can occur as a result of treatment with EQUETRO. In many cases, the hyponatremia appears to be caused by the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). The risk of developing SIADH with EQUETRO treatment appears to be dose-related. Elderly patients and patients treated with diuretics are at greater risk of developing hyponatremia. Consider discontinuing EQUETRO in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia. Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, new or increased seizure frequency, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which can lead to falls. Consider discontinuing EQUETRO in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia.



    5.8 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  EQUETRO has the potential to cause impairment in judgment, cognition, and motor function. Caution patients about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain the EQUETRO does not affect them adversely. Adverse reactions in the clinical trials in bipolar disorder included (EQUETRO, N= 251 and Placebo, N= 248): somnolence (32% vs. 13%), ataxia (15% vs. 0.4%), dizziness (44% vs. 12%), vertigo (2% vs. 1%), thinking abnormal (2% vs. 0.4%), tremor (3% vs. 1%), and blurred vision (6% vs. 2%) [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  .



    5.9 Decreased Antiviral Effect of Non-nucleoside Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors with Concomitant use of EQUETRO



  Coadministration of EQUETRO with non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors, including delavirdine, may lead to loss of virologic response and possible resistance. Through induction of CYP3A4, EQUETRO can markedly decrease the concentrations of these drugs. Coadministration of delavirdine and EQUETRO can decrease delavirdine concentrations by 90% [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  ), and Drug Interactions (  7.2  )]  .



    5.10 Hepatic Porphyria



  The use of EQUETRO should be avoided in patients with a history of hepatic porphyria (e.g., acute intermittent porphyria, variegate porphyria, porphyria cutanea tarda). Acute attacks have been reported in such patients receiving carbamazepine therapy. Carbamazepine administration has also been demonstrated to increase porphyrin precursors in rodents, a presumed mechanism for the induction of acute attacks of porphyria.



    5.11 Increased Intraocular Pressure



  Carbamazepine has mild anticholinergic activity. In patients with a history of increased intraocular pressure, consider assessing intraocular pressure before initiating treatment and periodically during therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
