<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="eraxis" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reactions reported with ERAXIS are:



 *  Hepatic effects [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
   *  Candidemia and other forms of Candida infections: Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=15%) are hypokalemia, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, pyrexia, insomnia (  6.2  ) 
 *  Esophageal candidiasis: Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) are diarrhea, pyrexia, anemia, headache, vomiting, nausea and dyspepsia (  6.3  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of ERAXIS for Injection was assessed in 929 individuals, including 257 healthy subjects and 672 patients in clinical trials of candidemia, other forms of  Candida  infections, and esophageal candidiasis. A total of 633 patients received ERAXIS at daily doses of either 50 mg or 100 mg. A total of 481 patients received ERAXIS for &gt;=14 days.



   6.2 Candidemia/other  Candida  Infections

  Three studies (one comparative vs. fluconazole, two non-comparative) assessed the efficacy and safety of ERAXIS (100 mg) in patients with candidemia and other  Candida  infections.



 The data described below reflect exposure to ERAXIS and fluconazole in 127 and 118 patients, respectively, with candidemia and other forms of invasive candidiasis, in the randomized, comparative trial of the efficacy and safety of ERAXIS to that of fluconazole. In ERAXIS-treated patients, the age range was 16-89 years, the gender distribution was 51% male and 49% female, and the race distribution was 72% White, 18% Black/African American, 9% other races. Patients were randomized to receive once daily IV ERAXIS (200 mg loading dose followed by 100 mg maintenance dose) or IV fluconazole (800 mg loading dose followed by 400 mg maintenance dose). Treatment was administered for at least 14 and not more than 42 days.



 The number of patients with adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of study medication was 11.5% in the ERAXIS arm and 21.6% in the fluconazole arm. The most common adverse reactions leading to study drug discontinuation were multi-organ failure and systemic  Candida  infection in the ERAXIS arm.



 Table 2 presents adverse reactions that were reported in &gt;=5% of subjects receiving ERAXIS or fluconazole therapy in this trial.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=5% of Subjects Receiving ERAXIS or Fluconazole Therapy for Candidemia/other Candida InfectionsA patient who experienced multiple reactions with a System Organ Class (SOC) or preferred term was counted one time for that class, one time for the preferred term and one time for "subjects with at least one adverse reaction", This trial was not designed to support comparative claims for ERAXIS for the adverse reactions reported in this table. 
                                                         ERAXIS100 mgN=131       Fluconazole400 mgN=125     
                                                               N (%)                      N (%)             
  
   Subjects with a least one adverse reaction                130 (99)                   122 (98)            
                                                                                                            
   Infections and infestations                                82 (63)                    80 (64)            
   Bacteremia                                                 23 (18)                    23 (18)            
   Urinary tract infection                                    19 (15)                    22 (18)            
   Sepsis                                                      9 (7)                     11 (9)             
   Pneumonia                                                   8 (6)                     19 (15)            
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                 81 (62)                    72 (58)            
   Nausea                                                     32 (24)                    15 (12)            
   Diarrhea                                                   24 (18)                    23 (18)            
   Vomiting                                                   23 (18)                    12 (10)            
   Constipation                                               11 (8)                     14 (11)            
   Abdominal pain                                              8 (6)                     16 (13)            
   General disorders and administration site conditions             70 (53)                    76 (61)            
   Pyrexia                                                    23 (18)                    23 (18)            
   Edema peripheral                                           14 (11)                    16 (13)            
   Chest pain                                                  7 (5)                      6 (5)             
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders             67 (51)                    55 (44)            
   Dyspnea                                                    15 (12)                     4 (3)             
   Pleural effusion                                           13 (10)                    11 (9)             
   Cough                                                       9 (7)                      7 (6)             
   Respiratory distress                                        8 (6)                      2 (2)             
   Investigations                                             66 (50)                    46 (37)            
   Blood alkaline phosphatase increased                       15 (12)                    14 (11)            
   White blood cell increased                                 11 (8)                      3 (2)             
   Hepatic enzyme increased                                    7 (5)                     14 (11)            
   Blood creatinine increased                                  7 (5)                      1 (1)             
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                         61 (47)                    61 (49)            
   Hypokalemia                                                33 (25)                    24 (19)            
   Hypomagnesemia                                             15 (12)                    14 (11)            
   Hypoglycemia                                                9 (7)                     10 (8)             
   Hyperkalemia                                                8 (6)                     14 (11)            
   Hyperglycemia                                               8 (6)                      8 (6)             
   Dehydration                                                 8 (6)                      2 (2)             
   Vascular disorders                                         50 (38)                    41 (33)            
   Hypotension                                                19 (15)                    18 (14)            
   Hypertension                                               15 (12)                     5 (4)             
   Deep vein thrombosis                                       13 (10)                     9 (7)             
   Psychiatric disorders                                      48(37)                     45 (36)            
   Insomnia                                                   20 (15)                    12 (10)            
   Confusional state                                          10 (8)                     10 (8)             
   Depression                                                  8 (6)                      5 (4)             
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders                       34 (26)                    36 (29)            
   Anemia                                                     12 (9)                     20 (16)            
   Thrombocythemia                                             8 (6)                      1 (1)             
   Leukocytosis                                                7 (5)                      6 (5)             
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                     30 (23)                    32 (26)            
   Decubitus ulcer                                             7 (5)                     10 (8)             
   Nervous system disorders                                   27 (21)                    31 (25)            
   Headache                                                   11 (8)                     10 (8)             
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders             27 (21)                    25 (20)            
   Back pain                                                   7 (5)                     13 (10)            
           6.3 Esophageal Candidiasis
   The data described below reflect exposure to ERAXIS and fluconazole in 300 and 301 patients, respectively, with esophageal candidiasis in a randomized trial comparing the efficacy and safety of ERAXIS to that of oral fluconazole. In ERAXIS-treated patients, the age range was 18-68 years, the gender distribution was 42% male and 58% female and the race distribution was 15% White, 49% Black/African American, 15% Asian, 0.3 % Hispanic, 21% other races. Patients were randomized to receive IV ERAXIS (100 mg on day 1, followed by 50 mg per day) or oral fluconazole (200 mg on day 1, followed by 100 mg per day) for 7 days beyond resolution of symptoms (range, 14-21 days).



 Twenty eight (9%) patients in the ERAXIS arm and 36 (12%) patients in the fluconazole arm had adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of study medication. The most common adverse reactions leading to study drug discontinuation were maculopapular rash for the ERAXIS arm. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were rash and increased AST for the fluconazole arm.



 Table 3 presents adverse reactions that were reported in &gt;=5% of subjects receiving ERAXIS therapy.



 Table 3 Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=5% of Subjects Receiving ERAXIS or Fluconazole Therapy for Esophageal CandidiasisA patient who experienced multiple reactions with a System Organ Class (SOC) or preferred term was counted one time for that class, one time for the preferred term and one time for "subjects with at least one adverse reaction", This trial was not designed to support comparative claims for ERAXIS for the adverse reactions reported in this table. 
                                                         ERAXIS50 mgN=300        Fluconazole100 mgN=301     
                                                               N (%)                      N (%)             
  
   Subjects with a least one adverse reactions               239 (80)                   227 (75)            
                                                                                                            
   Infections and infestations                               115 (38)                    99 (33)            
   Oral candidiasis                                           15 (5)                     10 (3)             
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                106 (35)                   113 (38)            
   Diarrhea                                                    27(9)                      26(9)             
   Vomiting                                                    27(7)                     30(10)             
   Nausea                                                      20(7)                      23(8)             
   Dyspepsia                                                   20(7)                      21(7)             
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders                       55 (18)                    50 (17)            
   Anemia                                                     25 (8)                     22 (7)             
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                         50 (17)                    46 (15)            
   Hypokalemia                                                14 (5)                     17 (6)             
   General disorders and administration site condition             49 (16)                    54 (18)            
   Pyrexia                                                     27(9)                      28(9)             
   Nervous system disorders                                   39 (13)                    36 (12)            
   Headache                                                   25 (8)                     20 (7)             
           6.4 Less Common Adverse Reactions
   The following selected adverse reactions occurred in &lt;2% of patients:



   Blood and Lymphatic  : coagulopathy, thrombocytopenia



   Cardiac  : atrial fibrillation, bundle branch block (right), sinus arrhythmia, ventricular extrasystoles



   Eye  : eye pain, vision blurred, visual disturbance



   General and Administration Site  : infusion related reaction, peripheral edema, rigors



   Hepatobiliary  : abnormal liver function tests, cholestasis, hepatic necrosis



   Infections  : clostridial infection



   Investigations  : amylase increased, bilirubin increased, CPK increased, electrocardiogram QT prolonged, gamma-glutamyl transferase increased, lipase increased, potassium decreased, prothrombin time prolonged, urea increased



   Nervous System  : convulsion, dizziness



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal  : cough



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue  : angioneurotic edema, erythema, pruritus, sweating increased, urticaria



   Vascular  : flushing, hot flushes, thrombophlebitis superficial



   6.5 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of anidulafungin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Immune  : Anaphylactic shock, anaphylactic reaction, bronchospasm [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hepatic Effects: Risk of abnormal liver function tests, hepatitis, hepatic failure; monitor hepatic function during therapy (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity: Anaphylaxis, including shock has been reported. Risk of infusion-related adverse reactions, possibly histamine-mediated, including rash, urticaria, flushing, pruritus, bronchospasm, dyspnea, and hypotension; to reduce occurrence, do not exceed a rate of infusion of 1.1 mg/minute (  2.3  ,  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatic Effects



  Laboratory abnormalities in liver function tests have been seen in healthy volunteers and patients treated with ERAXIS. In some patients with serious underlying medical conditions who were receiving multiple concomitant medications along with ERAXIS, clinically significant hepatic abnormalities have occurred. Isolated cases of significant hepatic dysfunction, hepatitis, or hepatic failure have been reported in patients; a causal relationship to ERAXIS has not been established. Patients who develop abnormal liver function tests during ERAXIS therapy should be monitored for evidence of worsening hepatic function and evaluated for risk/benefit of continuing ERAXIS therapy.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity



   Anaphylactic reactions, including shock were reported with the use of ERAXIS. If these reactions occur, ERAXIS should be discontinued and appropriate treatment administered [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.5)    ].  



  Infusion-related adverse reactions, possibly histamine-mediated, have been reported with ERAXIS, including rash, urticaria, flushing, pruritus, bronchospasm, dyspnea, and hypotension [ see  Adverse Reactions (6)    ]. To reduce occurrence of these reactions, do not exceed a rate of ERAXIS infusion of 1.1 mg/minute [ see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)    ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
