<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ertaczo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions observed in clinical trials (incidence &gt;2%) were contact dermatitis, dry skin, burning skin, application site skin tenderness. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical trials, cutaneous adverse events occurred in 7 of 297 (2%) subjects (2 of them severe) receiving ERTACZO  (r)  cream, 2%, and in 7 of 291 (2%) subjects (2 of them severe) receiving vehicle. These reported cutaneous adverse events included contact dermatitis, dry skin, burning skin, application site skin tenderness.



 In a dermal sensitization trial, 8 of 202 evaluable subjects tested with ERTACZO  (r)  cream, 2%, and 4 of 202 evaluable subjects tested with vehicle, exhibited a slight erythematous reaction in the challenge phase. There was no evidence of cumulative irritation or contact sensitization in a repeated insult patch test involving 202 healthy volunteers.



   6.2Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ERTACZO cream, 2%. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 In post-marketing surveillance for ERTACZO cream, 2%, the following were reported:



 Cutaneous adverse events: erythema, pruritus, vesiculation, desquamation, and hyperpigmentation.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   5.1Local Adverse Reactions



  If irritation develops, treatment should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted.



 Physicians should exercise caution when prescribing ERTACZO cream, 2%, to patients known to be sensitive to imidazole antifungals, since cross-reactivity may occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
