<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="estring" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  See    BOXED WARNINGS  ,  WARNINGS    and    PRECAUTIONS    



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In the two pivotal controlled studies, discontinuation of treatment due to an adverse event was required by 5.4 percent of patients receiving ESTRING and 3.9 percent of patients receiving conjugated estrogens vaginal cream. The most common reasons for withdrawal from ESTRING treatment due to an adverse event were vaginal discomfort and gastrointestinal symptoms.



 The adverse events reported with a frequency of 3 percent or greater in the two pivotal controlled studies by patients receiving ESTRING or conjugated estrogens vaginal cream are listed in Table 4.



 Table 4: Adverse Events Reported by 3 Percent or More of Patients Receiving Either ESTRING or Conjugated Estrogens Vaginal Cream in Two Pivotal Controlled Studies 
 ADVERSE EVENT                                        ESTRING(n = 257)%    Conjugated Estrogens Vaginal Cream (n = 129)%   
  
 Musculoskeletal                                                                                            
   Back Pain                                                  6                          8                  
   Arthritis                                                  4                          2                  
   Arthralgia                                                 3                          5                  
   Skeletal Pain                                              2                          4                  
 CNS/Peripheral Nervous System                                                                              
   Headache                                                   13                         16                 
 Psychiatric                                                                                                
   Insomnia                                                   4                          0                  
 Gastrointestinal                                                                                           
   Abdominal Pain                                             4                          2                  
   Nausea                                                     3                          2                  
 Respiratory                                                                                                
   Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                          5                          6                  
   Sinusitis                                                  4                          3                  
   Pharyngitis                                                1                          3                  
 Urinary                                                                                                    
   Urinary Tract Infection                                    2                          7                  
 Female Reproductive                                                                                        
   Leukorrhea                                                 7                          3                  
   Vaginitis                                                  5                          2                  
   Vaginal Discomfort/Pain                                    5                          5                  
   Vaginal Hemorrhage                                         4                          5                  
   Asymptomatic Genital Bacterial Growth                      4                          6                  
   Breast Pain                                                1                          7                  
 Resistance Mechanisms                                                                                      
   Genital Moniliasis                                         6                          7                  
 Body as a Whole                                                                                            
   Flu-Like Symptoms                                          3                          2                  
   Hot Flushes                                                2                          3                  
   Allergy                                                    1                          4                  
 Miscellaneous                                                                                              
   Family Stress                                              2                          3                  
         Other adverse events (listed alphabetically) occurring at a frequency of 1 to 3 percent in the two pivotal controlled studies by patients receiving ESTRING include: anxiety, bronchitis, chest pain, cystitis, dermatitis, diarrhea, dyspepsia, dysuria, flatulence, gastritis, genital eruption, urogenital pruritus, hemorrhoids, leg edema, migraine, otitis media, skin hypertrophy, syncope, toothache, tooth disorder, urinary incontinence.
 

   Post-Marketing Experience

    *  A few cases of toxic shock syndrome (TSS) have been reported in women using vaginal rings. TSS is a rare, but serious disease that may cause death. Warning signs of TSS include fever, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, muscle pain, dizziness, faintness, or a sunburn-rash on face and body. 
 *  A few cases of ring adherence to the vaginal wall, making ring removal difficult, have been reported. Vaginal wall ulceration or erosion should be carefully evaluated. If an ulceration or erosion has occurred, consideration should be given to leaving the ring out and not replacing it until healing is complete in order to prevent the ring from adhering to the healing tissue. 
 *  A few cases of bowel obstruction and vaginal ring use have been reported. Persistent abdominal complaints consistent with obstruction should be carefully evaluated. 
    The following additional adverse events were reported at least once by patients receiving ESTRING in the worldwide clinical program, which includes controlled and uncontrolled studies. A causal relationship with ESTRING has not been established.
 

   Body as a Whole  : allergic reaction



   CNS/Peripheral Nervous System  : dizziness



   Gastrointestinal  : enlarged abdomen, vomiting



   Metabolic/Nutritional Disorders  : weight decrease or increase



   Musculoskeletal  : arthropathy (including arthrosis)



   Psychiatric  : depression, decreased libido, nervousness



   Reproductive  : breast engorgement, breast enlargement, intermenstrual bleeding, genital edema, vulval disorder



   Skin/Appendages  : pruritus, pruritus ani



   Urinary  : micturition frequency, urethral disorder



   Vascular  : thrombophlebitis



   Vision  : abnormal vision



 The following additional adverse reactions have been reported with estrogens:



   Genitourinary system:  abnormal uterine bleeding/spotting; dysmenorrheal/pelvic pain; increase in size of uterine leiomyomata; vaginitis, including vaginal candidiasis; change in amount of cervical secretion; changes in cervical ectropion; ovarian cancer; endometrial hyperplasia; endometrial cancer



   Breasts:  tenderness, enlargement, pain, nipple discharge, galactorrhea; fibrocystic breast changes; breast cancer



   Cardiovascular:  deep and superficial venous thrombosis; pulmonary embolism; thrombophlebitis; myocardial infarction; stroke; increase in blood pressure



   Gastrointestinal  : nausea, vomiting; abdominal cramps, bloating; cholestatic jaundice; increased incidence of gallbladder disease; pancreatitis, enlargement of hepatic hemangiomas



   Skin:  chloasma or melasma that may persist when drug is discontinued; erythema multiforme; erythema nodosum; hemorrhagic eruption; loss of scalp hair; hirsutism, rash



   Eyes:  retinal vascular thrombosis; intolerance to contact lenses



   Central Nervous System:  headache; migraine; dizziness; mental depression; exacerbation of chorea; nervousness; mood disturbances; irritability; exacerbation of epilepsy, dementia



   Miscellaneous:  increase or decrease in weight; glucose intolerance; aggravation of porphyria; edema; arthralgias; leg cramps; changes in libido; angioedema; anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions; hypocalcemia (preexisting condition); exacerbation of asthma; increased triglycerides
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS

  WARNINGS

  ENDOMETRIAL CANCER

  Adequate diagnostic measures, including endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in all cases of undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal vaginal bleeding. (See     WARNINGS, Malignant neoplasms, Endometrial cancer    .)   



   CARDIOVASCULAR AND OTHER RISKS

  Estrogens with or without progestins should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Dementia    .)         



 The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 6.8 years and 7.1 years, respectively, of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE 0.625 mg) relative to placebo. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders    .)



 The estrogen plus progestin WHI substudy reported increased risks of myocardial infarction, stroke, invasive breast cancer, pulmonary emboli, and DVT in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE 0.625 mg combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA 2.5 mg), relative to placebo. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Malignant neoplasms, Breast cancer    .)



 The Women's Health Initiative Memory Study (WHIMS), a substudy of the WHI, reported increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE 0.625 mg alone and during 4 years of treatment with daily CE 0.625 mg combined with MPA 2.5 mg, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women.  (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Dementia     and     PRECAUTIONS, Geriatric Use    .)



 In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins. Because of these risks, estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.



 





    BOXED WARNING: 

    What is the most important information I should know about ESTRING (an estrogen hormone)?  



 *  Estrogens increase the chance of getting cancer of the uterus. 
    Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are using ESTRING. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterine (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause.  
 

 *  Do not use estrogens with or without progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes, or dementia. 
    Using estrogens with or without progestins may increase your chance of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, and blood clots. Using estrogens with or without progestins may increase your risk of dementia, based on a study of women age 65 years or older.
 

 You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with ESTRING.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
