<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="evamist" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Cardiovascular Disorders [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Malignant Neoplasms [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (    5.2    )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5 percent) are: headache, breast tenderness and nipple pain, nausea, back pain, and nasopharyngitis (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ther-Rx Corporation at 1-877-567-7676 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In a 12-week, randomized, placebo-controlled trial of Evamist in 454 women, 80 to 90 percent of women randomized to active drug received at least 70 days of therapy and 75 to 85 percent randomized to placebo received at least 70 days of therapy.



 The adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5 percent of women in any treatment group are shown in  Table 1  .



 Table 1. Frequency of Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5 Percent) in Any Treatment Group in a Controlled Study of Evamist 
                           Frequency n (%)     
   System Organ Class    Preferred Term      1 Spray      2 Sprays      3 Sprays     
   Placebo    (N = 77)      Evamist    (N = 76)      Placebo    (N = 76)      Evamist    (N = 74)      Placebo    (N = 75)      Evamist    (N = 76)     
  
  Reproductive System and Breast Disorders    
  Breast tenderness       0 (0)        4 (5)        4 (5)        5 (7)        0 (0)        4 (5)        
  Nipple pain             0 (0)        2 (3)        0 (0)        5 (7)        0 (0)        1 (1)        
  Gastrointestinal Disorders    
  Nausea                  5 (7)        1 (1)        1 (1)        2 (3)        4 (5)        2 (3)        
  Infections and Infestations    
  Nasopharyngitis         1 (1)        4 (5)        2 (3)        3 (4)        1 (1)        1 (1)        
  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    
  Back pain               1 (1)        2 (3)        2 (3)        4 (5)        1 (1)        2 (3)        
  Arthralgia              1 (1)        1 (1)        4 (5)        1 (1)        0 (0)        3 (4)        
  Nervous system          
  Headache                4 (5)        7 (9)        5 (7)        9 (12)       7 (9)        8 (11)       
             Application site reactions were reported in 3 out of 226 (1.3%) women treated with Evamist.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Evamist. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Breasts:  Breast swelling, breast mass, breast enlargement



   Cardiovascular:  Heart rate increased



   Central nervous system:  Dizziness, dysgeusia, paresthesia, lethargy, hypoesthesia



   Eyes:  Eye irritation, ocular hyperemia



   Gastrointestinal:  Abdominal pain, diarrhea, constipation, abdominal distension, dry mouth, decreased appetite



   Genitourinary system:  Vaginal bleeding



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle spasms, arthritis



   Psychiatric:  Insomnia, mood swings, anxiety, irritability, mood altered, depression



   Respiratory tract:  Cough, dyspnea, dry throat



   Skin:  Nipple and areola discoloration, usually on the same side of the body as the inner forearm on which Evamist is applied, rash, pruritus, alopecia, urticaria, dry skin, skin discoloration, chloasma



   Miscellaneous:  Weight increased, malaise, fatigue, asthenia    
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER, PROBABLE DEMENTIA AND UNINTENTIONAL SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO ESTROGEN

  WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER, PROBABLE DEMENTIA AND UNINTENTIONAL SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO ESTROGEN

      Estrogen-Alone Therapy    



   Endometrial Cancer  



   There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens.  Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.  Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed and random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in all cases of undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    



   Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,   5.3  , and Clinical Studies (  14.2  ,   14.3  )]  .  



   The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg]-alone, relative to placebo   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].    



   The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )].    



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and other dosage forms of estrogens.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.  



     Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy    



   Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,   5.3  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].    



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].    



   The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )].    



   Breast Cancer  



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].    



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.  



   Unintentional Secondary Exposure  



   Breast budding and breast masses in prepubertal females and gynecomastia and breast masses in prepubertal males have been reported following unintentional secondary exposure to Evamist by women using this product.  In most cases, the condition resolved with removal of Evamist exposure. Women should ensure that children do not come into contact with the site(s) where Evamist is applied.  Healthcare providers should advise patients to strictly adhere to recommended instructions for use   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER, PROBABLE DEMENTIA, AND UNINTENTIONAL SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO ESTROGEN



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



     Estrogen-Alone Therapy    



    There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens (  5.2  )  



    Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (  5.1  ,   5.3  )  



    The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) (  5.1  )  



    The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (  5.3  )  



     Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy    



    Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (  5.1  ,   5.3  )  



    The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of stroke, DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), and myocardial infarction (MI) (  5.1  )  



    The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of invasive breast cancer (  5.2  )  



    The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (  5.3  )  



     Unintentional Secondary Exposure     



    Breast budding, breast masses, and gynecomastia have been reported in children following unintentional secondary exposure to Evamist (  5.4  )  



 









    BOXED WARNING: 

  Patient Information

    EVAMIST (EE-vuh-mist)  



   (estradiol transdermal spray)  



 Read this Patient Information before you start using EVAMIST and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This information does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your menopausal symptoms or your treatment.



   

    What is the most important information I should know about EVAMIST (an estrogen hormone)?  



 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb). Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are using EVAMIST. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find the cause. 
 *  Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia (decline in brain function). 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting strokes or blood clots. 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years or older. 
 *  Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attack, strokes, or dementia. 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots. 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years and older. 
 *  The estrogen in EVAMIST spray can transfer from the area of skin where it was sprayed to other people. Do not allow others, especially children, to come into contact with the area of your skin where you sprayed EVAMIST. Young children who are accidentally exposed to estrogen through contact with women using EVAMIST may show signs of puberty that are not expected (for example, breast budding). 
 *  You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with EVAMIST. 
        What is EVAMIST?  
 

 EVAMIST is a prescription medicine spray that contains estradiol (an estrogen hormone).



   What is EVAMIST used for?  



 EVAMIST spray is used after menopause to:



 *  Reduce moderate to severe hot flashes Estrogens are hormones made by a woman's ovaries. The ovaries normally stop making estrogens when a woman is between 45 and 55 years old. This drop in body estrogen levels causes the "change of life" or menopause (the end of monthly menstrual periods). Sometimes, both ovaries are removed during an operation before natural menopause takes place. The sudden drop in estrogen levels causes "surgical menopause."When the estrogen levels begin dropping, some women get very uncomfortable symptoms, such as feelings of warmth in the face, neck, and chest, or sudden strong feelings of heat and sweating ("hot flashes" or "hot flushes"). In some women, the symptoms are mild, and they will not need to use estrogens. In other women, symptoms can be more severe. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with EVAMIST. 
      Who should not use EVAMIST?  
 

   Do not start using EVAMIST if you:  



 *  have unusual vaginal bleedingVaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  currently have or have had certain cancersEstrogens may increase the chance of getting certain types of cancers, including cancer of the breast or uterus. If you have or have had cancer, talk with your healthcare provider about whether you should use EVAMIST. 
 *  had a stroke or heart attack 
 *  currently have or have had blood clots 
 *  currently have or have had liver problems 
 *  have been diagnosed with a bleeding disorder 
 *  are allergic to EVAMIST or any of its ingredientsSee the list of ingredients in EVAMIST at the end of this leaflet 
 *  think you may be pregnantEVAMIST is not for pregnant women. If you think you may be pregnant, you should have a pregnancy test and know the results. Do not use EVAMIST if the test is positive and talk to your healthcare provider. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before I use EVAMIST?  
 

   Before you use EVAMIST, tell your healthcare provider if you:  



 *  have any unusual vaginal bleedingVaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  have any other medical conditionsYour healthcare provider may need to check you more carefully if you have certain conditions, such as asthma (wheezing), epilepsy (seizures), diabetes, migraine, endometriosis, lupus, angioedema (swelling of face and tongue), or problems with your heart, liver, thyroid, kidneys, or have high calcium levels in your blood. 
 *  are going to have surgery or will be on bed restYour healthcare provider will let you know if you need to stop using EVAMIST. 
 *  are breast feedingThe hormone in EVAMIST can pass into your breast milk. 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take   including prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins and herbal supplements.  Some medicines may affect how EVAMIST works.  EVAMIST may also affect how your other medicines work.  Keep a list of your medicines and show it to your healthcare provider and pharmacist when you get a new medicine.
 

   How should I use EVAMIST?  



   For detailed instructions, see the step-by-step instructions for using EVAMIST at the end of this Patient Information.  



 *  Use EVAMIST exactly as your healthcare provider tells you to use it. 
 *  EVAMIST is for skin use only. 
 *  Apply EVAMIST at the same time each day. 
 *  If you use sunscreen 1 hour after you use EVAMIST, it may reduce the amount of EVAMIST absorbed by your skin. 
 *  The estrogen in EVAMIST spray can transfer from the area of skin where it was sprayed to other people or pets. Do not allow other people, especially children to come into contact with the area of your skin where you have sprayed EVAMIST. 
 *  If another person accidentally touches the area of your skin where you have sprayed EVAMIST, that area of their skin should be washed with soap and water right away. 
 *  Do not let pets lick or touch your arm where you have sprayed EVAMIST, especially small pets. EVAMIST may harm them. Cover your skin with clothing where you have sprayed EVAMIST if you think a pet could come in contact with that area of your skin. 
 *  If a pet accidentally comes in contact with the area of your skin where you have sprayed EVAMIST, the area of the pet's skin should be washed with soap and water right away. 
 *  Young children who are accidentally exposed to estrogen through contact with women using EVAMIST may show signs and symptoms of puberty that are not expected. Signs and symptoms in children of exposure to EVAMIST may include:obreast budding or breast lumpsoother signs of abnormal sexual development 
 *       If a child shows signs and symptoms of accidental exposure to EVAMIST:ohave the child checked right away by their healthcare provider.ostop using EVAMIST and call your healthcare provider right away.otalk to your healthcare provider about the correct use of EVAMIST when around children. 
 *  Talk to your healthcare provider about other treatments for your menopause symptoms if accidental exposure to EVAMIST cannot be avoided. 
 *  You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly (for example, every 3 to 6 months) about the dose you are taking and whether you still need treatment with EVAMIST. 
      What should I avoid while using EVAMIST?  
 

 *  Do not allow others to make contact with the area of skin where you have applied the EVAMIST spray. 
 *  EVAMIST contains alcohol, which is flammable. Avoid fire, flame, or smoking until the area of your skin where you have applied EVAMIST has dried. 
      What are the possible side effects of EVAMIST?  
 

   Side effects are grouped by how serious they are and how often they happen when you are treated.  



   Serious, but less common side effects include:  



 *  heart attack 
 *  stroke 
 *  blood clots 
 *  dementia 
 *  breast cancer 
 *  cancer of the lining of the uterus (womb) 
 *  cancer of the ovary 
 *  high blood pressure 
 *  high blood sugar 
 *  gallbladder disease 
 *  liver problems 
 *  changes in your thyroid hormone levels 
 *  enlargement of benign tumors of the uterus ("fibroids") 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you get any of the following warning signs or any other unusual symptoms that concern you:  
 

 *  new breast lumps 
 *  unusual vaginal bleeding 
 *  changes in vision or speech 
 *  sudden new severe headaches 
 *  severe pains in your chest or legs with or without shortness of breath, weakness and fatigue 
      Less serious, but common side effects include:  
 

 *  headache 
 *  breast pain 
 *  irregular vaginal bleeding or spotting 
 *  stomach or abdominal cramps, bloating 
 *  nausea and vomiting 
 *  hair loss 
 *  fluid retention 
 *  vaginal yeast infection 
    These are not all the possible side effects of EVAMIST. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.  Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or does not go away.  You may report side effects to Ther-Rx at 1-877-567-7676 or to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.
 

   What can I do to lower my chances of a serious side effect with EVAMIST?  



 *  Talk with your healthcare provider regularly about whether you should continue using EVAMIST. 
 *  If you have a uterus, talk with your healthcare provider about whether the addition of a progestin is right for you. 
 *  The addition of a progestin is generally recommended for women with a uterus to reduce the chance of getting cancer of the uterus. 
 *  See your healthcare provider right away if you get vaginal bleeding while using EVAMIST. 
 *  Have a pelvic exam, breast exam, and mammogram (breast X-ray) every year unless your healthcare provider tells you something else. 
 *  If members of your family have had breast cancer or if you have ever had breast lumps or an abnormal mammogram, you may need to have breast exams more often. 
 *  If you have high blood pressure, high cholesterol (fat in the blood), diabetes, are overweight, or if you use tobacco, you may have a higher chance of getting heart disease. 
 *   Ask your healthcare provider for ways to lower your chances of getting heart disease. 
      How should I store EVAMIST?  
 

 *  Store EVAMIST at room temperature 68 degrees F to 77 degrees F (20 degrees C to 25 degrees C ) 
 *  Do not freeze. 
 *  Safely throw away medicine that is out of date or no longer needed. 
      Keep EVAMIST and all medicines out of the reach of children.  
 

   General information about the safe and effective use of EVAMIST.  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for conditions other than those listed in patient information leaflets. Do not use EVAMIST for conditions for which it was not prescribed. Do not give EVAMIST to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them.



 This leaflet summarizes the most important information about EVAMIST. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider or pharmacist.  You can ask for information about EVAMIST that is written for health professionals.



 For more information, go to www.Evamist.com or call Ther-Rx at 1-877-567-7676.



   What are the ingredients in EVAMIST?  



 Active ingredient: estradiol 



 Inactive ingredients: octisalate, alcohol



   Instructions for Use  



   EVAMIST (EE-vuh-mist)  



   (estradiol transdermal spray)  



 Read this Instructions for Use before you start using EVAMIST and each time you get a refill.  There may be new information.  This information does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your menopausal symptoms of your treatment.



   The parts of your EVAMIST applicator   



 EVAMIST comes in a spray applicator that delivers a measured amount of estradiol to your skin with each spray (see Figure A).



 *   Figure A 
 *   Step 1. Priming your EVAMIST 
   *  Before you use your EVAMIST applicator for the first time, the applicator must be primed. 
 *  Hold the EVAMIST applicator upright. Keep the cover on. Fully press down the pump button 3 times with your thumb or index finger (see Figure B). After priming, the EVAMIST applicator is ready to use. 
 *  The EVAMIST applicator should be primed only 1 time when you first start using a new applicator. Do not prime the EVAMIST applicator before your dose each day. 
 *    
      Figure B  
 

   Step 2. Using your EVAMIST  



 *  Remove the plastic cover. 
 *  Apply EVAMIST to a clean, dry, unbroken skin area on the inside of your forearm between the elbow and the wrist (see Figure C). This area must be clean, dry, and the skin must be without open wounds, cuts, abrasions, or rashes. 
 *  Hold the EVAMIST applicator upright and rest the plastic cone flat against your skin. You may need to change the position of your arm or the position of the cone on your arm so that the cone is flat against your skin and there are no gaps between the cone and your skin (see Figure C). 
 *  Press the pump button down fully 1 time (see Figure C). 
 *    
 *   Figure C 
 *   If your healthcare provider tells you to increase your dose to 2 or 3 sprays, move the cone before applying the second or third spray to an area of your skin next to but not touching the area of the previous spray (see Figure D). 
 *    
 *   Figure D 
   *  Do not apply EVAMIST to your breasts or in and around your vagina. 
 *  Do not massage or rub EVAMIST into your skin. 
 *  Let EVAMIST spray dry on your skin for at least:o2 minutes before you cover your skin with clothing.o1 hour before you wash your skin. 
 *   Step 3. After you use EVAMIST 
   *  Place the plastic cover back on the EVAMIST applicator cone. 
 *  EVAMIST is flammable until dry. Avoid fire, flame, or smoking until the area of your skin where you have applied EVAMIST has completely dried. 
 *   Step 4. Throwing away used EVAMIST applicators 
   *  Your EVAMIST applicator contains enough medicine to allow for initial priming of the pump with 3 sprays and application of 56 sprays. 
 *  Do not use your EVAMIST applicator for more than 56 application sprays even though the bottle may not be completely empty. You may not get the correct dose. 
 *  Always replace the cover over the cone of your EVAMIST applicator before you throw it away to prevent accidental exposure to other people or pets. 
    This Patient Information and Instructions for Use have been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.
 

 P0000Revised 03/2014



 Manufactured byDPT Laboratories. LtdSan Antonio, TX  78215



 ForTher-Rx CorporationChesterfield, MO  63005



 (c) 2013 Ther-Rx Corporation 03/14



  Figure A  Figure B  Figure C  Figure D 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Estrogens increase the risk of gallbladder disease (  5.5  ) 
 *    Discontinue estrogens if severe hypercalcemia, loss of vision, severe hypertriglyceridemia or cholestatic jaundice occurs (  5.6  ,  5.7  ,  5.10  ,  5.11  ) 
 *    Monitor thyroid function in women on thyroid hormone replacement therapy (  5.12  ,  5.21  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Disorders



  An increased risk of stroke and DVT has been reported with estrogen-alone therapy. An increased risk of PE, DVT, stroke, and MI has been reported with estrogen plus progestin therapy. Should any of these occur or be suspected, estrogen with or without progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 Risk factors for arterial vascular disease (for example, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, tobacco use, hypercholesterolemia, and obesity) and/or venous thromboembolism (VTE) (for example, personal history or family history of VTE, obesity, and systemic lupus erythematosus) should be managed appropriately.



    Stroke  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (45 versus 33 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in risk was demonstrated in year 1 and persisted [ see Clinical Studies  (   14.2     )  ]. Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone should be discontinued immediately.



 Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest no increased risk of stroke for those women receiving CE (0.625 mg)-alone versus those receiving placebo (18 versus 21 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (33 versus 25 per 10,000 women-years). [ see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )  ]. The increase in risk was demonstrated after the first year and persisted.  1  Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



    Coronary Heart Disease  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, no overall effect on coronary heart disease (CHD) events (defined as non-fatal MI, silent MI, or CHD death) was reported in women receiving estrogen-alone compared to placebo  2   [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  .



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, there was a statistically non-significant increase risk of CHD events reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (41 versus 34 per 10,000 women-years)  1  . An increase in relative risk was demonstrated in year 1, and a trend toward decreasing relative risk was reported in years 2 through 5 [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  .



 Subgroup analysis of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest a statistically non-significant reduction in CHD events (CE [0.635 mg]-alone compared to placebo) in women with less than 10 years since menopause (8 versus 16 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In postmenopausal women with documented heart disease (n = 2,763, average 66.7 years of age), in a controlled clinical trial of secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease (Heart and Estrogen/Progestin Replacement Study [HERS]), treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) demonstrated no cardiovascular benefit. During an average follow-up of 4.1 years, treatment with CE plus MPA did not reduce the overall rate of CHD events in postmenopausal women with established CHD. There were more CHD events in the CE plus MPA-treated group than in the placebo group in year 1, but not during the subsequent years. Two thousand, three hundred and twenty-one (2,321) women from the original HERS trial agreed to participate in an open label extension of HERS, HERS II. Average follow-up in HERS II was an additional 2.7 years, for a total of 6.8 years overall. Rates of CHD events were comparable among women in the CE plus MPA group and the placebo group in HERS, HERS II, and overall.



    Venous Thromboembolism  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, the risk of VTE (DVT and PE) was increased for women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to placebo (30 versus 22 per 10,000 women-years), although only the increased risk of DVT reached statistical significance (23 versus 15 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first two years  3   [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  . Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant 2-fold greater rate of VTE was reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (35 versus 17 per 10,000 women-years). Statistically significant increases in risk for both DVT (26 versus 13 per 10,000 women-years) and PE (18 versus 8 per 10,000 women-years) were also demonstrated. The increase in VTE risk was observed during the first year and persisted  4  [ see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )  ]. Should VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 If feasible, estrogens should be discontinued at least 4 to 6 weeks before surgery of the type associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, or during periods of prolonged immobilization.



    5.2 Malignant Neoplasms



   Endometrial Cancer  



 An increased risk of endometrial cancer has been reported with the use of unopposed estrogen therapy in women with a uterus. The reported endometrial cancer risk among unopposed estrogen users is about 2 to 12 times greater than in nonusers, and appears dependent on duration of treatment and on estrogen dose. Most studies show no significant increased risk associated with use of estrogens for less than 1 year. The greatest risk appears associated with prolonged use, with an increased risk of 15- to 24-fold for 5 to 10 years or more. This risk has been shown to persist for at least 8 to 15 years after estrogen therapy is discontinued.



 Clinical surveillance of all women using estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy is important. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in all cases of undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding. There is no evidence that the use of natural estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens of equivalent estrogen dose. Adding a progestin to postmenopausal estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



    Breast Cancer  



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen-alone users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone. In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, after an average follow-up of 7.1 years, daily CE-alone was not associated with an increased risk of invasive breast cancer (relative risk [RR] 0.80)  5   [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].  



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen plus progestin users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg). After a mean follow-up of 5.6 years, the estrogen plus progestin substudy reported an increased risk of invasive breast cancer in women who took daily CE plus MPA. In this substudy, prior use of estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy was reported by 26 percent of the women. The relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.24 and the absolute risk was 41 versus 33 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo [ see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )  ]. Among women who reported prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.86, and the absolute risk was 46 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported no prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.09, and the absolute risk was 40 versus 36 cases per 10,000 women-years for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. In the same substudy, invasive breast cancers were larger, were more likely to be node positive, and were diagnosed at a more advanced stage in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group compared with the placebo group. Metastatic disease was rare, with no apparent difference between the two groups. Other prognostic factors, such as histologic subtype, grade and hormone receptor status did not differ between the groups  6   [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )].  



 Consistent with the WHI clinical trial, observational studies have also reported an increased risk of breast cancer for estrogen plus progestin therapy, and a smaller increased risk for estrogen-alone therapy, after several years of use. The risk increased with duration of use, and appeared to return to baseline over about 5 years after stopping treatment (only the observational studies have substantial data on risk after stopping). Observational studies also suggest that the risk of breast cancer was greater, and became apparent earlier, with estrogen plus progestin therapy as compared to estrogen-alone therapy. However, these studies have not found significant variation in the risk of breast cancer among different estrogens or among different estrogen plus progestin combinations, doses, or routes of administration.



 The use of estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin has been reported to result in an increase in abnormal mammograms requiring further evaluation.



 All women should receive yearly breast examinations by a healthcare provider and perform monthly breast self-examinations. In addition, mammography examinations should be scheduled based on patient age, risk factors, and prior mammogram results.



    Ovarian Cancer  



 The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported a statistically non-significant increased risk of ovarian cancer. After an average follow-up of 5.6 years, the relative risk for ovarian cancer for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 1.58 (95 percent CI, 0.77-3.24). The absolute risk for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 4 versus 3 cases per 10,000 women-years.  7  In some epidemiologic studies, the use of estrogen plus progestin and estrogen-only products, in particular for 5 or more years, has been associated with an increased risk of ovarian cancer. However, the duration of exposure associated with increased risk is not consistent across all epidemiologic studies and some report no association.



    5.3 Probable Dementia



  In the WHIMS estrogen-alone ancillary study of the WHI, a population of 2,947 hysterectomized women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone or placebo.



 After an average follow-up of 5.2 years, 28 women in the estrogen-alone group and 19 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 1.49 (95 percent CI, 0.83-2.66). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 37 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years  8   [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ) and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  .



 In the WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study, a population of 4,532 postmenopausal women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) or placebo. After an average follow-up of 4 years, 40 women in the CE plus MPA group and 21 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 2.05 (95 percent CI, 1.21-3.48). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 45 versus 22 cases per 10,000 women-years  8   [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ) and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  .



 When data from the two populations in the WHIMS estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin ancillary studies were pooled as planned in the WHIMS protocol, the reported overall relative risk for probable dementia was 1.76 (95 percent CI, 1.19-2.60). Since both ancillary studies were conducted in women 65 to 79 years of age, it is unknown whether these findings apply to younger postmenopausal women  8   [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ) and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  .



    5.4 Unintentional Secondary Exposure to Estrogen



  Postmarketing reports of breast budding and breast masses in prepubertal females and gynecomastia and breast masses in prepubertal males following unintentional secondary exposure to Evamist have been reported. In most cases, the condition resolved with removal of Evamist exposure.



 Unexpected changes in breast tissue or other signs of abnormal sexual development in prepubertal children as well as the possibility of unintentional secondary exposure to Evamist should be brought to the attention of a physician. The physician should identify the cause of abnormal sexual development in the child. If unexpected breast development or changes are determined to be the result of unintentional exposure to Evamist, the physician should counsel the woman on the appropriate use and handling of Evamist when around children. Women should cover the Evamist application site with clothing if another person may come into contact with the site. Consideration should be given to discontinuing Evamist if conditions for safe use cannot be met [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.2  )]  .



    5.5 Gallbladder Disease



  A 2- to 4-fold increase in the risk of gallbladder disease requiring surgery in postmenopausal women receiving estrogens has been reported.



    5.6 Hypercalcemia



  Estrogen administration may lead to severe hypercalcemia in women with breast cancer and bone metastases. If hypercalcemia occurs, use of the drug should be stopped and appropriate measures taken to reduce the serum calcium level.



    5.7 Visual Abnormalities



  Retinal vascular thrombosis has been reported in women receiving estrogens. Discontinue medication pending examination if there is sudden partial or complete loss of vision, or a sudden onset of proptosis, diplopia, or migraine. If examination reveals papilledema or retinal vascular lesions, estrogens should be permanently discontinued.



    5.8 Addition of a Progestin When a Woman Has Not Had a Hysterectomy



  Studies of the addition of a progestin for 10 or more days of a cycle of estrogen administration, or daily with estrogen in a continuous regimen, have reported a lowered incidence of endometrial hyperplasia than would be induced by estrogen treatment alone. Endometrial hyperplasia may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



 There are, however, possible risks that may be associated with the use of progestins with estrogens compared to estrogen alone regimens. These include an increased risk of breast cancer.



    5.9 Elevated Blood Pressure



  In a small number of case reports, substantial increases in blood pressure have been attributed to idiosyncratic reactions to estrogens. In a large, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial, a generalized effect of estrogens on blood pressure was not seen.



    5.10 Hypertriglyceridemia



  In women with preexisting hypertriglyceridemia, estrogen therapy may be associated with elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis. Consider discontinuation of treatment if pancreatitis occurs.



    5.11 Hepatic Impairment and/or Past History of Cholestatic Jaundice



  Estrogens may be poorly metabolized in women with impaired liver function. For women with a history of cholestatic jaundice associated with past estrogen use or with pregnancy, caution should be exercised, and in the case of recurrence, medication should be discontinued.



    5.12 Hypothyroidism



  Estrogen administration leads to increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels. Women with normal thyroid function can compensate for the increased TBG by making more thyroid hormone, thus maintaining free T4and T3serum concentrations in the normal range. Women dependent on thyroid hormone replacement therapy who are also receiving estrogens may require increased doses of their thyroid hormone replacement therapy. These women should have their thyroid function monitored in order to maintain their free thyroid hormone levels in an acceptable range.



    5.13 Fluid Retention



  Estrogens may cause some degree of fluid retention. Women who have conditions that might be influenced by this factor, such as a cardiac or renal impairment, warrant careful observation when estrogen-alone is prescribed.



    5.14 Hypocalcemia



  Estrogen therapy should be used with caution in women with hypoparathyroidism as estrogen-induced hypocalcemia may occur.



    5.15 Exacerbation of Endometriosis



  A few cases of malignant transformation of residual endometrial implants have been reported in women treated post-hysterectomy with estrogen alone therapy. For women known to have residual endometriosis post-hysterectomy, the addition of progestin should be considered.



     5.16 Hereditary Angiodema  



   Exogenous estrogens may exacerbate symptoms of angioedema in women with hereditary angioedema.  



    5.17 Exacerbation of Other Conditions



  Estrogen therapy may cause an exacerbation of asthma, diabetes mellitus, epilepsy, migraine, porphyria, systemic lupus erythematosus and hepatic hemangiomas and should be used with caution in women with these conditions.



    5.18 Alcohol-Based Products are Flammable



  Avoid fire, flame or smoking until the spray has dried.



    5.19 Application of Sunscreen



  When sunscreen is applied approximately one hour after application of Evamist, estradiol absorption was decreased by 11 percent. When sunscreen is applied approximately one hour before the application of Evamist, no significant change in estradiol absorption was observed.



    5.20 Laboratory Tests



  Serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels have not been shown to be useful in the management of moderate to severe vasomotor symptoms.



    5.21 Drug and Laboratory Test Interactions



  Accelerated prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet aggregation time; increased platelet count; increased factors II, VII antigen, VIII antigen, VIII coagulant activity, IX, X, XII, VII-X complex, II-VII-X complex, and beta- thromboglobulin; decreased levels of antifactor Xa and antithrombin III, decreased antithrombin III activity; increased levels of fibrinogen and fibrinogen activity; increased plasminogen antigen and activity.



 Increased TBG levels leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone levels, as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T4levels (by column or by radioimmunoassay) or T3levels by radioimmunoassay. T3resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG. Free T4and free T3concentrations are unaltered. Women on thyroid hormone replacement therapy may require higher doses of thyroid hormone.



 Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum, for example, corticosteroid binding globulin (CBG), sex hormone binding globulin (SHBG), leading to increased total circulating corticosteroids and sex steroids, respectively. Free hormone concentrations, such as testosterone and estradiol, may be decreased. Other plasma proteins may be increased (angiotensinogen/rennin substrate, alpha-1-antitrypsin, ceruloplasmin).



 Increased plasma high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and HDL2cholesterol subfraction concentrations, reduced low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol concentration, increased triglyceride levels.



 Impaired glucose tolerance.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
