<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="evarrest" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The adverse reactions reported during clinical trials were blood fibrinogen increased, post procedural and intra-abdominal hemorrhage, abdominal distension, anemia, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, thoracic cavity drainage, pleural effusion, post-procedural bile leak, abdominal abscess, ascites, deep vein thrombosis, localized intra-abdominal fluid collection, and pulmonary embolism.



   EXCERPT:   The adverse reactions reported during clinical trials were blood fibrinogen increased, post procedural and intra-abdominal hemorrhage, abdominal distension, anemia, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, thoracic cavity drainage, pleural effusion, post-procedural bile leak, abdominal abscess, ascites, deep vein thrombosis, localized intra-abdominal fluid collection, and pulmonary embolism.  (  6  )  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ETHICON Customer Support Center at 1-877-384-4266 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates of adverse reactions in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 EVARREST  (r)  was used to treat soft tissue bleeding during retroperitoneal, intra-abdominal, pelvic, or thoracic surgery, suture hole bleeding during cardiovascular surgery, and parenchymal bleeding during hepatic or renal surgery across all clinical trials involving 306 subjects treated with EVARREST and 191 control subjects. Of the 306 subjects, 302 subjects were treated with EVARREST as an adjunct to hemostasis. Twenty-eight percent (28%) of treated subjects (87 subjects out of 306) and 35% of control subjects (67 subjects out of 191) experienced one or more serious adverse events.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials 
 Adverse Reactions                      EVARREST TotalN=306n(%)  EVARREST RandomizedN=225n(%)    CONTROLN=191n(%)      
  
 Blood fibrinogen increased                    3 (1%)                 3 (1%)                 1 (1%)           
 Post procedural hemorrhage                    2 (1%)                 2 (1%)                 2 (1%)           
 Abdominal distension                          1 (0%)                 1 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Intra-abdominal hemorrhage                    1 (0%)                 1 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Anemia                                        1 (0%)                 1 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Gastrointestinal hemorrhage                   1 (0%)                 1 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Thoracic cavity drainage                      1 (0%)                 1 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Pleural effusion                              1 (0%)                 1 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Post-procedural bile leak Abdominal           1 (0%)                 1 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 abscess                                       1 (0%)                 0 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Ascites                                       1 (0%)                 0 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Deep vein thrombosis                          1 (0%)                 0 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Localized intra-abdominal fluid collection         1 (0%)                 0 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
 Pulmonary embolism                            1 (0%)                 0 (0%)                 0 (0%)           
          Demographic characteristics (gender, race, body mass index) were balanced across the treatment groups. No significant differences were observed in the occurrence of adverse reactions between demographic groups.
 

 Immunogenicity was evaluated in soft tissue clinical studies by testing blood samples collected at baseline, 4 to 6 weeks, and 8 to 10 weeks post-surgery for antibodies to human thrombin and fibrinogen by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays. Three subjects out of 145 (~2%) in the group treated with EVARREST showed an increase in the titer of anti-thrombin antibodies after treatment. Two subjects out of 145 (~1%) in the group treated with EVARREST showed a transient increase in fibrinogen antibody titers, with titer levels back at background levels at the 8 to 10 week time point. No immune response to fibrinogen was detected in any of the other subjects.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Thrombosis can occur if absorbed systemically. Apply topically to the bleeding site only. (   5.1   ) 
 *  Can cause hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis. (   5.2   ) 
 *  Avoid application to contaminated areas of the body or in the presence of active infection. Infection can occur. (   5.3   ) 
 *  EVARREST  (r)  contains oxidized regenerated cellulose which adheres to bleeding surfaces. Inadvertent adhesions can occur. (   5.4   ) 
 *  Avoid use in closed spaces (e.g., in, around, or in proximity to, foramina in bone or areas of bony confine) where swelling may cause compression. (   5.5   ) 
 *  Use the least number of patches required to cover the entire bleeding area. (   5.6   ) 
 *  May carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. (   5.7   ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thrombosis



  Thrombosis can occur if EVARREST  (r)  is absorbed systemically. Apply EVARREST topically to the bleeding site only.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  EVARREST  (r)  can cause hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic reactions. Symptoms associated with allergic anaphylactic reactions include flush, urticaria, pruritus, nausea, drop in blood pressure, tachycardia or bradycardia, dyspnea, severe hypotension and anaphylactic shock.



    5.3 Infection



  Avoid application to contaminated or infected areas of the body, or in the presence of active infection. Infection can occur from application to an infected site.



    5.4 Adhesions



  EVARREST  (r)  contains oxidized regenerated cellulose which adheres to bleeding surfaces. Inadvertent adhesions can occur. Meticulous hemostasis should be achieved, particularly in gynecological procedures, to reduce the potential for postoperative adhesions.



    5.5 Compression



  Avoid using EVARREST  (r)  in closed spaces (e.g., in, around, or in proximity to, foramina in bone or areas of bony confine) where swelling may cause nerve or blood vessel compression.



    5.6 Dislodged Patch Material



  Use the least number of patches possible during surgical procedures because portions of excess patch material can become dislodged and migrate to other areas of the body. For example, during urological procedures dislodged patch material can plug the urethra, ureter, or a catheter.



    5.7 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because the biological components of this product are made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. The risk of transmitting viral agents has been minimized by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, by testing for the presence of certain current virus infections, and by inactivating and removing certain viruses during the manufacturing process [see  Description (11)  ]  . Despite these measures, such products still potentially can transmit disease. There is also the possibility that unknown infectious agents may be present in such products.



 Any infection considered by a physician to possibly have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to ETHICON Customer Support Center at 1-877-384-4266.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
