<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="evicel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions reported in clinical trials (&gt;=5%) are bradycardia, nausea, hypokalemia, insomnia, hypotension, pyrexia, graft infection, vascular graft occlusion, peripheral edema, and constipation  (  6.1  )  .



 The most common additional adverse reactions reported in post-marketing experience are edema, pyrexia, seroma, hematoma, tachycardia, dyspnea and urticaria  (  6.2  )  .



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact  ETHICON Customer Support Center at (877) 384-4266  or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The following adverse reactions which occurred during clinical studies were evaluated as having a possible causal relationship to treatment with EVICEL  (r)  (Table 4). The frequency of all of the reactions listed below was common (defined as &gt; 1/100, &lt; 1/10).



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions Clinical Trials Experience 
 MedDRA System Organ Class                           Preferred Term                                       
  
   Adverse Reactions in Retroperitoneal or Intra-Abdominal Surgery Study     
 Infections and infestations                         Abdominal abscess                                    
   Adverse Reactions in Vascular Surgery Study        
 Infections and infestations                         Graft infection, staphylococcal infection            
 Vascular disorders                                  Hematoma                                             
 General disorders and administration site conditions  Edema, peripheral                                    
 Investigations                                      Decreased hemoglobin                                 
 Injury, poisoning and procedural complications      Incision site hemorrhage                             
            Adverse Reaction Rates in Retroperitoneal or Intra-Abdominal Surgery Study  
 

 Among 135 subjects undergoing retroperitoneal and intra-abdominal surgery (67 subjects treated with EVICEL  (r)  and 68 controls), one abdominal abscess in the EVICEL  (r)  group and one abdominal and one pelvic abscess in the control group were considered adverse reactions.



     Adverse Reactions - Vascular Surgery  



 In a controlled study involving 147 subjects undergoing vascular grafting procedures (75 treated with EVICEL  (r)  and 72 controls), nine subjects experienced 12 adverse reactions including graft or staphylococcal infection, hematoma, incision site hemorrhage, peripheral edema and decreased hemoglobin.



     Adverse Reactions - Liver Surgery  



 In a controlled study involving 121 subjects undergoing liver surgery (58 treated with fibrin sealant and 63 controls), no adverse reactions were observed.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  Because the following adverse reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Post-marketing fatalities attributable to air or gas embolism have been reported in association with the use of EVICEL  (r)  when applied using a spray device. These cases have occurred where EVICEL  (r)  was sprayed at a pressure higher than indicated for the device in use and when the spray tip was placed closer than the specified distance from the target site.



 The following adverse reactions have been reported in post-marketing experience with EVICEL    (r)    and are categorized by MedDRA System Organ Class and Preferred Terms in order of decreasing frequency (Table 5):



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions Post-Marketing Experience 
 MedDRA System Organ Class                                     Preferred Term                             
  
 General disorders and administration site conditions          Edema, pyrexia                             
 Injury, poisoning and procedural complications                Seroma                                     
 Vascular disorders                                            Hematoma                                   
 Infections and infestations                                   Abdominal abscess                          
 Cardiac disorders                                             Tachycardia, cardiac arrest                
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders               Dyspnea, pulmonary embolism                
 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                        Urticaria                                  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Life-threatening air or gas embolism has occurred with the use of spray devices employing a pressure regulator to administer EVICEL   (r)   . This event appears to be related to the use of the spray device at pressures higher than recommended and/or at distances closer than recommended to the surface of the tissue (  5.1  ) . 
 *  Monitor changes in blood pressure, pulse, oxygen saturation and end-tidal CO2when spraying EVICEL   (r)   because of the possibility of gas embolism (  5.1  ) . 
 *  To reduce the risk of potentially life-threatening gas embolism, spray EVICEL   (r)   using only pressurized CO2gas at the pressures and distances recommended for the specific tips (  2.3  ) . 
 *  Use EVICEL   (r)   spray application only if it is possible to accurately judge the spray distance, especially during endoscopic or laparoscopic procedures (  2.3  ,  4.4  ) . 
 *  Apply EVICEL   (r)   as a thin layer (  2.3  ) . 
 *  Prior to applying EVICEL   (r)   , dry surface areas of the wound by standard techniques (e.g. intermittent application of compresses, swabs, use of suction devices) (  2.3  ) . 
 *  Prepare and administer EVICEL   (r)   according to the instructions and with only devices recommended for this product (  2.3  ) . 
 *  May carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent and, theoretically, the classic (CJD) agent (  5.2  ) . 
    
 

   5.1 Application Precautions



   Excessive product application thickness may negatively interfere with the product's efficacy and the wound healing process. Apply EVICEL(r) as a thin layer.  



 To reduce the risk of potentially life threatening air embolism, follow specific spray instructions for the pressure and distance from tissue recommended for each type of surgical procedure and length of application tip [see   Dosage and Administration (2.2)    ].



 Spray EVICEL  (r)  using pressurized CO2gas only.



 The Airless Spray Accessory does not require a connection to CO2supply for spray application.



 Use EVICEL  (r)  spray application only if it is possible to accurately judge the distance from the spray tip to the tissue surface, especially during laparoscopic or endoscopic procedures.



 Monitor changes in blood pressure, pulse, oxygen saturation and end-tidal CO2when spraying EVICEL   (r)    because of the possibility of gas embolism.



 Prior to applying EVICEL  (r)  , dry surface areas of the wound by standard techniques (e.g. intermittent application of compresses, swabs, use of suction devices).



    5.2 Infection Risk from Human Plasma



  Because EVICEL  (r)  is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g. viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent, and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob (CJD) agent. There is also the possibility that unknown infectious agents may be present in such products.



 All infections thought by a physician to have been possibly transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to ETHICON Customer Support Center at (877) 384-4266. The physician should discuss the risks and benefits of this product with the patient.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
