<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="evista" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions (&gt;2% and more common than with placebo) include: hot flashes, leg cramps, peripheral edema, flu syndrome, arthralgia, sweating.  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-545-5979 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1  Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to EVISTA in 8429 patients who were enrolled in placebo-controlled trials, including 6666 exposed for 1 year and 5685 for at least 3 years.



   Osteoporosis Treatment Clinical Trial (MORE)  - The safety of raloxifene in the treatment of osteoporosis was assessed in a large (7705 patients) multinational, placebo-controlled trial. Duration of treatment was 36 months, and 5129 postmenopausal women were exposed to raloxifene hydrochloride (2557 received 60 mg/day, and 2572 received 120 mg/day). The incidence of all-cause mortality was similar among groups: 23 (0.9%) placebo, 13 (0.5%) EVISTA-treated (raloxifene HCl 60 mg), and 28 (1.1%) raloxifene HCl 120 mg women died. Therapy was discontinued due to an adverse reaction in 10.9% of EVISTA-treated women and 8.8% of placebo-treated women.



   Venous Thromboembolism  : The most serious adverse reaction related to EVISTA was VTE (deep venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, and retinal vein thrombosis). During an average of study-drug exposure of 2.6 years, VTE occurred in about 1 out of 100 patients treated with EVISTA. Twenty-six EVISTA-treated women had a VTE compared to 11 placebo-treated women, the hazard ratio was 2.4 (95% confidence interval, 1.2, 4.5), and the highest VTE risk was during the initial months of treatment.



 Common adverse reactions considered to be related to EVISTA therapy were hot flashes and leg cramps. Hot flashes occurred in about one in 10 patients on EVISTA and were most commonly reported during the first 6 months of treatment and were not different from placebo thereafter. Leg cramps occurred in about one in 14 patients on EVISTA.



   Placebo-Controlled Osteoporosis Prevention Clinical Trials  - The safety of raloxifene has been assessed primarily in 12 Phase 2 and Phase 3 studies with placebo, estrogen, and estrogen-progestin therapy control groups. The duration of treatment ranged from 2 to 30 months, and 2036 women were exposed to raloxifene HCl (371 patients received 10 to 50 mg/day, 828 received 60 mg/day, and 837 received from 120 to 600 mg/day).



 Therapy was discontinued due to an adverse reaction in 11.4% of 581 EVISTA-treated women and 12.2% of 584 placebo-treated women. Discontinuation rates due to hot flashes did not differ significantly between EVISTA and placebo groups (1.7% and 2.2%, respectively).



 Common adverse reactions considered to be drug-related were hot flashes and leg cramps. Hot flashes occurred in about one in four patients on EVISTA versus about one in six on placebo. The first occurrence of hot flashes was most commonly reported during the first 6 months of treatment.



 Table 1 lists adverse reactions occurring in either the osteoporosis treatment or in five prevention placebo-controlled clinical trials at a frequency &gt;=2.0% in either group and in more EVISTA-treated women than in placebo-treated women. Adverse reactions are shown without attribution of causality. The majority of adverse reactions occurring during the studies were mild and generally did not require discontinuation of therapy.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Occurring in Placebo-Controlled Osteoporosis Clinical Trials at a Frequency &gt;=2.0% and in More EVISTA-Treated (60 mg Once Daily) Women than Placebo-Treated Women 
                                        Treatment         Prevention        
                                        EVISTAN=2557%     PlaceboN=2576%    EVISTAN=581%      Placebo N=584%    
  Body as a Whole                                                                                               
    Infection                           A                 A                 15.1              14.6              
    Flu Syndrome                        13.5              11.4              14.6              13.5              
    Headache                            9.2               8.5               A                 A                 
    Leg Cramps                          7.0               3.7               5.9               1.9               
    Chest Pain                          A                 A                 4.0               3.6               
    Fever                               3.9               3.8               3.1               2.6               
  Cardiovascular System                                                                                         
    Hot Flashes                         9.7               6.4               24.6              18.3              
    Migraine                            A                 A                 2.4               2.1               
    Syncope                             2.3               2.1               B                 B                 
    Varicose Vein                       2.2               1.5               A                 A                 
  Digestive System                                                                                              
    Nausea                              8.3               7.8               8.8               8.6               
    Diarrhea                            7.2               6.9               A                 A                 
    Dyspepsia                           A                 A                 5.9               5.8               
    Vomiting                            4.8               4.3               3.4               3.3               
    Flatulence                          A                 A                 3.1               2.4               
    Gastrointestinal Disorder           A                 A                 3.3               2.1               
    Gastroenteritis                     B                 B                 2.6               2.1               
  Metabolic and Nutritional                                                                                     
    Weight Gain                         A                 A                 8.8               6.8               
    Peripheral Edema                    5.2               4.4               3.3               1.9               
  Musculoskeletal System                                                                                        
    Arthralgia                          15.5              14.0              10.7              10.1              
    Myalgia                             A                 A                 7.7               6.2               
    Arthritis                           A                 A                 4.0               3.6               
    Tendon Disorder                     3.6               3.1               A                 A                 
  Nervous System                                                                                                
    Depression                          A                 A                 6.4               6.0               
    Insomnia                            A                 A                 5.5               4.3               
    Vertigo                             4.1               3.7               A                 A                 
    Neuralgia                           2.4               1.9               B                 B                 
    Hypesthesia                         2.1               2.0               B                 B                 
  Respiratory System                                                                                            
    Sinusitis                           7.9               7.5               10.3              6.5               
    Rhinitis                            10.2              10.1              A                 A                 
    Bronchitis                          9.5               8.6               A                 A                 
    Pharyngitis                         5.3               5.1               7.6               7.2               
    Cough Increased                     9.3               9.2               6.0               5.7               
    Pneumonia                           A                 A                 2.6               1.5               
    Laryngitis                          B                 B                 2.2               1.4               
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                           
    Rash                                A                 A                 5.5               3.8               
    Sweating                            2.5               2.0               3.1               1.7               
  Special Senses                                                                                                
    Conjunctivitis                      2.2               1.7               A                 A                 
  Urogenital System                                                                                             
    Vaginitis                           A                 A                 4.3               3.6               
    Urinary Tract Infection             A                 A                 4.0               3.9               
    Cystitis                            4.6               4.5               3.3               3.1               
    Leukorrhea                          A                 A                 3.3               1.7               
    Uterine DisorderIncludes only patients with an intact uterus: Prevention Trials: EVISTA, n=354, Placebo, n=364; Treatment Trial: EVISTA, n=1948, Placebo, n=1999.,    3.3               2.3               A                 A                 
    Endometrial Disorder                B                 B                 3.1               1.9               
    Vaginal Hemorrhage                  2.5               2.4               A                 A                 
    Urinary Tract Disorder              2.5               2.1               A                 A                 
        Comparison of EVISTA and Hormone Therapy  - EVISTA was compared with estrogen-progestin therapy in three clinical trials for prevention of osteoporosis. Table 2 shows adverse reactions occurring more frequently in one treatment group and at an incidence &gt;=2.0% in any group. Adverse reactions are shown without attribution of causality.
 

 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported in the Clinical Trials for Osteoporosis Prevention with EVISTA (60 mg Once Daily) and Continuous Combined or Cyclic Estrogen Plus Progestin (Hormone Therapy) at an Incidence &gt;=2.0% in any Treatment Group 
                                   EVISTA(N=317)            Hormone Therapy-Continuous Combined (N=96)    Hormone Therapy-Cyclic (N=219)    
                                   %                        %                        %                        
  Urogenital                                                                                                  
      Breast Pain                  4.4                      37.5                     29.7                     
      Vaginal Bleeding             6.2                      64.2                     88.5                     
  Digestive                                                                                                   
      Flatulence                   1.6                      12.5                     6.4                      
  Cardiovascular                                                                                              
      Hot Flashes                  28.7                     3.1                      5.9                      
  Body as a Whole                                                                                             
      Infection                    11.0                     0                        6.8                      
      Abdominal Pain               6.6                      10.4                     18.7                     
      Chest Pain                   2.8                      0                        0.5                      
        Breast Pain  - Across all placebo-controlled trials, EVISTA was indistinguishable from placebo with regard to frequency and severity of breast pain and tenderness. EVISTA was associated with less breast pain and tenderness than reported by women receiving estrogens with or without added progestin.
 

   Gynecologic Cancers  - EVISTA-treated and placebo-treated groups had similar incidences of endometrial cancer and ovarian cancer.



   Placebo-Controlled Trial of Postmenopausal Women at Increased Risk for Major Coronary Events (RUTH)  - The safety of EVISTA (60 mg once daily) was assessed in a placebo-controlled multinational trial of 10,101 postmenopausal women (age range 55-92) with documented coronary heart disease (CHD) or multiple CHD risk factors. Median study drug exposure was 5.1 years for both treatment groups    [see Clinical Studies (14.3)]    . Therapy was discontinued due to an adverse reaction in 25% of 5044 EVISTA-treated women and 24% of 5057 placebo-treated women. The incidence per year of all-cause mortality was similar between the raloxifene (2.07%) and placebo (2.25%) groups.



 Adverse reactions reported more frequently in EVISTA-treated women than in placebo-treated women included peripheral edema (14.1% raloxifene versus 11.7% placebo), muscle spasms/leg cramps (12.1% raloxifene versus 8.3% placebo), hot flashes (7.8% raloxifene versus 4.7% placebo), venous thromboembolic events (2.0% raloxifene versus 1.4% placebo), and cholelithiasis (3.3% raloxifene versus 2.6% placebo)    [see Clinical Studies (14.3,        14.5)]    .



   Tamoxifen-Controlled Trial of Postmenopausal Women at Increased Risk for Invasive Breast Cancer (STAR)  - The safety of EVISTA 60 mg/day versus tamoxifen 20 mg/day over 5 years was assessed in 19,747 postmenopausal women (age range 35-83 years) in a randomized, double-blind trial. As of 31 December 2005, the median follow-up was 4.3 years. The safety profile of raloxifene was similar to that in the placebo-controlled raloxifene trials    [see Clinical Studies (14.4)]    .



   6.2  Postmarketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions reported very rarely since market introduction include retinal vein occlusion, stroke, and death associated with venous thromboembolism (VTE).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED RISK OF VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM AND DEATH FROM STROKE

  WARNING: INCREASED RISK OF VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM AND DEATH FROM STROKE

  



 *  Increased risk of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism have been reported with EVISTA [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. Women with active or past history of venous thromboembolism should not take EVISTA [see Contraindications (4.1)]. 
 *  Increased risk of death due to stroke occurred in a trial in postmenopausal women with documented coronary heart disease or at increased risk for major coronary events. Consider risk-benefit balance in women at risk for stroke [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) and Clinical Studies (14.5)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: INCREASED RISK OF VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLISM AND DEATH FROM STROKE  
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 



 *  Increased risk of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism have been reported with EVISTA (5.1). Women with active or past history of venous thromboembolism should not take EVISTA (4.1). 
 *  Increased risk of death due to stroke occurred in a trial in postmenopausal women with documented coronary heart disease or at increased risk for major coronary events. Consider risk-benefit balance in women at risk for stroke (5.2, 14.5). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    EXCERPT:   



 *    Venous Thromboembolism : Increased risk of deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, and retinal vein thrombosis. Discontinue use 72 hours prior to and during prolonged immobilization.  (5.1,    6.1)  



 
 *    Death Due to Stroke : Increased risk of death due to stroke occurred in a trial in postmenopausal women with documented coronary heart disease or at increased risk for major coronary events. No increased risk of stroke was seen in this trial. Consider risk-benefit balance in women at risk for stroke.  (5.2,    14.5)  



 
 *    Cardiovascular Disease : EVISTA should not be used for the primary or secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease.  (5.3,    14.5)  



 
 *    Premenopausal Women : Use is not recommended.  (5.4)  



 
 *    Hepatic Impairment : Use with caution.  (5.5)  



 
 *    Concomitant Use with Systemic Estrogens : Not recommended.  (5.6)  



 
 *    Hypertriglyceridemia : If previous treatment with estrogen resulted in hypertriglyceridemia, monitor serum triglycerides.  (5.7)  



 
    



   5.1  Venous Thromboembolism



  In clinical trials, EVISTA-treated women had an increased risk of venous thromboembolism (deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism). Other venous thromboembolic events also could occur. A less serious event, superficial thrombophlebitis, also has been reported more frequently with EVISTA than with placebo. The greatest risk for deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism occurs during the first 4 months of treatment, and the magnitude of risk appears to be similar to the reported risk associated with use of hormone therapy. Because immobilization increases the risk for venous thromboembolic events independent of therapy, EVISTA should be discontinued at least 72 hours prior to and during prolonged immobilization (e.g., post-surgical recovery, prolonged bed rest), and EVISTA therapy should be resumed only after the patient is fully ambulatory. In addition, women taking EVISTA should be advised to move about periodically during prolonged travel. The risk-benefit balance should be considered in women at risk of thromboembolic disease for other reasons, such as congestive heart failure, superficial thrombophlebitis, and active malignancy   [see Contraindications (4.1)       and Adverse Reactions (6.1)]    .



    5.2  Death Due to Stroke



  In a clinical trial of postmenopausal women with documented coronary heart disease or at increased risk for coronary events, an increased risk of death due to stroke was observed after treatment with EVISTA. During an average follow-up of 5.6 years, 59 (1.2%) EVISTA-treated women died due to a stroke compared to 39 (0.8%) placebo-treated women (22 versus 15 per 10,000 women-years; hazard ratio 1.49; 95% confidence interval, 1.00-2.24; p=0.0499). There was no statistically significant difference between treatment groups in the incidence of stroke (249 in EVISTA [4.9%] versus 224 placebo [4.4%]). EVISTA had no significant effect on all-cause mortality. The risk-benefit balance should be considered in women at risk for stroke, such as prior stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA), atrial fibrillation, hypertension, or cigarette smoking   [see Clinical Studies (14.5)]    .



    5.3  Cardiovascular Disease



  EVISTA should not be used for the primary or secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease. In a clinical trial of postmenopausal women with documented coronary heart disease or at increased risk for coronary events, no cardiovascular benefit was demonstrated after treatment with raloxifene for 5 years   [see Clinical Studies (14.5)]    .



    5.4  Premenopausal Use



  There is no indication for premenopausal use of EVISTA. Safety of EVISTA in premenopausal women has not been established and its use is not recommended.



    5.5  Hepatic Impairment



  EVISTA should be used with caution in patients with hepatic impairment. Safety and efficacy have not been established in patients with hepatic impairment   [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]    .



    5.6  Concomitant Estrogen Therapy



  The safety of concomitant use of EVISTA with systemic estrogens has not been established and its use is not recommended.



    5.7  History of Hypertriglyceridemia when Treated with Estrogens



  Limited clinical data suggest that some women with a history of marked hypertriglyceridemia (&gt;5.6 mmol/L or &gt;500 mg/dL) in response to treatment with oral estrogen or estrogen plus progestin may develop increased levels of triglycerides when treated with EVISTA. Women with this medical history should have serum triglycerides monitored when taking EVISTA.



    5.8  Renal Impairment



  EVISTA should be used with caution in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment. Safety and efficacy have not been established in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment   [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]    .



    5.9  History of Breast Cancer



  EVISTA has not been adequately studied in women with a prior history of breast cancer.



    5.10  Use in Men



  There is no indication for the use of EVISTA in men. EVISTA has not been adequately studied in men and its use is not recommended.



    5.11  Unexplained Uterine Bleeding



  Any unexplained uterine bleeding should be investigated as clinically indicated. EVISTA-treated and placebo-treated groups had similar incidences of endometrial proliferation   [see Clinical Studies (14.1,       14.2)]    .



    5.12  Breast Abnormalities



  Any unexplained breast abnormality occurring during EVISTA therapy should be investigated. EVISTA does not eliminate the risk of breast cancer   [see Clinical Studies (14.4)]    .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
