<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="evotaz" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    cardiac conduction abnormalities [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]  
 *    rash [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]  
 *    effects on serum creatinine [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]  
 *    new onset or worsening renal impairment when used with tenofovir DF [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ]  
 *    nephrolithiasis and cholelithiasis [see ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    
 *    hepatotoxicity [see ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)    
 *    hyperbilirubinemia [see ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)    
    For additional safety information about atazanavir and cobicistat consult the full prescribing information for these individual products.
 

   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions seen with atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat (greater than 2%, Grades 2-4) are jaundice, ocular icterus, and nausea.  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience in Adults

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of atazanavir and cobicistat coadministered as single agents has been established from a Phase 2 trial, Study 105, and a Phase 3 trial, Study 114. In the pooled analysis, 771 HIV-1 infected, antiretroviral treatment-naive adults received for at least 48 weeks:



 *    atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF (N=394) or 
 *    atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF (N=377). 
    The most common adverse reactions (all Grades) and reported in &gt;10% of subjects in the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat group were jaundice (13%), ocular icterus (15%), and nausea (12%); the most common adverse reactions in the atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir group were jaundice (11%), ocular icterus (17%), nausea (11%), and diarrhea (11%).
 

 The proportion of subjects who discontinued study treatment due to adverse events, regardless of severity, was 7% in both the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat and atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir groups. Table 2 lists the frequency of adverse reactions (Grades 2-4) occurring in at least 2% of subjects in the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat group in pooled Studies 105 and 114.



 Table 2: Selected Adverse Reactions (Grades 2-4) Reported in &gt;=2% of HIV-1 Infected Treatment-Naive Adults in the Atazanavir Coadministered with Cobicistat Group in Studies 105 and 114 (Week 48 pooled analysis) a 
                                      Atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF (n=394)      Atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF (n=377)     
  
   Frequencies of adverse reactions are based on Grades 2-4 adverse events attributed to study drugs.   Rash events include dermatitis allergic, drug hypersensitivity, pruritus generalized, eosinophilic pustular folliculitis, rash, rash generalized, rash macular, rash maculopapular, rash morbilliform, rash papular, and urticaria.  a    b     
  
  Jaundice                           5%                                 3%                                 
  Rash b                             5%                                 4%                                 
  Ocular icterus                     3%                                 1%                                 
  Nausea                             2%                                 2%                                 
         Nephrolithiasis has previously been identified in patients receiving atazanavir . In the pooled analysis of Studies 105 and 114 through 48 weeks, 8 subjects (2%) receiving atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat developed nephrolithiasis compared with no subjects in the atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir group. Median time to onset of nephrolithiasis in the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat group was 24 weeks. Causality in these cases could not be determined with certainty, but the majority of renal stone events were not serious and no subject discontinued study drug.  Nephrolithiasis:    [see ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    
 

   Less Common Adverse Reactions

  Selected adverse reactions of at least moderate severity (&gt;= Grade 2) occurring in less than 2% of subjects receiving atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF are listed below. These events have been included because of investigator's assessment of potential causal relationship and were considered serious or have been reported in more than one subject treated with atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat, and reported with greater frequency compared with the atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir group.



 diarrhea, vomiting, upper abdominal pain  Gastrointestinal Disorders:  



 fatigue  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  



 rhabdomyolysis  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  



 headache  Nervous System Disorders:  



 depression, abnormal dreams, insomnia  Psychiatric Disorders:  



 nephropathy, Fanconi syndrome  Renal and Urinary Disorders:  



   Laboratory Abnormalities

  The frequency of laboratory abnormalities (Grades 3-4) occurring in at least 2% of subjects in the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat group in Studies 105 and 114 is presented in Table 3.



 Table 3: Laboratory Abnormalities (Grades 3-4) Reported in &gt;=2% of HIV-1 Infected Treatment-Naive Adults in the Atazanavir Coadministered with Cobicistat Group in Studies 105 and 114 (Week 48 pooled analysis) 
                                       48 weeks Atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF      48 weeks Atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF     
   Laboratory Parameter Abnormality      (n=394)                            (n=377)                           
  
 For subjects with serum amylase &gt;1.5 * upper limit of normal, lipase test was also performed. The frequency of increased lipase (Grades 3-4) occurring in the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat group (N=44) and atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir group (N=34) was 9% and 6%, respectively.  a       
  
  Total Bilirubin (&gt;2.5 * ULN)        65%                                56%                                
  Creatine Kinase (&gt;=10.0 * ULN)      5%                                 6%                                 
  Serum Amylase (&gt;2.0 * ULN) a        4%                                 2%                                 
  ALT (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                    3%                                 2%                                 
  AST (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                    3%                                 2%                                 
  GGT (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                    2%                                 1%                                 
  Urine Glucose (Glycosuria &gt;=1000 mg/dL)    3%                                 1%                                 
  Urine RBC (Hematuria) (&gt;75 RBC/HPF)    3%                                 2%                                 
         Cobicistat, a component of EVOTAZ, has been shown to increase serum creatinine and decrease estimated creatinine clearance due to inhibition of tubular secretion of creatinine without affecting actual renal glomerular function . In Studies 105 and 114, increases in serum creatinine and decreases in estimated creatinine clearance occurred early in treatment in the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat group after which they stabilized. The mean (+/- SD) change in estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) by Cockcroft-Gault method after 48 weeks of treatment was -13.4 +/- 15.2 mL/min in the atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat group and -9.1 +/- 14.7 mL/min in the atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir group.  Increase in Serum Creatinine:    [see and ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    
 

   Serum Lipids

  Changes from baseline in total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, and triglycerides are presented in Table 4. In both groups, mean values for serum lipids remained within the normal range for each laboratory test. The clinical significance of these changes is unknown.



 Table 4: Lipid Values, Mean Change from Baseline, Reported in HIV-1 Infected Treatment-Naive Adults Receiving Atazanavir Coadministered with Cobicistat and Emtricitabine/Tenofovir DF or Atazanavir Coadministered with Ritonavir and Emtricitabine/Tenofovir DF in Studies 105 and 114 (Week 48 pooled analysis) 
                                  Atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF      Atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir and emtricitabine/tenofovir DF     
                                  Baseline mg/dL      Week 48 change from baseline  a        Baseline mg/dL      Week 48 change from baseline  a       
  
   The change from baseline is the mean of within-patient changes from baseline for patients with both baseline and Week 48 values and excludes subjects receiving an HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor drug.  a     
  
  Total Cholesterol (fasted)     164 [N=307]         +4 [N=307]          165 [N=299]         +8 [N=299]          
  HDL-cholesterol (fasted)       44 [N=306]          +3 [N=306]          43 [N=299]          +3 [N=299]          
  LDL-cholesterol (fasted)       102 [N=307]         +5 [N=307]          103 [N=300]         +7 [N=300]          
  Triglycerides (fasted)         128 [N=307]         +15 [N=307]         131 [N=299]         +29 [N=299]         
             6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   See the full prescribing information for atazanavir for postmarketing information on atazanavir.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    PR interval prolongation may occur in some patients. Consider ECG monitoring in patients with preexisting conduction system disease or when administered with other drugs that may prolong the PR interval. , , , , Cardiac conduction abnormalities:   (5.1    6.2    7.3    12.2    17)   
 *    Discontinue if severe rash develops. , , Severe Skin Reactions:   (5.2    6.2    17)   
 *    Assess creatinine clearance (CLcr) before initiating treatment. Consider alternative medications that do not require dosage adjustments in patients with renal impairment.  (5.3)   
 *    When cobicistat, a component of EVOTAZ, is used in combination with a tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (tenofovir DF)-containing regimen, cases of acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome have been reported.  (5.4)   
 *    When used with tenofovir DF, assess urine glucose and urine protein at baseline and monitor CLcr, urine glucose, and urine protein. Monitor serum phosphorus in patients with or at risk for renal impairment. Coadministration with tenofovir DF is not recommended in patients with CLcr below 70 mL/min or in patients also receiving a nephrotoxic agent.  (5.4)   
 *    have been reported. Consider temporary interruption or discontinuation. , Nephrolithiasis and cholelithiasis   (5.5    6.2)   
 *    Patients with hepatitis B or C coinfection are at risk of increased transaminases or hepatic decompensation. Monitor hepatic laboratory tests prior to therapy and during treatment. , , Hepatotoxicity:   (2.4    5.6    8.7)   
 *    The concomitant use of EVOTAZ and certain other medications may result in known or potentially significant drug interactions. Consult the full prescribing information prior to and during treatment for potential drug interactions. ( ,  5.7    7.3)   
 *    EVOTAZ is not recommended for use with atazanavir or cobicistat, with ritonavir or products containing ritonavir, or in combination with other antiretroviral drugs that require CYP3A inhibition to achieve adequate exposures (e.g., other protease inhibitors and elvitegravir). Antiretrovirals that are not recommended:   (5.8)   
 *    Most patients experience asymptomatic increases in indirect bilirubin, which is reversible upon discontinuation. If a concomitant transaminase increase occurs, evaluate for alternative etiologies. , Hyperbilirubinemia:   (5.9    6.1)   
 *    Patients receiving EVOTAZ may develop immune reconstitution syndrome , new onset or exacerbations of diabetes mellitus/hyperglycemia , , and redistribution/accumulation of body fat .  (5.10)    (5.11    6.2)    (5.12)   
 *    Spontaneous bleeding may occur and additional factor VIII may be required. Hemophilia:   (5.13)   
    
 

   5.1 Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities



  Atazanavir prolongs the PR interval of the electrocardiogram in some patients. In healthy volunteers and in patients, abnormalities in atrioventricular (AV) conduction were asymptomatic and generally limited to first-degree AV block. There have been reports of second-degree AV block and other conduction abnormalities . In clinical trials of atazanavir that included electrocardiograms, asymptomatic first-degree AV block was observed in 6% of atazanavir-treated patients (n=920) and 5% of patients (n=118) treated with atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir. Because of limited clinical experience in patients with preexisting conduction system disease (e.g., marked first-degree AV block or second- or third-degree AV block), consider ECG monitoring in these patients. [see and ]  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    Overdosage (10)     [See .]  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    



    5.2 Severe Skin Reactions



  Cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiforme, and toxic skin eruptions, including drug rash, eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS) syndrome, have been reported in patients receiving atazanavir. EVOTAZ should be discontinued if severe rash develops. [See and .]  Contraindications (4)    Adverse Reactions (6.1)    



 Mild-to-moderate maculopapular skin eruptions have also been reported in atazanavir clinical trials. These reactions had a median time to onset of 7.3 weeks and median duration of 1.4 weeks and generally did not result in treatment discontinuation.



    5.3 Effects on Serum Creatinine



  Cobicistat decreases estimated creatinine clearance due to inhibition of tubular secretion of creatinine without affecting actual renal glomerular function. This effect should be considered when interpreting changes in estimated creatinine clearance in patients initiating EVOTAZ, particularly in patients with medical conditions or receiving drugs needing monitoring with estimated creatinine clearance.



 Prior to initiating therapy with EVOTAZ, assess estimated creatinine clearance . Dosage recommendations are not available for drugs that require dosage adjustments in cobicistat-treated patients with renal impairment . Consider alternative medications that do not require dosage adjustments in patients with renal impairment. [see ]  Dosage and Administration (2.2)     [see , , and ]  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    Drug Interactions (7.3)    Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    



 Although cobicistat may cause modest increases in serum creatinine and modest declines in estimated creatinine clearance without affecting renal glomerular function, patients who experience a confirmed increase in serum creatinine of greater than 0.4 mg/dL from baseline should be closely monitored for renal safety.



    5.4 New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment When Used with Tenofovir DF



  Renal impairment, including cases of acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome, has been reported when cobicistat was used in an antiretroviral regimen that contained tenofovir DF. Therefore, coadministration of EVOTAZ and tenofovir DF is not recommended in patients who have an estimated creatinine clearance below 70 mL/min . [see ]  Dosage and Administration (2.3)    



 *    When EVOTAZ is used with tenofovir DF, document urine glucose and urine protein at baseline and perform routine monitoring of estimated creatinine clearance, urine glucose, and urine protein during treatment. 
 *    Measure serum phosphorus in patients at risk for renal impairment. 
 *    Coadministration of EVOTAZ and tenofovir DF in combination with concomitant or recent use of a nephrotoxic agent is not recommended. 
    In the clinical trials over 48 weeks (N=771), six (1.5%) subjects treated with atazanavir coadministered with cobicistat and tenofovir DF discontinued study drug due to a renal adverse event, five of which had laboratory findings consistent with proximal renal tubulopathy. None of the five subjects had renal impairment at baseline (e.g., estimated creatinine clearance less than 70 mL/min). The laboratory findings in these five subjects with evidence of proximal tubulopathy improved but did not completely resolve in all subjects upon discontinuation of cobicistat coadministered with atazanavir and tenofovir DF. Renal replacement therapy was not required in any subject.
 

    5.5 Nephrolithiasis and Cholelithiasis



  Cases of nephrolithiasis and/or cholelithiasis have been reported during postmarketing surveillance in HIV-infected patients receiving atazanavir therapy. Some patients required hospitalization for additional management and some had complications. Because these events were reported voluntarily during clinical practice, estimates of frequency cannot be made. If signs or symptoms of nephrolithiasis and/or cholelithiasis occur, temporary interruption or discontinuation of therapy may be considered. [See , .]  Adverse Reactions (6.1    6.2)    



    5.6 Hepatotoxicity



  Patients with underlying hepatitis B or C viral infections or marked elevations in transaminases may be at increased risk for developing further transaminase elevations or hepatic decompensation. In these patients, hepatic laboratory testing should be conducted prior to initiating therapy with EVOTAZ and during treatment. [See and .]  Dosage and Administration (2.4)    Use in Specific Populations (8.7)    



    5.7 Risk of Serious Adverse Reactions or Loss of Virologic Response Due to Drug Interactions



   Initiation of EVOTAZ, a CYP3A inhibitor, in patients receiving medications metabolized by CYP3A or initiation of medications metabolized by CYP3A in patients already receiving EVOTAZ, may increase plasma concentrations of medications metabolized by CYP3A.  



  Initiation of medications that inhibit or induce CYP3A may increase or decrease concentrations of EVOTAZ, respectively. These interactions may lead to:  



 *       clinically significant adverse reactions, potentially leading to severe, life threatening, or fatal events from greater exposures of concomitant medications.  
 *       clinically significant adverse reactions from greater exposures of EVOTAZ.  
 *       loss of therapeutic effect of EVOTAZ and possible development of resistance.  
     See Table 5 for steps to prevent or manage these possible and known significant drug interactions, including dosing recommendations [see ]. Consider the potential for drug interactions prior to and during EVOTAZ therapy; review concomitant medications during EVOTAZ therapy; and monitor for the adverse reactions associated with the concomitant medications [see and ].   Drug Interactions (7)       Contraindications (4)       Drug Interactions (7)      
 

 When used with concomitant medications, EVOTAZ may result in different drug interactions than those observed or expected with atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir. Complex or unknown mechanisms of drug interactions preclude extrapolation of drug interactions with atazanavir coadministered with ritonavir to certain EVOTAZ interactions . [see , and ]  Drug Interactions (7)    Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    



    5.8 Antiretrovirals that are Not Recommended



  EVOTAZ is not recommended in combination with other antiretroviral drugs that require CYP3A inhibition to achieve adequate exposures (e.g., other HIV protease inhibitors or elvitegravir) because dosing recommendations for such combinations have not been established and coadministration may result in decreased plasma concentrations of the antiretroviral agents, leading to loss of therapeutic effect and development of resistance.



 EVOTAZ is not recommended in combination with products containing the individual components of EVOTAZ (atazanavir or cobicistat).



 EVOTAZ is not recommended in combination with ritonavir or products containing ritonavir due to similar effects of cobicistat and ritonavir on CYP3A.



 See for additional recommendations on use with other antiretroviral agents.   Drug Interactions (7)    



    5.9 Hyperbilirubinemia



  Most patients taking atazanavir experience asymptomatic elevations in indirect (unconjugated) bilirubin related to inhibition of UDP-glucuronosyltransferase (UGT). This hyperbilirubinemia is reversible upon discontinuation of atazanavir. Hepatic transaminase elevations that occur with hyperbilirubinemia should be evaluated for alternative etiologies. No long-term safety data are available for patients experiencing persistent elevations in total bilirubin greater than 5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN). Alternative antiretroviral therapy to EVOTAZ may be considered if jaundice or scleral icterus associated with bilirubin elevations presents cosmetic concerns for patients. [See .]  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    



    5.10 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including atazanavir, a component of EVOTAZ. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as infection, cytomegalovirus, pneumonia, or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment. Mycobacterium avium   Pneumocystis jiroveci  



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.11 Diabetes Mellitus/Hyperglycemia



  New-onset diabetes mellitus, exacerbation of preexisting diabetes mellitus, and hyperglycemia have been reported during postmarketing surveillance in HIV-infected patients receiving protease inhibitor therapy. Some patients required either initiation or dose adjustments of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents for treatment of these events. In some cases, diabetic ketoacidosis has occurred. In those patients who discontinued protease inhibitor therapy, hyperglycemia persisted in some cases. Because these events have been reported voluntarily during clinical practice, estimates of frequency cannot be made and a causal relationship between protease inhibitor therapy and these events has not been established.



    5.12 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.13 Hemophilia



  There have been reports of increased bleeding, including spontaneous skin hematomas and hemarthrosis, in patients with hemophilia type A and B treated with protease inhibitors. In some patients additional factor VIII was given. In more than half of the reported cases, treatment with protease inhibitors was continued or reintroduced. A causal relationship between protease inhibitor therapy and these events has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
