<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="evzio0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Precipitation of Severe Opioid Withdrawal [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
    Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

 The following adverse reactions were observed in EVZIO clinical studies. In two pharmacokinetic studies with a total of 54 healthy adult subjects exposed to 0.4 mg EVZIO, 0.8 mg EVZIO (two 0.4 mg EVZIOs) or 2 mg EVZIO, adverse reactions occurring in more than one subject were dizziness and injection site erythema.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of naloxone hydrochloride in the post-operative setting. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: Hypotension, hypertension, ventricular tachycardia and fibrillation, dyspnea, pulmonary edema, and cardiac arrest. Death, coma, and encephalopathy have been reported as sequelae of these events. Excessive doses of naloxone hydrochloride in post-operative patients have resulted in significant reversal of analgesia and have caused agitation  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .



 Other events that have been reported in post-marketing use of EVZIO include agitation, disorientation, confusion, and anger.



 Abrupt reversal of opioid effects in persons who were physically dependent on opioids has precipitated an acute withdrawal syndrome. Signs and symptoms have included: body aches, fever, sweating, runny nose, sneezing, piloerection, yawning, weakness, shivering or trembling, nervousness, restlessness or irritability, diarrhea, nausea or vomiting, abdominal cramps, increased blood pressure, tachycardia. In the neonate, opioid withdrawal signs and symptoms also included: convulsions, excessive crying, hyperactive reflexes  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .



   EXCERPT:   The following adverse reactions were most commonly observed in EVZIO clinical studies: dizziness and injection site erythema. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact contact kaleo, Inc. at 1-855-773-8946 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Risk of Recurrent Respiratory and CNS Depression : Due to the duration of action of naloxone relative to the opioid, keep the patient under continued surveillance and administer repeated doses of naloxone using a new EVZIO, as necessary, while awaiting emergency medical assistance. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Risk of Limited Efficacy with Partial Agonists or Mixed Agonists/Antagonists : Reversal of respiratory depression caused by partial agonists or mixed agonists/antagonists such as buprenorphine and pentazocine, may be incomplete. Larger or repeat doses may be required. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Precipitation of Severe Opioid Withdrawal : Use in patients who are opioid dependent may precipitate opioid withdrawal. In neonates, opioid withdrawal may be life-threatening if not recognized and properly treated. Monitor for the development of opioid withdrawal. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Risk of Cardiovascular (CV) Effects : Abrupt postoperative reversal of opioid depression may results in adverse CV effects. These events have primarily occurred in patients who had pre-existing CV disorders or received other drugs that may have similar CV effects. Monitor these patients closely in an appropriate healthcare setting after use of naloxone hydrochloride. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Recurrent Respiratory and Central Nervous System Depression



  The duration of action of most opioids may exceed that of EVZIO resulting in a return of respiratory and/or central nervous system depression after an initial improvement in symptoms. Therefore, it is necessary to seek emergency medical assistance immediately after delivering the first dose of EVZIO. Keep the patient under continued surveillance, and administer additional doses of EVZIO as necessary [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  . Additional supportive and/or resuscitative measures may be helpful while awaiting emergency medical assistance.



    5.2 Risk of Limited Efficacy with Partial Agonists or Mixed Agonist/Antagonists



  Reversal of respiratory depression by partial agonists or mixed agonist/antagonists such as buprenorphine and pentazocine, may be incomplete. Larger or repeat doses of naloxone hydrochloride may be required to antagonize buprenorphine because the latter has a long duration of action due to its slow rate of binding and subsequent slow dissociation from the opioid receptor [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )]  . Buprenorphine antagonism is characterized by a gradual onset of the reversal effects and a decreased duration of action of the normally prolonged respiratory depression.



    5.3 Precipitation of Severe Opioid Withdrawal



  The use of EVZIO in patients who are opioid dependent may precipitate an acute abstinence syndrome characterized by the following signs and symptoms: body aches, diarrhea, tachycardia, fever, runny nose, sneezing, piloerection, sweating, yawning, nausea or vomiting, nervousness, restlessness or irritability, shivering or trembling, abdominal cramps, weakness, and increased blood pressure. In neonates, opioid withdrawal may be life-threatening if not recognized and properly treated and may include the following signs and symptoms: convulsions, excessive crying and hyperactive reflexes. Monitor patients for the development of the signs and symptoms of opioid withdrawal.



 Abrupt postoperative reversal of opioid depression after using naloxone hydrochloride may result in nausea, vomiting, sweating, tremulousness, tachycardia, hypotension, hypertension, seizures, ventricular tachycardia and fibrillation, pulmonary edema, and cardiac arrest. Death, coma, and encephalopathy have been reported as sequelae of these events. These events have primarily occurred in patients who had pre-existing cardiovascular disorders or received other drugs that may have similar adverse cardiovascular effects. Although a direct cause and effect relationship has not been established, after use of naloxone hydrochloride, monitor patients with pre-existing cardiac disease or patients who have received medications with potential adverse cardiovascular effects for hypotension, ventricular tachycardia or fibrillation, and pulmonary edema in an appropriate healthcare setting. It has been suggested that the pathogenesis of pulmonary edema associated with the use of naloxone hydrochloride is similar to neurogenic pulmonary edema, i.e., a centrally mediated massive catecholamine response leading to a dramatic shift of blood volume into the pulmonary vascular bed resulting in increased hydrostatic pressures.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
