<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="exelon" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . 
 *  Skin Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . 
 *  Other Adverse Reactions from Increased Cholinergic Activity [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)] . 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5% and higher than with placebo): Nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 EXELON PATCH has been administered to 4516 patients with Alzheimer's disease during clinical trials worldwide. Of these, 3005 patients have been treated for at least 26 weeks, 1771 patients have been treated for at least 52 weeks, 974 patients have been treated for at least 78 weeks and 24 patients have been treated for at least 104 weeks.



   Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease  



   24-Week International Placebo-Controlled Trial (Study 1)  



   Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 The most common adverse reactions in patients administered EXELON PATCH in Study 1  [see Clinical Studies (14)]  , defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in the 9.5 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH arm and at a frequency at higher than in the placebo group, were nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea. These reactions were dose-related, with each being more common in patients using the unapproved 17.4 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH than in those using the 9.5 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH.



   Discontinuation Rates  



 In Study 1, which randomized a total of 1195 patients, the proportions of patients in the EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours, EXELON Capsules 6 mg twice daily, and placebo groups who discontinued treatment due to adverse events were 10%, 8%, and 5%, respectively.



 The most common adverse reactions in the EXELON PATCH-treated groups that led to treatment discontinuation in this study were nausea and vomiting. The proportions of patients who discontinued treatment due to nausea were 0.7%, 1.7%, and 1.3% in the EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours, EXELON Capsules 6 mg twice daily, and placebo groups, respectively. The proportions of patients who discontinued treatment due to vomiting were 0%, 2.0%, and 0.3% in the EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours, EXELON Capsules 6 mg twice daily, and placebo groups, respectively.



   Adverse Reactions Observed at an Incidence of &gt;=2%  



 Table 1 lists adverse reactions seen at an incidence of &gt;=2% in either EXELON PATCH-treated group in Study 1 and for which the rate of occurrence was greater for patients treated with that dose of EXELON PATCH than for those treated with placebo. The unapproved 17.4 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH arm is included to demonstrate the increased rates of gastrointestinal adverse reactions over those seen with the 9.5 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH.



 Table 1: Proportion of Adverse Reactions Observed with a Frequency of &gt;=2% and Occurring at a Rate Greater Than Placebo in Study 1 
 *Vomiting was severe in 0% of patients who received EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours, 1% of patients who received EXELON PATCH 17.4 mg/24 hours, 1% of patients who received the EXELON Capsule at doses up to 6 mg twice daily, and 0% of those who received placebo.    
 **Weight Decreased as presented in Table 1 is based upon clinical observations and/or adverse events reported by patients or caregivers. Body weight was also monitored at prespecified time points throughout the course of the clinical study. The proportion of patients who had weight loss equal to or greater than 7% of their baseline weight was 8% of those treated with EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours, 12% of those treated with EXELON PATCH 17.4 mg/24 hours, 11% of patients who received the EXELON Capsule at doses up to 6 mg twice daily and 6% of those who received placebo. It is not clear how much of the weight loss was associated with anorexia, nausea, vomiting, and the diarrhea associated with the drug.   
  
                    EXELON PATCH    9.5 mg/24 hours      EXELON PATCH    17.4 mg/24 hours      EXELON Capsule    6 mg twice daily      Placebo         
 Total Patients Studied  291              303              294              302               
 Total Percentage of Patients with ARs (%)  51               66               63               46                
 Nausea           7                21               23               5                 
 Vomiting*        6                19               17               3                 
 Diarrhea         6                10               5                3                 
 Depression       4                4                4                1                 
 Headache         3                4                6                2                 
 Anxiety          3                3                2                1                 
 Anorexia/Decreased Appetite  3                9                9                2                 
 Weight Decreased**  3                8                5                1                 
 Dizziness        2                7                7                2                 
 Abdominal Pain   2                4                1                1                 
 Urinary Tract Infection  2                2                1                1                 
 Asthenia         2                3                6                1                 
 Fatigue          2                2                1                1                 
 Insomnia         1                4                2                2                 
 Abdominal Pain Upper  1                3                2                2                 
 Vertigo          0                2                1                1                 
             48-Week International Active Comparator-Controlled Trial (Study 2)  
 

   Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 In Study 2  [see Clinical Studies (14)]  of the commonly observed adverse reactions (&gt;=3% in any treatment group) the most frequent event in the EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours group was nausea, followed by vomiting, fall, weight decreased, application site erythema, decreased appetite, diarrhea and urinary tract infection (Table 3). The percentage of patients with these events was higher in the EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours group than in the EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours group. Patients with nausea, vomiting, diarrhea and decreased appetite experienced these reactions more often during the first 4 weeks of the double-blind treatment phase. These reactions decreased over time in each treatment group. Weight decreased was reported to have increased over time in each treatment group.



   Discontinuation Rates  



 Table 2 displays the most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation during the 48-week, double-blind treatment phase in Study 2.



 Table 2: Proportion of Most Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;1% at Any Dose) Leading to Discontinuation During 48-week Double-Blind Treatment Phase in Study 2 
                  EXELON PATCH13.3 mg/24 hours  EXELON PATCH9.5 mg/24 hours  Total             
 Total Patients Studied  280              283              563               
 Total Percentage of Patients with ARs Leading to Discontinuation (%)  9.6              12.7             11.2              
 Vomiting         1.4              0.4              0.9               
 Application site pruritus  1.1              1.1              1.1               
 Aggression       0.4              1.1              0.7               
            Most Common Adverse Reactions &gt;=3%  
 

 Other adverse reactions of interest which occurred less frequently, but which were observed in a markedly higher percentage of patients in the EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours group than in the EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours group in Study 2, included dizziness and upper abdominal pain. The percentage of patients with these reactions decreased over time in each treatment group (Table 3). The adverse reaction severity profile was generally similar for both the EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours and 9.5 mg/24 hours groups.



 Table 3: Proportion of Adverse Reactions Over Time in the 48-week Double-Blind (DB) Treatment Phase (at Least 3% in any Treatment Group) in Study 2 
 *Decreased Weight as presented in Table 3 is based upon clinical observations and/or adverse events reported by patients or caregivers. Body weight was monitored as a vital sign at pre-specified time points throughout the course of the clinical study. The proportion of patients who had weight loss equal to or greater than 7% of their baseline weight was 15.2% of those treated with EXELON PATCH 9.5 mg/24 hours and 18.6% of those treated with EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours during the 48-week double-blind treatment period.   
  
                  Cumulative Week 0 to 48 (DB Phase)  Week 0 to 24 (DB Phase)  Week &gt;24 to 48 (DB Phase)   
 Preferred Term   EXELON PATCH13.3 mg/24 hours  EXELON PATCH9.5 mg/24 hours  EXELON PATCH13.3 mg/24 hours  EXELON PATCH9.5 mg/24 hours  EXELON PATCH13.3 mg/24 hours  EXELON PATCH9.5 mg/24 hours   
 Total Patients Studied  280              283              280              283              241              246               
 Total Percentage of Patients with ARs (%)  75               68               65               55               42               40                
 Nausea           12               5                10               4                4                2                 
 Vomiting         10               5                9                3                3                2                 
 Fall             8                6                4                4                4                3                 
 Weight decreased*  7                3                3                1                5                2                 
 Application site erythema  6                6                6                5                1                2                 
 Decreased appetite  6                3                5                2                2                &lt;1                
 Diarrhea         6                5                5                4                2                &lt;1                
 Urinary tract infection  5                4                3                3                3                2                 
 Agitation        5                5                4                3                1                2                 
 Depression       5                5                3                3                3                2                 
 Dizziness        4                1                3                &lt;1               2                &lt;1                
 Application site pruritus  4                4                4                3                &lt;1               1                 
 Headache         4                4                4                4                &lt;1               &lt;1                
 Insomnia         4                3                2                1                3                2                 
 Abdominal pain upper  4                1                3                1                1                &lt;1                
 Anxiety          4                3                2                2                2                1                 
 Hypertension     3                3                3                2                1                1                 
 Urinary incontinence  3                2                2                1                1                &lt;1                
 Psychomotor hyperactivity  3                3                2                3                2                1                 
 Aggression       2                3                1                3                1                1                 
               Severe Alzheimer's Disease  
 

   24-Week US Controlled Trial (Study 3)  



   Most Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions  



 The most common adverse reactions in patients administered EXELON PATCH in the controlled clinical trial, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in the 13.3 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH arm and at a frequency higher than in the 4.6 mg/24 hours EXELON PATCH were application site erythema, fall, insomnia, vomiting, diarrhea, weight decreased, and nausea (Table 4). Patients in the lower dose group reported more events of agitation, urinary tract infection, and hallucinations than patients in the higher dose group.



   Discontinuation Rates  



 In Study 3  [see Clinical Studies (14)]  , the proportions of patients in the EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours (n=355) and EXELON PATCH 4.6 mg/24 hours (n=359), who discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions were 21% and 14%, respectively.



 The most frequent adverse reaction leading to discontinuation in the 13.3 mg/24 hours treatment group versus the 4.6 mg/24 hours treatment group was agitation (2.8% versus 2.2%), followed by vomiting (2.5% and 1.1%), nausea (1.7% and 1.1%), decreased appetite (1.7% and 0%), aggression (1.1% and 0.3%), fall (1.1% and 0.3%) and syncope (1.1% and 0.3%). Otherwise, all AEs leading to discontinuation were reported in &lt;1% of patients.



   Most Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions &gt;=5%  



 Other adverse reactions of interest which were observed in a higher percentage of patients in the EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours group than in the EXELON PATCH 4.6 mg/24 hours group, included application site erythema, fall, insomnia, vomiting, diarrhea, weight decreased, and nausea (Table 4). Overall, the majority of patients in this study experienced adverse reactions that were mild (30.7%) or moderate (32.1%) in severity. Slightly more patients in the 4.6 mg/24 hours patch group reported mild events than in the 13.3 mg/24 hours patch group, while the numbers of patients reporting moderate events were comparable between groups. Severe adverse reactions were reported at a slightly higher percentage at the higher dose (12.4%) than at the lower dose (10%) treatment groups. With the exception of severe adverse reactions of agitation (13.3 mg: 1.1%; 4.6 mg: 1.4%), fall (13.3 mg: 1.1%) and urinary tract infection (4.6 mg: 1.1%), all adverse reactions reported as severe occurred in less than 1% of patients in either treatment group.



 Table 4: Proportion of Adverse Reactions in the 24-week Double-Blind (DB) Treatment Phase (at Least 5% in Any Treatment Group) in Study 3 
 *Weight Decreased as presented in Table 4 is based upon clinical observations and/or adverse events reported by patients or caregivers. Body weight was monitored as a vital sign at prespecified time points throughout the course of the clinical study. The proportion of patients who had weight loss equal to or greater than 7% of their baseline weight was 11% of those treated with EXELON PATCH 4.6 mg/24 hours and 14.1% of those treated with EXELON PATCH 13.3 mg/24 hours during the 24-week double-blind treatment.   
  
   Preferred term      EXELON PATCH13.3 mg/24 hours      EXELON PATCH4.6 mg/24 hours     
 Total number of patients studied  355              359               
 Total percentage of patients with ARs (%)  75               73                
 Application site erythema  13               12                
 Agitation        12               14                
 Urinary tract infection  8                10                
 Fall             8                6                 
 Insomnia         7                4                 
 Vomiting         7                3                 
 Diarrhea         7                5                 
 Weight decreased*  7                3                 
 Nausea           6                3                 
 Depression       5                4                 
 Decreased appetite  5                1                 
 Anxiety          5                5                 
 Hallucination    2                5                 
           Application Site Reactions  
 

 Application site skin reactions leading to discontinuation were observed in &lt;=2.3% of EXELON PATCH patients. This number was 4.9% and 8.4% in the Chinese population and Japanese population, respectively.



 Cases of skin irritation were captured separately on an investigator-rated skin irritation scale. Skin irritation, when observed, was mostly slight or mild in severity and was rated as severe in &lt;=2.2% of EXELON PATCH patients in a double-blind controlled study and in &lt;=3.7% of EXELON PATCH patients in a double-blind controlled study in Japanese patients.



   Parkinson's Disease Dementia  



   76-week International Open-Label Trial (Study 4)  



 EXELON PATCH has been administered to 288 patients with mild to moderate Parkinson's Disease Dementia in a single, 76-week, open-label, active-comparator safety study. Of these, 256 have been treated for at least 12 weeks, 232 for at least 24 weeks, and 196 for at least 52 weeks.



 Treatment with EXELON PATCH was initiated at 4.6 mg/24 hours and if tolerated the dose was increased after 4 weeks to 9.5 mg/24 hours. EXELON Capsule (target maintenance dose of 12 mg/day) served as the active comparator and was administered to 294 patients. Adverse reactions are presented in Table 5.



 Table 5: Proportion of Adverse Reactions Reported at a Rate &gt;=2% During the Initial 24-Week Period in Study 4 
   Adverse drug reactions      EXELON PATCH     
 Total patients studied  288               
                    Percentage (%)     
   Psychiatric disorders                      
 Insomnia         6                 
 Depression       6                 
 Anxiety          5                 
 Agitation        3                 
   Nervous system disorders                      
 Tremor           7                 
 Dizziness        6                 
 Somnolence       4                 
 Hypokinesia      4                 
 Bradykinesia     4                 
 Cogwheel rigidity  3                 
 Dyskinesia       3                 
   Gastrointestinal disorders                      
 Abdominal pain   2                 
   Vascular disorders                      
 Hypertension     3                 
   General disorders and administration site conditions                      
 Fall             12                
 Application site erythema  11                
 Application site irritation, pruritus, rash  3; 5; 2           
 Fatigue          4                 
 Asthenia         2                 
 Gait disturbance  4                 
        Additional adverse reactions observed during the 76-week prospective, open-label study in patients with dementia associated with Parkinson's disease treated with EXELON PATCH: Frequent (those occurring in at least 1/100 patients): dehydration, weight decreased, aggression, hallucination visual.
 

 In patients with dementia associated with Parkinson's disease the following adverse drug reactions have only been observed in clinical trials with EXELON Capsules: Frequent: nausea, vomiting, decreased appetite, restlessness, worsening of Parkinson's disease, bradycardia, diarrhea, dyspepsia, salivary hypersecretion, sweating increased; Infrequent (those occurring between 1/100 to 1/1000 patients): dystonia, atrial fibrillation, atrioventricular block.



   6.2     Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of EXELON. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



          Hypertension, application site hypersensitivity, urticaria, blister, allergic dermatitis, seizure, Parkinson's         disease (worsening), tachycardia, abnormal liver function tests, disseminated allergic dermatitis, and         tremor.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hospitalization and, rarely, death have been reported due to application of multiple patches at same time. Ensure patients or caregivers receive instruction on proper dosing and administration. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Gastrointestinal adverse reactions: May include significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss, and may necessitate treatment interruption. Dehydration may result from prolonged vomiting or diarrhea and can be associated with serious outcomes. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Application site reactions may occur with the patch form of rivastigmine. Discontinue treatment if application site reactions spread beyond the patch size, if there is evidence of a more intense local reaction (e.g., increasing erythema, edema, papules, vesicles), and if symptoms do not significantly improve within 48 hours after patch removal. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Medication Errors Resulting in Overdose 



  Medication errors with EXELON PATCH have resulted in serious adverse reactions; some cases have required hospitalization, and rarely, led to death. The majority of medication errors have involved not removing the old patch when putting on a new one and the use of multiple patches at one time.



  Instruct patients and their caregivers on important administration instructions for EXELON PATCH [see Dosage and Administration (2.4)]  .  



    5.2     Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions



  EXELON PATCH can cause gastrointestinal adverse reactions, including significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss. Dehydration may result from prolonged vomiting or diarrhea and can be associated with serious outcomes. The incidence and severity of these reactions are dose-related [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . For this reason, initiate treatment with EXELON PATCH at a dose of 4.6 mg/24 hours and titrate to a dose of 9.5 mg/24 hours and then to a dose of 13.3 mg/24 hours, if appropriate [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  .



 If treatment is interrupted for more than 3 days because of intolerance, reinitiate EXELON PATCH with the 4.6 mg/24 hours dose to reduce the possibility of severe vomiting and its potentially serious sequelae. A postmarketing report described a case of severe vomiting with esophageal rupture following inappropriate reinitiation of treatment of an oral formulation of rivastigmine without retitration after 8 weeks of treatment interruption.



 Inform caregivers to monitor for gastrointestinal adverse reactions and to inform the physician if they occur.  It is critical to inform caregivers that if therapy has been interrupted for more than 3 days because of intolerance, the next dose should not be administered without contacting the physician regarding proper retitration.



    5.3     Skin Reactions



   Skin application site reactions may occur with EXELON PATCH These reactions are not in themselves an indication of sensitization. However, use of rivastigmine patch may lead to allergic contact dermatitis.  



 Allergic contact dermatitis should be suspected if application site reactions spread beyond the patch size, if there is evidence of a more intense local reaction (e.g. increasing erythema, edema, papules, vesicles) and if symptoms do not significantly improve within 48 hours after patch removal. In these cases, treatment should be discontinued [see Contraindications (4)]  .



 In patients who develop application site reactions to EXELON PATCH suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis and who still require rivastigmine, treatment should be switched to oral rivastigmine only after negative allergy testing and under close medical supervision. It is possible that some patients sensitized to rivastigmine by exposure to rivastigmine patch may not be able to take rivastigmine in any form.



  There have been isolated postmarketing reports of patients experiencing disseminated allergic dermatitis when administered rivastigmine irrespective of the route of administration (oral or transdermal). In these cases, treatment should be discontinued [see Contraindications (4)]  . Patients and caregivers should be instructed accordingly.  



    5.4     Other Adverse Reactions from Increased Cholinergic Activity



   Neurologic Effects  



  Extrapyramidal Symptoms  : Cholinomimetics, including rivastigmine may exacerbate or induce extrapyramidal symptoms. Worsening of parkinsonian symptoms, particularly tremor, has been observed in patients with dementia associated with Parkinson's disease who were treated with EXELON Capsules.



  Seizures  : Drugs that increase cholinergic activity are believed to have some potential for causing seizures. However, seizure activity also may be a manifestation of Alzheimer's disease.



  Peptic Ulcers/Gastrointestinal Bleeding  



 Cholinesterase inhibitors, including rivastigmine, may increase gastric acid secretion due to increased cholinergic activity. Monitor patients using EXELON PATCH for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers, e.g., those with a history of ulcer disease or those receiving concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). Clinical studies of rivastigmine have shown no significant increase, relative to placebo, in the incidence of either peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding.



  Use with Anesthesia  



 Rivastigmine, as a cholinesterase inhibitor, is likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia.



  Cardiac Conduction Effects  



 Because rivastigmine increases cholinergic activity, use of the EXELON PATCH may have vagotonic effects on heart rate (e.g., bradycardia). The potential for this action may be particularly important in patients with sick sinus syndrome or other supraventricular cardiac conduction conditions. In clinical trials, rivastigmine was not associated with any increased incidence of cardiovascular adverse events, heart rate or blood pressure changes, or ECG abnormalities. 



  Genitourinary Effects  



 Although not observed in clinical trials of rivastigmine, drugs that increase cholinergic activity may cause urinary obstruction.



  Pulmonary Effects  



 Drugs that increase cholinergic activity, including EXELON PATCH should be used with care in patients with a history of asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease.



    5.5     Impairment in Driving or Use of Machinery



  Dementia may cause gradual impairment of driving performance or compromise the ability to use machinery. The administration of rivastigmine may also result in adverse reactions that are detrimental to these functions. During treatment with the EXELON PATCH, routinely evaluate the patient's ability to continue driving or operating machinery.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
