<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="exemestane" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXEMESTANE was generally well tolerated and adverse events were usually mild to moderate.



 In the adjuvant treatment of early breast cancer, adverse events occurring in &gt;=10% of patients in any treatment group (EXEMESTANE vs. tamoxifen) were hot flushes (21.2% vs. 19.9%), fatigue (16.1% vs. 14.7%), arthralgia (14.6% vs. 8.6%), headache (13.1% vs. 10.8%), insomnia (12.4% vs. 8.9%), and increased sweating (11.8% vs. 10.4%). Discontinuation rates due to AEs were similar between EXEMESTANE and tamoxifen (6.3% vs. 5.1%). Incidences of cardiac ischemic events (myocardial infarction, angina, and myocardial ischemia) were EXEMESTANE 1.6%, tamoxifen 0.6%. Incidence of cardiac failure: EXEMESTANE 0.4%, tamoxifen 0.3%.



 In the treatment of advanced breast cancer, the most common adverse events were mild to moderate and included hot flushes (13% vs. 5%), nausea (9% vs. 5%), fatigue (8% vs. 10%), increased sweating (4% vs. 8%), and increased appetite (3% vs. 6%) for EXEMESTANE and megestrol acetate, respectively.



    EXCERPT:    *  Early breast cancer: Adverse events occurring in &gt;=10% of patients in any treatment group (EXEMESTANE vs. tamoxifen) were hot flushes (21.2% vs. 19.9%), fatigue (16.1% vs. 14.7%), arthralgia (14.6% vs. 8.6%), headache (13.1% vs. 10.8%), insomnia (12.4% vs. 8.9%), and increased sweating (11.8% vs. 10.4%). Discontinuation rates due to AEs were similar between EXEMESTANE and tamoxifen (6.3% vs. 5.1%). Incidences of cardiac ischemic events (myocardial infarction, angina, and myocardial ischemia) were EXEMESTANE 1.6%, tamoxifen 0.6%. Incidence of cardiac failure: EXEMESTANE 0.4%, tamoxifen 0.3% (  6  ,  6.1  ). 
 *  Advanced breast cancer: Most common adverse events were mild to moderate and included hot flushes (13% vs. 5%), nausea (9% vs. 5%), fatigue (8% vs. 10%), increased sweating (4% vs. 8%), and increased appetite (3% vs. 6%) for EXEMESTANE and megestrol acetate, respectively (  6  ,  6.1  ). 
    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Adjuvant Therapy  



 The data described below reflect exposure to EXEMESTANE in 2325 postmenopausal women with early breast cancer. EXEMESTANE tolerability in postmenopausal women with early breast cancer was evaluated in two well-controlled trials: the IES study (  14.1  ) and the 027 study (a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, parallel group study specifically designed to assess the effects of EXEMESTANE on bone metabolism, hormones, lipids, and coagulation factors over 2 years of treatment).



 The median duration of adjuvant treatment was 27.4 months and 27.3 months for patients receiving EXEMESTANE or tamoxifen, respectively, within the IES study and 23.9 months for patients receiving EXEMESTANE or placebo within the 027 study. Median duration of observation after randomization for EXEMESTANE was 34.5 months and for tamoxifen was 34.6 months. Median duration of observation was 30 months for both groups in the 027 study.



 Certain adverse events, which were expected based on the known pharmacological properties and side effect profiles of test drugs, were actively sought through a positive checklist. Signs and symptoms were graded for severity using CTC in both studies. Within the IES study, the presence of some illnesses/conditions was monitored through a positive checklist without assessment of severity. These included myocardial infarction, other cardiovascular disorders, gynecological disorders, osteoporosis, osteoporotic fractures, other primary cancer, and hospitalizations.



 EXEMESTANE was generally well tolerated and adverse events were usually mild to moderate. Within the IES study, discontinuations due to adverse events occurred in 6.3% and 5.1% of patients receiving EXEMESTANE and tamoxifen, respectively, and in 12.3% and 4.1% of patients receiving EXEMESTANE or placebo respectively within study 027.



 Deaths due to any cause were reported for 1.3% of the EXEMESTANE treated patients and 1.4% of the tamoxifen treated patients within the IES study. There were 6 deaths due to stroke on the EXEMESTANE arm compared to 2 on tamoxifen. There were 5 deaths due to cardiac failure on the EXEMESTANE arm compared to 2 on tamoxifen.



 The incidence of cardiac ischemic events (myocardial infarction, angina, and myocardial ischemia) was 1.6% in EXEMESTANE treated patients and 0.6% in tamoxifen treated patients in the IES study. Cardiac failure was observed in 0.4% of EXEMESTANE treated patients and 0.3% of tamoxifen treated patients.



 Treatment-emergent adverse events and illnesses including all causalities and occurring with an incidence of &gt;=5% in either treatment group of the IES study during or within one month of the end of treatment are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2. Incidence (%) of Adverse Events of all GradesGraded according to Common Toxicity Criteria; and Illnesses Occurring in (&gt;=5%) of Patients in Any Treatment Group in Study IES in Postmenopausal Women with Early Breast Cancer 
                                                               % of patients          
 Body system and Adverse Event by MedDRA dictionary            EXEMESTANE25 mg daily(N=2252)  Tamoxifen20 mg daily(N=2280)   
  
   Eye                                                                                                      
   Visual disturbances                                         5.0                   3.8                    
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
   Nausea                                                      8.5                   8.7                    
   General Disorders                                                                                        
   Fatigue                                                     16.1                  14.7                   
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                          
   Arthralgia                                                  14.6                  8.6                    
   Pain in limb                                                9.0                   6.4                    
   Back pain                                                   8.6                   7.2                    
   Osteoarthritis                                              5.9                   4.5                    
   Nervous System                                                                                           
   Headache                                                    13.1                  10.8                   
   Dizziness                                                   9.7                   8.4                    
   Psychiatric                                                                                              
   Insomnia                                                    12.4                  8.9                    
   Depression                                                  6.2                   5.6                    
   Skin &amp; Subcutaneous Tissue                                                                               
   Increased sweating                                          11.8                  10.4                   
   Vascular                                                                                                 
   Hot flushes                                                 21.2                  19.9                   
   Hypertension                                                9.8                   8.4                    
         In the IES study, as compared to tamoxifen, EXEMESTANE was associated with a higher incidence of events in musculoskeletal disorders and in nervous system disorders, including the following events occurring with frequency lower than 5% (osteoporosis [4.6% vs. 2.8%], osteochondrosis and trigger finger [0.3% vs. 0 for both events], paresthesia [2.6% vs. 0.9%], carpal tunnel syndrome [2.4% vs. 0.2%], and neuropathy [0.6% vs. 0.1%]). Diarrhea was also more frequent in the EXEMESTANE group (4.2% vs. 2.2%). Clinical fractures were reported in 94 patients receiving EXEMESTANE (4.2%) and 71 patients receiving tamoxifen (3.1%). After a median duration of therapy of about 30 months and a median follow-up of about 52 months, gastric ulcer was observed at a slightly higher frequency in the EXEMESTANE group compared to tamoxifen (0.7% vs. &lt;0.1%). The majority of patients on EXEMESTANE with gastric ulcer received concomitant treatment with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents and/or had a prior history.
 

 Tamoxifen was associated with a higher incidence of muscle cramps [3.1% vs. 1.5%], thromboembolism [2.0% vs. 0.9%], endometrial hyperplasia [1.7% vs. 0.6%], and uterine polyps [2.4% vs. 0.4%].



 Common adverse events occurring in study 027 are described in Table 3.



 Table 3. Incidence of Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events of all CTC GradesMost events were CTC grade 1-2 Occurring in &gt;= 5% of Patients in Either Arm in Study 027 
 Adverse Event                                       EXEMESTANEN=73(% incidence)  PlaceboN=73(% incidence)    
  
 Hot flushes                                         32.9                       24.7                        
 Arthralgia                                          28.8                       28.8                        
 Increased sweating                                  17.8                       20.6                        
 Alopecia                                            15.1                       4.1                         
 Hypertension                                        15.1                       6.9                         
 Insomnia                                            13.7                       15.1                        
 Nausea                                              12.3                       16.4                        
 Fatigue                                             11.0                       19.2                        
 Abdominal pain                                      11.0                       13.7                        
 Depression                                          9.6                        6.9                         
 Diarrhea                                            9.6                        1.4                         
 Dizziness                                           9.6                        9.6                         
 Dermatitis                                          8.2                        1.4                         
 Headache                                            6.9                        4.1                         
 Myalgia                                             5.5                        4.1                         
 Edema                                               5.5                        6.9                         
 Anxiety                                             4.1                        5.5                         
           
     Treatment of Advanced Breast Cancer  



 A total of 1058 patients were treated with EXEMESTANE 25 mg once daily in the clinical trials program. Only one death was considered possibly related to treatment with EXEMESTANE; an 80-year-old woman with known coronary artery disease had a myocardial infarction with multiple organ failure after 9 weeks on study treatment. In the clinical trials program, only 3% of the patients discontinued treatment with EXEMESTANE because of adverse events, mainly within the first 10 weeks of treatment; late discontinuations because of adverse events were uncommon (0.3%).



 In the comparative study, adverse reactions were assessed for 358 patients treated with EXEMESTANE and 400 patients treated with megestrol acetate. Fewer patients receiving EXEMESTANE discontinued treatment because of adverse events than those treated with megestrol acetate (2% vs. 5%). Adverse events that were considered drug related or of indeterminate cause included hot flashes (13% vs. 5%), nausea (9% vs. 5%), fatigue (8% vs. 10%), increased sweating (4% vs. 8%), and increased appetite (3% vs. 6%) for EXEMESTANE and megestrol acetate, respectively. The proportion of patients experiencing an excessive weight gain (&gt;10% of their baseline weight) was significantly higher with megestrol acetate than with EXEMESTANE (17% vs. 8%). Table 4 shows the adverse events of all CTC grades, regardless of causality, reported in 5% or greater of patients in the study treated either with EXEMESTANE or megestrol acetate.



 Table 4. Incidence (%) of Adverse Events of all GradesGraded according to Common Toxicity Criteria and Causes Occurring in &gt;=5% of Advanced Breast Cancer Patients In Each Treatment Arm in the Comparative Study 
 Body system and Adverse Event by WHO ART dictionary           EXEMESTANE25 mg once daily (N=358)  Megestrol Acetate40 mg QID (N=400)   
  
   Autonomic Nervous                                                                                        
   Increased sweating                                          6                     9                      
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Fatigue                                                     22                    29                     
   Hot flashes                                                 13                    6                      
   Pain                                                        13                    13                     
   Influenza-like symptoms                                     6                     5                      
   Edema (includes edema, peripheral edema, leg edema)         7                     6                      
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
   Hypertension                                                5                     6                      
   Nervous                                                                                                  
   Depression                                                  13                    9                      
   Insomnia                                                    11                    9                      
   Anxiety                                                     10                    11                     
   Dizziness                                                   8                     6                      
   Headache                                                    8                     7                      
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
   Nausea                                                      18                    12                     
   Vomiting                                                    7                     4                      
   Abdominal pain                                              6                     11                     
   Anorexia                                                    6                     5                      
   Constipation                                                5                     8                      
   Diarrhea                                                    4                     5                      
   Increased appetite                                          3                     6                      
   Respiratory                                                                                              
   Dyspnea                                                     10                    15                     
   Coughing                                                    6                     7                      
         Less frequent adverse events of any cause (from 2% to 5%) reported in the comparative study for patients receiving EXEMESTANE 25 mg once daily were fever, generalized weakness, paresthesia, pathological fracture, bronchitis, sinusitis, rash, itching, urinary tract infection, and lymphedema.
 

 Additional adverse events of any cause observed in the overall clinical trials program (N = 1058) in 5% or greater of patients treated with EXEMESTANE 25 mg once daily but not in the comparative study included pain at tumor sites (8%), asthenia (6%), and fever (5%). Adverse events of any cause reported in 2% to 5% of all patients treated with EXEMESTANE 25 mg in the overall clinical trials program but not in the comparative study included chest pain, hypoesthesia, confusion, dyspepsia, arthralgia, back pain, skeletal pain, infection, upper respiratory tract infection, pharyngitis, rhinitis, and alopecia.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of EXEMESTANE. Because reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Immune system disorders  - hypersensitivity



   Hepatobiliary disorders  - hepatitis including cholestatic hepatitis



   Nervous system disorders-  paresthesia



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders-  acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, urticaria, pruritus
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Reductions in bone mineral density (BMD) over time are seen with exemestane use (  5.3  ). 
 *  Routine assessment of 25-hydroxy vitamin D levels prior to the start of aromatase inhibitor treatment should be performed (  5.4  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Administration with Estrogen-Containing Agents



  EXEMESTANE should not be coadministered with estrogen-containing agents as these could interfere with its pharmacologic action.



    5.2 Laboratory Tests



  In patients with early breast cancer, the incidence of hematological abnormalities of Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) grade &gt;=1 was lower in the EXEMESTANE treatment group, compared with tamoxifen. Incidence of CTC grade 3 or 4 abnormalities was low (approximately 0.1%) in both treatment groups. Approximately 20% of patients receiving EXEMESTANE in clinical studies in advanced breast cancer experienced CTC grade 3 or 4 lymphocytopenia. Of these patients, 89% had a pre-existing lower grade lymphopenia. Forty percent of patients either recovered or improved to a lesser severity while on treatment. Patients did not have a significant increase in viral infections, and no opportunistic infections were observed. Elevations of serum levels of AST, ALT, alkaline phosphatase, and gamma glutamyl transferase &gt; 5 times the upper value of the normal range (i.e., &gt;= CTC grade 3) have been rarely reported in patients treated for advanced breast cancer but appear mostly attributable to the underlying presence of liver and/or bone metastases. In the comparative study in advanced breast cancer patients, CTC grade 3 or 4 elevation of gamma glutamyl transferase without documented evidence of liver metastasis was reported in 2.7% of patients treated with EXEMESTANE and in 1.8% of patients treated with megestrol acetate.



 In patients with early breast cancer, elevations in bilirubin, alkaline phosphatase, and creatinine were more common in those receiving EXEMESTANE than either tamoxifen or placebo. Treatment-emergent bilirubin elevations (any CTC grade) occurred in 5.3% of EXEMESTANE patients and 0.8% of tamoxifen patients on the Intergroup EXEMESTANE Study (IES), and in 6.9% of EXEMESTANE treated patients vs. 0% of placebo treated patients in the 027 study. CTC grade 3-4 increases in bilirubin occurred in 0.9% of EXEMESTANE treated patients compared to 0.1% of tamoxifen treated patients. Alkaline phosphatase elevations of any CTC grade occurred in 15.0% of EXEMESTANE treated patients on the IES compared to 2.6% of tamoxifen treated patients, and in 13.7% of EXEMESTANE treated patients compared to 6.9% of placebo treated patients in study 027. Creatinine elevations occurred in 5.8% of EXEMESTANE treated patients and 4.3% of tamoxifen treated patients on the IES and in 5.5% of EXEMESTANE treated patients and 0% of placebo treated patients in study 027.



    5.3 Reductions in Bone Mineral Density (BMD)



  Reductions in bone mineral density (BMD) over time are seen with EXEMESTANE use. Table 1 describes changes in BMD from baseline to 24 months in patients receiving EXEMESTANE compared to patients receiving tamoxifen (IES) or placebo (027). Concomitant use of bisphosphonates, vitamin D supplementation, and calcium was not allowed.



 Table 1. Percent Change in BMD from Baseline to 24 months, EXEMESTANE vs. Control1 
                       IES                                         027                                          
 BMD                   EXEMESTANE  N=29      Tamoxifen  1    N=38  EXEMESTANE  N=59      Placebo  1    N=65     
  
 Lumbar spine (%)      -3.14                 -0.18                 -3.51                 -2.35                  
 Femoral neck (%)      -4.15                 -0.33                 -4.57                 -2.59                  
            During adjuvant treatment with exemestane, women with osteoporosis or at risk of osteoporosis should have their bone mineral density formally assessed by bone densitometry at the commencement of treatment. Patients treated with exemestane should be carefully monitored and treatment for osteoporosis should be initiated as appropriate.  
 

    5.4 Vitamin D Assessment



   Routine assessment of 25-hydroxy vitamin D levels prior to the start of aromatase inhibitor treatment should be performed, due to the high prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in women with early breast cancer (EBC). Women with vitamin D deficiency should receive supplementation with vitamin D.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
