<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="exforge1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6              ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   In placebo-controlled clinical trials, discontinuation due to side effects occurred in 1.8% of patients in the Exforge-treated patients and 2.1% in the placebo-treated group. The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy with Exforge were peripheral edema and vertigo. The adverse experiences that occurred in clinical trials (&gt;=2% of patients) at a higher incidence than placebo included peripheral edema, nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection and dizziness. (  6  )



  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.   

    6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



   Studies with    Exforge    :  



 Exforge has been evaluated for safety in over 2,600 patients with hypertension; over 1,440 of these patients were treated for at least 6 months and over 540 of these patients were treated for at least one year. Adverse reactions have generally been mild and transient in nature and have only infrequently required discontinuation of therapy.



 The overall frequency of adverse reactions was neither dose-related nor related to gender, age, or race. In placebo-controlled clinical trials, discontinuation due to side effects occurred in 1.8% of patients in the Exforge-treated patients and 2.1% in the placebo-treated group. The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy with Exforge were peripheral edema (0.4%), and vertigo (0.2%).



 The adverse reactions that occurred in placebo-controlled clinical trials in at least 2% of patients treated with Exforge but at a higher incidence in amlodipine/valsartan patients (n=1,437) than placebo (n=337) included peripheral edema (5.4% vs. 3.0%), nasopharyngitis (4.3% vs. 1.8%), upper respiratory tract infection (2.9% vs 2.1%) and dizziness (2.1% vs 0.9%).



 Orthostatic events (orthostatic hypotension and postural dizziness) were seen in less than 1% of patients.



 Other adverse reactions that occurred in placebo-controlled clinical trials with Exforge (&gt;= 0.2%) are listed below. It cannot be determined whether these events were causally related to Exforge.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Lymphadenopathy



   Cardiac Disorders:  Palpitations, tachycardia



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  Ear pain



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Diarrhea, nausea, constipation, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, gastritis, vomiting, abdominal discomfort, abdominal distention, dry mouth, colitis



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Fatigue, chest pain, asthenia, pitting edema, pyrexia, edema



   Immune System Disorders:  Seasonal allergies



   Infections and Infestations:  Nasopharyngitis, sinusitis, bronchitis, pharyngitis, gastroenteritis, pharyngotonsillitis, bronchitis acute, tonsillitis



   Injury    and    Poisoning  : Epicondylitis, joint sprain, limb injury



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Gout, non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus, hypercholesterolemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Arthralgia, back pain, muscle spasms, pain in extremity, myalgia, osteoarthritis, joint swelling, musculoskeletal chest pain



   Nervous System Disorders:  Headache, sciatica, paresthesia, cervicobrachial syndrome, carpal tunnel syndrome, hypoesthesia, sinus headache, somnolence



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Insomnia, anxiety, depression



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Hematuria, nephrolithiasis, pollakiuria



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  Erectile dysfunction



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Cough, pharyngolaryngeal pain, sinus congestion, dyspnea, epistaxis, productive cough, dysphonia, nasal congestion



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Pruritus, rash, hyperhidrosis, eczema, erythema



   Vascular Disorders:  Flushing, hot flush



 Isolated cases of the following clinically notable adverse reactions were also observed in clinical trials: exanthema, syncope, visual disturbance, hypersensitivity, tinnitus, and hypotension.



   Studies with Amlodipine:  



 Norvasc  (r)    *  has been evaluated for safety in more than 11,000 patients in U.S. and foreign clinical trials. Other adverse events that have been reported &lt;1% but &gt;0.1% of patients in controlled clinical trials or under conditions of open trials or marketing experience where a causal relationship is uncertain were:



   Cardiovascular:  arrhythmia (including ventricular tachycardia and atrial fibrillation), bradycardia, chest pain, peripheral ischemia, syncope, postural hypotension, vasculitis



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  neuropathy peripheral, tremor



   Gastrointestinal:  anorexia, dysphagia, pancreatitis, gingival hyperplasia



   General:  allergic reaction, hot flushes, malaise, rigors, weight gain, weight loss



   Musculoskeletal System:  arthrosis, muscle cramps



   Psychiatric:  sexual dysfunction (male and female), nervousness, abnormal dreams, depersonalization



   Respiratory System:  dyspnea



   Skin and Appendages:  angioedema, erythema multiforme, rash erythematous, rash maculopapular



   Special Senses:  abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, diplopia, eye pain, tinnitus



   Urinary System:  micturition frequency, micturition disorder, nocturia



   Autonomic Nervous System:  sweating increased



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  hyperglycemia, thirst



   Hemopoietic:  leukopenia, purpura, thrombocytopenia



 Other events reported with amlodipine at a frequency of &lt;=0.1% of patients include: cardiac failure, pulse irregularity, extrasystoles, skin discoloration, urticaria, skin dryness, alopecia, dermatitis, muscle weakness, twitching, ataxia, hypertonia, migraine, cold and clammy skin, apathy, agitation, amnesia, gastritis, increased appetite, loose stools, rhinitis, dysuria, polyuria, parosmia, taste perversion, abnormal visual accommodation, and xerophthalmia. Other reactions occurred sporadically and cannot be distinguished from medications or concurrent disease states such as myocardial infarction and angina.



 Adverse reactions reported for amlodipine for indications other than hypertension may be found in the prescribing information for Norvasc.



   Studies with Valsartan:  



 Diovan  (r)  has been evaluated for safety in more than 4,000 hypertensive patients in clinical trials. In trials in which valsartan was compared to an ACE inhibitor with or without placebo, the incidence of dry cough was significantly greater in the ACE inhibitor group (7.9%) than in the groups who received valsartan (2.6%) or placebo (1.5%). In a 129 patient trial limited to patients who had had dry cough when they had previously received ACE inhibitors, the incidences of cough in patients who received valsartan, HCTZ, or lisinopril were 20%, 19%, and 69% respectively (p&lt;0.001).



 Other adverse reactions, not listed above, occurring in &gt;0.2% of patients in controlled clinical trials with valsartan are:



   Body as a Whole:  allergic reaction, asthenia



   Musculoskeletal:  muscle cramps



   Neurologic and Psychiatric:  paresthesia



   Respiratory:       sinusitis, pharyngitis



   Urogenital:   impotence



 Other reported events seen less frequently in clinical trials were: angioedema.



 Adverse reactions reported for valsartan for indications other than hypertension may be found in the prescribing information for Diovan.



     6.2    Post    m    arketing Experience  

    Amlodipine:  Gynecomastia has been reported infrequently and a causal relationship is uncertain. Jaundice and hepatic enzyme elevations (mostly consistent with cholestasis or hepatitis), in some cases severe enough to require hospitalization, have been reported in association with use of amlodipine.



   Valsartan:  The following additional adverse reactions have been reported in postmarketing experience with valsartan:



   Blood and Lymphatic:  There are very rare reports of thrombocytopenia.



   Hypersensitivity:  There are rare reports of angioedema.



   Digestive:  Elevated liver enzymes and very rare reports of hepatitis



   Renal:  Impaired renal function



   Clinical Laboratory Tests:  Hyperkalemia



   Dermatologic:  Alopecia



   Vascular:  Vasculitis



 Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: AVOID USE IN PREGNANCY

    WARNING:     AVOID     USE IN PREGNANCY  

    When pregnancy is detected,     discontinue     Exforge as soon as possible    .     Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus    .     [    See         W    arnings         and     P    recautions         (5.1)    ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:         AVOID     USE IN PREGNANCY       



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    .  



   When pregnancy is detected,     discontinue     Exforge as soon as possible.         D    rugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus. (  5.1  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5           WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Avoid fetal or neonatal exposure (  5.1  ) 
 *  Assess for hypotension. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Warn patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease about the risk of myocardial infarction or increased angina (  5.3  ) 
 *  Titrate slowly in patients with impaired hepatic (  5.4  ) or severely impaired renal (  5.5  ) function 
    
 

    5.1   Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality  



  Exforge can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus .  



 Drugs that act on the renin angiotensin system can cause fetal and neonatal morbidity and mortality when used in pregnancy. In several dozen published cases, ACE inhibitor use during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy was associated with fetal and neonatal injury, including hypotension, neonatal skull hypoplasia, anuria, reversible or irreversible renal failure, and death [ s   ee Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ] .  



     5.2 Hypotension  



  Excessive hypotension was seen in 0.4% of patients with uncomplicated hypertension treated with Exforge in placebo-controlled studies. In patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume-and/or salt-depleted patients receiving high doses of diuretics, symptomatic hypotension may occur in patients receiving angiotensin receptor blockers. Volume depletion should be corrected prior to administration of Exforge. Treatment with Exforge should start under close medical supervision.



 Initiate therapy cautiously in patients with heart failure or recent myocardial infarction and in patients undergoing surgery or dialysis. Patients with heart failure or post-myocardial infarction patients given valsartan commonly have some reduction in blood pressure, but discontinuation of therapy because of continuing symptomatic hypotension usually is not necessary when dosing instructions are followed. In controlled trials in heart failure patients, the incidence of hypotension in valsartan-treated patients was 5.5% compared to 1.8% in placebo-treated patients. In the Valsartan in Acute Myocardial Infarction Trial (VALIANT), hypotension in post-myocardial infarction patients led to permanent discontinuation of therapy in 1.4% of valsartan-treated patients and 0.8% of captopril-treated patients.



 Since the vasodilation induced by amlodipine is gradual in onset, acute hypotension has rarely been reported after oral administration. Nonetheless, caution, as with any other peripheral vasodilator, should be exercised when administering amlodipine, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis.



 If excessive hypotension occurs with Exforge, the patient should be placed in a supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.



     5.3   Risk of   Myocardial Infarction   or Increased Angina      



  Rarely, patients, particularly those with severe obstructive coronary artery disease, have developed documented increased frequency, duration or severity of angina or acute myocardial infarction on starting calcium channel blocker therapy or at the time of dosage increase. The mechanism of this effect has not been elucidated.



     5.4 Impaired Hepatic Function  



   Studies with   A   mlodipine:  Amlodipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and the plasma elimination half-life (t1/2) is 56 hours in patients with impaired hepatic function, therefore, caution should be exercised when administering amlodipine to patients with severe hepatic impairment.



  Studies with   V   alsartan:  As the majority of valsartan is eliminated in the bile, patients with mild-to-moderate hepatic impairment, including patients with biliary obstructive disorders, showed lower valsartan clearance (higher AUCs). Care should be exercised in administering valsartan to these patients.



     5.5 Impaired Renal Function - Hypertension  



  In studies of ACE inhibitors in hypertensive patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen have been reported. In a 4-day trial of valsartan in 12 hypertensive patients with unilateral renal artery stenosis, no significant increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen were observed. There has been no long-term use of valsartan in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but an effect similar to that seen with ACE inhibitors should be anticipated.



 As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, changes in renal function may occur particularly in volume depleted patients. In patients with severe heart failure whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar outcomes have been reported with valsartan.



     5.6 Congestive Heart Failure  



   Studies with   A   mlodipine:  In general, calcium channel blockers should be used with caution in patients with heart failure. Amlodipine (5-10 mg per day) has been studied in a placebo-controlled trial of 1,153 patients with NYHA Class III or IV heart failure on stable doses of ACE inhibitor, digoxin, and diuretics. Follow-up was at least 6 months, with a mean of about 14 months. There was no overall adverse effect on survival or cardiac morbidity (as defined by life-threatening arrhythmia, acute myocardial infarction, or hospitalization for worsened heart failure). Amlodipine has been compared to placebo in four 8-12 week studies of patients with NYHA class II/III heart failure, involving a total of 697 patients. In these studies, there was no evidence of worsened heart failure based on measures of exercise tolerance, NYHA classification, symptoms, or LVEF.



  Studies with   V   alsartan:  Some patients with heart failure have developed increases in blood urea nitrogen, serum creatinine, and potassium on valsartan. These effects are usually minor and transient, and they are more likely to occur in patients with pre-existing renal impairment. Dosage reduction and/or discontinuation of the diuretic and/or valsartan may be required. In the Valsartan Heart Failure Trial, in which 93% of patients were on concomitant ACE inhibitors, treatment was discontinued for elevations in creatinine or potassium (total of 1.0% on valsartan vs. 0.2% on placebo). In the Valsartan in Acute Myocardial Infarction Trial (VALIANT), discontinuation due to various types of renal dysfunction occurred in 1.1% of valsartan-treated patients and 0.8% of captopril-treated patients. Evaluation of patients with heart failure or post-myocardial infarction should always include assessment of renal function.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
