<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="exjade" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   In patients with transfusional iron overload, the most frequently occurring (&gt;5%) adverse reactions are diarrhea, vomiting, nausea, abdominal pain, skin rashes, and increases in serum creatinine. In Exjade-treated patients with NTDT syndromes, the most frequently occurring (&gt;5%) adverse reactions are diarrhea, rash and nausea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  The following adverse reactions are also discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Renal Toxicity, Renal Failure, and Proteinuria [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *  Hepatic Toxicity and Failure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *  Gastrointestinal (GI) Hemorrhage [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *  Bone Marrow Suppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *  Hypersensitivity [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]  
 *  Severe Skin Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)]  
 *  Skin Rash [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  
 *  Auditory and Ocular Abnormalities [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)]  
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

   Transfusional Iron Overload  



 A total of 700 adult and pediatric patients were treated with Exjade (deferasirox) for 48 weeks in premarketing studies. These included 469 patients with beta-thalassemia, 99 with rare anemias, and 132 with sickle cell disease. Of these patients, 45% were male, 70% were Caucasian and 292 patients were &lt;16 years of age. In the sickle cell disease population, 89% of patients were black. Median treatment duration among the sickle cell patients was 51 weeks. Of the 700 patients treated, 469 (403 beta-thalassemia and 66 rare anemias) were entered into extensions of the original clinical protocols. In ongoing extension studies, median durations of treatment were 88-205 weeks.



 Six hundred twenty-seven patients with MDS were enrolled across 5 uncontrolled trials. These studies varied in duration from 1 to 5 years. The discontinuation rate across studies in the first year was 46% (AEs 20%, withdrawal of consent 10%, death 8%, other 4%, lab abnormalities 3%, and lack of efficacy 1%). Among 47 patients enrolled in the study of 5-year duration, 10 remained on Exjade at the completion of the study.



 Table 1 displays adverse reactions occurring in &gt;5% of Exjade-treated beta-thalassemia patients (Study 1), sickle cell disease patients (Study 3), and patients with MDS (MDS pool). Abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, skin rashes, and increases in serum creatinine were the most frequent adverse reactions reported with a suspected relationship to Exjade. Gastrointestinal symptoms, increases in serum creatinine, and skin rash were dose related.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions* Occurring in &gt;5% of Exjade-treated Patients in Study 1, Study 3, and MDS Pool 
 *Adverse reaction frequencies are based on adverse events reported regardless of relationship to study drug.   
 **Includes 'abdominal pain', 'abdominal pain lower', and 'abdominal pain upper' which were reported as adverse events.   
 ***Includes 'blood creatinine increased' and 'blood creatinine abnormal' which were reported as adverse events. Also see Table 2.   
  
                    Study 1 (Beta-thalassemia)      Study 3 (Sickle Cell Disease)      MDS Pool        
   Preferred Term      EXJADE    N=296    n (%)      Deferoxamine    N=290    n (%)      EXJADE    N=132    n (%)      Deferoxamine    N=63    n (%)      EXJADE    N=627    n (%)     
 Abdominal Pain**  63 (21)          41 (14)          37 (28)          9 (14)           145 (23)          
 Diarrhea         35 (12)          21 (7)           26 (20)          3 (5)            297 (47)          
 Creatinine Increased***  33 (11)          0 (0)            9 (7)            0                89 (14)           
 Nausea           31 (11)          14 (5)           30 (23)          7 (11)           161 (26)          
 Vomiting         30 (10)          28 (10)          28 (21)          10 (16)          83 (13)           
 Rash             25 (8)           9 (3)            14 (11)          3 (5)            83 (13)           
             In Study 1, a total of 113 (38%) patients treated with Exjade had increases in serum creatinine &gt;33% above baseline on 2 separate occasions (Table 2) and 25 (8%) patients required dose reductions. Increases in serum creatinine appeared to be dose related [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.1  )]. In this study, 17 (6%) patients treated with Exjade developed elevations in SGPT/ALT levels &gt;5 times the upper limit of normal at 2 consecutive visits. Of these, 2 patients had liver biopsy proven drug-induced hepatitis and both discontinued Exjade therapy [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]. An additional 2 patients, who did not have elevations in SGPT/ALT &gt;5 times the upper limit of normal, discontinued Exjade because of increased SGPT/ALT. Increases in transaminases did not appear to be dose related. Adverse reactions that led to discontinuations included abnormal liver function tests (2 patients) and drug-induced hepatitis (2 patients), skin rash, glycosuria/proteinuria, Henoch Schonlein purpura, hyperactivity/insomnia, drug fever, and cataract (1 patient each).
 

 In Study 3, a total of 48 (36%) patients treated with Exjade had increases in serum creatinine &gt;33% above baseline on 2 separate occasions (Table 2) [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.1  )]. Of the patients who experienced creatinine increases in Study 3, 8 Exjade-treated patients required dose reductions. In this study, 5 patients in the Exjade group developed elevations in SGPT/ALT levels &gt;5 times the upper limit of normal at 2 consecutive visits and 1 patient subsequently had Exjade permanently discontinued. Four additional patients discontinued Exjade due to adverse reactions with a suspected relationship to study drug, including diarrhea, pancreatitis associated with gallstones, atypical tuberculosis, and skin rash.



 In the MDS pool, in the first year, a total of 229 (37%) patients treated with Exjade had increases in serum creatinine &gt;33% above baseline on 2 consecutive occasions (Table 2) and 8 (3.5%) patients permanently discontinued  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  . A total of 5 (0.8%) patients developed SGPT/ALT levels &gt;5 times the upper limit of normal at 2 consecutive visits. The most frequent adverse reactions that led to discontinuation included increases in serum creatinine, diarrhea, nausea, rash, and vomiting. Death was reported in the first year in 52 (8%) of patients  [see Clinical Studies (14)]  .



 Table 2. Number (%) of Patients with Increases in Serum Creatinine or SGPT/ALT in Study 1, Study 3, and MDS Pool 
                    Study 1 (Beta-thalassemia)      Study 3 (Sickle Cell Disease)      MDS Pool        
   Laboratory Parameter      EXJADE    N=296    n (%)      Deferoxamine    N=290    n (%)      EXJADE    N=132    n (%)      Deferoxamine    N=63    n (%)      EXJADE    N=627    n (%)     
   Serum Creatinine     
 Creatinine increase &gt;33% at 2 consecutive postbaseline visits  113 (38)         41 (14)          48 (36)          14 (22)          229 (37)          
 Creatinine increase &gt;33% and &gt;ULN at 2 consecutive postbaseline visits  7 (2)            1 (0)            3 (2)            2 (3)            126 (20)          
   SGPT/ALT        
 SGPT/ALT &gt;5 x ULN at 2 postbaseline visits  25 (8)           7 (2)            2 (2)            0                9 (1)             
 SGPT/ALT &gt;5 x ULN at 2 consecutive postbaseline visits  17 (6)           5 (2)            5 (4)            0                5 (1)             
              Non-Transfusion-Dependent Thalassemia Syndromes  
 

 In Study 4, 110 patients with NTDT received 1 year of treatment with Exjade 5 or 10 mg/kg/day and 56 patients received placebo in a double-blind, randomized trial. In Study 5, 130 of the patients who completed Study 4 were treated with open-label Exjade at 5, 10, or 20 mg/kg/day (depending on the baseline LIC) for 1 year  [see Clinical Studies (14)]  . Table 3 displays adverse reactions occurring in &gt;5% in any group. The most frequent adverse reactions with a suspected relationship to study drug were nausea, rash, and diarrhea.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;5% in NTDT Patients 
                    Study 4          Study 5         
                    EXJADE           Placebo          EXJADE          
                    N=110            N=56             N=130           
                    n (%)            n (%)            n (%)           
   Any adverse reaction      31 (28)          9 (16)           27 (21)         
 Nausea           7 (6)            4 (7)            2 (2)             
 Rash             7 (6)            1 (2)            2 (2)             
 Diarrhea         5 (5)            1 (2)            7 (5)             
          In Study 4, 1 patient in the placebo 10 mg/kg/day group experienced an ALT increase to &gt;5 times ULN and &gt;2 times baseline (Table 4). Three Exjade-treated patients (all in the 10 mg/kg/day group) had 2 consecutive serum creatinine level increases &gt;33% from baseline and &gt;ULN. Serum creatinine returned to normal in all 3 patients (in 1 spontaneously and in the other 2 after drug interruption). Two additional cases of ALT increase and 2 additional cases of serum creatinine increase were observed in the 1-year extension of Study 4.
 

 Table 4. Number (%) of NTDT Patients with Increases in Serum Creatinine or SGPT/ALT 
                    Study 4          Study 5         
                    EXJADE           Placebo          EXJADE          
                    N=110            N=56             N=130           
   Laboratory Parameter      n (%)            n (%)            n (%)           
 Serum creatinine (&gt;33% increase from baseline and &gt;ULN at &gt;=2 consecutive postbaseline values)  3 (3)            0                2 (2)             
 SGPT/ALT (&gt;5 x ULN and &gt;2 x baseline)  1 (1)            1 (2)            2 (2)             
            Proteinuria  
 

 In clinical studies, urine protein was measured monthly. Intermittent proteinuria (urine protein/creatinine ratio &gt;0.6 mg/mg) occurred in 18.6% of Exjade-treated patients compared to 7.2% of deferoxamine-treated patients in Study 1  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .



   Other Adverse Reactions  



 In the population of more than 5,000 patients with transfusional iron overload who have been treated with Exjade during clinical trials, adverse reactions occurring in 0.1% to 1% of patients included gastritis, edema, sleep disorder, pigmentation disorder, dizziness, anxiety, maculopathy, cholelithiasis, pyrexia, fatigue, pharyngolaryngeal pain, early cataract, hearing loss, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastric ulcer (including multiple ulcers), duodenal ulcer, and renal tubulopathy (Fanconi's Syndrome). Adverse reactions occurring in 0.01% to 0.1% of patients included optic neuritis, esophagitis, and erythema multiforme. Adverse reactions which most frequently led to dose interruption or dose adjustment during clinical trials were rash, gastrointestinal disorders, infections, increased serum creatinine, and increased serum transaminases.



   6.2     Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been spontaneously reported during post-approval use of Exjade in the transfusional iron overload setting. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, in which patients may have received concomitant medication, it is not always possible to reliably estimate frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders: Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS), leukocytoclastic vasculitis, urticaria, alopecia



 Immune system disorders: hypersensitivity reactions (including anaphylaxis and angioedema)



 Renal and urinary disorders: renal tubular necrosis, acute renal failure, tubulointerstitial nephritis



 Hepatobiliary disorders: hepatic failure



 Gastrointestinal disorders: gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastrointestinal perforation



 Blood and lymphatic system disorders: worsening anemia
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RENAL FAILURE, HEPATIC FAILURE, AND GASTROINTESTINAL HEMORRHAGE

    WARNING: RENAL FAILURE, HEPATIC FAILURE, AND GASTROINTESTINAL HEMORRHAGE  

    Renal Failure  



 *  Exjade can cause acute renal failure and death, particularly in patients with comorbidities and those who are in the advanced stages of their hematologic disorders. 
 *  Measure serum creatinine and determine creatinine clearance in duplicate prior to initiation of therapy and monitor renal function at least monthly thereafter. For patients with baseline renal impairment or increased risk of acute renal failure, monitor creatinine weekly for the first month, then at least monthly. Consider dose reduction, interruption, or discontinuation based on increases in serum creatinine [see Dosage and Administration (2.4, 2.5), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      Hepatic Failure  
 

 *  Exjade can cause hepatic injury including hepatic failure and death. 
 *  Measure serum transaminases and bilirubin in all patients prior to initiating treatment, every 2 weeks during the first month, and at least monthly thereafter. 
 *  Avoid use of Exjade in patients with severe (Child-Pugh C) hepatic impairment and reduce the dose in patients with moderate (Child Pugh B) hepatic impairment [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage  
 

 *  Exjade can cause gastrointestinal (GI) hemorrhages, which may be fatal, especially in elderly patients who have advanced hematologic malignancies and/or low platelet counts. 
 *  Monitor patients and discontinue Exjade for suspected GI ulceration or hemorrhage [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: RENAL FAILURE, HEPATIC FAILURE, AND GASTROINTESTINAL HEMORRHAGE   
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   Exjade may cause:  



 *  renal toxicity, including failure (5.1) 
 *  hepatic toxicity, including failure (5.2) 
 *  gastrointestinal hemorrhage (5.3) 
      Exjade therapy requires close patient monitoring, including laboratory tests of renal and hepatic function. (  5  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Renal toxicity: Measure serum creatinine and creatinine clearance in duplicate before starting therapy. Monitor renal function during Exjade therapy and reduce dose or interrupt therapy for toxicity. (  2.4  ,  5.1  ) 
 *  Hepatic toxicity: Monitor hepatic function. Reduce dose or interrupt therapy for toxicity. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Fatal and nonfatal gastrointestinal bleeding, ulceration, and irritation: Risk may be greater in patients who are taking Exjade in combination with drugs that have known ulcerogenic or hemorrhagic potential. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Bone marrow suppression: Neutropenia, agranulocytosis, worsening anemia, and thrombocytopenia, including fatal events; monitor blood counts during Exjade therapy. Interrupt therapy for toxicity. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Elderly: Monitor closely for toxicity due to the greater frequency of decreased hepatic, renal, and/or cardiac function. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Serious and severe hypersensitivity reactions: Discontinue Exjade and institute medical intervention. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Severe skin reactions including Stevens Johnson Syndrome: Discontinue Exjade. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Renal Toxicity, Renal Failure, and Proteinuria



  Exjade can cause acute renal failure, fatal in some patients and requiring dialysis in others. Postmarketing experience showed that most fatalities occurred in patients with multiple comorbidities and who were in advanced stages of their hematological disorders. In the clinical trials, Exjade-treated patients experienced dose-dependent increases in serum creatinine. In patients with transfusional iron overload, these increases in creatinine occurred at a greater frequency compared to deferoxamine-treated patients (38% versus 14%, respectively, in Study 1 and 36% versus 22%, respectively, in Study 3) [see Adverse Reactions (6.1, 6.2)]  .



 Measure serum creatinine in duplicate (due to variations in measurements) and determine the creatinine clearance (estimated by the Cockcroft-Gault method) before initiating therapy in all patients in order to establish a reliable pretreatment baseline. Monitor serum creatinine weekly during the first month after initiation or modification of therapy and at least monthly thereafter. Monitor serum creatinine and/or creatinine clearance more frequently if creatinine levels are increasing. Dose reduction, interruption, or discontinuation based on increases in serum creatinine may be necessary [see Dosage and Administration (2.5)]  .



 Exjade is contraindicated in patients with creatinine clearance less than 40 mL/minute or serum creatinine greater than 2 times the age appropriate upper limit of normal.



 Renal tubular damage, including Fanconi's Syndrome, has been reported in patients treated with Exjade, most commonly in children and adolescents with beta-thalassemia and serum ferritin levels &lt;1500 mcg/L.



 Intermittent proteinuria (urine protein/creatinine ratio &gt;0.6 mg/mg) occurred in 18.6% of Exjade-treated patients compared to 7.2% of deferoxamine-treated patients in Study 1. In clinical trials in patients with transfusional iron overload, Exjade was temporarily withheld until the urine protein/creatinine ratio fell below 0.6 mg/mg. Monthly monitoring for proteinuria is recommended. The mechanism and clinical significance of the proteinuria are uncertain [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  .



    5.2     Hepatic Toxicity and Failure



  Exjade can cause hepatic injury, fatal in some patients. In Study 1, 4 patients (1.3%) discontinued Exjade because of hepatic toxicity (drug-induced hepatitis in 2 patients and increased serum transaminases in 2 additional patients). Hepatic toxicity appears to be more common in patients greater than 55 years of age. Hepatic failure was more common in patients with significant comorbidities, including liver cirrhosis and multiorgan failure [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  .



 Measure transaminases (AST and ALT) and bilirubin in all patients before the initiation of treatment and every 2 weeks during the first month and at least monthly thereafter. Consider dose modifications or interruption of treatment for severe or persistent elevations.



 Avoid the use of Exjade in patients with severe (Child-Pugh C) hepatic impairment. Reduce the starting dose in patients with moderate (Child-Pugh B) hepatic impairment [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.7)]  . Patients with mild (Child-Pugh A) or moderate (Child-Pugh B) hepatic impairment may be at higher risk for hepatic toxicity.



    5.3     Gastrointestinal (GI) Ulceration, Hemorrhage, and Perforation



   GI hemorrhage, including deaths, has been reported, especially in elderly patients who had advanced hematologic malignancies and/or low platelet counts. Nonfatal upper GI irritation, ulceration and hemorrhage have been reported in patients, including children and adolescents, receiving Exjade [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Monitor for signs and symptoms of GI ulceration and hemorrhage during Exjade therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI adverse event is suspected. The risk of gastrointestinal hemorrhage may be increased when administering Exjade in combination with drugs that have ulcerogenic or hemorrhagic potential, such as nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), corticosteroids, oral bisphosphonates, or anticoagulants. There have been reports of ulcers complicated with gastrointestinal perforation (including fatal outcome) [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .  



    5.4     Bone Marrow Suppression



  Neutropenia, agranulocytosis, worsening anemia, and thrombocytopenia, including fatal events, have been reported in patients treated with Exjade. Preexisting hematologic disorders may increase this risk. Monitor blood counts in all patients. Interrupt treatment with Exjade in patients who develop cytopenias until the cause of the cytopenia has been determined. Exjade is contraindicated in patients with platelet counts below 50 x 10  9  /L.



    5.5     Increased Risk of Toxicity in the Elderly



  Exjade has been associated with serious and fatal adverse reactions in the postmarketing setting, predominantly in elderly patients. Monitor elderly patients treated with Exjade more frequently for toxicity [see Use in Specific Populations (8.5)]  .



    5.6     Hypersensitivity



  Exjade may cause serious hypersensitivity reactions (such as anaphylaxis and angioedema), with the onset of the reaction usually occurring within the first month of treatment [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]. If reactions are severe, discontinue Exjade and institute appropriate medical intervention. Exjade is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to Exjade.



    5.7     Severe Skin Reactions



   Severe skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and erythema multiforme, have been reported during Exjade therapy [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  . If SJS or erythema multiforme is suspected, discontinue Exjade immediately and do not reintroduce Exjade therapy.  



    5.8     Skin Rash



   Rashes may occur during Exjade treatment [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . For rashes of mild to moderate severity, Exjade may be continued without dose adjustment, since the rash often resolves spontaneously. In severe cases, interrupt treatment with Exjade. Reintroduction at a lower dose with escalation may be considered after resolution of the rash.  



    5.9     Auditory and Ocular Abnormalities



  Auditory disturbances (high frequency hearing loss, decreased hearing), and ocular disturbances (lens opacities, cataracts, elevations in intraocular pressure, and retinal disorders) were reported at a frequency of &lt;1% with Exjade therapy in the clinical studies. Perform auditory and ophthalmic testing (including slit lamp examinations and dilated fundoscopy) before starting Exjade treatment and thereafter at regular intervals (every 12 months). If disturbances are noted, monitor more frequently. Consider dose reduction or interruption.



    5.10     Overchelation



  For patients with transfusional iron overload, measure serum ferritin monthly to assess for possible overchelation of iron. If the serum ferritin falls below 500 mcg/L, consider interrupting therapy with Exjade, since overchelation may increase Exjade toxicity [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  .



 For patients with NTDT, measure LIC by liver biopsy or by using an FDA-cleared or approved method for monitoring patients receiving deferasirox therapy every 6 months on treatment. Interrupt Exjade administration when the LIC is less than 3 mg Fe/g dw. Measure serum ferritin monthly, and if the serum ferritin falls below 300 mcg/L, interrupt Exjade and obtain a confirmatory LIC [see Clinical Studies (14)]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
