<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="exondys" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=35% and higher than placebo) were balance disorder and vomiting (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sarepta Therapeutics, Inc. at 1-888-SAREPTA (1-888-727-3782) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In the EXONDYS 51 clinical development program, 107 patients received at least one intravenous dose of EXONDYS 51, ranging between 0.5 mg/kg (0.017 times the recommended dosage) and 50 mg/kg (1.7 times the recommended dosage). All patients were male and had genetically confirmed Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Age at study entry was 4 to 19 years. Most (89%) patients were Caucasian.



 EXONDYS 51 was studied in a double-blind, placebo-controlled study for 24 weeks (Study 1), followed by an open label extension (Study 2). In Study 1, 12 patients were randomized to receive weekly intravenous infusions of EXONDYS 51 (n=8) or placebo (n=4) for 24 weeks. All 12 patients continued in Study 2 and received open-label EXONDYS 51 weekly for up to 208 weeks.



 In Study 1, 4 patients received placebo, 4 patients received EXONDYS 51 30 mg/kg, and 4 patients received EXONDYS 51 50 mg/kg (1.7 times the recommended dosage). In Study 2, 6 patients received EXONDYS 51 30 mg/kg/week and 6 patients received EXONDYS 51 50 mg/kg/week  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  .



 Adverse reactions that occurred in 2 or more patients who received EXONDYS 51 and were more frequent than in the placebo group in Study 1 are presented in  Table 1  (the 30 and 50 mg/kg groups are pooled). Because of the small numbers of patients, these represent crude frequencies that may not reflect the frequencies observed in practice. The 50 mg/kg once weekly dosing regimen of EXONDYS 51 is not recommended  [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )].  



 The most common adverse reactions were balance disorder and vomiting.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions in DMD Patients Treated with 30 or 50 mg/kg/week1 EXONDYS 51 with Incidence at Least 25% More than Placebo (Study 1) 
  1 50 mg/kg/week = 1.7 times the recommended dosage    
  
 Adverse Reactions                           EXONDYS 51 (N=8)                        Placebo (N=4)        
                                             %                                       %                    
 Balance disorder                            38                                      0                    
 Vomiting                                    38                                      0                    
 Contact dermatitis                          25                                      0                    
         In the 88 patients who received &gt;=30 mg/kg/week of EXONDYS 51 for up to 208 weeks in clinical studies, the following events were reported in &gt;=10% of patients and occurred more frequently than on the same dose in Study 1: vomiting, contusion, excoriation, arthralgia, rash, catheter site pain, and upper respiratory tract infection.
 

 There have been reports of transient erythema, facial flushing, and elevated temperature occurring on days of EXONDYS 51 infusion.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
