<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="exparel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions reported with an incidence greater than or equal to 10% following EXPAREL administration were nausea, constipation, and vomiting (  6.2  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pacira Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-855-RX-EXPAREL (1-855-793-9727) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 General

  The most commonly encountered acute adverse experiences to bupivacaine and all amide-type local anesthetics that demand immediate counter-measures are related to the central nervous and cardiovascular systems.



 High plasma concentrations of bupivacaine can occur from overdosage, unintended intravascular injection, or accumulation of bupivacaine in plasma secondary to decreased hepatic metabolic degradation of the drug or diminished plasma protein binding capacity due to acidosis, pathologically lowered plasma protein production, or competition with other drugs for protein binding sites. Although rare, some individuals have a lower tolerance to and are supersensitive to bupivacaine and other amide-type local anesthetics and may rapidly develop signs of toxicity at low doses [  See Overdosage (  10  )  ].



   6.2 Adverse Reactions Reported in All Wound Infiltration Clinical Studies

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of EXPAREL was evaluated in 10 randomized, double-blind, local administration into the surgical site clinical studies involving 823 patients undergoing various surgical procedures. Patients were administered a dose ranging from 66 to 532 mg of EXPAREL. In these studies, the most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 10%) following EXPAREL administration were nausea, constipation, and vomiting.



 The common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 2% to less than 10%) following EXPAREL administration were pyrexia, dizziness, edema peripheral, anemia, hypotension, pruritus, tachycardia, headache, insomnia, anemia postoperative, muscle spasms, hemorrhagic anemia, back pain, somnolence, and procedural pain.



 The less common/rare adverse reactions (incidence less than 2%) following EXPAREL administration were chills, erythema, bradycardia, anxiety, urinary retention, pain, edema, tremor, dizziness postural, paresthesia, syncope, incision site edema, procedural hypertension, procedural hypotension, procedural nausea, muscular weakness, neck pain, pruritus generalized, rash pruritic, hyperhidrosis, cold sweat, urticaria, bradycardia, palpitations, sinus bradycardia, supraventricular extrasystoles, ventricular extrasystoles, ventricular tachycardia, hypertension, pallor, anxiety, confusional state, depression, agitation, restlessness, hypoxia, laryngospasm, apnea, respiratory depression, respiratory failure, body temperature increased, blood pressure increased, blood pressure decreased, oxygen saturation decreased, urinary incontinence, vision blurred, tinnitus, drug hypersensitivity, and hypersensitivity.



   Neurological and Cardiac Adverse Reactions Reported in All Wound Infiltration Clinical Studies  



 In the EXPAREL wound infiltration studies, adverse reactions with an incidence greater than or equal to 1% in the Nervous System Disorders system organ class following EXPAREL administration were dizziness (6.2%), headache (3.8%), somnolence (2.1%), hypoesthesia (1.5%), and lethargy (1.3%). The adverse reactions with an incidence greater than or equal to 1% in the Cardiac Disorders system organ class following EXPAREL administration were tachycardia (3.9%) and bradycardia (1.6%).



   Adverse Reactions Reported in Placebo-Controlled Wound Infiltration Clinical Studies  



 Adverse reactions with an incidence greater than or equal to 2% reported by patients in clinical studies comparing 8 mL EXPAREL 1.3% (106 mg) to placebo and 20 mL EXPAREL 1.3% (266 mg) to placebo are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions (TEAE) with an Incidence Greater than or Equal to 2%: Placebo Controlled Studies 
   a  Study 1: Bunionectomy   
   b  Study 2: Hemorrhoidectomy   
 At each level of summation (overall, system organ class, preferred term), patients are only counted once.Preferred terms are included where at least 2% of patients reported the event in any treatment group.TEAE = treatment-emergent adverse event.   
  
                              STUDY 1  a                 STUDY 2  b                
                              EXPAREL                    Placebo                    EXPAREL                    Placebo                   
   System Organ Class     Preferred Term      8 mL/1.3% (106 mg)(N=97)n (%)      (N=96)n (%)                20 mL/1.3% (266 mg)(N=95)n (%)      (N=94)n (%)               
                             
 Any TEAE                   53 (54.6)                  59 (61.5)                  10 (10.5)                  17 (18.1)                   
                             
 Gastrointestinal Disorders  41 (42.3)                  38 (39.6)                  7 (7.4)                    13 (13.8)                   
      Nausea                39 (40.2)                  36 (37.5)                  2 (2.1)                    1 (1.1)                     
      Vomiting              27 (27.8)                  17 (17.7)                  2 (2.1)                    4 (4.3)                     
      Constipation          2 (2.1)                    1 (1.0)                    2 (2.1)                    2 (2.1)                     
      Anal Hemorrhage       0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    3 (3.2)                    4 (4.3)                     
      Painful Defecation    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    2 (2.1)                    5 (5.3)                     
      Rectal Discharge      0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    1 (1.1)                    3 (3.2)                     
                             
 Nervous System Disorders   20 (20.6)                  30 (31.3)                  0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Dizziness             11 (11.3)                  25 (26.0)                  0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Headache              5 (5.2)                    8 (8.3)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Somnolence            5 (5.2)                    1 (1.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Syncope               2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
                             
 Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  8 (8.2)                    7 (7.3)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Pruritus Generalized  5 (5.2)                    6 (6.3)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Pruritus              3 (3.1)                    1 (1.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
                             
 Investigations             5 (5.2)                    3 (3.1)                    4 (4.2)                    3 (3.2)                     
      Alanine Aminotransferase Increased  3 (3.1)                    3 (3.1)                    1 (1.1)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased  3 (3.1)                    2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Blood Creatinine Increased  2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Body Temperature Increased  0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    3 (3.2)                    3 (3.2)                     
                             
 General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions  4 (4.1)                    0 (0.0)                    1 (1.1)                    1 (1.1)                     
      Feeling Hot           2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Pyrexia               2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    1 (1.1)                    1 (1.1)                     
                             
 Infections And Infestations  2 (2.1)                    1 (1.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Fungal Infection      2 (2.1)                    1 (1.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
                             
 Injury, Poisoning And Procedural Complications  2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Post Procedural Swelling  2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
                             
 Metabolism And Nutrition Disorders  2 (2.1)                    2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
      Decreased Appetite    2 (2.1)                    2 (2.1)                    0 (0.0)                    0 (0.0)                     
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Monitoring of cardiovascular and neurological status, as well as vital signs should be performed during and after injection of EXPAREL as with other local anesthetic products (  5.1  ). 
 *  Because amide-type local anesthetics, such as bupivacaine, are metabolized by the liver, EXPAREL should be used cautiously in patients with hepatic disease. Patients with severe hepatic disease, because of their inability to metabolize local anesthetics normally, are at a greater risk of developing toxic plasma concentrations (  5.1  ). 
 *  Other formulations of bupivacaine should not be administered within 96 hours following administration of EXPAREL (  5.2  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Warnings and Precautions for Bupivacaine Containing Products



  The safety and effectiveness of bupivacaine and other amide-containing products depend on proper dosage, correct technique, adequate precautions, and readiness for emergencies. As there is a potential risk of severe life-threatening adverse effects associated with the administration of bupivacaine, any bupivacaine-containing product should be administered in a setting where trained personnel and equipment are available to promptly treat patients who show evidence of neurological or cardiac toxicity [ See Overdosage (  10  )  ].



 Careful and constant monitoring of cardiovascular and respiratory (adequacy of ventilation) vital signs and the patient's state of consciousness should be performed after injection of bupivacaine and other amide-containing products. Restlessness, anxiety, incoherent speech, lightheadedness, numbness and tingling of the mouth and lips, metallic taste, tinnitus, dizziness, blurred vision, tremors, twitching, depression, or drowsiness may be early warning signs of central nervous system toxicity.



 Bupivacaine and other amide-containing products should also be used with caution in patients with impaired cardiovascular function because they may be less able to compensate for functional changes associated with the prolongation of AV conduction produced by these drugs.



 Injection of multiple doses of bupivacaine and other amide-containing products may cause significant increases in plasma concentrations with each repeated dose due to slow accumulation of the drug or its metabolites, or to slow metabolic degradation. Tolerance to elevated blood concentrations varies with the status of the patient.



 Because amide-type local anesthetics, such as bupivacaine, are metabolized by the liver, these drugs should be used cautiously in patients with hepatic disease. Patients with severe hepatic disease, because of their inability to metabolize local anesthetics normally, are at a greater risk of developing toxic plasma concentrations.



  Central Nervous System Reactions  



 The incidences of adverse neurologic reactions associated with the use of local anesthetics may be related to the total dose of local anesthetic administered and are also dependent upon the particular drug used, the route of administration, and the physical status of the patient. Many of these effects may be related to local anesthetic techniques, with or without a contribution from the drug. Neurologic effects following infiltration of soft tissue may include persistent anesthesia, paresthesias, weakness, and paralysis, all of which may have slow, incomplete, or no recovery.



 Central nervous system reactions are characterized by excitation and/or depression. Restlessness, anxiety, dizziness, tinnitus, blurred vision, or tremors may occur, possibly proceeding to convulsions. However, excitement may be transient or absent, with depression being the first manifestation of an adverse reaction. This may quickly be followed by drowsiness merging into unconsciousness and respiratory arrest. Other central nervous system effects may be nausea, vomiting, chills, and constriction of the pupils. The incidence of convulsions associated with the use of local anesthetics varies with the procedure used and the total dose administered.



  Cardiovascular System Reactions  



 Toxic blood concentrations depress cardiac conductivity and excitability, which may lead to atrioventricular block, ventricular arrhythmias, and cardiac arrest, sometimes resulting in fatalities. In addition, myocardial contractility is depressed and peripheral vasodilation occurs, leading to decreased cardiac output and arterial blood pressure [ See Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) and Overdosage (  10  )  ].



  Allergic Reactions  



 Allergic-type reactions are rare and may occur as a result of hypersensitivity to the local anesthetic or to other formulation ingredients. These reactions are characterized by signs such as urticaria, pruritus, erythema, angioneurotic edema (including laryngeal edema), tachycardia, sneezing, nausea, vomiting, dizziness, syncope, excessive sweating, elevated temperature, and possibly anaphylactoid-like symptoms (including severe hypotension). Cross-sensitivity among members of the amide-type local anesthetic group has been reported. The usefulness of screening for sensitivity has not been definitively established.



  Chondrolysis  



 Intra-articular infusions of local anesthetics following arthroscopic and other surgical procedures is an unapproved use, and there have been postmarketing reports of chondrolysis in patients receiving such infusions. The majority of reported cases of chondrolysis have involved the shoulder joint; cases of gleno-humerol chondrolysis have been described in pediatric patients and adult patients following intra-articular infusions of local anesthetics with and without epinephrine for periods of 48 to 72 hours. There is insufficient information to determine whether shorter infusion periods are not associated with these findings. The time of onset of symptoms, such as joint pain, stiffness, and loss of motion can be variable, but may begin as early as the second month after surgery. Currently, there is no effective treatment for chondrolysis; patients who have experienced chondrolysis have required additional diagnostic and therapeutic procedures and some required arthroplasty or shoulder replacement.



    5.2 Warnings and Precautions Specific for EXPAREL



  As there is a potential risk of severe life-threatening adverse effects associated with the administration of bupivacaine, EXPAREL should be administered in a setting where trained personnel and equipment are available to promptly treat patients who show evidence of neurological or cardiac toxicity [ See Overdosage (  10  )  ].



 Caution should be taken to avoid accidental intravascular injection of EXPAREL. Convulsions and cardiac arrest have occurred following accidental intravascular injection of bupivacaine and other amide-containing products.



 Using EXPAREL followed by other bupivacaine formulations has not been studied in clinical trials. Other formulations of bupivacaine should not be administered within 96 hours following administration of EXPAREL [ See Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )  ].



 EXPAREL has not been evaluated for the following uses and, therefore, is not recommended for these types of analgesia or routes of administration.



 *  epidural 
 *  intrathecal 
 *  regional nerve blocks 
 *  intravascular or intra-articular use 
    EXPAREL has not been evaluated for use in the following patient population and, therefore, it is not recommended for administration to these groups.
 

 *  patients younger than 18 years old 
 *  pregnant patients 
 *  nursing patients 
    The ability of EXPAREL to achieve effective anesthesia has not been studied. Therefore, EXPAREL is not indicated for pre-incisional or pre-procedural loco-regional anesthetic techniques that require deep and complete sensory block in the area of administration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
