<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="extraneal" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reaction (incidence &gt; 5%) was rash. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare Corporation at 1-866-888-2472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  EXTRANEAL was originally studied in controlled clinical trials of 493 patients with end-stage renal disease who received a single daily exchange of EXTRANEAL for the long dwell (8-to 16- hours). There were 215 patients exposed for at least 6 months and 155 patients exposed for at least one year. The population was 18-83 years of age, 56% male and 44% female, 73% Caucasian, 18% Black, 4% Asian, 3% Hispanic, and it included patients with the following comorbid conditions: 27% diabetes, 49% hypertension and 23% hypertensive nephropathy.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



 Rash was the most frequently occurring EXTRANEAL-related adverse event (5.5%, EXTRANEAL; 1.7% Control). Seven patients on EXTRANEAL discontinued treatment due to rash, and one patient on EXTRANEAL discontinued due to exfoliative dermatitis. The rash typically appeared within the first three weeks of treatment and resolved with treatment discontinuation or, in some patients, with continued treatment.



 Table 1 shows the adverse events reported in these clinical studies regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;= 5% of patients and more common on EXTRANEAL than control.



 Table 1 - Adverse Experiences in &gt;=5% of Patients and More Common on EXTRANEAL 
                                              EXTRANEAL                        Control                      
                                              N = 493                          N = 347                      
  Peritonitis                                 26%                              25%                          
  Upper respiratory infection                 15%                              13%                          
  Hypertension                                13%                              8%                           
  Rash                                        10%                              5%                           
  Headache                                    9%                               7%                           
  Abdominal Pain                              8%                               6%                           
  Flu syndrome                                7%                               6%                           
  Nausea                                      7%                               5%                           
  Cough increase                              7%                               4%                           
  Edema                                       6%                               5%                           
  Accidental injury                           6%                               4%                           
  Chest pain                                  5%                               4%                           
  Dyspepsia                                   5%                               4%                           
  Hyperglycemia                               5%                               4%                           
         Adverse reactions reported with an incidence of &gt; 5% and at least as common on dextrose control included pain, asthenia, exit site infection, infection, back pain, hypotension, diarrhea, vomiting, nausea/vomiting, anemia, peripheral edema, hypokalemia, hyperphosphatemia, hypoproteinemia, hypervolemia, arthralgia, dizziness, dyspnea, skin disorder, pruritis.
 

 Additional adverse events occurring at an incidence of &lt; 5% and that may or may not have been related to EXTRANEAL include: pain on infusion, abdominal enlargement, cloudy effluent, ultrafiltration decrease, postural hypotension, heart failure, hyponatremia, hypochloremia, hypercalcemia, hypoglycemia, alkaline phosphatase increase, SGPT increase, SGOT increase, cramping, confusion, lung edema, facial edema, exfoliative dermatitis, eczema, vesicobullous rash, maculopapular rash, erythema multiforme. All reported events are included in the list except those already listed in Table 1 or the following two paragraphs, those not plausibly associated with EXTRANEAL, and those that were associated with the condition being treated or related to the dialysis procedure.



 EXTRANEAL was additionally studied in a subpopulation of 92 high average/high transporter APD patients in a two-week controlled clinical trial where patients received a single daily exchange of EXTRANEAL (n=47) or dextrose control (n=45) for the long dwell (14 +/- 2 hours). Consistent with the data reported in the original trials of EXTRANEAL, rash was the most frequently occurring event.



       Peritoneal Dialysis-Related Adverse Reactions    

  Adverse events common to peritoneal dialysis therapy, including peritonitis, infection around the catheter, fluid and electrolyte imbalance, and pain, were observed at a similar frequency with EXTRANEAL and controls  [See Warnings and Precautions (  5  )]  .



       Clinical Laboratory Findings    

  An increase in mean serum alkaline phosphatase has been observed in clinical studies of ESRD patients receiving EXTRANEAL. No associated increases in other liver chemistry tests were observed. Serum alkaline phosphatase levels did not show progressive increase over a 12-month study period. Levels returned to normal approximately two weeks after discontinuation of EXTRANEAL.



 Decreases in serum sodium and chloride have been observed in patients using EXTRANEAL. The mean change in serum sodium from baseline to the last study visit was -2.8 mmol/L for patients on EXTRANEAL and -0.3 mmol/L for patients on control solution. Four EXTRANEAL patients and two control patients developed serum sodium &lt; 125 mmol/L. The mean change in serum chloride from baseline to last study visit was -2 mmol/L for EXTRANEAL patients and + 0.6 mmol/L for control patients. Similar changes in serum chemistries were observed in an additional clinical study in a subpopulation of high average/high transporter patients. The declines in serum sodium and chloride may be related to dilution resulting from the presence of icodextrin metabolites in plasma.



 An apparent decrease in serum amylase activity has been observed in patients administered EXTRANEAL. Preliminary investigations indicate that icodextrin and its metabolites interfere with enzymatic-based amylase assays, resulting in inaccurately low values. This should be taken into account when evaluating serum amylase levels for diagnosis or monitoring of pancreatitis in patients using EXTRANEAL.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of EXTRANEAL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to estimate their frequency reliably or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 INFECTIONS AND INFESTATIONS: Fungal peritonitis, Peritonitis bacterial, Catheter related infection



 BLOOD AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM DISORDERS: Thrombocytopenia, Leukopenia, Leukocytosis



 IMMUNE SYSTEM DISORDERS: Vasculitis, Serum sickness, Hypersensitivity



 METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS: Hypoglycemic shock, Dehydration



 NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS: Hypoglycemic coma, Burning sensation



 EYE DISORDERS: Vision blurred



 RESPIRATORY, THORACIC, AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS: Bronchospasm, Stridor



 GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS: Sclerosing encapsulating peritonitis, Aseptic peritonitis, Ileus, Ascites, Inguinal hernia



 SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS DISORDERS: Toxic epidermal necrolysis, Angioedema, Urticaria generalized, Prurigo, Dermatitis (including bullous, allergic and contact), Erythema, Onychomadesis, Dry skin, Skin chapped, Blister



 MUSCULOSKELETAL, CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS: Arthralgia, Back pain, Musculoskeletal pain



 REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM AND BREAST DISORDERS: Penile edema, Scrotal edema



 GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATIVE SITE CONDITIONS: Discomfort, Pyrexia, Chills, Malaise, Catheter site erythema, Catheter site inflammation, Infusion related reaction (including Infusion site pain, Instillation site pain)



 INVESTIGATIONS: Liver function test abnormal, Urine output decreased
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: UNRECOGNIZED HYPOGLYCEMIA RESULTING FROM DRUG-DEVICE INTERACTION

  WARNING: UNRECOGNIZED HYPOGLYCEMIA RESULTING FROM DRUG-DEVICE INTERACTION

    *  Only use glucose-specific monitors and test strips to measure blood glucose levels in patients using EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) Peritoneal Dialysis Solution. Blood glucose monitoring devices using glucose dehydrogenase pyrroloquinolinequinone (GDH-PQQ) or glucose-dye-oxidoreductase (GDO)-based methods must not be used. In addition, some blood glucose monitoring systems using glucose dehydrogenase flavin-adenine dinucleotide (GDH-FAD)-based methods must not be used. Use of GDH-PQQ, GDO, and GDH-FAD-based glucose monitors and test strips has resulted in falsely elevated glucose readings (due to the presence of maltose) [see Warnings and Precautions(5.1)]. Falsely elevated glucose readings have led patients or health care providers to withhold treatment of hypoglycemia or to administer insulin inappropriately. Both of these situations have resulted in unrecognized hypoglycemia, which has led to loss of consciousness, coma, permanent neurological damage, and death. Plasma levels of EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) and its metabolites return to baseline within approximately 14 days following cessation of EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) administration. Therefore falsely elevated glucose levels may be measured up to two weeks following cessation of EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) therapy when GDH-PQQ, GDO, and GDH-FAD-based blood glucose monitors and test strips are used. 
 *  To avoid improper insulin administration, educate all patients to alert health care providers of this interaction particularly in hospital settings. 
 *  The manufacturer(s) of the monitor and test strips should be contacted to determine if icodextrin or maltose causes interference or falsely elevated glucose readings. For a list of toll free numbers for glucose monitor and test strip manufacturers, please contact the Baxter Renal Clinical Help Line 1-888-RENAL-HELP or visit www.glucosesafety.com. 
 *  Because of the risk of unrecognized hypoglycemia that could result from a drug-device interaction, EXTRANEAL is available only through a restricted program (5.2). 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: UNRECOGNIZED HYPOGLYCEMIA RESULTING FROM DRUG-DEVICE INTERACTION
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Use of non-specific glucose monitors has resulted in falsely elevated glucose readings due to maltose interference leading to inappropriate insulin administration or withholding of hypoglycemia treatment. Permanent neurological damage and death have been reported. (5.1) 
 *  Only use glucose-specific monitoring systems in patients using EXTRANEAL (see glucosesafety.com). (5.1) 
 *  Blood glucose monitoring devices using glucose dehydrogenase pyrroloquinolinequinone (GDH-PQQ), glucose-dye-oxidoreductase (GDO), or some glucose dehydrogenase flavin-adenine dinucleotide (GDH-FAD)-based methods must not be used. (5.1) 
 *  Falsely elevated glucose levels may be measured up to two weeks following cessation of EXTRANEAL therapy. (5.1, 12.3) 
 *  Educate all patients to alert health care providers of this interaction whenever they are admitted to the hospital. (5.1, 17) 
 *  Because of the risk of unrecognized hypoglycemia that could result from drug-device interaction, EXTRANEAL is available only through a restricted program. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Encapsulating peritoneal sclerosis (  5.3  ) 
 *    Peritonitis: Initiate appropriate antimicrobial therapy. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Hypersensitivity reactions: Serious reactions have been reported. Discontinue use of EXTRANEAL if serious reaction is suspected. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Monitor for lactic acidosis in patients at risk (  5.5  ) 
 *    Monitor for electrolyte, fluid, and nutrition imbalances (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Unrecognized Hypoglycemia Resulting From Drug-Device Interaction



  Only use glucose-specific monitors and test strips to measure blood glucose levels in patients using EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) Peritoneal Dialysis Solution. Blood glucose monitoring devices using glucose dehydrogenase pyrroloquinolinequinone (GDH-PQQ) or glucose-dye-oxidoreductase (GDO)-based methods must not be used. In addition, some blood glucose monitoring systems using glucose dehydrogenase flavin-adenine dinucleotide (GDH-FAD)-based methods must not be used. Use of GDH-PQQ, GDO, and GDH-FAD-based glucose monitors and test strips has resulted in falsely elevated glucose readings (due to the presence of maltose). Falsely elevated glucose readings have led patients or health care providers to withhold treatment of hypoglycemia or to administer insulin inappropriately. Both of these situations have resulted in unrecognized hypoglycemia, which has led to loss of consciousness, coma, permanent neurological damage, and death. Plasma levels of EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) and its metabolites return to baseline within approximately 14 days following cessation of EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) administration. Therefore falsely elevated glucose levels may be measured up to two weeks following cessation of EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) therapy when GDH-PQQ, GDO, and GDH-FAD-based blood glucose monitors and test strips are used.



 Because GDH-PQQ, GDO, and GDH-FAD-based blood glucose monitors may be used in hospital settings, it is important that the health care providers of all peritoneal dialysis patients using EXTRANEAL (icodextrin) carefully review the product information of the blood glucose testing system, including that of test strips, to determine if the system is appropriate for use with EXTRANEAL (icodextrin).



 To avoid improper insulin administration, educate all patients to alert health care providers of this interaction whenever they are admitted to the hospital.



 The manufacturer(s) of the monitor and test strips should be contacted to determine if icodextrin or maltose causes interference or falsely elevated glucose readings. For a list of toll free numbers for glucose monitor and test strip manufacturers, please contact the Baxter Renal Clinical Help Line 1-888-RENAL-HELP or visit  www.glucosesafety.com  .



    5.2 REMS Program for EXTRANEAL



  Because of the risk of unrecognized hypoglycemia resulting from a drug-device interaction, EXTRANEAL is available only through a restricted program under a REMS [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  . Required components of the EXTRANEAL REMS Program include the following:



 *    Dialysis clinic staff must be trained about the risk of undetected hypoglycemia resulting from a drug-device interactions involving EXTRANEAL in order to manage the treatment of patients prescribed EXTRANEAL. 
 *    Patients must be educated at a trained dialysis center before their initial EXTRANEAL treatment. 
    Further information, including a listing of blood glucose monitor compatibility information provided by the manufacturers of blood glucose monitors, is available by visiting  www.glucosesafety.com  or by calling Baxter Renal Clinical Help Line 1-888-RENAL-HELP.
 

    5.3 Peritonitis and Encapsulating Peritoneal Sclerosis



  Infections and aseptic peritonitis has been associated with EXTRANEAL use. Following EXTRANEAL use, inspect the drained fluid for the presence of fibrin or cloudiness, which may indicate the presence of peritonitis.



 If peritonitis occurs, the choice and dosage of antibiotics should be based upon the results of identification and sensitivity studies of the isolated organism(s) when possible. Prior to the identification of the involved organism(s), broad-spectrum antibiotics may be indicated.



 Encapsulating peritoneal sclerosis (EPS), sometimes fatal, is a complication of peritoneal dialysis therapy and has been reported in patients using EXTRANEAL.



    5.4 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious hypersensitivity reactions to EXTRANEAL have been reported such as toxic epidermal necrolysis, angioedema, serum sickness, erythema multiforme and vasculitis [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  and  6.2  )  ]. Anaphylactic or anaphylactoid reactions may occur. Stop the infusion immediately and drain the solution from the peritoneal cavity if any signs or symptoms of a suspected hypersensitivity reaction develop. Institute appropriate therapeutic countermeasures as clinically indicated.



    5.5 Lactic Acidosis



  Monitor patients with conditions known to increase the risk of lactic acidosis [e.g., severe hypotension or sepsis that can be associated with acute renal failure, inborn errors of metabolism, treatment with drugs such as nucleoside/nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs)] for lactic acidosis before the start of treatment and during treatment with EXTRANEAL.



    5.6 Peritoneal Dialysis-Related Considerations



  Effective use of EXTRANEAL may be compromised in patients with abdominal conditions predisposing them to complications of peritoneal dialysis, including infection.



    5.7 Overinfusion



  Overinfusion of peritoneal dialysis solution volume into the peritoneal cavity may be characterized by abdominal distention, feeling of fullness and/or shortness of breath. Drain the peritoneal dialysis solution from the peritoneal cavity to treat overinfusion.



    5.8 Electrolyte, Fluid, and Nutrition Imbalances



  Peritoneal dialysis may affect a patient's protein, water-soluble vitamin, potassium, sodium, chloride, bicarbonate, and magnesium levels and volume status [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  . Monitor electrolytes and blood chemistry periodically and take appropriate clinical action.



 Potassium is omitted from EXTRANEAL solutions because dialysis may be performed to correct hyperkalemia. In situations where there is a normal serum potassium level or hypokalemia, the addition of potassium chloride (up to a concentration of 4 mEq/L) may be indicated to prevent severe hypokalemia.



 Monitor fluid status to avoid hyper- or hypovolemia and potentially severe consequences including congestive heart failure, volume depletion, and hypovolemic shock.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
