<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fareston" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are hot flashes, sweating, nausea and vaginal discharge. (  6.1  )



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ProStrakan Inc., at 877-362-7595 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Adverse drug reactions are principally due to the antiestrogenic actions of FARESTON and typically occur at the beginning of treatment.



 The incidences of the following eight clinical toxicities were prospectively assessed in the North American Study. The incidence reflects the toxicities that were considered by the investigator to be drug related or possibly drug related.




                                                North American Study        
                                                       FAR60                           TAM20                
                                                      n = 221                         n = 215               
 Hot Flashes                                            35%                             30%                 
 Sweating                                               20%                             17%                 
 Nausea                                                 14%                             15%                 
 Vaginal Discharge                                      13%                             16%                 
 Dizziness                                               9%                              7%                 
 Edema                                                   5%                              5%                 
 Vomiting                                                4%                              2%                 
 Vaginal Bleeding                                        2%                              4%                 
         Approximately 1% of patients receiving FARESTON (n = 592) in the three controlled studies discontinued treatment as a result of adverse reactions (nausea and vomiting, fatigue, thrombophlebitis, depression, lethargy, anorexia, ischemic attack, arthritis, pulmonary embolism, and myocardial infarction).
 

 Serious adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of patients receiving FARESTON in the three major trials are listed in the table below.



 Three prospective, randomized, controlled clinical studies (North American, Eastern European, and Nordic) were conducted. The patients were randomized to parallel groups receiving FARESTON 60 mg (FAR60) or tamoxifen 20 mg (TAM20) in the North American Study or tamoxifen 40 mg (TAM40) in the Eastern European and Nordic studies. The North American and Eastern European studies also included high-dose toremifene arms of 200 and 240 mg daily, respectively  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  .




 * Most of the ocular abnormalities were observed in the North American Study in which on-study and biannual ophthalmic examinations were performed. No cases of retinopathy were observed in any arm.** Elevated defined as follows: North American Study: AST &gt;100 IU/L; alkaline phosphatase &gt;200 IU/L; bilirubin &gt; 2 mg/dL. Eastern European and Nordic studies: AST, alkaline phosphatase, and bilirubin - WHO Grade 1 (1.25 times the upper limit of normal).   
  
   Adverse Reactions             North American      Eastern European       Nordic      
                                  FAR60         TAM20         FAR60         TAM40         FAR60         TAM40       
                                 n=221(%)      n=215(%)      n=157(%)      n=149(%)      n=214(%)      n=201(%)     
   Cardiac                                                                                                          
 Cardiac Failure                  2 (1)         1 (&lt;1)          -           1 (&lt;1)        2 (1)        3 (1.5)      
 Myocardial Infarction            2 (1)        3 (1.5)        1 (&lt;1)        2 (1)           -           1 (&lt;1)      
 Arrhythmia                         -             -             -             -          3 (1.5)        1 (&lt;1)      
 Angina Pectoris                    -             -           1 (&lt;1)          -           1 (&lt;1)        2 (1)       
   Ocular*                                                                                                          
 Cataracts                       22 (10)       16 (7.5)         -             -             -           5 (3)       
 Dry Eyes                         20 (9)       16 (7.5)         -             -             -             -         
 Abnormal Visual Fields           8 (4)         10 (5)          -             -             -           1 (&lt;1)      
 Corneal Keratopathy              4 (2)         2 (1)           -             -             -             -         
 Glaucoma                        3 (1.5)        2 (1)         1 (&lt;1)          -             -           1 (&lt;1)      
 Abnormal Vision/Diplopia           -             -             -             -          3 (1.5)          -         
   Thromboembolic                                                                                                   
 Pulmonary Embolism               4 (2)         2 (1)         1 (&lt;1)          -             -           1 (&lt;1)      
 Thrombophlebitis                   -           2 (1)         1 (&lt;1)        1 (&lt;1)        4 (2)        3 (1.5)      
 Thrombosis                         -           1 (&lt;1)        1 (&lt;1)          -          3 (1.5)        4 (2)       
 CVA/TIA                          1 (&lt;1)          -             -           1 (&lt;1)        4 (2)         4 (2)       
   Elevated Liver Tests**                                                                                           
 AST                              11 (5)        4 (2)        30 (19)       22 (15)       32 (15)       35 (17)      
 Alkaline Phosphatase            41 (19)       24 (11)       16 (10)        13 (9)        18 (8)       31 (15)      
 Bilirubin                       3 (1.5)        4 (2)         2 (1)         1 (&lt;1)        2 (1)        3 (1.5)      
 Hypercalcemia                    6 (3)         6 (3)         1 (&lt;1)          -             -             -         
             Other adverse reactions included leukopenia and thrombocytopenia, skin discoloration or dermatitis, constipation, dyspnea, paresis, tremor, vertigo, pruritus, anorexia, reversible corneal opacity (corneal verticulata), asthenia, alopecia, depression, jaundice, and rigors.
 

 The incidence of AST elevations was greater in the 200 and 240 mg FARESTON dose arms than in the tamoxifen arms. Higher doses of FARESTON were also associated with an increase in nausea.



 Approximately 4% of patients were withdrawn for toxicity from the high-dose FARESTON treatment arms. Reasons for withdrawal included hypercalcemia, abnormal liver function tests, and one case each of toxic hepatitis, depression, dizziness, incoordination, ataxia, blurry vision, diffuse dermatitis, and a constellation of symptoms consisting of nausea, sweating, and tremor.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions were identified during post approval use of FARESTON. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions reported during post approval use of FARESTON have been consistent with clinical trial experience. The most frequently reported adverse reactions related to FARESTON use since market introduction include hot flash, sweating, nausea, and vaginal discharge.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

WARNING: QT PROLONGATION



  

WARNING: QT PROLONGATION



    FARESTON has been shown to prolong the QTc interval in a dose- and concentration-related manner   [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  . Prolongation of the QT interval can result in a type of ventricular tachycardia called Torsade de pointes, which may result in syncope, seizure, and/or death. Toremifene should not be prescribed to patients with congenital/acquired QT prolongation, uncorrected hypokalemia or uncorrected hypomagnesemia. Drugs known to prolong the QT interval and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors should be avoided   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: QT PROLONGATION  



   FARESTON has been shown to prolong the QTc interval in a dose- and concentration-related manner   [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  . Prolongation of the QT interval can result in a type of ventricular tachycardia called Torsade de pointes, which may result in syncope, seizure, and/or death. Toremifene should not be prescribed to patients with congenital/acquired QT prolongation, uncorrected hypokalemia or uncorrected hypomagnesemia. Drugs known to prolong the QT interval and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors should be avoided   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Prolongation of the QT Interval (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypercalcemia and Tumor Flare (  5.2  ) 
 *  Tumorigenicity (  5.3  ) 
 *  General (  5.4  ) 
 *  Laboratory Tests (  5.5  ) 
 *  Pregnancy: Fetal harm may occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised not to become pregnant when taking FARESTON. (  5.6  ,  8.1  ) 
 *  Women of Childbearing Potential: Use effective nonhormonal contraception during FARESTON therapy. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Prolongation of the QT Interval



  Toremifene has been shown to prolong the QTc interval in a dose- and concentration-related manner [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  . Prolongation of the QT interval can result in a type of ventricular tachycardia called Torsade de pointes, which may result in syncope, seizure, and/or death.



 Toremifene should be avoided in patients with long QT syndrome. Caution should be exercised in patients with congestive heart failure, hepatic impairment and electrolyte abnormalities. Hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia must be corrected prior to initiating toremifene and these electrolytes should be monitored periodically during therapy. Drugs that prolong the QT interval should be avoided. In patients at increased risk, electrocardiograms (ECGs) should be obtained at baseline and as clinically indicated [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  )  and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  .



    5.2 Hypercalcemia and Tumor Flare



  As with other antiestrogens, hypercalcemia and tumor flare have been reported in some breast cancer patients with bone metastases during the first weeks of treatment with FARESTON. Tumor flare is a syndrome of diffuse musculoskeletal pain and erythema with increased size of tumor lesions that later regress. It is often accompanied by hypercalcemia. Tumor flare does not imply failure of treatment or represent tumor progression. If hypercalcemia occurs, appropriate measures should be instituted and, if hypercalcemia is severe, FARESTON treatment should be discontinued.



    5.3 Tumorigenicity



  Since most toremifene trials have been conducted in patients with metastatic disease, adequate data on the potential endometrial tumorigenicity of long-term treatment with FARESTON are not available. Endometrial hyperplasia has been reported. Some patients treated with FARESTON have developed endometrial cancer, but circumstances (short duration of treatment or prior antiestrogen treatment or premalignant conditions) make it difficult to establish the role of FARESTON. Endometrial hyperplasia of the uterus was observed in animals treated with toremifene [see Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.1  )]  .



    5.4 General



  Patients with a history of thromboembolic diseases should generally not be treated with FARESTON. In general, patients with preexisting endometrial hyperplasia should not be given long-term FARESTON treatment. Patients with bone metastases should be monitored closely for hypercalcemia during the first weeks of treatment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  . Leukopenia and thrombocytopenia have been reported rarely; leukocyte and platelet counts should be monitored when using FARESTON in patients with leukopenia and thrombocytopenia.



    5.5 Laboratory Tests



  Periodic complete blood counts, calcium levels, and liver function tests should be obtained.



    5.6 Use in Pregnancy



  Based on its mechanism of action in humans and findings of increased pregnancy loss and fetal malformation in animal studies, FARESTON can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Toremifene caused embryo-fetal toxicities at maternal doses that were lower than the 60 mg daily recommended human dose on a mg/m  2  basis. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women using FARESTON. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



    5.7 Women of Childbearing Potential



  FARESTON is indicated only in postmenopausal women. However, premenopausal women prescribed FARESTON should use effective non-hormonal contraception and should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus should pregnancy occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
