<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="faslodex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    The most common, clinically significant adverse reactions occurring in &gt;= 5% of patients receiving FASLODEX 500 mg were: injection site pain, nausea, bone pain, arthralgia, headache, back pain, fatigue, pain in extremity, hot flash, vomiting, anorexia, asthenia, musculoskeletal pain, cough, dyspnea, and constipation. (6.1) 
 *    Increased hepatic enzymes (ALT, AST, ALP) occurred in &gt;15% of FASLODEX patients and were not dose-dependent. 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch for voluntary reporting of adverse reactions  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Comparison of FASLODEX 500 mg and FASLODEX 250 mg    



 The following frequency categories for adverse reactions (ARs) were calculated based on the safety analysis of Study 1 that compared FASLODEX 500 mg with FASLODEX 250 mg. The most frequently reported adverse reactions in the fulvestrant 500 mg group were injection site pain (11.6% of patients), nausea (9.7% of patients) and bone pain (9.4% of patients); the most frequently reported adverse reactions in the fulvestrant 250 mg group were nausea (13.6% of patients), back pain (10.7% of patients) and injection site pain (9.1% of patients).



 Table 1 lists adverse reactions reported with an incidence of 5% or greater, regardless of assessed causality, from the controlled clinical trial Study 1 comparing the administration of FASLODEX 500 mg intramuscularly once a month with FASLODEX 250 mg intramuscularly once a month.



   Table 1: Summary of Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions in Study 1 (&gt;= 5% in either treatment group): Safety Population  




  Body System  and Adverse Reaction    Number (%) of Patients    
  Fulvestrant 500 mg  N=361    Fulvestrant 250 mg  N=374    
  Body as a Whole           
  Injection Site Pain       42 (11.6)              34 (9.1)               
  Headache                  28 (7.8)               25 (6.7)               
  Back Pain                 27 (7.5)               40 (10.7)              
  Fatigue                   27 (7.5)               24 (6.4)               
  Pain in Extremity         25 (6.9)               26 (7.0)               
  Asthenia                  21 (5.8)               23 (6.1)               
  Vascular System           
  Hot Flash                 24 (6.6)               22 (5.9)               
  Digestive System          
  Nausea                    35 (9.7)               51 (13.6)              
  Vomiting                  22 (6.1)               21 (5.6)               
  Anorexia                  22 (6.1)               14 (3.7)               
  Constipation              18 (5.0)               13 (3.5)               
  Musculoskeletal System    
  Bone Pain                 34 (9.4)               28 (7.5)               
  Arthralgia                29 (8.0)               29 (7.8)               
  Musculoskeletal Pain      20 (5.5)               12 (3.2)               
  Respiratory System        
  Cough                     19 (5.3)               20 (5.3)               
  Dyspnea                   16 (4.4)               19 (5.1)               
         In the pooled safety population (N=1127) from clinical trials comparing FASLODEX 500 mg to FASLODEX 250 mg, post-baseline increases of &gt;=1 CTC grade in either AST, ALT, or alkaline phosphatase were observed in &gt; 15% of patients receiving FASLODEX. Grade 3-4 increases were observed in 1-2% of patients. The incidence and severity of increased hepatic enzymes (ALT, AST, ALP) did not differ between the 250 mg and the 500 mg FASLODEX arms.
 

     Comparison of FASLODEX 250 mg and Anastrozole 1 mg in Combined Trials (Studies 2 and 3)    



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions in the FASLODEX and anastrozole treatment groups, regardless of the investigator's assessment of causality, were gastrointestinal symptoms (including nausea, vomiting, constipation, diarrhea and abdominal pain), headache, back pain, vasodilatation (hot flashes), and pharyngitis.



 Injection site reactions with mild transient pain and inflammation were seen with FASLODEX and occurred in 7% of patients (1% of treatments) given the single 5 mL injection (predominantly European Trial Study 3) and in 27% of patients (4.6% of treatments) given the 2 x 2.5 mL injections (North American Trial Study 2).



 Table 2 lists adverse reactions reported with an incidence of 5% or greater, regardless of assessed causality, from the two controlled clinical trials comparing the administration of FASLODEX 250 mg intramuscularly once a month with anastrozole 1 mg orally once a day.



   Table 2: Combined Data from Studies 2 and 3, Adverse Reactions &gt;= 5%  




   Body System and Adverse Reaction         FASLODEX 250 mg    N=423    (%)      Anastrozole 1 mg    N=423    (%)     
  
  Body as a Whole                          68.3                     67.6                 
  Asthenia                                 22.7                     27.0                 
  Pain                                     18.9                     20.3                 
  Headache                                 15.4                     16.8                 
  Back Pain                                14.4                     13.2                 
  Abdominal Pain                           11.8                     11.6                 
  Injection Site PainAll patients on FASLODEX received injections, but only those anastrozole patients who were in the North American Study 2 received placebo injections.    10.9                     6.6                  
  Pelvic Pain                              9.9                      9.0                  
  Chest Pain                               7.1                      5.0                  
  Flu Syndrome                             7.1                      6.4                  
  Fever                                    6.4                      6.4                  
  Accidental Injury                        4.5                      5.7                  
  Cardiovascular System                    30.3                     27.9                 
  Vasodilatation                           17.7                     17.3                 
  Digestive System                         51.5                     48.0                 
  Nausea                                   26.0                     25.3                 
  Vomiting                                 13.0                     11.8                 
  Constipation                             12.5                     10.6                 
  Diarrhea                                 12.3                     12.8                 
  Anorexia                                 9.0                      10.9                 
  Hemic and Lymphatic Systems              13.7                     13.5                 
  Anemia                                   4.5                      5.0                  
  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders      18.2                     17.7                 
  Peripheral Edema                         9.0                      10.2                 
  Musculoskeletal System                   25.5                     27.9                 
  Bone Pain                                15.8                     13.7                 
  Arthritis                                2.8                      6.1                  
  Nervous System                           34.3                     33.8                 
  Dizziness                                6.9                      6.6                  
  Insomnia                                 6.9                      8.5                  
  Paresthesia                              6.4                      7.6                  
  Depression                               5.7                      6.9                  
  Anxiety                                  5.0                      3.8                  
  Respiratory System                       38.5                     33.6                 
  Pharyngitis                              16.1                     11.6                 
  Dyspnea                                  14.9                     12.3                 
  Cough Increased                          10.4                     10.4                 
  Skin and Appendages                      22.2                     23.4                 
  Rash                                     7.3                      8.0                  
  Sweating                                 5.0                      5.2                  
  Urogenital System                        18.2                     14.9                 
  Urinary Tract Infection                  6.1                      3.5                  
           6.2 Post-Marketing Experience
   For FASLODEX 250 mg, other adverse reactions reported as drug-related and seen infrequently (&lt;1%) include thromboembolic phenomena, myalgia, vertigo, leukopenia, and hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema and urticaria.



 Vaginal bleeding has been reported infrequently (&lt;1%), mainly in patients during the first 6 weeks after changing from existing hormonal therapy to treatment with FASLODEX. If bleeding persists, further evaluation should be considered.



 Elevation of bilirubin, elevation of gamma GT, hepatitis, and liver failure have been reported infrequently (&lt;1%).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Blood Disorders: Should be used with caution in patients with bleeding diatheses, thrombocytopenia, or anticoagulant use. (5.1) 
 *    Hepatic Impairment: A 250 mg dose is recommended in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (2.2, 5.2, 8.6) 
 *    Pregnancy: Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised of the potential hazard to the fetus and to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving FASLODEX. (5.3) 
    
 

   5.1 Blood Disorders



  Because FASLODEX is administered intramuscularly, it should be used with caution in patients with bleeding diatheses, thrombocytopenia, or anticoagulant use.



    5.2 Hepatic Impairment



  The safety and pharmacokinetics of FASLODEX were evaluated in a study in seven subjects with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class B) and seven subjects with normal hepatic function. Exposure was increased in patients with moderate hepatic impairment, therefore a dose of 250 mg is recommended [see Dosage and Administration  (2.2)  ].  



 FASLODEX has not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.6)  ].  



    5.3 Use in Pregnancy



  Based on its mechanism of action and findings in animals, FASLODEX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Fulvestrant caused fetal loss or abnormalities in animals when administered during the period of organogenesis at doses significantly smaller than the maximum recommended human dose based on the body surface area. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women using FASLODEX. Women of childbearing potential should be advised not to become pregnant while receiving FASLODEX. If FASLODEX is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while receiving this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
