<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="feiba" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  FEIBA NF can precipitate allergic-type hypersensitivity reactions; these reactions can be severe and can be systemic. Other infusion reactions, such as chills, pyrexia, and hypertension have also been reported.



   Adverse Reactions From Clinical Trials

  The adverse reactions presented in this section have been reported from two studies with FEIBA for the treatment of bleeding episodes in pediatric and adult patients with hemophilia A or B and inhibitors to factors VIII or IX. One study also enrolled acquired hemophilia patients with factor VIII inhibitors (4 of 49 patients).



 Clinical Trial Adverse ReactionsA precise estimate of the rate of these adverse reactions is not possible from the available data. 
   System Organ Class (SOC)                                Preferred MedDRA Term                         
  BLOOD AND LYMPHATIC   SYSTEM DISORDERS                 Increase of inhibitor titer (anamnestic response)   
   NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                               Somnolence  Dizziness  Dysgeusia Hypoesthesia   
   RESPIRATORY, THORACIC, AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS      Dyspnea                                         
   GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                            Nausea                                          
   GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS     Chills  Pyrexia  Chest pain Chest discomfort   
          Post-marketing Adverse Reactions
   The following adverse reactions have been reported in the post-marketing experience, listed by MedDRA System Organ Class (SOC), then by Preferred Term in order of severity, where feasible. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 BLOOD AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM DISORDERS: Disseminated intravascular coagulation



 IMMUNE SYSTEM DISORDERS: Anaphylactic reaction, Hypersensitivity



 NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS: Paresthesia, Thrombotic stroke, Embolic stroke, Headache



 CARDIAC DISORDERS: Myocardial infarction, Tachycardia



 VASCULAR DISORDERS: Thrombosis, Venous thrombosis, Arterial thrombosis, Hypotension, Hypertension, Flushing



 RESPIRATORY, THORACIC, AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS: Pulmonary embolism, Bronchospasm, Wheezing, Cough



 GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS: Vomiting, Diarrhea, Abdominal discomfort



 SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS: Angioedema, Urticaria, Pruritus, Rash



 GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS: Malaise, Feeling hot, Injection site pain.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

   



   Nanofiltered

                                and Vapor Heated   



   Lyophilized powder for solution  



   Intravenous  



   WARNING

    Thrombotic and thromboembolic

                                        events have been reported during postmarketing surveillance

                                        following infusion of FEIBA VH or FEIBA NF, particularly

                                        following the administration of high doses and/or in

                                        patients with thrombotic risk factors (See WARNINGS,

                                        PRECAUTIONS and ADVERSE

                                REACTIONS).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
