<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="felbatol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Meda Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-526-3840 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 The most common adverse reactions seen in association with Felbatol(r) (felbamate) in adults during monotherapy are anorexia, vomiting, insomnia, nausea, and headache. The most common adverse reactions seen in association with Felbatol(r) in adults during adjunctive therapy are anorexia, vomiting, insomnia, nausea, dizziness, somnolence, and headache.



 The most common adverse reactions seen in association with Felbatol(r) in children during adjunctive therapy are anorexia, vomiting, insomnia, headache, and somnolence.



 The dropout rate because of adverse experiences or intercurrent illnesses among adult felbamate patients was 12 percent (120/977). The dropout rate because of adverse experiences or intercurrent illnesses among pediatric felbamate patients was six percent (22/357). In adults, the body systems associated with causing these withdrawals in order of frequency were: digestive (4.3%), psychological (2.2%), whole body (1.7%), neurological (1.5%), and dermatological (1.5%). In children, the body systems associated with causing these withdrawals in order of frequency were: digestive (1.7%), neurological (1.4%), dermatological (1.4%), psychological (1.1%), and whole body (1.0%). In adults, specific events with an incidence of 1% or greater associated with causing these withdrawals, in order of frequency were: anorexia (1.6%), nausea (1.4%), rash (1.2%), and weight decrease (1.1%). In children, specific events with an incidence of 1% or greater associated with causing these withdrawals, in order of frequency was rash (1.1%).



   Incidence in Clinical Trials:  The prescriber should be aware that the figures cited in the following table cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different investigators, treatments, and uses including the use of Felbatol(r) (felbamate) as adjunctive therapy where the incidence of adverse events may be higher due to drug interactions. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the side effect incidence rate in the population studied.



   Adults    Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials--Monotherapy Studies in Adults:  The table that follows enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 2% or more among 58 adult patients who received Felbatol(r) monotherapy at dosages of 3600 mg/day in double-blind controlled trials. Table 3 presents reported adverse events that were classified using standard WHO-based dictionary terminology.



 Table 3 Adults Treatment-Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in Controlled Monotherapy Trials 
 *3600 mg/day;** 15 mg/kg/day   
  
                            Felbatol(r)* (N=58)        Low Dose Valproate** (N=50)   
 Body System Event          %                          %                           
 Body as a Whole  Fatigue  Weight Decrease  Face Edema   6.93.43.4                  4.000                      
 Central Nervous System  Insomnia  Headache  Anxiety   8.66.95.2                  4.018.02.0                 
 Dermatological  Acne  Rash   3.43.4                     00                         
 Digestive  Dyspepsia  Vomiting  Constipation  Diarrhea  SGPT Increased   8.68.66.95.25.2            2.02.02.002.0              
 Metabolic/Nutritional  Hypophosphatemia   3.4                        0                          
 Respiratory  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection  Rhinitis   8.66.9                     4.00                       
 Special Senses  Diplopia  Otitis Media   3.43.4                     4.00                       
 Urogenital  Intramenstrual Bleeding  Urinary Tract Infection   3.43.4                     02.0                       
        Incidence in Controlled Add-On Clinical Studies in Adults:  Table 4 enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 2% or more among 114 adult patients who received Felbatol(r) adjunctive therapy in add-on controlled trials at dosages up to 3600 mg/day. Reported adverse events were classified using standard WHO-based dictionary terminology.
 

 Many adverse experiences that occurred during adjunctive therapy may be a result of drug interactions. Adverse experiences during adjunctive therapy typically resolved with conversion to monotherapy, or with adjustment of the dosage of other antiepileptic drugs.



 Table 4 Adults Treatment-Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in Controlled Add-On Trials 
                            Felbatol(r)                Placebo                     
 (N=114)                    (N=43)                      
 Body System/Event          %                          %                           
 Body as a Whole  Fatigue  Fever  Chest Pain   16.82.62.6                 7.04.70                    
 Central Nervous System  Headache  Somnolence  Dizziness  Insomnia  Nervousness  Tremor  Anxiety  Gait Abnormal  Depression  Paraesthesia  Ataxia  Mouth Dry  Stupor   36.819.318.417.57.06.15.35.35.33.53.52.62.6   9.37.014.07.02.32.34.7002.3000   
 Dermatological  Rash        3.5                        4.7                        
 Digestive  Nausea  Anorexia  Vomiting  Dyspepsia  Constipation  Diarrhea  Abdominal Pain  SGPT Increased   34.219.316.712.311.45.35.33.5   2.32.34.77.02.32.300       
 Musculoskeletal  Myalgia    2.6                        0                          
 Respiratory  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection  Sinusitis  Pharyngitis   5.33.52.6                  7.000                      
 Special Senses  Diplopia  Taste Perversion  Vision Abnormal   6.16.15.3                  002.3                      
        Children    Incidence in a Controlled Add-On Trial in Children with Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome:  Table 5 enumerates adverse events that occurred more than once among 31 pediatric patients who received Felbatol(r) up to 45 mg/kg/day or a maximum of 3600 mg/day. Reported adverse events were classified using standard WHO-based dictionary terminology.
 

 Table 5 Children Treatment-Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in Controlled Add-On Lennox-Gastaut Trials 
                            Felbatol(r)                Placebo                     
 (N=31)                     (N=27)                      
 Body System/Event          %                          %                           
 Body as a Whole  Fever  Fatigue  Weight Decrease  Pain   22.69.76.56.5              11.13.700                  
 Central Nervous System  Somnolence  Insomnia  Nervousness  Gait Abnormal  Headache  Thinking Abnormal  Ataxia  Urinary Incontinence  Emotional Lability  Miosis   48.416.116.19.76.56.56.56.56.56.5   11.114.818.5018.53.73.77.400   
 Dermatological  Rash        9.7                        7.4                        
 Digestive  Anorexia  Vomiting  Constipation  Hiccup  Nausea  Dyspepsia   54.838.712.99.76.56.5      14.814.803.703.7           
 Hematologic  Purpura  Leukopenia   12.96.5                    7.40                       
 Respiratory  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection  Pharyngitis  Coughing   45.29.76.5                 25.93.70                   
 Special Senses  Otitis Media   9.7                        0                          
        Other Events Observed in Association with the Administration of Felbatol(r) (felbamate):  In the paragraphs that follow, the adverse clinical events, other than those in the preceding tables, that occurred in a total of 977 adults and 357 children exposed to Felbatol(r) (felbamate) and that are reasonably associated with its use are presented. They are listed in order of decreasing frequency. Because the reports cite events observed in open-label and uncontrolled studies, the role of Felbatol(r) in their causation cannot be reliably determined.
 

 Events are classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions: frequent adverse events are defined as those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100-1/1000 patients; and rare events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



 Event frequencies are calculated as the number of patients reporting an event divided by the total number of patients (N=1334) exposed to Felbatol(r).



   Body as a Whole:    Frequent:  Weight increase, asthenia, malaise, influenza-like symptoms;  Rare:  anaphylactoid reaction, chest pain substernal.  Cardiovascular:    Frequent:  Palpitation, tachycardia;  Rare:  supraventricular tachycardia.  Central Nervous System:    Frequent:  Agitation, psychological disturbance, aggressive reaction:  Infrequent:  hallucination, euphoria, suicide attempt, migraine.  Digestive:    Frequent:  SGOT increased;  Infrequent:  esophagitis, appetite increased;  Rare:  GGT elevated.  Hematologic:    Infrequent:  Lymphadenopathy, leukopenia, leukocytosis, thrombocytopenia, granulocytopenia;  Rare:  antinuclear factor test positive, qualitative platelet disorder, agranulocytosis.  Metabolic/Nutritional:    Infrequent:  Hypokalemia, hyponatremia, LDH increased, alkaline phosphatase increased, hypophosphatemia;  Rare:  creatinine phosphokinase increased.  Musculoskeletal:    Infrequent:  Dystonia.  Dermatological:    Frequent:  Pruritus;  Infrequent:  urticaria, bullous eruption;  Rare:  buccal mucous membrane swelling, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome.  Special Senses:    Rare:  Photosensitivity allergic reaction.



   Postmarketing Adverse Event Reports:  Voluntary reports of adverse events in patients taking Felbatol(r) (usually in conjunction with other drugs) have been received since market introduction and may have no causal relationship with the drug(s). These include the following by body system:  Body as a Whole:  neoplasm, sepsis, L.E. syndrome, SIDS, sudden death, edema, hypothermia, rigors, hyperpyrexia.  Cardiovascular:  atrial fibrillation, atrial arrhythmia, cardiac arrest, torsade de pointes, cardiac failure, hypotension, hypertension, flushing, thrombophlebitis, ischemic necrosis, gangrene, peripheral ischemia, bradycardia, Henoch-Schonlein purpura (vasculitis).  Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System:  delusion, paralysis, mononeuritis, cerebrovascular disorder, cerebral edema, coma, manic reaction, encephalopathy, paranoid reaction, nystagmus, choreoathetosis, extrapyramidal disorder, confusion, psychosis, status epilepticus, dyskinesia, dysarthria, respiratory depression, apathy, concentration impaired.  Dermatological:  abnormal body odor, sweating, lichen planus, livedo reticularis, alopecia, toxic epidermal necrolysis.  Digestive:  (Refer to    WARNINGS    ) hepatitis, hepatic failure, G.I. hemorrhage, hyperammonemia, pancreatitis, hematemesis, gastritis, rectal hemorrhage, flatulence, gingival bleeding, acquired megacolon, ileus, intestinal obstruction, enteritis, ulcerative stomatitis, glossitis, dysphagia, jaundice, gastric ulcer, gastric dilatation, gastroesophageal reflux.  Fetal Disorders:  fetal death, microcephaly, genital malformation, anencephaly, encephalocele.  Hematologic:  (Refer to    WARNINGS    ) increased and decreased prothrombin time, anemia, hypochromic anemia, aplastic anemia, pancytopenia, hemolytic uremic syndrome, increased mean corpuscular volume (mcv) with and without anemia, coagulation disorder, embolism-limb, disseminated intravascular coagulation, eosinophilia, hemolytic anemia, leukemia, including myelogenous leukemia, and lymphoma, including T-cell and B-cell lymphoproliferative disorders.  Metabolic/Nutritional:  hypernatremia, hypoglycemia, SIADH, hypomagnesemia, dehydration, hyperglycemia, hypocalcemia.  Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, muscle weakness, involuntary muscle contraction, rhabdomyolysis.  Respiratory:  dyspnea, pneumonia, pneumonitis, hypoxia, epistaxis, pleural effusion, respiratory insufficiency, pulmonary hemorrhage, asthma.  Special Senses:  hemianopsia, decreased hearing, conjunctivitis.  Urogenital:  menstrual disorder, acute renal failure, hepatorenal syndrome, hematuria, urinary retention, nephrosis, vaginal hemorrhage, abnormal renal function, dysuria, placental disorder.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

  WARNING

    1. APLASTIC ANEMIA

          THE USE OF FELBATOL(r) (felbamate) IS ASSOCIATED

       WITH A MARKED INCREASE IN THE INCIDENCE OF APLASTIC ANEMIA. ACCORDINGLY,

       FELBATOL(r) SHOULD ONLY BE USED IN PATIENTS WHOSE EPILEPSY IS SO

       SEVERE THAT THE RISK OF APLASTIC ANEMIA IS DEEMED ACCEPTABLE IN LIGHT OF

       THE BENEFITS CONFERRED BY ITS USE (SEE     INDICATIONS    ). ORDINARILY, A PATIENT SHOULD NOT BE PLACED ON AND/OR

       CONTINUED ON FELBATOL(r) WITHOUT CONSIDERATION OF APPROPRIATE

       EXPERT HEMATOLOGIC CONSULTATION. 



 AMONG FELBATOL(r) TREATED PATIENTS, APLASTIC ANEMIA

       (PANCYTOPENIA IN THE PRESENCE OF A BONE MARROW LARGELY DEPLETED OF

       HEMATOPOIETIC PRECURSORS) OCCURS AT AN INCIDENCE THAT MAY BE MORE THAN A

       100 FOLD GREATER THAN THAT SEEN IN THE UNTREATED POPULATION (I.E., 2 TO

       5 PER MILLION PERSONS PER YEAR). THE RISK OF DEATH IN PATIENTS WITH

       APLASTIC ANEMIA GENERALLY VARIES AS A FUNCTION OF ITS SEVERITY AND

       ETIOLOGY; CURRENT ESTIMATES OF THE OVERALL CASE FATALITY RATE ARE IN THE

       RANGE OF 20 TO 30%, BUT RATES AS HIGH AS 70% HAVE BEEN

       REPORTED IN THE PAST. 



 THERE ARE TOO FEW FELBATOL(r) ASSOCIATED CASES, AND TOO

       LITTLE KNOWN ABOUT THEM TO PROVIDE A RELIABLE ESTIMATE OF THE SYNDROME'S

       INCIDENCE OR ITS CASE FATALITY RATE OR TO IDENTIFY THE FACTORS, IF ANY,

       THAT MIGHT CONCEIVABLY BE USED TO PREDICT WHO IS AT GREATER OR LESSER

       RISK. 



 IN MANAGING PATIENTS ON FELBATOL(r), IT SHOULD BE BORNE IN

       MIND THAT THE CLINICAL MANIFESTATION OF APLASTIC ANEMIA MAY NOT BE SEEN

       UNTIL AFTER A PATIENT HAS BEEN ON FELBATOL(r) FOR SEVERAL MONTHS

       (E.G., ONSET OF APLASTIC ANEMIA AMONG FELBATOL(r) EXPOSED

       PATIENTS FOR WHOM DATA ARE AVAILABLE HAS RANGED FROM 5 TO 30 WEEKS).

       HOWEVER, THE INJURY TO BONE MARROW STEM CELLS THAT IS HELD TO BE

       ULTIMATELY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ANEMIA MAY OCCUR WEEKS TO MONTHS EARLIER.

       ACCORDINGLY, PATIENTS WHO ARE DISCONTINUED FROM FELBATOL(r)

       REMAIN AT RISK FOR DEVELOPING ANEMIA FOR A VARIABLE, AND UNKNOWN, PERIOD

       AFTERWARDS. 



 IT IS NOT KNOWN WHETHER OR NOT THE RISK OF DEVELOPING APLASTIC

       ANEMIA CHANGES WITH DURATION OF EXPOSURE. CONSEQUENTLY, IT IS NOT SAFE

       TO ASSUME THAT A PATIENT WHO HAS BEEN ON FELBATOL(r) WITHOUT

       SIGNS OF HEMATOLOGIC ABNORMALITY FOR LONG PERIODS OF TIME IS WITHOUT

       RISK. 



 IT IS NOT KNOWN WHETHER OR NOT THE DOSE OF FELBATOL(r)

       AFFECTS THE INCIDENCE OF APLASTIC ANEMIA. 



 IT IS NOT KNOWN WHETHER OR NOT CONCOMITANT USE OF ANTIEPILEPTIC

       DRUGS AND/OR OTHER DRUGS AFFECTS THE INCIDENCE OF APLASTIC ANEMIA.



 APLASTIC ANEMIA TYPICALLY DEVELOPS WITHOUT PREMONITORY CLINICAL

       OR LABORATORY SIGNS, THE FULL BLOWN SYNDROME PRESENTING WITH SIGNS OF

       INFECTION, BLEEDING, OR ANEMIA. ACCORDINGLY, ROUTINE BLOOD TESTING

       CANNOT BE RELIABLY USED TO REDUCE THE INCIDENCE OF APLASTIC ANEMIA, BUT,

       IT WILL, IN SOME CASES, ALLOW THE DETECTION OF THE HEMATOLOGIC CHANGES

       BEFORE THE SYNDROME DECLARES ITSELF CLINICALLY. FELBATOL(r)

       SHOULD BE DISCONTINUED IF ANY EVIDENCE OF BONE MARROW DEPRESSION OCCURS. 



   2. HEPATIC

       FAILURE   EVALUATION OF POSTMARKETING EXPERIENCE SUGGESTS

       THAT ACUTE LIVER FAILURE IS ASSOCIATED WITH THE USE OF

       FELBATOL(r). THE REPORTED RATE IN THE U.S. HAS BEEN ABOUT 6 CASES

       OF LIVER FAILURE LEADING TO DEATH OR TRANSPLANT PER 75,000 PATIENT YEARS

       OF USE. THIS RATE IS AN UNDERESTIMATE BECAUSE OF UNDER REPORTING, AND

       THE TRUE RATE COULD BE CONSIDERABLY GREATER THAN THIS. FOR EXAMPLE, IF

       THE REPORTING RATE IS 10%, THE TRUE RATE WOULD BE ONE CASE PER

       1,250 PATIENT YEARS OF USE. 



 OF THE CASES REPORTED, ABOUT 67% RESULTED IN DEATH OR

       LIVER TRANSPLANTATION, USUALLY WITHIN 5 WEEKS OF THE ONSET OF SIGNS AND

       SYMPTOMS OF LIVER FAILURE. THE EARLIEST ONSET OF SEVERE HEPATIC

       DYSFUNCTION FOLLOWED SUBSEQUENTLY BY LIVER FAILURE WAS 3 WEEKS AFTER

       INITIATION OF FELBATOL(r). ALTHOUGH SOME REPORTS DESCRIBED DARK

       URINE AND NONSPECIFIC PRODROMAL SYMPTOMS (E.G., ANOREXIA, MALAISE, AND

       GASTROINTESTINAL SYMPTOMS), IN OTHER REPORTS IT WAS NOT CLEAR IF ANY

       PRODROMAL SYMPTOMS PRECEDED THE ONSET OF JAUNDICE.



 IT IS NOT KNOWN WHETHER OR NOT THE RISK OF DEVELOPING HEPATIC

       FAILURE CHANGES WITH DURATION OF EXPOSURE. 



 IT IS NOT KNOWN WHETHER OR NOT THE DOSAGE OF FELBATOL(r)

       AFFECTS THE INCIDENCE OF HEPATIC FAILURE.



 IT IS NOT KNOWN WHETHER CONCOMITANT USE OF OTHER ANTIEPILEPTIC

       DRUGS AND/OR OTHER DRUGS AFFECT THE INCIDENCE OF HEPATIC FAILURE.



 FELBATOL(r) SHOULD NOT BE PRESCRIBED FOR ANYONE WITH A

       HISTORY OF HEPATIC DYSFUNCTION. 



 TREATMENT WITH FELBATOL(r) SHOULD BE INITIATED ONLY IN

       INDIVIDUALS WITHOUT ACTIVE LIVER DISEASE AND WITH NORMAL BASELINE SERUM

       TRANSAMINASES. IT HAS NOT BEEN PROVED THAT PERIODIC SERUM TRANSAMINASE

       TESTING WILL PREVENT SERIOUS INJURY BUT IT IS GENERALLY BELIEVED THAT

       EARLY DETECTION OF DRUG-INDUCED HEPATIC INJURY ALONG WITH IMMEDIATE

       WITHDRAWAL OF THE SUSPECT DRUG ENHANCES THE LIKELIHOOD FOR RECOVERY.

       THERE IS NO INFORMATION AVAILABLE THAT DOCUMENTS HOW RAPIDLY PATIENTS

       CAN PROGRESS FROM NORMAL LIVER FUNCTION TO LIVER FAILURE, BUT OTHER

       DRUGS KNOWN TO BE HEPATOTOXINS CAN CAUSE LIVER FAILURE RAPIDLY (E.G.,

       FROM NORMAL ENZYMES TO LIVER FAILURE IN 2-4 WEEKS). ACCORDINGLY,

       MONITORING OF SERUM TRANSAMINASE LEVELS (AST AND ALT) IS RECOMMENDED AT

       BASELINE AND PERIODICALLY THEREAFTER. WHILE THE MORE FREQUENT THE

       MONITORING THE GREATER THE CHANCES OF EARLY DETECTION, THE PRECISE

       SCHEDULE FOR MONITORING IS A MATTER OF CLINICAL JUDGEMENT. 



 FELBATOL(r) SHOULD BE DISCONTINUED IF EITHER SERUM AST OR

       SERUM ALT LEVELS BECOME INCREASED &gt;= 2 TIMES THE UPPER LIMIT OF

       NORMAL, OR IF CLINICAL SIGNS AND SYMPTOMS SUGGEST LIVER FAILURE (SEE

          PRECAUTIONS  ). PATIENTS WHO DEVELOP EVIDENCE OF

       HEPATOCELLULAR INJURY WHILE ON FELBATOL(r) AND ARE WITHDRAWN FROM

       THE DRUG FOR ANY REASON SHOULD BE PRESUMED TO BE AT INCREASED RISK FOR

       LIVER INJURY IF FELBATOL(r) IS REINTRODUCED. ACCORDINGLY, SUCH

       PATIENTS SHOULD NOT BE CONSIDERED FOR RE-TREATMENT.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
