<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fentora" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common (frequency &gt;=10%): nausea, dizziness, vomiting, fatigue, anemia, constipation, edema peripheral, asthenia, dehydration and headache. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Teva Pharmaceuticals, at 1-800-896-5855 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of FENTORA has been evaluated in 304 opioid-tolerant cancer patients with breakthrough pain. The average duration of therapy was 76 days with some patients being treated for over 12 months.



 The most commonly observed adverse events seen with FENTORA are typical of opioid side effects. Opioid side effects should be expected and managed accordingly.



 The clinical trials of FENTORA were designed to evaluate safety and efficacy in treating patients with cancer and breakthrough pain; all patients were taking concomitant opioids, such as sustained-release morphine, sustained-release oxycodone or transdermal fentanyl, for their persistent pain.



 The adverse event data presented here reflect the actual percentage of patients experiencing each adverse effect among patients who received FENTORA for breakthrough pain along with a concomitant opioid for persistent pain. There has been no attempt to correct for concomitant use of other opioids, duration of FENTORA therapy or cancer-related symptoms.



 Table 2 lists, by maximum dose received, adverse events with an overall frequency of 5% or greater within the total population that occurred during titration. The ability to assign a dose-response relationship to these adverse events is limited by the titration schemes used in these studies.



   Table 2.  



   Adverse Events Which Occurred During Titration at a Frequency of &gt;= 5%  




  System Organ Class   MeDRA preferred term, n (%)     100 mcg  (N=45)    200 mcg  (N=34)    400 mcg  (N=53)    600 mcg  (N=56)    800 mcg  (N=113)    Total  (N=304)*    
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
 Nausea                    4 (9)       5 (15)       10 (19)      13 (23)         18 (16)         50 (17)          
 Vomiting                  0           2 (6)        2 (4)        7 (13)          3 (3)           14 (5)           
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
 Fatigue                   3 (7)       1 (3)        9 (17)       1 (2)           5 (4)           19 (6)           
   Nervous system disorders     
 Dizziness                 5 (11)      2 (6)        12 (23)      18 (32)         21 (19)         58 (19)          
 Somnolence                2 (4)       2 (6)        6 (12)       7 (13)          3 (3)           20 (7)           
 Headache                  1 (2)       3 (9)        4 (8)        8 (14)          10 (9)          26 (9)           
              * Three hundred and two (302) patients were included in the safety analysis.
 

 Table 3 lists, by successful dose, adverse events with an overall frequency of &gt;=5% within the total population that occurred after a successful dose had been determined.



   Table 3.  



   Adverse Events Which Occurred During Long-Term Treatment at a Frequency of &gt;= 5%  




  System Organ Class MeDRA preferred term,   n (%)     100 mcg   (N=19)     200 mcg   (N=31)     400 mcg   (N=44)     600 mcg   (N=48)     800 mcg   (N=58)     Total   (N=200)     
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders     
 Anemia                      6 (32)        4 (13)        4 (9)         5 (10)        7 (13)         26 (13)        
 Neutropenia                 0             2 (6)         1 (2)         4 (8)         4 (7)          11 (6)         
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
 Nausea                      8 (42)        5 (16)        14 (32)       13 (27)       17 (31)        57 (29)        
 Vomiting                    7 (37)        5 (16)        9 (20)        8 (17)        11 (20)        40 (20)        
 Constipation                5 (26)        4 (13)        5 (11)        4 (8)         6 (11)         24 (12)        
 Diarrhea                    3 (16)        0             4 (9)         3 (6)         5 (9)          15 (8)         
 Abdominal pain              2 (11)        1 (3)         4 (9)         7 (15)        4 (7)          18 (9)         
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
 Edema peripheral            6 (32)        5 (16)        4 (9)         5 (10)        3 (5)          23 (12)        
 Asthenia                    3 (16)        5 (16)        2 (5)         3 (6)         8 (15)         21 (11)        
 Fatigue                     3 (16)        3 (10)        9 (20)        9 (19)        8 (15)         32 (16)        
   Infections and infestations     
 Pneumonia                   1 (5)         5 (16)        1 (2)         1 (2)         4 (7)          12 (6)         
   Investigations             
 Weight decreased            1 (5)         1 (3)         3 (7)         2 (4)         6 (11)         13 (7)         
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders     
 Dehydration                 4 (21)        0             4 (9)         6 (13)        7 (13)         21 (11)        
 Anorexia                    1 (5)         2 (6)         4 (9)         3 (6)         6 (11)         16 (8)         
 Hypokalemia                 0             2 (6)         0             1 (2)         8 (15)         11 (6)         
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
 Back pain                   2 (11)        0             2 (5)         3 (6)         2 (4)          9 (5)          
 Arthralgia                  0             1 (3)         3 (7)         4 (8)         3 (5)          11 (6)         
   Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (including cysts and polyps)     
 Cancer pain                 3 (16)        1 (3)         3 (7)         2 (4)         1 (2)          10 (5)         
   Nervous system disorders     
 Dizziness                   5 (26)        3 (10)        5 (11)        6 (13)        6 (11)         25 (13)        
 Headache                    2 (11)        1 (3)         4 (9)         5 (10)        8 (15)         20 (10)        
 Somnolence                  0             1 (3)         4 (9)         4 (8)         8 (15)         17 (9)         
   Psychiatric disorders      
 Confusional state           3 (16)        1 (3)         2 (5)         3 (6)         5 (9)          14 (7)         
 Depression                  2 (11)        1 (3)         4 (9)         3 (6)         5 (9)          15 (8)         
 Insomnia                    2 (11)        1 (3)         3 (7)         2 (4)         4 (7)          12 (6)         
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders     
 Cough                       1 (5)         1 (3)         2 (5)         4 (8)         5 (9)          13 (7)         
 Dyspnea                     1 (5)         6 (19)        0             7 (15)        4 (7)          18 (9)         
              
 

  In addition, a small number of patients (n=11) with Grade 1 mucositis were included in clinical trials designed to support the safety of FENTORA. There was no evidence of excess toxicity in this subset of patients.



 The duration of exposure to FENTORA  varied greatly, and included open-label and double-blind studies. The frequencies listed below represent the &gt;=1% of patients (and not listed in Tables 2 and 3 above) from three clinical trials (titration and post-titration periods combined) who experienced that event while receiving FENTORA.  Events are classified by system organ class.



   Adverse Events (&gt;=1%)  



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Thrombocytopenia, Leukopenia



   Cardiac Disorders:  Tachycardia



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Stomatitis, Dry Mouth, Dyspepsia, Upper Abdominal Pain, Abdominal Distension, Dysphagia, Gingival Pain, Stomach Discomfort, Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease, Glossodynia, Mouth Ulceration



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Pyrexia, Application Site Pain, Application Site Ulcer, Chest Pain, Chills, Application Site Irritation, Edema, Mucosal Inflammation, Pain



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Jaundice



   Infections and Infestations:  Oral Candidiasis, Urinary Tract Infection, Cellulitis, Nasopharyngitis, Sinusitis, Upper Respiratory Tract Infection, Influenza, Tooth Abscess



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  Fall, Spinal Compression Fracture



   Investigations:  Decreased Hemoglobin, Increased Blood Glucose, Decreased Hematocrit, Decreased Platelet Count



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Decreased Appetite, Hypoalbuminemia, Hypercalcemia, Hypomagnesemia, Hyponatremia, Reduced Oral Intake



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Pain in Extremity, Myalgia, Chest Wall Pain, Muscle Spasms, Neck Pain, Shoulder Pain



   Nervous System Disorders:  Hypoesthesia, Dysgeusia, Lethargy, Peripheral Neuropathy, Paresthesia, Balance Disorder, Migraine, Neuropathy



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Anxiety, Disorientation, Euphoric Mood, Hallucination, Nervousness



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Renal Failure



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Pharyngolaryngeal Pain, Exertional Dyspnea, Pleural Effusion, Decreased Breathing Sounds, Wheezing



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Pruritus, Rash, Hyperhidrosis, Cold Sweat



   Vascular Disorders:  Hypertension, Hypotension, Pallor, Deep Vein Thrombosis
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL

  WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL

      RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION    



   Fatal respiratory depression has occurred in patients treated with FENTORA, including following use in opioid non-tolerant patients and  improper dosing.    The substitution of FENTORA for any other fentanyl product may result in fatal overdose.    



   Due to the risk of respiratory depression, FENTORA is contraindicated in the management of acute or postoperative pain including headache/migraine and in opioid non-tolerant patients.      [see Contraindications (4)]      



   FENTORA must be kept out of reach of children.   [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.1  ) and How Supplied/Storage and Handling (  16.1  )    ]      



   The concomitant use of FENTORA with CYP3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentrations, and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression     [see Drug Interactions (7)]    .   



     MEDICATION ERRORS    



   Substantial differences exist in the pharmacokinetic profile of FENTORA compared to other fentanyl products that result in clinically important differences in the extent of absorption of fentanyl that could result in fatal overdose.    



   - When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other fentanyl products to FENTORA.   [see Dosage and Administration   (    2.1  )]    



   - When dispensing, do not substitute a FENTORA prescription for other fentanyl products.    



     ABUSE POTENTIAL    



   FENTORA contains fentanyl, an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance, with an abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics.  FENTORA can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit.  This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing FENTORA in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse or diversion.    



   Because of the risk for misuse, abuse, addiction, and overdose, FENTORA is available only through a restricted program required by the Food and Drug Administration, called a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS). Under the Transmucosal Immediate Release Fentanyl (TIRF) REMS Access program, outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program.   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]   Further information is available at www.TIRFREMSAccess.com or by calling 1-866-822-1483.  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Due to the risk of fatal respiratory depression, FENTORA is contraindicated in opioid non-tolerant patients (1) and in management of acute or postoperative pain, including headache/migraines. (4) 
 *  Keep out of reach of children. (5.3) 
 *  Use with CYP3A4 inhibitors may cause fatal respiratory depression. (7) 
 *  When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other oral transmucosal fentanyl product to FENTORA. (2.1, 5.2) 
 *  When dispensing, do not substitute with any other fentanyl products. (5.1) 
 *  Contains fentanyl, a Schedule II controlled substance with abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics. (9.1) 
 *  FENTORA is available only through a restricted program called the TIRF REMS Access program. Outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors are required to enroll in the program. (5.11) 
    
 







    BOXED WARNING: MEDICATION GUIDE

  MEDICATION GUIDE

    FENTORA  (r)    (fen-tor-a)    CII  



   (fentanyl buccal tablet  )



   100 mcg, 200 mcg, 400 mcg,     600 mcg, 800 mcg  



  



     IMPORTANT:  



   Do not use FENTORA unless you are regularly using another opioid pain medicine around-the-clock for your cancer pain and your body is used to these medicines (this means you are opioid tolerant). You can ask your healthcare provider if you are opioid tolerant.  



   Keep FENTORA in a safe place away from children.    



   Get emergency help right away if:  



 *  a child takes FENTORA. FENTORA can cause an overdose and death in any child who takes it. 
 *  an adult who has not been prescribed FENTORA uses it 
 *  an adult who is not already taking opioids around-the-clock, uses FENTORA. 
      These are medical emergencies that can cause death. If possible, try to remove FENTORA from the mouth.  
 

      Read this Medication Guide completely     before you start using FENTORA, and each time you get a new prescription.  There may be new information.  This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or your treatment.  Share this important information with members of your household and other caregivers.



   What is the most important information I should know about FENTORA?  



   FENTORA can cause life-threatening breathing problems which can lead to death.  



   1.  Do not use FENTORA if you are not opioid tolerant.  



 2.  If you stop taking your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine for your cancer pain,   you must stop   using FENTORA. You may no longer be opioid tolerant. Talk to your healthcare provider about how to treat your pain.



 3.    Use FENTORA exactly as prescribed by your healthcare provider.  



 *  You must not use more than 2 doses of FENTORA for each episode of breakthrough cancer pain. 
 *  You must wait at least 4 hours before treating a new episode of breakthrough pain with FENTORA. See the Medication Guide section "How should I use FENTORA?" and the Instructions for Use at the end of this Medication Guide for detailed information about how to use FENTORA the right way. 
    4.    Do not switch from FENTORA to other medicines that contain fentanyl without talking with your healthcare provider.    The amount of fentanyl in a dose of FENTORA is not the same as the amount of fentanyl in other medicines that contain fentanyl.  Your healthcare provider will prescribe a starting dose of FENTORA that may be different than other fentanyl containing medicines you may have been taking.
 

 5.    Do not   use FENTORA for short-term pain that you would expect to go away in a few days, such as:



 *  pain after surgery 
 *  headache or migraine 
 *  dental pain 
    6.    Never give FENTORA to anyone else  , even if they have the same symptoms you have.  It may harm them or even cause death.
 

 FENTORA is a federally controlled substance (CII) because it is a strong opioid (narcotic) pain medicine that can be misused by people who abuse prescription medicines or street drugs.  



 *  Prevent theft, misuse or abuse. Keep FENTORA in a safe place to protect it from being stolen. FENTORA can be a target for people who abuse (narcotic) medicines or street drugs. 
 *  Selling or giving away this medicine is against the law. 
    7.  FENTORA is available only through a program called the   T  ransmucosal   I  mmediate   R  elease   F  entanyl (TIRF)   R  isk   E  valuation and   M  itigation   S  trategy (REMS) Access program.  To receive FENTORA, you must:
 

 *  talk to your healthcare provider 
 *  understand the benefits and risks of FENTORA 
 *  agree to all of the instructions 
 *  sign the Patient-Prescriber Agreement form. 
      What is FENTORA?   
 

 *  FENTORA is a prescription medicine that contains the medicine fentanyl.   
   *  FENTORA is used to manage breakthrough pain in adults with cancer who are already routinely taking other opioid pain medicines around-the-clock for cancer pain. 
 *  FENTORA is started only after you have been taking other opioid pain medicines and your body has become used to them (you are opioid tolerant). Do not use FENTORA if you are not opioid tolerant.  
 *  You must stay under your healthcare provider's care while using FENTORA. 
 *  FENTORA is only:available through the TIRF REMS Access programgiven to people who are opioid tolerant 
    It is not known if FENTORA is safe and effective in children under 18 years of age.
 

   Who should not use FENTORA?  



   Do not use FENTORA:  



 *  if you are not opioid tolerant.Opioid tolerant means that you are already taking other opioid pain medicines around-the-clock for your cancer pain, and your body is used to these medicines. 
 *  for short-term pain that you would expect to go away in a few days, such as:pain after surgery headaches or migrainesdental pain 
 *  if you are allergic to any of the ingredients in FENTORA. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in FENTORA. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before starting FENTORA?  
 

 Before using FENTORA, tell your healthcare provider if you:



 *  have trouble breathing or lung problems such as asthma, wheezing, or shortness of breath 
 *  have or had a head injury or brain problem 
 *  have liver or kidney problems 
 *  have seizures 
 *  have a slow heart rate or other heart problems 
 *  have low blood pressure 
 *  have mental problems including major depression, schizophrenia or hallucinations (seeing or hearing things that are not there) 
 *  have a past or present drinking problem (alcoholism), or a family history of drinking problems 
 *  have a past or present drug abuse problem or addiction problem, or a family history of a drug abuse problem or addiction problem 
 *  have any other medical conditions 
 *  are pregnant or plan to become pregnant.  FENTORA may cause serious harm to your unborn baby. 
 *  are breastfeeding or plan to breastfeed. FENTORA passes into your breast milk. It can cause serious harm to your baby. You should not take FENTORA while breastfeeding. 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take,   including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements.  Some medicines may cause serious or life-threatening side effects when taken with FENTORA.  Sometimes, the doses of certain medicines and FENTORA need to be changed if used together. 
 

 *  Do not take any medicine while using FENTORA until you have talked to your healthcare provider. Your healthcare provider will tell you if it is safe to take other medicines while you are using FENTORA. 
 *  Be very careful about taking other medicines that may make you sleepy, such as other pain medicines, anti-depressant medicines, sleeping pills, anti-anxiety medicines, antihistamines, or tranquilizers. 
    Know the medicines you take.  Keep a list of them to show your healthcare provider and pharmacist when you get a new medicine.
 

   How should I use FENTORA?  



   Before you can begin to use FENTORA:  



 *  Your healthcare provider will explain the TIRF REMS Access program to you. 
 *  You will sign the TIRF REMS Access program Patient-Prescriber Agreement form. 
 *  FENTORA is only available at pharmacies that are part of the TIRF REMS Access program. Your healthcare provider will let you know the pharmacy closest to your home where you can have your FENTORA prescription filled. 
      Using FENTORA:  
 

 *  Use FENTORA exactly as prescribed.Do not use FENTORA more often than prescribed. 
 *  Your healthcare provider will change the dose until you and your healthcare provider find the right dose for you. 
 *  See the detailed Instructions for Use at the end of this Medication Guide for information about how to use FENTORA the right way. 
 *  Use FENTORA tablets whole. 
 *  Do not crush, split, suck, or chew FENTORA tablets, or swallow the tablets whole. You will get less relief for your breakthrough cancer pain. 
 *  Wait 30 minutes after using FENTORA. If there is any of the FENTORA tablet left in your mouth, you may drink a glass of water to help you swallow the left over medicine. 
 *  You must not use more than 2 doses of FENTORA for each episode of breakthrough cancer pain.Use 1 dose of FENTORA for an episode of breakthrough cancer pain. If your breakthrough cancer pain does not get better 30 minutes after taking the first dose of FENTORA, you can use only 1 more dose of FENTORA as instructed by your healthcare provider.If your breakthrough pain does not get better after the second dose of FENTORA, call your healthcare provider for instructions. Do not use another dose of FENTORA at this time. 
 *  Wait at least 4 hours before treating a new episode of breakthrough cancer pain with FENTORA. If you only need to take 1 dose of FENTORA for an episode of breakthrough pain, you must wait 4 hours from the time of that dose to take a dose of FENTORA for a new episode of  breakthrough pain.If you need to use 2 doses of FENTORA for an episode of breakthrough pain, you must wait 4 hours after the second dose to take a dose of FENTORA for a new episode of breakthrough pain. 
 *  It is important for you to keep taking your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine while using FENTORA. 
 *  Talk to your healthcare provider if your dose of FENTORA does not relieve your breakthrough cancer pain. Your healthcare provider will decide if your dose of FENTORA needs to be changed. 
 *  Talk to your healthcare provider if you have more than 4 episodes of breakthrough cancer pain per day.  The dose of your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine may need to be adjusted. 
 *  If you begin to feel dizzy, sick to your stomach, or very sleepy before the tablet is completely dissolved, rinse your mouth with water and spit the remaining pieces of the tablet into a sink or toilet right away. Rinse the sink or flush the toilet to dispose of any remaining tablet pieces. 
 *  If you use too much FENTORA or overdose, you or your caregiver should call for emergency medical help or have someone take you to the nearest hospital emergency room. 
      What should I avoid while taking FENTORA?  
 

 *  Do not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how FENTORA affects you. FENTORA can make you sleepy. Ask your healthcare provider when it is okay to do these activities. 
 *  Do not drink alcohol while using FENTORA. It can increase your chance of getting dangerous side effects. 
      What are the possible side effects of FENTORA?  
 

   FENTORA can cause serious side effects, including:  



 *  Breathing problems that can become life-threatening. See "What is the most important information I should know about FENTORA?"Call your healthcare provider or get emergency medical help right away if you:have trouble breathinghave drowsiness with slowed breathinghave slow, shallow breathing (little chest movement with breathing)feel faint, very dizzy, confused, or have unusual symptoms These symptoms can be a sign that you have taken too much FENTORA or the dose is too high for you. These symptoms may lead to serious problems or death if not treated right away. If you have any of these symptoms, do not take any more FENTORA until you have talked to your healthcare provider. 
 *  Decreased blood pressure. This can make you feel dizzy or lightheaded if you get up too fast from sitting or lying down. 
 *  Physical dependence.Do not stop using FENTORA or taking any other opioid without talking to your healthcare provider. You could become sick with uncomfortable withdrawal symptoms because your body has become used to these medicines. Physical dependency is not the same as drug addiction. 
 *  A chance of abuse or addiction. This chance is higher if you are or have been addicted to or abused other medicines, street drugs, or alcohol, or if you have a history of mental health problems. 
 *  Pain, irritation, or sores at the application site (on your gum, on the inside of your cheek, or under your tongue). Tell your healthcare provider if this is a problem for you. 
    The most common side effects of FENTORA  are: 
 

 *  nausea 
 *  vomiting 
 *  dizziness 
 *  low red blood cell count 
 *  tiredness 
 *  swelling of the arms, hands, legs and feet 
 *  headache 
    Constipation (not often enough or hard bowel movements) is a very common side effect of pain medicines (opioids) including FENTORA and is unlikely to go away without treatment.  Talk to your healthcare provider about dietary changes, and the use of laxatives (medicines to treat constipation) and stool softeners to prevent or treat constipation while taking FENTORA.
 

 Talk to your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away.



 These are not all the possible side effects of FENTORA.  For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.



 Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.



  



   How should I store FENTORA?  



 *  Always keep FENTORA in a safe place away from children and from anyone for whom it has not been prescribed. Protect FENTORA from theft. 
 *  Store FENTORA at room temperature, 59oF  to 86oF (15o C to 30oC)  until ready to use. Do not freeze FENTORA. 
 *  Keep FENTORA in the original blister unit. Do not remove FENTORA from its blister packaging for storage in a temporary container, such as a pill box. 
 *  Keep FENTORA dry. 
       How should I dispose of unused FENTORA tablets when they are no longer needed?  
 

 *  Dispose of any unused FENTORA tablets remaining from a prescription as soon as they are no longer needed.Remove FENTORA tablets from blister packages and flush down the toilet. 
 *  Do not flush the FENTORA packaging (card, blister units, or cartons) down the toilet. 
 *  If you need help with disposal of FENTORA, call Teva Pharmaceuticals at 1-800-896-5855 or call your local Drug Enforcement Agency (DEA) office. 
     
 

   General information about FENTORA  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide.   Use FENTORA only for the purpose for which it was prescribed.     Do not give FENTORA to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have.    FENTORA can harm other people and even cause death.  Sharing FENTORA is against the law  .  



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about FENTORA.  If you would like more information, talk with your doctor.  You can ask your pharmacist or healthcare provider for information about FENTORA that is written for health professionals.  



 For more information about the TIRF REMS Access program, go to   www.TIRFREMSAccess.com   or call 1-866-822-1483.



   What are the ingredients of FENTORA?  



   Active Ingredient:  fentanyl citrate  



   Inactive Ingredients:    mannitol, sodium starch glycolate, sodium bicarbonate, sodium carbonate, citric acid, and magnesium stearate.



   Instructions for Use  



 Before you use FENTORA, it is important that you read the Medication Guide and these Instructions for Use.  Be sure that you read, understand, and follow these Instructions for Use so that you use FENTORA the right way.  Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you have any questions about the right way to use FENTORA.



   When you get an episode of breakthrough cancer pain, use the dose of FENTORA prescribed by your healthcare provider as follows:  



 *  FENTORA comes packaged as a blister card containing 4 blister units. Each blister unit contains 1 FENTORA tablet. Do not open a blister unit until ready to use. 
 *  Separate one of the blister units from the blister card by tearing apart at the perforations. Bend the blister unit along the line where indicated. The product strength of your FENTORA tablets will be printed in the boxed area shown as (See Figure 1). 
   Figure 1  *  Peel back foil on blister unit to expose tablet (See Figure 2). 
   Figure 2  *  Do not push the tablet through the foil on the blister unit because this could damage the tablet. 
 *  When removed from the blister unit, FENTORA tablet must be used right away. 
 *  Use FENTORA tablets whole. 
 *  Do not crush, split, suck, or chew FENTORA tablets, or swallow the tablets whole. You will get less relief for your breakthrough cancer pain. 
 *  You can place a FENTORA tablet:in your mouth above a rear molar tooth between the upper cheek and gum (See Figure 3). Switch (alternate) sides of your mouth for each dose. 
   Figure 3     OR,  
 

 *   on the floor of your mouth, under your tongue (See Figures 4a, 4b, 4c, 4d). 
 *  When placing the tablet under your tongue, first lift your tongue (4b), then place the tablet under your tongue (4c), and lower your tongue over the tablet (4d). 
    
 

   Figure 4a  



 



   Figure 4b  



 



   Figure 4c  



 



   Figure 4d  



 *  Leave the tablet in place until it dissolves. A FENTORA tablet generally takes between 14 to 25 minutes to dissolve. 
 *  After 30 minutes, if there is any FENTORA left in your mouth, you may drink a glass of water to help you swallow the left over medicine. 
 *  If you cannot use FENTORA in this manner, tell your healthcare provider. Your healthcare provider will tell you what to do. 
    This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.
 

 Distributed By:



 Teva Pharmaceuticals USA, Inc.  



 North Wales, PA 19454 



 Revised February 2013



 FENT-008



 FENTMG-007



 FENTORA is a trademark of Cephalon, Inc. or its affiliates.



 (c)2006-2013 Cephalon, Inc., a wholly owned subsidiary of Teva Pharmaceutical Industries Ltd. All rights reserved.



  strength box  Figure 1 blister  Figure 2 peeling  Figure 3 inserting  Figure 4a  Figure 4B  Figure 4c  Figure 4d 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    See Boxed Warning    



    EXCERPT:    *  Clinically significant respiratory and CNS depression can occur. Monitor patients accordingly. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Fentora is not bioequivalent to other fentanyl products. Do not convert from other fentanyl products on a mcg per mcg basis. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Use with other CNS depressants and cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors may increase depressant effects including hypoventilation, hypotension, and profound sedation. Consider dosage adjustments if warranted. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Titrate FENTORA cautiously in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or preexisting medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression and in patients susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention. (  5.6  ,  5.7  ) 
 *  Application site reactions occurred in 10% of patients in clinical trials and ranged from paresthesia to ulceration and bleeding. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Respiratory Depression



  Respiratory depression is the chief hazard of opioid agonists, including fentanyl, the active ingredient in FENTORA. Respiratory depression is more likely to occur in patients with underlying respiratory disorders and elderly or debilitated patients, usually following large initial doses in opioid non-tolerant patients, or when opioids are given in conjunction with other drugs that depress respiration.



 Respiratory depression from opioids is manifested by a reduced urge to breathe and a decreased rate of respiration, often associated with the "sighing" pattern of breathing (deep breaths separated by abnormally long pauses). Carbon dioxide retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids. This makes overdoses involving drugs with sedative properties and opioids especially dangerous.



    5.2 Important Information Regarding Prescribing and Dispensing



   FENTORA is not bioequivalent with other fentanyl products. Do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from other fentanyl products. There are no conversion directions available for patients on any other fentanyl products other than Actiq. (Note: This includes oral, transdermal, or parenteral formulations of fentanyl.) For patients being converted from Actiq, it is necessary to follow the instructions found in Table 1 in  Section 2.1  ,  .as Actiq and FENTORA are not equivalent on a microgram per microgram basis. FENTORA is NOT a generic version of Actiq. All patients should be titrated from the 100 mcg dose.  



 The initial dose of FENTORA should be 100 mcg. Titrate each patient individually to provide adequate analgesia while minimizing side effects.     [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]        



  When dispensing, DO NOT substitute a FENTORA prescription for an Actiq prescription under any circumstances. FENTORA and Actiq are not equivalent.  Substantial differences exist in the pharmacokinetic profile of FENTORA compared to other fentanyl products including Actiq that result in clinically important differences in the rate and extent of absorption of fentanyl. As a result of these differences, the substitution of the same dose of FENTORA for the same dose of Actiq or any other fentanyl product may result in a fatal overdose.  



    5.3 Patient/Caregiver Instructions



   Patients and their caregivers must be instructed that FENTORA contains a medicine in an amount which can be fatal to a child.  Patients and their caregivers must be instructed to keep tablets out of the reach of children. [see How Supplied/Storage and Handling    (  16.1  )    ]  



    5.4 Additive CNS Depressant Effects



  The concomitant use of FENTORA with other CNS depressants, including other opioids, sedatives or hypnotics, general anesthetics, phenothiazines, tranquilizers, skeletal muscle relaxants, sedating antihistamines, and alcoholic beverages may produce increased depressant effects (e.g., hypoventilation, hypotension, and profound sedation). Concomitant use with potent inhibitors of cytochrome P450 3A4 isoform (e.g., erythromycin, ketoconazole, and certain protease inhibitors) may increase fentanyl levels, resulting in increased depressant effects   [see Drug Interactions (7)]    .



 Patients on concomitant CNS depressants must be monitored for a change in opioid effects. Consideration should be given to adjusting the dose of FENTORA if warranted.



    5.5 Effects on Ability to Drive and Use Machines



  Opioid analgesics impair the mental and/or physical ability required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks (e.g., driving a car or operating machinery). Warn patients taking FENTORA of these dangers and counsel them accordingly.



    5.6 Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Because potent opioids can cause respiratory depression, titrate FENTORA with caution in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or pre-existing medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression. In such patients, even normal therapeutic doses of FENTORA may further decrease respiratory drive to the point of respiratory failure.



    5.7 Head Injuries and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Administer FENTORA with extreme caution in patients who may be particularly susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention such as those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or impaired consciousness. Opioids may obscure the clinical course of a patient with a head injury and should be used only if clinically warranted.



    5.8 Application Site Reactions



  In clinical trials, 10% of all patients exposed to FENTORA reported application site reactions. These reactions ranged from paresthesia to ulceration and bleeding. Application site reactions occurring in &gt;=1% of patients were pain (4%), ulcer (3%), and irritation (3%). Application site reactions tended to occur early in treatment, were self-limited and only resulted in treatment discontinuation for 2% of patients.



    5.9 Cardiac Disease



  Intravenous fentanyl may produce bradycardia. Therefore, use FENTORA with caution in patients with bradyarrhythmias.



    5.10 MAO Inhibitors



  FENTORA is not recommended for use in patients who have received MAO inhibitors within 14 days, because severe and unpredictable potentiation by MAO inhibitors has been reported with opioid analgesics.



    5.11 Transmucosal Immediate Release Fentanyl (TIRF) Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) Access Program



  Because of the risk for misuse, abuse, addiction, and overdose   [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)]    , FENTORA is available only through a restricted program called the TIRF REMS Access program.  Under the TIRF REMS Access program, outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe for outpatient use, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program. For inpatient administration (e.g., hospitals, hospices, and long-term care facilities that prescribe for inpatient use) of FENTORA, patient and prescriber enrollment is not required.



 Required components of the TIRF REMS Access program are:



 *  Healthcare professionals, who prescribe FENTORA for outpatient use, must review the prescriber educational materials for the TIRF REMS Access program, enroll in the program, and comply with the REMS requirements. 
 *  To receive FENTORA, outpatients must understand the risks and benefits and sign a Patient-Prescriber Agreement. 
 *  Pharmacies that dispense FENTORA must enroll in the program and agree to comply with the REMS requirements. 
 *  Wholesalers and distributors that distribute FENTORA must enroll in the program, and distribute only to authorized pharmacies. 
     
 

 Further information, including a list of qualified pharmacies/distributors, is available at  www.TIRFREMSAccess.com  or by calling 1-866-822-1483.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
