<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fentanyl1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common (frequency &gt;=5%): nausea, dizziness, somnolence, vomiting, asthenia, and headache, dyspnea, constipation, anxiety, confusion, depression, rash, and insomnia. (  6.1  )



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Cephalon, Inc., at 1-800-896-5855 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  The safety of Oral Transmucosal Fentanyl Citrate (OTFC) has been evaluated in 257 opioid-tolerant chronic cancer pain patients. The duration of OTFC use varied during the open-label study. Some patients were followed for over 21 months. The average duration of therapy in the open-label study was 129 days.



 The adverse reactions seen with OTFC are typical opioid side effects. Frequently, these adverse reactions will cease or decrease in intensity with continued use of OTFC, as the patient is titrated to the proper dose. Expect opioid side effects and manage them accordingly.



 The most serious adverse reactions associated with all opioids including OTFC are respiratory depression (potentially leading to apnea or respiratory arrest), circulatory depression, hypotension, and shock. Follow all patients for symptoms of respiratory depression.



 Because the clinical trials of OTFC were designed to evaluate safety and efficacy in treating breakthrough cancer pain, all patients were also taking concomitant opioids, such as sustained-release morphine or transdermal fentanyl, for their persistent cancer pain. The adverse event data presented here reflect the actual percentage of patients experiencing each adverse effect among patients who received OTFC for breakthrough cancer pain along with a concomitant opioid for persistent cancer pain. There has been no attempt to correct for concomitant use of other opioids, duration of OTFC therapy, or cancer-related symptoms. Adverse reactions are included regardless of causality or severity.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Three short-term clinical trials with similar titration schemes were conducted in 257 patients with malignancy and breakthrough cancer pain. Data are available for 254 of these patients. The goal of titration in these trials was to find the dose of OTFC that provided adequate analgesia with acceptable side effects (successful dose). Patients were titrated from a low dose to a successful dose in a manner similar to current titration dosing guidelines. Table 1 lists, by dose groups, adverse reactions with an overall frequency of 1% or greater that occurred during titration and are commonly associated with opioid administration or are of particular clinical interest. The ability to assign a dose-response relationship to these adverse reactions is limited by the titration schemes used in these studies. Adverse reactions are listed in descending order of frequency within each body system.



   Table 1. Percent of Patients with Specific Adverse Events Commonly Associated with Opioid Administration or of Particular Clinical Interest Which Occurred During Titration (Events in 1% or More of Patients)  



 *Any Dose = A patient who experienced the same adverse event at multiple doses was only counted once.



 The following adverse reactions not reflected in Table 1 occurred during titration with an overall frequency of 1% or greater and are listed in descending order of frequency within each body system.



   Body as a Whole:  Pain, fever, abdominal pain, chills, back pain, chest pain, infection



   Cardiovascular:  Migraine



   Digestive:  Diarrhea, dyspepsia, flatulence



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Peripheral edema, dehydration



   Nervous:  Hypesthesia



   Respiratory:  Pharyngitis, cough increased



 The following reactions occurred during titration with an overall frequency of less than 1% and are listed in descending order of frequency within each body system.



 *      Body as a Whole: Flu syndrome, abscess, bone pain 
 *      Cardiovascular: Deep thrombophlebitis, hypertension, hypotension 
      Digestive:  Anorexia, eructation, esophageal stenosis, fecal impaction, gum hemorrhage, mouth ulceration, oral moniliasis
 

 *      Hemic and Lymphatic: Anemia, leukopenia 
 *      Metabolic and Nutritional: Edema, hypercalcemia, weight loss 
 *      Musculoskeletal: Myalgia, pathological fracture, myasthenia 
      Nervous:  Abnormal dreams, urinary retention, agitation, amnesia, emotional lability, euphoria, incoordination, libido decreased, neuropathy, paresthesia, speech disorder
 

   Respiratory:  Hemoptysis, pleural effusion, rhinitis, asthma, hiccup, pneumonia, respiratory insufficiency, sputum increased



 *      Skin and Appendages: Alopecia, exfoliative dermatitis 
      Special Senses:  Taste perversion
 

   Urogenital:  Vaginal hemorrhage, dysuria, hematuria, urinary incontinence, urinary tract infection



 A long-term extension study was conducted in 156 patients with malignancy and breakthrough cancer pain who were treated for an average of 129 days. Data are available for 152 of these patients. Table 2 lists by dose groups, adverse reactions with an overall frequency of 1% or greater that occurred during the long-term extension study and are commonly associated with opioid administration or are of particular clinical interest. Adverse reactions are listed in descending order of frequency within each body system.



   Table 2. Percent of Patients with Adverse Events Commonly Associated with Opioid Administration or of Particular Clinical Interest Which Occurred During Long Term Treatment (Events in 1% or More of Patients)  



 *Any dose = A patient who experienced the same adverse event at multiple doses was only counted once.



 *     The following reactions not reflected in Table 2 occurred with an overall frequency of 1% or greater in the long-term extension study and are listed in descending order of frequency within each body system. 
      Body as a Whole:  Pain, fever, back pain, abdominal pain, chest pain, flu syndrome, chills, infection, abdomen enlarged, bone pain, ascites, sepsis, neck pain, viral infection, fungal infection, cachexia, cellulitis, malaise, pelvic pain
 

   Cardiovascular:  Deep thrombophlebitis, migraine, palpitation, vascular disorder



   Digestive:  Diarrhea, anorexia, dyspepsia, dysphagia, oral moniliasis, mouth ulceration, rectal disorder, stomatitis, flatulence, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gingivitis, jaundice, periodontal abscess, eructation, glossitis, rectal hemorrhage



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  Anemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, ecchymosis, lymphadenopathy, lymphedema, pancytopenia



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Peripheral edema, edema, dehydration, weight loss, hyperglycemia, hypokalemia, hypercalcemia, hypomagnesemia



   Musculoskeletal:  Myalgia, pathological fracture, joint disorder, leg cramps, arthralgia, bone disorder



 *      Nervous: Hypesthesia, paresthesia, hypokinesia, neuropathy, speech disorder 
      Respiratory:  Cough increased, pharyngitis, pneumonia, rhinitis, sinusitis, bronchitis, epistaxis, asthma, hemoptysis, sputum increased
 

 *      Skin and Appendages: Skin ulcer, alopecia 
      Special Senses:  Tinnitus, conjunctivitis, ear disorder, taste perversion
 

   Urogenital:  Urinary tract infection, urinary incontinence, breast pain, dysuria, hematuria, scrotal edema, hydronephrosis, kidney failure, urinary urgency, urination impaired, breast neoplasm, vaginal hemorrhage, vaginitis



 *     The following reactions occurred with a frequency of less than 1% in the long-term extension study and are listed in descending order of frequency within each body system. 
      Body as a Whole:  Allergic reaction, cyst, face edema, flank pain, granuloma, bacterial infection, injection site pain, mucous membrane disorder, neck rigidity
 

   Cardiovascular:  Angina pectoris, hemorrhage, hypotension, peripheral vascular disorder, postural hypotension, tachycardia



   Digestive:  Cheilitis, esophagitis, fecal incontinence, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal disorder, gum hemorrhage, hemorrhage of colon, hepatorenal syndrome, liver tenderness, tooth caries, tooth disorder



 *      Hemic and Lymphatic: Bleeding time increased 
      Metabolic and Nutritional:  Acidosis, generalized edema, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, hypoproteinemia, thirst
 

   Musculoskeletal:  Arthritis, muscle atrophy, myopathy, synovitis, tendon disorder



   Nervous:  Acute brain syndrome, agitation, cerebral ischemia, facial paralysis, foot drop, hallucinations, hemiplegia, miosis, subdural hematoma



   Respiratory:  Hiccup, hyperventilation, lung disorder, pneumothorax, respiratory failure, voice alteration



   Skin and Appendages:  Herpes zoster, maculopapular rash, skin discoloration, urticaria, vesiculobullous rash



   Special Senses:  Ear pain, eye hemorrhage, lacrimation disorder, partial permanent deafness, partial transitory deafness



 *      Urogenital: Kidney pain, nocturia, oliguria, polyuria, pyelonephritis 
     Table-01.jpg  Table-02.jpg   6.2 Postmarketing Experience
     *     Adverse reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, and, therefore, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of the reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to OTFC .  
 *     The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of OTFC (which contains approximately 2 grams of sugar per unit): 
 *      Digestive: Dental decay of varying severity including dental caries, tooth loss, and gum line erosion. 
 *      General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions: Application site reactions including irritation, pain, and ulcer. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

      RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION     



   Fatal respiratory depression has occurred in patients treated with Oral Transmucosal Fentanyl Citrate (OTFC), including following use in opioid non-tolerant patients and improper dosing.    The substitution of OTFC for any other fentanyl product may result in fatal overdose.    



   Due to the risk of respiratory depression, OTFC is contraindicated in the management of acute or postoperative pain including headache/migraine and in opioid non-tolerant patients.   [see Contraindications (  4  )]    



   Death has been reported in children who have accidentally ingested OTFC. OTFC must be kept out of reach of children.   [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.3  ) and How Supplied/Storage and Handling (  16.1  )      ]      



 The concomitant use of OTFC with CYP3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentrations, and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression   [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  . 



     MEDICATION ERRORS    



   Substantial differences exist in the pharmacokinetic profile of OTFC compared to other fentanyl products that result in clinically important differences in the extent of absorption of fentanyl that could result in fatal overdose.  



     



 *   - When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other fentanyl products to OTFC. [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)] 
 *   - When dispensing, do not substitute an OTFC prescription for other fentanyl products. 
        ABUSE POTENTIAL     
 

   OTFC contains fentanyl, an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance, with an abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics.    



   OTFC can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit.  This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing OTFC in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse or diversion.  



     



 Because of the risk for misuse, abuse, addiction, and overdose, OTFC is available only through a restricted program required by the Food and Drug Administration, called a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS). Under the Transmucosal Immediate Release Fentanyl (TIRF) REMS Access program, outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program.   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]   Further information is available at www.TIRFREMSAccess.com or by calling 1-866-822-1483.



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL 



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Due to the risk of fatal respiratory depression, OTFC is contraindicated in opioid non-tolerant patients (1) and in management of acute or postoperative pain, including headache/migraines. (4) 
 *  Keep out of reach of children. (5.3) 
 *  Use with CYP3A4 inhibitors may cause fatal respiratory depression. (7) 
 *  When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other oral transmucosal fentanyl product to OTFC. (2.1, 5.1) 
 *  When dispensing, do not substitute with any other fentanyl products. (5.1) 
 *  Contains fentanyl, a Schedule II controlled substance with abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics. (9.1) 
 *  OTFC is available only through a restricted program called the TIRF REMS Access program. Outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors are required to enroll in the program. (5.10) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    See  Boxed Warning  - WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL    



    EXCERPT:    *    Clinically significant respiratory and CNS depression can occur. Monitor patients accordingly. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Full and partially consumed OTFC units contain medicine that can be fatal to a child. Ensure proper storage and disposal. Interim safe storage container available ("OTFC Child Safety Kit"). (  5.3  ) 
 *    Use with other CNS depressants and potent cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors may increase depressant effects including respiratory depression, hypotension, and profound sedation. Consider dosage adjustments if warranted. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Titrate OTFC cautiously in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or preexisting medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression and in patients susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention. (  5.6  .  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Respiratory Depression



  Respiratory depression is the chief hazard of opioid agonists, including fentanyl, the active ingredient in Oral Transmucosal Fentanyl Citrate (OTFC). Respiratory depression is more likely to occur in patients with underlying respiratory disorders and elderly or debilitated patients, usually following large initial doses in opioid non-tolerant patients, or when opioids are given in conjunction with other drugs that depress respiration.



 Respiratory depression from opioids is manifested by a reduced urge to breathe and a decreased rate of respiration, often associated with the "sighing" pattern of breathing (deep breaths separated by abnormally long pauses). Carbon dioxide retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids. This makes overdoses involving drugs with sedative properties and opioids especially dangerous.



    5.2 Important Information Regarding Prescribing and Dispensing



   When prescribing, DO NOT convert a patient to OTFC from any other fentanyl product on a mcg per mcg basis  as OTFC and other fentanyl products are not equivalent on a microgram per microgram basis.



 OTFC is NOT a generic version of Fentora  (r)  . When dispensing, DO NOT substitute an OTFC prescription for a Fentora prescription under any circumstances. Fentora and OTFC are not equivalent.  Substantial differences exist in the pharmacokinetic profile of OTFC compared to other fentanyl products including Fentora that result in clinically important differences in the rate and extent of absorption of fentanyl. As a result of these differences, the substitution of OTFC for any other fentanyl product may result in a fatal overdose.  



  There are no safe conversion directions available for patients on any other fentanyl products. (Note: This includes oral, transdermal, or parenteral formulations of fentanyl.)  Therefore, for opioid tolerant patients, the initial dose of OTFC should always  be 200 mcg. Each patient should be individually titrated to provide adequate analgesia while minimizing side effects [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )].  



    5.3 Patient/Caregiver Instructions



   Patients and their caregivers must be instructed that OTFC contains a medicine in an amount which can be fatal to a child. Death has been reported in children who have accidentally ingested OTFC.  Patients and their caregivers must be instructed to keep both used and unused dosage units out of the reach of children. While all units should be disposed of immediately after use, partially consumed units represent a special risk to children. In the event that a unit is not completely consumed it must be properly disposed as soon as possible [see How Supplied/Storage and Handling (  16.1  ,  16.2  ), Patient Counseling Information (  17.3  ) and  Medication Guide  ].  



 Physicians and dispensing pharmacists must specifically question patients or caregivers about the presence of children in the home (on a full time or visiting basis) and counsel them regarding the dangers to children from inadvertent exposure.



 OTFC could be fatal to individuals for whom it is not prescribed and for those who are not opioid-tolerant.



    5.4 Additive CNS Depressant Effects



  The concomitant use of OTFC with other CNS depressants, including other opioids, sedatives or hypnotics, general anesthetics, phenothiazines, tranquilizers, skeletal muscle relaxants, sedating antihistamines, and alcoholic beverages may produce increased depressant effects (e.g., respiratory depression, hypotension, and profound sedation). Concomitant use with potent inhibitors of cytochrome P450 3A4 isoform (e.g., erythromycin, ketoconazole, and certain protease inhibitors) may increase fentanyl levels, resulting in increased depressant effects [see Drug Interactions (  7  )].  



 Patients on concomitant CNS depressants must be monitored for a change in opioid effects. Consideration should be given to adjusting the dose of OTFC if warranted.



    5.5 Effects on Ability to Drive and Use Machines



  Opioid analgesics impair the mental and/or physical ability required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks (e.g., driving a car or operating machinery). Warn patients taking OTFC of these dangers and counsel them accordingly.



    5.6 Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Because potent opioids can cause respiratory depression, titrate OTFC with caution in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or preexisting medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression. In such patients, even normal therapeutic doses of OTFC may further decrease respiratory drive to the point of respiratory failure.



    5.7 Head Injuries and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Administer OTFC with extreme caution in patients who may be particularly susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2 retention such as those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or impaired consciousness. Opioids may obscure the clinical course of a patient with a head injury and should be used only if clinically warranted.



    5.8 Cardiac Disease



  Intravenous fentanyl may produce bradycardia. Therefore, use OTFC with caution in patients with bradyarrhythmias.



    5.9 MAO Inhibitors



  OTFC is not recommended for use in patients who have received MAO inhibitors within 14 days, because severe and unpredictable potentiation by MAO inhibitors has been reported with opioid analgesics.



    5.10 Transmucosal Immediate Release Fentanyl (TIRF) Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) Access Program



   Because of the risk for misuse, abuse, addiction, and overdose [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (       9   )]     , OTFC is available only through a restricted program called the TIRF REMS Access program. Under the TIRF REMS Access program, outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe for outpatient use, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program. For inpatient administration (e.g., hospitals, hospices, and long-term care facilities that prescribe for inpatient use) of OTFC, patient and prescriber enrollment is not required.  



  Required components of the TIRF REMS Access program are:  



 *     Healthcare professionals, who prescribe OTFC for outpatient use, must review the prescriber educational materials for the TIRF REMS Access program, enroll in the program, and comply with the REMS requirements.  
 *     To receive OTFC, outpatients must understand the risks and benefits and sign a Patient-Prescriber Agreement.  
 *     Pharmacies that dispense OTFC must enroll in the program, and agree to comply with the REMS requirements.  
 *     Wholesalers and distributors that distribute OTFC must enroll in the program, and distribute only to authorized pharmacies.  
     Further information, including a list of qualified pharmacies/distributors, is available at www.TIRFREMSAccess.com or by calling 1-866-822-1483.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
