<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fentanyl0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    In post-marketing experience, deaths from hypoventilation due to use of fentanyl transdermal system have been reported (see  BOX WARNING  and  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ).  



   Pre-Marketing Clinical Trial Experience

  Although fentanyl transdermal system use in post-operative or acute pain and in patients who are not opioid-tolerant is CONTRAINDICATED, the safety of fentanyl transdermal system was originally evaluated in 357 post-operative adult patients for 1 to 3 days and 153 cancer patients for a total of 510 patients. The duration of fentanyl transdermal system use varied in cancer patients; 56% of patients used fentanyl transdermal system for over 30 days, 28% continued treatment for more than 4 months, and 10% used fentanyl transdermal system for more than 1 year.



 Hypoventilation was the most serious adverse reaction observed in 13 (4%) post-operative patients and in 3 (2%) of the cancer patients. Hypotension and hypertension were observed in 11 (3%) and 4 (1%) of the opioid-naive patients.



 Various adverse events were reported; a causal relationship to fentanyl transdermal system was not always determined. The frequencies presented here reflect the actual frequency of each adverse effect in patients who received fentanyl transdermal system. There has been no attempt to correct for a placebo effect, concomitant use of other opioids, or to subtract the frequencies reported by placebo-treated patients in controlled trials.



 Adverse reactions reported in 153 cancer patients at a frequency of 1% or greater are presented in Table 1; similar reactions were seen in the 357 post-operative patients.



 In the pediatric population, the safety of fentanyl transdermal system has been evaluated in 291 patients with chronic pain 2-18 years of age. The duration of fentanyl transdermal system use varied; 20% of pediatric patients were treated for &lt;= 15 days; 46% for 16-30 days; 16% for 31-60 days; and 17% for at least 61 days. Twenty-five patients were treated with fentanyl transdermal system for at least 4 months and 9 patients for more than 9 months.



 There was no apparent pediatric-specific risk associated with fentanyl transdermal system use in children as young as 2 years old when used as directed. The most common adverse events were fever (35%), vomiting (33%), and nausea (24%).



 Adverse events reported in pediatric patients at a rate of &gt;=1% are presented in Table 1.



 TABLE 1: ADVERSE EVENTS (at rate of &gt;= 1%) Adult (N=380) and Pediatric (N=291) Clinical Trial Experience 
 Body System                Adults                                    Pediatrics                            
  
 Body as a Whole            Abdominal pain, headache, fatigue, back pain, fever, influenza-like symptoms, accidental injury, rigors  Pain, headache, fever, syncope, abdominal pain, allergic reaction, flushing   
 Cardiovascular             Arrhythmia, chest pain                    Hypertension, tachycardia             
 Digestive                  Nausea, vomiting, constipation, dry mouth, anorexia, diarrhea, dyspepsia, flatulence  Nausea, vomiting, constipation, dry mouth, diarrhea   
 Nervous                    Somnolence, insomnia, confusion, asthenia, dizziness, nervousness, hallucinations, anxiety, depression, euphoria, tremor, abnormal coordination, speech disorder, abnormal thinking, abnormal gait, abnormal dreams, agitation, paresthesia, amnesia, syncope, paranoid reaction  Somnolence, nervousness, insomnia, asthenia, hallucinations, anxiety, depression, convulsions, dizziness, tremor, speech disorder, agitation, stupor, confusion, paranoid reaction   
 Respiratory                Dyspnea, hypoventilation, apnea, hemoptysis, pharyngitis, hiccups, bronchitis, rhinitis, sinusitis, upper respiratory tract infection  Dyspnea, respiratory depression, rhinitis, coughing   
 Skin and Appendages        Sweating, pruritus, rash, application site reaction - erythema, papules, itching, edema  Pruritus, application site reaction, sweating increased, rash, rash erythematous, skin reaction localized   
 Urogenital                 Urinary retention, Micturition disorder   Urinary retention                     
         The following adverse effects have been reported in less than 1% of the 510 adult post-operative and cancer patients studied:
 

   Cardiovascular:  bradycardia



   Digestive:  abdominal distention



   Nervous:  aphasia, hypertonia, vertigo, stupor, hypotonia, depersonalization, hostility



   Respiratory:  stertorous breathing, asthma, respiratory disorder



   Skin and Appendages, General:  exfoliative dermatitis, pustules



   Special Senses  : amblyopia



   Urogenital:  bladder pain, oliguria, urinary frequency



   Post-Marketing Experience - Adults

  The following adverse reactions have been reported in association with the use of fentanyl transdermal system and not reported in the pre-marketing adverse reactions section above:



   Body as a Whole:  edema



   Cardiovascular:  tachycardia



   Metabolic and Nutritional  : weight loss



   Special Senses:  blurred vision



   Urogenital:  decreased libido, anorgasmia, ejaculatory difficulty
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    Fentanyl Transdermal System contains a high concentration of a potent Schedule II opioid agonist, fentanyl. Schedule II opioid substances which include fentanyl, hydromorphone, methadone, morphine, oxycodone, and oxymorphone have the highest potential for abuse and associated risk of fatal overdose due to respiratory depression. Fentanyl can be abused and is subject to criminal diversion. The high content of fentanyl in the patches (fentanyl transdermal system) may be a particular target for abuse and diversion.  



   Fentanyl transdermal system is indicated for management of   persistent  , moderate to severe chronic pain that:  



 *  requires continuous, around-the-clock opioid administration for an extended period of time, and 
 *  cannot be managed by other means such as non-steroidal analgesics, opioid combination products, or immediate-release opioids 
      Fentanyl transdermal system should ONLY be used in patients who are already receiving opioid therapy, who have demonstrated opioid tolerance, and who require a total daily dose at least equivalent to fentanyl transdermal system 25 mcg/h. Patients who are considered opioid-tolerant are those who have been taking, for a week or longer, at least 60 mg of morphine daily, or at least 30 mg of oral oxycodone daily, or at least 8 mg of oral hydromorphone daily or an equianalgesic dose of another opioid.  
 

   Because serious or life-threatening hypoventilation could occur, fentanyl transdermal system is contraindicated:  



 *  in patients who are not opioid-tolerant 
 *  in the management of acute pain or in patients who require opioid analgesia for a short period of time 
 *  in the management of post-operative pain, including use after out-patient or day surgeries (e.g., tonsillectomies) 
 *  in the management of mild pain 
 *  in the management of intermittent pain (e.g., use on an as needed basis [prn]) 
      (See   CONTRAINDICATIONS   for further information.)  
 

   Since the peak fentanyl concentrations generally occur between 20 and 72 hours of treatment, prescribers should be aware that serious or life threatening hypoventilation may occur, even in opioid-tolerant patients, during the initial application period.  



   The concomitant use of fentanyl transdermal system   with all cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors   (such as ritonavir, ketoconazole, itraconazole, troleandomycin, clarithromycin, nelfinavir, nefazodone, amiodarone, amprenavir, aprepitant, diltiazem, erythromycin, fluconazole, fosamprenavir, grapefruit juice, and verapamil) may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentrations, which could increase or prolong adverse drug effects and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression. Patients receiving   fentanyl transdermal system and any CYP3A4 inhibitor should be carefully monitored for an extended period of time and dosage adjustments should be made if warranted (see   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY - Drug Interactions  ,   WARNINGS  ,   PRECAUTIONS  , and   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION   for further information).    



   The safety of  fentanyl transdermal system has not been established in children under 2 years of age. Fentanyl transdermal system should be administered to children only if they are opioid-tolerant and 2 years of age or older (see   PRECAUTIONS - Pediatric Use  ).  



     Fentanyl transdermal system is ONLY for use in patients who are already tolerant to opioid therapy of comparable potency. Use in non-opioid tolerant patients may lead to fatal respiratory depression.   Overestimating the fentanyl transdermal system dose when converting patients from another opioid medication can result in fatal overdose with the first dose (see   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION - Initial Fentanyl Transdermal System Dose Selection  ). Due to the mean half-life of approximately 20-27 hours, patients who are thought to have had a serious adverse event, including overdose, will require monitoring and treatment for at least 24 hours.  



   Fentanyl transdermal system can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. This risk should be considered when administering, prescribing, or dispensing fentanyl transdermal system in situations where the healthcare professional is concerned about increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion.  



   Persons at increased risk for opioid abuse include those with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). Patients should be assessed for their clinical risks for opioid abuse or addiction prior to being prescribed opioids. All patients receiving opioids should be routinely monitored for signs of misuse, abuse, and addiction. Patients at increased risk of opioid abuse may still be appropriately treated with modified-release opioid formulations; however, these patients will require intensive monitoring for signs of misuse, abuse, or addiction.  



   Fentanyl transdermal system patches are intended for transdermal use (on intact skin) only. Do not use a fentanyl transdermal system patch if the pouch seal is broken or the patch is cut, damaged, or changed in any way.  



   Avoid exposing the fentanyl transdermal system application site and surrounding area to direct external heat sources, such as heating pads or electric blankets, heat or tanning lamps, saunas, hot tubs, and heated water beds, while wearing the system. Avoid taking hot baths or sunbathing.  There is a potential for temperature-dependent increases in fentanyl released from the system resulting in possible overdose and death. Patients wearing fentanyl transdermal systems who develop fever or increased core body temperature due to strenuous exertion should be monitored for opioid side effects and the fentanyl transdermal system dose should be adjusted if necessary.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
