<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ferrlecit" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Hypersensitivity [see   Contraindications (4)   and   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Hypotension [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) in adult patients were nausea, vomiting and/or diarrhea, injection site reaction, hypotension, cramps, hypertension, dizziness, dyspnea, chest pain, leg cramps and pain. In patients 6 to 15 years of age the most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) were hypotension, headache, hypertension, tachycardia and vomiting. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi-aventis U.S. LLC at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) in adult patients were nausea, vomiting and/or diarrhea, injection site reaction, hypotension, cramps, hypertension, dizziness, abnormal erythrocytes (e.g., changes in morphology, color, or number of red blood cells), dyspnea, chest pain, leg cramps and pain. In patients 6 to 15 years of age the most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) were hypotension, headache, hypertension, tachycardia and vomiting.



     Studies A and B  



 In multiple dose Studies A and B (total 126 adult patients), the most frequent treatment emergent adverse reactions following Ferrlecit were:



   Body as a Whole:  injection site reaction (33%), chest pain (10%), pain (10%), asthenia (7%), headache (7%), fatigue (6%), fever (5%), malaise, infection, abscess, chills, rigors, carcinoma, flu-like syndrome, sepsis, lightheadedness, weakness.



   Nervous System:  cramps (25%), dizziness (13%), paresthesias (6%), agitation, somnolence, decreased level of consciousness.



   Respiratory System:  dyspnea (11%), coughing (6%), upper respiratory infections (6%), rhinitis, pneumonia.



   Cardiovascular System:  hypotension (29%), hypertension (13%), syncope (6%), tachycardia (5%), bradycardia, vasodilatation, angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, pulmonary edema.



   Gastrointestinal System:  nausea, vomiting and/or diarrhea (35%), anorexia, abdominal pain (6%), rectal disorder, dyspepsia, eructation, flatulence, gastrointestinal disorder, melena.



   Musculoskeletal System:  leg cramps (10%), myalgia, arthralgia, back pain, arm pain.



   Skin and Appendages:  pruritus (6%), rash, increased sweating.



   Genitourinary System:  urinary tract infection, and menorrahagia.



   Special Senses:  conjunctivitis, rolling of the eyes, watery eyes, puffy eye lids, arcus senilis, redness of the eye, diplopia, and deafness.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  hyperkalemia (6%), generalized edema (5%), leg edema, peripheral edema, hypoglycemia, edema, hypervolemia, hypokalemia.



   Hematologic System:  abnormal erythrocytes (11%) (changes in morphology, color, or number of red blood cells), anemia, leukocytosis, lymphadenopathy.



     Study C - Pediatric  



   Pediatric Patients:  In a clinical trial of 66 iron-deficient pediatric hemodialysis patients, 6 to 15 years of age, inclusive, who were receiving a stable erythropoietin dosing regimen, the most common adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;=5%, regardless of treatment dosage, were: hypotension (35%), headache (24%), hypertension (23%), tachycardia (17%), vomiting (11%), fever (9%), nausea (9%), abdominal pain (9%), pharyngitis (9%), diarrhea (8%), infection (8%), rhinitis (6%), and thrombosis (6%). More patients in the higher dose group (3.0 mg/kg) than in the lower dose group (1.5 mg/kg) experienced the following adverse events: hypotension (41% vs. 28%), tachycardia (21% vs. 13%), fever (15% vs. 3%), headache (29% vs. 19%), abdominal pain (15% vs. 3%), nausea (12% vs. 6%), vomiting (12% vs. 9%), pharyngitis (12% vs. 6%), and rhinitis (9% vs. 3%).



   6.2 Post Marketing Experience

  In the single-dose, postmarketing safety study, 11% of patients who received Ferrlecit and 9.4% of patients who received placebo reported adverse reactions. The most frequent adverse reactions following Ferrlecit were: hypotension (2%), nausea, vomiting and/or diarrhea (2%), pain (0.7%), hypertension (0.6%), allergic reaction (0.5%), chest pain (0.5%), pruritus (0.5%), and back pain (0.4%). The following additional events were reported in two or more patients: hypertonia, nervousness, dry mouth, and hemorrhage.



 In the multiple-dose, open-label surveillance study, 28% of the patients received concomitant angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor (ACEi) therapy. The incidences of both drug intolerance or suspected allergic events following first dose Ferrlecit administration were 1.6% in patients with concomitant ACEi use compared to 0.7% in patients without concomitant ACEi use. The patient with a life-threatening event was not on ACEi therapy. One patient had facial flushing immediately on Ferrlecit exposure. No hypotension occurred and the event resolved rapidly and spontaneously without intervention other than drug withdrawal.



 The following additional adverse reactions have been identified with the use of Ferrlecit from postmarketing spontaneous reports: anaphylactic-type reactions, shock, loss of consciousness, convulsion, skin discoloration, pallor, phlebitis, dysgeusia, and hypoesthesia.



 Individual doses exceeding 125 mg may be associated with a higher incidence and/or severity of adverse events based on information from postmarketing spontaneous reports. These adverse events included hypotension, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, dizziness, dyspnea, urticaria, chest pain, paresthesia, and peripheral swelling.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity Reactions: Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity during and after Ferrlecit administration for at least 30 minutes and until clinically stable following completion of the infusion. Only administer Ferrlecit when personnel and therapies are immediately available for the treatment of anaphylaxis and other hypersensitivity reactions. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypotension: Ferrlecit may cause hypotension. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hypotension during and following each Ferrlecit dose. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Iron Overload: Regularly monitor hematologic responses during Ferrlecit therapy. Do not administer Ferrlecit to patients with iron overload. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Benzyl Alcohol Toxicity: Premature and low-birthweight infants may be more likely to develop toxicity. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



   Serious hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic-type reactions, some of which have been life-threatening and fatal, have been reported in patients receiving Ferrlecit in post marketing experience. Patients may present with shock, clinically significant hypotension, loss of consciousness, or collapse. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity during and after Ferrlecit administration for at least 30 minutes and until clinically stable following completion of the infusion. Only administer Ferrlecit when personnel and therapies are immediately available for the treatment of anaphylaxis and other hypersensitivity reactions [see   Adverse Reactions (6)    ].  



 In the single-dose, post-marketing, safety study one patient experienced a life-threatening hypersensitivity reaction (diaphoresis, nausea, vomiting, severe lower back pain, dyspnea, and wheezing for 20 minutes) following Ferrlecit administration. Among 1,097 patients who received Ferrlecit in this study, there were 9 patients (0.8%) who had an adverse reaction that, in the view of the investigator, precluded further Ferrlecit administration. These included one life-threatening reaction, six allergic reactions (pruritus x2, facial flushing, chills, dyspnea/chest pain, and rash), and two other reactions (hypotension and nausea). Another 2 patients experienced (0.2%) allergic reactions not deemed to represent drug intolerance (nausea/malaise and nausea/dizziness) following Ferrlecit administration.



    5.2 Hypotension



  Ferrlecit may cause clinically significant hypotension. Hypotension associated with lightheadedness, malaise, fatigue, weakness or severe pain in the chest, back, flanks, or groin has been reported. These hypotensive reactions may or may not be associated with signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity reactions and usually resolve within one to two hours. In the single dose safety study, post-administration hypotensive events were observed in 22/1,097 patients (2%) following Ferrlecit administration. Transient hypotension may occur during dialysis. Administration of Ferrlecit may augment hypotension caused by dialysis. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hypotension during and following Ferrlecit administration [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.3 Iron Overload



  Excessive therapy with parenteral iron can lead to excess storage of iron with the possibility of iatrogenic hemosiderosis. Patients receiving Ferrlecit require periodic monitoring of hematologic and iron parameters (hemoglobin, hematocrit, serum ferritin, and transferrin saturation).



    5.4 Benzyl Alcohol Toxicity



  Ferrlecit contains benzyl alcohol as a preservative. Benzyl alcohol has been associated with serious adverse events and death in pediatric patients. The minimum amount of benzyl alcohol at which toxicity may occur is not known. Premature and low-birth weight infants may be more likely to develop toxicity [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
