<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="firmagon" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 1325 patients with prostate cancer received FIRMAGON either as a monthly treatment (60-160 mg) or as a single dose (up to 320 mg). A total of 1032 patients (78%) were treated for at least 6 months and 853 patients (64%) were treated for one year or more. The most commonly observed adverse reactions during FIRMAGON therapy included injection site reactions (e.g., pain, erythema, swelling or induration), hot flashes, increased weight, fatigue, and increases in serum levels of transaminases and gamma-glutamyltransferase (GGT). The majority of the adverse reactions were Grade 1 or 2, with Grade 3/4 adverse reaction incidences of 1% or less.



 FIRMAGON was studied in an active-controlled trial (N = 610) in which patients with prostate cancer were randomized to receive FIRMAGON (subcutaneous) or leuprolide (intramuscular) monthly for 12 months. Adverse reactions reported in 5% of patients or more are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients in an Active Controlled Study 
                                 FIRMAGON 240/160 mg (subcutaneous)N = 202  FIRMAGON 240/80 mg (subcutaneous)N = 207  Leuprolide 7.5 mg (intramuscular)N = 201   
  
 Percentage of subjects with adverse events            83%                       79%                      78%             
   Body as a whole                                                                                            
 Injection site adverse events             44%                       35%                      &lt;1%             
 Weight increase                           11%                       9%                       12%             
 Fatigue                                   6%                        3%                        6%             
 Chills                                    4%                        5%                        0%             
   Cardiovascular system                                                                                      
 Hot flash                                 26%                       26%                      21%             
 Hypertension                              7%                        6%                        4%             
   Musculoskeletal system                                                                                     
 Back pain                                 6%                        6%                        8%             
 Arthralgia                                4%                        5%                        9%             
   Urogenital system                                                                                          
 Urinary tract infection                   2%                        5%                        9%             
   Digestive system                                                                                           
 Increases in Transaminases and GGT            10%                       10%                       5%             
 Constipation                              3%                        5%                        5%             
          The most frequently reported adverse reactions at the injection sites were pain (28%), erythema (17%), swelling (6%), induration (4%) and nodule (3%). These adverse reactions were mostly transient, of mild to moderate intensity, occurred primarily with the starting dose and led to few discontinuations (&lt;1%). Grade 3 injection site reactions occurred in 2% or less of patients receiving degarelix.
 

 Hepatic laboratory abnormalities were primarily Grade 1 or 2 and were generally reversible. Grade 3 hepatic laboratory abnormalities occurred in less than 1% of patients.



 In 1-5% of patients the following adverse reactions, not already listed, were considered related to FIRMAGON by the investigator:



   Body as a whole:  Asthenia, fever, night sweats;  Digestive system:  Nausea;  Nervous system:  Dizziness, headache, insomnia.



 The following adverse reactions, not already listed, were reported to be drug-related by the investigator in &gt;=1% of patients: erectile dysfunction, gynecomastia, hyperhidrosis, testicular atrophy, and diarrhea.



   The safety of FIRMAGON administered monthly was evaluated further in an extension study in 385 patients who completed the above active-controlled trial. Of the 385 patients, 251 patients continued treatment with FIRMAGON and 135 patients crossed over treatment from leuprolide to FIRMAGON. The median treatment duration on the extension study was approximately 43 months (range 1 to 58 months). The most common adverse reactions reported in &gt;=10% of the patients were injection site reactions (e.g., pain, erythema, swelling, induration or inflammation), pyrexia, hot flush, weight loss or gain, fatigue, increases in serum levels of hepatic transaminases and GGT. One percent of patients had injection site infections including abscess. Hepatic laboratory abnormalities in the extension study included the following: Grade 1/2 elevations in hepatic transaminases occurred in 47% of patients and Grade 3 elevations occurred in 1% of patients.  



 Changes in bone density:



 Decreased bone density has been reported in the medical literature in men who have had orchiectomy or who have been treated with a GnRH agonist. It can be anticipated that long periods of medical castration in men will result in decreased bone density.



 Anti-degarelix antibody development has been observed in 10% of patients after treatment with FIRMAGON for 1 year. There is no indication that the efficacy or safety of FIRMAGON treatment is affected by antibody formation.



   EXCERPT:   The most commonly observed adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) during FIRMAGON therapy included injection site reactions (e.g., pain, erythema, swelling or induration), hot flashes, increased weight, and increases in serum levels of transaminases and gamma-glutamyltransferase (GGT). (  6  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ferring at 1-888-FERRING (1-888-337-7464) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity: Anaphylaxis, urticaria and angioedema have been reported. Discontinue Firmagon if a serious hypersensitivity reaction occurs, and manage as clinically indicated. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Effect on QT/QTc Interval: Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval. Consider risks and benefits. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Use in Pregnancy



   Pregnancy Category X  



 Women who are or may become pregnant should not take FIRMAGON. [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, urticaria and angioedema, have been reported post-marketing with Firmagon. In case of a serious hypersensitivity reaction, discontinue Firmagon immediately if the injection has not been completed, and manage as clinically indicated. Patients with a known history of serious hypersensitivity reactions to Firmagon should not be re-challenged with Firmagon.



    5.3 Effect on QT/QTc Interval



   Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval. Providers should consider whether the benefits of androgen deprivation therapy outweigh the potential risks in patients with congenital long QT syndrome, electrolyte abnormalities, or congestive heart failure and in patients taking Class IA (e.g. quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic medications.  



 In the randomized, active-controlled trial comparing FIRMAGON to leuprolide, periodic electrocardiograms were performed. Seven patients, three (&lt;1%) in the pooled degarelix group and four (2%) patients in the leuprolide 7.5 mg group, had a QTcF &gt;= 500 msec. From baseline to end of study the median change for FIRMAGON was 12.3 msec and for leuprolide was 16.7 msec.



    5.4 Laboratory Testing



  Therapy with FIRMAGON results in suppression of the pituitary gonadal system. Results of diagnostic tests of the pituitary gonadotropic and gonadal functions conducted during and after FIRMAGON may be affected. The therapeutic effect of FIRMAGON should be monitored by measuring serum concentrations of prostate-specific antigen (PSA) periodically. If PSA increases, serum concentrations of testosterone should be measured.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
