<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="flebogamma" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions (reported in at least 5% of clinical trial adult subjects) were headache, pyrexia/fever, pain, infusion site reactions, diarrhea, rigors or chills, urticaria, and infusion site inflammation.



 The most common adverse reactions (reported in at least 5% of clinical trial pediatric subjects) were headache, pyrexia, hypotension, tachycardia, diastolic hypotension, nausea, abdominal pain, diarrhea, pain, and vomiting.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Grifols Biologicals at 1-888-GRIFOLS (1-888-474-3657) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (reported in at least 5% of clinical trial adult subjects) were headache, pyrexia/fever, pain, infusion site reactions, diarrhea, rigors or chills, urticaria, and infusion site inflammation. (  6  )



 The most common adverse reactions (reported in at least 5% of clinical trial pediatric subjects) were headache, pyrexia, hypotension, tachycardia, diastolic hypotension, nausea, abdominal pain, diarrhea, pain, and vomiting. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Grifols Biologicals at 1-888-GRIFOLS (1-888-474-3657) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.  



 Adverse reactions were reported in a study of 46 individuals with PI receiving infusions every 3 to 4 weeks of 300-600 mg per kg body weight. Thirty-one subjects (67.4%) had at least one adverse reaction at some time during the study that was considered product-related. None of the 46 subjects who participated in this study discontinued the study prematurely due to an adverse drug reaction.



 Adverse reactions that occurred with an incidence of at least 5% on a per-subject basis are summarized in  Table 1  .



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in at Least 5% of Subjects 
  a. include combined reported terms of pyrexia and body temperature increase.    
  b. include combined reported terms of pain such as pain (not otherwise specified), injection site pain, back pain, abdominal pain (not otherwise specified), and abdominal pain upper.    
  c. include combined reported terms of infusion site inflammation and others such as injection site oedema and injection site swelling.    
  
   Adverse Reaction                      Subjects (%) N=46               Number of Events                  
      Headache                           10 (21.7)                       24                                
      Pyrexia      a                     9 (19.6)                        12                                
      Pain      b                        7 (15.2)                        11                                
      Injection site reaction            6 (13.0)                        10                                
      Diarrhoea                          4 (8.7)                         5                                 
      Rigors                             4 (8.7)                         7                                 
      Urticaria                          3 (6.5)                         3                                 
      Infusion site inflammation      c        3 (6.6)                         3                                 
         Other common adverse drug reactions reported in fewer than 5% of the subjects included hypertension, sinusitis, nausea/vomiting, positive Coombs test, arthralgia, myalgia, dizziness, bronchitis, and hypotension.
 

 The total number of adverse reactions reported whose onset were within 72 hours after the end of an infusion of Flebogamma 5% DIF was 107. There were a total of 709 infusions, resulting in a rate of 0.15 temporally associated adverse reactions per infusion (the upper bound of the 1-sided 95% confidence interval = 0.18). There were 70 infusions (9.7%, 1-sided 95% upper bound CI = 12.4%) associated with at least one adverse reaction that began within 72 hours after the completion of an infusion.



 In 58 infusions the subjects reported mild adverse reactions, 25 infusions were recorded with moderate adverse reactions, and in 1 infusion the subject reported a severe adverse reaction. The percentages of infusions with a mild, moderate, or severe adverse reaction were 8.2% (upper bound 95% CI=10.5%), 3.5% (upper bound 95% CI=5.2%), and 0.1% (upper bound 95% CI=0.8%), respectively.



 Three subjects (6.5%) experienced a treatment-emergent rise in AST (&gt; 3x the upper-limit of normal), and 1 subject (2.2%) experienced a treatment-emergent rise in ALT (&gt; 3x the upper-limit of normal). None of these abnormal lab values were long-lasting (i.e. they occurred at 1 or 2 infusions), and none of these subjects had a concomitant treatment-emergent rise in total bilirubin.



 A clinical study with Flebogamma 5% DIF for the treatment of PI was conducted in 24 pediatric subjects aged 2-16 years to determine whether they respond differently from adult subjects. Pediatric subjects received intravenous infusions of 262-625 mg per kg body weight every 3-4 weeks. Twenty subjects (83.3%) had at least one adverse reaction at some time during the study that was considered product-related. There were no deaths or serious adverse reactions.



 In 317 infusions, 20 pediatric subjects reported 159 treatment-related adverse drug reactions (ADR). Treatment-related adverse reactions that occurred with an incidence of at least 5% on a per-subject basis included headache (42%), pyrexia (29%), hypotension (25%), tachycardia (25%), diastolic hypotension (21%), nausea (8%), abdominal pain (8%), diarrhea (8%), pain (8%), and vomiting (8%). Of these, 99 ADRs were mild, 54 were moderate, and 6 were severe in intensity. The most common severe ADR was headache. Tachycardia was defined as mild, moderate, or severe by ratio of heart rate over baseline of 1.2-1.4, 1.41-1.6, or &gt;1.6, respectively. Two episodes of tachycardia were moderate and 14 were mild, 1 mild case had the infusion interrupted and the rest had no action taken, and all resolved. Hypotension was defined as mild, moderate, or severe by the decrease in pressure below baseline of 10-15%, 16-25%, and &gt;25%, respectively. Ten episodes of hypotension/diastolic hypotension were moderate and 29 were mild, one moderate case had the infusion interrupted and the rest had no action taken, and all resolved. None of the ADRs related to fluctuation in vital signs were severe, all resolved without sequelae, and none were considered clinically significant.



 One subject (6.5%) experienced a treatment-emergent rise in ALT (over 2.5x the upper-limit of normal). This was considered a mild treatment-related AE and resolved without sequelae. All other lab values were within normal limits. One subject experienced one positive Coombs' test result after baseline (experienced 14 days after the final infusion). No subjects experienced clinically significant abnormal lab values for LDH, bilirubin, serum creatinine. In addition, no subjects experienced positive test results for HBsAg, HCV, or HIV.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

    Because adverse reactions are reported voluntarily post-approval from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during the post-approval use of IGIV products  19, 20  , including Flebogamma 5% DIF.




   Infusion Reactions                         Hypersensitivity (e.g. anaphylaxis), headache, diarrhea, tachycardia, fever, fatigue, dizziness, malaise, chills, flushing, urticaria or other skin reactions, wheezing or other chest discomfort, nausea, vomiting, rigors, back pain, myalgia, arthralgia, and changes in blood pressure   
   Renal                                      Acute renal dysfunction/failure, osmotic nephropathy       
   Respiratory                                Apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS), Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI), cyanosis, hypoxemia, pulmonary edema, dyspnea, bronchospasm   
   Cardiovascular                             Cardiac arrest, thromboembolism, vascular collapse, hypotension   
   Neurological                               Coma, loss of consciousness, seizures, tremor, aseptic meningitis syndrome   
   Integumentary                              Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, epidermolysis, erythema multiformae, dermatitis (e.g. bullous dermatitis)   
   Hematologic                                Pancytopenia, leukopenia, hemolysis, positive direct antiglobulin (Coombs) test   
   Musculoskeletal                            Back pain                                                  
   Gastrointestinal                           Hepatic dysfunction, abdominal pain                        
   General/Body as a Whole                    Pyrexia, rigors                                            
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION, and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE



  WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION, and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE



    *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors. (see Warnings and Precautions [5.4] and Patient Counseling Information [17]) 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patient at risk for hyperviscosity. (see Dosage and Administration [2.3] and Warnings and Precautions [5.4]) 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death1 have been related to intravenous immune globulin (IGIV) products. Patients predisposed to acute renal failure include patients with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs. 
 *  Administer FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF at the minimum dose and rate of infusion practicable in patients at risk for renal dysfunction or failure. 
 *  Reports of renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose as a stabilizer. They account for a disproportionate share of the total number of reported cases of renal dysfunction and acute renal failure. FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF does not contain sucrose. (see Dosage and Administration [2.3] and Warnings and Precautions [5.2]) 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION, and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis administer FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk of hyperviscosity. 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis and death may occur with the administration of human immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products, particularly those products that contain sucrose. FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of renal dysfunction or failure, administer FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  IgA-deficient patients with antibodies to IgA are at greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Monitor renal function, including blood urea nitrogen, serum creatinine, and urine output in patients at risk of developing acute renal failure. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia may occur in patients receiving Flebogamma 5% DIF therapy. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Thrombosis may occur. Monitor patients with known risk factors for thrombosis and consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity for those at risk of hyperviscosity. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Aseptic meningitis syndrome (AMS) may occur in patients receiving Flebogamma 5% DIF therapy, especially with high doses or rapid infusion. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hemolysis, either intravascular or due to enhanced red blood cell sequestration, can develop subsequent to Flebogamma 5% DIF treatments. Risk factors include high doses and non-O blood group. Monitor patients for hemolysis and hemolytic anemia. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions (transfusion-related acute lung injury, TRALI). (  5.7  ) 
 *  Patients receiving Flebogamma 5% DIF for the first time or being restarted on the product after a treatment hiatus of more than 8 weeks may be at a higher risk for development of fever, chills, nausea, and vomiting. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Flebogamma 5% DIF is made from human plasma and may contain infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Passive transfer of antibodies may confound serologic testing. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions and anaphylactic reactions with a fall in blood pressure may occur, even in patients who had tolerated previous treatment with IGIV. ( see Contraindications [  4  ]  ) If hypersensitivity reaction develops, discontinue Flebogamma 5% DIF infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment.



 Flebogamma 5% DIF contains trace amounts of IgA (less than 50 mug/mL). ( see Description [  11  ]  ) Patients with antibodies to IgA have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. Flebogamma 5% DIF is contraindicated in patients with antibodies against IgA and a history of hypersensitivity reaction. ( see Contraindications [  4  ]  )



    5.2 Renal Dysfunction/Failure



  Acute renal dysfunction/failure, acute tubular necrosis, proximal tubular nephropathy, osmotic nephrosis, and death have been reported in patients receiving IGIV, particularly those products containing sucrose  2  . Flebogamma 5% DIF does not contain sucrose.



 Ensure that patients are not volume-depleted before administering Flebogamma 5% DIF. For patients judged to be at risk for developing renal dysfunction, including patients with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs, administer Flebogamma 5% DIF at the minimum dose and rate of infusion practicable  3  . ( see  Boxed Warning  , Dosing and Administration [  2.3  ]  )



 Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure  1  . Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of Flebogamma 5% DIF and at appropriate intervals thereafter. If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuation of the product.



    5.3 Hyperproteinemia, Increased Serum Viscosity, and Hyponatremia



  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia may occur in patients receiving Flebogamma 5% DIF therapy. It is clinically critical to distinguish true hyponatremia from a pseudohyponatremia that is temporally or causally related to hyperproteinemia with concomitant decreased calculated serum osmolarity or elevated osmolar gap, because treatment aimed at decreasing serum free water in patients with pseudohyponatremia may lead to volume depletion, a further increase in serum viscosity, and a higher risk of thrombosis.



       5.4 Thrombosis



     Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products, including FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF. Risk factors may include advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors.



    Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. ( see Warnings and Precautions [  5.10  ]  ) For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer FLEBOGAMMA 5% DIF at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity. ( see  Boxed Warning  , Dosage and Administration [  2.3  ], and Patient Counseling Information [  17  ]  )



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



  AMS has been reported to occur following IGIV treatment. Discontinuation of IGIV treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae  7-10  . The symptoms of AMS usually begin within several hours to 2 days following IGIV treatment.



 AMS is characterized by the following signs and symptoms: severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea, and vomiting. ( see Patient Counseling Information [  17  ]  ) Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies frequently reveal pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per cubic millimeter, predominantly from the granulocytic series, and elevated protein levels up to several hundred mg/dL, but negative culture results. Conduct a thorough neurological examination to patients exhibiting such signs and symptoms, including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis.



 AMS may occur more frequently following high-dose (e.g. over 1.0 g per kg body weight) or rapid infusion of IGIV.



    5.6 Hemolysis



  Flebogamma 5% DIF may contain blood group antibodies that may act as hemolysins and induce in vivo  coating of red blood cells (RBCs) with immunoglobulin, causing a positive direct antiglobulin test (DAT) (Coombs' test) result and hemolysis  11-14  . Delayed hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to IGIV therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration and acute hemolysis, consistent with intravascular hemolysis, has been reported  15  . Cases of severe hemolysis-related renal dysfunction/failure or disseminated intravascular coagulation have occurred following infusion of IGIV.



 The following risk factors may be associated with the development of hemolysis following IGIV administration: high doses (e.g., at least 2 g per kg), given either as a single administration or divided over several days, and non-O blood group  16  . Other individual patient factors, such as an underlying inflammatory state (as may be reflected by, for example, elevated C-reactive protein or erythrocyte sedimentation rate), have been hypothesized to increase the risk of hemolysis following administration of IGIV  17  , but their role is uncertain. Hemolysis has been reported following administration of IGIV for a variety of indications, including ITP and PI  14  . Monitor patients for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis, particularly patients with risk factors noted above. Consider appropriate laboratory testing in higher risk patients, including measurement of hemoglobin or hematocrit prior to infusion and within 36 to 96 hours post infusion. If clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis or a significant drop in hemoglobin or hematocrit have been observed, perform appropriate confirmatory laboratory testing. If transfusion is indicated for patients who develop hemolysis with clinically compromising anemia after receiving IGIV, perform adequate cross-matching to avoid exacerbating on-going hemolysis. ( see Patient Counseling Information [  17  ]  )



    5.7 Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Non-cardiogenic pulmonary edema has been reported in patients following IGIV treatment  18  . TRALI is characterized by severe respiratory distress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function, and fever. Symptoms typically appear within 1 to 6 hours after transfusion.



 Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions. ( see Patient Counseling Information [  17  ]  ) If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of antineutrophil antibodies and anti-HLA antibodies in both the product and patient serum. TRALI may be managed by using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



    5.8 Infusion Reactions



  Individuals receiving Flebogamma 5% DIF for the first time, or being restarted on the product after a treatment hiatus of more than 8 weeks, may be at a higher risk for the development of fever, chills, nausea, and vomiting. Careful monitoring of recipients and adherence to recommendations regarding dosage and administration may reduce the risk of these types of events. (see Dosage and Administration [  2.3  ])



    5.9 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because Flebogamma 5% DIF is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. This also applies to unknown or emerging viruses and other pathogens. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have been associated with the use of Flebogamma 5% DIF. All infections suspected by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Grifols Biologicals at 1-888-474-3657.



 Before prescribing or administering Flebogamma 5% DIF, the physician should discuss the risks and benefits of its use with the patient. ( see Patient Counseling Information [  17  ]  )



    5.10 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



    *  Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of BUN and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of Flebogamma 5% DIF and at appropriate intervals thereafter. 
 *  Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies because of the potentially increased risk of thrombosis. 
 *  If signs and/or symptoms of hemolysis are present after an infusion of Flebogamma 5% DIF, perform appropriate laboratory testing for confirmation. 
 *  If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of antineutrophil antibodies and anti-HLA antibodies in both the product and patient serum. 
       5.11 Interference with Laboratory Tests
 

  After infusion of IgG, the transitory rise of the various passively transferred antibodies in the patient's blood may yield positive serological testing results, with the potential for misleading interpretation. Passive transmission of antibodies to erythrocyte antigens (e.g. A, B, and D) may cause a positive direct or indirect antiglobulin (Coombs') test.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
