<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="flomax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

     EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse events (&gt;=2% of patients and at a higher incidence than placebo) with the 0.4 mg dose or 0.8 mg dose were headache, dizziness, rhinitis, infection, abnormal ejaculation, asthenia, back pain, diarrhea, pharyngitis, chest pain, cough increased, somnolence, nausea, sinusitis, insomnia, libido decreased, tooth disorder, and blurred vision  (6.1)   
        To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1  Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events has been ascertained from six short-term U.S. and European placebo-controlled clinical trials in which daily doses of 0.1 to 0.8 mg FLOMAX capsules were used. These studies evaluated safety in 1783 patients treated with FLOMAX capsules and 798 patients administered placebo. Table 1 summarizes the treatment-emergent adverse events that occurred in &gt;=2% of patients receiving either FLOMAX capsules 0.4 mg or 0.8 mg and at an incidence numerically higher than that in the placebo group during two 13-week U.S. trials (US92-03A and US93-01) conducted in 1487 men.



 Table 1   Treatment-Emergent1 Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;=2% of FLOMAX Capsules or Placebo Patients in Two U.S. Short-Term Placebo-Controlled Clinical Studies 
     BODY SYSTEM/        ADVERSE EVENT          FLOMAX CAPSULES GROUPS          PLACEBO                 
                                0.4 mg        n=502          0.8 mg        n=492                  n=493           
  
 The adverse event occurred for the first time after initial dosing with double-blind study medication. 
 The adverse event was present prior to or at the time of initial dosing with double-blind study medication and subsequently increased in severity during double-blind treatment; or 
 The adverse event was present prior to or at the time of initial dosing with double-blind study medication, disappeared completely, and then reappeared during double-blind treatment. 
                              1  A treatment-emergent adverse event was defined as any event satisfying one of the following criteria:   
   2  Coding preferred terms also include cold, common cold, head cold, flu, and flu-like symptoms.   
   3  Coding preferred terms also include nasal congestion, stuffy nose, runny nose, sinus congestion, and hay fever.   
  
     BODY AS WHOLE                                                                                            
 Headache                   97 (19.3%)                 104 (21.1%)                99 (20.1%)                  
 Infection  2               45 (9.0%)                  53 (10.8%)                 37 (7.5%)                   
 Asthenia                   39 (7.8%)                  42 (8.5%)                  27 (5.5%)                   
 Back pain                  35 (7.0%)                  41 (8.3%)                  27 (5.5%)                   
 Chest pain                 20 (4.0%)                  20 (4.1%)                  18 (3.7%)                   
     NERVOUS SYSTEM                                                                                           
 Dizziness                  75 (14.9%)                 84 (17.1%)                 50 (10.1%)                  
 Somnolence                 15 (3.0%)                  21 (4.3%)                  8 (1.6%)                    
 Insomnia                   12 (2.4%)                  7 (1.4%)                   3 (0.6%)                    
 Libido decreased           5 (1.0%)                   10 (2.0%)                  6 (1.2%)                    
     RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                                                                                        
 Rhinitis  3                66 (13.1%)                 88 (17.9%)                 41 (8.3%)                   
 Pharyngitis                29 (5.8%)                  25 (5.1%)                  23 (4.7%)                   
 Cough increased            17 (3.4%)                  22 (4.5%)                  12 (2.4%)                   
 Sinusitis                  11 (2.2%)                  18 (3.7%)                  8 (1.6%)                    
     DIGESTIVE SYSTEM                                                                                         
 Diarrhea                   31 (6.2%)                  21 (4.3%)                  22 (4.5%)                   
 Nausea                     13 (2.6%)                  19 (3.9%)                  16 (3.2%)                   
 Tooth disorder             6 (1.2%)                   10 (2.0%)                  7 (1.4%)                    
     UROGENITAL SYSTEM                                                                                        
 Abnormal ejaculation       42 (8.4%)                  89 (18.1%)                 1 (0.2%)                    
     SPECIAL SENSES                                                                                           
 Blurred vision             1 (0.2%)                   10 (2.0%)                  2 (0.4%)                    
            Signs and Symptoms of Orthostasis    
   In the two U.S. studies, symptomatic postural hypotension was reported by 0.2% of patients (1 of 502) in the 0.4 mg group, 0.4% of patients (2 of 492) in the 0.8 mg group, and by no patients in the placebo group. Syncope was reported by 0.2% of patients (1 of 502) in the 0.4 mg group, 0.4% of patients (2 of 492) in the 0.8 mg group, and 0.6% of patients (3 of 493) in the placebo group. Dizziness was reported by 15% of patients (75 of 502) in the 0.4 mg group, 17% of patients (84 of 492) in the 0.8 mg group, and 10% of patients (50 of 493) in the placebo group. Vertigo was reported by 0.6% of patients (3 of 502) in the 0.4 mg group, 1% of patients (5 of 492) in the 0.8 mg group, and by 0.6% of patients (3 of 493) in the placebo group.



 Multiple testing for orthostatic hypotension was conducted in a number of studies. Such a test was considered positive if it met one or more of the following criteria: (1) a decrease in systolic blood pressure of &gt;=20 mmHg upon standing from the supine position during the orthostatic tests; (2) a decrease in diastolic blood pressure &gt;=10 mmHg upon standing, with the standing diastolic blood pressure &lt;65 mmHg during the orthostatic test; (3) an increase in pulse rate of &gt;=20 bpm upon standing with a standing pulse rate &gt;=100 bpm during the orthostatic test; and (4) the presence of clinical symptoms (faintness, lightheadedness/lightheaded, dizziness, spinning sensation, vertigo, or postural hypotension) upon standing during the orthostatic test.



 Following the first dose of double-blind medication in Study 1, a positive orthostatic test result at 4 hours post-dose was observed in 7% of patients (37 of 498) who received FLOMAX capsules 0.4 mg once daily and in 3% of the patients (8 of 253) who received placebo. At 8 hours post-dose, a positive orthostatic test result was observed for 6% of the patients (31 of 498) who received FLOMAX capsules 0.4 mg once daily and 4% (9 of 250) who received placebo (Note: patients in the 0.8 mg group received 0.4 mg once daily for the first week of Study 1).



 In Studies 1 and 2, at least one positive orthostatic test result was observed during the course of these studies for 81 of the 502 patients (16%) in the FLOMAX capsules 0.4 mg once-daily group, 92 of the 491 patients (19%) in the FLOMAX capsules 0.8 mg once-daily group, and 54 of the 493 patients (11%) in the placebo group.



 Because orthostasis was detected more frequently in FLOMAX capsule-treated patients than in placebo recipients, there is a potential risk of syncope [    see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)      ].



       Abnormal Ejaculation    

  Abnormal ejaculation includes ejaculation failure, ejaculation disorder, retrograde ejaculation, and ejaculation decrease. As shown in Table 1, abnormal ejaculation was associated with FLOMAX capsules administration and was dose-related in the U.S. studies. Withdrawal from these clinical studies of FLOMAX capsules because of abnormal ejaculation was also dose-dependent, with 8 of 492 patients (1.6%) in the 0.8 mg group and no patients in the 0.4 mg or placebo groups discontinuing treatment due to abnormal ejaculation.



       Laboratory Tests    

  No laboratory test interactions with FLOMAX capsules are known. Treatment with FLOMAX capsules for up to 12 months had no significant effect on prostate-specific antigen (PSA).



   6.2  Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of FLOMAX capsules. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to FLOMAX capsules.



 Allergic-type reactions such as skin rash, urticaria, pruritus, angioedema, and respiratory symptoms have been reported with positive rechallenge in some cases. Priapism has been reported rarely. Infrequent reports of palpitations, hypotension, skin desquamation, constipation, and vomiting have been received during the postmarketing period.



 During cataract surgery, a variant of small pupil syndrome known as Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been reported in association with alpha1blocker therapy [    see Warnings and Precautions  (5.5)      ].
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  Advise patients about the possibility of symptoms related to postural hypotension and to avoid situations where injury could result should syncope occur  (5.1)   
 *  Should not be used in combination with strong inhibitors of CYP3A4. Use with caution in combination with moderate inhibitors of CYP3A4, with strong or moderate inhibitors of CYP2D6, in patients known to be CYP2D6 poor metabolizers, or in combination with other cytochrome P450 inhibitors.  (5.2  ,  7.1  ,  12.3)   
 *  Should not be used in combination with other alpha adrenergic blocking agents  (5.2  ,  7.2  ,  12.3)   
 *  Exercise caution with concomitant administration of warfarin  (5.2  ,  7.4  ,  12.3)   
 *  Advise patients about the possibility and seriousness of priapism  (5.3)   
 *  Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients. Advise patients considering cataract surgery to tell their ophthalmologist that they have taken FLOMAX capsules.  (5.5)   
 *  Advise patients to be screened for the presence of prostate cancer prior to treatment and at regular intervals afterwards  (5.4)   
    
 

   5.1  Orthostasis



  The signs and symptoms of orthostasis (postural hypotension, dizziness, and vertigo) were detected more frequently in FLOMAX capsule-treated patients than in placebo recipients. As with other alpha adrenergic blocking agents there is a potential risk of syncope [  see Adverse Reactions  (6.1)      ]. Patients beginning treatment with FLOMAX capsules should be cautioned to avoid situations in which injury could result should syncope occur [  see Patient Counseling Information  (17.1)      ].



    5.2  Drug Interactions



   Tamsulosin is extensively metabolized, mainly by CYP3A4 and CYP2D6. FLOMAX capsules 0.4 mg should not be used in combination with strong inhibitors of CYP3A4 (e.g., ketoconazole) [  see Drug Interactions  (7.1)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ]. FLOMAX capsules should be used with caution in combination with moderate inhibitors of CYP3A4 (e.g., erythromycin), in combination with strong (e.g., paroxetine) or moderate (e.g., terbinafine) inhibitors of CYP2D6, in patients known to be CYP2D6 poor metabolizers particularly at a dose higher than 0.4 mg (e.g., 0.8 mg) [  see Drug Interactions  (7.1)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].  



  FLOMAX capsules should be used with caution in combination with cimetidine, particularly at a dose higher than 0.4 mg (e.g., 0.8 mg) [  see Drug Interactions  (7.1)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].  



  FLOMAX capsules should not be used in combination with other alpha adrenergic blocking agents [  see Drug Interactions  (7.2)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].  



  Caution is advised when alpha adrenergic blocking agents including FLOMAX are co-administered with PDE5 inhibitors. Alpha-adrenergic blockers and PDE5 inhibitors are both vasodilators that can lower blood pressure. Concomitant use of these two drug classes can potentially cause symptomatic hypotension [  see Drug Interactions  (7.3)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].  



 Caution should be exercised with concomitant administration of warfarin and FLOMAX capsules [  see Drug Interactions  (7.4)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].



    5.3  Priapism



  Rarely (probably less than 1 in 50,000 patients), tamsulosin, like other alpha1antagonists, has been associated with priapism (persistent painful penile erection unrelated to sexual activity). Because this condition can lead to permanent impotence if not properly treated, patients must be advised about the seriousness of the condition [  see Patient Counseling Information  (17.2)      ].



    5.4  Screening for Prostate Cancer



   Prostate cancer and BPH frequently co-exist; therefore, patients should be screened for the presence of prostate cancer prior to treatment with FLOMAX capsules and at regular intervals afterwards [  see Patient Counseling Information  (17.3)      ].  



    5.5  Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome



  Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) has been observed during cataract surgery in some patients treated with alpha1blockers, including FLOMAX capsules [  see Adverse Reactions  (6.2)      ]. Most reports were in patients taking the alpha1blocker when IFIS occurred, but in some cases, the alpha1blocker had been stopped prior to surgery. In most of these cases, the alpha1blocker had been stopped recently prior to surgery (2 to 14 days), but in a few cases, IFIS was reported after the patient had been off the alpha1blocker for a longer period (5 weeks to 9 months). IFIS is a variant of small pupil syndrome and is characterized by the combination of a flaccid iris that billows in response to intraoperative irrigation currents, progressive intraoperative miosis despite preoperative dilation with standard mydriatic drugs and potential prolapse of the iris toward the phacoemulsification incisions. The patient's ophthalmologist should be prepared for possible modifications to their surgical technique, such as the utilization of iris hooks, iris dilator rings, or viscoelastic substances. The benefit of stopping alpha1blocker therapy prior to cataract surgery has not been established.



    5.6  Sulfa Allergy



  In patients with sulfa allergy, allergic reaction to FLOMAX capsules has been rarely reported. If a patient reports a serious or life-threatening sulfa allergy, caution is warranted when administering FLOMAX capsules.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
