<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fluarix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The safety experience with FLUARIX (trivalent influenza vaccine) is relevant to FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT because both vaccines are manufactured using the same process and have overlapping compositions  [see Description (11)]  .



    EXCERPT:    *    In adults, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection site adverse reaction was pain (36%); the most common systemic adverse events were muscle aches (16%), headache (16%), and fatigue (16%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    In children aged 3 through 17 years, the injection site adverse reactions were pain (44%), redness (23%), and swelling (19%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    In children aged 3 through 5 years, the most common (&gt;=10%) systemic adverse events were drowsiness (17%), irritability (17%), and loss of appetite (16%); in children aged 6 through 17 years, the most common systemic adverse events were fatigue (20%), muscle aches (18%), headache (16%), arthralgia (10%), and gastrointestinal symptoms (10%). (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. There is the possibility that broad use of FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT could reveal adverse reactions not observed in clinical trials.



 In adults who received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection site adverse reaction was pain (36%). The most common (&gt;=10%) systemic adverse events were muscle aches (16%), headache (16%), and fatigue (16%).



 In children aged 3 through 17 years who received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, injection site adverse reactions were pain (44%), redness (23%), and swelling (19%). In children aged 3 through 5 years, the most common (&gt;=10%) systemic adverse events were drowsiness (17%), irritability (17%), and loss of appetite (16%); in children aged 6 through 17 years, the most common systemic adverse events were fatigue (20%), muscle aches (18%), headache (16%), arthralgia (10%), and gastrointestinal symptoms (10%).



   FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT in Adults  



 Trial 1 was a randomized, double-blind (2 arms) and open-label (one arm), active-controlled, safety, and immunogenicity trial. In this trial, subjects received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT (N = 3,036) or one of two formulations of comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (FLUARIX, TIV-1, N = 1,010 or TIV-2, N = 610), each containing an influenza type B virus that corresponded to one of the two type B viruses in FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT (a type B virus of the Victoria lineage or a type B virus of the Yamagata lineage). The population was aged 18 years and older (mean age: 58 years) and 57% were female; 69% were white, 27% were Asian, and 4% were of other racial/ethnic groups. Solicited events were collected for 7 days (day of vaccination and the next 6 days). The frequencies of solicited adverse events are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2. FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT: Incidence of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events within 7 Daysa of Vaccination in Adultsb (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                FLUARIX QUADRIVALENTc  N = 3,011-3,015  %    Trivalent Influenza Vaccine (TIV)    
  TIV-1  (B Victoria)d  N = 1,003  %    TIV-2  (B Yamagata)e  N = 607  %    
  Local                         
  Pain                          36                                  37                  31                    
  Redness                       2                                   2                   2                     
  Swelling                      2                                   2                   1                     
  Systemic                      
  Muscle aches                  16                                  19                  16                    
  Headache                      16                                  16                  13                    
  Fatigue                       16                                  18                  15                    
  Arthralgia                    8                                   10                  9                     
  Gastrointestinal symptomsf    7                                   7                   6                     
  Shivering                     4                                   5                   4                     
  Fever &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)    2                                   1                   2                     
          Total vaccinated cohort for safety included all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  7 days included day of vaccination and the subsequent 6 days.



   b  Trial 1: NCT01204671.



   c  Contained the same composition as FLUARIX (trivalent formulation) manufactured for the 2010-2011 season and an additional influenza type B virus of Yamagata lineage.



   d  Contained the same composition as FLUARIX manufactured for the 2010-2011 season (2 influenza A subtype viruses and an influenza type B virus of Victoria lineage).



   e  Contained the same 2 influenza A subtype viruses as FLUARIX manufactured for the 2010-2011 season and an influenza type B virus of Yamagata lineage.



   f  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain.



 Unsolicited events occurring within 21 days of vaccination (Day 0 to 20) were reported in 13%, 14%, and 15% of subjects who received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1, or TIV-2, respectively. The unsolicited adverse reactions that occurred most frequently (&gt;=0.1% for FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT) included dizziness, injection site hematoma, injection site pruritus, and rash. Serious adverse events occurring within 21 days of vaccination were reported in 0.5%, 0.6%, and 0.2% of subjects who received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1, or TIV-2, respectively.



   FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT in Children  



 Trial 2 was a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled, safety, and immunogenicity trial. In this trial, subjects received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT (N = 915) or one of two formulations of comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (FLUARIX, TIV-1, N = 912 or TIV-2, N = 911), each containing an influenza type B virus that corresponded to one of the two type B viruses in FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT (a type B virus of the Victoria lineage or a type B virus of the Yamagata lineage). Subjects were aged 3 through 17 years and 52% were male; 56% were white, 29% were Asian, 12% were black, and 3% were of other racial/ethnic groups. Children aged 3 through 8 years with no history of influenza vaccination received 2 doses approximately 28 days apart. Children aged 3 through 8 years with a history of influenza vaccination and children aged 9 years and older received one dose. Solicited local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events were collected using diary cards for 7 days (day of vaccination and the next 6 days). The frequencies of solicited adverse events are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3. FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT: Incidence of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events within 7 Daysa after First Vaccination in Children Aged 3 through 17 Yearsb (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                 FLUARIX QUADRIVALENTc  %            Trivalent Influenza Vaccine (TIV)    
  TIV-1  (B Victoria)d  %        TIV-2  (B Yamagata)e  %             
                                 Aged 3 through 17 Years             
  Local                          N = 903                             N = 901             N = 905               
  Painf                          44                                  42                  40                    
  Redness                        23                                  21                  21                    
  Swelling                       19                                  17                  15                    
                                 Aged 3 through 5 Years              
  Systemic                       N = 291                             N = 314             N = 279               
  Drowsiness                     17                                  12                  14                    
  Irritability                   17                                  13                  14                    
  Loss of appetite               16                                  8                   10                    
  Fever &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)    9                                   9                   8                     
                                 Aged 6 through 17 Years             
  Systemic                       N = 613                             N = 588             N = 626               
  Fatigue                        20                                  19                  16                    
  Muscle aches                   18                                  16                  16                    
  Headache                       16                                  19                  15                    
  Arthralgia                     10                                  9                   7                     
  Gastrointestinal symptomsg     10                                  10                  7                     
  Shivering                      6                                   4                   5                     
  Fever &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)    6                                   9                   6                     
          Total vaccinated cohort for safety included all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  7 days included day of vaccination and the subsequent 6 days.



   b  Trial 2: NCT01196988.



   c  Contained the same composition as FLUARIX (trivalent formulation) manufactured for the 2010-2011 season and an additional influenza type B virus of Yamagata lineage.



   d  Contained the same composition as FLUARIX manufactured for the 2010-2011 season (2 influenza A subtype viruses and an influenza type B virus of Victoria lineage).



 *       e  Contained the same 2 influenza A subtype viruses as FLUARIX manufactured for the 2010-2011 season and an influenza type B virus of Yamagata lineage. 
 *       f  Percentage of subjects with pain by age subgroup: 39%, 38%, and 37% for FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1, and TIV-2, respectively, in children aged 3 through 8 years and 52%, 50%, and 46% for FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1, and TIV-2, respectively, in children aged 9 through 17 years. 
 *       g  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain. 
    In children who received a second dose of FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1, or TIV-2, the incidences of adverse events following the second dose were generally lower than those observed after the first dose.
 

 Unsolicited adverse events occurring within 28 days of any vaccination were reported in 31%, 33%, and 34% of subjects who received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1, or TIV-2, respectively. The unsolicited adverse reactions that occurred most frequently (&gt;=0.1% for FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT) included injection site pruritus and rash. Serious adverse events occurring within 28 days of any vaccination were reported in 0.1%, 0.1%, and 0.1% of subjects who received FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1, or TIV-2, respectively.



   FLUARIX (Trivalent Formulation)  



 FLUARIX has been administered to 10,317 adults aged 18 through 64 years, 606 subjects aged 65 years and older, and 2,115 children aged 6 months through 17 years in clinical trials. The incidence of solicited adverse events in each age group is shown in Tables 4 and 5.



 Table 4. FLUARIX (Trivalent Formulation): Incidence of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events within 4 Daysa of Vaccination in Adults (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                   Trial 3b             Trial 4c         
  Aged 18 through 64 Years         Aged 65 Years and Older    
  FLUARIX  N = 760  %              Placebo  N = 192  %    FLUARIX  N = 601-602  %    Comparator  N = 596  %    
  Local                            
  Pain                             55                   12               19                 18                  
  Redness                          18                   10               11                 13                  
  Swelling                         9                    6                6                  9                   
  Systemic                         
  Muscle aches                     23                   12               7                  7                   
  Fatigue                          20                   18               9                  10                  
  Headache                         19                   21               8                  8                   
  Arthralgia                       6                    6                6                  5                   
  Shivering                        3                    3                2                  2                   
  Fever &gt;=100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)    2                    2                -                  -                   
  Fever &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)    -                    -                2                  1                   
           Total vaccinated cohort for safety included all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  4 days included day of vaccination and the subsequent 3 days.



   b  Trial 3 was a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, safety, and immunogenicity trial (NCT00100399).



   c  Trial 4 was a randomized, single-blind, active-controlled, safety, and immunogenicity trial (NCT00197288). The active control was FLUZONE(r), a US-licensed trivalent, inactivated influenza vaccine (Sanofi Pasteur SA).



 Table 5. FLUARIX (Trivalent Formulation): Incidence of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events within 4 Daysa of First Vaccination in Children Aged 3 through 17 Yearsb (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                   Aged 3 through 4 Years    Aged 5 through 17 Years    
  FLUARIX  N = 350  %              Comparator  N = 341  %    FLUARIX  N = 1,348  %    Comparator  N = 451  %    
  Local                            
  Pain                             35                38                  56                56                  
  Redness                          23                20                  18                16                  
  Swelling                         14                13                  14                13                  
  Systemic                         
  Irritability                     21                22                  -                 -                   
  Loss of appetite                 13                15                  -                 -                   
  Drowsiness                       13                20                  -                 -                   
  Fever &gt;=99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)    7                 8                   4                 3                   
  Muscle aches                     -                 -                   29                29                  
  Fatigue                          -                 -                   20                19                  
  Headache                         -                 -                   15                16                  
  Arthralgia                       -                 -                   6                 6                   
  Shivering                        -                 -                   3                 4                   
           Total vaccinated cohort for safety included all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  4 days included day of vaccination and the subsequent 3 days.



   b  Trial 6 was a single-blind, active-controlled, safety, and immunogenicity US trial (NCT00383123). The active control was FLUZONE, a US-licensed trivalent, inactivated influenza vaccine (Sanofi Pasteur SA).



 In children who received a second dose of FLUARIX or the comparator vaccine, the incidences of adverse events following the second dose were similar to those observed after the first dose.



   Serious Adverse Events:  In the 4 clinical trials in adults (N = 10,923), there was a single case of anaphylaxis within one day following administration of FLUARIX (&lt;0.01%).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Beyond those events reported above in the clinical trials for FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT or FLUARIX, the following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during postapproval use of FLUARIX (trivalent influenza vaccine). This list includes serious events or events which have causal connection to FLUARIX. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Lymphadenopathy.



   Cardiac Disorders  



 Tachycardia.



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders  



 Vertigo.



   Eye Disorders  



 Conjunctivitis, eye irritation, eye pain, eye redness, eye swelling, eyelid swelling.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  



 Abdominal pain or discomfort, swelling of the mouth, throat, and/or tongue.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  



 Asthenia, chest pain, feeling hot, injection site mass, injection site reaction, injection site warmth, body aches.



   Immune System Disorders  



 Anaphylactic reaction including shock, anaphylactoid reaction, hypersensitivity, serum sickness.



   Infections and Infestations  



 Injection site abscess, injection site cellulitis, pharyngitis, rhinitis, tonsillitis.



   Nervous System Disorders  



 Convulsion, encephalomyelitis, facial palsy, facial paresis, Guillain-Barre syndrome, hypoesthesia, myelitis, neuritis, neuropathy, paresthesia, syncope.



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders  



 Asthma, bronchospasm, dyspnea, respiratory distress, stridor.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Angioedema, erythema, erythema multiforme, facial swelling, pruritus, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, sweating, urticaria.



   Vascular Disorders  



 Henoch-Schonlein purpura, vasculitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT should be based on careful consideration of potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS) has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks.



 The 1976 swine influenza vaccine was associated with an increased frequency of GBS. Evidence for a causal relation of GBS with subsequent vaccines prepared from other influenza viruses is inconclusive. If influenza vaccine does pose a risk, it is probably slightly more than one additional case/one million persons vaccinated.



    5.2 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.



    5.3 Preventing and Managing Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Prior to administration, the healthcare provider should review the immunization history for possible vaccine sensitivity and previous vaccination-related adverse reactions. Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT.



    5.4 Altered Immunocompetence



  If FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT is administered to immunosuppressed persons, including individuals receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the immune response may be lower than in immunocompetent persons.



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT may not protect all susceptible individuals.



    5.6 Persons at Risk of Bleeding



  As with other intramuscular injections, FLUARIX QUADRIVALENT should be given with caution in individuals with bleeding disorders such as hemophilia or on anticoagulant therapy, to avoid the risk of hematoma following the injection.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
