<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fluad" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most common (&gt;= 10%) local (injection site) adverse reactions observed in clinical studies were injection site pain (25%) and tenderness (21%). (  6  ) 
 *  The most common (&gt;= 10%) systemic adverse reactions observed in clinical studies were myalgia (15%), headache (13%) and fatigue (13%). (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Vaccines at 1- 855-358-8966 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 and    www.vaers.hhs.gov  .
 

 

  6.1. Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect rates observed in clinical practice.



 Solicited adverse reactions were assessed in a multicenter, observer-blind, randomized controlled study (Study 1) conducted in the United States, Colombia, Panama and the Philippines. The safety analysis set included 3545 FLUAD recipients and 3537 AGRIFLU (Influenza Vaccine) recipients. The enrolled subject population in Study 1 was 65 to 97 years of age (mean 72 years) and 64% were female. Within each treatment group, 53% were Asian, 28% were Caucasian, 18% were Hispanic, 1% were Black, and fewer than 1% each were Native American/Alaskan, Pacific Islander/Hawaiian, or Other.



 Solicited local (injection site) and systemic adverse reactions were collected from subjects in Study 1 who completed a symptom diary card for seven days following vaccination. The reported frequencies of solicited local and systemic adverse events from Study 1 are presented in  Table 1  .



 Table 1: Percentages of Subjects &gt;= 65 Years of Age With Solicited Local and Systemic Adverse Reactions in Days 1-7 After Administration of FLUAD or AGRIFLU (a U.S. Licensed Comparator) NCT01162122 
  a N = number of subjects with safety data.    
  b Moderate: pain, tenderness, myalgia, fatigue, headache, arthralgia, chills, nausea, vomiting defined as "some limitation in normal daily activity", diarrhea defined as "4 to 5 stools a day".    
  c Severe: pain, tenderness, myalgia, fatigue, headache, arthralgia, chills, nausea, vomiting defined as "unable to perform normal daily activity", diarrhea defined as "6 or more watery stools a day".    
  d Potentially life threatening (PLT) reaction defined as requiring emergency room visit or hospitalization.    
  
   Study 1             
                        FLUAD    (N      a      =3418-3496)    Percentage      AGRIFLU    (N      a      =3420-3488)    Percentage     
      Local            
   Injection site Pain    Any                          25.0                         12.2                          
 Moderate  b          3.9                          1.9                           
 Severe  c            0.3                          0.2                           
   Tenderness         Any                          21.1                         11.2                          
 Moderate             3.0                          1.0                           
 Severe               0.1                          0.2                           
   Erythema           Any                          1.2                          0.5                           
 25 to &lt;= 50 mm       1.1                          0.5                           
 51 to &lt;= 100 mm      0.2                          &lt;0.1                          
 &gt; 100 mm             0.0                          0.0                           
   Induration         Any                          1.3                          0.5                           
 25 to &lt;= 50 mm       1.0                          0.5                           
 51 to &lt;= 100 mm      0.3                          0.0                           
 &gt; 100 mm             0.0                          0.0                           
   Swelling           Any                          1.2                          0.4                           
 25 to &lt;= 50 mm       1.0                          0.4                           
 51 to &lt;= 100 mm      0.2                          &lt;0.1                          
 &gt; 100 mm             &lt;0.1                         0.0                           
      Systemic         
   Myalgia            Any                          14.7                         9.7                           
 Moderate             2.6                          1.8                           
 Severe               0.3                          0.7                           
   Fatigue            Any                          13.3                         10.4                          
 Moderate             3.1                          2.4                           
 Severe               0.4                          0.6                           
 PLT  d               0.0                          &lt;0.1                          
   Headache           Any                          13.2                         11.2                          
 Moderate             3.0                          2.6                           
 Severe               0.4                          0.6                           
 PLT                  0.0                          &lt;0.1                          
   Arthralgia         Any                          8.5                          7.8                           
 Moderate             1.6                          1.6                           
 Severe               0.2                          0.6                           
   Chills             Any                          6.7                          4.7                           
 Moderate             1.5                          1.2                           
 Severe               0.3                          0.3                           
 PLT                  &lt;0.1                         0.0                           
   Diarrhea           Any                          4.8                          4.5                           
 Moderate             1.3                          0.9                           
 Severe               0.3                          0.2                           
 PLT                  &lt;0.1                         &lt;0.1                          
   Fever              Any                          3.6                          3.4                           
 &gt;= 38.0 degrees C to &lt;= 38.4 degrees C  1.8                          1.7                           
 &gt;= 38.5 degrees C to &lt;= 38.9 degrees C  1.3                          1.3                           
 39.0 degrees C to &lt;= 40.0 degrees C  0.4                          0.4                           
 &gt;= 40.0 degrees C    0.1                          0.0                           
   Nausea             Any                          2.9                          2.8                           
 Moderate             0.4                          0.6                           
 Severe               0.1                          0.1                           
 PLT                  &lt;0.1                         0.0                           
   Vomiting           Any                          1.4                          1.7                           
 Moderate             0.4                          0.5                           
 Severe               &lt;0.1                         0.1                           
 PLT                  &lt;0.1                         0.0                           
              Unsolicited Adverse Events (AEs)  : The clinical safety of FLUAD was assessed in fifteen (15) randomized, controlled studies. The total safety population in these trials included 10,952 adults 65 years of age and older, comprising 5,754 who received FLUAD and 5,198 who received other US licensed influenza vaccines. The percentage of subjects with an unsolicited AE within 30 days following vaccination was similar between vaccine groups (16.9% FLUAD vs. 18.0% active comparator).
 

     Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) and Deaths  : In Study 1, in which subjects were followed for SAEs and deaths for one year following vaccination (N=3,545 FLUAD, N=3,537 AGRIFLU), the percentages of subjects with an SAE were similar between vaccine groups (7% FLUAD vs. 7% AGRIFLU). Four SAEs (1 FLUAD and 3 AGRIFLU) were assessed as related to study vaccination over one year of observation and 2 of these occurred (1 FLUAD and 1 AGRIFLU) within 21 days following study vaccination. There were 98 deaths (n=52 FLUAD, n=46 AGRIFLU) over one year of which none occurred within the first 21 days following vaccination.



 In 14 additional randomized, controlled studies, SAEs were collected over a 3 to 4-week period in 4 studies, over a 8-week period in 1 study, and over a 6-month period in 9 studies (N= 2,209 FLUAD, N=1,661 US licensed influenza vaccines). The percentages of subjects with an SAE within 30 days (1.1% FLUAD vs. 1.8% AGRIFLU) or within 6 months (4.3% FLUAD vs. 5.9% AGRIFLU) were similar between vaccine groups. The percentages of deaths within 30 days (0.3% FLUAD vs. 0.6% active comparator) or within 6 months (1.0% FLUAD vs. 1.5% active comparator) were also similar.



     Adverse Events of Special Interest (AESIs):  Rates of new onset neuroinflammatory and immune mediated diseases were assessed in a  post hoc  analysis of the 15 randomized controlled studies over the time periods specified above for SAEs. The percentage of subjects with an AESI at any time after vaccination was similar between vaccine groups (0.9% FLUAD vs. 0.9% active comparator). There were no notable imbalances for specific AESIs.



     Safety of Annual Revaccination  : In 5 of the randomized, controlled trials, subjects were followed for SAEs and deaths for 6 months following revaccination (N=492 FLUAD, N=330 US licensed and non-US licensed influenza vaccines). After the second annual vaccination, the percentages of subjects with an SAE were similar between vaccine groups (6.1% FLUAD vs. 5.5% comparator influenza vaccines); 23 deaths (n=17 FLUAD, n=6 comparator influenza vaccines) were reported. Causes of death included cardiovascular events, malignancy, trauma, gastrointestinal disorders, and respiratory failure. Clinical characteristics of the deaths, including the variable causes, timing since vaccination, and underlying medical conditions, do not provide evidence for a causal relationship with FLUAD.



   6.2. Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during post-approval use of FLUAD in Europe and other regions since 1997. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  



 Thrombocytopenia (some cases were severe with platelet counts less than 5,000 per mm  3  ), lymphadenopathy



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  



 Extensive swelling of injected limb lasting more than one week, injection site cellulitis-like reactions (some cases of swelling, pain, and redness extending more than 10 cm and lasting more than 1 week)



   Immune system disorders:  



 Allergic reactions including anaphylactic shock, anaphylaxis and angioedema



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  



 Muscular weakness



   Nervous system disorders:  



 Encephalomyelitis, Guillain-Barre Syndrome, convulsions, neuritis, neuralgia, paraesthesia, syncope, presyncope



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  



 Generalized skin reactions including erythema multiforme, urticaria, pruritis or non-specific rash



   Vascular disorders:  



 Vasculitis with transient renal involvement
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  If Guillain-Barre Syndrome (GBS) has occurred within six weeks of previous influenza vaccination, the decision to give FLUAD should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
 *  The tip caps of the prefilled syringes contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1. Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS) has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLUAD should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. The 1976 swine influenza vaccine was associated with an elevated risk of GBS. Evidence for a causal relationship of GBS with other influenza vaccines is inconclusive; if an excess risk exists, it is probably slightly more than 1 additional case per 1 million persons vaccinated. [see References (  1  )]  



    5.2. Preventing and Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine.



    5.3. Latex



  The tip caps of the prefilled syringes contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals. [see Description (  11  )]  



    5.4. Altered Immunocompetence



  The immune response to FLUAD in immunocompromised persons, including individuals receiving immunosuppressive therapy, may be lower than in immunocompetent individuals. [see Concurrent Use With Immunosuppressive Therapies (  7.2  )]  



    5.5. Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) may occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines including FLUAD. Ensure procedures are in place to avoid injury from falling associated with syncope.



    5.6 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with FLUAD may not protect all vaccine recipients against influenza disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
