<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="flucelvax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in adults 18-64 years of age were injection site pain (45.4%) headache (18.7%), fatigue (17.8%) and myalgia (15.4%), injection site erythema (13.4%), and induration (11.6%). (  6  ) 
 *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in adults &gt;=65 years of age were injection site pain (21.6%) and injection site erythema (11.9%). (  6  ) 
 *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in children 4 to &lt;6 years of age were tenderness at the injection site (46%), injection site erythema (18%), sleepiness (19%), irritability (16%), injection site induration (13%) and change in eating habits (10%). (  6  ) 
 *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in children 6 through 8 years of age were pain at the injection site (54%), injection site erythema (22%), injection site induration (16%), headache (14%), fatigue (13%) and myalgia (12%). (  6  ) 
 *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in children and adolescents 9 through 17 years of age were pain at the injection site (58%), headache (22%), injection site erythema (19%),fatigue (18%) myalgia (16%), and injection site induration (15%). (  6  ) 
    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Seqirus Inc. at 1-855-358-8966 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 and  www.vaers.hhs.gov  .
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in adults 18-64 years of age were injection site pain (45.4%) headache (18.7%), fatigue (17.8%) and myalgia (15.4%), injection site erythema (13.4%), and induration (11.6%).



 The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in adults &gt;=65 years of age were injection site pain (21.6%), and injection site erythema (11.9%).



 The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in children 4 to &lt;6 years of age after first dose of vaccine were tenderness at the injection site (46%), injection site erythema (18%), sleepiness (19%), irritability (16%), injection site induration (13%) and change in eating habits (10%).



 The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in children 6 through 8 years of age after first dose of vaccine were pain at the injection site (54%), injection site erythema (22%), injection site induration (16%), headache (14%), fatigue (13%) and myalgia (12%).



 The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in children and adolescents 9 through 17 years of age were pain at the injection site (58%), headache (22%), injection site erythema (19%), fatigue (18%) myalgia (16%), and injection site induration (15%).



 Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical studies of another vaccine, and may not reflect rates observed in clinical practice.



     Adults 18 years of age and older:  



 The safety of FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT in adults was evaluated in a randomized, double-blind, controlled study conducted in the US (Study 1). The safety population included a total of 2680 adults 18 years of age and older; 1340 adults 18 through 64 years of age and 1340 adults 65 years of age and older.



 In this study, subjects received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT or one of the two formulations of comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (TIV1c and TIV2c) (FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT (n=1335), TIV1c, n=676 or TIV2c n= 669). The mean age of subjects who received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT was 57.4 years of age; 54.8% of subjects were female and 75.6% were Caucasian, 13.4% were Black, 9.1% were Hispanics, 0.7% were American Indian and 0.3%, 0.1% and 0.7% were Asian, Native Hawaiian and others, respectively. The safety data observed are summarized in  Table 2  .



 In this study, solicited local injection site and systemic adverse reactions were collected from subjects who completed a symptom diary card for 7 days following vaccination.



 Solicited adverse reactions for FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT and comparator are summarized in  Table 2  .



 Table 2: Incidence of Solicited Adverse Reactions in the Safety Population1 Reported Within 7 Days of Vaccination (Study 1) 
                      18 through 64 years of age      &gt;= 65 years of age     
   Percentages (%)      2       
   FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENTN=663      Trivalent Influenza Vaccine      FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENTN=656      Trivalent Influenza Vaccine     
   TIV1cN=330         TIV2cN=327      TIV1cN=340      TIV2cN=336     
  
  1Safety population: all subjects in the exposed population who provided post-vaccination safety data    
  2Percentage of severe adverse reactions are presented in parenthesis    
  Study 1: NCT01992094    
  
   Local Adverse Reactions     
 Injection site induration  11.6 (0)        9.7 (0.3)     10.4 (0)    8.7 (0)       6.8 (0)         7.7(0)       
 Injection site erythema  13.4(0)         13.3(0)       10.1(0)     11.9(0)       10.6(0)         10.4(0)      
 Injection site ecchymosis  3.8 (0)         3.3(0.3)      5.2(0)      4.7(0)        4.4(0)          5.4(0)       
 Injection site pain  45.4(0.5)       37.0(0.3)     40.7(0)     21.6(0)       18.8(0)         18.5(0)      
   Systemic Adverse Reactions     
 Chills             6.2(0.2)        6.4(0.6)      6.4(0)      4.4(0.3)      4.1(0.3)        4.5(0.6)     
 Nausea             9.7 (0.3)       7.3 (0.9)     8.9 (1.2)   3.8 (0.2)     4.1(0)          4.2 (0.3)    
 Myalgia            15.4 (0.8)      14.5 (0.9)    15.0 (1.2)  8.2 (0.2)     9.4 (0.3)       8.3 (0.6)    
 Arthralgia         8.1 (0.5)       8.2 (0)       9.5 (0.9)   5.5 (0.5)     5.0 (0.3)       6.8 (0.9)    
 Headache           18.7 (0.9)      18.5 (0.9)    18.7 (0.6)  9.3 (0.3)     8.5 (0.6)       8.3(0.6)     
 Fatigue            17.8 (0.6)      22.1 (0.3)    15.6 (1.5)  9.1 (0.8)     10.6 (0.3)      8.9 (0.6)    
 Vomiting           2.6 (0)         1.5 (0.3)     0.9 (0)     0.9 (0.2)     0.3 (0)         0.6 (0)      
 Diarrhea           7.4 (0.6)       7.6 (0)       7.6 (0.6)   4.3 (0.5)     5.0 (0.9)       5.1 (0.3)    
 Loss of appetite   8.3 (0.3)       8.5 (0.3)     8.3 (0.9)   4.0 (0.2)     5.0 (0)         3.6 (0.3)    
 Fever: &gt;=38.0  degrees C (&gt;=40.0 degrees C)  0.8 (0)         0.6 (0)       0.3 (0)     0.3 (0)       0.9 (0)         0.6 (0)      
                Unsolicited adverse events were collected for 21 days after vaccination. In adults 18 years of age and older, unsolicited adverse events were reported in 16.1% of subjects who received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT, within 21 days after vaccination.
 

 In adults 18 years of age and older, serious adverse events (SAEs) were collected throughout the study duration (until 6 months after vaccination) and were reported by 3.9%, of the subjects who received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT. None of the SAEs were assessed as being related to study vaccine.



     Children and Adolescents 4 through 17 years of age:  



 The safety of FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT in children was evaluated in a randomized, double-blind, controlled study conducted in the US (Study 2). The safety population included a total of 2332 children 4 through 17 years of age; 1161 children 4 through 8 years of age and 1171 children 9 through 17 years of age.



 In this study, subjects received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT or one of the two formulations of comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT n=1159, TIV1c, n=593 or TIV2c n= 580). Children 9 through 17 years of age received a single dose of FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT or comparator vaccine. Children 4 through 8 years of age received one or two doses (separated by 4 weeks) of FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT or comparator vaccine based on determination of the subject's prior influenza vaccination history. The mean age of subjects who received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT was 9.6 years of age; 48% of subjects were female and 53% were Caucasian. The safety data observed are summarized in  Table 3  and  Table 4  .



 In this study, solicited local injection site and systemic adverse reactions were collected from subjects who completed a symptom diary card for 7 days following vaccination.



 Solicited adverse reactions for FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT and comparator are summarized in  Table 3  and  Table 4  .



 Table 3: Incidence of Solicited Adverse Reactions in the Safety Population1 (4 through 5 years of age) Reported Within 7 Days of the First dose of Vaccination (Study 2) 
                         Children 4 through 5 years        
   Percentages (%)      2       
   FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENTN=182      Trivalent Influenza Vaccine       
   TIV1cN=91             TIV2cN=93                         
  
  1Safety population: all subjects in the exposed population who provided post-vaccination safety data.    
  2Percentage of subjects with severe adverse reactions are presented in parenthesis.    
  Study 2: NCT01992107    
  
   Local Adverse Reactions     
 Injection site induration  13 (1)                             20 (2)                    13 (0)                   
 Injection site erythema  18 (1)                             23 (1)                    17 (0)                   
 Injection site ecchymosis  9 (0)                              11 (0)                    8 (0)                    
 Injection site tenderness  46 (1)                             45 (1)                    43 (0)                   
   Systemic Adverse Reactions     
 Change in eating habits  10 (1)                             7                         6                        
 Sleepiness            19 (1)                             12 (3)                    10 (0)                   
 Irritability          16 (2)                             10 (2)                    10 (1)                   
 Chills                5 (1)                              2 (0)                     1 (0)                    
 Vomiting              4 (0)                              2 (0)                     2 (0)                    
 Diarrhea              4 (0)                              2 (0)                     2 (0)                    
 Fever: &gt;=38.0  degrees C (&gt;=40.0  degrees C)  4 (0)                              4 (0)                     3 (0)                    
         Table 4: Incidence of Solicited Adverse Reactions in the Safety Population1 (Children 6 through 17 years of age) Reported Within 7 Days of Vaccination (Study 2) 
                        Children 6 through 8 years (after first dose)      Children 9 through 17 years     
   Percentages (%)      2       
   FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENTN=371-372      Trivalent Influenza vaccine      FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENTN=579      Trivalent Influenza Vaccine     
   TIV1cN=185           TIV2cN=186          TIV1cN=294      TIV2cN=281-282     
  
  1Safety population: all subjects in the exposed population who provided post-vaccination safety data.    
  2Percentage of subjects with severe adverse reactions are presented in parenthesis.    
  Study 2: NCT 01992107    
  
   Local Adverse Reactions     
 Injection site induration  16 (0)              19 (1)    13 (0)  15 (0)    15 (0)              13 (&lt;1)      
 Injection site erythema  22 (0)              23 (1)    20 (0)  19 (&lt;1)   17 (0)              15 (&lt;1)      
 Injection site ecchymosis  9 (0)               9 (0)     8 (0)  4 (0)     5 (0)               5 (0)        
 Injection site pain  54 (1)              57 (1)    58 (2)  58 (1)    51(&lt;1)              50 (0)       
   Systemic Adverse Events     
 Chills               4 (1)               3 (0)     4 (0)  7 (0)     6 (1)               4 (1)        
 Nausea               8 (1)               5 (0)     5 (1)  9 (&lt;1)    8 (1)               7 (1)        
 Myalgia              12 (1)              14 (0)    10 (0)  16 (&lt;1)   17 (&lt;1)             15 (&lt;1)      
 Arthralgia           4 (0)               5 (0)     4 (0)  6 (0)     6 (0)               8 (&lt;1)       
 Headache             14 (1)              13 (0)    12 (0)  22 (1)    23 (2)              18 (1)       
 Fatigue              13 (2)              14 (0)    18 (0)  18 (&lt;1)   16 (1)              16 (&lt;1)      
 Vomiting             3 (1)               3 (0)     3 (0)  2 (0)     1 (0)               2 (0)        
 Diarrhea             3 (&lt;1)              6 (1)     5 (0)  4 (0)     4 (0)               3 (&lt;1)       
 Loss of appetite     9 (&lt;1)              5 (0)     8 (1)  9 (0)     9 (&lt;1)              9 (0)        
 Fever: &gt;=38.0  degrees C (&gt;=40.0  degrees C)  4 (0)               3 (0)     2 (0)  1 (&lt;1)    3 (0)               1 (0)        
              In children who received a second dose of FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT, TIV1c, or TIV2c, the incidence of adverse reactions following the second dose of vaccine were similar to those observed with the first dose.
 

 Unsolicited adverse events were collected for 21 days after last vaccination. In children 4 through 17 years of age, unsolicited adverse events were reported in 24.3 of subjects who received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT, within 3 weeks after last vaccination.



 In children 4 through 17 years of age, serious adverse events (SAEs) were collected throughout the study duration (until 6 months after last vaccination) and were reported by 0.5%, of the subjects who received FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT. None of the SAEs were assessed as being related to study vaccine.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The safety experience with FLUCELVAX (trivalent influenza vaccine) is relevant to FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT, because both vaccines are manufactured using the same process and have overlapping compositions.



 The following additional adverse events have been identified during post-approval use of FLUCELVAX. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine.



   Immune system disorders  : Anaphylactic reaction, angioedema.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : Generalized skin reactions including pruritus, urticaria or non-specific rash.



   Nervous systems disorders:  Syncope, Presyncope



   General disorders and administration site conditions  : Extensive swelling of injected limb.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  The 1976 swine influenza vaccine was associated with an elevated risk of Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS). Evidence for a causal relation of GBS with other influenza vaccines is inconclusive; if an excess risk exists, it is probably slightly more than 1 additional case per 1 million persons vaccinated.  1  If GBS has occurred after receipt of a prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENTshould be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks.



    5.2 Preventing and Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine.



    5.3 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including Flucelvax. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope by maintaining a supine or Trendelenburg position.



    5.4 Altered Immunocompetence



  After vaccination with FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT, immunocompromised individuals, including those receiving immunosuppressive therapy, may have a reduced immune response.



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with FLUCELVAX QUADRIVALENT may not protect all vaccine recipients against influenza disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
