<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fludarabine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most common adverse reactions include myelosuppression (neutropenia, thrombocytopenia and anemia), fever and chills, infection, and nausea and vomiting. Other commonly reported events include malaise, fatigue, anorexia, and weakness. Serious opportunistic infections have occurred in CLL patients treated with fludarabine phosphate. The most frequently reported adverse reactions and those reactions which are more clearly related to the drug are arranged below according to body system.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt; 30%) include myelosuppression (neutropenia, thrombocytopenia and anemia), fever, infection, nausea and vomiting, fatigue, anorexia, cough and weakness (    6    ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sandoz Inc. at 1-800-525-8747 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Hematopoietic Systems

  Hematologic events (neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and/or anemia) were reported in the majority of CLL patients treated with fludarabine phosphate. During fludarabine phosphate treatment of 133 patients with CLL, the absolute neutrophil count decreased to less than 500/mm  3  in 59% of patients, hemoglobin decreased from pretreatment values by at least 2 grams percent in 60%, and platelet count decreased from pretreatment values by at least 50% in 55%. Myelosuppression may be severe, cumulative, and may affect multiple cell lines. Bone marrow fibrosis occurred in one CLL patient treated with fludarabine phosphate.



 Several instances of trilineage bone marrow hypoplasia or aplasia resulting in pancytopenia, sometimes resulting in death, have been reported in post-marketing surveillance. The duration of clinically significant cytopenia in the reported cases has ranged from approximately 2 months to approximately 1 year. These episodes have occurred both in previously treated or untreated patients.



 Life-threatening and sometimes fatal autoimmune hemolytic anemias have been reported to occur in patients receiving fludarabine phosphate. [  See  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ] The majority of patients rechallenged with fludarabine phosphate developed a recurrence in the hemolytic process.



   6.2 Metabolic

  Tumor lysis syndrome has been reported in CLL patients treated with fludarabine phosphate. This complication may include hyperuricemia, hyperphosphatemia, hypocalcemia, metabolic acidosis, hyperkalemia, hematuria, urate crystalluria, and renal failure. The onset of this syndrome may be heralded by flank pain and hematuria.



   6.3 Nervous System

  Objective weakness, agitation, confusion, visual disturbances, and coma have occurred in CLL patients treated with fludarabine phosphate at the recommended dose. Peripheral neuropathy has been observed in patients treated with fludarabine phosphate and one case of wrist-drop was reported. [  See  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]



 In post marketing experience, cases of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy have been reported. Most cases had a fatal outcome. Many of these cases were confounded by prior and/or concurrent chemotherapy. The median time to onset was approximately one year.



   6.4 Pulmonary System

  Pneumonia, a frequent manifestation of infection in CLL patients, occurred in 16%, and 22% of those treated with fludarabine phosphate in the MDAH and SWOG studies, respectively. Pulmonary hypersensitivity reactions to fludarabine phosphate characterized by dyspnea, cough and interstitial pulmonary infiltrate have been observed.



 In post-marketing experience, cases of severe pulmonary toxicity have been observed with fludarabine phosphate use which resulted in ARDS, respiratory distress, pulmonary hemorrhage, pulmonary fibrosis, and respiratory failure. After an infectious origin has been excluded, some patients experienced symptom improvement with corticosteroids.



   6.5 Gastrointestinal System

  Gastrointestinal disturbances such as nausea and vomiting, anorexia, diarrhea, stomatitis and gastrointestinal bleeding have been reported in patients treated with fludarabine phosphate.



   6.6 Cardiovascular

  Edema has been frequently reported. One patient developed a pericardial effusion possibly related to treatment with fludarabine phosphate. No other severe cardiovascular events were considered to be drug related.



   6.7 Genitourinary System

  Hemorrhagic cystitis has been reported in patients treated with fludarabine phosphate.



   6.8 Skin

  Skin toxicity, consisting primarily of skin rashes, has been reported in patients treated with fludarabine phosphate.



   6.9 Adverse Reactions from Clinical Trials

  Data in Table 1 are derived from the 133 patients with CLL who received fludarabine phosphate in the MDAH and SWOG studies.



 TABLE 1: PERCENT OF CLL PATIENTS REPORTING NON-HEMATOLOGIC ADVERSE REACTIONS 
 ADVERSE REACTIONS                                                 MDAH(N=101)            SWOG(N=32)        
  
 ANY ADVERSE REACTION                                                   88                    91            
 BODY AS A WHOLE                                                        72                    84            
   FEVER                                                                60                    69            
   CHILLS                                                               11                    19            
   FATIGUE                                                              10                    38            
   INFECTION                                                            33                    44            
   PAIN                                                                 20                    22            
   MALAISE                                                              8                     6             
   DIAPHORESIS                                                          1                     13            
   ALOPECIA                                                             0                     3             
   ANAPHYLAXIS                                                          1                     0             
   HEMORRHAGE                                                           1                     0             
   HYPERGLYCEMIA                                                        1                     6             
   DEHYDRATION                                                          1                     0             
 NEUROLOGICAL                                                           21                    69            
   WEAKNESS                                                             9                     65            
   PARESTHESIA                                                          4                     12            
   HEADACHE                                                             3                     0             
   VISUAL DISTURBANCE                                                   3                     15            
   HEARING LOSS                                                         2                     6             
   SLEEP DISORDER                                                       1                     3             
   DEPRESSION                                                           1                     0             
   CEREBELLAR SYNDROME                                                  1                     0             
   IMPAIRED MENTATION                                                   1                     0             
 PULMONARY                                                              35                    69            
   COUGH                                                                10                    44            
   PNEUMONIA                                                            16                    22            
   DYSPNEA                                                              9                     22            
   SINUSITIS                                                            5                     0             
   PHARYNGITIS                                                          0                     9             
   UPPER RESPIRATORY INFECTION                                          2                     16            
   ALLERGIC PNEUMONITIS                                                 0                     6             
   EPISTAXIS                                                            1                     0             
   HEMOPTYSIS                                                           1                     6             
   BRONCHITIS                                                           1                     0             
   HYPOXIA                                                              1                     0             
 GASTROINTESTINAL                                                       46                    63            
   NAUSEA/VOMITING                                                      36                    31            
   DIARRHEA                                                             15                    13            
   ANOREXIA                                                             7                     34            
   STOMATITIS                                                           9                     0             
   GI BLEEDING                                                          3                     13            
   ESOPHAGITIS                                                          3                     0             
   MUCOSITIS                                                            2                     0             
   LIVER FAILURE                                                        1                     0             
   ABNORMAL LIVER FUNCTION TEST                                         1                     3             
   CHOLELITHIASIS                                                       0                     3             
   CONSTIPATION                                                         1                     3             
   DYSPHAGIA                                                            1                     0             
 CUTANEOUS                                                              17                    18            
   RASH                                                                 15                    15            
   PRURITUS                                                             1                     3             
   SEBORRHEA                                                            1                     0             
 GENITOURINARY                                                          12                    22            
   DYSURIA                                                              4                     3             
   URINARY INFECTION                                                    2                     15            
   HEMATURIA                                                            2                     3             
   RENAL FAILURE                                                        1                     0             
   ABNORMAL RENAL FUNCTION TEST                                         1                     0             
   PROTEINURIA                                                          1                     0             
   HESITANCY                                                            0                     3             
 CARDIOVASCULAR                                                         12                    38            
   EDEMA                                                                8                     19            
   ANGINA                                                               0                     6             
   CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE                                             0                     3             
   ARRHYTHMIA                                                           0                     3             
   SUPRAVENTRICULAR TACHYCARDIA                                         0                     3             
   MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION                                                0                     3             
   DEEP VENOUS THROMBOSIS                                               1                     3             
   PHLEBITIS                                                            1                     3             
   TRANSIENT ISCHEMIC ATTACK                                            1                     0             
   ANEURYSM                                                             1                     0             
   CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT                                             0                     3             
 MUSCULOSKETAL                                                          7                     16            
   MYALGIA                                                              4                     16            
   OSTEOPOROSIS                                                         2                     0             
   ARTHRALGIA                                                           1                     0             
 TUMOR LYSIS SYNDROME                                                   1                     0             
         More than 3000 adult patients received fludarabine phosphate in studies of other leukemias, lymphomas, and other solid tumors. The spectrum of adverse effects reported in these studies was consistent with the data presented above.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CNS TOXICITY, HEMOLYTIC ANEMIA, AND PULMONARY TOXICITY

  WARNING: CNS TOXICITY, HEMOLYTIC ANEMIA, AND PULMONARY TOXICITY

    Fludarabine Phosphate Injection should be administered under the supervision of a qualified physician experienced in the use of antineoplastic therapy. Fludarabine phosphate can severely suppress bone marrow function. When used at high doses in dose-ranging studies in patients with acute leukemia, fludarabine phosphate was associated with severe neurologic effects, including blindness, coma, and death. This severe central nervous system toxicity occurred in 36% of patients treated with doses approximately four times greater (96 mg/m  2  /day for 5 to 7 days) than the recommended dose. Similar severe central nervous system toxicity has been rarely (&lt;=0.2%) reported in patients treated at doses in the range of the dose recommended for chronic lymphocytic leukemia. [  See   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]  



   Instances of life-threatening and sometimes fatal autoimmune hemolytic anemia have been reported to occur after one or more cycles of treatment with fludarabine phosphate. Patients undergoing treatment with Fludarabine Phosphate Injection should be evaluated and closely monitored for hemolysis. [  See   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]   



   In a clinical investigation using fludarabine phosphate in combination with pentostatin (deoxycoformycin) for the treatment of refractory chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), there was an unacceptably high incidence of fatal pulmonary toxicity. Therefore, the use of Fludarabine Phosphate Injection in combination with pentostatin is not recommended [  See   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)    ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: CNS TOXICITY, HEMOLYTIC ANEMIA, AND PULMONARY TOXICITY  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Severe central nervous system toxicity occurred in 36% of patients treated with doses approximately four times greater (96 mg/m2/day for 5 to 7 days) than the recommended dose. This toxicity was seen in &lt;=0.2% of patients treated at the recommended dose levels (25 mg/m2). (5.1) 
 *  Instances of life-threatening and sometimes fatal autoimmune hemolytic anemia have been reported after one or more cycles of treatment. (5.2) 
 *  In a clinical investigation of the combination of fludarabine phosphate with pentostatin (deoxycoformycin) for the treatment of refractory chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), there was an unacceptably high incidence of fatal pulmonary toxicity. (5.6) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Severe bone marrow suppression, notably anemia, thrombocytopenia and neutropenia. Monitor blood counts before and during treatment. (   5.2   ) 
 *  Transfusion-associated graft-versus-host disease. Use only irradiated blood products for transfusions. (   5.5   ) 
 *  Infections. Monitor for infection. (   5.3   ) 
 *  Renal Insufficiency. Reduce dose for moderate renal impairment and monitor closely. Do not administer to patients with severe renal impairment. (   5.7   ) 
 *  Tumor lysis syndrome (TLS). Take precautions for patients at high risk for TLS. (   5.4   ) 
 *  May cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant. (   5.9   ) 
    
 

   5.1 Neurotoxicity



  There are clear dose dependent toxic effects seen with fludarabine phosphate. Dose levels approximately 4 times greater (96 mg/m  2  /day for 5 to 7 days) than that recommended for CLL (25 mg/m  2  /day for 5 days) were associated with a syndrome characterized by delayed blindness, coma and death. Symptoms appeared from 21 to 60 days following the last dose. Thirteen of 36 patients (36%) who received fludarabine phosphate at high doses (96 mg/m  2  /day for 5 to 7 days) developed this severe neurotoxicity. This syndrome has been reported rarely in patients treated with doses in the range of the recommended CLL dose of 25 mg/m  2  /day for 5 days every 28 days. The effect of chronic administration of fludarabine phosphate on the central nervous system is unknown; however, patients have received the recommended dose for up to 15 courses of therapy.



    5.2 Hematological Adverse Reactions



  Severe bone marrow suppression, notably anemia, thrombocytopenia and neutropenia, has been reported in patients treated with fludarabine phosphate. In a Phase I study in adult solid tumor patients, the median time to nadir counts was 13 days (range, 3 to 25 days) for granulocytes and 16 days (range, 2 to 32 days) for platelets. Most patients had hematologic impairment at baseline either as a result of disease or as a result of prior myelosuppressive therapy. Cumulative myelosuppression may be seen. While chemotherapy-induced myelosuppression is often reversible, administration of Fludarabine Phosphate Injection requires careful hematologic monitoring.



 Several instances of trilineage bone marrow hypoplasia or aplasia resulting in pancytopenia, sometimes resulting in death, have been reported in adult patients. The duration of clinically significant cytopenia in the reported cases has ranged from approximately 2 months to approximately 1 year. These episodes have occurred both in previously treated or untreated patients.



 Instances of life-threatening and sometimes fatal autoimmune hemolytic anemia have been reported to occur after one or more cycles of treatment with fludarabine phosphate in patients with or without a previous history of autoimmune hemolytic anemia or a positive Coombs' test and who may or may not be in remission from their disease. Steroids may or may not be effective in controlling these hemolytic episodes. The majority of patients rechallenged with fludarabine phosphate developed a recurrence in the hemolytic process. The mechanism(s) which predispose patients to the development of this complication has not been identified. Patients undergoing treatment with Fludarabine Phosphate Injection should be evaluated and closely monitored for hemolysis.



    5.3 Infections



  Of the 133 adult CLL patients in the two trials, there were 29 fatalities during study. Approximately 50% of the fatalities were due to infection and 25% due to progressive disease.



    5.4 Tumor Lysis Syndrome



  Tumor lysis syndrome associated with fludarabine phosphate treatment has been reported in CLL patients with large tumor burdens. Since fludarabine phosphate can induce a response as early as the first week of treatment, precautions should be taken in those patients at risk of developing this complication.



    5.5 Use of Transfusions



  Transfusion-associated graft-versus-host disease has been observed rarely after transfusion of non-irradiated blood in fludarabine phosphate treated patients. Consideration should, therefore, be given to the use of irradiated blood products in those patients requiring transfusions while undergoing treatment with Fludarabine Phosphate Injection.



    5.6 Pulmonary Toxicity



  In a clinical investigation using fludarabine phosphate in combination with pentostatin (deoxycoformycin) for the treatment of refractory chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) in adults, there was an unacceptably high incidence of fatal pulmonary toxicity. Therefore, the use of Fludarabine Phosphate Injection in combination with pentostatin is not recommended.



    5.7 Renal Impairment



  There are inadequate data on dosing of patients with renal insufficiency. Fludarabine Phosphate Injection must be administered cautiously in patients with renal insufficiency. The total body clearance of 2-fluoro-ara-A has been shown to be directly correlated with creatinine clearance. Patients with moderate impairment of renal function (creatinine clearance 30 to 70 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ) should have their fludarabine phosphate dose reduced by 20% and be monitored closely. Fludarabine phosphate is not recommended for patients with severely impaired renal function (creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ). [ See  Dosage and Administration (2.2)    ]



    5.8 Monitoring



    *  Hematologic and Nonhematologic Toxicity 
    Fludarabine Phosphate Injection is an antineoplastic agent with potentially significant toxic side effects. Patients undergoing therapy should be closely observed for signs of hematologic and nonhematologic toxicity. Periodic assessment of peripheral blood counts is recommended to detect the development of anemia, neutropenia and thrombocytopenia.
 

 *  Hematopoietic Suppression 
    During treatment, the patient's hematologic profile (particularly neutrophils and platelets) should be monitored regularly to determine the degree of hematopoietic suppression.
 

    5.9 Pregnancy



  Pregnancy Category D: Fludarabine phosphate may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Fludarabine phosphate was teratogenic in rats and in rabbits. Fludarabine phosphate was administered intravenously at doses of 0, 1, 10 or 30 mg/kg/day to pregnant rats on days 6 to 15 of gestation. At 10 and 30 mg/kg/day in rats, there was an increased incidence of various skeletal malformations. Fludarabine phosphate was administered intravenously at doses of 0, 1, 5 or 8 mg/kg/day to pregnant rabbits on days 6 to 15 of gestation. Dose-related teratogenic effects manifested by external deformities and skeletal malformations were observed in the rabbits at 5 and 8 mg/kg/day. Drug-related deaths or toxic effects on maternal and fetal weights were not observed. There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women.



 If Fludarabine Phosphate Injection is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
