<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="flulaval" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    In adults, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited local adverse reaction was pain (60%); most common solicited systemic adverse events were muscle aches (26%), headache (22%), fatigue (22%), and arthralgia (15%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    In children aged 3 through 17 years, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited local adverse reaction was pain (65%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    In children aged 3 through 4 years, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited systemic adverse events were irritability (26%), drowsiness (21%), and loss of appetite (17%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    In children aged 5 through 17 years, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited systemic adverse events were muscle aches (29%), fatigue (22%), headache (22%), arthralgia (13%), and gastrointestinal symptoms (10%). (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or    www.vaers.hhs.gov  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. There is the possibility that broad use of FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT could reveal adverse reactions not observed in clinical trials.



 In adults who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited local adverse reaction was pain (60%); the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited systemic adverse events were muscle aches (26%), headache (22%), fatigue (22%), and arthralgia (15%).



 In children aged 3 through 17 years who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited local adverse reaction was pain (65%). In children aged 3 through 4 years, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited systemic adverse events were irritability (26%), drowsiness (21%), and loss of appetite (17%). In children aged 5 through 17 years, the most common (&gt;=10%) systemic adverse events were muscle aches (29%), fatigue (22%), headache (22%), arthralgia (13%), and gastrointestinal symptoms (10%).



 FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT has been administered to 1,384 adults aged 18 years and older and 3,516 pediatric subjects aged 3 through 17 years in 4 clinical trials.



     FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT in Adults  



 Trial 1 was a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled, safety and immunogenicity trial. In this trial, subjects received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT (N = 1,272), or one of two formulations of a comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (FLULAVAL, TIV-1, N = 213 or TIV-2, N = 218), each containing an influenza type B virus that corresponded to one of the two B viruses in FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT (a type B virus of the Victoria lineage or a type B virus of the Yamagata lineage). The population was aged 18 years and older (mean age: 50 years) and 61% were female; 61% of subjects were white, 3% were black, 1% were Asian, and 35% were of other racial/ethnic groups. Solicited adverse events were collected for 7 days (day of vaccination and the next 6 days). The incidence of local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events occurring within 7 days of vaccination in adults are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2. FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT: Incidence of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events within 7 Daysa of Vaccination in Adults Aged 18 Years and Olderb (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENTc  N = 1,260  %    Trivalent Influenza Vaccine (TIV)    
  TIV-1  (B Victoria)d  N = 208  %    TIV-2  (B Yamagata)e  N = 216  %      
  Local Adverse Reactions       
  Pain                          60                                    45                 41                   
  Swelling                      3                                     1                  4                    
  Redness                       2                                     3                  1                    
  Systemic Adverse Events       
  Muscle aches                  26                                    25                 19                   
  Headache                      22                                    20                 23                   
  Fatigue                       22                                    22                 17                   
  Arthralgia                    15                                    17                 15                   
  Gastrointestinal symptomsf    9                                     10                 7                    
  Shivering                     9                                     8                  6                    
  Fever &gt;=100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)    2                                     1                  1                    
          Total vaccinated cohort for safety included all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  7 days included day of vaccination and the subsequent 6 days.



   b  Trial 1: NCT01196975.



   c  Contained two A strains and two B strains, one of Victoria lineage and one of Yamagata lineage.



   d  Contained two A strains and a B strain of Victoria lineage.



   e  Contained the same two A strains as FLULAVAL and a B strain of Yamagata lineage.



   f  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain.



 Unsolicited adverse events occurring within 21 days of vaccination were reported in 19%, 23%, and 23% of subjects who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT (N = 1,272), TIV-1 (B Victoria) (N = 213), or TIV-2 (B Yamagata) (N = 218), respectively. The unsolicited adverse events that occurred most frequently (&gt;=1% for FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT) included nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, headache, cough and oropharyngeal pain. Serious adverse events occurring within 21 days of vaccination were reported in 0.4%, 0%, and 0% of subjects who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT, TIV-1 (B Victoria), or TIV-2 (B Yamagata), respectively.



     FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT in Children  



 Trial 2 was a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled trial. In this trial, subjects received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT (N = 932), or one of two formulations of a comparator trivalent influenza vaccine [FLUARIX  (r)  (Influenza Vaccine), TIV-1, N = 929 or TIV-2, N = 932], each containing an influenza type B virus that corresponded to one of the two B viruses in FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT (a type B virus of the Victoria lineage or a type B virus of the Yamagata lineage). The population was aged 3 through 17 years (mean age: 9 years) and 53% were male; 65% were white, 13% were Asian, 9% were black, and 13% were of other racial/ethnic groups. Children aged 3 through 8 years with no history of influenza vaccination received 2 doses approximately 28 days apart. Children aged 3 through 8 years with a history of influenza vaccination and children aged 9 years and older received one dose. Solicited local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events were collected for 7 days (day of vaccination and the next 6 days). The incidence of local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events occurring within 7 days of vaccination in children are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3. FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT: Incidence of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events within 7 Daysa of First Vaccination in Children Aged 3 through 17 Yearsb (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                    FLULAVAL  QUADRIVALENTc  %    Trivalent Influenza Vaccine (TIV)    
  TIV-1  (B Victoria)d  %           TIV-2  (B Yamagata)e  %     
                                    Aged 3 through 17 Years     
  Local Adverse Reactions           N = 913                     N = 911               N = 915                 
  Pain                              65                          55                    56                      
  Swelling                          6                           3                     4                       
  Redness                           5                           3                     4                       
                                    Aged 3 through 4 Years      
  Systemic Adverse Events           N = 185                     N = 187               N = 189                 
  Irritability                      26                          17                    22                      
  Drowsiness                        21                          20                    23                      
  Loss of appetite                  17                          16                    13                      
  Fever &gt;=100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)    5                           6                     4                       
                                    Aged 5 through 17 Years     
  Systemic Adverse Events           N = 727                     N = 724               N = 725                 
  Muscle aches                      29                          25                    25                      
  Fatigue                           22                          24                    23                      
  Headache                          22                          22                    20                      
  Arthralgia                        13                          12                    11                      
  Gastrointestinal symptomsf        10                          10                    9                       
  Shivering                         7                           7                     7                       
  Fever &gt;=100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)    2                           4                     3                       
          Total vaccinated cohort for safety included all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  7 days included day of vaccination and the subsequent 6 days.



   b  Trial 2: NCT01198756.



   c  Contained two A strains and two B strains, one of Victoria lineage and one of Yamagata lineage.



   d  Contained two A strains and a B strain of Victoria lineage.



   e  Contained the same two A strains as FLUARIX and a B strain of Yamagata lineage.



   f  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain.



 In children who received a second dose of FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT, FLUARIX TIV-1 (B Victoria), or TIV-2 (B Yamagata), the incidences of adverse events following the second dose were generally lower than those observed after the first dose.



 Unsolicited adverse events occurring within 28 days of vaccination were reported in 30%, 31% and 30% of subjects who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT (N = 932), FLUARIX TIV-1 (B Victoria) (N = 929), or TIV-2 (B Yamagata) (N = 932), respectively. The unsolicited adverse events that occurred most frequently (&gt;=1% for FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT) included vomiting, pyrexia, bronchitis, nasopharyngitis, pharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, headache, cough, oropharyngeal pain, and rhinorrhea. Serious adverse events occurring within 28 days of any vaccination were reported in 0.1%, 0.2%, and 0.2% of subjects who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT, FLUARIX TIV-1 (B Victoria), or TIV-2 (B Yamagata), respectively.



 Trial 3 was a randomized, observer-blind, non-influenza vaccine-controlled trial evaluating the efficacy of FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT. The trial included subjects aged 3 through 8 years who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT (N = 2,584) or HAVRIX  (r)  (Hepatitis A Vaccine) (N = 2,584), as a control vaccine. Children with no history of influenza vaccination received 2 doses of FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT or HAVRIX approximately 28 days apart. Children with a history of influenza vaccination received one dose of FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT or HAVRIX. In the overall population, 52% were male; 60% were Asian, 5% were white, and 35% were of other racial/ethnic groups. The mean age of subjects was 5 years. Solicited local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events were collected for 7 days (day of vaccination and the next 6 days). The incidence of local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events occurring within 7 days of vaccination in children are shown in Table 4.



 Table 4. FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT: Incidence of Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events within 7 Daysa of First Vaccination in Children Aged 3 through 8 Yearsb (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                         FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT  %                        HAVRIXc  %        
                                         Aged 3 through 8 Years                          
  Local Adverse Reactions                N = 2,546                                       N = 2,551         
  Pain                                   39                                              28                
  Swelling                               1                                               0.3               
  Redness                                0.4                                             0.2               
                                         Aged 3 through 4 Years                          
  Systemic Adverse Events                N = 898                                         N = 895           
  Loss of appetite                       9                                               8                 
  Irritability                           8                                               8                 
  Drowsiness                             8                                               7                 
  Fever &gt;=100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)    4                                               4                 
                                         Aged 5 through 8 Years                          
  Systemic Adverse Events                N = 1,648                                       N = 1,654         
  Muscle aches                           12                                              10                
  Headache                               11                                              11                
  Fatigue                                8                                               7                 
  Arthralgia                             6                                               5                 
  Gastrointestinal symptomsd             6                                               6                 
  Shivering                              3                                               3                 
  Fever &gt;=100.4 degrees F (38.0 degrees C)    3                                               3                 
         Total vaccinated cohort for safety included all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  7 days included day of vaccination and the subsequent 6 days.



   b  Trial 3: NCT01218308.



   c  Hepatitis A Vaccine used as a control vaccine.



   d  Gastrointestinal symptoms included nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and/or abdominal pain.



 In children who received a second dose of FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT or HAVRIX, the incidences of adverse events following the second dose were generally lower than those observed after the first dose.



 The frequency of unsolicited adverse events occurring within 28 days of vaccination was similar in both groups (33% for both FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT and HAVRIX). The unsolicited adverse events that occurred most frequently (&gt;=1% for FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT) included diarrhea, pyrexia, gastroenteritis, nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, varicella, cough, and rhinorrhea. Serious adverse events occurring within 28 days of any vaccination were reported in 0.7% of subjects who received FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT and in 0.2% of subjects who received HAVRIX.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  There are no postmarketing data available for FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT. The following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during postapproval use of FLULAVAL (trivalent influenza vaccine). Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their incidence rate or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine. Adverse events described here are included because: a) they represent reactions which are known to occur following immunizations generally or influenza immunizations specifically; b) they are potentially serious; or c) the frequency of reporting.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Lymphadenopathy.



   Eye Disorders  



 Eye pain, photophobia.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  



 Dysphagia, vomiting.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  



 Chest pain, injection site inflammation, asthenia, injection site rash, influenza-like symptoms, abnormal gait, injection site bruising, injection site sterile abscess.



   Immune System Disorders  



 Allergic reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema.



   Infections and Infestations  



 Rhinitis, laryngitis, cellulitis.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  



 Muscle weakness, arthritis.



   Nervous System Disorders  



 Dizziness, paresthesia, hypoesthesia, hypokinesia, tremor, somnolence, syncope, Guillain-Barre syndrome, convulsions/seizures, facial or cranial nerve paralysis, encephalopathy, limb paralysis.



   Psychiatric Disorders  



 Insomnia.



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders  



 Dyspnea, dysphonia, bronchospasm, throat tightness.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Urticaria, localized or generalized rash, pruritus, sweating.



   Vascular Disorders  



 Flushing, pallor.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS) has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks.



 The 1976 swine influenza vaccine was associated with an elevated risk of GBS. Evidence for a causal relation of GBS with other influenza vaccines is inconclusive; if an excess risk exists, it is probably slightly more than one additional case/one million persons vaccinated.



    5.2 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.



    5.3 Preventing and Managing Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Prior to administration, the healthcare provider should review the immunization history for possible vaccine sensitivity and previous vaccination-related adverse reactions. Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT.



    5.4 Altered Immunocompetence



  If FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT is administered to immunosuppressed persons, including individuals receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the immune response may be lower than in immunocompetent persons.



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT may not protect all susceptible individuals.



    5.6 Persons at Risk of Bleeding



  As with other intramuscular injections, FLULAVAL QUADRIVALENT should be given with caution in individuals with bleeding disorders such as hemophilia or on anticoagulant therapy to avoid the risk of hematoma following the injection.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
