<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="flumist" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   The most common solicited adverse reactions (&gt;= 10% in vaccine recipients and at least 5% greater than in placebo recipients) reported after FluMist were runny nose or nasal congestion (ages 2 years through 49 years), fever over 100 degrees F (children ages 2 years through 6 years), and sore throat (adults ages 18 years through 49 years). Among children and adolescents 2 through 17 years of age who received FluMist Quadrivalent, 32% reported runny nose or nasal congestion and 7% reported fever over 100 degrees F. Among adults 18 through 49 years of age who received FluMist Quadrivalent, 44% reported runny nose or nasal congestion and 19% reported sore throat. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact MedImmune at 1-877-633-4411 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or http://vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

    6.1    Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 This safety experience with FluMist is relevant to FluMist Quadrivalent because both vaccines are manufactured using the same process and have overlapping compositions [see    Description (11)    ]. A total of 9537 children and adolescents 1 through 17 years of age and 3041 adults 18 through 64 years of age received FluMist in randomized, placebo-controlled Studies D153-P501, AV006, D153-P526, AV019, and AV009 [3 used Allantoic Fluid containing Sucrose-Phosphate-Glutamate (AF-SPG) placebo, and 2 used saline placebo] described below. In addition, 4179 children 6 through 59 months of age received FluMist in Study MI-CP111, a randomized, active-controlled trial. Among pediatric FluMist recipients 6 months through 17 years of age, 50% were female; in the study of adults, 55% were female. In MI-CP111, AV006, D153-P526, AV019, and AV009, subjects were White (71%), Hispanic (11%), Asian (7%), Black (6%), and Other (5%), while in D153-P501, 99% of subjects were Asian.



 A total of 1382 children and adolescents 2 through 17 years of age and 1198 adults 18 through 49 years of age received FluMist Quadrivalent in randomized, active-controlled Studies MI-CP208 and MI-CP185. Among pediatric FluMist Quadrivalent recipients 2 through 17 years of age, 51% were female; in the study of adults, 55% were female. In Studies MI-CP208 and MI-CP185, subjects were White (73%), Asian (1%), Black or African-American (19%), and Other (7%); overall, 22% were Hispanic or Latino.



   FluMist in Children and Adolescents  



 The safety of FluMist was evaluated in an AF-SPG placebo-controlled study (AV019) conducted in a Health Maintenance Organization (HMO) in children 1 through 17 years of age (FluMist = 6473, placebo = 3216). An increase in asthma events, captured by review of diagnostic codes, was observed in children younger than 5 years of age who received FluMist compared to those who received placebo (Relative Risk 3.53, 90% CI: 1.1, 15.7).



 In Study MI-CP111, children 6 through 59 months of age were randomized to receive FluMist or inactivated Influenza Virus Vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur Inc. Wheezing requiring bronchodilator therapy or accompanied by respiratory distress or hypoxia was prospectively monitored from randomization through 42 days post last vaccination. Hospitalization due to all causes was prospectively monitored from randomization through 180 days post last vaccination. Increases in wheezing and hospitalization (for any cause) were observed in children 6 months through 23 months of age who received FluMist compared to those who received inactivated Influenza Virus Vaccine, as shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Percentages of Children with Hospitalizations and Wheezing from Study MI-CP111a 
    Adverse Reaction       Age Group        FluMist    (n/N)       Active    Control      b      (n/N)     
  Hospitalizations  c      6-23 months      4.2%(84/1992)    3.2%(63/1975)    
                   24-59 months     2.1%(46/2187)    2.5%(56/2198)    
  Wheezing  d      6-23 months      5.9%(117/1992)   3.8%(75/1975)    
                   24-59 months     2.1%(47/2187)    2.5%(56/2198)    
            a   NCT00128167; see www.clinicaltrials.gov  b   Inactivated Influenza Virus Vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur Inc., administered intramuscularly.  c   Hospitalization due to any cause from randomization through 180 days post last vaccination.  d   Wheezing requiring bronchodilator therapy or accompanied by respiratory distress or hypoxia evaluated from randomization through 42 days post last vaccination.
 

 Most hospitalizations observed were due to gastrointestinal and respiratory tract infections and occurred more than 6 weeks post vaccination. In post-hoc analysis, rates of hospitalization in children 6 through 11 months of age were 6.1% (42/684) in FluMist recipients and 2.6% (18/683) in inactivated Influenza Virus Vaccine recipients.



 Table 2 shows pooled solicited adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of FluMist recipients and at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) compared to placebo post Dose 1 for Studies D153-P501 and AV006, and solicited adverse reactions post Dose 1 for Study MI-CP111. Solicited adverse reactions were those about which parents/guardians were specifically queried after receipt of FluMist, placebo, or control vaccine. In these studies, solicited reactions were documented for 10 days post vaccination. Solicited reactions following the second dose of FluMist were similar to those following the first dose and were generally observed at a lower frequency.



 Table 2: Summary of Solicited Adverse Reactions Observed Within 10 Days after Dose 1 for FluMist and Either Placebo or Active Control Recipients in Children 2 through 6 Years of Age 
                     Studies D153-P501      a      &amp; AV006       Study MI-CP111      b       
                     FluMist    N = 876-1759      e         Placebo      c      N = 424-1034      e         FluMist    N = 2170      e         Active    Control      d      N = 2165      e       
    Event          %                %                %                %                
  Runny Nose/Nasal Congestion   58               50               51               42               
  Decreased Appetite   21               17               13               12               
  Irritability     21               19               12               11               
  Decreased Activity(Lethargy)   14               11               7                6                
  Sore Throat      11               9                5                6                
  Headache         9                7                3                3                
  Muscle Aches     6                3                2                2                
  Chills           4                3                2                2                
  Fever                                                                                
   &gt; 100  o  F Oral  &gt; 100 - &lt;= 101  o  F Oral  &gt; 101 - &lt;= 102  o  F Oral   1694             1163             1364             1143             
             a   NCT00192244; see www.clinicaltrials.gov  b  NCT00128167; see www.clinicaltrials.gov  c  Study D153-P501 used saline placebo; Study AV006 used AF-SPG placebo.  d   Inactivated Influenza Virus Vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur Inc., administered intramuscularly.  e   Number of evaluable subjects (those who returned diary cards) for each reaction. Range reflects differences in data collection between the 2 pooled studies.
 

 In clinical studies D153-P501 and AV006, unsolicited adverse reactions in children occurring in at least 1% of FluMist recipients and at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) compared to placebo were abdominal pain (2% FluMist vs. 0% placebo) and otitis media (3% FluMist vs. 1% placebo). An additional adverse reaction identified in the active-controlled trial MI-CP111 occurring in at least 1% of FluMist recipients and at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) compared to active control was sneezing (2% FluMist vs. 1% active control).



 In a separate saline placebo-controlled trial (D153-P526) in a subset of older children and adolescents 9 through 17 years of age who received one dose of FluMist, the solicited adverse reactions as well as unsolicited adverse reactions reported were generally consistent with observations from the trials in Table 2.     Abdominal pain was reported in 12% of FluMist recipients compared to 4% of placebo recipients and decreased activity was reported in 6% of FluMist recipients compared to 0% of placebo recipients.



 In Study AV018, in which FluMist was concomitantly administered with Measles, Mumps, and Rubella Virus Vaccine Live (MMR, manufactured by Merck &amp; Co., Inc.) and Varicella Virus Vaccine Live (manufactured by Merck &amp; Co., Inc.) to children 12 through 15 months of age, adverse reactions were similar to those seen in other clinical trials of FluMist.



   FluMist Quadrivalent in Children and Adolescents  



 In the randomized, active-controlled Study MI-CP208 that compared FluMist Quadrivalent and FluMist in children and adolescents 2 through 17 years of age, the rates of solicited adverse reactions reported were similar between subjects who received FluMist Quadrivalent and FluMist. Table 3 includes solicited adverse reactions post Dose 1 from Study MI-CP208 that either occurred at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) in FluMist Quadrivalent recipients compared to FluMist recipients or were identified in previous FluMist clinical studies (see  Table 2  ). In this study, solicited adverse reactions were documented for 14 days post vaccination. Solicited adverse reactions post Dose 2 were observed at a lower frequency compared to those post Dose 1 for FluMist Quadrivalent and were similar between subjects who received FluMist Quadrivalent and FluMist.



 Table 3: Summary of Solicited Adverse Reactionsa Observed Within 14 Days after Dose 1 for FluMist Quadrivalent and FluMist Recipients in Study MI-CP208b in Children and Adolescents 2 through 17 Years of Age 
                     FluMist    Quadrivalent    N = 1341-1377      d         FluMist      c      N = 901-920      d       
    Event          %                %                
 Runny Nose/Nasal CongestionHeadacheDecreased Activity (Lethargy)Sore ThroatDecreased AppetiteMuscle AchesFever&gt; 100  o  F by any route&gt; 100 - &lt;= 101  o  F by any route&gt; 101 - &lt;= 102  o  F by any route   321310964732     3212101075522    
           a   Solicited adverse reactions that occurred at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) in FluMist Quadrivalent recipients compared to FluMist recipients or were identified in previous FluMist trials (see  Table 2  ).  b  NCT01091246; see www.clinicaltrials.gov  c   Represents pooled data from the two FluMist study arms. [see     Clinical Studies (14.2)    ]  d   Number of evaluable subjects for each event.
 

 In Study MI-CP208, no unsolicited adverse reactions occurred at a higher rate (1% or greater) in FluMist Quadrivalent recipients compared to FluMist recipients.



   FluMist in Adults  



 In adults 18 through 49 years of age in Study AV009, solicited adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of FluMist recipients and at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) compared to AF-SPG placebo include runny nose (44% FluMist vs. 27% placebo), headache (40% FluMist vs. 38% placebo), sore throat (28% FluMist vs. 17% placebo), tiredness/weakness (26% FluMist vs. 22% placebo), muscle aches (17% FluMist vs. 15% placebo), cough (14% FluMist vs. 11% placebo), and chills (9% FluMist vs. 6% placebo).



 In Study AV009, unsolicited adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of FluMist recipients and at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) compared to placebo were nasal congestion (9% FluMist vs. 2% placebo) and sinusitis (4% FluMist vs. 2% placebo).



   FluMist Quadrivalent in Adults  



 In the randomized, active-controlled Study MI-CP185 that compared FluMist Quadrivalent and FluMist in adults 18 through 49 years of age, the rates of solicited adverse reactions reported were generally similar between subjects who received FluMist Quadrivalent and FluMist. Table 4 presents solicited adverse reactions that either occurred at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) in FluMist Quadrivalent recipients compared to FluMist recipients or were identified in Study AV009.



 Table 4: Summary of Solicited Adverse Reactionsa Observed Within 14 Days after Dose 1 for FluMist Quadrivalent and FluMist Recipients in Study MI-CP185b in Adults 18 through 49 Years of Age 
                     FluMist    Quadrivalent    N = 1197      d         FluMist      c      N = 597      d       
    Event          %                %                
 Runny Nose/Nasal CongestionHeadacheSore ThroatDecreased Activity (Lethargy)CoughMuscle AchesDecreased Appetite   4428191814106    4027201813105    
           a  Solicited adverse reactions that occurred at a higher rate (&gt;= 1% rate difference after rounding) in FluMist Quadrivalent recipients compared to FluMist recipients or were identified in Study AV009.  b  NCT00860067; see www.clinicaltrials.gov  c  Represents pooled data from the two FluMist study arms.  [see      Clinical Studies (14.4)      ]    d  Number of evaluable subjects for each event.
 

 In Study MI-CP185, no unsolicited adverse reactions occurred at a higher rate (1% or greater) in FluMist Quadrivalent recipients compared to FluMist recipients.



     6.2    Postmarketing    Experience   

  The following events have been spontaneously reported during post approval use of FluMist. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure.



 Cardiac disorders: Pericarditis



 Congenital, familial, and genetic disorders: Exacerbation of symptoms of mitochondrial encephalomyopathy (Leigh syndrome)



 Gastrointestinal disorders: Nausea, vomiting, diarrhea



 Immune system disorders: Hypersensitivity reactions (including anaphylactic reaction, facial edema, and urticaria)



 Nervous system disorders: Guillain-Barre syndrome, Bell's Palsy, meningitis, eosinophilic meningitis, vaccine-associated encephalitis



 Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders: Epistaxis



 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders: Rash
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  In clinical trials, risks of hospitalization and wheezing were increased in children younger than 2 years of age who received FluMist (trivalent Influenza Vaccine Live, Intranasal). (  5.1  ) 
 *  Children younger than 5 years of age with recurrent wheezing and persons of any age with asthma may be at increased risk of wheezing following the administration of FluMist Quadrivalent. (  5.2  ) 
 *  If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of any prior influenza vaccination, the decision to give FluMist Quadrivalent should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. (  5.3  )  
 *  FluMist Quadrivalent has not been studied in immunocompromised persons. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

    5.1   Risks of Hospitalization and Wheezing in Children Younger than 24 Months of Age  



  In clinical trials, risks of hospitalization and wheezing were increased in children younger than 2 years of age who received FluMist (trivalent Influenza Vaccine Live, Intranasal) [see    Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]. This observation with FluMist is relevant to FluMist Quadrivalent because both vaccines are manufactured using the same process and have overlapping compositions [see   Description (11)    ].



     5.2   Asthma, Recurrent Wheezing, and Active Wheezing  



  Children younger than 5 years of age with recurrent wheezing and persons of any age with asthma may be at increased risk of wheezing following administration of FluMist Quadrivalent. FluMist Quadrivalent has not been studied in persons with severe asthma or active wheezing.



     5.3   Guillain-Barre   Syndrome  



  The 1976 swine influenza vaccine (inactivated) was associated with an elevated risk of Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS). Evidence for causal relation of GBS with other influenza vaccines is inconclusive; if an excess risk exists, based on data for inactivated influenza vaccines, it is probably slightly more than 1 additional case per 1 million persons vaccinated [1]. If GBS has occurred within 6 weeks of any prior influenza vaccination, the decision to give FluMist Quadrivalent should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and potential risks.



     5.4   Altered   Immunocompetence  



  FluMist Quadrivalent has not been studied in immunocompromised persons. The effectiveness of FluMist has not been studied in immunocompromised persons. Data on safety and shedding of vaccine virus after administration of FluMist in immunocompromised persons are limited to 173 persons with HIV infection and 10 mild to moderately immunocompromised children and adolescents with cancer [see       Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ].



     5.5   Medical Conditions Predisposing to Influenza Complications  



  The safety of FluMist Quadrivalent in individuals with underlying medical conditions that may predispose them to complications following wild-type influenza infection has not been established.



     5.6   Management of Acute Allergic Reactions  



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine [see   Contraindications (4.1)    ].



     5.7   Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness  



  FluMist Quadrivalent may not protect all individuals receiving the vaccine.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
