<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fluoxetine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and at least twice that for placebo):



 abnormal dreams, abnormal ejaculation, anorexia, anxiety, asthenia, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, flu syndrome, impotence, insomnia, libido decreased, nausea, nervousness, pharyngitis, rash, sinusitis, somnolence, sweating, tremor, vasodilatation, and yawn (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Edgemont Pharmaceuticals, LLC, at 1-888-594-4332 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect or predict the rates observed in practice.



 Multiple doses of fluoxetine had been administered to 10,782 patients with various diagnoses in U.S. clinical trials. In addition, there have been 425 patients administered fluoxetine in panic clinical trials. Adverse reactions were recorded by clinical investigators using descriptive terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse reactions without first grouping similar types of reactions into a limited (i.e., reduced) number of standardized reaction categories.



 In the tables and tabulations that follow, COSTART Dictionary terminology has been used to classify reported adverse reactions. The stated frequencies represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, an adverse reaction of the type listed. An adverse reaction was included if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation. It is important to emphasize that adverse reactions reported during therapy were not necessarily caused by it.



 The prescriber should be aware that the figures in the tables and tabulations cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse reactions in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the side effect incidence rate in the population studied.



   Incidence in MDD, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder placebo-controlled clinical trials (excluding data from extensions of trials)  -    Table 2    enumerates the most common adverse reactions associated with the use of fluoxetine (incidence of at least 5% for fluoxetine and at least twice that for placebo within at least 1 of the indications) for the treatment of MDD, OCD, and bulimia in U.S. controlled clinical trials and Panic Disorder in U.S. plus non-U.S. controlled trials.    Table 3    provides combined data for the pool of studies that are provided separately by indication in    Table 2  .  



 Table 2. Most Common Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Major Depressive Disorder, Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials 
 Note: Includes U.S. data for MDD, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-U.S. data for Panic Disorder clinical trials.    a    = Denominator used was for males only (  N  = 690 fluoxetine MDD;  N  = 410 placebo MDD;  N  = 116 fluoxetine OCD;  N  = 43 placebo OCD;  N  = 14 fluoxetine Bulimia;  N  = 1 placebo Bulimia;  N  = 162 fluoxetine Panic Disorder;  N  = 121 placebo Panic Disorder).-- = Incidence less than 1%.   
  
                        Percentage of Patients Reporting Event    
                        MDD          OCD         Bulimia      Panic Disorder    
  Body System/Adverse Reaction    Fluoxetine (N = 1728)       Placebo (N = 975)       Fluoxetine    (N = 266)    Placebo (N = 89)       Fluoxetine    (N = 450)    Placebo (N = 267)       Fluoxetine    (N = 425)    Placebo (N = 342)       
  Body as a Whole                                                                                                          
     Asthenia           9            5           15           11         21           9           7            7           
     Flu Syndrome       3            4           10           7          8            3           5            5           
  Cardiovascular System                                                                                                          
     Vasodilatation     3            2           5            --         2            1           1            --          
  Digestive System                                                                                                         
     Nausea             21           9           26           13         29           11          12           7           
     Diarrhea           12           8           18           13         8            6           9            4           
     Anorexia           11           2           17           10         8            4           4            1           
     Dry Mouth          10           7           12           3          9            6           4            4           
     Dyspepsia          7            5           10           4          10           6           6            2           
  Nervous System                                                                                                           
     Insomnia           16           9           28           22         33           13          10           7           
     Anxiety            12           7           14           7          15           9           6            2           
     Nervousness        14           9           14           15         11           5           8            6           
     Somnolence         13           6           17           7          13           5           5            2           
     Tremor             10           3           9            1          13           1           3            1           
     Libido Decreased    3            --          11           2          5            1           1            2           
     Abnormal Dreams    1            1           5            2          5            3           1            1           
  Respiratory System                                                                                                       
     Pharyngitis        3            3           11           9          10           5           3            3           
     Sinusitis          1            4           5            2          6            4           2            3           
     Yawn               --           --          7            --         11           --          1            --          
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                                       
     Sweating           8            3           7            --         8            3           2            2           
     Rash               4            3           6            3          4            4           2            2           
  Urogenital System                                                                                                        
     Impotencea         2            --          --           --         7            --          1            --          
     Abnormal Ejaculationa       --           --          7            --         7            --          2            1           
              Table 3. Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Major Depressive Disorder, Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials 
 Note: Includes U.S. data for MDD, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-U.S. data for Panic Disorder clinical trials.-- = Incidence less than 1%.   
  
                                       Percentage of Patients Reporting Event    
                                       MDD, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Combined    
  Body System/Adverse Reaction            Fluoxetine (N = 2869)             Placebo (N = 1673)             
  Body as a Whole                                                                                          
     Headache                          21                                19                                
     Asthenia                          11                                6                                 
     Flu Syndrome                      5                                 4                                 
     Fever                             2                                 1                                 
  Cardiovascular System                                                                                    
     Vasodilatation                    2                                 1                                 
  Digestive System                                                                                         
     Nausea                            22                                9                                 
     Diarrhea                          11                                7                                 
     Anorexia                          10                                3                                 
     Dry Mouth                         9                                 6                                 
     Dyspepsia                         8                                 4                                 
     Constipation                      5                                 4                                 
     Flatulence                        3                                 2                                 
     Vomiting                          3                                 2                                 
  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                           
     Weight Loss                       2                                 1                                 
  Nervous System                                                                                           
     Insomnia                          19                                10                                
     Nervousness                       13                                8                                 
     Anxiety                           12                                6                                 
     Somnolence                        12                                5                                 
     Dizziness                         9                                 6                                 
     Tremor                            9                                 2                                 
     Libido Decreased                  4                                 1                                 
     Thinking Abnormal                 2                                 1                                 
  Respiratory System                                                                                       
     Yawn                              3                                 --                                
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                      
     Sweating                          7                                 3                                 
     Rash                              4                                 3                                 
     Pruritus                          3                                 2                                 
  Special Senses                                                                                           
     Abnormal Vision                   2                                 1                                 
           Associated with discontinuation in MDD, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder placebo-controlled clinical trials (excluding data from extensions of trials) -  Table 4    lists the adverse reactions associated with discontinuation of fluoxetine treatment (incidence at least twice that for placebo and at least 1% for fluoxetine in clinical trials collecting only a primary reaction associated with discontinuation) in MDD, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-U.S. Panic Disorder clinical trials.
 

 Table 4. Most Common Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation in Major Depressive Disorder, Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials 
 Note: Includes U.S. data for MDD, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-U.S. data for Panic Disorder clinical trials.   
  
  MDD, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Combined (N = 1533)    MDD(N = 392)         OCD (N = 266)        Bulimia (N = 450)    Panic Disorder (N = 425)    
  Anxiety (1%)            --                   Anxiety (2%)         --                   Anxiety (2%)           
  --                      --                   --                   Insomnia (2%)        --                     
  --                      Nervousness (1%)       --                   --                   Nervousness (1%)       
  --                      --                   Rash (1%)            --                   --                     
             Other adverse reactions in pediatric patients (children and adolescents)  - Adverse reactions were collected in 322 pediatric patients (180 fluoxetine-treated, 142 placebo-treated). The overall profile of adverse reactions was generally similar to that seen in adult studies, as shown in    Table 2    and    Table 3    . However, the following adverse reactions (excluding those which appear in the body or footnotes of    Table 2    and    Table 3    and those for which the COSTART terms were uninformative or misleading) were reported at an incidence of at least 2% for fluoxetine and greater than placebo: thirst, hyperkinesia, agitation, personality disorder, epistaxis, urinary frequency, and menorrhagia.
 

 The most common adverse reaction (incidence at least 1% for fluoxetine and greater than placebo) associated with discontinuation in 3 pediatric placebo-controlled trials (  N  = 418 randomized; 228 fluoxetine-treated; 190 placebo-treated) was mania/hypomania (1.8% for fluoxetine-treated, 0% for placebo-treated). In these clinical trials, only a primary reaction associated with discontinuation was collected.



   Male and female sexual dysfunction with SSRIs  - Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that SSRIs can cause such untoward sexual experiences. Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, however, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance, cited in product labeling, are likely to underestimate their actual incidence. In patients enrolled in U.S. MDD, OCD, and bulimia placebo-controlled clinical trials, decreased libido was the only sexual side effect reported by at least 2% of patients taking fluoxetine (4% fluoxetine, &lt;1% placebo). There have been spontaneous reports in women taking fluoxetine of orgasmic dysfunction, including anorgasmia.



 There are no adequate and well-controlled studies examining sexual dysfunction with fluoxetine treatment.



 Symptoms of sexual dysfunction occasionally persist after discontinuation of fluoxetine treatment.



 Priapism has been reported with all SSRIs.



 While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Fluoxetine-  Following is a list of adverse reactions reported by patients treated with fluoxetine in clinical trials. This listing is not intended to include reactions (1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, (2) for which a drug cause was remote, (3) which were so general as to be uninformative, (4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or (5) which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo.



 Reactions are classified by body system using the following definitions: frequent adverse reactions are those occurring in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



   Body as a Whole  -  Frequent:  chills;  Infrequent:  suicide attempt;  Rare:  acute abdominal syndrome, photosensitivity reaction.



   Cardiovascular System  -  Frequent:  palpitation;  Infrequent:  arrhythmia, hypotension  1  .



   Digestive System  -  Infrequent:  dysphagia, gastritis, gastroenteritis, melena, stomach ulcer;  Rare:  bloody diarrhea, duodenal ulcer, esophageal ulcer, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hematemesis, hepatitis, peptic ulcer, stomach ulcer hemorrhage.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  -  Infrequent:  ecchymosis;  Rare:  petechia, purpura.



   Nervous System  -  Frequent  : emotional lability;  Infrequent  : akathisia, ataxia, balance disorder  1  , bruxism  1  , buccoglossal syndrome, depersonalization, euphoria, hypertonia, libido increased, myoclonus, paranoid reaction;  Rare  : delusions.



   Respiratory System  -  Rare:  larynx edema.



   Skin and Appendages  -  Infrequent  : alopecia;  Rare  : purpuric rash.



   Special Senses  -  Frequent:  taste perversion;  Infrequent:  mydriasis.



   Urogenital System  -  Frequent  : micturition disorder;  Infrequent  :dysuria, gynecological bleeding  2  .



   1  MedDRA dictionary term from integrated database of placebo-controlled trials of 15,870 patients, of which 9,673 received fluoxetine.



   2  Group term that includes individual MedDRA terms: cervix hemorrhage uterine, dysfunctional uterine bleeding, genital hemorrhage, menometrorrhagia, menorrhagia, metrorrhagia, polymenorrhea, postmenopausal hemorrhage, uterine hemorrhage, vaginal hemorrhage. Adjusted for gender.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of fluoxetine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is difficult to reliably estimate their frequency or evaluate a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Voluntary reports of adverse reactions temporally associated with fluoxetine that have been received since market introduction and that may have no causal relationship with the drug include the following: aplastic anemia, atrial fibrillation  1  , cataract, cerebrovascular accident  1  , cholestatic jaundice, dyskinesia (including, for example, a case of buccal-lingual-masticatory syndrome with involuntary tongue protrusion reported to develop in a 77-year-old female after 5 weeks of fluoxetine therapy and which completely resolved over the next few months following drug discontinuation), eosinophilic pneumonia  1  , epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, erythema nodosum, exfoliative dermatitis, gynecomastia, heart arrest  1  , hepatic failure/necrosis, hyperprolactinemia, hypoglycemia, immune-related hemolytic anemia, kidney failure, memory impairment, movement disorders developing in patients with risk factors including drugs associated with such reactions and worsening of preexisting movement disorders, optic neuritis, pancreatitis  1  , pancytopenia, pulmonary embolism, pulmonary hypertension, QT prolongation, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, thrombocytopenia  1  , thrombocytopenic purpura, ventricular tachycardia (including torsade de pointes-type arrhythmias), vaginal bleeding, and violent behaviors  1  .



   1  These terms represent serious adverse events, but do not meet the definition for adverse drug reactions. They are included here because of their seriousness.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS

  WARNING:  SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders.  Anyone considering the use of fluoxetine tablets or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need.  Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.  Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide.  Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior.  Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber.  Fluoxetine is approved for use in pediatric patients with MDD and Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD) [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )].    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .  



   Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents,  



   and young adults taking antidepressants for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders (  5.1  ).  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk: Monitor for clinical worsening and suicidal thinking and behavior (  5.1  ) 
 *     Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-Like Reactions: Have been reported with fluoxetine. Discontinue fluoxetine and initiate supportive treatment (  5.2  ) 
 *     Activation of Mania/Hypomania: Screen for Bipolar Disorder and monitor for mania/hypomania (  5.4  ) 
 *     Abnormal Bleeding: May increase the risk of bleeding. Use with NSAIDs, aspirin, warfarin, or drugs that affect coagulation may potentiate the risk of gastrointestinal or other bleeding (  5.7  ,  7.6  ) 
 *     Angle Closure Glaucoma: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants (  5.8  ) 
 *     Hyponatremia: Has been reported with fluoxetine in association with syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone (SIADH) (  5.9  ) 
 *     Long Half-Life: Changes in dose will not be fully reflected in plasma for several weeks (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



  Patients with MDD, both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18 to 24) with MDD and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, OCD, or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug versus placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in   Table 1    .



 Table 1. Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated 
  Age Range                                  Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated    
                                             Increases Compared to Placebo                                
  &lt;18                                        14 additional cases                                          
  18-24                                      5 additional cases                                           
                                             Decreases Compared to Placebo                                
  25-64                                      1 fewer case                                                 
  &gt;=65                                       6 fewer cases                                                
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



 All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



 If the decision has been made to discontinue treatment, medication should be tapered, as rapidly as is feasible, but with recognition that abrupt discontinuation can be associated with certain symptoms [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.14  )  ].



 Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. Prescriptions for fluoxetine should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



 It should be noted that fluoxetine is approved in the pediatric population only for MDD and OCD.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-Like Reactions



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome or neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS)-like reactions have been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs alone, including fluoxetine treatment, but particularly with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (including triptans) with drugs which impair metabolism of serotonin (including MAOIs), or with antipsychotics or other dopamine antagonists. Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination) and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Serotonin syndrome, in its most severe form can resemble neuroleptic malignant syndrome, which includes hyperthermia, muscle rigidity, autonomic instability with possible rapid fluctuation of vital signs, and mental status changes. Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome or NMS-like signs and symptoms.



 The concomitant use of fluoxetine with MAOIs intended to treat depression is contraindicated [ see Contraindications (  4  ) and Drug Interactions (  7.1  )  ].



 If concomitant treatment of fluoxetine with a 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor agonist (triptan) is clinically warranted, careful observation of the patient is advised, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases [ see Drug Interactions (  7.4  )  ].



 The concomitant use of fluoxetine with serotonin precursors (such as tryptophan) is not recommended [ see Drug Interactions (  7.3  )  ].



 Treatment with fluoxetine and any concomitant serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents, including antipsychotics, should be discontinued immediately if the above reactions occur, and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Allergic Reactions and Rash



  In U.S. fluoxetine clinical trials, 7% of 10,782 patients developed various types of rashes and/or urticaria. Among the cases of rash and/or urticaria reported in premarketing clinical trials, almost a third were withdrawn from treatment because of the rash and/or systemic signs or symptoms associated with the rash. Clinical findings reported in association with rash include fever, leukocytosis, arthralgias, edema, carpal tunnel syndrome, respiratory distress, lymphadenopathy, proteinuria, and mild transaminase elevation. Most patients improved promptly with discontinuation of fluoxetine and/or adjunctive treatment with antihistamines or steroids, and all patients experiencing these reactions were reported to recover completely.



 In premarketing clinical trials, 2 patients are known to have developed a serious cutaneous systemic illness. In neither patient was there an unequivocal diagnosis, but one was considered to have a leukocytoclastic vasculitis, and the other, a severe desquamating syndrome that was considered variously to be a vasculitis or erythema multiforme. Other patients have had systemic syndromes suggestive of serum sickness.



 Since the introduction of fluoxetine, systemic reactions, possibly related to vasculitis and including lupus-like syndrome, have developed in patients with rash. Although these reactions are rare, they may be serious, involving the lung, kidney, or liver. Death has been reported to occur in association with these systemic reactions.



 Anaphylactoid reactions, including bronchospasm, angioedema, laryngospasm, and urticaria alone and in combination, have been reported.



 Pulmonary reactions, including inflammatory processes of varying histopathology and/or fibrosis, have been reported rarely. These reactions have occurred with dyspnea as the only preceding symptom.



 Whether these systemic reactions and rash have a common underlying cause or are due to different etiologies or pathogenic processes is not known. Furthermore, a specific underlying immunologic basis for these reactions has not been identified. Upon the appearance of rash or of other possibly allergic phenomena for which an alternative etiology cannot be identified, fluoxetine should be discontinued.



    5.4 Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder and Monitoring for Mania/Hypomania



  A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of Bipolar Disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/ manic episode in patients at risk for Bipolar Disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described for clinical worsening and suicide risk represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for Bipolar Disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, Bipolar Disorder, and depression. It should be noted that fluoxetine monotherapy is not approved for use in treating Bipolar I Disorder.



 In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for MDD, mania/hypomania was reported in 0.1% of patients treated with fluoxetine and 0.1% of patients treated with placebo. Activation of mania/hypomania has also been reported in a small proportion of patients with Major Affective Disorder treated with other marketed drugs effective in the treatment of MDD [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )  ].



 In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for OCD, mania/hypomania was reported in 0.8% of patients treated with fluoxetine and no patients treated with placebo. No patients reported mania/hypomania in U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for bulimia. In all U.S. fluoxetine clinical trials, 0.7% of 10,782 patients reported mania/hypomania [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )  ].



    5.5 Seizures



  In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for MDD, convulsions (or reactions described as possibly having been seizures) were reported in 0.1% of patients treated with fluoxetine and 0.2% of patients treated with placebo. No patients reported convulsions in U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for either OCD or bulimia. In all U.S. fluoxetine clinical trials, 0.2% of 10,782 patients reported convulsions. The percentage appears to be similar to that associated with other marketed drugs effective in the treatment of MDD. Fluoxetine should be introduced with care in patients with a history of seizures. There have been rare reports of prolonged seizures in patients on fluoxetine receiving ECT treatment.



    5.6 Altered Appetite and Weight



  Significant weight loss, especially in underweight depressed or bulimic patients, may be an undesirable result of treatment with fluoxetine.



 In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for MDD, 11% of patients treated with fluoxetine and 2% of patients treated with placebo reported anorexia (decreased appetite). Weight loss was reported in 1.4% of patients treated with fluoxetine and in 0.5% of patients treated with placebo. However, only rarely have patients discontinued treatment with fluoxetine because of anorexia or weight loss [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )  ].



 In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for OCD, 17% of patients treated with fluoxetine and 10% of patients treated with placebo reported anorexia (decreased appetite). One patient discontinued treatment with fluoxetine because of anorexia [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )  ].



 In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for Bulimia Nervosa, 8% of patients treated with fluoxetine 60 mg and 4% of patients treated with placebo reported anorexia (decreased appetite). Patients treated with fluoxetine 60 mg on average lost 0.45 kg compared with a gain of 0.16 kg by patients treated with placebo in the 16 week double-blind trial. Weight change should be monitored during therapy.



    5.7 Abnormal Bleeding



  SNRIs and SSRIs, including fluoxetine, may increase the risk of bleeding reactions. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, warfarin, and other anti-coagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding reactions related to SNRIs and SSRIs use have ranged from ecchymoses, hematomas, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages. Patients should be cautioned about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of fluoxetine and NSAIDs, aspirin, warfarin, or other drugs that affect coagulation [ see Drug Interactions (  7.6  )  ].



     5.8 Angle Closure Glaucoma  



   The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including fluoxetine may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.  



    5.9 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia has been reported during treatment with SNRIs and SSRIs, including fluoxetine. In many cases, this hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported and appeared to be reversible when fluoxetine was discontinued. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with SNRIs and SSRIs. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume-depleted may be at greater risk [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )  ]. Discontinuation of fluoxetine should be considered in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia and appropriate medical intervention should be instituted.



 Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which may lead to falls. More severe and/or acute cases have been associated with hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.10 Anxiety and Insomnia



  In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for MDD, 12% to 16% of patients treated with fluoxetine and 7% to 9% of patients treated with placebo reported anxiety, nervousness, or insomnia.



 In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for OCD, insomnia was reported in 28% of patients treated with fluoxetine and in 22% of patients treated with placebo. Anxiety was reported in 14% of patients treated with fluoxetine and in 7% of patients treated with placebo.



 In U.S. placebo-controlled clinical trials for Bulimia Nervosa, insomnia was reported in 33% of patients treated with fluoxetine 60 mg, and 13% of patients treated with placebo. Anxiety and nervousness were reported, respectively, in 15% and 11% of patients treated with fluoxetine 60 mg and in 9% and 5% of patients treated with placebo.



 Among the most common adverse reactions associated with discontinuation (incidence at least twice that for placebo and at least 1% for fluoxetine in clinical trials collecting only a primary reaction associated with discontinuation) in U.S. placebo-controlled fluoxetine clinical trials were anxiety (2% in OCD), insomnia (1% in combined indications and 2% in bulimia), and nervousness (1% in MDD) [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ].



    5.11 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with fluoxetine in patients with concomitant systemic illness is limited. Caution is advisable in using fluoxetine in patients with diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses.



  Cardiovascular  - Fluoxetine has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were systematically excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarket testing. However, the electrocardiograms of 312 patients who received fluoxetine in double-blind trials were retrospectively evaluated; no conduction abnormalities that resulted in heart block were observed. The mean heart rate was reduced by approximately 3 beats/min.



  Glycemic Control  - In patients with diabetes, fluoxetine may alter glycemic control. Hypoglycemia has occurred during therapy with fluoxetine, and hyperglycemia has developed following discontinuation of the drug. As is true with many other types of medication when taken concurrently by patients with diabetes, insulin and/or oral hypoglycemic, dosage may need to be adjusted when therapy with fluoxetine is instituted or discontinued.



    5.12 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  As with any CNS-active drug, fluoxetine has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that the drug treatment does not affect them adversely.



    5.13 Long Elimination Half-Life



  Because of the long elimination half-lives of the parent drug and its major active metabolite, changes in dose will not be fully reflected in plasma for several weeks, affecting both strategies for titration to final dose and withdrawal from treatment. This is of potential consequence when drug discontinuation is required or when drugs are prescribed that might interact with fluoxetine and norfluoxetine following the discontinuation of fluoxetine [ see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )  ].



    5.14 Discontinuation of Treatment



  During marketing of fluoxetine, SNRIs, and SSRIs, there have been spontaneous reports of adverse reactions occurring upon discontinuation of these drugs, particularly when abrupt, including the following: dysphoric mood, irritability, agitation, dizziness, sensory disturbances (e.g., paresthesias such as electric shock sensations), anxiety, confusion, headache, lethargy, emotional lability, insomnia, and hypomania. While these reactions are generally self-limiting, there have been reports of serious discontinuation symptoms. Patients should be monitored for these symptoms when discontinuing treatment with fluoxetine. A gradual reduction in the dose rather than abrupt cessation is recommended whenever possible. If intolerable symptoms occur following a decrease in the dose or upon discontinuation of treatment, then resuming the previously prescribed dose may be considered. Subsequently, the physician may continue decreasing the dose but at a more gradual rate. Plasma fluoxetine and norfluoxetine concentration decrease gradually at the conclusion of therapy which may minimize the risk of discontinuation symptoms with this drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
