<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fluticasone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Clinical Trial Experience:  In 2 multicenter vehicle-controlled clinical trials of once-daily application of Fluticasone Propionate Lotion by 196 adult and 242 pediatric patients, the total incidence of adverse reactions considered drug related by investigators was approximately 4%. Events were local cutaneous events, usually mild and self-limiting, and consisted primarily of burning/stinging (2%). All other drug-related events occurred with an incidence of less than 1%, and inclusively were contact dermatitis, exacerbation of atopic dermatitis, folliculitis of legs, pruritus, pustules on arm, rash, and skin infection.



 The incidence of drug-related events on drug compared to vehicle (4% and 5%, respectively) was similar. The incidence of drug-related events between study populations of 242 pediatric patients (age 3 months to &lt; 17 years) and 196 adult patients (17 years or older) (4% and 5%, respectively) was also similar.



 In an open-label study of 44 pediatric patients applying Fluticasone Propionate Lotion to at least 35% of body surface area twice daily for 3 or 4 weeks, the overall incidence of drug-related adverse events was 14%. Events were local, cutaneous, and inclusively were dry skin (7%), stinging at application site (5%), and excoriation (2%).



 Table 2: Drug Related Adverse Events from Controlled Clinical Trials (n=438) 
 Adverse Events                            Fluticasone Propionate Lotion        Vehicle                   
                                           N=221                                N=217                     
 Burning/Stinging skin                     4 (2%)                                    3 (1%)               
 Contact Dermatitis                        0                                         1 (&lt;1%)              
 Exacerbation of Atopic dermatitis         0                                         1 (&lt;1%)              
 Folliculitis of legs                      2 (&lt;1%)                                   0                    
 Irritant Contact Dermatitis               0                                         1 (&lt;1%)              
 Pruritus                                  1 (&lt;1%)                                   1 (&lt;1%)              
 Pustules on Arms                          1 (&lt;1%)                                   0                    
 Rash                                      1 (&lt;1%)                                   2 (&lt;1%)              
 Skin Infection                            0                                         3 (1%)               
        Table 3: Drug Related Adverse Events From Pediatric Open Label Trial (n=44) 
 Adverse Events                         Fluticasone Propionate Lotion Twice Daily                        
 Dry skin at multiple sites             3 (7%)                                                           
 Stinging at Application Sites          2 (5%)                                                           
 Excoriation                            1 (2%)                                                           
        The table below summarizes all adverse events by body system that occurred in at least 1% of patients in either the drug or vehicle group in controlled clinical trials.
 

 Table 4: Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;= 1% of Patients from Either Arm from Controlled Clinical Trials (n=438) 
   Body System                      Fluticasone Propionate Lotion           Vehicle Lotion                         
                                    N = 221                        N = 217                                
 Any Adverse Event                77 (35%)                       82 (38%)                                 
 Skin                                                                                                     
      Burning and Stinging        4 (2%)                         3 (1%)                                   
      Pruritus                    3 (1%)                         5 (2%)                                   
      Rash                        2 (&lt;1%)                        3 (1%)                                   
      Skin Infection              0                              3 (1%)                                   
 Ear, Nose, Throat                                                                                        
      Common Cold                 9 (4%)                         5 (2%)                                   
      Ear Infection               3 (1%)                         3 (1%)                                   
      Nasal Sinus Infection       2 (&lt;1%)                        4 (2%)                                   
      Rhinitis                    1 (&lt;1%)                        3 (1%)                                   
      Upper RespiratoryTract Infection       6 (3%)                         7 (3%)                                   
 Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
      Normal Tooth Eruption       2 (&lt; 1%)                       3 (1%)                                   
      Diarrhea                    3 (1%)                         0                                        
      Vomiting                    3 (1%)                         2 (&lt;1%)                                  
 Lower Respiratory                                                                                        
      Cough                       7 (3%)                         6 (3%)                                   
      Influenza                   5 (2%)                         0                                        
      Wheeze                      0                              3 (1%)                                   
 Neurology                                                                                                
      Headache                    4 (2%)                         5 (2%)                                   
 Non-Site Specific                                                                                        
      Fever                       8 (4%)                         8 (4%)                                   
      Seasonal Allergy            2 (&lt;1%)                        3 (1%)                                   
         During the clinical trials, eczema herpeticum occurred in a 33-year-old male patient treated with Fluticasone Propionate Lotion. Additionally, a 4-month-old patient treated with Fluticasone Propionate Lotion in the open-label trial had marked elevations of the hepatic enzymes AST and ALT.
 

     Post Marketing Experience:  Systemic adverse events with Fluticasone Propionate Cream and Fluticasone Propionate Ointment have included: immunosuppression/Pneumocystis carinii; pneumonia/leukopenia/thrombocytopenia; hyperglycemia/glycosuria; Cushing syndrome; generalized body edema/blurred vision; and acute urticarial reaction (edema, urticaria, pruritus, and throat swelling).



 The following localized adverse reactions have been reported during post approval use of Fluticasone Propionate Lotion : erythema, edema/swelling, bleeding, and a reported lack of efficacy.



 Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
