<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fluvirin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most frequently reported adverse reactions are mild hypersensitivity reactions (such as rash), local reactions at the injection site, and influenza-like symptoms. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS contact Seqirus at 1-855-358-8966 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 and    www.vaers.hhs.gov    .  



 

  6.1 Overall Adverse Reaction Profile

  Serious allergic reactions, including anaphylactic shock, have been observed in individuals receiving FLUVIRIN  (r)  during postmarketing surveillance.



   6.2 Clinical Trial Experience

  Adverse event information from clinical trials provides a basis for identifying adverse events that appear to be related to vaccine use and for approximating the rates of these events. However, because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect rates observed in clinical practice.



     Adult and Geriatric Subjects  



 Safety data were collected in a total of 2768 adult and geriatric subjects (18 years of age and older) who have received FLUVIRIN  (r)  in 29 clinical studies since 1982.



 In 9 clinical studies since 1997, among 1261 recipients of FLUVIRIN  (r)  , 745 (59%) were women; 1211 (96%) were White, 23 (2%) Asian, 15 (1%) Black and 12 (1%) other; 370 (29%) of subjects were elderly (&gt;=65 years of age). All studies have been conducted in the UK, apart from a study run in the US in 2005-2006 where FLUVIRIN  (r)  was used as a comparator for an unlicensed vaccine.



 After vaccination, the subjects were observed for 30 minutes for hypersensitivity or other immediate reactions. Subjects were instructed to complete a diary card for three days following immunization (i.e. Day 1 to 4) to collect local and systemic reactions (see  Tables 2  and  3  ). All local and systemic adverse events were considered to be at least possibly related to the vaccine. Local and systemic reactions mostly began between day 1 and day 2. The overall adverse events reported in clinical trials since 1998 in at least 5% of the subjects are summarized in  Table 4  .



 TABLE 2 Solicited Adverse Events in the First 72-96 Hours After Administration of FLUVIRIN(r) in Adult (18-64 years of age) and Geriatric (&gt;=65 years of age) Subjects. 
                               1998-1999      *S        1999-2000      *S        2000-2001      *S       
   18-64 yrs                   &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs     
   N = 66                      N = 44        N = 76        N = 34        N = 75        N = 35       
   Local Adverse Events                                                                                           
      Pain                   16 (24%)      4 (9%)        16 (21%)      -             9 (12%)       -              
      Mass                   7 (11%)       1 (2%)        4 (5%)        -             8 (11%)       1 (3%)         
      Inflammation           5 (8%)        2 (5%)        6 (8%)        -             7 (9%)        1 (3%)         
      Ecchymosis             4 (6%)        1 (2%)        3 (4%)        1 (3%)        4 (5%)        -              
      Edema                  2 (3%)        1 (2%)        1 (1%)        2 (6%)        3 (4%)        1 (3%)         
      Reaction               2 (3%)        -             2 (3%)        -             4 (5%)        1 (3%)         
      Hemorrhage             -             -             1 (1%)        -             -             -              
   Systemic Adverse Events                                                                                         
      Headache               7 (11%)       1 (2%)        17 (22%)      3 (9%)        4 (5%)        -              
      Fatigue                3 (5%)        2 (5%)        4 (5%)        1 (3%)        3 (4%)        -              
      Malaise                2 (3%)        1 (2%)        2 (3%)        1 (3%)        1 (1%)        -              
 Myalgia                     1 (2%)        -             2 (3%)        -             -             -              
      Fever                  1 (2%)        -             1 (1%)        -             -             -              
      Arthralgia             -             1 (2%)        -             1 (3%)        -             -              
      Sweating               -             -             3 (4%)        -             1 (1%)        1 (3%)         
           
  Results reported to the nearest whole percent; Fever defined as &gt;38 degrees C    
  - not reported              
  * Solicited adverse events in the first 72 hours after administration of FLUVIRIN(r)    
  S Solicited adverse events reported by COSTART preferred term    
  ^ Solicited adverse events reported by MEDDRA preferred term    
  
                               2001-2002      *^        2002-2003      *^        2004-2005*      ^       
   18-64 yrs                   &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs     
   N = 75                      N = 35        N = 107       N = 88        N = 74        N = 61       
   Local Adverse Events                                                                                           
      Pain                   12 (16%)      1 (3%)        14 (13%)      7 (8%)        15 (20%)      9 (15%)        
      Mass                   4 (5%)        1 (3%)        -             -             -             -              
      Ecchymosis             2 (3%)        -             3 (3%)        3 (3%)        2 (3%)        1 (2%)         
      Edema                  2 (3%)        1 (3%)        6 (6%)        2 (2%)        -             -              
      Erythema               5 (7%)        -             11 (10%)      5 (6%)        16 (22%)      5 (8%)         
      Swelling               -             -             -             -             11 (15%)      4 (7%)         
      Reaction               -             -             2 (2%)        -             -             -              
      Induration             -             -             14 (13%)      3 (3%)        11 (15%)      1 (2%)         
      Pruritus               -             -             1 (1%)        -             -             -              
   Systemic Adverse Events                                                                                         
      Headache               8 (11%)       1 (3%)        12 (11%)      9 (10%)       14 (19%)      3 (5%)         
      Fatigue                1 (1%)        1 (3%)        -             -             5 (7%)        2 (3%)         
      Malaise                3 (4%)        -             3 (3%)        4 (5%)        1 (1%)        1 (2%)         
      Myalgia                3 (4%)        -             5 (5%)        3 (3%)        8 (11%)       1 (2%)         
      Fever                  -             -             -             1 (1%)        -             -              
      Arthralgia             -             -             2 (2%)        -             1 (1%)        -              
      Sweating               3 (4%)        1 (3%)        -             2 (2%)        -             -              
      Shivering              -             -             -             1 (1%)        -             -              
            TABLE 3 Solicited Adverse Events in the First 72 Hours After Administration of FLUVIRIN(r) in Adult Subjects (18-49 years of age). 
  Results reported to the nearest whole percent         
  - not reported                                        
  
                                                         2005-2006 US Trial                              
   FLUVIRIN      (r)                                    
   N = 304                                              
   Local Adverse Events                                                                                  
      Pain                                             168 (55%)                                         
      Erythema                                         48 (16%)                                          
      Ecchymosis                                       22 (7%)                                           
      Induration                                       19 (6%)                                           
      Swelling                                         16 (5%)                                           
   Systemic Adverse Events                                                                               
      Headache                                         91 (30%)                                          
      Myalgia                                          64 (21%)                                          
      Malaise                                          58 (19%)                                          
      Fatigue                                          56 (18%)                                          
      Sore throat                                      23 (8%)                                           
      Chills                                           22 (7%)                                           
      Nausea                                           21 (7%)                                           
      Arthralgia                                       20 (7%)                                           
      Sweating                                         17 (6%)                                           
      Cough                                            18 (6%)                                           
      Wheezing                                         4 (1%)                                            
      Chest tightness                                  4 (1%)                                            
      Other difficulties breathing                     3 (1%)                                            
      Facial edema                                     -                                                 
       TABLE 4 Adverse Events Reported by at least 5% of Subjects in Clinical Trials since 1998 
                               1998-1999      S        1999-2000      S        2000-2001      S       
   18-64 yrs                   &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs     
   N = 66                      N = 44        N = 76        N = 34        N = 75        N = 35       
   Adverse Events                                                                                                 
 Fatigue                     8 (12%)       2 (5%)        8 (11%)       2 (6%)        5 (7%)        -              
 Back pain                   4 (6%)        3 (7%)        -             -             -             -              
 Cough increased             2 (3%)        2 (5%)        -             -             -             -              
 Ecchymosis                  4 (6%)        1 (2%)        4 (5%)        1 (3%)        5 (7%)        -              
 Fever                       3 (5%)        -             -             -             -             -              
 Headache                    12 (18%)      5 (11%)       22 (29%)      5 (15%)       14 (19%)      2 (6%)         
 Infection                   3 (5%)        2 (5%)        -             -             -             -              
 Malaise                     4 (6%)        4 (9%)        4 (5%)        1 (3%)        -             -              
 Migraine                    4 (6%)        1 (2%)        -             -             -             -              
 Myalgia                     4 (6%)        1 (2%)        -             -             -             -              
 Sweating                    5 (8%)        1 (2%)        -             -             -             -              
 Rhinitis                    3 (5%)        1 (2%)        -             -             5 (7%)        2 (6%)         
 Pharingitis                 6 (9%)        1 (2%)        10 (13%)      -             6 (8%)        -              
 Arthralgia                  -             -             -             2 (6%)        -             -              
 Injection site pain         16 (24%)      4 (9%)        16 (21%)      -             9 (12%)       -              
 Injection site ecchymosis   4 (6%)        1 (2%)        -             -             4 (5%)        -              
 Injection site mass         7 (11%)       1 (2%)        4 (5%)        -             8 (11%)       1 (3%)         
 Injection site edema        -             -             1 (1%)        2 (6%)        -             -              
 Injection site inflammation  5 (8%)        2 (5%)        6 (8%)        -             7 (9%)        1 (3%)         
 Injection site reaction     -             -             -             -             4 (5%)        1 (3%)         
           
  Results reported to the nearest whole percent; Fever defined as &gt;38 degrees C    
  - not reaching the cut-off of 5%    
  S Solicited adverse events reported by COSTART preferred term    
  ^ Solicited adverse events reported by MEDDRA preferred term    
  
                               2001-2002      ^        2002-2003      ^        2004-2005      ^       
   18-64 yrs                   &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs      18-64 yrs      &gt;= 65 yrs     
   N = 75                      N = 35        N = 107       N = 88        N = 74        N = 61       
   Adverse Events                                                                                                 
 Fatigue                     5 (7%)        4 (11%)       11 (10%)      8 (9%)        4 (5%)        2 (3%)         
 Hypertension                -             -             1 (1%)        4 (5%)        -             -              
 Rinorrhea                   -             -             2 (2%)        5 (6%)        -             -              
 Headache                    20 (27%)      2 (6%)        35 (33%)      18 (20%)      12 (16%)      1 (2%)         
 Malaise                     6 (8%)        1 (3%)        13 (12%)      8 (9%)        -             -              
 Myalgia                     4 (5%)        1 (3%)        10 (9%)       4 (5%)        -             -              
 Sweating                    3 (4%)        3 (9%)        2 (2%)        5 (6%)        -             -              
 Rhinitis                    4 (5%)        -             -             -             -             -              
 Pharingitis                 -             -             -             -             6 (8%)        -              
 Arthralgia                  -             -             5 (5%)        4 (5%)        -             -              
 Sore throat                 4 (5%)        1 (3%)        5 (5%)        4 (5%)        -             -              
 Injection site pain         13 (17%)      3 (9%)        14 (13%)      7 (8%)        6 (8%)        2 (3%)         
 Injection site ecchymosis   4 (5%)        1 (3%)        4 (4%)        4 (5%)        -             -              
 Injection site erythema     5 (7%)        2 (6%)        11 (10%)      5 (6%)        4 (5%)        -              
 Injection site mass         4 (5%)        1 (3%)        -             -             -             -              
 Injection site edema        -             -             6 (6%)        2 (2%)        4 (5%)        1 (2%)         
 Injection site induration   -             -             14 (13%)      3 (3%)        7 (9%)        -              
               Adults (18 to 64 years of age)  
 

 In adult subjects, solicited local adverse events occurred with similar frequency in all trials. The most common solicited adverse events occurring in the first 96 hours after administration (  Tables 2  and  3  ) were associated with the injection site (such as pain, erythema, mass, induration and swelling) but were generally mild/moderate and transient. The most common solicited systemic adverse events were headache and myalgia.



 The most common overall events in adult subjects (18-64 years of age) were headache, fatigue, injection site reactions (pain, mass, erythema, and induration) and malaise (  Table 4  ).



     Geriatric Subjects (65 years of age and older)  



 In geriatric subjects, solicited local and systemic adverse events occurred less frequently than in adult subjects. The most common solicited local and systemic adverse events were injection site pain, and headache (  Tables 2  and  3  ). All were considered mild/moderate and were transient.



 The most common overall events in elderly subjects (&gt;=65 years of age) were headache and fatigue.



 Only 11 serious adverse events in adult and geriatric subjects (18 years and older) have been reported to date from all the trials performed. These serious adverse events were a minor stroke experienced by a 67 year old subject 14 days after vaccination (1990), death of an 82 year old subject 35 days after vaccination (1990) in very early studies; death of a 72 year old subject 19 days after vaccination (1998-1999), a hospitalization for hemorrhoidectomy of a 38 year old male subject (1999-2000), a severe respiratory tract infection experienced by a 74 year old subject 12 days after vaccination (2002-2003), a planned transurethral resection of the prostate in a subject with prior history of prostatism (2004-2005), two cases of influenza (2005-2006), a drug overdose (2005-2006), cholelithiasis (2005-2006) and a nasal septal operation (2005-2006). None of these events were considered causally related to vaccination.



     Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Subjects  



 In 1987 a clinical study was carried out in 38 'at risk' children aged between 4 and 12 years (17 females and 21 males). To record the safety of FLUVIRIN  (r)  , participants recorded their symptoms on a diary card during the three days after vaccination and noted any further symptoms they thought were attributable to the vaccine. The only reactions recorded were tenderness at the site of vaccination in 21% of the participants on day 1, which was still present in 16% on day 2 and 5% on day 3. In one child, the tenderness was also accompanied by redness at the site of injection for two days. The reactions were not age-dependent and there was no bias towards the younger children.



 Three clinical studies were carried out between 1995 and 2004 in a total of 520 pediatric subjects (age range 6 - 47 months). Of these, 285 healthy subjects plus 41 'at risk' subjects received FLUVIRIN  (r)  . No serious adverse events were reported.



 FLUVIRIN  (r)  should only be used for the immunization of persons aged 4 years and over.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of FLUVIRIN  (r)  . Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure. Adverse events described here are included because: a) they represent reactions which are known to occur following immunizations generally or influenza immunizations specifically; b) they are potentially serious; or c) the frequency of reporting.



 *   Body as a whole : Local injection site reactions (including pain, pain limiting limb movement, redness, swelling, warmth, ecchymosis, induration), hot flashes/flushes; chills; fever; malaise; shivering; fatigue; asthenia; facial edema. 
 *   Immune system disorders: Hypersensitivity reactions (including throat and/or mouth edema). In rare cases, hypersensitivity reactions have lead to anaphylactic shock and death. 
 *   Cardiovascular disorders: Vasculitis (in rare cases with transient renal involvement), presyncope, syncope shortly after vaccination. 
 *   Digestive disorders: Diarrhea; nausea; vomiting; abdominal pain. 
 *   Blood and lymphatic disorders: Local lymphadenopathy; thrombocytopenia (some very rare cases were severe with platelet counts less than 5,000 per mm  3  ). 
 *   Metabolic and nutritional disorders: Loss of appetite. 
 *   Musculoskeletal : Arthralgia; myalgia; myasthenia. 
 *   Nervous system disorders: Headache; dizziness; neuralgia; paraesthesia; confusion; febrile convulsions; Guillain-Barre Syndrome; myelitis (including encephalomyelitis and transverse myelitis); neuropathy (including neuritis); paralysis (including Bell's Palsy). 
 *   Respiratory disorders: Dyspnea; chest pain; cough; pharyngitis; rhinitis. 
 *   Skin and appendages : Stevens-Johnson syndrome; sweating; pruritus; urticaria; rash (including non-specific, maculopapular, and vesiculobulbous). 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions: Injection site cellulitis-like reaction (very rare cases of swelling, pain, and redness were large and extended to the entire arm) 
      6.4 Other Adverse Reactions Associated with Influenza Vaccination
   Anaphylaxis has been reported after administration of FLUVIRIN  (r)  . Although FLUVIRIN  (r)  contains only a limited quantity of egg protein, this protein can induce immediate hypersensitivity reactions among persons who have severe egg allergy. Allergic reactions include hives, angioedema, allergic asthma, and systemic anaphylaxis [see CONTRAINDICATIONS (  4  )].



 The 1976 swine influenza vaccine was associated with an increased frequency of Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS). Evidence for a causal relation of GBS with subsequent vaccines prepared from other influenza viruses is unclear. If influenza vaccine does pose a risk, it is probably slightly more than 1 additional case/1 million persons vaccinated.



 Neurological disorders temporally associated with influenza vaccination such as encephalopathy, optic neuritis/neuropathy, partial facial paralysis, and brachial plexus neuropathy have been reported.



 Microscopic polyangiitis (vasculitis) has been reported temporally associated with influenza vaccination.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLUVIRIN  (r)  should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Immunocompromised persons may have a reduced immune response to FLUVIRIN  (r)  . (  5.2  ) 
 *  The tip caps of the FLUVIRIN  (r)  prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals. 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of prior influenza vaccine, the decision to give FLUVIRIN  (r)  should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks.



    5.2 Altered Immunocompetence



  If FLUVIRIN  (r)  is administered to immunocompromised persons, including individuals receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained.



    5.3 Preventing and Managing Allergic Reactions



  Prior to administration of any dose of FLUVIRIN  (r)  , the healthcare provider should review the patient's prior immunization history for possible adverse events, to determine the existence of any contraindication to immunization with FLUVIRIN  (r)  and to allow an assessment of benefits and risks. Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine.



 The tip caps of the FLUVIRIN  (r)  prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals.



    5.4 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with FLUVIRIN  (r)  may not protect all individuals.



    5.5 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including Fluvirin. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope by maintaining a supine or Trendelenburg position.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
