<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="focalinxr" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6          ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  Focalin XR was administered to 46 children and 7 adolescents with ADHD for up to 7 weeks and 206 adults with ADHD in clinical studies. During the clinical studies, 101 adult patients were treated for at least 6 months.



 Adverse events during exposure were obtained primarily by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of events into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and listings that follow, MedDRA terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events. The stated frequencies of adverse events represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (at least 5% and twice the incidence among placebo-treated patients) are dyspepsia, decreased appetite, headache, and anxiety for pediatric patients and dry mouth, dyspepsia, headache, and anxiety for adult patients (6).



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6.1    Adverse Events Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment         in Acute Clinical Studies with Focalin XR    -    Children  

  Overall, 50 of 684 children treated with Focalin immediate-release formulation (7.3%) experienced an adverse event that resulted in discontinuation. The most common reasons for discontinuation were twitching (described as motor or vocal tics), anorexia, insomnia, and tachycardia (approximately 1% each). None of the 53 Focalin XR-treated pediatric patients discontinued treatment due to adverse events in the 7-week placebo-controlled study.



     6.2    Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 5% or    M    ore    A    mong Focalin XR-    T    reated    P    atients-Children  

  Table 1 enumerates treatment-emergent adverse events for the placebo-controlled, parallel-group study in children and adolescents with ADHD at flexible Focalin XR doses of 5-30 mg/day. The table includes only those events that occurred in 5% or more of patients treated with Focalin XR and for which the incidence in patients treated with Focalin XR was at least twice the incidence in placebo-treated patients. The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 1.Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events1 Occurring During Double-Blind Treatment-Pediatric Patients 
                    Focalin XR    N=53      Placebo    N=47     
   No. of Patients with AEs                                       
       Total      76%              57%               
        Primary System Organ Class/         Adverse Event Preferred Term                                       
   Gastrointestinal Disorders    38%              19%               
       Dyspepsia  8%               4%                
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders    34%              11%               
       Decreased Appetite  30%              9%                
   Nervous System Disorders    30%              13%               
       Headache   25%              11%               
   Psychiatric Disorders    26%              15%               
       Anxiety    6%               0%                
           1  Events, regardless of causality, for which the incidence for patients treated with Focalin XR was at least 5% and twice the incidence among placebo-treated patients. Incidence has been rounded to the nearest whole number.
 

 Table 2 below enumerates the incidence of dose-related adverse events that occurred during a fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo controlled trial of Focalin XR up to 30mg/day versus placebo in children and adolescents with ADHD.



 Table 2: Dose-related Adverse Events from a Fixed-dose Study of Double-Blind Treatment in Pediatric Patients By Organ-System and Preferred Term 
   ADVERSE EVENT      F    ocalin         XR    10         mg/d    N=64      F    ocalin         XR    20         mg/d    N=60      F    ocalin         XR    30         mg/d    N=58      P    lacebo    N=63     
   Gastrointestinal disorders    22%              23%              29%              24%               
 Vomiting         2%               8%               9%               0                 
   Metabolism and nutritional disorders    16%              17%              22%              5%                
 Anorexia         5%               5%               7%               0                 
   Psychiatric Disorders    19%              20%              38%              8%                
 Insomnia         5%               8%               17%              3%                
 Depression       0                0                3%               0                 
 Mood swings      0                0                3%               2%                
   Other Adverse events                                                                         
 Irritability     0                2%               5%               0                 
 Nasal Congestion  0                0                5%               0                 
 Pruritus         0                0                3%               0                 
               6.3    Adverse Events Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment         in Clinical Studies with Focalin XR    -    Adults  
   In the adult placebo-controlled study, 10.7% of the Focalin XR-treated patients and 7.5% of the placebo-treated patients discontinued for adverse events. Among Focalin XR-treated patients, insomnia (1.8%, n=3), feeling jittery (1.8%, n=3), anorexia (1.2%, n=2), and anxiety (1.2%, n=2) were the reasons for discontinuation reported by more than 1 patient.



     6.4    Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 5% or More Among Focalin XR-Treated Patients    -Adults  

  Table 3 enumerates treatment-emergent adverse events for the placebo-controlled, parallel-group study in adults with ADHD at fixed Focalin XR doses of 20, 30, and 40 mg/day. The table includes only those events that occurred in 5% or more of patients in a Focalin XR dose group and for which the incidences in patients treated with Focalin XR appeared to increase with dose. The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 3. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events1 Occurring During Double-Blind Treatment-Adults 
                    Focalin XR    20 mg    N=57      Focalin XR    30 mg    N=54      Focalin XR    40 mg    N=54      Placebo    N=53     
   No. of Patients with AEs                                                                         
       Total      84%              94%              85%              68%               
   Primary System Organ Class/    Adverse Event Preferred Term                                                                         
   Gastrointestinal Disorders    28%              32%              44%              19%               
       Dry Mouth  7%               20%              20%              4%                
       Dyspepsia  5%               9%               9%               2%                
   Nervous System Disorders    37%              39%              50%              28%               
       Headache   26%              30%              39%              19%               
   Psychiatric Disorders    40%              43%              46%              30%               
       Anxiety    5%               11%              11%              2%                
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    16%              9%               15%              8%                
       Pharyngolaryngeal Pain  4%               4%               7%               2%                
             1  Events, regardless of causality, for which the incidence was at least 5% in a Focalin XR group and which appeared to increase with randomized dose. Incidence has been rounded to the nearest whole number.
 

 Two other adverse reactions occurring in clinical trials with Focalin XR at a frequency greater than placebo, but which were not dose related were: Feeling jittery (12% and 2%, respectively) and Dizziness (6% and 2%, respectively).



 Table 4 summarizes changes in vital signs and weight that were recorded in the adult study (N=218) of Focalin XR in the treatment of ADHD.



 Table 4. Changes (Mean +/- SD) in Vital Signs and Weight by Randomized Dose during Double-Blind Treatment - Adults 
                    Focalin XR    20 mg    (N=57)      Focalin XR    30 mg    (N=54)      Focalin XR    40 mg    (N=54)      Placebo    (N=53)     
   Pulse (bpm)    3.1 +/- 11.1     4.3 +/- 11.7     6.0 +/- 10.1     -1.4 +/- 9.3      
   Diastolic BP (mmHg)    -0.2 +/- 8.2     1.2 +/- 8.9      2.1 +/- 8.0      0.3 +/- 7.8       
   Weight (kg)    -1.4 +/- 2.0     -1.2 +/- 1.9     -1.7 +/- 2.3     -0.1 +/- 3.9      
               6.5    Adverse Events with Other Methylphenidate HCl Dosage Forms       
   Nervousness and insomnia are the most common adverse reactions reported with other methylphenidate products. In children, loss of appetite, abdominal pain, weight loss during prolonged therapy, insomnia, and tachycardia may occur more frequently; however, any of the other adverse reactions listed below may also occur.



 Other reactions include:



   Cardiac:  angina, arrhythmia, palpitations, pulse increased or decreased, tachycardia



   Gastrointestinal:  abdominal pain, nausea



   Immune:  hypersensitivity reactions including skin rash, urticaria, fever, arthralgia, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme with histopathological findings of necrotizing vasculitis, and thrombocytopenic purpura



   Metabolism/Nutrition:  anorexia, weight loss during prolonged therapy



   Nervous System:  dizziness, drowsiness, dyskinesia, headache, rare reports of Tourette's syndrome, toxic psychosis



   Vascular:  blood pressure increased or decreased, cerebral arteritis and/or occlusion



 Although a definite causal relationship has not been established, the following have been reported in patients taking methylphenidate:



   Blood/Lymphatic:  leukopenia and/or anemia



   Hepatobiliary:  abnormal liver function, ranging from transaminase elevation to hepatic coma



   Psychiatric:  transient depressed mood, aggressive behavior



   Skin/Subcutaneous:  scalp hair loss



 Very rare reports of neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS) have been received, and, in most of these, patients were concurrently receiving therapies associated with NMS. In a single report, a ten-year-old boy who had been taking methylphenidate for approximately 18 months experienced an NMS-like event within 45 minutes of ingesting his first dose of venlafaxine. It is uncertain whether this case represented a drug-drug interaction, a response to either drug alone, or some other cause.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: DRUG DEPENDENCE

    WARNING: DRUG DEPENDENCE  

  Focalin XR should be given cautiously to patients with a history of drug dependence or alcoholism. Chronic abusive use can lead to marked tolerance and psychological dependence with varying degrees of abnormal behavior. Frank psychotic episodes can occur, especially with parenteral abuse. Careful supervision is required during withdrawal from abusive use, since severe depression may occur. Withdrawal following chronic therapeutic use may unmask symptoms of the underlying disorder that may require follow-up.



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: D    RUG DEPENDENCE  



   See full prescribing     i    nformation for complete boxed warning  



   Focalin XR should be given cautiously to patients with a history of drug dependence or alcoholism    .     Chronic abusive use     can lead to marked tolerance and psychological dependence    ,     with varying     degrees of abnormal behavior    .       
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5        WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious Cardiovascular Events: Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at usual doses in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. Sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults taking stimulant drugs at usual doses for ADHD. Stimulant products generally should not be used in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, coronary artery disease, or other serious heart problems. (5.1) 
 *  Increased Blood Pressure and Heart Rate: have been reported. Monitor patients for changes in blood pressure and heart rate. Caution should be exercised in treating patients whose underlying medical conditions might be compromised by increases in blood pressure or heart rate (5.2) 
 *  Assess Cardiovascular Status: prior to stimulant treatment, assess for cardiac disease with history and exam and, if suggested by findings, conduct further cardiac evaluation. Patients with emerging symptoms suggestive of cardiac disease should undergo a prompt cardiac evaluation (5.3) 
 *  Psychotic Symptoms: may be exacerbated in patients with psychotic disorders (5.4) 
 *  Bipolar Disorder: Use with particular care in ADHD patients with comorbid Bipolar Disorder. Before initiating stimulant therapy, obtain a detailed psychiatric history for patients with comorbid depressive symptoms, in order to determine risk for Bipolar Disorder. (5.5) 
 *  Emergence of New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms: Treatment-emergent psychotic or manic symptoms without a prior history can be caused by stimulants at usual doses. Discontinuation of stimulant therapy may be indicated (5.6) 
 *  Aggression: Monitor for appearance of or worsening of aggressive behavior or hostility (5.7)  
 *  Long-Term Suppression of Growth: monitor height and weight in pediatric patients at appropriate intervals. Patients who are not growing or gaining weight as expected may need to have their treatment interrupted (5.8) 
 *  Seizures: The threshold for seizures may be lowered. In the presence of seizure, discontinue treatment. (5.9) 
 *  Visual Disturbance: difficulties with accommodation and blurring of vision have been reported with stimulant treatment (5.10) 
 *  Hematologic Monitoring: periodic monitoring of CBC with differential is advised during prolonged therapy (5.12) 
    
 

    5.1       Sudden Death and Pre-Existing Structural Cardiac Abnormalities or Other Serious Heart Problems  



  Children and Adolescents



 Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at usual doses in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. Although some serious heart problems alone carry an increased risk of sudden death, stimulant products generally should not be used in children or adolescents with known serious structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, or other serious cardiac problems that may place them at increased vulnerability to the sympathomimetic effects of a stimulant drug.



 Adults



 Sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults taking stimulant drugs at usual doses for ADHD. Although the role of stimulants in these adult cases is also unknown, adults have a greater likelihood than children of having serious structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, coronary artery disease, or other serious cardiac problems. Adults with such abnormalities should also generally not be treated with stimulant drugs.



     5.2   Hypertension and other Cardiovascular Conditions  



  Stimulant medications cause a modest increase in average blood pressure (about 2-4 mmHg) and average heart rate (about 3-6 bpm), and individuals may have larger increases. While the mean changes alone would not be expected to have short-term consequences, all patients should be monitored for larger changes in heart rate and blood pressure. Caution is indicated in treating patients whose underlying medical conditions might be compromised by increases in blood pressure or heart rate, e.g., those with pre-existing hypertension, heart failure, recent myocardial infarction, or ventricular arrhythmia.



     5.3   Assessing Cardiovascular Status in Patients being Treated with Stimulant Medications  



  Children, adolescents, or adults who are being considered for treatment with stimulant medications should have a careful history (including assessment for a family history of sudden death or ventricular arrhythmia) and physical exam to assess for the presence of cardiac disease, and should receive further cardiac evaluation if findings suggest such disease (e.g., electrocardiogram and echocardiogram). Patients who develop symptoms such as exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or other symptoms suggestive of cardiac disease during stimulant treatment should undergo a prompt cardiac evaluation.



     5.4   Pre-Existing Psychosis  



  Administration of stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with a pre-existing psychotic disorder.



     5.5   Bipolar Illness  



  Particular care should be taken in using stimulants to treat ADHD in patients with comorbid bipolar disorder because of concern for possible induction of a mixed/manic episode in such patients. Prior to initiating treatment with a stimulant, patients with comorbid depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression.



     5.6   Emergence of New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms  



  Treatment emergent psychotic or manic symptoms, e.g., hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania in children and adolescents without a prior history of psychotic illness or mania can be caused by stimulants at usual doses. If such symptoms occur, consideration should be given to a possible causal role of the stimulant, and discontinuation of treatment may be appropriate. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies, such symptoms occurred in about 0.1% (4 patients with events out of 3,482 exposed to methylphenidate or amphetamine for several weeks at usual doses) of stimulant-treated patients compared to 0 in placebo-treated patients.



     5.7   Aggression  



  Aggressive behavior or hostility is often observed in children and adolescents with ADHD, and has been reported in clinical trials and the post marketing experience of some medications indicated for the treatment of ADHD. Although there is no systematic evidence that stimulants cause aggressive behavior or hostility, patients beginning treatment for ADHD should be monitored for the appearance of or worsening of aggressive behavior or hostility.



     5.8   Long-Term Suppression of Growth  



  Careful follow-up of weight and height in children ages 7 to 10 years who were randomized to either methylphenidate or non-medication treatment groups over 14 months, as well as in naturalistic subgroups of newly methylphenidate-treated and non-medication treated children over 36 months (to the ages of 10 to 13 years), suggests that consistently medicated children (i.e., treatment for 7 days per week throughout the year) have a temporary slowing in growth rate (on average, a total of about 2 cm less growth in height and 2.7 kg less growth in weight over 3 years), without evidence of growth rebound during this period of development. In the 7-week double-blind placebo-controlled study of Focalin XR, the mean weight gain was greater for patients receiving placebo (+0.4 kg) than for patients receiving Focalin XR (-0.5 kg). Published data are inadequate to determine whether chronic use of amphetamines may cause a similar suppression of growth, however, it is anticipated that they likely have this effect as well. Therefore, growth should be monitored during treatment with stimulants, and patients who are not growing or gaining height or weight as expected may need to have their treatment interrupted.



     5.9   Seizures  



  There is some clinical evidence that stimulants may lower the convulsive threshold in patients with prior history of seizures, in patients with prior EEG abnormalities in absence of seizures, and, very rarely, in patients without a history of seizures and no prior EEG evidence of seizures. In the presence of seizures, the drug should be discontinued.



     5.10   Visual Disturbance  



  Difficulties with accommodation and blurring of vision have been reported with stimulant treatment.



     5.11   Use in Children Under Six Years of Age  



  Focalin XR should not be used in children under 6 years of age, since safety and efficacy in this age group have not been established.



     5.12   Hematologic Monitoring  



  Periodic CBC, differential, and platelet counts are advised during prolonged therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
