<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="follistim" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Atelectasis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Thromboembolism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Ovarian Torsion [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Multi-fetal Gestation and Birth [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Congenital Anomalies [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Ectopic Pregnancy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Spontaneous Abortion [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) in women undergoing ovulation induction are ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome, ovarian cyst, abdominal discomfort, abdominal pain and lower abdominal pain. (  6.1  )
 

 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) in women undergoing controlled ovarian stimulation as part of an IVF or ICSI cycle are pelvic discomfort, headache, ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome, pelvic pain, nausea and fatigue. (  6.1  )



 The most common (&gt;=2%) adverse reactions in men undergoing induction of spermatogenesis are headache, acne, injection site reaction, injection site pain, gynecomastia, rash and dermoid cyst. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Study Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trial of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Ovulation Induction  



 In a single cycle, multi-center, assessor-blind, parallel group, comparative study, a total of 172 chronic anovulatory women who had failed to ovulate and/or conceive with clomiphene citrate therapy, were randomized and treated with Follistim (105) or a urofollitropin comparator. Adverse reactions with an incidence of greater than 2% in either treatment group are listed in Table 2.



 Table 2: Common Adverse Reactions Reported at a Frequency of &gt;=2% in an Assessor-Blind, Comparative Study of Anovulatory Women Receiving Ovulation Induction 
 System Organ Class/Adverse Reactions                TreatmentNumber (%) of Women   
 FollistimN=105n (%)                                    ComparatorN=67n (%)      
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                         
   Abdominal discomfort                                       3 (2.9)                    1 (1.5)            
   Abdominal pain                                             3 (2.9)                    2 (3.0)            
   Abdominal pain lower                                       3 (2.9)                    1 (1.5)            
   Reproductive system and breast disorders           
   Ovarian cyst                                               3 (2.9)                    2 (3.0)            
   Ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome                          8 (7.6)                    3 (4.5)            
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
   Pyrexia                                                    0 (0.0)                    2 (3.0)            
         Adverse reactions reported commonly (greater than or equal to 2% of women treated with Follistim) in other ovulation induction clinical trials were headache, abdominal distension, constipation, diarrhea, nausea, pelvic pain, uterine enlargement, vaginal hemorrhage and injection site reaction.
 

     In Vitro Fertilization/Intracytoplasmic Sperm Injection  



 In a single cycle, multi-center, double-blind, parallel group, comparative study, a total of 1509 women were randomized to receive controlled ovarian stimulation with either Follistim AQ Cartridge (751 women were treated with Follistim AQ Cartridge) or a comparator and pituitary suppression with a gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH) antagonist as part of an in vitro fertilization (IVF) or intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) cycle. Table 3 lists adverse reactions with an incidence of greater than 2% in the group of women treated with Follistim AQ Cartridge.



 Table 3: Common Adverse Reactions Reported at a Frequency of &gt;=2% in a Randomized, Double-blind, Active-controlled, Comparative Study of Normal Ovulatory Women Undergoing Controlled Ovarian Stimulation as Part of an In Vitro Fertilization or Intracytoplasmic Sperm Injection Cycle 
 System Organ Class/Adverse Reactions                   Follistim AQ Cartridge TreatmentN = 751n(%)       
  
   Nervous System disorders                                                                               
   Headache                                                              55 (7.3%)                        
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                             
   Nausea                                                                29 (3.9%)                        
   Reproductive system and breast disorders                                                               
   Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome                                     48 (6.4%)                        
   Pelvic discomfort                                                     62 (8.3%)                        
   Pelvic Pain                                                           41 (5.5%)                        
   General disorders and Administration site conditions                                                         
   Fatigue                                                               17 (2.3%)                        
            Induction of Spermatogenesis  
 

 In an open-label, non-comparative clinical trial, 49 men with hypogonadotropic hypogonadism were enrolled to receive pretreatment with hCG, followed by combination therapy with hCG and Follistim for induction of spermatogenesis. Of the 49 men, 30 received weekly Follistim doses of 450 international units; 24 of these 30 men received a total of 48 weeks of treatment with Follistim. Adverse reactions occurring with an incidence of greater than 2% in the 30 men treated with Follistim are listed in Table 4.



 Table 4: Common Adverse Reactions Reported at a Frequency of &gt;=2% in an Open-Label Clinical Trial in Men with Hypogonadotropic Hypogonadism 
 System Organ Class/Adverse Reactions                                         Follistim TreatmentN=30n (%)   
  
   Nervous system disorders                                                                               
   Headache                                                                            2 (6.7)            
   General disorders and administration site disorders                                                    
   Injection site reaction                                                             2 (6.7)            
   Injection site pain                                                                 2 (6.7)            
   Skin and cutaneous tissue disorders                                                                    
   Acne                                                                                2 (6.7)            
   Rash                                                                                1 (3.3)            
   Reproductive system and breast disorders                                                               
   Gynecomastia                                                                        1 (3.3)            
   Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified                                                            
   Dermoid cyst                                                                        1 (3.3)            
          6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Follistim and/or Follistim AQ Cartridge. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal disorders  Abdominal distension, abdominal pain, constipation, diarrhea



   General disorders and administration site conditions  Injection site reaction



   Reproductive system and breast disorders  Breast tenderness, metrorrhagia, ovarian enlargement, vaginal hemorrhage



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  Rash



   Vascular disorders  Thromboembolism  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  Follistim AQ Cartridge should be used only by physicians who are experienced in infertility treatment. Follistim AQ Cartridge contains a potent gonadotropic substance capable of causing Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome (OHSS) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  with or without pulmonary or vascular complications [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  and multiple births [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  . Gonadotropin therapy requires the availability of appropriate monitoring facilities [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  .



 Careful attention should be given to the diagnosis of infertility and in the selection of candidates for Follistim AQ Cartridge therapy [see  Indications and Usage (1.1  ,  1.2  ,  1.3)  and  Dosage and Administration (2.2  ,  2.3  ,  2.4)  ]  .



 Switching to Follistim AQ Cartridge from other brands (manufacturer), types (recombinant, urinary), and/or methods of administration (Follistim Pen, conventional syringe) may necessitate an adjustment of the dose [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ].  



   EXCERPT:   Treatment with Follistim AQ may result in:



 *  Abnormal Ovarian Enlargement (  5.1  ) 
 *  Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome (OHSS) (  5.2  ) 
 *  Pulmonary and Vascular Complications (  5.3  ) 
 *  Ovarian Torsion (  5.4  ) 
 *  Multi-fetal Gestation and Birth (  5.5  ) 
 *  Congenital Anomalies (  5.6  ) 
 *  Ectopic Pregnancy (  5.7  ) 
 *  Spontaneous Abortion (  5.8  ) 
 *  Ovarian Neoplasms (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Abnormal Ovarian Enlargement



  In order to minimize the hazards associated with abnormal ovarian enlargement that may occur with Follistim AQ therapy, treatment should be individualized and the lowest effective dose should be used [  see   Dosage and Administration (2.2  ,  2.3)     ]  . Use of ultrasound monitoring of ovarian response and/or measurement of serum estradiol levels is important to minimize the risk of overstimulation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]    .



 If the ovaries are abnormally enlarged on the last day of Follistim AQ therapy, hCG should not be administered in order to reduce the chances of developing Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome (OHSS). Intercourse should be prohibited in patients with significant ovarian enlargement after ovulation because of the danger of hemoperitoneum resulting from ruptured ovarian cysts [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



    5.2 Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome (OHSS)



  OHSS is a medical entity distinct from uncomplicated ovarian enlargement and may progress rapidly to become a serious medical condition. OHSS is characterized by a dramatic increase in vascular permeability, which can result in a rapid accumulation of fluid in the peritoneal cavity, thorax, and potentially, the pericardium. The early warning signs of OHSS developing are severe pelvic pain, nausea, vomiting, and weight gain. Abdominal pain, abdominal distension, gastrointestinal symptoms including nausea, vomiting and diarrhea, severe ovarian enlargement, weight gain, dyspnea, and oliguria have been reported with OHSS. Clinical evaluation may reveal hypovolemia, hemoconcentration, electrolyte imbalances, ascites, hemoperitoneum, pleural effusions, hydrothorax, acute pulmonary distress, and thromboembolic reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  . Transient liver function test abnormalities suggestive of hepatic dysfunction with or without morphologic changes on liver biopsy have also been reported in association with OHSS.



 OHSS occurs after gonadotropin treatment has been discontinued, and it can develop rapidly, reaching its maximum about seven to ten days following treatment. Usually, OHSS resolves spontaneously with the onset of menses. If there is a risk for OHSS evident prior to hCG administration [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  , the hCG must be withheld. Cases of OHSS are more common, more severe, and more protracted if pregnancy occurs; therefore, women should be assessed for the development of OHSS for at least two weeks after hCG administration.



 If serious OHSS occurs, gonadotropins, including hCG, should be stopped and consideration should be given as to whether the patient needs to be hospitalized. Treatment is primarily symptomatic and overall should consist of bed rest, fluid and electrolyte management, and analgesics (if needed). Because the use of diuretics can accentuate the diminished intravascular volume, diuretics should be avoided except in the late phase of resolution as described below. The management of OHSS may be divided into three phases as follows:



 *  *     Management should be directed at preventing hemoconcentration due to loss of intravascular volume to the third space and minimizing the risk of thromboembolic phenomena and kidney damage. Fluid intake and output, weight, hematocrit, serum and urinary electrolytes, urine specific gravity, BUN and creatinine, total proteins with albumin: globulin ratio, coagulation studies, electrocardiogram to monitor for hyperkalemia, and abdominal girth should be thoroughly assessed daily or more often based on the clinical need. Treatment, consisting of limited intravenous fluids, electrolytes, and human serum albumin is intended to normalize electrolytes while maintaining an acceptable but somewhat reduced intravascular volume. Full correction of the intravascular volume deficit may lead to an unacceptable increase in the amount of third space fluid accumulation. 
    Acute Phase : 
 *  *     After the acute phase is successfully managed as above, excessive fluid accumulation in the third space should be limited by instituting severe potassium, sodium, and fluid restriction. 
    Chronic Phase : 
 *  *     As third space fluid returns to the intravascular compartment, a fall in hematocrit and increasing urinary output are observed in the absence of any increase in intake. Peripheral and/or pulmonary edema may result if the kidneys are unable to excrete third space fluid as rapidly as it is mobilized. Diuretics may be indicated during the resolution phase, if necessary, to combat pulmonary edema. 
    Resolution Phase : 
    OHSS increases the risk of injury to the ovary. The ascitic, pleural, and pericardial fluid should not be removed unless there is the necessity to relieve symptoms such as pulmonary distress or cardiac tamponade. Pelvic examination may cause rupture of an ovarian cyst, which may result in hemoperitoneum, and should therefore be avoided. If bleeding occurs and requires surgical intervention, the clinical objective should be to control the bleeding and retain as much ovarian tissue as possible.
 

 During clinical trials with Follistim or Follistim AQ Cartridge therapy, OHSS occurred in 7.6% of 105 women (OI) and 6.4% of 751 women (IVF or ICSI) treated with Follistim and Follistim AQ Cartridge, respectively.



    5.3 Pulmonary and Vascular Complications



  Serious pulmonary conditions (e.g., atelectasis, acute respiratory distress syndrome) have been reported in women treated with gonadotropins. In addition, thromboembolic reactions both in association with, and separate from OHSS have been reported following gonadotropin therapy. Intravascular thrombosis, which may originate in venous or arterial vessels, can result in reduced blood flow to vital organs or the extremities. Women with generally recognized risk factors for thrombosis, such as a personal or family history, severe obesity, or thrombophilia, may have an increased risk of venous or arterial thromboembolic events, during or following treatment with gonadotropins. Sequelae of such reactions have included venous thrombophlebitis, pulmonary embolism, pulmonary infarction, cerebral vascular occlusion (stroke), and arterial occlusion resulting in loss of limb and rarely in myocardial infarction. In rare cases, pulmonary complications and/or thromboembolic reactions have resulted in death. In women with recognized risk factors, the benefits of ovulation induction, in vitro fertilization (IVF) or intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) treatment need to be weighed against the risks. It should be noted, that pregnancy itself also carries an increased risk of thrombosis.



    5.4 Ovarian Torsion



  Ovarian torsion has been reported after treatment with Follistim AQ Cartridge and after intervention with other gonadotropins. This may be related to OHSS, pregnancy, previous abdominal surgery, past history of ovarian torsion, previous or current ovarian cyst and polycystic ovaries. Damage to the ovary due to reduced blood supply can be limited by early diagnosis and immediate detorsion.



    5.5 Multi-fetal Gestation and Birth



  Multi-fetal gestation and births have been reported with all gonadotropin treatments including Follistim AQ Cartridge treatment. The woman and her partner should be advised of the potential risk of multi-fetal gestation and births before starting treatment.



    5.6 Congenital Anomalies



  The incidence of congenital malformations after IVF or ICSI may be slightly higher than after spontaneous conception. This slightly higher incidence is thought to be related to differences in parental characteristics (e.g., maternal age, sperm characteristics) and to the higher incidence of multi-fetal gestations after IVF or ICSI. There are no indications that the use of gonadotropins during IVF or ICSI is associated with an increased risk of congenital malformations.



    5.7 Ectopic Pregnancy



  Since infertile women undergoing IVF or ICSI often have tubal abnormalities, the incidence of ectopic pregnancies might be increased. Early confirmation of an intrauterine pregnancy should be determined by beta-hCG testing and transvaginal ultrasound.



    5.8 Spontaneous Abortion



  The risk of spontaneous abortions (miscarriage) is increased with gonadotropin products. However, causality has not been established. The increased risk may be a factor of the underlying infertility.



    5.9 Ovarian Neoplasms



  There have been infrequent reports of ovarian neoplasms, both benign and malignant, in women who have undergone multiple drug regimens for controlled ovarian stimulation; however, a causal relationship has not been established.



    5.10 Laboratory Tests



   For Women  :



 In most instances, treatment with Follistim AQ Cartridge will result only in follicular growth and maturation. In order to complete the final phase of follicular maturation and to induce ovulation, hCG must be given following the administration of Follistim AQ Cartridge or when clinical assessment indicates that sufficient follicular maturation has occurred. The degree of follicular maturation and the timing of hCG administration can both be determined with the use of sonographic visualization of the ovaries and endometrial lining in conjunction with measurement of serum estradiol levels. The combination of transvaginal ultrasonography and measurement of serum estradiol levels is also useful for minimizing the risk of OHSS and multi-fetal gestations.



 The clinical confirmation of ovulation is obtained by the following direct or indirect indices of progesterone production as well as sonographic evidence of ovulation.



 Direct or indirect indices of progesterone production are:



 *  Urinary or serum luteinizing hormone (LH) rise 
 *  A rise in basal body temperature 
 *  Increase in serum progesterone 
 *  Menstruation following the shift in basal body temperature 
    The following provide sonographic evidence of ovulation:
 

 *  Collapsed follicle 
 *  Fluid in the cul-de-sac 
 *  Features consistent with corpus luteum formation 
    Sonographic evaluation of the early pregnancy is also important to rule out ectopic pregnancy.
 

    For Men  :



 Clinical monitoring for spermatogenesis utilizes the following indirect or direct measures:



 *  Serum testosterone level 
 *  Semen analysis 
       5.11 Follistim Pen
 

  The Follistim Pen is intended only for use with Follistim AQ Cartridge. The Follistim Pen is not recommended for the blind or visually impaired without the assistance of an individual with good vision who is trained in the proper use of the injection device.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
