<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fondaparinux" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reactions reported with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution are bleeding complications and thrombocytopenia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5)  ]  .



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The adverse reaction information below is based on data from 8,877 patients exposed to Fondaparinux Sodium Solution in controlled trials of hip fracture, hip replacement, major knee, or abdominal surgeries, and DVT and PE treatment. These trials consisted of the following:



 *    2 peri-operative dose-response trials (n = 989) 
 *    4 active-controlled peri-operative VTE prophylaxis trials with enoxaparin sodium (n = 3,616), an extended VTE prophylaxis trial (n = 327), and an active-controlled trial with dalteparin sodium (n = 1,425) 
 *    a dose-response trial (n = 111) and an active-controlled trial with enoxaparin sodium in DVT treatment (n = 1,091) 
 *    an active-controlled trial with heparin in PE treatment (n = 1,092) 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions associated with the use of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution are bleeding complications. (  6.1  ) Mild local irritation (injection site bleeding, rash, and pruritus) may occur following subcutaneous injection. (  6.2  )
 

 Anemia, insomnia, increased wound drainage, hypokalemia, dizziness, hypotension, confusion, bullous eruption, hematoma, post-operative hemorrhage, and purpura may occur. (  6.4  )



     



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Mylan Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-877-446-3679 (1-877-4-INFO-RX) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Hemorrhage

  During administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution, the most common adverse reactions were bleeding complications  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



     Hip Fracture, Hip Replacement, and Knee Replacement Surgery  

  The rates of major bleeding events reported during the hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery clinical trials with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution 2.5 mg are provided in Table 2.



 Table 2. Bleeding Across Randomized, Controlled Hip Fracture, Hip Replacement, and Knee Replacement Surgery Studies 
                            Peri-Operative Prophylaxis(Day 1 to Day 7 +/- 1 post-surgery)    Extended Prophylaxis(Day 8 to Day 28 +/- 2 post-surgery)    
  Fondaparinux Sodium Solution  2.5 mg SC  once daily  N = 3,616    Enoxaparin SodiumEnoxaparin sodium dosing regimen: 30 mg every 12 hours or 40 mg once daily., Not approved for use in patients undergoing hip fracture surgery.  N = 3,956    Fondaparinux Sodium Solution  2.5 mg SC  once daily  N = 327    Placebo  SC once daily  N = 329    
  Major bleedingMajor bleeding was defined as clinically overt bleeding that was (1) fatal, (2) bleeding at critical site (e.g. intracranial, retroperitoneal, intraocular, pericardial, spinal, or into adrenal gland), (3) associated with re-operation at operative site, or (4) with a bleeding index (BI) &gt;=2.    96 (2.7%)            75 (1.9%)            8 (2.4%)              2 (0.6%)            
     Hip fracture           18/831 (2.2%)        19/842 (2.3%)        8/327 (2.4%)          2/329 (0.6%)        
     Hip replacement        67/2,268 (3.0%)      55/2,597 (2.1%)      -                     -                   
     Knee replacement       11/517 (2.1%)        1/517 (0.2%)         -                     -                   
  Fatal bleeding            0 (0.0%)             1 (&lt;0.1%)            0 (0.0%)              0 (0.0%)            
  Non-fatal bleeding at critical site    0 (0.0%)             1 (&lt;0.1%)            0 (0.0%)              0 (0.0%)            
  Re-operation due to bleeding    12 (0.3%)            10 (0.3%)            2 (0.6%)              2 (0.6%)            
  BI &gt;=2BI &gt;=2: Overt bleeding associated only with a bleeding index (BI) &gt;=2 calculated as [number of whole blood or packed red blood cell units transfused + [(pre-bleeding) - (post-bleeding)] hemoglobin (g/dL) values].    84 (2.3%)            63 (1.6%)            6 (1.8%)              0 (0.0%)            
  Minor bleedingMinor bleeding was defined as clinically overt bleeding that was not major.    109 (3.0%)           116 (2.9%)           5 (1.5%)              2 (0.6%)            
           A separate analysis of major bleeding across all randomized, controlled, peri-operative, prophylaxis clinical studies of hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery according to the time of the first injection of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution after surgical closure was performed in patients who received Fondaparinux Sodium Solution only post-operatively. In this analysis, the incidences of major bleeding were as follows: &lt;4 hours was 4.8% (5/104), 4 to 6 hours was 2.3% (28/1,196), 6 to 8 hours was 1.9% (38/1,965). In all studies, the majority (&gt;=75%) of the major bleeding events occurred during the first 4 days after surgery.
 

     Abdominal Surgery  

  In a randomized study of patients undergoing abdominal surgery, Fondaparinux Sodium Solution 2.5 mg once daily (n = 1,433) was compared with dalteparin 5,000 IU once daily (n = 1,425). Bleeding rates are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3. Bleeding in the Abdominal Surgery Study 
                                       Fondaparinux Sodium Solution  2.5 mg SC once daily    Dalteparin Sodium  5,000 IU SC once daily    
  N = 1,433                            N = 1,425                         
  Major bleedingMajor bleeding was defined as bleeding that was (1) fatal, (2) bleeding at the surgical site leading to intervention, (3) non-surgical bleeding at a critical site (e.g. intracranial, retroperitoneal, intraocular, pericardial, spinal, or into adrenal gland), or leading to an intervention, and/or with a bleeding index (BI) &gt;=2.    49 (3.4%)                         34 (2.4%)                         
  Fatal bleeding                       2 (0.1%)                          2 (0.1%)                          
  Non-fatal bleeding at critical site    0 (0.0%)                          0 (0.0%)                          
  Other non-fatal major bleeding                                                                           
     Surgical site                     38 (2.7%)                         26 (1.8%)                         
     Non-surgical site                 9 (0.6%)                          6 (0.4%)                          
  Minor bleedingMinor bleeding was defined as clinically overt bleeding that was not major.    31 (2.2%)                         23 (1.6%)                         
         The rates of major bleeding according to the time interval following the first Fondaparinux Sodium Solution injection were as follows: &lt;6 hours was 3.4% (9/263) and 6 to 8 hours was 2.9% (32/1112).
 

     Treatment of Deep Vein Thrombosis and Pulmonary Embolism  

  The rates of bleeding events reported during the DVT and PE clinical trials with the Fondaparinux Sodium Solution injection treatment regimen are provided in Table 4.



 Table 4. BleedingBleeding rates are during the study drug treatment period (approximately 7 days). Patients were also treated with vitamin K antagonists initiated within 72 hours after the first study drug administration. in Deep Vein Thrombosis and Pulmonary Embolism Treatment Studies 
                              Fondaparinux Sodium Solution  N = 2,294    Enoxaparin Sodium  N = 1,101    Heparin  aPTT adjusted IV  N = 1,092    
  Major bleedingMajor bleeding was defined as clinically overt: -and/or contributing to death - and/or in a critical organ including intracranial, retroperitoneal, intraocular, spinal, pericardial, or adrenal gland - and/or associated with a fall in hemoglobin level &gt;=2 g/dL - and/or leading to a transfusion &gt;=2 units of packed red blood cells or whole blood.    28 (1.2%)                 13 (1.2%)                12 (1.1%)                    
  Fatal bleeding              3 (0.1%)                  0 (0.0%)                 1 (0.1%)                     
  Non-fatal bleeding at a critical site    3 (0.1%)                  0 (0.0%)                 2 (0.2%)                     
  Intracranial bleeding       3 (0.1%)                  0 (0.0%)                 1 (0.1%)                     
  Retro-peritoneal bleeding    0 (0.0%)                  0 (0.0%)                 1 (0.1%)                     
  Other clinically overt bleedingClinically overt bleeding with a 2 g/dL fall in hemoglobin and/or leading to transfusion of PRBC or whole blood &gt;=2 units.    22 (1.0%)                 13 (1.2%)                10 (0.9%)                    
  Minor bleedingMinor bleeding was defined as clinically overt bleeding that was not major.    70 (3.1%)                 33 (3.0%)                57 (5.2%)                    
            6.2 Local Reactions
   Local irritation (injection site bleeding, rash, and pruritus) may occur following subcutaneous injection of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution.



   6.3 Elevations of Serum Aminotransferases

  In the peri-operative prophylaxis randomized clinical trials of 7 +/- 2 days, asymptomatic increases in aspartate (AST) and alanine (ALT) aminotransferase levels greater than 3 times the upper limit of normal were reported in 1.7% and 2.6% of patients, respectively, during treatment with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution 2.5 mg once daily versus 3.2% and 3.9% of patients, respectively, during treatment with enoxaparin sodium 30 mg every 12 hours or 40 mg once daily enoxaparin sodium. These elevations are reversible and rarely associated with increases in bilirubin. In the extended prophylaxis clinical trial, no significant differences in AST and ALT levels between Fondaparinux Sodium Solution 2.5 mg and placebo-treated patients were observed.



 In the DVT and PE treatment clinical trials, asymptomatic increases in AST and ALT levels greater than 3 times the upper limit of normal of the laboratory reference range were reported in 0.7% and 1.3% of patients, respectively, during treatment with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution. In comparison, these increases were reported in 4.8% and 12.3% of patients, respectively, in the DVT treatment trial during treatment with enoxaparin sodium 1 mg/kg every 12 hours and in 2.9% and 8.7% of patients, respectively, in the PE treatment trial during treatment with aPTT adjusted heparin.



 Since aminotransferase determinations are important in the differential diagnosis of myocardial infarction, liver disease, and pulmonary emboli, elevations that might be caused by drugs like Fondaparinux Sodium Solution should be interpreted with caution.



   6.4 Other Adverse Reactions

  Other adverse reactions that occurred during treatment with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution in clinical trials with patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery are provided in Table 5.



 Table 5. Adverse Reactions Across Randomized, Controlled, Hip Fracture Surgery, Hip Replacement Surgery, and Knee Replacement Surgery Studies 
  Adverse Reactions      Peri-Operative Prophylaxis(Day 1 to Day 7 +/- 1 post-surgery)    Extended Prophylaxis(Day 8 to Day 28 +/- 2 post-surgery)    
  Fondaparinux Sodium Solution  2.5 mg SC  once daily    Enoxaparin SodiumEnoxaparin sodium dosing regimen: 30 mg every 12 hours or 40 mg once daily., Not approved for use in patients undergoing hip fracture surgery.    Fondaparinux Sodium Solution  2.5 mg SC  once daily    Placebo  SC once daily    
                         N = 3,616            N = 3,956            N = 327               N = 329               
  Anemia                 707 (19.6%)          670 (16.9%)          5 (1.5%)              4 (1.2%)              
  Insomnia               179 (5.0%)           214 (5.4%)           3 (0.9%)              1 (0.3%)              
  Wound drainage increased    161 (4.5%)           184 (4.7%)           2 (0.6%)              0 (0.0%)              
  Hypokalemia            152 (4.2%)           164 (4.1%)           0 (0.0%)              0 (0.0%)              
  Dizziness              131 (3.6%)           165 (4.2%)           2 (0.6%)              0 (0.0%)              
  Purpura                128 (3.5%)           137 (3.5%)           0 (0.0%)              0 (0.0%)              
  Hypotension            126 (3.5%)           125 (3.2%)           1 (0.3%)              0 (0.0%)              
  Confusion              113 (3.1%)           132 (3.3%)           4 (1.2%)              1 (0.3%)              
  Bullous eruptionLocalized blister coded as bullous eruption.    112 (3.1%)           102 (2.6%)           0 (0.0%)              1 (0.3%)              
  Hematoma               103 (2.8%)           109 (2.8%)           7 (2.1%)              1 (0.3%)              
  Post-operative hemorrhage    85 (2.4%)            69 (1.7%)            2 (0.6%)              2 (0.6%)              
           Adverse reactions in the abdominal surgery study and in the VTE treatment trials generally occurred at lower rates than in the hip and knee surgery trials described above. The most common adverse reaction in the abdominal surgery trial was post-operative wound infection (4.9%), and the most common adverse reaction in the VTE treatment trials was epistaxis (1.3%).
 

   6.5 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 In the postmarketing experience, epidural or spinal hematoma has been reported in association with the use of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution by subcutaneous (SC) injection  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].  Isolated occurrences of thrombocytopenia with thrombosis that manifested similar to heparin-induced thrombocytopenia have been reported in the postmarketing experience and isolated cases of elevated aPTT temporally associated with bleeding events have been reported following administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution (with or without concomitant administration of other anticoagulants)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].  



 Serious allergic reactions, including angioedema, anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions have been reported with the use of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution  [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMAS 

  WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMAS 

    Epidural or spinal hematomas may occur in patients who are anticoagulated with low molecular weight heparins (LMWH), heparinoids, or fondaparinux sodium and are receiving neuraxial anesthesia or undergoing spinal puncture. These hematomas may result in long-term or permanent paralysis. Consider these risks when scheduling patients for spinal procedures. Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include:  



 *  use of indwelling epidural catheters 
 *  concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, or other anticoagulants 
 *  a history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal puncture 
 *  a history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery 
 *  Optimal timing between the administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution and neuraxial procedures is not known. 
      Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment. If neurologic compromise is noted, urgent treatment is necessary.  
 

   Consider the benefit and risks before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or to be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis.   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   and   Drug Interactions (7)  .]    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SPINAL/EPIDURAL HEMATOMAS 



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Epidural or spinal hematomas may occur in patients who are anticoagulated with low molecular weight heparins (LMWH), heparinoids, or fondaparinux sodium and are receiving neuraxial anesthesia or undergoing spinal puncture. These hematomas may result in long-term or permanent paralysis. Consider these risks when scheduling patients for spinal procedures. Factors that can increase the risk of developing epidural or spinal hematomas in these patients include:   



 *  use of indwelling epidural catheters 
 *  concomitant use of other drugs that affect hemostasis, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), platelet inhibitors, or other anticoagulants 
 *  a history of traumatic or repeated epidural or spinal puncture 
 *  a history of spinal deformity or spinal surgery 
      Monitor patients frequently for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment. If neurologic compromise is noted, urgent treatment is necessary.  
 

   Consider the benefit and risks before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or to be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis.   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   and   Drug Interactions (7)  .]    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Use with caution in patients who have conditions or are taking concomitant medications that increase risk of hemorrhage. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Bleeding risk is increased in renal impairment and in patients with low body weight &lt;50 kg. (  5.2  ,  5.3  ) 
 *    Thrombocytopenia can occur with administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Periodic routine complete blood counts (including platelet counts), serum creatinine level, and stool occult blood tests are recommended (  5.6  ) 
 *    The packaging (needle guard) contains dry natural rubber and may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hemorrhage



  Use Fondaparinux Sodium Solution with extreme caution in conditions with increased risk of hemorrhage, such as congenital or acquired bleeding disorders, active ulcerative and angiodysplastic gastrointestinal disease, hemorrhagic stroke, uncontrolled arterial hypertension, diabetic retinopathy, or shortly after brain, spinal, or ophthalmological surgery. Isolated cases of elevated aPTT temporally associated with bleeding events have been reported following administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution (with or without concomitant administration of other anticoagulants) [see  Adverse Reactions (6.5)  ].  



 Do not administer agents that enhance the risk of hemorrhage with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution unless essential for the management of the underlying condition, such as vitamin K antagonists for the treatment of VTE. If co-administration is essential, closely monitor patients for signs and symptoms of bleeding.



 Do not administer the initial dose of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution earlier than 6 to 8 hours after surgery. Administration earlier than 6 hours after surgery increases risk of major bleeding [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.2 Renal Impairment and Bleeding Risk



  Fondaparinux Sodium Solution increases the risk of bleeding in patients with impaired renal function due to reduced clearance [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.4)  ].  



 The incidence of major bleeding by renal function status reported in clinical trials of patients receiving Fondaparinux Sodium Solution for VTE surgical prophylaxis is provided in Table 1. In these patient populations, the following is recommended:



 Do not use Fondaparinux Sodium Solution for VTE prophylaxis and treatment in patients with CrCl &lt;30 mL/min [see  Contraindications (4)  ].  



 Use Fondaparinux Sodium Solution with caution in patients with CrCl 30 to 50 mL/min.



 Table 1. Incidence of Major Bleeding in Patients Treated With Fondaparinux Sodium Solution by Renal Function Status for Surgical Prophylaxis and Treatment of Deep Vein Thrombosis (DVT) and Pulmonary Embolism (PE) 
 CrCl = creatinine clearance.   
  
                                           Degree of Renal Impairment    
  Population             Timing of Dose    Normal  %  (n/N)    Mild  %  (n/N)    Moderate  %  (n/N)    Severe  %  (n/N)    
  CrCl (mL/min)                            &gt;=80            &gt;=50 - &lt;80        &gt;=30 - &lt;50        &lt;30               
  Orthopedic surgeryHip fracture, hip replacement, and knee replacement surgery prophylaxis.    Overall           1.6%  (25/1,565)    2.4%  (31/1,288)    3.8%  (19/504)    4.8%  (4/83)      
                         6-8 hours after surgery    1.8%  (16/905)    2.2%  (15/675)    2.3%  (6/265)     0%  (0/40)        
  Abdominal surgery      Overall           2.1%  (13/606)    3.6%  (22/613)    6.7%  (12/179)    7.1%  (1/14)      
                         6-8 hours after surgery    2.1%  (10/467)    3.3%  (16/481)    5.8%  (8/137)     7.7%  (1/13)      
  DVT and PE  Treatment                      0.4%  (4/1,132)    1.6%  (12/733)    2.2%  (7/318)     7.3%  (4/55)      
            Assess renal function periodically in patients receiving Fondaparinux Sodium Solution. Discontinue the drug immediately in patients who develop severe renal impairment while on therapy. After discontinuation of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution, its anticoagulant effects may persist for 2 to 4 days in patients with normal renal function (i.e., at least 3 to 5 half-lives). The anticoagulant effects of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution may persist even longer in patients with renal impairment [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.4)  ].  
 

    5.3 Body Weight &lt;50 Kg and Bleeding Risk



  Fondaparinux Sodium Solution increases the risk for bleeding in patients who weigh less than 50 kg, compared to patients with higher weights.



 In patients who weigh less than 50 kg:



 *    Do not administer Fondaparinux Sodium Solution as prophylactic therapy for patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery [see  Contraindications (4)  ].  
 *    Use Fondaparinux Sodium Solution with caution in the treatment of PE and DVT. 
    During the randomized clinical trials of VTE prophylaxis in the peri-operative period following hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery, major bleeding occurred at a higher rate among patients with a body weight &lt;50 kg compared to those with a body weight &gt;50 kg (5.4% versus 2.1% in patients undergoing hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery; 5.3% versus 3.3% in patients undergoing abdominal surgery).
 

    5.4 Thrombocytopenia



  Thrombocytopenia can occur with the administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution. Thrombocytopenia of any degree should be monitored closely. Discontinue Fondaparinux Sodium Solution if the platelet count falls below 100,000/mm  3  . Moderate thrombocytopenia (platelet counts between 100,000/mm  3  and 50,000/mm  3  ) occurred at a rate of 3.0% in patients given Fondaparinux Sodium Solution 2.5 mg in the peri-operative hip fracture, hip replacement, or knee replacement surgery and abdominal surgery clinical trials. Severe thrombocytopenia (platelet counts less than 50,000/mm  3  ) occurred at a rate of 0.2% in patients given Fondaparinux Sodium Solution 2.5 mg in these clinical trials. During extended prophylaxis, no cases of moderate or severe thrombocytopenia were reported.



 Moderate thrombocytopenia occurred at a rate of 0.5% in patients given the Fondaparinux Sodium Solution treatment regimen in the DVT and PE treatment clinical trials. Severe thrombocytopenia occurred at a rate of 0.04% in patients given the Fondaparinux Sodium Solution treatment regimen in the DVT and PE treatment clinical trials.



 Isolated occurrences of thrombocytopenia with thrombosis that manifested similar to heparin-induced thrombocytopenia have been reported with the use of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution in postmarketing experience. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.5)  .]  



    5.5 Neuraxial Anesthesia and Post-operative Indwelling Epidural Catheter Use



   Spinal or epidural hematomas, which may result in long-term or permanent paralysis, can occur with the use of anticoagulants and neuraxial (spinal/epidural) anesthesia or spinal puncture. The risk of these events may be higher with post-operative use of indwelling epidural catheters or concomitant use of other drugs affecting hemostasis such as NSAIDs [see  Boxed Warning  ].  In the postmarketing experience, epidural or spinal hematoma has been reported in association with the use of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution by subcutaneous (SC) injection. Optimal timing between the administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution and neuraxial procedures is not known. Monitor patients undergoing these procedures for signs and symptoms of neurologic impairment such as midline back pain, sensory and motor deficits (numbness, tingling, or weakness in lower limbs), and bowel or bladder dysfunction. Consider the potential risks and benefits before neuraxial intervention in patients anticoagulated or who may be anticoagulated for thromboprophylaxis.  



    5.6 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  Routine coagulation tests such as Prothrombin Time (PT) and Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) are relatively insensitive measures of the activity of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution and international standards of heparin or LMWH are not calibrators to measure anti-Factor Xa activity of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution. If unexpected changes in coagulation parameters or major bleeding occur during therapy with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution, discontinue Fondaparinux Sodium Solution.   In postmarketing experience, isolated occurrences of aPTT elevations have been reported following administration of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution [see  Adverse Reactions (6.5)  ]  .



 Periodic routine complete blood counts (including platelet count), serum creatinine level, and stool occult blood tests are recommended during the course of treatment with Fondaparinux Sodium Solution.



 The anti-Factor Xa activity of fondaparinux sodium can be measured by anti-Xa assay using the appropriate calibrator (fondaparinux). The activity of fondaparinux sodium is expressed in milligrams (mg) of the fondaparinux and cannot be compared with activities of heparin or low molecular weight heparins. [See  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2  ,  12.3)  .]  



    5.7 Latex



  The packaging (needle guard) of the prefilled syringe of Fondaparinux Sodium Solution contains dry natural latex rubber that may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
