<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="foradil" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Long-acting beta    2    -adrenergic agonists (LABA), including formoterol, the active ingredient in FORADIL AEROLIZER, increase the risk of asthma-related death and may increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalizations in pediatric and adolescent patients. Clinical trials with FORADIL AEROLIZER suggested a higher incidence of serious asthma exacerbations in patients who received FORADIL AEROLIZER than in those who received placebo. (See WARNINGS)  



     Experience in Pediatric, Adolescent and Adult Patients with Asthma  

  Of the 5,824 patients in multiple-dose controlled clinical trials, 1,985 were treated with FORADIL AEROLIZER at the recommended dose of 12 mcg twice daily. The following table shows adverse events where the frequency was greater than or equal to 1% in the FORADIL twice daily group and where the rates in the FORADIL group exceeded placebo. Three adverse events showed dose ordering among tested doses of 6, 12 and 24 mcg administered twice daily; tremor, dizziness and dysphonia.



 NUMBER AND FREQUENCY OF ADVERSE EXPERIENCES IN PATIENTS 5 YEARS OF AGE AND OLDER FROM MULTIPLE-DOSE CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS 
 Adverse Event    FORADIL AEROLIZER12 mcg twice daily  Placebo           
                  n                (%)              n                (%)               
 Total Patients   1985             (100)            969              (100)             
                                                                                       
 Infection viral  341              (17.2)           166              (17.1)            
 Bronchitis       92               (4.6)            42               (4.3)             
 Chest infection  54               (2.7)            4                (0.4)             
 Dyspnea          42               (2.1)            16               (1.7)             
 Chest pain       37               (1.9)            13               (1.3)             
 Tremor           37               (1.9)            4                (0.4)             
 Dizziness        31               (1.6)            15               (1.5)             
 Insomnia         29               (1.5)            8                (0.8)             
 Tonsillitis      23               (1.2)            7                (0.7)             
 Rash             22               (1.1)            7                (0.7)             
 Dysphonia        19               (1.0)            9                (0.9)             
                
 

       In two 12-week controlled trials with combined enrollment of 1095 patients 12 years of age and older, FORADIL AEROLIZER 12 mcg twice daily was compared to FORADIL AEROLIZER 24 mcg twice daily, albuterol 180 mcg four times daily, and placebo. Serious asthma exacerbations (acute worsening of asthma resulting in hospitalization) occurred more commonly with FORADIL AEROLIZER 24 mcg twice daily than with the recommended dose of FORADIL AEROLIZER 12 mcg twice daily, albuterol, or placebo. The results are shown in the following table.



 NUMBER AND FREQUENCY OF SERIOUS ASTHMA EXACERBATIONS IN PATIENTS 12 YEARS OF AGE AND OLDER FROM TWO 12-WEEK CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS 
                    Foradil 12 mcg twice daily      Foradil 24 mcg twice daily      Albuterol 180 mcg four times daily      Placebo         
   Trial #1        
   Serious asthma exacerbations    0/136 (0)        4/135 (3.0%)  1    2/134 (1.5%)     0/136 (0)         
   Trial #2        
   Serious asthma exacerbations    1/139 (0.7%)     5/136 (3.7%)  2    0/138 (0)        2/141 (1.4%)      
   1  1 patient required intubation  2  2 patients had respiratory arrest; 1 of the patients died   
                
 

       In a 16-week, randomized, multi-center, double-blind, parallel-group trial, patients who received either 24 mcg twice daily or 12 mcg twice daily doses of FORADIL AEROLIZER experienced more serious asthma exacerbations than patients who received placebo (see CLINICAL TRIALS). The results are shown in the following table.



 NUMBER AND FREQUENCY OF SERIOUS ASTHMA EXACERBATIONS IN PATIENTS 12 YEARS OF AGE AND OLDER FROM A 16-WEEK TRIAL 
                    Foradil 12 mcg twice daily      Foradil 24 mcg twice daily      Placebo         
   Serious asthma exacerbations    3/527 (0.6%)     2/527 (0.4%)     1/514 (0.2%)      
              Experience in Children with Asthma  
   The safety of FORADIL AEROLIZER 12 mcg twice daily compared to FORADIL AEROLIZER 24 mcg twice daily and placebo was investigated in one large, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, 52-week clinical trial in 518 children with asthma (ages 5-12 years) in need of daily bronchodilators and anti-inflammatory treatment. More children who received FORADIL AEROLIZER 24 mcg twice daily than children who received FORADIL AEROLIZER 12 mcg twice daily or placebo experienced serious asthma exacerbations, as shown in the next table.



 NUMBER AND FREQUENCY OF SERIOUS ASTHMA EXACERBATIONS IN PATIENTS 5-12 YEARS OF AGE FROM A 52-WEEK TRIAL 
                    Foradil 12 mcg twice daily      Foradil 24 mcg twice daily      Placebo         
   Serious asthma exacerbations    8/171 (4.7%)     11/171 (6.4%)    0/176 (0)         
               
 

       The numbers and percent of patients who reported adverse events were comparable in the 12 mcg twice daily and placebo groups. In general, the pattern of the adverse events observed in children differed from the usual pattern seen in adults. The adverse events that were more frequent in the formoterol group than in the placebo group reflected infection/inflammation (viral infection, rhinitis, tonsillitis, gastroenteritis) or abdominal complaints (abdominal pain, nausea, dyspepsia).



     Experience in Adult Patients with COPD  

  Of the 1634 patients in two pivotal multiple-dose Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) controlled trials, 405 were treated with FORADIL AEROLIZER 12 mcg twice daily. The numbers and percent of patients who reported adverse events were comparable in the 12 mcg twice daily and placebo groups. Adverse events (AE's) experienced were similar to those seen in asthmatic patients, but with a higher incidence of COPD-related AE's in both placebo and formoterol treated patients.



       The following table shows adverse events where the frequency was greater than or equal to 1% in the FORADIL AEROLIZER group and where the rates in the FORADIL AEROLIZER group exceeded placebo. The two clinical trials included doses of 12 mcg and 24 mcg, administered twice daily. Seven adverse events showed dose ordering among tested doses of 12 and 24 mcg administered twice daily; pharyngitis, fever, muscle cramps, increased sputum, dysphonia, myalgia, and tremor.



 NUMBER AND FREQUENCY OF ADVERSE EXPERIENCES IN ADULT COPD PATIENTS TREATED IN MULTIPLE-DOSE CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS 
 Adverse Event    FORADIL AEROLIZER12 mcg twice daily  Placebo           
                  n                (%)              n                (%)               
                                                                                       
 Total patients   405              (100)            420              (100)             
                                                                                       
 Upper respiratory tract infection  30               (7.4)            24               (5.7)             
 Pain back        17               (4.2)            17               (4.0)             
 Pharyngitis      14               (3.5)            10               (2.4)             
 Pain chest       13               (3.2)            9                (2.1)             
 Sinusitis        11               (2.7)            7                (1.7)             
 Fever            9                (2.2)            6                (1.4)             
 Cramps leg       7                (1.7)            2                (0.5)             
 Cramps muscle    7                (1.7)            0                                  
 Anxiety          6                (1.5)            5                (1.2)             
 Pruritus         6                (1.5)            4                (1.0)             
 Sputum increased  6                (1.5)            5                (1.2)             
 Mouth dry        5                (1.2)            4                (1.0)             
                
 

       Overall, the frequency of all cardiovascular adverse events in the two pivotal studies was low and comparable to placebo (6.4% for FORADIL AEROLIZER 12 mcg twice daily, and 6.0% for placebo). There were no frequently-occurring specific cardiovascular adverse events for FORADIL AEROLIZER (frequency greater than or equal to 1% and greater than placebo).



       Other adverse reactions to FORADIL AEROLIZER are similar in nature to other selective beta2-adrenoceptor agonists; e.g., angina, hypertension or hypotension, tachycardia, arrhythmias, nervousness, headache, tremor, dry mouth, palpitation, muscle cramps, nausea, dizziness, fatigue, malaise, hypokalemia, hyperglycemia, metabolic acidosis and insomnia.



     Post Marketing Experience  

  In extensive worldwide marketing experience with FORADIL, serious exacerbations of asthma, including some that have been fatal, have been reported. While most of these cases have been in patients with severe or acutely deteriorating asthma (see WARNINGS), a few have occurred in patients with less severe asthma. It is not possible to determine from these individual case reports whether FORADIL AEROLIZER contributed to the events.



       Rare reports of anaphylactic reactions, including severe hypotension and angioedema, have also been received in association with the use of formoterol fumarate inhalation powder.  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ASTHMA RELATED DEATH

  WARNING: ASTHMA RELATED DEATH

    Long-acting beta    2    -adrenergic agonists (LABA), such as formoterol the active ingredient in FORADIL AEROLIZER, increase the risk of asthma-related death. Data from a large placebo-controlled US study that compared the safety of another LABA (salmeterol) or placebo added to usual asthma therapy showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in patients receiving salmeterol.  This finding with salmeterol is considered a class effect of LABA, including formoterol (see WARNINGS).  Currently available data are inadequate to determine whether concurrent use of inhaled corticosteroids or other long-term asthma control drugs mitigates the increased risk of asthma-related death from LABA.  



   Because of this risk, use of FORADIL AEROLIZER for the treatment of asthma without a concomitant long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid, is contraindicated. Use FORADIL AEROLIZER only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Once asthma control is achieved and maintained, assess the patient at regular intervals and step down therapy (e.g. discontinue FORADIL AEROLIZER) if possible without loss of asthma control, and maintain the patient on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Do not use FORADIL AEROLIZER for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low or medium dose inhaled corticosteroids.  



   Pediatric and Adolescent Patients  



   Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. For pediatric and adolescent patients with asthma who require addition of a LABA to an inhaled corticosteroid, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an inhaled corticosteroid and LABA should ordinarily be considered to ensure adherence with both drugs. In cases where use of a separate long-term asthma control medication (e.g. inhaled corticosteroid) and LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components. If adherence cannot be assured, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an inhaled corticosteroid and LABA is recommended.   
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
