<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="forfivo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following risks are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Clinical worsening and suicide risk [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ] 
 *    Neuropsychiatric symptoms and suicide risk in smoking cessation treatment [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ] 
 *    Activation of mania or hypomania [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )  ] 
 *    Seizures [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )  ] 
 *    Psychosis, and other neuropsychiatric events [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )  ] 
 *    Angle Closure Glaucoma [ see Warnings and precautions (  5.6  )  ] 
 *    Severe hypertension [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )  ] 
 *    Agitation and insomnia [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )  ] 
 *    Altered appetite and weight [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )  ] 
 *    Hypersensitivity reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )  ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are (incidence &gt;= 5%; &gt;= 2 times placebo rate): Dry mouth, nausea, insomnia, dizziness, pharyngitis, abdominal pain, agitation, anxiety, tremor, palpitation, sweating, tinnitus, myalgia, anorexia, urinary frequency, rash (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Edgemont Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-888- 594-4332 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or     www.fda.gov/medwatch      .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Controlled Clinical Trials  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Adverse reactions from    Table 5    occurring in at least 5% of patients treated with the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed below for the 300- and 400-mg/day dose groups.



   300 mg/day of bupropion sustained release:    Anorexia, dry mouth, rash, sweating, tinnitus, and tremor.



   400 mg/day of bupropion sustained release:    Abdominal pain, agitation, anxiety, dizziness, dry mouth, insomnia, myalgia, nausea, palpitation, pharyngitis, sweating, tinnitus, and urinary frequency.



 FORFIVO XL is bioequivalent to three 150 mg tablets of WELLBUTRIN XL  (r)  , which has been demonstrated to have similar bioavailability both to the immediate-release formulation of bupropion and to the sustained-release formulation of bupropion. The information included under this subsection and under subsections  6.2  and  6.3  is based primarily on data from controlled clinical trials with the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride.



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment with Bupropion Immediate Release or Bupropion Sustained Release  



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials, 9% and 11% of patients treated with 300 and 400 mg/day, respectively, of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride and 4% of patients treated with placebo discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions. The specific adverse reactions in these trials that led to discontinuation in at least 1% of patients treated with either 300 mg/day or 400 mg/day of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed in    Table 4    .



 Table 4. Treatment Discontinuations Due to Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Trials for Major Depressive Disorder using Bupropion Hydrochloride Sustained Release Formulation 
  Adverse Reaction               Bupropion HCl     300 mg/day(n = 376)         Bupropion HCl     400 mg/day(n = 114)    Placebo     (n = 385)         
  Rash                      2.4%                       0.9%                       0.0%                
  Nausea                    0.8%                       1.8%                       0.3%                
  Agitation                 0.3%                       1.8%                       0.3%                
  Migraine                  0.0%                       1.8%                       0.3%                
          In clinical trials with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion, 10% of patients and volunteers discontinued due to an adverse reaction. Reactions resulting in discontinuation, in addition to those listed above for the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, include vomiting, seizures, and sleep disturbances.
 

   Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among Patients Treated With Bupropion Immediate Release or Bupropion Sustained Release  



     Table 5    enumerates adverse reactions that occurred among patients treated with 300 and 400 mg/day of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride and with placebo in controlled trials. Reactions that occurred in either the 300- or 400-mg/day group at an incidence of 1% or more and were more frequent than in the placebo group are included. Reported adverse reactions were classified using a COSTART-based Dictionary.



 Accurate estimates of the incidence of adverse reactions associated with the use of any drug are difficult to obtain. Estimates are influenced by drug dose, detection technique, setting, physician judgments, etc. The figures cited cannot be used to predict precisely the incidence of untoward reactions in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. These incidence figures also cannot be compared with those obtained from other clinical studies involving related drug products as each group of drug trials is conducted under a different set of conditions.



 Finally, it is important to emphasize that the tabulation does not reflect the relative severity and/or clinical importance of the reactions. A better perspective on the serious adverse reactions associated with the use of bupropion is provided in the    Warnings and Precautions (  5  )    .



 Table 5. Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled TrialsAdverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of patients treated with either 300 or 400 mg/day of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, but equally or more frequently in the placebo group, were: abnormal dreams, accidental injury, acne, appetite increased, back pain, bronchitis, dysmenorrhea, dyspepsia, flatulence, flu syndrome, hypertension, neck pain, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, and tooth disorder. for Major Depressive Disorder 
 - Hyphen denotes adverse reactions occurring in greater than 0 but less than 0.5% of patients.   
  
  Body System/Adverse Reaction               Bupropion HCl   300 mg/day(n = 376)       Bupropion HCl   400 mg/day(n = 114)    Placebo     (n = 385)       
  Body (General)                                                                                              
    Headache                              26%                     25%                     23%                 
    Infection                             8%                      9%                      6%                  
    Abdominal pain                        3%                      9%                      2%                  
    Asthenia                              2%                      4%                      2%                  
    Chest pain                            3%                      4%                      1%                  
    Pain                                  2%                      3%                      2%                  
    Fever                                 1%                      2%                      -                   
  Cardiovascular                                                                                              
    Palpitation                           2%                      6%                      2%                  
    Flushing                              1%                      4%                      -                   
    Migraine                              1%                      4%                      1%                  
    Hot flashes                           1%                      3%                      1%                  
  Digestive                                                                                                   
    Dry mouth                             17%                     24%                     7%                  
    Nausea                                13%                     18%                     8%                  
    Constipation                          10%                     5%                      7%                  
    Diarrhea                              5%                      7%                      6%                  
    Anorexia                              5%                      3%                      2%                  
    Vomiting                              4%                      2%                      2%                  
    Dysphagia                             0%                      2%                      0%                  
  Musculoskeletal                                                                                             
    Myalgia                               2%                      6%                      3%                  
    Arthralgia                            1%                      4%                      1%                  
    Arthritis                             0%                      2%                      0%                  
    Twitch                                1%                      2%                      -                   
  Nervous system                                                                                              
    Insomnia                              11%                     16%                     6%                  
    Dizziness                             7%                      11%                     5%                  
    Agitation                             3%                      9%                      2%                  
    Anxiety                               5%                      6%                      3%                  
    Tremor                                6%                      3%                      1%                  
    Nervousness                           5%                      3%                      3%                  
    Somnolence                            2%                      3%                      2%                  
    Irritability                          3%                      2%                      2%                  
    Memory decreased                      -                       3%                      1%                  
    Paresthesia                           1%                      2%                      1%                  
    Central nervous system stimulation         2%                      1%                      1%                  
  Respiratory                                                                                                 
    Pharyngitis                           3%                      11%                     2%                  
    Sinusitis                             3%                      1%                      2%                  
    Increased cough                       1%                      2%                      1%                  
  Skin                                                                                                        
    Sweating                              6%                      5%                      2%                  
    Rash                                  5%                      4%                      1%                  
    Pruritus                              2%                      4%                      2%                  
    Urticaria                             2%                      1%                      0%                  
  Special senses                                                                                              
    Tinnitus                              6%                      6%                      2%                  
    Taste perversion                      2%                      4%                      -                   
    Blurred vision or diplopia            3%                      2%                      2%                  
  Urogenital                                                                                                  
    Urinary frequency                     2%                      5%                      2%                  
    Urinary urgency                       -                       2%                      0%                  
    Vaginal hemorrhageIncidence based on the number of female patients.    0%                      2%                      -                   
    Urinary tract infection               1%                      0%                      -                   
          Additional reactions to those listed in    Table 5    that occurred at an incidence of at least 1% in controlled clinical trials of the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride (300 to 600 mg/day) and that were numerically more frequent than placebo were: cardiac arrhythmias (5% vs. 4%), hypertension (4% vs. 2%), hypotension (3% vs. 2%), tachycardia (11% vs. 9%), appetite increase (4% vs. 2%), dyspepsia (3% vs. 2%), menstrual complaints (5% vs. 1%), akathisia (2% vs. 1%), impaired sleep quality (4% vs. 2%), sensory disturbance (4% vs. 3%), confusion (8% vs. 5%), decreased libido (3% vs. 2%), hostility (6% vs. 4%), auditory disturbance (5% vs. 3%), and gustatory disturbance (3% vs. 1%).
 

   Other adverse reactions occurring &lt; 1% in clinical trials:  



 Chills, facial edema, postural hypotension, stroke, syncope, bruxism, gastric reflux, gingivitis, glossitis, increased salivation, mouth ulcers, stomatitis, edema of tongue, ecchymosis, edema, abnormal coordination, decreased libido, depersonalization, emotional lability, hyperkinesia, hypertonia, hypesthesia, ataxia, and derealization, bronchospasm, accommodation abnormality, dry eye, impotence, and prostate disorder.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Bupropion hydrochloride. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Only those adverse reactions not previously listed for bupropion are included. The extent to which these reactions may be associated with FORFIVO XL is unknown.



   Cardiovascular-  complete atrioventricular block, extrasystoles, myocardial infarction, phlebitis, and pulmonary embolism.



   Gastrointestinal-  colitis, esophagitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gum hemorrhage, intestinal perforation, pancreatitis, and stomach ulcer.



   Endocrine-  hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia, and syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone.



   Hemic and Lymphatic-  anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional-  glycosuria.



   Musculoskeletal-  muscle rigidity/fever/rhabdomyolysis and muscle weakness.



   Nervous System-  abnormal electroencephalogram (EEG), aggression, akinesia, aphasia, coma, delirium,-dysarthria, dyskinesia, dystonia, extrapyramidal syndrome, hypokinesia, increased libido, neuralgia, neuropathy, and unmasking tardive dyskinesia.



   Skin-  alopecia, exfoliative dermatitis, and hirsutism.



   Eye-  mydriasis.



   Urogenital-  abnormal ejaculation, cystitis, dyspareunia, dysuria, gynecomastia, painful erection, salpingitis, urinary incontinence, and urinary retention.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SUICIDALITY and ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS; PSYCHIATRIC EVENTS and SMOKING CESSATION

  WARNING: SUICIDALITY and ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS; PSYCHIATRIC EVENTS and SMOKING CESSATION

    SUICIDALITY and ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS:  



   Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of FORFIVO XL or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. FORFIVO XL is not approved for use in pediatric patients [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ].   



   PSYCHIATRIC EVENTS and SMOKING CESSATION:  



   FORVIVO XL is not approved for smoking cessation treatment, but bupropion under the name ZYBAN(r) is approved for this use. Serious neuropsychiatric events, including but not limited to depression, suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation. Some cases may have been complicated by the symptoms of nicotine withdrawal in patients who stopped smoking. Depressed mood may be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. Depression, rarely including suicidal ideation, has been reported in smokers undergoing a smoking cessation attempt without medication. However, some of these symptoms have occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke.  



   All patients being treated with bupropion for smoking cessation treatment should be observed for neuropsychiatric symptoms including changes in behavior, hostility, agitation, depressed mood, and suicide-related events, including ideation, behavior, and attempted suicide. These symptoms, as well as worsening of pre-existing psychiatric illness and completed suicide have been reported in some patients attempting to quit smoking while taking ZYBAN in the postmarketing experience. When symptoms were reported, most were during treatment with ZYBAN, but some were following discontinuation of treatment with ZYBAN. These events have occurred in patients with and without pre-existing psychiatric disease; some have experienced worsening of their psychiatric illnesses. Patients with serious psychiatric illness such as schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, and major depressive disorder did not participate in the premarketing studies of ZYBAN.  



   Advise patients and caregivers that the patient using bupropion for smoking cessation should stop taking bupropion and contact a healthcare provider immediately if agitation, hostility, depressed mood, or changes in thinking or behavior that are not typical for the patient are observed, or if the patient develops suicidal ideation or suicidal behavior. In many postmarketing cases, resolution of symptoms after discontinuation of ZYBAN was reported, although in some cases the symptoms persisted; therefore, ongoing monitoring and supportive care should be provided until symptoms resolve.  



   The risks of using bupropion for smoking cessation should be weighed against the benefits of its use. ZYBAN has been demonstrated to increase the likelihood of abstinence from smoking for as long as 6 months compared to treatment with placebo. The health benefits of quitting smoking are immediate and substantial [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17  )  ].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: SUICIDALITY and ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS; PSYCHIATRIC EVENTS and SMOKING CESSATION  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Closely monitor for clinical worsening and suicidal thinking and behavior (5.1). 
 *  Serious neuropsychiatric events, including depression, suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation. Stop bupropion and contact a healthcare provider immediately if agitation, hostility, depressed mood, or changes in thinking or behavior that are not typical for the patient are observed, or if the patient develops suicidal ideation or suicidal behavior (5.2). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Activation of mania/ hypomania: Screen patients for bipolar disorder and monitor for manic symptoms. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Seizure risk: The risk is dose-dependent. Discontinue if seizure occurs (  4  ,  5.4  ,  7.6  ) 
 *    Psychosis and other neuropsychiatric events: Discontinue if these events occur. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Angle Closure Glaucoma: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants (  5.6  ) 
 *    Severe hypertension: Monitor blood pressure periodically. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk in Treating Psychiatric Disorder



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) show that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4,400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1,000 patients treated) are provided in   Table 1    .



 Table 1. Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1,000 Patients Treated 
       Age Range                                                                                         
                        Increases Compared to Placebo                                                   
  &lt;18                   14 additional cases                                                             
  18-24                 5 additional cases                                                              
                             Decreases Compared to Placebo                                              
  25-64                 1 fewer case                                                                    
  &gt;=65                  6 fewer cases                                                                   
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



 All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases [ see    Boxed Warning  and Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )    ].



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



 Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers [ see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )    ]. Prescription for FORFIVO XL should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



    5.2 Neuropsychiatric Symptoms and Suicide Risk in Smoking Cessation Treatment



  FORFIVO XL is not approved forsmoking cessation treatment, but bupropion under the name ZYBAN is approved for this use. Serious neuropsychiatric symptoms have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation [ see    Boxed Warning  and Adverse Reactions (  6  )    ]. These have included changes in mood (including depression and mania), psychosis, hallucinations, paranoia, delusions, homicidal ideation, hostility, agitation, aggression, anxiety, and panic, as well as suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide [ see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )    ].



    5.3 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



  A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It should be noted that FORFIVO XL is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



    5.4 Seizures



  Bupropion is associated with a dose-related risk of seizures. The risk of seizures is also related to patient factors, clinical situations, and concomitant medications, which must be considered in selection of patients for therapy with FORFIVO XL. FORFIVO XL should be discontinued and not restarted in patients who experience a seizure while on treatment.



  Dose  



 At doses up to 300 mg/day of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride (WELLBUTRIN SR  (r)  ), the incidence of seizure is approximately 0.1% (1/1,000).



 Data for the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride revealed a seizure incidence of approximately 0.4% (i.e., 13 of 3,200 patients followed prospectively) in patients treated at doses in a range of 300 to 450 mg/day. This seizure incidence (0.4%) may exceed that of some other marketed antidepressants.



 Additional data accumulated for the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride suggested that the estimated seizure incidence increases almost tenfold between 450 and 600 mg/day. The 600 mg dose is twice the usual adult dose and one and one-third the maximum recommended daily dose (450 mg) of FORFIVO XL. This disproportionate increase in seizure incidence with dose incrementation calls for caution in dosing.



  Patient Factors  



 Predisposing factors that may increase the risk of seizure with bupropion use include history of head trauma or prior seizure, central nervous system (CNS) tumor, the presence of severe hepatic cirrhosis, and concomitant medications that lower seizure threshold.



  Clinical Situations  



 Circumstances associated with an increased seizure risk include, among others, excessive use of alcohol or sedatives; addiction to opiates, cocaine, or stimulants; use of over-the-counter stimulants and anorectics; and diabetes treated with oral hypoglycemics or insulin.



  Concomitant Medications  



 Many medications (e.g., antipsychotics, antidepressants, theophylline, and systemic steroids) are known to lower seizure threshold.



  Recommendations for Reducing the Risk of Seizure:  



 Retrospective analysis of clinical experience gained during the development of bupropion suggests that the risk of seizure may be minimized if



 *    the total daily dose of bupropion does not   exceed 450 mg, 
 *    the rate of incrementation of the bupropion dose is gradual. 
       5.5 Psychosis and Other Neuropsychiatric Events
 

  Depressed patients treated with bupropion have been reported to show a variety of neuropsychiatric signs and symptoms, including delusions, hallucinations, psychosis, concentration disturbance, paranoia, and confusion. In some cases, these symptoms abated upon dose reduction and/or withdrawal of treatment. It is recommended stopping bupropion when the symptoms occurred.



     5.6 Angle Closure Glaucoma  



   Angle Closure Glaucoma: The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including FORFIVO XL may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.  



    5.7 Severe Hypertension



  In clinical practice, hypertension, in some cases severe, requiring acute treatment, has been reported in patients receiving bupropion alone and in combination with nicotine replacement therapy. These reactions have been observed in both patients with and without evidence of preexisting hypertension.



 Data from a comparative study of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride (ZYBAN Sustained-Release Tablets), nicotine transdermal system (NTS), the combination of sustained-release bupropion hydrochloride plus NTS, and placebo as an aid to smoking cessation suggest a higher incidence of treatment-emergent hypertension in patients treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion hydrochloride and NTS. Monitoring of blood pressure is recommended in patients who receive the combination of bupropion and nicotine replacement.



 There is no clinical experience establishing the safety of FORFIVO XL tablets in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Therefore, care should be exercised if it is used in these groups.



 Bupropion was well tolerated in depressed patients who had previously developed orthostatic hypotension while receiving tricyclic antidepressants, and was also generally well tolerated in a group of 36 depressed inpatients with stable congestive heart failure (CHF). However, bupropion was associated with a rise in supine blood pressure in the study of patients with CHF, resulting in discontinuation of treatment in 2 patients for exacerbation of baseline hypertension.



    5.8 Agitation and Insomnia



  Increased restlessness, agitation, anxiety, and insomnia, especially shortly after initiation of treatment, have been associated with treatment with bupropion.



 Patients in placebo-controlled trials of major depressive disorder with sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, experienced agitation, anxiety, and insomnia as shown in   Table 2    .



 Table 2. Incidence of Agitation, Anxiety, and Insomnia in Placebo-Controlled Trials of Bupropion HCl Sustained-release Tablets for Major Depressive Disorder 
  Adverse Reactions     Term         Bupropion HCl     300 mg/day(n = 376)         Bupropion HCl     400 mg/day(n = 114)    Placebo     (n = 385)         
  Agitation                  3%                         9%                         2%                  
  Anxiety                    5%                         6%                         3%                  
  Insomnia                   11%                        16%                        6%                  
          In clinical studies of major depressive disorder, these symptoms were sometimes of sufficient magnitude to require treatment with sedative/hypnotic drugs.
 

 Symptoms in these studies were sufficiently severe to require discontinuation of treatment in 1% and 2.6% of patients treated with 300 and 400 mg/day, respectively, of bupropion hydrochloride sustained-release tablets and 0.8% of patients treated with placebo.



    5.9 Altered Appetite and Weight



  In placebo-controlled short-term studies of major depressive disorder using the sustained-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, patients experienced weight gain or weight loss as shown in   Table 3    .



 Table 3. Incidence of Weight Gain and Weight Loss in Placebo-Controlled Trials of Bupropion Hydrochloride Sustained-release tablets for Major Depressive Disorder 
  Weight Change                Bupropion HCl     300 mg/day(n = 339)         Bupropion HCl     400 mg/day(n = 112)    Placebo     (n = 347)         
  Gained &gt;5 lbs           3%                         2%                         4%                  
  Lost &gt;5 lbs             14%                        19%                        6%                  
          In studies conducted with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride, 35% of patients receiving tricyclic antidepressants gained weight, compared to 9% of patients treated with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion hydrochloride. If weight loss is a major presenting sign of a patient's depressive illness, the anorectic and/or weight-reducing potential of FORFIVO XL tablets should be considered.
 

    5.10 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions characterized by symptoms such as pruritus, urticaria, angioedema, and dyspnea requiring medical treatment have been reported in clinical trials with bupropion. In addition, there have been rare spontaneous postmarketing reports of erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and anaphylactic shock associated with bupropion. A patient should stop taking FORFIVO XL and consult a doctor if experiencing allergic or anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions (e.g., skin rash, pruritus, hives, chest pain, edema, and shortness of breath) during treatment.



 Arthralgia, myalgia, and fever with rash and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity have been reported in association with bupropion. These symptoms may resemble serum sickness [ see Contraindications (  4  )    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
