<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fortesta" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reaction (incidence &gt;= 3%) is skin reactions at the application site (16.1%). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ENDO at 1-800-462-3636 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

    6.1 Clinical Trial Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In a controlled multicenter, open label, non-comparative 90-day clinical study, 149 hypogonadal patients were treated with FORTESTA  [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  . Adverse reactions occurred in 22.8% (34/149) of patients. The most common adverse reaction reported in this study was skin reactions associated with the site of application (16.1%; 24/149) of which 79% (19/24) were mild, and the remainder were moderate (21%; 5/24) (Table 3).



 Table 3 - Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;1% Patients in the US Phase 3 Clinical Trial of FORTESTA 
 Adverse Reaction  Number (%) of PatientsN = 149   
   Skin reaction   24 (16.1%)       
   Prostatic specific antigen increased   2 (1.3%)         
   Abnormal dreams   2 (1.3%)         
        During the 90 day trial 5 patients (3.4%) discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions. These reactions were: 1 patient with contact dermatitis (considered probably related to FORTESTA application), 1 with application site reaction (considered probably related to FORTESTA application), 1 with gastrointestinal hypomotility (considered possibly related to FORTESTA application), 1 with severe dyspnea (considered not related to FORTESTA application), and 1 with moderate contusion (considered not related to FORTESTA application).
 

     6.2 Postmarketing Experience  

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of FORTESTA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure (Table 4).



 Table 4 - Adverse Drug Reactions from Post approval Experience of FORTESTA by System Organ Class 
 System Organ Class  Adverse Reaction   
  Blood and lymphatic system disorders   Polycythemia     
  Eye disorders    Vitreous detachment   
  Gastrointestinal disorders   Abdominal symptoms   
  General disorders and administrative site conditions   Application site erythema, irritation, pruritus, and swelling; fatigue, influenza like illness, and malaise.   
  Investigations   Decreased serum testosterone, increased hematocrit and hemoglobin   
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders   Pain in extremity   
  Nervous system disorders   Dizziness, headache, and migraine   
  Reproductive system and breast disorders   Erectile dysfunction, and priapism   
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders   Allergic dermatitis, erythema, rash, and papular rash.       
  Vascular disorders       Venous thromboembolism   
  Cardiovascular disorders   Myocardial infarction, stroke   
          Secondary Exposure to Testosterone in Children  Cases of secondary exposure to testosterone resulting in virilization of children have been reported in postmarketing surveillance of testosterone gel products. Signs and symptoms of these reported cases have included enlargement of the clitoris (with surgical intervention) or the penis, development of pubic hair, increased erections and libido, aggressive behavior, and advanced bone age. In most cases with a reported outcome, these signs and symptoms were reported to have regressed with removal of the testosterone gel exposure. In a few cases, however, enlarged genitalia did not fully return to age appropriate normal size, and bone age remained modestly greater than chronological age. In some of the cases, direct contact with the sites of application on the skin of men using testosterone gel was reported. In at least one reported case, the reporter considered the possibility of secondary exposure from items such as the testosterone gel user's shirts and/or other fabric, such as towels and sheets  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE

    WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE  

    *  Virilization has been reported in children who were secondarily exposed to testosterone gel [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) and Adverse Reactions (6.2)]. 
 *  Children should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using FORTESTA [see Dosage and Administration (2.2) and Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  Healthcare providers should advise patients to strictly adhere to recommended instructions for use [see Dosage and Administration (2.2), Warnings and Precautions (5.2) and Patient Counseling Information (17)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: SECONDARY EXPOSURE TO TESTOSTERONE  
 

 *  Virilization has been reported in children who were secondarily exposed to testosterone gel. (5.2, 6.2) 
 *  Children should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using FORTESTA. (2.2, 5.2) 
 *  Healthcare providers should advise patients to strictly adhere to recommended instructions for use. (2.2, 5.2, 17) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Monitor patients with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) for worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Avoid unintentional exposure of women or children to FORTESTA. Secondary exposure to testosterone can produce signs of virilization. FORTESTA should be discontinued until the cause of virilization is identified. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Venous thromboembolism (VTE), including deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE) have been reported in patients using testosterone products. Evaluate patients with signs or symptoms consistent with DVT or PE. (  5.4  )  
 *  Some postmarketing studies have shown an increased risk of myocardial infarction and stroke associated with use of testosterone replacement therapy. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Exogenous administration of androgens may lead to azoospermia. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Edema with or without congestive heart failure (CHF) may be a complication in patients with pre-existing cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Sleep apnea may occur in those with risk factors. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Monitor serum testosterone, prostate specific antigen (PSA), hemoglobin, hematocrit, liver function tests and lipid concentrations periodically. (  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.8  ,  5.12  ) 
 *  FORTESTA is flammable until dry. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

    5.1 Worsening of Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia (BPH) and Potential Risk of Prostate Cancer  



    *  Patients with BPH treated with androgens are at an increased risk of worsening of signs and symptoms of BPH. Monitor patients with BPH for worsening signs and symptoms. 
 *  Patients treated with androgens may be at increased risk for prostate cancer. Evaluation of the patients for the presence of prostate cancer prior to initiating and during treatment with androgens is appropriate [see Contraindications (  4  )] . 
        5.2 Potential for Secondary Exposure to Testosterone  
 

  Cases of secondary exposure resulting in virilization of children have been reported in postmarketing surveillance of testosterone gel products. Signs and symptoms have included enlargement of the penis or clitoris, development of pubic hair, increased erections and libido, aggressive behavior, and advanced bone age. In most cases, these signs and symptoms regressed with removal of the exposure to testosterone gel. In a few cases, however, enlarged genitalia did not fully return to age-appropriate normal size, and bone age remained modestly greater than chronological age. The risk of transfer was increased in some of these cases by not adhering to precautions for the appropriate use of the topical testosterone product. Children and women should avoid contact with unwashed or unclothed application sites in men using FORTESTA [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )  ].



 Inappropriate changes in genital size or development of pubic hair or libido in children, or changes in body hair distribution, significant increase in acne, or other signs of virilization in adult women should be brought to the attention of a physician and the possibility of secondary exposure to testosterone gel should also be brought to the attention of a physician. Testosterone gel should be promptly discontinued until the cause of virilization has been identified.



     5.3 Polycythemia  



  Increases in hematocrit, reflective of increases in red blood cell mass, may require lowering or discontinuation of testosterone. Check hematocrit prior to initiating treatment. It would also be appropriate to re-evaluate the hematocrit 3 to 6 months after starting treatment, and then annually. If hematocrit becomes elevated, stop therapy until hematocrit decreases to an acceptable concentration. An increase in red blood cell mass may increase the risk of thromboembolic events.



     5.4 Venous Thromboembolism  



   There have been Postmarketing reports of venous thromboembolic events, including deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE), in patients using testosterone products, such as FORTESTA. Evaluate patients who report symptoms of pain, edema, warmth and erythema in the lower extremity for DVT and those who present with acute shortness of breath for PE. If a venous thromboembolic event is suspected, discontinue treatment with FORTESTA and initiate appropriate workup and management.  



     5.5 Cardiovascular Risk  



   Long term clinical safety trials have not been conducted to assess the cardiovascular outcomes of testosterone replacement therapy in men. To date, epidemiologic studies and randomized controlled trials have been inconclusive for determining the risk of major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE), such as non-fatal myocardial infarction, non-fatal stroke, and cardiovascular death, with the use of testosterone compared to non-use. Some studies, but not all, have reported an increased risk of MACE in association with use of testosterone replacement therapy in men. Patients should be informed of this possible risk when deciding whether to use or to continue to use FORTESTA.  



     5.6 Use in Women  



  Due to the lack of controlled evaluations in women and potential virilizing effects, FORTESTA is not indicated for use in women [see Contraindications (  4  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ,  8.3  )]  .



     5.7 Potential for Adverse Effects on Spermatogenesis  



  With large doses of exogenous androgens, including FORTESTA, spermatogenesis may be suppressed through feedback inhibition of pituitary FSH which could possibly lead to adverse effects on semen parameters including sperm count.



     5.8 Hepatic Adverse Effects  



  Prolonged use of high doses of orally active 17-alpha-alkyl androgens (e.g. methyltestosterone) has been associated with serious hepatic adverse effects (peliosis hepatis, hepatic neoplasms, cholestatic hepatitis and jaundice). Peliosis hepatis can be a life-threatening or fatal complication. Long-term therapy with testosterone enanthate has produced multiple hepatic adenomas. FORTESTA is not known to cause these adverse effects.



     5.9 Edema  



  Androgens, including FORTESTA, may promote retention of sodium and water. Edema, with or without congestive heart failure, may be a serious complication in patients with pre-existing cardiac, renal, or hepatic disease [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )]  .



     5.10 Gynecomastia  



  Gynecomastia may develop and persist in patients being treated with androgens, including FORTESTA, for hypogonadism.



     5.11 Sleep Apnea  



  The treatment of hypogonadal men with testosterone may potentiate sleep apnea in some patients, especially those with risk factors such as obesity or chronic lung diseases.



     5.12 Lipids  



  Changes in serum lipid profile may require dose adjustment or discontinuation of testosterone therapy.



     5.13 Hypercalcemia  



  Androgens, including FORTESTA, should be used with caution in cancer patients at risk of hypercalcemia (and associated hypercalciuria). Regular monitoring of serum calcium concentrations is recommended in these patients.



     5.14 Decreased Thyroxine-binding globulin  



  Androgens, including FORTESTA, may decrease concentrations of thyroxin-binding globulins, resulting in decreased total T4 serum concentrations and increased resin uptake of T3 and T4. Free thyroid hormone concentrations remain unchanged, however, and there is no clinical evidence of thyroid dysfunction.



     5.15 Flammability  



  Alcohol based products, including FORTESTA, are flammable; therefore, patients should be advised to avoid smoking, fire or flame until the FORTESTA gel has dried.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
