<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="forteo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;10%) include: arthralgia, pain, and nausea (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-545-5979 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Treatment of Osteoporosis in Men and Postmenopausal Women  



 The safety of FORTEO in the treatment of osteoporosis in men and postmenopausal women was assessed in two randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials of 1382 patients (21% men, 79% women) aged 28 to 86 years (mean 67 years). The median durations of the trials were 11 months for men and 19 months for women, with 691 patients exposed to FORTEO and 691 patients to placebo. All patients received 1000 mg of calcium plus at least 400 IU of vitamin D supplementation per day.



 The incidence of all cause mortality was 1% in the FORTEO group and 1% in the placebo group. The incidence of serious adverse events was 16% in FORTEO patients and 19% in placebo patients. Early discontinuation due to adverse events occurred in 7% of FORTEO patients and 6% of placebo patients.



   Table 1  lists adverse events from the two principal osteoporosis trials in men and postmenopausal women that occurred in &gt;=2% of FORTEO-treated and more frequently than placebo-treated patients.



 Table 1. Percentage of Patients with Adverse Events Reported by at Least 2% of FORTEO-Treated Patients and in More FORTEO-Treated Patients than Placebo-Treated Patients from the Two Principal Osteoporosis Trials in Women and MenAdverse Events are Shown Without Attribution of Causality 
                                                                  FORTEO  N=691        Placebo  N=691      
     Event Classification                                         (%)                  (%)                 
     Body as a Whole                                                                                       
   Pain                                                         21.3                 20.5                  
   Headache                                                     7.5                  7.4                   
   Asthenia                                                     8.7                  6.8                   
   Neck pain                                                    3.0                  2.7                   
     Cardiovascular                                                                                        
   Hypertension                                                 7.1                  6.8                   
   Angina pectoris                                              2.5                  1.6                   
   Syncope                                                      2.6                  1.4                   
     Digestive System                                                                                      
   Nausea                                                       8.5                  6.7                   
   Constipation                                                 5.4                  4.5                   
   Diarrhea                                                     5.1                  4.6                   
   Dyspepsia                                                    5.2                  4.1                   
   Vomiting                                                     3.0                  2.3                   
   Gastrointestinal disorder                                    2.3                  2.0                   
   Tooth disorder                                               2.0                  1.3                   
     Musculoskeletal                                                                                       
   Arthralgia                                                   10.1                 8.4                   
   Leg cramps                                                   2.6                  1.3                   
     Nervous System                                                                                        
   Dizziness                                                    8.0                  5.4                   
   Depression                                                   4.1                  2.7                   
   Insomnia                                                     4.3                  3.6                   
   Vertigo                                                      3.8                  2.7                   
     Respiratory System                                                                                    
   Rhinitis                                                     9.6                  8.8                   
   Cough increased                                              6.4                  5.5                   
   Pharyngitis                                                  5.5                  4.8                   
   Dyspnea                                                      3.6                  2.6                   
   Pneumonia                                                    3.9                  3.3                   
     Skin and Appendages                                                                                   
   Rash                                                         4.9                  4.5                   
   Sweating                                                     2.2                  1.7                   
             Immunogenicity  - In the clinical trial, antibodies that cross-reacted with teriparatide were detected in 3% of women (15/541) receiving FORTEO. Generally, antibodies were first detected following 12 months of treatment and diminished after withdrawal of therapy. There was no evidence of hypersensitivity reactions or allergic reactions among these patients. Antibody formation did not appear to have effects on serum calcium, or on bone mineral density (BMD) response.
 

     Laboratory Findings  



     Serum Calcium  - FORTEO transiently increased serum calcium, with the maximal effect observed at approximately 4 to 6 hours post-dose. Serum calcium measured at least 16 hours post-dose was not different from pretreatment levels. In clinical trials, the frequency of at least 1 episode of transient hypercalcemia in the 4 to 6 hours after FORTEO administration was increased from 2% of women and none of the men treated with placebo to 11% of women and 6% of men treated with FORTEO. The number of patients treated with FORTEO whose transient hypercalcemia was verified on consecutive measurements was 3% of women and 1% of men.



     Urinary Calcium  - FORTEO increased urinary calcium excretion, but the frequency of hypercalciuria in clinical trials was similar for patients treated with FORTEO and placebo  [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  .



     Serum Uric Acid  - FORTEO increased serum uric acid concentrations. In clinical trials, 3% of FORTEO patients had serum uric acid concentrations above the upper limit of normal compared with 1% of placebo patients. However, the hyperuricemia did not result in an increase in gout, arthralgia, or urolithiasis.



     Renal Function  - No clinically important adverse renal effects were observed in clinical studies. Assessments included creatinine clearance; measurements of blood urea nitrogen (BUN), creatinine, and electrolytes in serum; urine specific gravity and pH; and examination of urine sediment.



     Studies in Men and Women with Glucocorticoid-Induced Osteoporosis  



 The safety of FORTEO in the treatment of men and women with glucocorticoid-induced osteoporosis was assessed in a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled trial of 428 patients (19% men, 81% women) aged 22 to 89 years (mean 57 years) treated with &gt;= 5mg per day prednisone or equivalent for a minimum of 3 months. The duration of the trial was 18 months with 214 patients exposed to FORTEO and 214 patients exposed to oral daily bisphosphonate (active control). All patients received 1000 mg of calcium plus 800 IU of vitamin D supplementation per day.



 The incidence of all cause mortality was 4% in the FORTEO group and 6% in the active control group. The incidence of serious adverse events was 21% in FORTEO patients and 18% in active control patients, and included pneumonia (3% FORTEO, 1% active control). Early discontinuation because of adverse events occurred in 15% of FORTEO patients and 12% of active control patients, and included dizziness (2% FORTEO, 0% active control).



 Adverse events reported at a higher incidence in the FORTEO group and with at least a 2% difference in FORTEO-treated patients compared with active control-treated patients were: nausea (14%, 7%), gastritis (7%, 3%), pneumonia (6%, 3%), dyspnea (6%, 3%), insomnia (5%, 1%), anxiety (4%, 1%), and herpes zoster (3%, 1%), respectively.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of FORTEO. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  Osteosarcoma: Cases of bone tumor and osteosarcoma have been reported rarely in the postmarketing period. The causality to FORTEO use is unclear. Long term osteosarcoma surveillance studies are ongoing [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Hypercalcemia: Hypercalcemia greater than 13.0 mg/dL has been reported with FORTEO use. 
    Adverse events reported since market introduction that were temporally (but not necessarily causally) related to FORTEO therapy include the following:
 

 *  Allergic Reactions: Anaphylactic reactions, drug hypersensitivity, angioedema, urticaria 
 *  Investigations: Hyperuricemia 
 *  Respiratory System: Acute dyspnea, chest pain 
 *  Musculoskeletal: Muscle spasms of the leg or back 
 *  Other: Injection site reactions including injection site pain, swelling and bruising; oro-facial edema 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK OF OSTEOSARCOMA



  WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK OF OSTEOSARCOMA



    In male and female rats, teriparatide caused an increase in the incidence of osteosarcoma (a malignant bone tumor) that was dependent on dose and treatment duration. The effect was observed at systemic exposures to teriparatide ranging from 3 to 60 times the exposure in humans given a 20-mcg dose. Because of the uncertain relevance of the rat osteosarcoma finding to humans, prescribe FORTEO  (r)   only for patients for whom the potential benefits are considered to outweigh the potential risk. FORTEO should not be prescribed for patients who are at increased baseline risk for osteosarcoma (including those with Paget's disease of bone or unexplained elevations of alkaline phosphatase, pediatric and young adult patients with open epiphyses, or prior external beam or implant radiation therapy involving the skeleton)   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), Adverse Reactions (  6.2  ), and Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.1  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK OF OSTEOSARCOMA  



   See full prescribing information for complete   boxed warning  .  



 *  In rats, teriparatide caused an increase in the incidence of osteosarcoma, a malignant bone tumor. (5.1, 13.1) 
 *  Because of the uncertain relevance of the rat osteosarcoma finding to humans, prescribe FORTEO only for patients for whom potential benefits outweigh potential risk. (5.1) 
 *  FORTEO should not be prescribed for patients at increased baseline risk for osteosarcoma (e.g., those with Paget's disease of bone or unexplained elevations of alkaline phosphatase, pediatric and young adult patients with open epiphyses, or prior external beam or implant radiation therapy involving the skeleton). (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Patients with Paget's disease of bone, pediatric and young adult patients with open epiphyses, and patients with prior external beam or implant radiation involving the skeleton: Should not be treated with FORTEO (  5.1  ,  8.4  ) 
 *  Treatment duration: Use of FORTEO for more than 2 years during a patient's lifetime is not recommended. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Patients with bone metastases, history of skeletal malignancies, metabolic bone diseases other than osteoporosis, or hypercalcemic disorders: Should not be treated with FORTEO (  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.5  ) 
 *  Laboratory alterations: FORTEO may increase serum calcium, urinary calcium, and serum uric acid (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Urolithiasis: Use with caution in patients with active or recent urolithiasis because of risk of exacerbation (  5.6  ) 
 *  Orthostatic hypotension: Transient orthostatic hypotension may occur with initial doses of FORTEO (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Osteosarcoma



  In male and female rats, teriparatide caused an increase in the incidence of osteosarcoma (a malignant bone tumor) that was dependent on dose and treatment duration [see  Boxed Warning  and Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.1  )]  . FORTEO should not be prescribed for patients at increased baseline risk of osteosarcoma.



 These include:



 *  Paget's disease of bone. Unexplained elevations of alkaline phosphatase may indicate Paget's disease of bone. 
 *  Pediatric and young adult patients with open epiphyses. 
 *  Prior external beam or implant radiation therapy involving the skeleton. 
    Patients should be encouraged to enroll in the voluntary FORTEO Patient Registry, which is designed to collect information about any potential risk of osteosarcoma in patients who have taken FORTEO. Enrollment information can be obtained by calling 1-866-382-6813, or by visiting www.forteoregistry.rti.org  
 

    5.2 Treatment Duration



  The safety and efficacy of FORTEO have not been evaluated beyond 2 years of treatment. Consequently, use of the drug for more than 2 years during a patients' lifetime is not recommended.



    5.3 Bone Metastases and Skeletal Malignancies



  Patients with bone metastases or a history of skeletal malignancies should not be treated with FORTEO.



    5.4 Metabolic Bone Diseases



  Patients with metabolic bone diseases other than osteoporosis should not be treated with FORTEO.



    5.5 Hypercalcemia and Hypercalcemic Disorders



  FORTEO has not been studied in patients with pre-existing hypercalcemia. These patients should not be treated with FORTEO because of the possibility of exacerbating hypercalcemia. Patients known to have an underlying hypercalcemic disorder, such as primary hyperparathyroidism, should not be treated with FORTEO.



    5.6 Urolithiasis or Pre-existing Hypercalciuria



  In clinical trials, the frequency of urolithiasis was similar in patients treated with FORTEO and placebo. However, FORTEO has not been studied in patients with active urolithiasis. If active urolithiasis or pre-existing hypercalciuria are suspected, measurement of urinary calcium excretion should be considered. FORTEO should be used with caution in patients with active or recent urolithiasis because of the potential to exacerbate this condition.



    5.7 Orthostatic Hypotension



  FORTEO should be administered initially under circumstances in which the patient can sit or lie down if symptoms of orthostatic hypotension occur. In short-term clinical pharmacology studies with teriparatide, transient episodes of symptomatic orthostatic hypotension were observed in 5% of patients. Typically, an event began within 4 hours of dosing and spontaneously resolved within a few minutes to a few hours. When transient orthostatic hypotension occurred, it happened within the first several doses, it was relieved by placing the person in a reclining position, and it did not preclude continued treatment.



    5.8 Drug Interactions



  Hypercalcemia may predispose patients to digitalis toxicity. Because FORTEO transiently increases serum calcium, patients receiving digoxin should use FORTEO with caution [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
