<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fosamax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

     Clinical Studies In clinical studies of up to five years in duration adverse experiences associated with FOSAMAX usually were mild, and generally did not require discontinuation of therapy.



 FOSAMAX has been evaluated for safety in approximately 8000 postmenopausal women in clinical studies.



        Treatment of osteoporosis        Postmenopausal women In two identically designed, three-year, placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter studies (United States and Multinational; n=994), discontinuation of therapy due to any clinical adverse experience occurred in 4.1% of 196 patients treated with FOSAMAX 10 mg/day and 6.0% of 397 patients treated with placebo. In the Fracture Intervention Trial (n=6459), discontinuation of therapy due to any clinical adverse experience occurred in 9.1% of 3236 patients treated with FOSAMAX 5 mg/day for 2 years and 10 mg/day for either one or two additional years and 10.1% of 3223 patients treated with placebo. Discontinuations due to upper gastrointestinal adverse experiences were: FOSAMAX, 3.2%; placebo, 2.7%. In these study populations, 49-54% had a history of gastrointestinal disorders at baseline and 54-89% used nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or aspirin at some time during the studies. Adverse experiences from these studies considered by the investigators as possibly, probably, or definitely drug related in &gt;=1% of patients treated with either FOSAMAX or placebo are presented in the following table.



 Osteoporosis Treatment Studies in Postmenopausal Women: Adverse Experiences Considered Possibly, Probably, or Definitely Drug Related by the Investigators and Reported in &gt;=1% of Patients 
                                                                                                     United States/Studies  Multinational                     FractureTrial       Intervention                
                            FOSAMAX  *  %         (n=196)     Placebo%    (n=397)        FOSAMAX        %      (n=3236)   Placebo%(n=3223)            
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                                                      
    abdominal pain          6.6                        4.8                        1.5                        1.5                         
    nausea                  3.6                        4.0                        1.1                        1.5                         
    dyspepsia               3.6                        3.5                        1.1                        1.2                         
    constipation            3.1                        1.8                        0.0                        0.2                         
    diarrhea                3.1                        1.8                        0.6                        0.3                         
    flatulence              2.6                        0.5                        0.2                        0.3                         
    acid regurgitation      2.0                        4.3                        1.1                        0.9                         
    esophageal ulcer        1.5                        00                         0.1                        0.1                         
    vomiting                1.0                        1.5                        0.2                        0.3                         
    dysphagia               1.0                        0.0                        0.1                        0.1                         
    abdominal distention    1.0                        0.8                        0.0                        0.0                         
    gastritis               0.5                        1.3                        0.6                        0.7                         
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                                                       
    musculoskeletal (bone,   muscle or joint) pain  4.1                        2.5                        0.4                        0.3                         
    muscle cram             0.0                        1.0                        0.2                        0.1                         
   Nervous System/Psychiatric                                                                                                                 
    headache                2.6                        1.5                        0.2                        0.2                         
    dizziness               0.0                        1.0                        0.0                        0.1                         
   Special Senses                                                                                                                        
    taste perversion        0.5                        1.0                        0.1                        0.0                         
       *     10 mg/day for three years       5 mg/day for 2 years and 10 mg/day for either 1 or 2 additional years Rarely, rash and erythema have occurred.
 

 One patient treated with FOSAMAX (10 mg/day), who had a history of peptic ulcer disease and gastrectomy and who was taking concomitant aspirin developed an anastomotic ulcer with mild hemorrhage, which was considered drug related. Aspirin and FOSAMAX were discontinued and the patient recovered.



 The adverse experience profile was similar for the 401 patients treated with either 5 or 20 mg doses of FOSAMAX in the United States and Multinational studies. The adverse experience profile for the 296 patients who received continued treatment with either 5 or 10 mg doses of FOSAMAX in the two-year extension of these studies (treatment years 4 and 5) was similar to that observed during the three-year placebo-controlled period. During the extension period, of the 151 patients treated with FOSAMAX 10 mg/day, the proportion of patients who discontinued therapy due to any clinical adverse experience was similar to that during the first three years of the study.



 In a one-year, double-blind, multicenter study, the overall safety and tolerability profiles of once weekly FOSAMAX 70 mg and FOSAMAX 10 mg daily were similar. The adverse experiences considered by the investigators as possibly, probably, or definitely drug related in &gt;=1% of patients in either treatment group are presented in the following 



 table.



       Osteoporosis Treatment Studies in Postmenopausal Women: Adverse Experiences Considered Possibly, Probably, or Definitely Drug Related by the Investigators and Reported in &gt;=1% of Patients 
                                                     Once Weekly FOSAMAX70 mg%(n=519)  FOSAMAX10 mg/day%(n=370)    
  
   Gastrointestinal       abdominal pain     dyspepsia     acid regurgitation     nausea     abdominal distention     constipation     flatulence     gastritis     gastric ulcer  3.72.71.91.91.00.80.40.20.0  3.02.22.42.41.41.61.61.11.1   
   Musculoskeletal       musculoskeletal (bone, muscle,         joint) pain     muscle cramp  2.90.2                     3.21.1                      
                Men In two placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter studies in men (a two-year study of FOSAMAX 10 mg/day and a one-year study of once weekly FOSAMAX 70 mg) the rates of discontinuation of therapy due to any clinical adverse experience were 2.7% for FOSAMAX 10 mg/day vs. 10.5% for placebo, and 6.4% for once weekly FOSAMAX 70 mg vs. 8.6% for placebo. The adverse experiences considered by the investigators as possibly, probably, or definitely drug related in &gt;=2% of patients treated with either FOSAMAX or placebo are presented in the following table.
 

       Osteoporosis Studies in Men: Adverse Experiences Considered Possibly, Probably, or Definitely Drug Related by the Investigators and Reported in &gt;=2% of Patients 
                            Two-year Study        One-year Study      
                            FOSAMAX10 mg/day%    (n=146)  Placebo%    (n=95)  Once Weekly FOSAMAX 70 mg%(n=109)  Placebo%(n=58)    
  
   Gastrointestinal       acid regurgitation     flatulence     gastroesophageal         reflux disease     dyspepsia     diarrhea     abdominal pain     nausea  4.14.10.73.41.42.12.1  3.21.13.20.01.11.10.0  0.00.02.82.82.80.90.0  0.00.00.01.70.03.40.0   
                  Prevention of osteoporosis in postmenopausal women The safety of FOSAMAX 5 mg/day in postmenopausal women 40-60 years of age has been evaluated in three double-blind, placebo-controlled studies involving over 1,400 patients randomized to receive FOSAMAX for either two or three years. In these studies the overall safety profiles of FOSAMAX 5 mg/day and placebo were similar. Discontinuation of therapy due to any clinical adverse experience occurred in 7.5% of 642 patients treated with FOSAMAX 5 mg/day and 5.7% of 648 patients treated with placebo.
 

 In a one-year, double-blind, multicenter study, the overall safety and tolerability profiles of once weekly FOSAMAX 35 mg and FOSAMAX 5 mg daily were similar.



 The adverse experiences from these studies considered by the investigators as possibly, probably, or definitely drug related in &gt;=1% of patients treated with either once weekly FOSAMAX 35 mg, FOSAMAX 5 mg/day or placebo are presented in the following table.



       Osteoporosis Prevention Studies in Postmenopausal Women: Adverse Experiences Considered Possibly, Probably, or Definitely Drug Related by the Investigators and Reported in &gt;=1% of Patients 
                                    Two/Three-Year Studies      One-Year Study     
                                  FOSAMAX5 mg/day%  (n=642)    Placebo%  (n=648)    FOSAMAX5 mg/day%  (n=361)    Once Weekly FOSAMAX35 mg%  (n=362)     
  
   Gastrointestinal       dyspepsia     abdominal pain     acid regurgitation     nausea     diarrhea     constipation     abdominal distention  1.91.71.41.41.10.90.2  1.43.42.51.41.70.50.3  2.24.24.22.51.11.71.4  1.72.24.71.40.60.31.1   
   Musculoskeletal       musculoskeletal (bone,         muscle or joint) pain  0.8                0.9               1.9               2.2                
                  Concomitant use with estrogen/hormone replacement therapy In two studies (of one and two years' duration) of postmenopausal osteoporotic women (total: n=853), the safety and tolerability profile of combined treatment with FOSAMAX 10 mg once daily and estrogen +/- progestin (n=354) was consistent with those of the individual treatments.
 

        Treatment of glucocorticoid-induced osteoporosis In two, one-year, placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter studies in patients receiving glucocorticoid treatment, the overall safety and tolerability profiles of FOSAMAX 5 and 10 mg/day were generally similar to that of placebo. The adverse experiences considered by the investigators as possibly, probably, or definitely drug related in &gt;=1% of patients treated with either FOSAMAX 5 or 10 mg/day or placebo are presented in the following table.



       One-Year Studies in Glucocorticoid-Treated Patients: Adverse Experiences Considered Possibly, Probably, or Definitely Drug Related by the Investigators and Reported in &gt;=1% of Patients 
                                              FOSAMAX10 mg/day%  (n=157)    FOSAMAX5 mg/day%  (n=161)    Placebo%  (n=159)     
  
   Gastrointestinal       abdominal pain     acid regurgitation     constipation     melena     nausea     diarrhea  Nervous System/Psychiatric       headache  3.22.51.31.30.60.00.6  1.91.90.60.01.20.00.0  0.01.30.00.00.61.31.3   
          The overall safety and tolerability profile in the glucocorticoid-induced osteoporosis population that continued therapy for the second year of the studies (FOSAMAX: n=147) was consistent with that observed in the first year.
 

        Paget's disease of bone In clinical studies (osteoporosis and Paget's disease), adverse experiences reported in 175 patients taking FOSAMAX 40 mg/day for 3-12 months were similar to those in postmenopausal women treated with FOSAMAX 10 mg/day. However, there was an apparent increased incidence of upper gastrointestinal adverse experiences in patients taking FOSAMAX 40 mg/day (17.7% FOSAMAX vs. 10.2% placebo). One case of esophagitis and two cases of gastritis resulted in discontinuation of treatment.



 Additionally, musculoskeletal (bone, muscle or joint) pain, which has been described in patients with Paget's disease treated with other bisphosphonates, was considered by the investigators as possibly, probably, or definitely drug related in approximately 6% of patients treated with FOSAMAX 40 mg/day versus approximately 1% of patients treated with placebo, but rarely resulted in discontinuation of therapy. Discontinuation of therapy due to any clinical adverse experience occurred in 6.4% of patients with Paget's disease treated with FOSAMAX 40 mg/day and 2.4% of patients treated with placebo.



        Osteogenesis Imperfecta FOSAMAX is not indicated for use in children.



 The overall safety profile of FOSAMAX in OI patients treated for up to 24 months was generally similar to that of adults with osteoporosis treated with FOSAMAX. However, there was an increased occurrence of vomiting in OI patients treated with FOSAMAX compared to placebo. During the 24-month treatment period, vomiting was observed in 32 of 109 (29.4%) patients treated with FOSAMAX and 3 of 30 (10%) patients treated with placebo.



 In a pharmacokinetic study, 6 of 24 pediatric OI patients who received a single oral dose of FOSAMAX 35 or 70 mg developed fever, flu-like symptoms, and/or mild lymphocytopenia within 24 to 48 hours after administration. These events, lasting no more than 2 to 3 days and responding to acetaminophen, are consistent with an acute-phase response that has been reported in patients receiving bisphosphonates, including FOSAMAX. See  ADVERSE REACTIONS, Post-Marketing Experience, Body as a Whole  .



        Laboratory Test Findings In double-blind, multicenter, controlled studies, asymptomatic, mild, and transient decreases in serum calcium and phosphate were observed in approximately 18% and 10%, respectively, of patients taking FOSAMAX versus approximately 12% and 3% of those taking placebo. However, the incidences of decreases in serum calcium to less than 8.0 mg/dL (2.0 mM) and serum phosphate to less than or equal to 2.0 mg/dL (0.65 mM) were similar in both treatment groups.



        Post-Marketing Experience The following adverse reactions have been reported in post-marketing use:



   Body as a Whole:  hypersensitivity reactions including urticaria and rarely angioedema. Transient symptoms of myalgia, malaise, asthenia and rarely, fever have been reported with FOSAMAX, typically in association with initiation of treatment. Rarely, symptomatic hypocalcemia has occurred, generally in association with predisposing conditions. Rarely, peripheral edema.



   Gastrointestinal:  esophagitis, esophageal erosions, esophageal ulcers, rarely esophageal stricture or perforation, and oropharyngeal ulceration. Gastric or duodenal ulcers, some severe and with complications have also been reported (see  WARNINGS  ,  PRECAUTIONS, Information for Patients  , and  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ).



 Localized osteonecrosis of the jaw, generally associated with tooth extraction and/or local infection, often with delayed healing, has been reported rarely (see  PRECAUTIONS, Dental  ).



   Musculoskeletal:  bone, joint, and/or muscle pain, occasionally severe, and rarely incapacitating (see  PRECAUTIONS, Musculoskeletal Pain  ); joint swelling.



   Nervous system:  dizziness and vertigo.



   Skin:  rash (occasionally with photosensitivity), pruritus, alopecia, rarely severe skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis.



   Special Senses:  rarely uveitis, scleritis or episcleritis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
