<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="foscavir" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  THE MAJOR TOXICITY OF FOSCAVIR IS RENAL IMPAIRMENT (see  WARNINGS  section). Approximately 33% of 189 patients with AIDS and CMV retinitis who received FOSCAVIR (60 mg/kg TID), without adequate hydration, developed significant impairment of renal function (serum creatinine &gt;= 2.0 mg/dL). The incidence of renal impairment in subsequent clinical trials in which 1000 mL of normal saline or 5% dextrose solution was given with each infusion of FOSCAVIR was 12% (34/280).



 FOSCAVIR has been associated with changes in serum electrolytes including hypocalcemia (15-30%), hypophosphatemia (8-26%) and hyperphosphatemia (6%), hypomagnesemia (15-30%), and hypokalemia (16-48%) (see  WARNINGS  section). The higher percentages were derived from those patients receiving hydration.



 FOSCAVIR treatment was associated with seizures in 18/189 (10%) AIDS patients in the initial five controlled studies (see  WARNINGS  section). Risk factors associated with seizures included impaired baseline renal function, low total serum calcium, and underlying CNS conditions predisposing the patient to seizures. The rate of seizures did not increase with duration of treatment. Three cases were associated with overdoses of FOSCAVIR (see  OVERDOSAGE  section).



 In five controlled U.S. clinical trials the most frequently reported adverse events in patients with AIDS and CMV retinitis are shown in  Table 9  . These figures were calculated without reference to drug relationship or severity.



 TABLE 9 Adverse Events Reported in Five Controlled US Clinical Trials 
                           n = 189                                                     n = 189              
   Fever                 65%                     Abnormal Renal Function             27%                    
   Nausea                47%                     Vomiting                            26%                    
   Anemia                33%                     Headache                            26%                    
   Diarrhea              30%                     Seizures                            10%                    
          From the same controlled studies, adverse events categorized by investigator as "severe" are shown in  Table 10  . Although death was specifically attributed to FOSCAVIR in only one case, other complications of FOSCAVIR (i.e., renal impairment, electrolyte abnormalities, and seizures) may have contributed to patient deaths (see  WARNINGS  section).
 

 TABLE 10 Severe Adverse Events 
                                                                   n = 189                               
   Death                                                         14%                                     
   Abnormal Renal Function                                       14%                                     
   Marrow Suppression                                            10%                                     
   Anemia                                                        9%                                      
   Seizures                                                      7%                                      
        From the five initial U.S. controlled trials of FOSCAVIR, the following list of adverse events has been compiled regardless of causal relationship to FOSCAVIR. Evaluation of these reports was difficult because of the diverse manifestations of the underlying disease and because most patients received numerous concomitant medications.
 

   Incidence of 5% or Greater

    Body as a Whole:  fever, fatigue, rigors, asthenia, malaise, pain, infection, sepsis, death



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  headache, paresthesia, dizziness, involuntary muscle contractions, hypoesthesia, neuropathy, seizures including grand mal seizures (see  WARNINGS  )



   Gastrointestinal System:  anorexia, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, abdominal pain



   Hematologic:  anemia, granulocytopenia, leukopenia, neutropenia (see  PRECAUTIONS  )



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  mineral and electrolyte imbalances (see  WARNINGS  ) including hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, hypomagnesemia, hypophosphatemia, hyperphosphatemia



   Psychiatric:  depression, confusion, anxiety



   Respiratory System:  coughing, dyspnea



   Skin and Appendages:  rash, increased sweating



   Urinary:  alterations in renal function including increased serum creatinine, decreased creatinine clearance, and abnormal renal function (see  WARNINGS  )



   Special Senses:  vision abnormalities



   Incidence between 1% and 5%

    Application Site:  injection site pain, injection site inflammation



   Body as a Whole:  back pain, chest pain, edema, influenza-like symptoms, bacterial infections, moniliasis, fungal infections, abscess



   Cardiovascular:  hypertension, palpitations, ECG abnormalities including sinus tachycardia, first degree AV block and non-specific ST-T segment changes, hypotension, flushing, cerebrovascular disorder (see  WARNINGS  )



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  tremor, ataxia, dementia, stupor, generalized spasms, sensory disturbances, meningitis, aphasia, abnormal coordination, leg cramps, EEG abnormalities (see  WARNINGS  )



   Gastrointestinal:  constipation, dysphagia, dyspepsia, rectal hemorrhage, dry mouth, melena, flatulence, ulcerative stomatitis, pancreatitis



   Hematologic:  thrombocytopenia, platelet abnormalities, thrombosis, white blood cell abnormalities, lymphadenopathy



   Liver and Biliary:  abnormal A-G ratio, abnormal hepatic function, increased SGPT, increased SGOT



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  hyponatremia, decreased weight, increased alkaline phosphatase, increased LDH, increased BUN, acidosis, cachexia, thirst, hypocalcemia (see  WARNINGS  )



   Musculo-Skeletal:  arthralgia, myalgia



   Neoplasms:  lymphoma-like disorder, sarcoma



   Psychiatric:  insomnia, somnolence, nervousness, amnesia, agitation, aggressive reaction, hallucination



   Respiratory System:  pneumonia, sinusitis, pharyngitis, rhinitis, respiratory disorders, respiratory insufficiency, pulmonary infiltration, stridor, pneumothorax, hemoptysis, bronchospasm



   Skin and Appendages:  pruritus, skin ulceration, seborrhea, erythematous rash, maculo-papular rash, skin discoloration



   Special Senses:  taste perversions, eye abnormalities, eye pain, conjunctivitis



   Urinary System:  albuminuria, dysuria, polyuria, urethral disorder, urinary retention, urinary tract infections, acute renal failure, nocturia, facial edema



 Selected adverse events occurring at a rate of less than 1% in the five initial U.S. controlled clinical trials of FOSCAVIR include: syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion, pancytopenia, hematuria, dehydration, hypoproteinemia, increases in amylase and creatinine phosphokinase, cardiac arrest, coma, and other cardiovascular and neurologic complications.



 Selected adverse event data from the Foscarnet vs. Ganciclovir CMV Retinitis Trial (FGCRT), performed by the Studies of the Ocular Complications of AIDS (SOCA) Research Group, are shown in  Table 11  (see  CLINICAL TRIALS  section).



 TABLE 11 FGRCT: Selected Adverse Events* 
  * Values for the treatment groups refer only to patients who completed at least one follow-up visit - i.e., 133 to 119 patients in the ganciclovir group and 93 to 100 in the foscarnet group. "Events" denotes all events observed and "patients" the number of patients with one or more of the indicated events.    
  Per person-year at risk          
  ?Final frozen SOCA I database dated October 1991    
  
   EVENT                            GANCICLOVIR      FOSCARNET     
 No. ofEvents                     No. of Patients  Rates        No. ofEvents  No. of Patients  Rates         
 Absolute neutrophil count decreasing to &lt;0.50 x 10  9  per liter  63           41           1.30        31           17           0.72         
 Serum creatinine increasing to &gt;260 mumol per liter (&gt;2.9 mg/dL)  6            4            0.12        13           9            0.30         
 Seizure ?                        21           13           0.37        19           13           0.37         
 Catheterization-related infection  49           27           1.26        51           28           1.46         
 Hospitalization                  209          91           4.74        202          75           5.03         
             Selected adverse events from ACTG Study 228 (CRRT) comparing combination therapy with FOSCAVIR or ganciclovir monotherapy are shown in  Table 12  . The most common reason for a treatment change in patients assigned to either FOSCAVIR or ganciclovir was retinitis progression. The most frequent reason for a treatment change in the combination treatment group was toxicity.
 

 TABLE 12 CRRT: Selected Adverse Events 
  * Pts. = patients with event; Rate = events/person/year; ?ANC = absolute neutrophil count    
  
                                FoscavirN=88  GanciclovirN=93  CombinationN=93   
 No. Events                     No. Pts.*  Rate     No. Events  No. Pts.*  Rate     No. Events  No. Pts.*  Rate      
 Anemia (Hgb &lt;70g/L)            11        7        0.20     9         7        0.14     19        15       0.33      
 Neutropenia?     ANC &lt;0.75 x 10  9  cells/L     ANC &lt;0.50 x 10  9  cells/L  8650      3225     1.530.91  9549      4128     1.510.80  10750     5128     1.910.85   
 Thrombocytopenia     Platelets &lt;50 x 10  9  /L     Platelets &lt;20 x 10  9  /L  281       141      0.500.01  196       82       0.430.05  407       156      0.560.18   
 Nephrotoxicity     Creatinine &gt;260 mumol/L (&gt;2.9 mg/dL)  9         7        0.15     10        7        0.17     11        10       0.20      
 Seizures                       6         6        0.17     7         6        0.15     10        5        0.18      
 Hospitalizations               86        53       1.86     111       59       2.36     118       64       2.36      
                Adverse events that have been reported in post-marketing surveillance include: ventricular arrhythmia, prolongation of QT interval, gamma GT increased, diabetes insipidus (usually nephrogenic), renal calculus, esophageal ulceration, renal tubular acidosis, renal tubular necrosis, crystal-induced nephropathy and muscle disorders including myopathy, myositis, muscle weakness and rare cases of rhabdomyolysis. Cases of vesiculobullous eruptions including erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome have been reported. In most cases, patients were taking other medications that have been associated with toxic epidermal necrolysis or Stevens-Johnson Syndrome.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    WARNING  



   RENAL IMPAIRMENT IS THE MAJOR TOXICITY OF FOSCAVIR.  FREQUENT MONITORING OF SERUM CREATININE, WITH DOSE ADJUSTMENT FOR CHANGES IN RENAL FUNCTION, AND ADEQUATE HYDRATION WITH ADMINISTRATION OF FOSCAVIR IS IMPERATIVE.  (See   ADMINISTRATION section; Hydration.  )  



   SEIZURES, RELATED TO ALTERATIONS IN PLASMA MINERALS AND ELECTROLYTES, HAVE BEEN ASSOCIATED WITH FOSCAVIR TREATMENT.  THEREFORE, PATIENTS MUST BE CAREFULLY MONITORED FOR SUCH CHANGES AND THEIR POTENTIAL SEQUELAE. MINERAL AND ELECTROLYTE SUPPLEMENTATION MAY BE REQUIRED.  



   FOSCAVIR IS INDICATED FOR USE ONLY IN IMMUNOCOMPROMISED PATIENTS WITH CMV RETINITIS AND MUCOCUTANEOUS ACYCLOVIR-RESISTANT HSV INFECTIONS.  (See   INDICATIONS   section).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
