<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fusilev" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Allergic reactions were reported in patients receiving Fusilev. (6.3)



 Vomiting (38%), stomatitis (38%) and nausea (19%) were reported in patients receiving Fusilev as rescue after high-dose methotrexate therapy. (6.1)



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;50%) in patients with advanced colorectal cancer receiving Fusilev in combination with 5-FU were diarrhea, nausea and stomatitis. (6.2)



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Spectrum Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-877-387-4538 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies in High-Dose Methotrexate Therapy

  Since clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The following table presents the frequency of adverse reactions which occurred during the administration of 58 courses of high-dose methotrexate 12 grams/m  2  followed by Fusilev rescue for osteosarcoma in 16 patients age 6-21. Most patients received Fusilev 7.5 mg every 6 hours for 60 hours or longer beginning 24 hours after completion of methotrexate.



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions with High-Dose Methotrexate Therapy 
 Body System/Adverse Reactions  Number (%) of Patients with Adverse Reactions  Number (%) of Courses with Adverse Reactions   
                            (N =16)             (N = 58)             
                            All                 Grade 3+            All                 Grade 3+             
 Gastrointestinal                                                                                            
 Stomatitis                 6 (37.5)            1 (6.3)             10 (17.2)           1 (1.7)              
 Vomiting                   6 (37.5)            0                   14 (24.1)           0                    
 Nausea                     3 (18.8)            0                   3 (5.2)             0                    
 Diarrhea                   1 (6.3)             0                   1 (1.7)             0                    
 Dyspepsia                  1 (6.3)             0                   1 (1.7)             0                    
 Typhlitis                  1 (6.3)             1 (6.3)             1 (1.7)             1 (1.7)              
                                                                                                             
 Respiratory                                                                                                 
 Dyspnea                    1 (6.3)             0                   1 (1.7)             0                    
                                                                                                             
 Skin and Appendages                                                                                         
 Dermatitis                 1 (6.3)             0                   1 (1.7)             0                    
                                                                                                             
 Other                                                                                                       
 Confusion                  1 (6.3)             0                   1 (1.7)             0                    
 Neuropathy                 1 (6.3)             0                   1 (1.7)             0                    
 Renal function abnormal    1 (6.3)             0                   3 (5.2)             0                    
 Taste perversion           1 (6.3)             0                   1 (1.7)             0                    
                                                                                                             
 Total number of patients   9 (56.3)            2 (12.5)             
                                                                                                             
 Total number of courses    25 (43.1)           2 (3.4)              
           The incidence of adverse reactions may be underestimated because not all patients were fully evaluable for toxicity for all cycles in the clinical trials. Leukopenia and thrombocytopenia were observed, but could not be attributed to high-dose methotrexate with Fusilev rescue because patients were receiving other myelosuppressive chemotherapy.
 

   6.2 Clinical Studies in Combination with 5-FU in Colorectal Cancer

  A randomized controlled trial conducted by the North Central Cancer Treatment Group (NCCTG) in patients with advanced colorectal cancer failed to show superiority of a regimen of 5-FU + levoleucovorin to 5-FU +  d,l  -leucovorin in overall survival. Patients were randomized to 5-FU 370 mg/m  2  intravenously and levoleucovorin 100 mg/m  2  intravenously, both daily for 5 days, or with 5-FU 370 mg/m  2  intravenously and  d,l  -leucovorin 200 mg/m  2  intravenously, both daily for 5 days. Treatment was repeated week 4 and week 8, and then every 5 weeks until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. The following table presents the most frequent adverse reactions which occurred in patients in the 2 treatment arms.



 Table 3  Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=10% of Patients in Either Arm 
   Adverse Reaction                    Levoleucovorin/5FU   n=318     d,l-Leucovorin/5FU   n=307     
 Adverse Event N (%)                  Grade 1-4           Grade 3-4        Grade 1-4        Grade 3-4         
 Gastrointestinal Disorders            
 Stomatitis                           229 (72%)           37 (12%)         221 (72%)        44 (14%)          
 Diarrhea                             222 (70%)           61 (19%)         201 (65%)        51 (17%)          
 Nausea                               197 (62%)           25 (8%)          186 (61%)        26 (8%)           
 Vomiting                             128 (40%)           17 (5%)          114 (37%)        18 (6%)           
 Abdominal Pain  1                    45 (14%)            10 (3%)          57 (19%)         10 (3%)           
 General Disorders                     
 Asthenia/Fatigue/Malaise             91 (29%)            15 (5%)          99 (32%)         34 (11%)          
 Metabolism and Nutrition              
 Anorexia/Decreased Appetite          76 (24%)            13 (4%)          77 (25%)         5 (2%)            
 Skin Disorders                        
 Dermatitis                           91 (29%)            3 (1%)           86 (28%)         4 (1%)            
 Alopecia                             83 (26%)            1 (0.3%)         87 (28%)         3 (1%)            
              1  Includes abdominal pain, upper abdominal pain, lower abdominal pain, and abdominal tenderness
 

   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  Since adverse reactions from spontaneous reports are provided voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate reliably their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Spontaneously reported adverse reactions collected by the WHO Collaborating Center for International Drug Monitoring in Uppsala Sweden have yielded seven cases where levoleucovorin was administered with a regimen of methotrexate. The events were dyspnea, pruritus, rash, temperature change and rigors. For 217 adverse reactions (108 reports) where levoleucovorin was a suspected or interacting medication, there were 40 occurrences of "possible allergic reactions."



 In an analysis where calcium levoleucovorin was reported as the primary suspect drug and fluorouracil (FU) was reported as a concomitant medication, possible allergic reactions were reported among 47 cases (67 events).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Due to Ca  ++  content, no more than 16 mL (160 mg) of levoleucovorin solution should be injected intravenously per minute. (5.1)



 Fusilev enhances the toxicity of fluorouracil. (5.2,7)



 Concomitant use of d,l-  leucovorin with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia in HIV patients was associated with increased rates of treatment failure in a placebo-controlled study. (5.3)



 



   5.1 Rate of Administration



  Because of the Ca  ++  content of the levoleucovorin solution, no more than 16 mL (160 mg of levoleucovorin) should be injected intravenously per minute.



    5.2 Potential for Enhanced Toxicity with 5-Fluorouracil



  Fusilev enhances the toxicity of 5-fluorouracil. Deaths from severe enterocolitis, diarrhea, and dehydration have been reported in elderly patients receiving weekly d,l-  leucovorin and 5-fluorouracil. When these drugs are administered concurrently in the palliative treatment of advanced colorectal cancer, the dosage of 5-FU must be lower than usually administered. Although the toxicities observed in patients treated with the combination of Fusilev and 5-FU are qualitatively similar to those observed with 5-FU alone, gastrointestinal toxicities (particularly stomatitis and diarrhea) are observed more commonly and may be of greater severity and of prolonged duration in patients treated with the combination.



 In the first Mayo/NCCTG controlled trial, toxicity, primarily gastrointestinal, resulted in 7% of patients requiring hospitalization when treated with 5-FU alone or 5-FU in combination with 200 mg/m  2  of d,l  -leucovorin and 20% when treated with 5-FU in combination with 20 mg/m  2  of d,l  -leucovorin. In the second Mayo/NCCTG trial, hospitalizations related to treatment toxicity also appeared to occur more often in patients treated with the low dose d,l  -leucovorin/5-FU combination than in patients treated with the high dose combination - 11% versus 3%. Therapy with Fusilev and 5-FU must not be initiated or continued in patients who have symptoms of gastrointestinal toxicity of any severity, until those symptoms have completely resolved. Patients with diarrhea must be monitored with particular care until the diarrhea has resolved, as rapid clinical deterioration leading to death can occur. In an additional study utilizing higher weekly doses of 5-FU and d,l  -leucovorin, elderly and/or debilitated patients were found to be at greater risk for severe gastrointestinal toxicity.



 Seizures and/or syncope have been reported rarely in cancer patients receiving d,l  -leucovorin, usually in association with fluoropyrimidine administration, and most commonly in those with CNS metastases or other predisposing factors. However, a causal relationship has not been established.



    5.3 Potential for interaction with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole



  The concomitant use of d,l-  leucovorin with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for the acute treatment of Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia in patients with HIV infection was associated with increased rates of treatment failure and morbidity in a placebo-controlled study.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
