<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="fuzeon" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections:



 *  Administration with Biojector  (r)  2000 [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Pneumonia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are local injection site reactions, diarrhea, nausea, and fatigue. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genentech at 1-888-835-2555 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The overall safety profile of FUZEON is based on 2131 subjects who received at least 1 dose of FUZEON during various clinical trials. This includes 2051 adults, 658 of whom received the recommended dose for greater than 48 weeks, and 63 pediatric subjects.



 Assessment of treatment-emergent adverse events is based on the pooled data from the two randomized, controlled, open-label, multicenter trials in treatment-experienced subjects, T20-301 (TORO 1) and T20-302 (TORO 2).



     Local Injection Site Reactions  



 Local injection site reactions were the most frequent adverse events associated with the use of FUZEON. In T20-301 and T20-302, 98% of subjects had at least one local injection site reaction (ISR). A total of 7% of subjects discontinued treatment with FUZEON because of ISRs (4%) or difficulties with injecting FUZEON (3%) such as injection fatigue and inconvenience. Eighty-five percent of subjects experienced their first ISR during the initial week of treatment; ISRs continued to occur throughout treatment with FUZEON. For most subjects the severity of signs and symptoms associated with ISRs did not change during the 48 weeks of treatment. The majority of ISRs were associated with erythema, induration, the presence of nodules or cysts, and mild to moderate pain at the injection site (  Table 2  ). In addition, the average duration of individual ISRs was between three and seven days in 41% of subjects and more than seven days in 24% of subjects. Also, the numbers of ISRs per subject at any one time was between six to 14 ISRs in 26% of subjects and more than 14 ISRs in 1.3% of subjects. Infection at the injection site (including abscess and cellulitis) was reported in 1.7% of adult subjects.



 Table 2 Summary of Individual Signs/Symptoms Characterizing Local Injection Site Reactions to Enfuvirtide in Studies T20-301 and T20-302 Combined (% of Subjects) Through 48 Weeks 
                                      N=663             
 Event Category                Any Severity Grade      % of Subjects with Grade 3 Reactions  % of Subjects with Grade 4 Reactions   
  
 Pain/Discomfort                       96%                        11%                        0%               
 Induration                            90%                 39%&gt;25 but &lt;50 mm             18%&gt;=50 mm           
 Erythema                              91%                 22%&gt;50 but &lt;85 mm             10%&gt;=85 mm           
 Nodules and Cysts                     80%             23%&gt;3 cm average diameter        0.2%Draining          
 Pruritus                              65%                        3%                         NA               
 Ecchymosis                            52%                  5%&gt;3 but &lt;=5 cm                2%&gt;5 cm            
              Other Adverse Events  
 

 In T20-301 and T20-302, after study week 8, subjects on background alone who met protocol defined criteria for virological failure were permitted to revise their background regimens and add FUZEON. Exposure on FUZEON+background was 557 patient-years, and to background alone 162 patient-years. Due to this difference in exposure, safety results are expressed as the number of patients with an adverse event per 100 patient-years of exposure. For FUZEON+background, adverse events are also displayed by percent of subjects.



 The events most frequently reported in subjects receiving FUZEON+background regimen, excluding ISRs, were diarrhea (38 per 100 patient-years or 31.7%), nausea (27 per 100 patient-years or 22.8%), and fatigue (24 per 100 patient-years or 20.2%). These events were also commonly observed in subjects that received background regimen alone: diarrhea (73 per 100 patient-years), nausea (50 per 100 patient-years), and fatigue (38 per 100 patient-years).



 Treatment-emergent adverse events, regardless of causality and excluding ISRs, from Phase 3 studies are summarized for adult subjects, in  Table 3  . Any Grade 2 or above events occurring at &gt;=2 percent of subjects and at a higher rate in subjects treated with FUZEON are summarized in  Table 3  ; events that occurred at a higher rate in the control arms are not displayed.



 Rates of adverse events for subjects who switched to FUZEON after virological failure were similar.



 Table 3 Rates of Treatment-Emergent Adverse EventsExcludes Injection Site Reactions (&gt;=Grade 2) Reported in &gt;=2% of Subjects Treated with FUZEONEvents listed occurred more frequently in subjects treated with FUZEON (based on rates/100 patient-years). (Pooled Studies T20-301/T20-302 at 48 Weeks) 
 Adverse Event (by System Organ Class)  FUZEON+Background Regimen(N=663)  FUZEON+Background Regimen(N=663)  Background Regimen(N=334)   
                               663 subjects total       557 total patient-years    162 total patient-years    
                                   % frequency          rate/100 patient-years     rate/100 patient-years     
  
 Weight Decreased                     6.6%                        7.9                        6.2              
 Sinusitis                            6.0%                        7.2                        4.9              
 Abdominal Pain                       3.9%                        4.7                        3.7              
 Cough                                3.9%                        4.7                        2.5              
 Herpes Simplex                       3.5%                        4.1                        3.7              
 Appetite Decreased                   3.2%                        3.8                        2.5              
 Pancreatitis                         3.0%                        3.6                        2.5              
 Pain in Limb                         2.9%                        3.4                        3.1              
 Pneumonia (see text below)            2.7%                        3.2                        0.6              
 Myalgia                              2.7%                        3.2                        1.2              
 Influenza-Like Illness               2.4%                        2.9                        1.9              
 Folliculitis                         2.4%                        2.9                        2.5              
 Anorexia                             2.3%                        2.7                        1.9              
 Dry Mouth                            2.1%                        2.5                        1.9              
 Conjunctivitis                       2.0%                        2.3                        1.9              
              Less Common Events  
 

 The following adverse events have been reported in 1 or more subjects; however, a causal relationship to FUZEON has not been established.



   Immune System Disorders:  worsening abacavir hypersensitivity reaction



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  glomerulonephritis; tubular necrosis; renal insufficiency; renal failure (including fatal cases)



   Blood and Lymphatic Disorders:  thrombocytopenia; neutropenia; fever; lymphadenopathy



   Endocrine and Metabolic:  hyperglycemia



   Infections:  sepsis; herpes simplex



   Nervous System Disorders:  taste disturbance; Guillain-Barre syndrome (fatal); sixth nerve palsy; peripheral neuropathy



   Cardiac Disorders:  unstable angina pectoris



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  constipation; abdominal pain upper



   General:  asthenia



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  toxic hepatitis; hepatic steatosis



   Investigations:  increased amylase; increased lipase; increased AST; increased GGT; increased triglycerides



   Psychiatric Disorders:  insomnia; depression; anxiety; suicide attempt



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  pneumopathy; respiratory distress; cough



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  pruritus



     Laboratory Abnormalities  



   Table 4  shows the treatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities that occurred in at least 2 subjects per 100 patient-years and more frequently in those receiving FUZEON+background regimen than background regimen alone from T20-301 and T20-302.



 Table 4 Treatment-Emergent Laboratory Abnormalities in &gt;=2% of Subjects Receiving FUZEONEvents listed occurred more frequently in subjects treated with FUZEON (based on rates/100 patient-years). (Pooled Studies T20-301 and T20-302 at 48 Weeks) 
 Laboratory Parameters                         Grading      FUZEON+Background Regimen(N=663)  FUZEON+Background Regimen(N=663)  Background Regimen(N=334)   
                                                            663 subjects total  557 total patient-years  162 total patient-years   
                                                              % frequency    rate/100 patient-years  rate/100 patient-years   
  
 Eosinophilia                                                                                                   
 1-2 X ULN (0.7 * 10  9  /L)               0.7-1.4 * 10  9  /L       9.1%             10.8              3.7         
 &gt;2 X ULN (0.7 * 10  9  /L)                &gt;1.4 * 10  9  /L       1.8%              2.2              1.8         
 ALT                                                                                                            
 Grade 3                                     &gt;5-10 * ULN         4.1%              4.8              4.3         
 Grade 4                                      &gt;10 * ULN          1.2%              1.4              1.2         
 Creatine Phosphokinase (U/L)                                                                                   
 Grade 3                                     &gt;5-10 * ULN         6.9%              8.3              8.0         
 Grade 4                                      &gt;10 * ULN          2.6%              3.1              8.6         
               Adverse Events in Pediatric Patients  
 

 FUZEON has been studied in 63 pediatric subjects 5 through 16 years of age with duration of FUZEON exposure ranging from 1 dose to 134 weeks. Adverse experiences seen during clinical trials were similar to those observed in adult subjects, although infections at site of injection (cellulitis or abscess) were more frequent in adolescents than in adults, with 4 events occurring in 3 of 28 (11%) subjects.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Injection Site Reaction: 98% of subjects experienced at least one injection site reaction during FUZEON treatment in randomized, controlled, open-label, multicenter trials. Manifestations included pain and discomfort, erythema, nodules and cysts, and ecchymosis. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Biojector  (r)  2000: Administration of FUZEON with Biojector 2000 may result in neuralgia and/or paresthesia, bruising and hematomas. Patients receiving anticoagulants or persons with hemophilia, or other coagulation disorders, may have a higher risk of post-injection bleeding. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Pneumonia: Monitor for signs and symptoms of pneumonia in HIV-infected patients, especially those predisposed to pneumonia (e.g., low initial CD4 cell count). (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity: FUZEON should be discontinued immediately upon signs and symptoms of systemic hypersensitivity reactions. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Immune Reconstitution: Patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including FUZEON, may experience immune reconstitution syndrome requiring further evaluation and treatment. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Local Injection Site Reactions (ISRs)



  The majority of subjects (98%) receiving FUZEON in randomized, controlled, open-label, multicenter clinical trials had at least one local injection site reaction; ISRs occurred throughout treatment with FUZEON. Manifestations may include pain and discomfort, induration, erythema, nodules and cysts, pruritus, and ecchymosis [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  . Reactions are often present at more than one injection site. Patients must be familiar with the FUZEON Injection Instructions  in order to know how to inject FUZEON appropriately and how to monitor carefully for signs or symptoms of cellulitis or local infection.



    5.2 Administration with Biojector  (r)  2000



  Nerve pain (neuralgia and/or paresthesia) lasting up to 6 months associated with administration at anatomical sites where large nerves course close to the skin, bruising and hematomas have occurred with use of the Biojector 2000 needle-free device for administration of FUZEON. Patients receiving anticoagulants or persons with hemophilia, or other coagulation disorders, may have a higher risk of post-injection bleeding.



    5.3 Pneumonia



  An increased rate of bacterial pneumonia was observed in subjects treated with FUZEON in the Phase 3 clinical trials compared to the control arm. The incidence of pneumonia was 2.7% or 3.2 events/100 patient-years in subjects receiving FUZEON+background regimen. On analysis of all diagnoses of pneumonia (pneumonia, bacterial pneumonia, bronchopneumonia, and related terms) in T20-301 and T20-302, an increased rate of bacterial pneumonia was observed in subjects treated with FUZEON compared to the control arm (6.9%, 6.7 pneumonia events per 100 patient-years versus 0.6 events per 100 patient-years, respectively). Approximately half of the study subjects with pneumonia required hospitalization. Three subject deaths in the FUZEON arm were attributed to pneumonia; all three had serious concomitant AIDS-related illnesses that contributed to their deaths. Risk factors for pneumonia included low initial CD4 lymphocyte count, high initial viral load, intravenous drug use, smoking, and a prior history of lung disease.



 Because it was unclear whether the higher incidence rate of pneumonia was related to FUZEON use, an observational study in 1850 HIV-infected patients (740 FUZEON treated patients and 1110 non-FUZEON treated patients) was conducted to evaluate the risk of pneumonia in patients treated with FUZEON. A total of 123 patients had a confirmed or probable pneumonia event in this study (62 in the FUZEON treatment arm with 1962 patient-years of observation and 61 in the non-FUZEON treatment arm with 3378 patient-years of observation). The incidence of pneumonia was 3.2 events/100 patient-years in the FUZEON treatment arm and 1.8 events/100 patient-years in the non-FUZEON treatment arm. The hazard ratio, adjusting for other baseline risk factors, was 1.34 (95% C.I. = 0.90 - 2.00). Based on this observational study, it is not possible to exclude an increased risk of pneumonia in patients treated with FUZEON compared to non-FUZEON treated patients.



 It is unclear if the increased incidence of pneumonia is related to FUZEON use. However, because of these findings, patients with HIV-1 infection should be carefully monitored for signs and symptoms of pneumonia, especially if they have underlying conditions which may predispose them to pneumonia. Risk factors for pneumonia included low initial CD4 cell count, high initial viral load, intravenous drug use, smoking, and a prior history of lung disease.



    5.4 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Systemic hypersensitivity reactions have been associated with FUZEON therapy and may recur on re-challenge. Hypersensitivity reactions have occurred in &lt;1% of subjects studied and have included combinations of: rash, fever, nausea and vomiting, chills, rigors, hypotension, and/or elevated serum liver transaminases. Other adverse events that may be immune mediated and have been reported in subjects receiving FUZEON include primary immune complex reaction, respiratory distress, glomerulonephritis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome. Patients developing signs and symptoms suggestive of a systemic hypersensitivity reaction should discontinue FUZEON and should seek medical evaluation immediately. Therapy with FUZEON should not be restarted following systemic signs and symptoms consistent with a hypersensitivity reaction. Risk factors that may predict the occurrence or severity of hypersensitivity to FUZEON have not been identified.



    5.5 Non-HIV Infected Individuals



  There is a theoretical risk that FUZEON use may lead to the production of anti-enfuvirtide antibodies which cross react with HIV gp41. This could result in a false positive HIV test with an ELISA assay; a confirmatory western blot test would be expected to be negative. FUZEON has not been studied in non-HIV infected individuals.



    5.6 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including FUZEON. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia [PCP] or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
