<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gabitril" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most commonly observed adverse events in placebo-controlled, parallel-group, add-on epilepsy trials associated with the use of GABITRIL in combination with other antiepilepsy drugs not seen at an equivalent frequency among placebo-treated patients were dizziness/light-headedness, asthenia/lack of energy, somnolence, nausea, nervousness/irritability, tremor, abdominal pain, and thinking abnormal/difficulty with concentration or attention.



 Approximately 21% of the 2531 patients who received GABITRIL in clinical trials of epilepsy discontinued treatment because of an adverse event. The adverse events most commonly associated with discontinuation were dizziness (1.7%), somnolence (1.6%), depression (1.3%), confusion (1.1%), and asthenia (1.1%).



 In Studies 1 and 2 (U.S. studies), the double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group, add-on studies, the proportion of patients who discontinued treatment because of adverse events was 11% for the group treated with GABITRIL and 6% for the placebo group. The most common adverse events considered the primary reason for discontinuation were confusion (1.2%), somnolence (1.0%), and ataxia (1.0%).



              Adverse Event Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials   Table 5 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that occurred in at least 1% of patients treated with GABITRIL for epilepsy participating in parallel-group, placebo-controlled trials and were numerically more common in the GABITRIL group. In these studies, either GABITRIL or placebo was added to the patient's current antiepilepsy drug therapy. Adverse events were usually mild or moderate in intensity.



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures, obtained when GABITRIL was added to concurrent antiepilepsy drug therapy, cannot be used to predict the frequency of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice when patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those prevailing during clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be directly compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, or investigators. An inspection of these frequencies, however, does provide the prescribing physician with one basis to estimate the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidences in the population studied.



   Table 5: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Event  1  Incidence in Parallel-Group,  



   Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Trials (events in at least 1% of patients treated with GABITRIL and numerically more frequent than in the placebo group)  




   Body System/COSTART                       GABITRIL      N=494                             Placebo      N=275     
                                     %                               %                 
 BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                       
      Abdominal Pain                   7                                 3                 
      Pain (unspecified)                   5                                 3                 
                                                                                       
 CARDIOVASCULAR                                                                        
      Vasodilation                   2                                 1                 
                                                                                       
 DIGESTIVE                                                                             
      Nausea                       11                                9                 
      Diarrhea                     7                                 3                 
      Vomiting                     7                                 4                 
      Increased Appetite                   2                                 0                 
      Mouth Ulceration                   1                                 0                 
                                                                                       
 MUSCULOSKELETAL                                                                       
      Myasthenia                   1                                 0                 
                                                                                       
 NERVOUS SYSTEM                                                                        
      Dizziness                    27                                15                
      Asthenia                     20                                14                
      Somnolence                   18                                15                
      Nervousness                   10                                3                 
      Tremor                       9                                 3                 
      Difficulty with Concentration/Attention*                   6                                 2                 
      Insomnia                     6                                 4                 
      Ataxia                       5                                 3                 
      Confusion                    5                                 3                 
      Speech Disorder                   4                                 2                 
      Difficulty with Memory*                   4                                 3                 
      Paresthesia                   4                                 2                 
      Depression                   3                                 1                 
      Emotional Lability                   3                                 2                 
      Abnormal Gait                   3                                 2                 
      Hostility                    2                                 1                 
      Nystagmus                    2                                 1                 
      Language Problems*                   2                                 0                 
      Agitation                    1                                 0                 
                                                                                       
 RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                                                                       
      Pharyngitis                   7                                 4                 
      Cough Increased                   4                                 3                 
                                                                                       
 SKIN AND APPENDAGES                                                                       
      Rash                         5                                 4                 
      Pruritus                     2                                 0                 
             1  Patients in these add-on studies were receiving one to three concomitant enzyme-inducing antiepilepsy drugs in addition to GABITRIL or placebo. Patients may have reported multiple adverse experiences; thus, patients may be included in more than one category.
 

 *COSTART term substituted with a more clinically descriptive term.



 Other events reported by 1% or more of patients treated with GABITRIL but equally or more frequent in the placebo group were: accidental injury, chest pain, constipation, flu syndrome, rhinitis, anorexia, back pain, dry mouth, flatulence, ecchymosis, twitching, fever, amblyopia, conjunctivitis, urinary tract infection, urinary frequency, infection, dyspepsia, gastroenteritis, nausea and vomiting, myalgia, diplopia, headache, anxiety, acne, sinusitis, and incoordination.



 Study 1 was a dose-response study including doses of 32 mg and 56 mg. Table 6 shows adverse events reported at a rate of &gt;= 5% in at least one GABITRIL group and more frequent than in the placebo group. Among these events, depression, tremor, nervousness, difficulty with concentration/attention, and perhaps asthenia exhibited a positive relationship to dose.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
