<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="galantamine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in the following sections of the labeling:



 *  Serious skin reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Deaths in subjects with mild cognitive impairment (MCI) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) were nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, dizziness, headache, decreased appetite, and weight decreased (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact 1-800-667-8570 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    .    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most common adverse reactions in galantamine-treated patients from double-blind clinical trials (&gt;=5%) were nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, dizziness, headache, decreased appetite, and weight decreased.



 The most common adverse reactions associated with discontinuation (&gt;=1%) in galantamine-treated patients from double-blind clinical trials were nausea (7.7%), vomiting (4.1%), decreased appetite (1.9%), and dizziness (1.6%).



 The safety of the extended-release capsule and immediate-release tablet formulations of galantamine was evaluated in 2932 galantamine-treated patients who participated in 7 placebo-controlled clinical studies and 1454 subjects in 5 open-label clinical studies with mild to moderate dementia of the Alzheimer's type. In clinical studies, the safety profile of once-daily treatment with extended-release galantamine was similar in frequency and nature to that seen with tablets. The information presented in this section was derived from pooled double-blind studies and from pooled open-label data.



     Commonly-Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials  



 Table 1 lists the adverse reactions reported in &gt;=1% of galantamine-treated patients in 7 placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trials.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=1% of Galantamine-Treated Patients in Pooled Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Clinical Trials 
 System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction                  Galantamine(n=2932)%         Placebo(n=1525)%        
  
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                 
   Decreased appetite                                           5.2                        1.4              
   Anorexia                                                     3.8                        1.0              
   Psychiatric Disorders                              
   Depression                                                   4.2                        2.9              
   Nervous System Disorders                           
   Dizziness                                                    8.9                        4.6              
   Headache                                                     7.6                        5.4              
   Tremor                                                       2.0                        0.8              
   Syncope                                                      1.8                        0.7              
   Lethargy                                                     1.7                        0.7              
   Somnolence                                                   1.7                        0.8              
   Cardiac Disorders                                  
   Bradycardia                                                  1.2                        0.3              
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
   Nausea                                                      25.0                        7.6              
   Vomiting                                                    12.8                        3.1              
   Diarrhea                                                     9.0                        6.3              
   Abdominal pain                                               2.4                        0.9              
   Upper abdominal pain                                         2.0                        1.4              
   Dyspepsia                                                    1.8                        1.3              
   Stomach discomfort                                           1.6                        0.6              
   Abdominal discomfort                                         1.0                        0.4              
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders             
   Hyperhidrosis                                                1.2                        0.7              
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
   Muscle spasms                                                1.5                        0.8              
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions     
   Fatigue                                                      4.0                        2.2              
   Asthenia                                                     2.3                        1.7              
   Malaise                                                      1.4                        0.7              
   Investigations                                     
   Decreased weight                                             5.1                        1.4              
         The majority of these adverse reactions occurred during the dose-escalation period. In those patients who experienced the most frequent adverse reaction, nausea, the median duration of the nausea was 5-7 days.
 

     Other Adverse Reactions Observed in Clinical Trials of Galantamine  



 The following adverse reactions occurred in &lt;1% of all galantamine-treated patients (N=2932) in the above double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial data sets. In addition, the following also includes all adverse reactions reported at any frequency rate in patients (N=1454) who participated in open-label studies. Adverse reactions listed in Table 1 above were not included below:



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Dehydration



   Nervous System Disorders:  Dysgeusia, Hypersomnia, Paresthesia



   Eye Disorders:  Blurred vision



   Cardiac Disorders:  First degree atrioventricular block, Palpitations, Sinus bradycardia, Supraventricular extrasystoles



   Vascular Disorders:  Flushing, Hypotension



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Retching



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Muscular weakness



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  Fall



     Discontinuations Due to Adverse Reactions  



 In the 7 placebo-controlled studies of adults, 379 (12.9%) galantamine-treated patients (N=2932) and 42 (2.8%) placebo patients (N=1525) discontinued due to an adverse reaction. Those events with an incidence of &gt;=0.5% in the galantamine-treated patients included nausea (225, 7.7%), vomiting (119, 4.1%), decreased appetite (56, 1.9%), dizziness (48, 1.6%), diarrhea (27, 0.9%), headache (26, 0.9%), decreased weight (24, 0.8%), and abdominal pain (15, 0.5%). Those events with an incidence of &gt;=0.5% in placebo patients included nausea (14, 0.9%) and dizziness (8, 0.5%).



 In the 5 open-label studies, 103 (7.1%) patients (N=1454) discontinued due to an adverse reaction. Those events with an incidence of &gt;=0.5% included nausea (43, 3.0%), vomiting (23, 1.6%), decreased appetite (13, 0.9%), headache (12, 0.8%), decreased weight (9, 0.6%), dizziness (8, 0.6%), and diarrhea (7, 0.5%).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of GALANTAMINE HBr ER and GALANTAMINE HBr. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency:



   Immune System Disorders:  Hypersensitivity



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Hallucinations



   Nervous System Disorders:  Seizures



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  Tinnitus



   Vascular Disorders:  Hypertension



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Hepatitis, increased hepatic enzyme



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Stevens-Johnson syndrome, acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, erythema multiforme
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious skin reactions: discontinue at first appearance of skin rash (  5.1  ) 
 *  All patients should be considered at risk for adverse effects on cardiac conduction, including bradycardia and AV block, due to vagotonic effects on sinoatrial and atrioventricular nodes (  5.3  ) 
 *  Active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding: monitor, especially those with an increased risk for developing ulcers (  5.4  ) 
 *  Cholinomimetics may cause bladder outflow obstruction (  5.5  ) 
 *  Monitor for respiratory adverse events in patients with a history of severe asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Skin Reactions



   Serious skin reactions (Stevens-Johnson syndrome and acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis) have been reported in patients receiving GALANTAMINE HBr ER and GALANTAMINE HBr. Inform patients and caregivers that the use of GALANTAMINE HBr ER or GALANTAMINE HBr should be discontinued at the first appearance of a skin rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related. If signs or symptoms suggest a serious skin reaction, use of this drug should not be resumed and alternative therapy should be considered.  



    5.2 Anesthesia



  Galantamine, as a cholinesterase inhibitor, is likely to exaggerate the neuromuscular blocking effects of succinylcholine-type and similar neuromuscular blocking agents during anesthesia.



    5.3 Cardiovascular Conditions



  Because of their pharmacological action, cholinesterase inhibitors have vagotonic effects on the sinoatrial and atrioventricular nodes, leading to bradycardia and AV block. Bradycardia and all types of heart block have been reported in patients both with and without known underlying cardiac conduction abnormalities. Therefore, all patients should be considered at risk for adverse effects on cardiac conduction.



 Patients treated with galantamine up to 24 mg/day using the recommended dosing schedule showed a dose-related increase in risk of syncope (placebo 0.7% [2/286]; 4 mg twice daily 0.4% [3/692]; 8 mg twice daily 1.3% [7/552]; 12 mg twice daily 2.2% [6/273]).



    5.4 Gastrointestinal Conditions



  Through their primary action, cholinomimetics may be expected to increase gastric acid secretion due to increased cholinergic activity. Therefore, patients should be monitored closely for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those with an increased risk for developing ulcers, e.g., those with a history of ulcer disease or patients using concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). Clinical studies of galantamine have shown no increase, relative to placebo, in the incidence of either peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding.



 Galantamine, as a predictable consequence of its pharmacological properties, has been shown to produce nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia, and weight loss. During therapy, the patient's weight should be monitored.



    5.5 Genitourinary Conditions



  Although this was not observed in clinical trials with galantamine, cholinomimetics may cause bladder outflow obstruction.



    5.6 Neurological Conditions



  Seizures: Cholinesterase inhibitors are believed to have some potential to cause generalized convulsions [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . Seizure activity may also be a manifestation of Alzheimer's disease. Patients with Alzheimer's disease should be monitored closely for seizures while taking galantamine.



    5.7 Pulmonary Conditions



  Because of its cholinomimetic action, galantamine should be prescribed with care to patients with a history of severe asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease. Respiratory function should be monitored closely for the occurrence of respiratory adverse effects.



    5.8 Deaths in Subjects with Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI)



  In two randomized placebo controlled trials of 2 years duration in patients with mild cognitive impairment (MCI), a total of 13 patients on galantamine (n=1026) and 1 patient on placebo (n=1022) died. The deaths were due to various causes which could be expected in an elderly population; about half of the galantamine deaths appeared to result from various vascular causes (myocardial infarction, stroke, and sudden death).



 Although the difference in mortality between galantamine- and placebo-treated groups in these two studies was significant, the results are highly discrepant with other studies of galantamine. Specifically, in these two MCI studies, the mortality rate in the placebo-treated patients was markedly lower than the rate in placebo-treated patients in trials of galantamine in Alzheimer's disease or other dementias (0.7 per 1000 person years compared to 22-61 per 1000 person years, respectively). Although the mortality rate in the galantamine-treated MCI patients was also lower than that observed in galantamine-treated patients in Alzheimer's disease and other dementia trials (10.2 per 1000 person years compared to 23-31 per 1000 person years, respectively), the relative difference was much less. When the Alzheimer's disease and other dementia studies were pooled (n=6000), the mortality rate in the placebo group numerically exceeded that in the galantamine group. Furthermore, in the MCI studies, no patients in the placebo group died after 6 months, a highly unexpected finding in this population.



 Individuals with mild cognitive impairment demonstrate isolated memory impairment greater than expected for their age and education, but do not meet current diagnostic criteria for Alzheimer's disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
