<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gammaked" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  PI: Intravenous: The most common adverse reactions observed at a rate &gt;=5% in subjects with intravenous treatment in the clinical trials were headache, cough, injection site reaction, nausea, pharyngitis and urticaria.



 PI: Subcutaneous: The most common adverse reactions observed at a rate &gt;=5% of subjects with subcutaneous treatment in the clinical trials were infusion site reactions, headache, fatigue, arthralgia and pyrexia.



 ITP: The most common adverse reactions observed at a rate &gt;=5% in subjects in the clinical trials were headache, vomiting, fever, nausea, back pain and rash.



 CIDP: The most common adverse reactions observed at a rate &gt;=5% in subjects in the clinical trial were headache, fever, chills, hypertension, rash, nausea and asthenia.



   EXCERPT:   Serious adverse reactions which occurred in the clinical trials were an exacerbation of autoimmune pure red cell aplasia in one subject and pulmonary embolism in one subject with a history of PE. The most common adverse reactions observed in &gt;= 5% patients were (  6.1  ):



   PI  :   Intravenous  : Headache, cough, injection site reaction, nausea, pharyngitis and urticaria.        Subcutaneous  : Infusion site reactions, headache, fatigue, arthralgia and pyrexia.  ITP  : Headache, vomiting, fever, nausea, back pain and rash.  CIDP  : Headache, fever, chills, hypertension, rash, nausea and asthenia.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Grifols Therapeutics Inc. at 1-800-520-2807 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of one drug cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.  



     PI: Intravenous Administration    



 The most serious adverse event observed in clinical study subjects receiving GAMMAKED IV for PI was an exacerbation of autoimmune pure red cell aplasia in one subject.



 In four different clinical trials to study PI, out of 157 subjects treated with GAMMAKED, 4 subjects discontinued due to the following adverse events: Coombs negative hypochromic anemia, autoimmune pure red cell aplasia, arthralgia/hyperhidrosis/fatigue/myalgia/nausea and migraine.



 In a study of 87 subjects, 9 subjects in each treatment group were pretreated with non-steroidal medication prior to infusion, such as diphenhydramine and acetaminophen.



   Table 2  lists all adverse events occurring in greater than 10% of subjects irrespective of the causality assessment.



 Table 2:  Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;10% of Subjects Irrespective of Causality 
                                    GAMMAKEDTM                         GAMIMUNE  (r)   N, 10%              
                                    No. of subjects: 87                No. of subjects: 85                 
                                    No. of subjects with AE            No. of subjects with AE             
 Adverse Event                      (percentage of all subjects)       (percentage of all subjects)        
 Cough increased                    47 (54%)                           46 (54%)                            
 Rhinitis                           44 (51%)                           45 (53%)                            
 Pharyngitis                        36 (41%)                           39 (46%)                            
 Headache                           22 (25%)                           28 (33%)                            
 Fever                              24 (28%)                           27 (32%)                            
 Diarrhea                           24 (28%)                           27 (32%)                            
 Asthma                             25 (29%)                           17 (20%)                            
 Nausea                             17 (20%)                           22 (26%)                            
 Ear pain                           16 (18%)                           12 (14%)                            
 Asthenia                           9 (10%)                            13 (15%)                            
        Table 3  lists the adverse reactions reported by at least 5% of subjects during the 9-month treatment.
 

 Table 3:  Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of Subjects 
                                    GAMMAKEDTM                         GAMIMUNE  (r)  N, 10%               
                                    No. of subjects: 87                No. of subjects: 85                 
                                    No. of subjects with adverse reaction  No. of subjects with adverse reaction   
 Adverse Reactions                  (percentage of all subjects)       (percentage of all subjects)        
 Headache                           7 (8%)                             8 (9%)                              
 Cough increased                    6 (7%)                             4 (5%)                              
 Injection site reaction            4 (5%)                             7 (8%)                              
 Nausea                             4 (5%)                             4 (5%)                              
 Pharyngitis                        4 (5%)                             3 (4%)                              
 Urticaria                          4 (5%)                             1 (1%)                              
        Table 4  lists the frequency of adverse reactions, which were reported by at least 5% of subjects, and their relationship to infusions administered.
 

 Table 4: Adverse Experience Frequency 
                       GAMMAKEDTM            GAMIMUNE  (r)   N, 10%   
                       No. of infusions: 825  No. of infusions: 865   
 Adverse Experience    Number (percentage of all infusions)  Number (percentage of all infusions)   
 Cough increased        All                  154 (18.7%)           148 (17.1%)            
   Drug related          14 (1.7%)             11 (1.3%)            
 Pharyngitis           All                   96 (11.6%)            99 (11.4%)             
   Drug related          7 (0.8%)              9 (1.0%)             
 Headache               All                  57 (6.9%)             69 (8.0%)              
   Drug related          7 (0.8%)              11 (1.3%)            
 Fever                 All                   41 (5.0%)             65 (7.5%)              
   Drug related          1 (0.1%)              9 (1.0%)             
 Nausea                All                   31 (3.8%)             43 (5.0%)              
   Drug related          4 (0.5%)              4 (0.5%)             
 Urticaria             All                   5 (0.6%)              8 (0.9%)               
   Drug related          4 (0.5%)              5 (0.6%)             
      The mean number of adverse reactions per infusion that occurred during or on the same day as an infusion was 0.21 in both the GAMMAKED and GAMIMUNE  (r)   N, 10% [Immune Globulin Intravenous (Human), 10%] treatment groups.
 

 In all three trials in primary humoral immunodeficiencies, the maximum infusion rate was 0.08 mL/kg/min (8 mg/kg/min). The infusion rate was reduced for 11 of 222 exposed subjects (7 GAMMAKED, 4 GAMIMUNE N, 10%) at 17 occasions. In most instances, mild to moderate hives/urticaria, itching, pain or reaction at infusion site, anxiety or headache was the main reason. There was one case of severe chills. There were no anaphylactic or anaphylactoid reactions to GAMMAKED or GAMIMUNE N, 10% in clinical trials.



 In the IV efficacy and safety study, serum samples were drawn to monitor the viral safety at baseline and one week after the first infusion (for parvovirus B19), eight weeks after first and fifth infusion, and 16 weeks after the first and fifth infusion of IGIV (for hepatitis C) and at any time of premature discontinuation of the study. Viral markers of hepatitis C, hepatitis B, HIV-1, and parvovirus B19 were monitored by nucleic acid testing (NAT, Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)), and serological testing.



     PI: Subcutaneous Administration (PK and Safety Study)    



 Adverse experiences were divided into 2 types: 1) Local infusion site reactions, and 2) Non-infusion site adverse events.  Table 5   lists those adverse events occurring in &gt;= 2% of infusions during the SC phase of the study.



 Table 5: Most Frequent Adverse Experience (&gt;= 2% of infusions) by Infusion Irrespective of Causality in the SC Phase 
 Adverse Experience                                                     
 (&gt;=2% of infusions)                Number                              
 (Number of infusions: 725)         (Rate)                              
 Local Infusion Site Reactions      427 (0.59)                          
       Mild                         389 (0.54)                          
       Moderate                       29 (0.04)                         
       Severe                           9 (0.01)                        
 Non-infusion Site Adverse Events                                       
       Headache                       37 (0.05)                         
       Sinusitis                      11 (0.02)                         
        Table 6  lists the adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of subjects and the frequency of adverse reactions per infusion.  All local infusion site reactions were  a priori  considered drug-related.
 

 Table 6: Most Frequent Adverse Reactions (&gt;=5% of subjects) by Subject and Infusion in the SC phase 
   Adverse Reactions                 No. of Subjects                     No. of Adverse Reactions          
   (&gt;=5% of subjects)                 n=32 (%  )                         (Rate    )                        
 Local Infusion Site Reactions      24 (75%)                           427 (0.59)                          
 Non-infusion Site Adverse Reactions                                                                         
       Headache                     4 (13%)                            21  (0.03)                          
       Arthralgia                   2 (6.3%)                           4   (0.01)                          
       Fatigue                      2 (6.3%)                           3  (&lt;=0.01)                         
       Pyrexia                      2 (6.3%)                           2  (&lt;=0.01)                         
      There were no serious bacterial infections in the SC phase of the PK and safety study.
 

   Local Infusion Site Reactions  



 Local infusion site reactions with SC GAMMAKED consisted of erythema, pain and swelling. The majority of local infusion site reactions resolved within 3 days. The number of subjects experiencing an infusion site reaction and the number of infusion site reactions decreased over time as subjects received continued weekly SC infusions. At the beginning of the SC phase (week 1), a rate of approximately 1 infusion site reaction per infusion was reported, whereas at the end of the study (week 24) this rate was reduced to 0.5 infusion site reactions per infusion, a reduction of 50%.



     ITP    



 In two different clinical trials to study ITP, out of 76 subjects treated with GAMMAKED, 2 subjects discontinued due to the following adverse events: Hives and Headache/Fever/Vomiting.



 One subject, a 10-year-old boy, died suddenly from myocarditis 50 days after his second infusion of GAMMAKED. The death was judged to be unrelated to GAMMAKED.



 No pre-medication with corticosteroids was permitted by the protocol. Twelve ITP subjects treated in each treatment group were pretreated with medication prior to infusion. Generally, diphenhydramine and/or acetaminophen were used. More than 90% of the observed drug related adverse events were of mild to moderate severity and of transient nature.



 The infusion rate was reduced for 4 of the 97 exposed subjects (1 GAMMAKED, 3 GAMIMUNE N, 10%) on 4 occasions. Mild to moderate headache, nausea, and fever were the reported reasons.



   Table 7  lists any adverse events, irrespective of the causality, reported by at least 5% of subjects during the 3-month efficacy and safety study.



 Table 7: Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;= 5% of Subjects Irrespective of Causality 
                                    GAMMAKEDTM                         GAMIMUNE  (r)  N, 10%               
                                    No. of subjects: 48                No. of subjects: 49                 
                                    No. of subjects with AE            No. of subjects with AE             
  Adverse Event                     (percentage of all subjects)       (percentage of all subjects)        
 Headache                           28 (58%)                           30 (61%)                            
 Ecchymosis, Purpura                19 (40%)                           25 (51%)                            
 Hemorrhage (All systems)           14 (29%)                           16 (33%)                            
 Epistaxis                          11 (23%)                           12 (24%)                            
 Petechiae                          10 (21%)                           15 (31%)                            
 Fever                              10 (21%)                           7 (14%)                             
 Vomiting                           10 (21%)                           10 (20%)                            
 Nausea                             10 (21%)                           7 (14%)                             
 Thrombocytopenia                   7 (15%)                            8 (16%)                             
 Accidental injury                  6 (13%)                            8 (16%)                             
 Rhinitis                           6 (13%)                            6 (12%)                             
 Pharyngitis                        5 (10%)                            5 (10%)                             
 Rash                               5 (10%)                            6 (12%)                             
 Pruritis                           4 (8%)                             1 (2%)                              
 Asthenia                           3 (6%)                             5 (10%)                             
 Abdominal Pain                     3 (6%)                             4 (8%)                              
 Arthralgia                         3 (6%)                             6 (12%)                             
 Back Pain                          3 (6%)                             3 (6%)                              
 Dizziness                          3 (6%)                             3 (6%)                              
 Flu Syndrome                       3 (6%)                             3 (6%)                              
 Neck Pain                          3 (6%)                             1 (2%)                              
 Anemia                             3 (6%)                             0 (0%)                              
 Dyspepsia                          3 (6%)                             0 (0%)                              
        Table 8  lists the adverse reactions reported by at least 5% of subjects during the 3-month efficacy and safety study.
 

 Table 8: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of Subjects 
                                    GAMMAKEDTM                         GAMIMUNE  (r)   N, 10%              
                                    No. of subjects: 48                No. of subjects: 49                 
  Adverse Reaction                  Number (percentage of all subjects)  Number (percentage of all subjects)   
 Headache                           24 (50%)                           24 (49%)                            
 Vomiting                            6 (13%)                            8 (16%)                            
 Fever                               5 (10%)                            5 (10%)                            
 Nausea                              5 (10%)                              4 (8%)                           
 Back Pain                            3 (6%)                             2 (4%)                            
 Rash                                 3 (6%)                             0 (0%)                            
      Serum samples were drawn to monitor the viral safety of the ITP subjects at baseline, nine days after the first infusion (for parvovirus B19), and 3 months after the first infusion of IGIV and at any time of premature discontinuation of the study. Viral markers of hepatitis C, hepatitis B, HIV-1, and parvovirus B19 were monitored by nucleic acid testing (NAT, PCR), and serological testing. There were no treatment related emergent findings of viral transmission for either GAMMAKED or GAMIMUNE N, 10%.
 

     CIDP    



 In the CIDP efficacy and safety study, 113 subjects were exposed to GAMMAKED and 95 were exposed to Placebo.  (see  Clinical Studies      [14]  ) As a result of the study design, the drug exposure with GAMMAKED was almost twice that of Placebo, with 1096 GAMMAKED infusions versus 575 Placebo infusions. Therefore, adverse reactions are reported per infusion (represented as frequency) to correct for differences in drug exposure between the 2 groups. The majority of loading-doses were administered over 2 days. The majority of maintenance-doses were administered over 1 day. Infusions were administered in the mean over 2.7 hours.



   Table 9  shows the numbers of subjects per treatment group in the CIDP clinical trial, and the reason for discontinuation due to adverse events.



 Table 9: Reasons for Discontinuation Due to Adverse Events 
 Number of Subjects  Number of Subjects Discontinueddue to Adverse Events  Adverse Event                       
 GAMMAKEDTM         113               3 (2.7%)                           Urticaria, Dyspnea,Bronchopneumonia   
 Placebo            95                2 (2.1%)                           Cerebrovascular Accident,Deep Vein Thrombosis   
        Table 10  shows adverse events reported by at least 5% of subjects in any treatment group irrespective of causality.
 

 Table 10: Adverse Events Irrespective of Causality Occurring in &gt;= 5% of Subjects 
                               GAMMAKEDTMNo. of subjects: 113  PlaceboNo. of subjects: 95   
  MedDRAPreferred Term          No. of Subjects(%)   No. ofAdverseEvents  Incidence density   No. of Subjects(%)   No. ofAdverseEvents  Incidencedensity   
 Any Adverse Event             85 (75)       377           0.344         45 (47)       120           0.209          
 Headache                      36 (32)       57            0.052         8 (8)         15            0.026          
 Pyrexia (fever)               15 (13)       27            0.025         0             0             0              
 Hypertension                  10 (9)        20            0.018         4 (4)         6             0.010          
 Rash                          8 (7)         13            0.012         1 (1)         1             0.002          
 Arthralgia                    8 (7)         11            0.010         1 (1)         1             0.002          
 Asthenia                      9 (8)         10            0.009         3 (3)         4             0.007          
 Chills                        9 (8)         10            0.009         0             0             0              
 Back pain                     9 (8)         10            0.009         3 (3)         3             0.005          
 Nausea                        7 (6)         9             0.008         3 (3)         3             0.005          
 Dizziness                     7 (6)         3             0.006         1 (1)         1             0.002          
 Influenza                     6 (5)         6             0.005         2 (2)         2             0.003          
      The most common adverse reactions with GAMMAKED were headache and pyrexia.  Table 11  lists adverse reactions reported by at least 5% of subjects in any treatment group.
 

 Table 11: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 5% of Subjects 
                               GAMMAKEDTMNo. of subjects: 113  PlaceboNo. of subjects: 95   
  MedDRAPreferred Term         No. ofSubjects(%)  No. ofAdverseEvents  Incidence density  No. ofSubjects(%)  No. ofAdverseEvents  Incidencedensity   
 Any Adverse Reaction          62 (55)       194           0.177         16 (17)       25            0.043          
 Headache                      31 (27)       44            0.040         6  (6)        7             0.012          
 Pyrexia (fever)               15 (13)       26            0.024         0             0             0              
 Chills                        8 (7)         9             0.008         0             0             0              
 Hypertension                  7 (6)         16            0.015         3 (3)         3             0.005          
 Rash                          6 (5)         8             0.007         1 (1)         1             0.002          
 Nausea                        6 (5)         7             0.006         3 (3)         3             0.005          
 Asthenia                      6 (5)         6             0.005         0             0             0              
      The most serious adverse reaction observed in clinical study subjects receiving GAMMAKED for CIDP was pulmonary embolism (PE) in one subject with a history of PE.
 

     Laboratory Abnormalities    



 During the course of the clinical program, ALT and AST elevations were identified in some subjects.



 *  For ALT, in the IV PI study treatment emergent elevations above the upper limit of normal were transient and observed among 14/80 (18%) of subjects in the GAMMAKED group versus 5/88 (6%) of subjects in the GAMIMUNE N, 10% group (p=0.026). 
 *  In the SC PI study treatment emergent laboratory abnormalities during the SC phase occurred in several subjects. Four subjects (4/32, 13%) had elevated Alkaline Phosphatase and one subject (1/32, 3%) had a low Alkaline Phosphatase. One subject (1/32, 3%) had an elevated ALT and three subjects (3/32, 9%) had an elevated AST. No elevations were &gt;1.6 times the upper limit of normal. 
 *  In the ITP study which employed a higher dose per infusion, but a maximum of only two infusions, the reverse finding was observed among 3/44 (7%) of subjects in the GAMMAKED group versus 8/43 (19%) of subjects in the GAMIMUNE N, 10% group (p=0.118). 
 *  In the CIDP study, 15/113 (13%) of subjects in the GAMMAKED group and 7/95 (7%) in the Placebo group (p=0.168) had a treatment emergent transient elevation of ALT. 
    Elevations of ALT and AST were generally mild (&lt;3 times upper limit of normal), transient, and were not associated with obvious symptoms of liver dysfunction.
 

 GAMMAKED may contain low levels of anti-Blood Group A and B antibodies primarily of the IgG4class. Direct antiglobulin tests (DAT or direct Coombs tests), which are carried out in some centers as a safety check prior to red blood cell transfusions, may become positive temporarily. Hemolytic events not associated with positive DAT findings were observed in clinical trials.



 



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Because adverse reactions are voluntary and reported post-approval from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequencies or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



   GAMMAKED Postmarketing Experience  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during the post marketing use of GAMMAKED:




   Hematologic:             Hemolytic anemia            
   Infections and Infestations:    Aseptic meningitis          
      The following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during the overall post marketing use of IGIV products:  (17)  
 

 *   Respiratory: Apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS), TRALI, cyanosis, hypoxemia, pulmonary edema, dyspnea, bronchospasm 
 *   Cardiovascular: Cardiac arrest, thromboembolism, vascular collapse, hypotension 
 *   Neurological: Coma, loss of consciousness, seizures/convulsions, tremor 
 *   Integumentary: Stevens-Johnson syndrome, epidermolysis, erythema multiforme, bullous dermatitis 
 *   Hematologic: Pancytopenia, leukopenia, hemolysis, positive direct antiglobulin (Coombs test) 
 *   General/Body as a Whole: Pyrexia, rigors 
 *   Musculoskeletal: Back pain 
 *   Gastrointestinal: Hepatic dysfunction, abdominal pain 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION, and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE

  WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION, and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE

    *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including GAMMAKED. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors.  Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors. (see Warnings and Precautions [5.4], Patient Counseling Information [17])  
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer GAMMAKED at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity. (see Dosage and Administration [2.5], Warnings and Precautions [5.4]) 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products in predisposed patients. Patients predisposed to renal dysfunction include those with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs. 
 *  Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose.(1) GAMMAKED does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of renal dysfunction or failure, administer GAMMAKED at the minimum concentration available and the minimum infusion rate practicable. (see Warnings and Precautions [5.2]) 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including GAMMAKED. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer GAMMAKED at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity. 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products in predisposed patients. 
 *  Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose. GAMMAKED does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of renal dysfunction or failure, administer GAMMAKED at the minimum concentration available and the minimum infusion rate practicable. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  IgA deficient patients with antibodies against IgA are at greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. Have epinephrine available immediately to treat any acute severe hypersensitivity reactions. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Monitor renal function, including blood urea nitrogen, serum creatinine, and urine output in patients at risk of developing acute renal failure. (  5.2  )  
 *  Hyperproteinemia, with resultant changes in serum viscosity and electrolyte imbalances may occur in patients receiving IGIV therapy. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Thrombosis has occurred in patients receiving IGIV therapy. Monitor patients with known risk factors for thrombosis; consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity for those at risk of hyperviscosity. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS) has been reported with GAMMAKED and other IGIV treatments, especially with high doses or rapid infusion. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to IGIV therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration. Monitor patients for hemolysis and hemolytic anemia. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions (transfusion-related acute lung injury [TRALI]). (  5.7  ) 
 *  Volume overload. (  5.8  ) 
 *  GAMMAKED is made from human plasma and may contain infectious agents, e.g., viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent. (  5.9  ) 
 *  GAMMAKED is not approved for subcutaneous use in ITP patients. Due to a potential risk of hematoma formation, do not administer GAMMAKED subcutaneously in patients with ITP. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Passive transfer of antibodies may confound serologic testing. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur with IGIV products, including GAMMAKED. In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue GAMMAKED infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment. Have medications such as epinephrine available for immediate treatment of acute hypersensitivity reaction.



 GAMMAKED contains trace amounts of IgA (average 46 micrograms/mL). Patients with known antibodies to IgA may have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. It is contraindicated in IgA deficient patients with antibodies against IgA and history of hypersensitivity reaction. ( see     Contraindications      [4]  )



    5.2 Renal Failure



  Acute renal dysfunction/failure, acute tubular necrosis, proximal tubular nephropathy, osmotic nephrosis and death may occur upon use of IGIV products, especially those containing sucrose.(  17  ) GAMMAKED does not contain sucrose. Assure that patients are not volume depleted prior to the initiation of the infusion of GAMMAKED. Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to have a potential increased risk for developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN)/serum creatinine, prior to the initial infusion of GAMMAKED and again at appropriate intervals thereafter. If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuation of GAMMAKED. ( see  Patient Counseling Information       [17]  ) For patients judged to be at risk for developing renal dysfunction, including patients with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs, administer GAMMAKED at the minimum infusion rate practicable [less than 8 mg IG/kg/min (0.08 mL/kg/min)]. ( see  Dosage and Administration       [2.5]  )



    5.3 Hyperproteinemia, Increased Serum Viscosity, and Hyponatremia



  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity and hyponatremia may occur in patients receiving IGIV treatment, including GAMMAKED. It is clinically critical to distinguish true hyponatremia from a pseudohyponatremia that is associated with concomitant decreased calculated serum osmolality or elevated osmolar gap, because treatment aimed at decreasing serum free water in patients with pseudohyponatremia may lead to volume depletion, a further increase in serum viscosity and a possible predisposition to thrombosis.  (8)  



    5.4 Thrombosis



   Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products, including GAMMAKED. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors.  



  Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer GAMMAKED at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity. ( see  Boxed Warning  ,  Dosage and Administration      [2.5]  ,   Patient Counseling Information      [17]  )  



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



  AMS may occur infrequently with IGIV treatment, including GAMMAKED. Discontinuation of IGIV treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae.  The syndrome usually begins within several hours to two days following IGIV treatment. AMS is characterized by the following symptoms and signs:  severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea and vomiting. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies are frequently positive with pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per cu mm, predominantly from the granulocytic series, and with elevated protein levels up to several hundred mg/dL, but negative culture results. Conduct a thorough neurological examination on patients exhibiting such symptoms and signs including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis. AMS may occur more frequently in association with high doses (2 g/kg) and/or rapid infusion of IGIV.



    5.6 Hemolysis



  IGIV products, including GAMMAKED, may contain blood group antibodies which may act as hemolysins and induce in vivo coating of red blood cells (RBCs) with immunoglobulin, causing a positive direct antiglobulin reaction and, rarely, hemolysis.(  12-14  ) Delayed hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to IGIV therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration, and acute hemolysis consistent with intravascular hemolysis, has been reported. ( see  Adverse Reactions       [6])  



 The following risk factors may be related to the development of hemolysis: high doses (e.g., &gt;=2 grams/kg, single administration or divided over several days) and non-O blood group.  (29)  Underlying inflammatory state in an individual patient may increase the risk of hemolysis, but its role is uncertain.  (30)  



 Monitor patients for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis ( see     Warnings and Precautions       [5.11]  ), particularly patients with risk factors noted above. Consider appropriate laboratory testing in higher risk patients, including measurement of hemoglobin or hematocrit prior to infusion and within approximately 36 to 96 hours post infusion. If clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis or a significant drop in hemoglobin or hematocrit have been observed, perform additional confirmatory laboratory testing. If transfusion is indicated for patients who develop hemolysis with clinically compromising anemia after receiving IGIV, perform adequate cross-matching to avoid exacerbating on-going hemolysis.



    5.7 Transfusion-related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Noncardiogenic pulmonary edema may occur in patients following treatment with IGIV products, including GAMMAKED.  (16)  TRALI is characterized by severe respiratory distress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function, and fever. Symptoms typically occur within 1 to 6 hours after treatment.



 Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions. ( see     Patient Counseling Information      [17]  ) If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil and anti-HLA antibodies in both the product and patient serum. TRALI may be managed using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



    5.8 Volume Overload



  The high dose regimen (1g/kg x 1-2 days) is not recommended for individuals with expanded fluid volumes or where fluid volume may be a concern.



    5.9 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because GAMMAKED is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have ever been identified for GAMMAKED. ALL infections suspected by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Grifols Therapeutics Inc. [1-800-520-2807]



    5.10 Hematoma Formation



  Do not administer GAMMAKED subcutaneously in patients with ITP because of the risk of hematoma formation.



    5.11 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



    *  Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of BUN and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of GAMMAKED and at appropriate intervals thereafter. 
 *  Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies, because of the potentially increased risk of thrombosis. 
 *  If signs and/or symptoms of hemolysis are present after an infusion of GAMMAKED, perform appropriate laboratory testing for confirmation. 
 *  If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies and anti-HLA antibodies in both the product and patient's serum. 
       5.12 Interference with Laboratory Tests
 

  After infusion of IgG, the transitory rise of the various passively transferred antibodies in the patient's blood may yield positive serological testing results, with the potential for misleading interpretation. Passive transmission of antibodies to erythrocyte antigens (e.g., A, B, and D) may cause a positive direct or indirect antiglobulin (Coombs') test.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
