<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gammagard1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    PI: Intravenous  : The serious adverse reaction seen during intravenous treatment in the clinical trials for PI was aseptic meningitis. The most common adverse reactions for PI (observed in &gt;=5% of subjects) were headache, fatigue, pyrexia, nausea, chills, rigors, pain in extremity, diarrhea, migraine, dizziness, vomiting, cough, urticaria, asthma, pharyngolaryngeal pain, rash, arthralgia, myalgia, oedema peripheral, pruritus, and cardiac murmur.



   Subcutaneous  : No serious adverse reactions were observed during the clinical trial for subcutaneous treatment. The most common adverse reactions during subcutaneous treatment (observed in &gt;=5% of PI subjects) were infusion site (local) event, headache, fatigue, heart rate increased, pyrexia, abdominal pain upper, nausea, vomiting, asthma, blood pressure systolic increased, diarrhea, ear pain, aphthous stomatitis, migraine, oropharyngeal pain, and pain in extremity.



   MMN  : The serious adverse reactions in the clinical trial for MMN were pulmonary embolism and blurred vision. The most common adverse reactions for MMN (observed in &gt;=5% of subjects) were headache, chest discomfort, muscle spasms, muscular weakness, nausea, oropharyngeal pain, and pain in extremity.



   EXCERPT:   Serious adverse reactions which occurred in the clinical trials were aseptic meningitis, pulmonary embolism, and blurred vision (  6.1  )



 The most common adverse reactions observed in &gt;=5% of patients were (  6.1  ):



   PI  :  Intravenous Administration  : Headache, fatigue, pyrexia, nausea, chills, rigors, pain in extremity, diarrhea, migraine, dizziness, vomiting, cough, urticaria, asthma, pharyngolaryngeal pain, rash, arthralgia, myalgia, oedema peripheral, pruritus, and cardiac murmur.



   Subcutaneous Administration  : Infusion site (local) event, headache, fatigue, heart rate increased, pyrexia, abdominal pain upper, nausea, vomiting, asthma, blood pressure systolic increased, diarrhea, ear pain, aphthous stomatitis, migraine, oropharygneal pain, and pain in extremity.



   MMN  : Headache, chest discomfort, muscle spasms, muscular weakness, nausea, oropharyngeal pain, and pain in extremity.



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare Corporation at 1-866-888-2472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice  .



   PI: Intravenous Administration  



 The safety of GAMMAGARD LIQUID intravenous infusion was evaluated in 61 subjects  10  .



 Fifteen adverse reactions in 8 subjects were serious. Of these, two episodes of aseptic meningitis in one patient were deemed possibly related to the infusion of GAMMAGARD LIQUID.



 There were 400 non-serious adverse reactions. Of these, 217 were rated as mild (transient discomfort that resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention), 164 were rated as moderate (limited impairment of function and resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention with no sequelae), and 19 were rated as severe (marked impairment of function or can lead to temporary inability to resume normal life pattern; requires prolonged intervention or results in sequelae). All of the severe non-serious adverse experiences were transient, did not lead to hospitalization, and resolved without complication. One subject withdrew from the study due to a non-serious adverse experience (papular rash).



 Adverse reactions with a frequency of &gt;=5% (defined as adverse events occurring during or within 72 hours of infusion or any causally related event occurring within the study period) are shown in Table 5.



 Table 5 Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of Subjects 
  Events                     By Infusion N (%)  (N=1812 Infusions)    By Subject N (%)  (N=61 Subjects)          
  Headache                   94 (5.2%)                    29 (47.5%)                                 
  Fatigue                    33 (1.8%)                    14 (23.0%)                                 
  Pyrexia                    28 (1.5%)                    17 (27.9%)                                 
  Nausea                     17 (0.9%)                    11 (18.0%)                                 
  Chills                     14 (0.8%)                    8 (13.1%)                                  
  Rigors                     14 (0.8%)                    8 (13.1%)                                  
  Pain in extremity          13 (0.7%)                    7 (11.5%)                                  
  Diarrhea                   12 (0.7%)                    9 (14.8%)                                  
  Migraine                   12 (0.7%)                    4 (6.6%)                                   
  Dizziness                  11 (0.6%)                    8 (13.1%)                                  
  Vomiting                   11 (0.6%)                    9 (14.8%)                                  
  Cough                      9 (0.5%)                     8 (13.1%)                                  
  Urticaria                  9 (0.5%)                     5 (8.2%)                                   
  Asthma                     7 (0.4%)                     6 (9.8%)                                   
  Pharyngolaryngeal pain     7 (0.4%)                     5 (8.2%)                                   
  Rash                       6 (0.3%)                     4 (6.6%)                                   
  Arthralgia                 5 (0.3%)                     4 (6.6%)                                   
  Myalgia                    5 (0.3%)                     5 (8.2%)                                   
  Oedema peripheral          5 (0.3%)                     5 (8.2%)                                   
  Pruritus                   5 (0.3%)                     4 (6.6%)                                   
  Cardiac murmur             4 (0.2%)                     4 (6.6%)                                   
           PI: Subcutaneous Administration  
 

 The safety of GAMMAGARD LIQUID in subcutaneous infusion was evaluated in 47 subjects  11  .



 Adverse reactions with a frequency of &gt;=5% (defined as adverse events occurring during or within 72 hours of infusion or any causally related event occurring within the study period) are shown in Table 6.



 Table 6 Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of Subjects 
  Events                           By Infusion N (%)  (N=2294 infusions)    By Subject N (%)  (N=47 Subjects)    
  Infusion site (local) event      55 (2.4%)                        21 (44.7%)                       
  Headache                         31 (1.4%)                        19 (40.4%)                       
  Fatigue                          11 (0.5%)                        7 (14.9%)                        
  Heart rate increased             11 (0.5%)                        3 (6.4%)                         
  Pyrexia                          11 (0.5%)                        9 (19.1%)                        
  Abdominal pain upper             9 (0.4%)                         5 (10.6%)                        
  Nausea                           7 (0.3%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
  Vomiting                         7 (0.3%)                         5 (10.6%)                        
  Asthma                           6 (0.3%)                         4 (8.5%)                         
  Blood pressure systolic increased    6 (0.3%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
  Diarrhea                         5 (0.2%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
  Ear pain                         4 (0.2%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
  Aphthous stomatitis              3 (0.1%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
  Migraine                         3 (0.1%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
  Oropharyngeal pain               3 (0.1%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
  Pain in extremity                3 (0.1%)                         3 (6.4%)                         
         Of the 348 non-serious ARs, 228 were rated as mild (transient discomfort that resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention), 112 were rated as moderate (limited impairment of function and resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention with no sequelae), and 8 were rated as severe (marked impairment of function or can lead to temporary inability to resume normal life pattern; requires prolonged intervention or results in sequelae). Neither of the severe ARs required hospitalization or resulted in sequelae.
 

   Local AEs:  Local AEs reported as mild (transient discomfort that resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention) were rash, erythema, edema, hemorrhage, and irritation. Local AEs reported as mild or moderate (limited impairment of function and resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention with no sequelae) were pain, hematoma, pruritus, and swelling.



 One subject withdrew from the study after 10 treatments with GAMMAGARD LIQUID subcutaneous infusion (2.5 months) due to increased fatigue and malaise.



 The overall rate of local ARs (excluding infections) during the subcutaneous treatment periods was 2.4% per infusion. In subcutaneous naive patients, the incidence of local ARs (N=1757 infusions) was 2.8% (2.2% mild and 0.6% moderate with no severe AEs). In the subjects who were subcutaneous experienced (N=537 infusions), the incidence of local AEs was 1.1% (1.1% mild, and no moderate or severe AEs).



 In the clinical study after all subcutaneous doses were adjusted, all subjects but one reached their maximum rate allowed in the protocol, 20 mL/site/hour if weight was below 40 kg and 30/mL/hour for weight 40 kg and greater, for one or more of the infusions. 70% (31 of 44) of these subjects opted for the highest rate for all infusions.  No subject restricted the rate due to an AR. In the clinical study, median duration of each weekly infusion was 1.2 hours (range: 0.8-2.3 hours) after all subcutaneous doses were adjusted. The rate set on the pump was that rate per site multiplied by the number of sites, with no maximum.



 During all subcutaneous treatment periods, 99.8% of infusions were completed without a reduction, interruption, or discontinuation for tolerability reasons. The proportion of subjects who experienced local ARs (excluding infections) was highest immediately following the switch from intravenous to subcutaneous treatment in all age groups. The rate of all local ARs per infusion immediately after switching from intravenous to subcutaneous treatment was 4.9% (29/595), decreasing to 1.5% (8/538) by the end of the study and to 1.1% (10/893) in the Study Extension. Over subsequent subcutaneous infusions, there was a decrease of local ARs.



 Eight (17%) subjects experienced a local adverse reaction during the first infusion, but that decreased to 1 (2.2%) for the subsequent infusions, ranging from 0 to 4 (8.7%) during the first year of subcutaneous treatment. No subject reported a local adverse reaction from week 53 to end of study at week 68.



   MMN: Intravenous Infusion  



 The safety of GAMMAGARD LIQUID was evaluated in 44 subjects with MMN who received a total of 983 infusions. Two serious adverse reactions, pulmonary embolism, and blurred vision occurred.



 In the study, among the 317 non-serious AEs, 176 were considered ARs. Of these, 126 were mild (transient discomfort that resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention), 37 were moderate (limited impairment of function and resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention with no sequelae) and 13 were severe (marked impairment of function or can lead to temporary inability to resume normal life pattern; requires prolonged intervention or results in sequelae).



 Adverse reactions with a frequency of &gt;=5% (defined as adverse events occurring during or within 72 hours of infusion or any causally related event occurring within the study period) are shown in Table 7.



 Table 7 Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of MMN Subjects 
  Events              GAMMAGARD LIQUID      Placebo               
  By Infusion  N (%)  (N=983 Infusions)    By Subject  N (%)  (N=44 Subjects)    By Infusion  N (%)  (N=129 Infusions)    By Subject  N (%)  (N=43 Subjects)    
  Headache            28 (2.85%)            14 (31.82%)           3 (2.33%)             2 (4.65%)               
  Chest Discomfort    3 (0.31%)             3 (6.82%)             0 (0.00%)             0 (0.00%)               
  Muscle Spasms       3 (0.31%)             3 (6.82%)             0 (0.00%)             0 (0.00%)               
  Muscular weakness    4 (0.41%)             3 (6.82%)             1 (0.78%)             1 (2.33%)               
  Nausea              28 (2.85%)            3 (6.82%)             2 (1.55%)             1 (2.33%)               
  Oropharyngeal pain    4 (0.41%)             3 (6.82%)             0 (0.00%)             0 (0.00%)               
  Pain in extremity    4 (0.41%)             3 (6.82%)             1 (0.78%)             1 (2.33%)               
             6.2 Postmarketing Experience
     Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



 Intravenous ADRs 
  Hematologic                                 Leukopenia                                          
  Infusion Reactions                          Anaphylactic shock, anaphylactic reaction           
  Neurological                                Transient ischemic attack, tremor, burning sensation    
  Cardiovascular                              Hypotension, phlebitis, hypertension, chest pain    
  Respiratory                                 Pulmonary edema, dyspnea, oxygen saturation decreased    
  Gastrointestinal                            Abdominal pain                                      
  Integumentary                               Hyperhidrosis, allergic dermatitis                  
  Psychiatric                                 Anxiety, insomnia                                   
        In addition to the events listed above which were observed for GAMMAGARD LIQUID, the following events have been identified for IGIV products in general:
 


  Renal                                        Osmotic nephropathy                                 
  Respiratory                                  Cyanosis, hypoxemia, bronchospasm, apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS)    
  Integumentary                                Bullous dermatitis, epidermolysis, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome    
  Cardiovascular                               Cardiac arrest, vascular collapse                   
  Neurological                                 Coma, seizures, loss of consciousness               
  Hematologic  Gastrointestinal                Pancytopenia  Hepatic dysfunction                   
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE

  WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE

    *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including GAMMAGARD LIQUID. Risk factors may include advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors. [see Warnings and Precautions(5.4), Patient Counseling Information (17)] 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products in predisposed patients. Patients predisposed to renal dysfunction include those with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs. Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose. GAMMAGARD LIQUID does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer GAMMAGARD LIQUID at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk of hyperviscosity. [see Dosage and Administration (2.3) and Warnings and Precautions (5.4)] 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING:  THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including GAMMAGARD LIQUID. Risk factors may include advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur in predisposed patients with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products including GAMMAGARD LIQUID. Renal dysfunction and acute failure occur more commonly with IGIV products containing sucrose. GAMMAGARD LIQUID does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer GAMMAGARD LIQUID at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk of hyperviscosity. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    IgA deficient patients with antibodies to IgA are at greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reaction. (  5.1)   
 *    Monitor renal function, including blood urea nitrogen, serum creatinine, and urine output in patients at risk of acute renal failure. (  5.2)   
 *    Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity and hyponatremia may occur. (  5.3)   
 *    Thrombosis may occur. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity for those at risk for hyperviscosity. (  5.4)   
 *    Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS) may occur. (  5.5)   
 *    Hemolytic anemia can develop. Monitor for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis and hemolytic anemia. (  5.6)   
 *    Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions (transfusion-related acute lung injury, TRALI).  (5.7)   
 *    Product is made from human blood may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent (  5.8)   
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur, even in patients who had tolerated previous treatment with human normal immune globulin. In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue GAMMAGARD LIQUID infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment.



  GAMMAGARD LIQUID contains trace amount of IgA (average concentration of 37mug/mL). Patients with antibodies to IgA have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. GAMMAGARD LIQUID is contraindicated in patients with antibodies against IgA and a history of hypersensitivity reaction  [ see Contraindications (  4)    ].
 

    5.2 Renal Dysfunction/Failure



  Acute renal dysfunction/failure, acute tubular necrosis, proximal tubular nephropathy, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur upon use of IGIV treatment, especially those containing sucrose  3  . Acute renal dysfunction/failure has been reported in association with infusions of GAMMAGARD LIQUID. Assure that patients are not volume depleted prior to the initiation of infusion of GAMMAGARD LIQUID. In patients who are at risk of developing renal dysfunction, because of pre-existing renal insufficiency or predisposition to acute renal failure (such as diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs, etc.), administer GAMMAGARD LIQUID intravenously at the minimum rate of infusion practicable (not exceeding 3.3 milligram IgG/kg/min (&lt;2 mL/kg/hr) [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3)  ]  .



 Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk for developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of GAMMAGARD LIQUID and again at appropriate intervals thereafter. If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuation of GAMMAGARD LIQUID [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3)    ].



    5.3 Hyperproteinemia, Increased Serum Viscosity, and Hyponatremia



  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity and hyponatremia may occur in patients receiving GAMMAGARD LIQUID. It is critical to distinguish true hyponatremia from a pseudohyponatremia that is temporally or causally related to hyperproteinemia with concomitant decreased calculated serum osmolality or elevated osmolar gap; because treatment aimed at decreasing serum free water in patients with pseudohyponatremia may lead to volume depletion, a further increase in serum viscosity, and a predisposition to thromboembolic events  4  .



    5.4 Thrombosis



   Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products, including GAMMAGARD LIQUID. Risk factors may include advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors.  



  Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer GAMMAGARD LIQUID at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity  [see Boxed Warning,Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ), Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



  AMS may occur with IGIV treatment, and has been reported with intravenous use of GAMMAGARD LIQUID. Discontinuation of IGIV treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae. The syndrome usually begins within several hours to two days following IGIV treatment.



 AMS is characterized by the following signs and symptoms: severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea and vomiting [ see Patient Counseling Information  (17)]  .  Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies frequently reveal pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per mm  3  , predominantly from the granulocytic series, and elevated protein levels up to several hundred milligram/dL, but negative culture results. Conduct a thorough neurological examination on patients exhibiting such symptoms and signs, including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis.



 AMS may occur more frequently with high dose (2 grams/kg) IGIV treatment and/or rapid infusion of IGIV.



    5.6 Hemolysis



   GAMMAGARD LIQUID, contains blood group antibodies that may act as hemolysins and induce in vivo  coating of red blood cells (RBC) with immune globulin. This may cause a positive direct antiglobulin test [DAT (Coomb's test)]  5-6  . Delayed hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to GAMMAGARD LIQUID therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration; acute hemolysis, consistent with intravascular hemolysis, has been reported [  see Adverse Reactions     (  6  )]    5-8  .
 

 The following risk factors may be related to the development of hemolysis: high doses (e.g., &gt;=2 grams/kg, single administration or divided over several days) and non-O blood group.  5  Underlying inflammatory state in an individual patient may increase the risk of hemolysis  5  but its role is uncertain  8,9  .



 Monitor patients for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.9  )]  , particularly patients with risk factors noted above. Consider appropriate laboratory testing in higher risk patients, including measurement of hemoglobin or hematocrit prior to infusion and within approximately 36 to 96 hours post infusion. If clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis or a significant drop in hemoglobin or hematocrit have been observed, perform additional confirmatory laboratory testing. If transfusion is indicated for patients who develop hemolysis with clinically compromising anemia after receiving IGIV, perform adequate cross-matching to avoid exacerbating on-going hemolysis.



    5.7 Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Non-cardiogenic pulmonary edema (TRALI) has been reported in patients following treatment with IGIV products, including GAMMAGARD LIQUID. TRALI is characterized by severe respiratory distress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function, and fever. Symptoms typically occur within 1 to 6 hours after treatment.



 Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions [ see Patient Counseling Information  (17)]    . If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil and anti-HLA antibodies in both the product and patient serum. TRALI may be managed using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



    5.8 Transmittable Infectious Agents



  Because GAMMAGARD LIQUID is made from human blood and may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent. This also applies to unknown or emerging viruses and other pathogens. No confirmed cases of viral transmission or vCJD have been associated with GAMMAGARD LIQUID.



 All infections thought by a physician to possibly have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Baxter Healthcare Corporation, at 1-800-423-2862 (in the U.S.).



    5.9 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



    *    Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of BUN and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of GAMMAGARD LIQUID and at appropriate intervals thereafter. 
 *    Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies, because of the potentially increased risk of thrombosis  3,4  . 
 *    If signs and/or symptoms of hemolysis are present after an infusion of GAMMAGARD LIQUID, perform appropriate laboratory testing for confirmation. 
 *    If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies and anti-HLA antibodies in both the product and patient's serum. 
       5.10 Interference with Laboratory Tests
 

  After infusion of IgG, the transitory rise of the various passively transferred antibodies in the patient's blood may yield false positive serological testing results, with the potential for misleading interpretation. Passive transmission of antibodies to erythrocyte antigens (e.g., A, B, and D) may cause a positive direct or indirect antiglobulin (Coombs') test.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
