<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gammaplex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions (ARs) observed in clinical trial subjects with primary humoral immunodeficiency (PI) were thrombosis and chest pain. The one event of thrombosis (1 subject, 2%) was reported in an adult who also had a diagnosis of antiphospholipid syndrome which results in increased clotting tendency  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



 Serious ARs observed in clinical trial subjects with immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) were headache, vomiting and dehydration. In addition following a review of the data, 4 subjects (11%) were considered to have experienced asymptomatic suspected treatment-emergent hemolysis  [see  Clinical Trials Experience (6.1)  ]  .



 The following potential serious ARs are described above and/or elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Thrombotic Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Hemolysis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
    The most common ARs observed in the PI clinical trials were headache (29 subjects, 39%), pyrexia (11 subjects, 15%), nasal congestion/edema (10 subjects, 13%), fatigue (9 subjects, 12%), nausea (7 subjects, 9%), hypertension (6 subjects, 8%), rash (6 subjects, 8%), hypotension (5 subjects, 7%), infusion site reactions (5 subjects, 7%) vomiting (5 subjects, 7%), myalgia (4 subjects, 5%), chills (4 subjects, 5%), tachycardia (4 subjects, 5%), chest pain/discomfort (4 subjects, 5%), pain (4 subjects, 5%), dizziness (4 subjects, 5%), malaise (4 subjects, 5%), dysuria (4 subjects, 5%), and dry skin (4 subjects, 5%).
 

 The most common ARs observed in the chronic ITP clinical trial were headache (12 subjects, 34%), vomiting (8 subjects, 23%), nausea (5 subjects, 14%), pyrexia (5 subjects, 14%), pruritus (2 subjects, 6%) and arthralgia (2 subjects, 6%).



    EXCERPT:    *   PI - The most common adverse reactions reported in &gt;5% of clinical trial subjects were headache, pyrexia, nasal congestion/edema, fatigue, nausea, hypertension, rash, hypotension, infusion site reaction, vomiting, myalgia, chills, tachycardia, chest pain/discomfort, pain, dizziness, malaise, dysuria, and dry skin (  6  ). 
 *   Chronic ITP - The most common adverse reactions reported in &gt;5% of clinical trial subjects were headache, vomiting, nausea, pyrexia, pruritus, dehydration, and arthralgia (  6  ). 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact BPL Inc. (1-866-398-0825), FDA (1-800-FDA-1088) or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.  



     Primary Humoral Immunodeficiency Study  



 In a multicenter, open-label, non-randomized clinical trial, 50 subjects with primary humoral immunodeficiency received doses of Gammaplex ranging from 279 to 799 mg/kg every 21 days (mean dose 465 mg/kg) or 28 days (mean dose 458 mg/kg), for up to 12 months  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  .



 Twenty-four subjects (48%) had an AR at some time during the clinical trial that was considered product-related. Of these 24 subjects, three had ARs that were considered definitely related to Gammaplex including headache, pyrexia, tachycardia, chest discomfort, and hypertension. More subjects with the 21-day infusion cycle had at least one AR (14 of 22 subjects, 64%) than subjects with the 28-day infusion cycle (10 of 28 subjects, 36%). The total number of ARs during infusion or within 72 hours of infusion was 237 (a rate of 0.34 ARs per infusion), reflecting that some subjects experienced more than one AR during the observation period. The percentage of Gammaplex infusions with one or more ARs within 72 hours of infusion was 21%. The upper bound of the 1-sided 95% confidence interval for this percentage was 24%, which was below the pre-specified upper limit of 40% for this safety endpoint.



 The most common ARs observed in this clinical trial were headache (18 subjects, 36%), fatigue (6 subjects, 12%), nausea (6 subjects, 12%), pyrexia (6 subjects, 12%), pain (4 subjects, 8%), hypertension (3 subjects, 6%), chills (3 subjects, 6%), myalgia (3 subjects, 6%) and vomiting (3 subjects, 6%). Two subjects experienced serious ARs (thrombosis and chest pain).



 Forty-seven of the 50 subjects enrolled in this clinical trial had a negative direct antiglobulin test (DAT) at baseline. Of these 47 subjects, 4 (9%) developed a positive DAT at some time during the clinical trial. However, no subjects showed evidence of hemolytic anemia.



 There was no evidence of transmission of hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or parvovirus B19 during this clinical trial.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions (ARsAdverse Reactions (ARs) are defined as treatment emergent adverse events which met any of the following criteria: (a) adverse events which began during an infusion of Gammaplex or within 72 hours of the end of an infusion, (b) adverse events considered by the investigator or sponsor to have been possibly, probably, or definitely related to administration of Gammaplex, (c) adverse events for which the investigator's causality assessment was either missing or indeterminate.) Occurring in &gt;5% of Subjects with PIARs are presented for the PI studies if occurred in &gt;5% of subjects. ARs seen in the pediatric study are presented in a separate table if occurred in &gt;5% of pediatric subjects and were not reported in the major effectiveness study. 
 Adverse Reactions                         Subjects (%)                    Infusions (%)                    
 PI studies                                PI [n=75]                       PI [n=1071]                      
  
 Headache                                  29 (39%)                        74 (6.9%)                        
 Sinusitis                                 14 (19%)                        17 (1.6%)                        
 Pyrexia                                   11 (15%)                        13 (1.2%)                        
 Nasal Congestion / Edema                  10 (13%)                        8 (0.7%)                         
 Fatigue                                   9 (12%)                         13 (1.2%)                        
 Nausea                                    7 (9%)                          8 (0.7%)                         
 Hypertension                              6 (8%)                          8 (0.7%)                         
 Upper respiratory tract infection         6 (8%)                          8 (0.7%)                         
 Rash                                      6 (8%)                          6 (0.6%)                         
 Hypotension                               5 (7%)                          11 (1.0%)                        
 Infusion site reaction                    5 (7%)                          6 (0.6%)                         
 Vomiting                                  5 (7%)                          4 (0.4%)                         
 Myalgia                                   4 (5%)                          15 (1.4%)                        
 Chills                                    4 (5%)                          9 (0.8%)                         
 Tachycardia                               4 (5%)                          6 (0.6%)                         
 Rhinitis                                  4 (5%)                          6 (0.6%)                         
 Chest pain/discomfort                     4 (5%)                          5 (0.5%)                         
 Pain                                      4 (5%)                          5 (0.5%)                         
 Dizziness/ Vertigo                        4 (5%)                          4 (0.4%)                         
 Malaise / Asthenia / Lethargy             4 (5%)                          4 (0.4%)                         
 Dysuria / Cystitis / UTI                  4 (5%)                          4 (0.4%)                         
 Dry skin / Eczema                         4 (5%)                          4 (0.4%)                         
 Bronchitis                                4 (5%)                          4 (0.4%)                         
        Table 3: ARsAdverse Reactions (ARs) are defined as treatment emergent adverse events which met any of the following criteria: (a) adverse events which began during an infusion of Gammaplex or within 72 hours of the end of an infusion, (b) adverse events considered by the investigator or sponsor to have been possibly, probably, or definitely related to administration of Gammaplex, (c) adverse events for which the investigator's causality assessment was either missing or indeterminate. in &gt;5% of Pediatric Subjects with PIARs are presented for the PI studies if occurred in &gt;5% of subjects. ARs seen in the pediatric study are presented in a separate table if occurred in &gt;5% of pediatric subjects and were not reported in the major effectiveness study. 
 Adverse Reactions                         Subjects (%)                    Infusions (%)                    
 PI Pediatric                              PI [n=25]                       PI [n=368]                       
  
 Dyspnea                                   2 (8%)                          2 (0.5%)                         
 Otitis media acute                        2 (8%)                          2 (0.5%)                         
 Tonsillar disorder                        2 (8%)                          2 (0.5%)                         
             Pediatric Primary Humoral Immunodeficiency Study  
 

 In a multicenter, open-label, non-randomized clinical trial, 25 children and adolescents with primary humoral immunodeficiency received doses of Gammaplex ranging from 300 to 800 mg/kg every 21 days (mean dose 545 mg/kg) or 28 days (mean dose 521 mg/kg), for up to 12 months  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  .



 Fourteen subjects (56%) had an AR at some time during the clinical trial that was considered product-related. Of these 14 subjects, two had ARs that were considered definitely related to Gammaplex including headache, fatigue and myalgia. Seven subjects with the 21-day infusion cycle had at least one AR (7 of 14 subjects, 50%), as did seven subjects with the 28-day infusion cycle (7 of 11 subjects, 64%).



     Chronic Immune Thrombocytopenic Purpura Study  



 In a multicenter, open-label, non-randomized clinical trial, 35 subjects with chronic immune thrombocytopenic purpura were treated with a nominal dose of 1,000 mg/kg on each of two consecutive days (total dose 2,000 mg/kg). Doses of Gammaplex ranged from 482 to 1149 mg/kg on an infusion day. The median total dose per subject was 2035 mg/kg. Pre-medication with antihistamine or analgesic drugs was permitted if required, but corticosteroids were not permitted prior to infusion as pre-medication. Ten subjects received corticosteroids for ITP during the trial and one additional subject received corticosteroids as pre-medication in violation of the protocol. All 35 subjects received at least one infusion of clinical trial drug, and all but one subject completed the first course of treatment.



 Twenty-four subjects (69%) reported at least one AR (103 in total); the most commonly reported being headache (12 subjects, 34%), vomiting (8 subjects, 23%), nausea (5 subjects, 14%), pyrexia (5 subjects, 14%), pruritus (2 subjects, 6%), dehydration (2 subjects, 6%) and arthralgia (2 subjects, 6%). Three subjects experienced a total of five serious ARs. Of the five serious ARs, one subject had three concurrently (vomiting, dehydration and headache) and two subjects each had one serious AR (headache). One of these latter two subjects discontinued from the clinical trial because of the severe headache. Table 4 lists the ARs in more than 5% of subjects.



 Based on a review of clinical and laboratory data, 4/35 subjects (11%) with drops in hemoglobin exceeding 2 g/dL following administration of Gammaplex were considered to have experienced suspected treatment-emergent hemolysis. Milder treatment-emergent hemolysis could not be excluded for an additional 7 subjects, giving a total of 11 of 35 subjects (31%) for whom hemolysis could not be excluded (not including an additional two subjects who lacked follow-up testing for hemolysis, so their hemolysis status was considered unassessable). Data for two subjects were consistent with possible intravascular hemolysis, including one subject who may also have had an element of extravascular hemolysis. Nine of the possible hemolysis cases were mild and appeared consistent with possible extravascular hemolysis.



 There was no evidence of transmission of HBV, HCV, HIV and parvovirus B19 during this clinical trial.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions (ARsAdverse Reactions (ARs) are defined as treatment emergent adverse events which met any of the following criteria: (a) adverse events which began during an infusion of Gammaplex or within 72 hours of the end of an infusion, (b) adverse events considered by the investigator or sponsor to have been possibly, probably, or definitely related to administration of Gammaplex, (c) adverse events for which the investigator's causality assessment was either missing or indeterminate.) Occurring in &gt;5% of Subjects with ITP 
 Adverse Reactions                         Subjects (%)                    Infusions (%)                    
                                           ITP [n=35]                      ITP [n=94]                       
  
 Headache                                  12 (34%)                        15 (16%)                         
 Vomiting                                  8 (23%)                         9 (9.6%)                         
 Nausea                                    5 (14%)                         5 (5.3%)                         
 Pyrexia                                   5 (14%)                         7 (7.4%)                         
 Pain                                      2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Abdominal pain upper                      2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Gastritis                                 2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Contusion                                 2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Arthralgia                                2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Cough                                     2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Anemia                                    2 (6%)                          1 (1.1%)                         
 Ecchymosis                                2 (6%)                          3 (3.2%)                         
 Pruritus                                  2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Dehydration                               2 (6%)                          2 (2.1%)                         
 Hypertension                              2 (6%)                          1 (1.1%)                         
 Neck pain                                 2 (6%)                          1 (1.1%)                         
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
     Because adverse reactions are voluntarily reported post-approval from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



 In addition to the adverse reactions identified in clinical studies  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  , the following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of Gammaplex:



 *   Infusion reactions: Dizziness, 
 *   Respiratory: Pulmonary embolism, dyspnea, respiratory distress 
 *   Cardiovascular: Myocardial infarction, other thromboembolic event 
 *    Neurological : Migraine, aseptic meningitis 
 *   Integumentary: Rash, urticaria 
 *   Musculoskeletal: Musculoskeletal pain 
    The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-marketing use of intravenous immune globulins  9  :
 

 *   Infusion reactions: Hypersensitivity (e.g., anaphylaxis), headache, diarrhea, tachycardia, fever, fatigue, dizziness, malaise, chills, flushing, urticaria or other skin reactions, wheezing or other chest discomfort, nausea, vomiting, rigors, back pain, myalgia, arthralgia, and changes in blood pressure 
 *   Renal: Acute renal dysfunction/failure, osmotic nephropathy 
 *   Respiratory : Apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS), TRALI, cyanosis, hypoxemia, pulmonary edema, dyspnea, bronchospasm 
 *   Cardiovascular: Cardiac arrest, thromboembolism, vascular collapse, hypotension 
 *   Neurological: Coma, loss of consciousness, seizures, tremor, aseptic meningitis syndrome 
 *   Integumentary: Stevens-Johnson syndrome, epidermolysis, erythema multiforme, dermatitis (e.g., bullous dermatitis) 
 *   Hematologic: Pancytopenia, leukopenia, hemolysis, positive direct antiglobulin (Coombs') test 
 *   Gastrointestinal: Hepatic dysfunction, abdominal pain 
 *   General/Body as a Whole: Pyrexia, rigors 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE

    WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE  

    *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including Gammaplex. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors[see Warnings and Precautions (5.2), Patient Counseling Information (17)]. 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur in predisposed patients who receive immune globulin intravenous (lGIV) products, including Gammaplex1.Patients predisposed to renal dysfunction include those with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose. Gammaplex does not contain sucrose.For patients at risk of thrombosis, renal dysfunction or acute renal failure, administer Gammaplex at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity [see Dosage and Administration (2.3), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION and ACUTE RENAL FAILURE
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including Gammaplex. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors (5.2).Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death1 may occur in predisposed patients with immune globulin intravenous (lGIV) products, including Gammaplex.Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly with IGIV products containing sucrose. Gammaplex does not contain sucrose (5.1).For patients at risk of thrombosis, renal dysfunction or acute renal failure, administer Gammaplex at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity (2.3, 5.1). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  IgA-deficient patients with antibodies to IgA are at greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions (  5.3  ). 
 *  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia may occur in patients receiving IGIV therapy (  5.4  ). 
 *  Aseptic meningitis syndrome may occur, especially with high doses or rapid infusion (  5.5  ). 
 *  Hemolysis, either intravascular or due to enhanced red blood cell sequestration, can develop subsequent to Gammaplex treatments. Risk factors include high doses and non-O blood group. Closely monitor patients for hemolysis and hemolytic anemia (  5.6  ). 
 *  Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions (transfusion-related acute lung injury [TRALI]) (  5.7  ). 
 *  Volume overload can occur. Monitor for signs and symptoms (  5.8  ). 
 *  Consider risks and benefits before prescribing the high dose regimen for chronic ITP in patients at risk of thrombosis, hemolysis, acute kidney injury, or volume overload (  5  ). 
 *  Gammaplex is made from human plasma and may contain infectious agents, e.g., viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent (  5.9  ). 
 *  Passive transfer of antibodies may confound serologic testing (  5.10  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Renal Dysfunction / Failure



   Acute renal dysfunction/failure, osmotic nephropathy, and death  1  may occur upon use of human IGIV products. Ensure that patients are not volume depleted before administering Gammaplex. In patients who are at risk of developing renal dysfunction, because of pre-existing renal insufficiency, predisposition to acute renal failure (such as diabetes mellitus, hypovolemia, overweight, use of concomitant nephrotoxic medicinal products or age &gt;65 years), administer Gammaplex at the minimum infusion rate practicable [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  .  



 Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of Gammaplex and at appropriate intervals thereafter. If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuing Gammaplex.



    5.2 Thrombotic Events



   Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products, including Gammaplex  2  . Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors.  



  Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia / markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer Gammaplex at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable .  Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ,  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ].    



    5.3 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue Gammaplex infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment. Medications such as epinephrine should be available for immediate treatment of acute hypersensitivity reactions.



 Gammaplex contains trace amounts of IgA (&lt;10 mug/mL) [see  Description (11)  ]  . Patients with known antibodies to IgA may have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. Gammaplex is contraindicated in patients with antibodies against IgA and a history of hypersensitivity reaction [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.4 Hyperproteinemia, Increased Serum Viscosity, and Hyponatremia



  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia may occur in patients receiving IGIV therapy. It is critical to clinically distinguish true hyponatremia from a pseudohyponatremia that is associated with or causally related to hyperproteinemia with concomitant decreased calculated serum osmolality or elevated osmolar gap, because treatment aimed at decreasing serum free water in patients with pseudohyponatremia may lead to volume depletion, a further increase in serum viscosity, and a possible predisposition to thrombotic events  2  .



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



   AMS may occur with IGIV treatment. AMS usually begins within several hours to 2 days following IGIV treatment. Discontinuation of IGIV treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae  3  .  



 AMS is characterized by the following signs and symptoms: severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea, and vomiting [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies frequently reveal pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per cubic millimeter, predominantly from the granulocytic series, and elevated protein levels up to several hundred mg/dL, but negative culture results. Conduct a thorough neurological examination on patients exhibiting such signs and symptoms, including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis. AMS may occur more frequently in association with high doses (2 g/kg) and/or rapid infusion of IGIV.



    5.6 Hemolysis



  Gammaplex may contain blood group antibodies that can act as hemolysins and induce in vivo  coating of red blood cells (RBCs) with immunoglobulin, causing a positive direct antiglobulin test (DAT) (Coombs' test) result and hemolysis  4  . Delayed hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to IGIV therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration and acute hemolysis, consistent with intravascular hemolysis, has been reported  5  . Cases of severe hemolysis-related renal dysfunction/failure or disseminated intravascular coagulation have occurred following infusion of IGIV.



 The following risk factors may be associated with the development of hemolysis following IGIV administration: high doses (e.g., &gt;=2 g/kg), given either as a single administration or divided over several days, and non-O blood group  6  . Other individual patient factors, such as an underlying inflammatory state (as may be reflected by, for example, elevated C-reactive protein or erythrocyte sedimentation rate), have been hypothesized to increase the risk of hemolysis following administration of IGIV  7  , but their role is uncertain. Hemolysis has been reported following administration of IGIV for a variety of indications, including ITP and PI  4  .



 Closely monitor patients for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis, particularly patients with risk factors noted above. Consider appropriate laboratory testing in higher risk patients, including measurement of hemoglobin or hematocrit prior to infusion and within approximately 36 to 96 hours post infusion. If clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis or a significant drop in hemoglobin or hematocrit have been observed, perform confirmatory laboratory testing. If transfusion is indicated for patients who develop hemolysis with clinically compromising anemia after receiving IGIV, perform adequate cross-matching to avoid exacerbating on-going hemolysis.



    5.7 Transfusion-related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Noncardiogenic pulmonary edema may occur in patients following IGIV treatment  8  . TRALI is characterized by severe respiratory distress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function and fever. Symptoms typically appear within 1 to 6 hours following treatment.



 Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions. If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies in both the product and the patient's serum.



 TRALI may be managed using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



    5.8 Volume Overload



   Carefully consider the relative risks and benefits before prescribing the high dose regimen (for chronic ITP) in patients at increased risk of volume overload.  



    5.9 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because Gammaplex is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have been associated with the use of Gammaplex. All infections suspected by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare providers to BPL Inc. 1-866  - 398-0825  .



 Before prescribing Gammaplex, the physician should discuss the risks and benefits of its use with the patient [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ].  



    5.10 Laboratory Tests



    *   After infusion of immunoglobulin, the transitory rise of the various passively transferred antibodies in the patient's blood may yield positive serological testing results, with the potential for misleading interpretation.  
 *  Passive transmission of antibodies to erythrocyte antigens (e.g., A, B, and D) may cause a positive direct or indirect antiglobulin (Coombs') test. 
 *  Clinically assess patients with known renal dysfunction, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or those receiving nephrotoxic agents, and monitor as appropriate (BUN, serum creatinine, urine output) during therapy with Gammaplex. 
 *  Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with polycythemia, cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triglycerides, or monoclonal gammopathies. 
 *  Consider measuring hemoglobin or hematocrit at baseline and approximately 36 to 96 hours post infusion in patients at higher risk of hemolysis. If signs and/or symptoms of hemolysis are present after an infusion of Gammaplex, perform appropriate laboratory testing for confirmation. 
 *  If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies in both the product and patient's serum. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
