<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ganirelix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The safety of Ganirelix Acetate Injection was evaluated in two randomized, parallel-group, multicenter controlled clinical studies. Treatment duration for Ganirelix Acetate ranged from 1 to 14 days. Table IV represents adverse events (AEs) from first day of Ganirelix Acetate administration until confirmation of pregnancy by ultrasound at an incidence of &gt;= 1% in Ganirelix Acetate-treated subjects without regard to causality.



 TABLE IV: Incidence of common adverse events (Incidence &gt;= 1% in Ganirelix Acetate-treated subjects). Completed controlled clinical studies (All-subjects-treated group). 
 Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;= 1%                                   Ganirelix Acetate N=794% (n)         
  
 Abdominal Pain (gynecological)                                                4.8 (38)                   
 Death Fetal                                                                   3.7 (29)                   
 Headache                                                                      3.0 (24)                   
 Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome                                             2.4 (19)                   
 Vaginal Bleeding                                                              1.8 (14)                   
 Injection Site Reaction                                                       1.1 (9)                    
 Nausea                                                                        1.1 (9)                    
 Abdominal Pain (gastrointestinal)                                             1.0 (8)                    
        During post-marketing surveillance, rare cases of hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactoid reactions, have been reported, as early as with the first dose (see  PRECAUTIONS  ).
 

   Congenital Anomalies

  Clinical follow-up studies of 283 newborns of women administered Ganirelix Acetate Injection were reviewed. There were three neonates with major congenital anomalies and 18 neonates with minor congenital anomalies. The major congenital anomalies were: hydrocephalus/meningocele, omphalocele, and Beckwith-Wiedemann Syndrome. The minor congenital anomalies were: nevus, skin tags, sacral sinus, hemangioma, torticollis/asymmetric skull, talipes, supernumerary digit finger, hip subluxation, torticollis/high palate, occiput/abnormal hand crease, hernia umbilicalis, hernia inguinalis, hydrocele, undescended testis, and hydronephrosis.



 A subsequent analysis from an observational study in more than 1000 newborns compared the incidence of congenital anomalies in newborns of women administered Ganirelix to historical controls of a GnRH agonist. This analysis included the 283 newborns in the original studies. This study demonstrated that the incidence of congenital anomalies in children born after COH treatment in women using Ganirelix was comparable with that reported after a COH treatment cycle using a GnRH agonist. The causal relationship between these congenital anomalies and Ganirelix Acetate is unknown.



 The incidence of congenital malformations after Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART) may be slightly higher than after spontaneous conceptions. This slightly higher incidence is thought to be related to differences in parental characteristics (e.g., maternal age, sperm characteristics) and to the higher incidence of multiple gestations after ART.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
