<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gardasil1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reaction was headache. Common adverse reactions (frequency of at least 1.0% and greater than AAHS control or saline placebo) are fever, nausea, dizziness; and injection-site pain, swelling, erythema, pruritus, and bruising. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

    Overall Summary of Adverse Reactions  



 Headache, fever, nausea, and dizziness; and local injection site reactions (pain, swelling, erythema, pruritus, and bruising) occurred after administration with GARDASIL.



 Syncope, sometimes associated with tonic-clonic movements and other seizure-like activity, has been reported following vaccination with GARDASIL and may result in falling with injury; observation for 15 minutes after administration is recommended.  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    .  ]  



 Anaphylaxis has been reported following vaccination with GARDASIL.



   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Studies in Girls and Women (9 Through 45 Years of Age) and Boys and Men (9 Through 26 Years of Age)  



 In 7 clinical trials (5 Amorphous Aluminum Hydroxyphosphate Sulfate [AAHS]-controlled, 1 saline placebo-controlled, and 1 uncontrolled), 18,083 individuals were administered GARDASIL or AAHS control or saline placebo on the day of enrollment, and approximately 2 and 6 months thereafter, and safety was evaluated using vaccination report cards (VRC)-aided surveillance for 14 days after each injection of GARDASIL or AAHS control or saline placebo in these individuals. The individuals who were monitored using VRC-aided surveillance included 10,088 individuals 9 through 45 years of age at enrollment who received GARDASIL and 7,995 individuals who received AAHS control or saline placebo. Few individuals (0.2%) discontinued due to adverse reactions. The race distribution of the 9- through 26-year-old girls and women in the safety population was as follows: 62.3% White; 17.6% Hispanic (Black and White); 6.8% Asian; 6.7% Other; 6.4% Black; and 0.3% American Indian. The race distribution of the 24- through 45-year-old women in the safety population of Study 6 was as follows: 20.6% White; 43.2% Hispanic (Black and White); 0.2% Other; 4.8% Black; 31.2% Asian; and 0.1% American Indian. The race distribution of the 9- through 26-year-old boys and men in the safety population was as follows: 42.0% White; 19.7% Hispanic (Black and White); 11.0% Asian; 11.2% Other; 15.9% Black; and 0.1% American Indian.



     Common Injection-Site Adverse Reactions in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age  



 The injection site adverse reactions that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL at a frequency of at least 1.0% and also at a greater frequency than that observed among AAHS control or saline placebo recipients are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Injection-Site Adverse Reactions in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of AgeThe injection-site adverse reactions that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL were at a frequency of at least 1.0% and also at a greater frequency than that observed among AAHS control or saline placebo recipients. 
 Adverse Reaction(1 to 5 Days Postvaccination)    GARDASIL(N = 5088)%     AAHS Control(N = 3470)%   Saline Placebo(N = 320)%   
  
   Injection Site                                                                                             
   Pain                                  83.9                      75.4                      48.6             
   Swelling                              25.4                      15.8                      7.3              
   Erythema                              24.7                      18.4                      12.1             
   Pruritus                              3.2                       2.8                       0.6              
   Bruising                              2.8                       3.2                       1.6              
              Common Injection-Site Adverse Reactions in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age  
 

 The injection site adverse reactions that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL at a frequency of at least 1.0% and also at a greater frequency than that observed among AAHS control or saline placebo recipients are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2: Injection-Site Adverse Reactions in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of AgeThe injection-site adverse reactions that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL were at a frequency of at least 1.0% and also at a greater frequency than that observed among AAHS control or saline placebo recipients. 
 Adverse Reaction(1 to 5 Days Postvaccination)    GARDASIL(N = 3093)%     AAHS Control(N = 2029)%   Saline Placebo(N = 274)%   
  
   Injection Site                                                                                             
   Pain                                  61.4                      50.8                      41.6             
   Erythema                              16.7                      14.1                      14.5             
   Swelling                              13.9                      9.6                       8.2              
   Hematoma                              1.0                       0.3                       3.3              
              Evaluation of Injection-Site Adverse Reactions by Dose in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age  
 

 An analysis of injection-site adverse reactions in girls and women by dose is shown in Table 3. Of those girls and women who reported an injection-site reaction, 94.3% judged their injection-site adverse reaction to be mild or moderate in intensity.



 Table 3: Postdose Evaluation of Injection-Site Adverse Reactions in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age (1 to 5 Days Postvaccination) 
               GARDASIL(% occurrence)  AAHS Control(% occurrence)  Saline Placebo(% occurrence)   
 Adverse Reaction  Post-dose 1N= 5011  Post-dose 2N = 4924  Post-dose 3N = 4818  Post-dose 1N = 3410  Post-dose 2N = 3351  Post-dose 3N = 3295  Post-dose 1N = 315  Post-dose 2N = 301  Post-dose 3N = 300   
  
   Pain          63.4        60.7        62.7        57.0        47.8        49.6       33.7        20.3        27.3      
 Mild/Moderate    62.5        59.7        61.2        56.6        47.3        48.9       33.3        20.3        27.0      
 Severe           0.9        1.0         1.5         0.4         0.5         0.6         0.3        0.0         0.3       
   Swelling      10.2        12.8        15.1        8.2         7.5         7.6         4.4        3.0         3.3       
 Mild/Moderate     9.6        11.9        14.2        8.1         7.2         7.3         4.4        3.0         3.3       
 Severe           0.6        0.8         0.9         0.2         0.2         0.2         0.0        0.0         0.0       
   Erythema       9.2        12.1        14.7        9.8         8.4         8.9         7.3        5.3         5.7       
 Mild/Moderate     9.0        11.7        14.3        9.5         8.4         8.8         7.3        5.3         5.7       
 Severe           0.2        0.3         0.4         0.3         0.1         0.1         0.0        0.0         0.0       
                    Evaluation of Injection-Site Adverse Reactions by Dose in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age  
 

 An analysis of injection-site adverse reactions in boys and men by dose is shown in Table 4. Of those boys and men who reported an injection-site reaction, 96.4% judged their injection-site adverse reaction to be mild or moderate in intensity.



 Table 4: Postdose Evaluation of Injection-Site Adverse Reactions in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age (1 to 5 Days Postvaccination) 
               GARDASIL(% occurrence)  AAHS Control(% occurrence)  Saline Placebo(% occurrence)   
 Adverse Reaction  Post-dose 1N= 3003  Post-dose 2N = 2898  Post-dose 3N = 2826  Post-dose 1N = 1950  Post-dose 2N = 1854  Post-dose 3N = 1799  Post-dose 1N = 269  Post-dose 2N = 263  Post-dose 3N = 259   
  
   Pain          44.7        36.9        34.4        38.4        28.2        25.8       27.5        20.5        16.2      
 Mild/Moderate    44.5        36.4        34.1        37.9        28.2        25.5       27.5        20.2        16.2      
 Severe           0.2        0.5         0.3         0.4         0.1         0.3         0.0        0.4         0.0       
   Swelling       5.6        6.6         7.7         5.6         4.5         4.1         4.8        1.5         3.5       
 Mild/Moderate     5.3        6.2         7.1         5.4         4.5         4.0         4.8        1.5         3.1       
 Severe           0.2        0.3         0.5         0.2         0.0         0.1         0.0        0.0         0.4       
   Erythema       7.2        8.0         8.7         8.3         6.3         5.7         7.1        5.7         5.0       
 Mild/Moderate     6.8        7.7         8.3         8.0         6.2         5.6         7.1        5.7         5.0       
 Severe           0.3        0.2         0.3         0.2         0.1         0.1         0.0        0.0         0.0       
                    Common Systemic Adverse Reactions in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age  
 

 Headache was the most commonly reported systemic adverse reaction in both treatment groups (GARDASIL = 28.2% and AAHS control or saline placebo = 28.4%). Fever was the next most commonly reported systemic adverse reaction in both treatment groups (GARDASIL = 13.0% and AAHS control or saline placebo = 11.2%).



 Adverse reactions that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL, at a frequency of greater than or equal to 1.0% where the incidence in the GARDASIL group was greater than or equal to the incidence in the AAHS control or saline placebo group, are shown in Table 5.



 Table 5: Common Systemic Adverse Reactions in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age (GARDASIL &gt;=Control)The adverse reactions in this table are those that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL at a frequency of at least 1.0% and greater than or equal to those observed among AAHS control or saline placebo recipients. 
 Adverse Reactions(1 to 15 Days Postvaccination)  GARDASIL(N = 5088)%   AAHS Controlor Saline Placebo(N = 3790)%   
  
 Pyrexia                                                13.0                         11.2                   
 Nausea                                                 6.7                           6.5                   
 Dizziness                                              4.0                           3.7                   
 Diarrhea                                               3.6                           3.5                   
 Vomiting                                               2.4                           1.9                   
 Cough                                                  2.0                           1.5                   
 Toothache                                              1.5                           1.4                   
 Upper respiratory tract infection                      1.5                           1.5                   
 Malaise                                                1.4                           1.2                   
 Arthralgia                                             1.2                           0.9                   
 Insomnia                                               1.2                           0.9                   
 Nasal congestion                                       1.1                           0.9                   
             Common Systemic Adverse Reactions in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age  
 

 Headache was the most commonly reported systemic adverse reaction in both treatment groups (GARDASIL = 12.3% and AAHS control or saline placebo = 11.2%). Fever was the next most commonly reported systemic adverse reaction in both treatment groups (GARDASIL = 8.3% and AAHS control or saline placebo = 6.5%).



 Adverse reactions that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL, at a frequency of greater than or equal to 1.0% where the incidence in the group that received GARDASIL was greater than or equal to the incidence in the AAHS control or saline placebo group, are shown in Table 6.



 Table 6: Common Systemic Adverse Reactions in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age (GARDASIL &gt;=Control)The adverse reactions in this table are those that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL at a frequency of at least 1.0% and greater than or equal to those observed among AAHS control or saline placebo recipients. 
 Adverse Reactions(1 to 15 Days Postvaccination)  GARDASIL(N = 3093)%   AAHS Controlor Saline Placebo(N = 2303)%   
  
 Headache                                               12.3                         11.2                   
 Pyrexia                                                8.3                           6.5                   
 Oropharyngeal pain                                     2.8                           2.1                   
 Diarrhea                                               2.7                           2.2                   
 Nasopharyngitis                                        2.6                           2.6                   
 Nausea                                                 2.0                           1.0                   
 Upper respiratory tract infection                      1.5                           1.0                   
 Abdominal pain upper                                   1.4                           1.4                   
 Myalgia                                                1.3                           0.7                   
 Dizziness                                              1.2                           0.9                   
 Vomiting                                               1.0                           0.8                   
             Evaluation of Fever by Dose in Girls and Women  9  Through  26  Years of Age  
 

 An analysis of fever in girls and women by dose is shown in Table 7.



 Table 7: Postdose Evaluation of Fever in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age (1 to 5 Days Postvaccination) 
                   GARDASIL(% occurrence)  AAHS Controlor Saline Placebo(% occurrence)   
 Temperature( degrees F)  Postdose 1N= 4945  Postdose 2N = 4804  Postdose 3N = 4671  Postdose 1N = 3681  Postdose 2N = 3564  Postdose 3N = 3467   
  
  &gt;=100 to &lt;102         3.7             4.1             4.4             3.1             3.8             3.6         
      &gt;=102             0.3             0.5             0.5             0.2             0.4             0.5         
                 Evaluation of Fever by Dose in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age  
 

 An analysis of fever in boys and men by dose is shown in Table 8.



 Table 8: Postdose Evaluation of Fever in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age (1 to 5 Days Postvaccination) 
                   GARDASIL(% occurrence)  AAHS Controlor Saline Placebo(% occurrence)   
 Temperature( degrees F)  Postdose 1N= 2972  Postdose 2N = 2849  Postdose 3N = 2792  Postdose 1N = 2194  Postdose 2N = 2079  Postdose 3N = 2046   
  
  &gt;=100 to &lt;102         2.4             2.5             2.3             2.1             2.2             1.6         
      &gt;=102             0.6             0.5             0.5             0.5             0.3             0.3         
                 Serious Adverse Reactions in the Entire Study Population  
 

 Across the clinical studies, 258 individuals (GARDASIL N = 128 or 0.8%; placebo N = 130 or 1.0%) out of 29,323 (GARDASIL N = 15,706; AAHS control N = 13,023; or saline placebo N = 594) individuals (9- through 45-year-old girls and women; and 9- through 26-year-old boys and men) reported a serious systemic adverse reaction.



 Of the entire study population (29,323 individuals), 0.04% of the reported serious systemic adverse reactions were judged to be vaccine related by the study investigator. The most frequently (frequency of 4 cases or greater with either GARDASIL, AAHS control, saline placebo, or the total of all three) reported serious systemic adverse reactions, regardless of causality, were:



 Headache [0.02% GARDASIL (3 cases) vs. 0.02% AAHS control (2 cases)],Gastroenteritis [0.02% GARDASIL (3 cases) vs. 0.02% AAHS control (2 cases)],Appendicitis [0.03% GARDASIL (5 cases) vs. 0.01% AAHS control (1 case)],Pelvic inflammatory disease [0.02% GARDASIL (3 cases) vs. 0.03% AAHS control (4 cases)],Urinary tract infection [0.01% GARDASIL (2 cases) vs. 0.02% AAHS control (2 cases)],Pneumonia [0.01% GARDASIL (2 cases) vs. 0.02% AAHS control (2 cases)],Pyelonephritis [0.01% GARDASIL (2 cases) vs. 0.02% AAHS control (3 cases)],Pulmonary embolism [0.01% GARDASIL (2 cases) vs. 0.02% AAHS control (2 cases)].



 One case (0.006% GARDASIL; 0.0% AAHS control or saline placebo) of bronchospasm; and 2 cases (0.01% GARDASIL; 0.0% AAHS control or saline placebo) of asthma were reported as serious systemic adverse reactions that occurred following any vaccination visit.



 In addition, there was 1 individual in the clinical trials, in the group that received GARDASIL, who reported two injection-site serious adverse reactions (injection-site pain and injection-site joint movement impairment).



     Deaths in the Entire Study Population  



 Across the clinical studies, 40 deaths (GARDASIL N = 21 or 0.1%; placebo N = 19 or 0.1%) were reported in 29,323 (GARDASIL N = 15,706; AAHS control N = 13,023, saline placebo N = 594) individuals (9- through 45-year-old girls and women; and 9- through 26-year-old boys and men). The events reported were consistent with events expected in healthy adolescent and adult populations. The most common cause of death was motor vehicle accident (5 individuals who received GARDASIL and 4 individuals who received AAHS control), followed by drug overdose/suicide (2 individuals who received GARDASIL and 6 individuals who received AAHS control), gunshot wound (1 individual who received GARDASIL and 3 individuals who received AAHS control), and pulmonary embolus/deep vein thrombosis (1 individual who received GARDASIL and 1 individual who received AAHS control). In addition, there were 2 cases of sepsis, 1 case of pancreatic cancer, 1 case of arrhythmia, 1 case of pulmonary tuberculosis, 1 case of hyperthyroidism, 1 case of post-operative pulmonary embolism and acute renal failure, 1 case of traumatic brain injury/cardiac arrest, 1 case of systemic lupus erythematosus, 1 case of cerebrovascular accident, 1 case of breast cancer, and 1 case of nasopharyngeal cancer in the group that received GARDASIL; 1 case of asphyxia, 1 case of acute lymphocytic leukemia, 1 case of chemical poisoning, and 1 case of myocardial ischemia in the AAHS control group; and 1 case of medulloblastoma in the saline placebo group.



     Systemic Autoimmune Disorders in Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age  



 In the clinical studies, 9- through 26-year-old girls and women were evaluated for new medical conditions that occurred over the course of follow-up. New medical conditions potentially indicative of a systemic autoimmune disorder seen in the group that received GARDASIL or AAHS control or saline placebo are shown in Table 9. This population includes all girls and women who received at least one dose of GARDASIL or AAHS control or saline placebo, and had safety data available.



 Table 9: Summary of Girls and Women 9 Through 26 Years of Age Who Reported an Incident Condition Potentially Indicative of a Systemic Autoimmune Disorder After Enrollment in Clinical Trials of GARDASIL, Regardless of Causality 
 Conditions                                  GARDASIL(N = 10,706)     AAHS Controlor Saline Placebo(N = 9412)   
 n (%)                                               n (%)             
  
 N = Number of individuals enrolled         
 n = Number of individuals with specific new Medical Conditions   
 NOTE: Although an individual may have had two or more new Medical Conditions, the individual is counted only once within a category. The same individual may appear in different categories.   
  
 Arthralgia/Arthritis/Arthropathy                  120 (1.1)                       98 (1.0)                 
 Autoimmune Thyroiditis                             4 (0.0)                         1 (0.0)                 
 Celiac Disease                                    10 (0.1)                         6 (0.1)                 
 Diabetes Mellitus Insulin-dependent                2 (0.0)                         2 (0.0)                 
 Erythema Nodosum                                   2 (0.0)                         4 (0.0)                 
 Hyperthyroidism                                   27 (0.3)                        21 (0.2)                 
 Hypothyroidism                                    35 (0.3)                        38 (0.4)                 
 Inflammatory Bowel Disease                         7 (0.1)                        10 (0.1)                 
 Multiple Sclerosis                                 2 (0.0)                         4 (0.0)                 
 Nephritis                                          2 (0.0)                         5 (0.1)                 
 Optic Neuritis                                     2 (0.0)                         0 (0.0)                 
 Pigmentation Disorder                              4 (0.0)                         3 (0.0)                 
 Psoriasis                                         13 (0.1)                        15 (0.2)                 
 Raynaud's Phenomenon                               3 (0.0)                         4 (0.0)                 
 Rheumatoid Arthritis                               6 (0.1)                         2 (0.0)                 
 Scleroderma/Morphea                                2 (0.0)                         1 (0.0)                 
 Stevens-Johnson Syndrome                           1 (0.0)                         0 (0.0)                 
 Systemic Lupus Erythematosus                       1 (0.0)                         3 (0.0)                 
 Uveitis                                            3 (0.0)                         1 (0.0)                 
   All Conditions                                  245 (2.3)                       218 (2.3)                
             Systemic Autoimmune Disorders in Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age  
 

 In the clinical studies, 9- through 26-year-old boys and men were evaluated for new medical conditions that occurred over the course of follow-up. New medical conditions potentially indicative of a systemic autoimmune disorder seen in the group that received GARDASIL or AAHS control or saline placebo are shown in Table 10. This population includes all boys and men who received at least one dose of GARDASIL or AAHS control or saline placebo, and had safety data available.



 Table 10: Summary of Boys and Men 9 Through 26 Years of Age Who Reported an Incident Condition Potentially Indicative of a Systemic Autoimmune Disorder After Enrollment in Clinical Trials of GARDASIL, Regardless of Causality 
 Conditions                                   GARDASIL(N = 3093)      AAHS Controlor Saline Placebo(N = 2303)   
 n (%)                                               n (%)             
  
 N = Number of individuals who received at least one dose of either vaccine or placebo   
 n = Number of individuals with specific new Medical Conditions   
 NOTE: Although an individual may have had two or more new Medical Conditions, the individual is counted only once within a category. The same individual may appear in different categories.   
  
 Alopecia Areata                                    2 (0.1)                         0 (0.0)                 
 Ankylosing Spondylitis                             1 (0.0)                         2 (0.1)                 
 Arthralgia/Arthritis/Reactive Arthritis           30 (1.0)                        17 (0.7)                 
 Autoimmune Thrombocytopenia                        1 (0.0)                         0 (0.0)                 
 Diabetes Mellitus Type 1                           3 (0.1)                         2 (0.1)                 
 Hyperthyroidism                                    0 (0.0)                         1 (0.0)                 
 Hypothyroidism                                     3 (0.1)                         0 (0.0)                 
 Inflammatory Bowel Disease                         1 (0.0)                         2 (0.1)                 
 Myocarditis                                        1 (0.0)                         1 (0.0)                 
 Proteinuria                                        1 (0.0)                         0 (0.0)                 
 Psoriasis                                          0 (0.0)                         4 (0.2)                 
 Skin Depigmentation                                1 (0.0)                         0 (0.0)                 
 Vitiligo                                           2 (0.1)                         5 (0.2)                 
   All Conditions                                  46 (1.5)                        34 (1.5)                 
             Safety in Concomitant Use with RECOMBIVAX HB    (r)    [hepatitis B vaccine (recombinant)] in Girls and Women 16 Through 23 Years of Age  
 

 The safety of GARDASIL when administered concomitantly with RECOMBIVAX HB  (r)  [hepatitis B vaccine (recombinant)] was evaluated in an AAHS-controlled study of 1871 girls and women with a mean age of 20.4 years  [see  Clinical Studies (14.10)  ]  . The race distribution of the study individuals was as follows: 61.6% White; 23.8% Other; 11.9% Black; 1.6% Hispanic (Black and White); 0.8% Asian; and 0.3% American Indian. The rates of systemic and injection-site adverse reactions were similar among girls and women who received concomitant vaccination as compared with those who received GARDASIL or RECOMBIVAX HB [hepatitis B vaccine (recombinant)].



     Safety in Concomitant Use with Menactra [Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine] and Adacel [Tetanus Toxoid, Reduced Diphtheria Toxoid and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed (Tdap)]  



 The safety of GARDASIL when administered concomitantly with Menactra [Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine] and Adacel [Tetanus Toxoid, Reduced Diphtheria Toxoid and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed (Tdap)] was evaluated in a randomized study of 1040 boys and girls with a mean age of 12.6 years  [see  Clinical Studies (14.11)  ]  . The race distribution of the study subjects was as follows: 77.7% White; 1.4% Multi-racial; 12.3% Black; 6.8% Hispanic (Black and White); 1.2% Asian; 0.4% American Indian, and 0.2% Indian.



 There was an increase in injection-site swelling reported at the injection site for GARDASIL (concomitant = 10.9%, non-concomitant = 6.9%) when GARDASIL was administered concomitantly with Menactra and Adacel as compared to non-concomitant (separated by 1 month) vaccination. The majority of injection-site swelling adverse experiences were reported as being mild to moderate in intensity.



     Safety in Women 27 Through 45 Years of Age  



 The adverse reaction profile in women 27 through 45 years of age was comparable to the profile seen in girls and women 9 through 26 years of age.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during post-approval use of GARDASIL. Because these events were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or to establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure.



 Blood and lymphatic system disorders: Autoimmune hemolytic anemia, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, lymphadenopathy.



 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders: Pulmonary embolus.



 Gastrointestinal disorders: Nausea, pancreatitis, vomiting.



 General disorders and administration site conditions: Asthenia, chills, death, fatigue, malaise.



 Immune system disorders: Autoimmune diseases, hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions, bronchospasm, and urticaria.



 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders: Arthralgia, myalgia.



 Nervous system disorders: Acute disseminated encephalomyelitis, dizziness, Guillain-Barre syndrome, headache, motor neuron disease, paralysis, seizures, syncope (including syncope associated with tonic-clonic movements and other seizure-like activity) sometimes resulting in falling with injury, transverse myelitis.



 Infections and infestations: cellulitis.



 Vascular disorders: Deep venous thrombosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Because vaccinees may develop syncope, sometimes resulting in falling with injury, observation for 15 minutes after administration is recommended. Syncope, sometimes associated with tonic-clonic movements and other seizure-like activity, has been reported following vaccination with GARDASIL. When syncope is associated with tonic-clonic movements, the activity is usually transient and typically responds to restoring cerebral perfusion by maintaining a supine or Trendelenburg position. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Syncope



  Because vaccinees may develop syncope, sometimes resulting in falling with injury, observation for 15 minutes after administration is recommended. Syncope, sometimes associated with tonic-clonic movements and other seizure-like activity, has been reported following vaccination with GARDASIL. When syncope is associated with tonic-clonic movements, the activity is usually transient and typically responds to restoring cerebral perfusion by maintaining a supine or Trendelenburg position.



    5.2 Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be readily available in case of anaphylactic reactions following the administration of GARDASIL.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
