<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gardasil0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic adverse reactions in females 16 through 26 years of age were injection-site pain (89.9%), injection-site swelling (40.0%), injection-site erythema (34.0%) and headache (14.6%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in girls 9 through 15 years of age were injection-site pain (89.3%), injection- site swelling (47.8%), injection-site erythema (34.1%) and headache (11.4%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  The most common (&gt;=10%) local and systemic reactions in boys 9 through 15 years of age were injection-site pain (71.5%), injection-site swelling (26.9%), and injection-site erythema (24.9%). (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of GARDASIL 9 was evaluated in six clinical studies that included 13,234 individuals who received at least one dose of GARDASIL 9 and had safety follow-up. Study 1 and Study 3 also included 7,378 individuals who received at least one dose of GARDASIL as a control and had safety follow-up. The vaccines were administered on the day of enrollment and the subsequent doses administered approximately two and six months thereafter. Safety was evaluated using vaccination report card (VRC)-aided surveillance for 14 days after each injection of GARDASIL 9 or GARDASIL.



 The individuals who were monitored using VRC-aided surveillance included 8,022 women 16 through 26 years of age and 5,212 girls and boys 9 through 15 years of age (3,436 girls and 1,776 boys) at enrollment who received GARDASIL 9 and 7,078 women 16 through 26 years of age and 300 girls 9 through 15 years of age at enrollment who received GARDASIL. The race distribution of the integrated safety population for GARDASIL 9 was similar between women (56.3% White; 25.4% Other Races or Multiracial; 14.7% Asian; 3.7% Black) and girls and boys (62.0% White; 19.2% Other Races or Multiracial; 13.5% Asian; 5.4% Black). The race distribution of the safety population for GARDASIL was determined in two studies (Study 1 and Study 3) that had different profiles. In Study 1, the race distribution was similar to the integrated database for GARDASIL 9: 55.3% White; 26.9% Multiracial; 14.2% Asian; 3.3% Black; 0.2% Unknown; 0.1% American Indian or Alaskan Native; and 0.1% Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander. Study 3 race distribution was 98.0% White; 1.3% Multiracial; 0.3% Asian; and 0.3% Black.



     Solicited Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions  



 Injection-site reactions (pain, swelling, and erythema) and oral temperature were solicited using VRC-aided surveillance for five days after each injection of GARDASIL 9 during the clinical studies. The rates and severity of these solicited adverse reactions that occurred within five days following each dose of GARDASIL 9 compared with GARDASIL in Study 1 (girls and women 16 through 26 years of age) and Study 3 (girls 9 through 15 years of age) are presented in Table 1. Among subjects who received GARDASIL 9, the rates of injection-site pain were approximately equal across the three reporting time periods. Rates of injection-site swelling and injection-site erythema increased following each successive dose of GARDASIL 9. Recipients of GARDASIL 9 had numerically higher rates of injection-site reactions compared with recipients of GARDASIL.



 Table 1: Rates (%) and Severity of Solicited Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Occurring within Five Days of Each Vaccination with GARDASIL 9 Compared with GARDASIL (Studies 1 and 3) 
                               GARDASIL 9  GARDASIL    
 Post-dose 1                   Post-dose 2  Post-dose 3  Post any dose  Post-dose 1  Post-dose 2  Post-dose 3  Post any dose   
  
 The data for girls and women 16 through 26 years of age are from Study 1 (NCT00543543), and the data for girls 9 through 15 years of age are from Study 3 (NCT01304498).   
 N=number of subjects vaccinated with safety follow-up   
 n=number of subjects with temperature data   
 Pain, Any=mild, moderate, severe or unknown intensity   
 Pain, Severe=incapacitating with inability to work or do usual activity   
 Swelling, Any=any size or size unknown   
 Swelling, Severe=maximum size greater than 2 inches   
 Erythema, Any=any size or size unknown   
 Erythema, Severe=maximum size greater than 2 inches   
  
   Girls and Women 16 through 26 Years of Age                                                                                             
   Injection-Site Adverse Reactions      N=7069      N=6997      N=6909      N=7071      N=7076      N=6992      N=6909      N=7078     
 Pain, Any                       70.7       73.5       71.6       89.9       58.2       62.2       62.6       83.5      
 Pain, Severe                     0.7        1.7        2.6        4.3        0.4        1.0        1.7        2.6      
 Swelling, Any                   12.5       23.3       28.3       40.0        9.3       14.6       18.7       28.8      
 Swelling, Severe                 0.6        1.5        2.5        3.8        0.3        0.5        1.0        1.5      
 Erythema, Any                   10.6       18.0       22.6       34.0        8.1       12.9       15.6       25.6      
 Erythema, Severe                 0.2        0.5        1.1        1.6        0.2        0.2        0.4        0.8      
   Systemic Adverse Reactions      n=6995      n=6913      n=6743      n=7022      n=7003      n=6914      n=6725      n=7024     
 Temperature &gt;=100 degrees F      1.7        2.6        2.7        6.0        1.7        2.4        2.5        5.9      
 Temperature &gt;=102 degrees F      0.3        0.3        0.4        1.0        0.2        0.3        0.3        0.8      
   Girls 9 through 15 Years of Age                                                                                             
   Injection-Site Adverse Reactions      N=300      N=297      N=296      N=299      N=299      N=299      N=294      N=300     
 Pain, Any                       71.7       71.0       74.3       89.3       66.2       66.2       69.4       88.3      
 Pain, Severe                     0.7        2.0        3.0        5.7        0.7        1.3        1.7        3.3      
 Swelling, Any                   14.0       23.9       36.1       47.8       10.4       17.7       25.2       36.0      
 Swelling, Severe                 0.3        2.4        3.7        6.0        0.7        2.7        4.1        6.3      
 Erythema, Any                    7.0       15.5       21.3       34.1        9.7       14.4       18.4       29.3      
 Erythema, Severe                  0         0.3        1.4        1.7         0         0.3        1.7        2.0      
   Systemic Adverse Reactions      n=300      n=294      n=295      n=299      n=299      n=297      n=291      n=300     
 Temperature &gt;=100 degrees F      2.3        1.7        3.0        6.7        1.7        1.7         0         3.3      
 Temperature &gt;=102 degrees F       0         0.3        1.0        1.3        0.3        0.3         0         0.7      
                   Unsolicited Adverse Reactions  
 

 Unsolicited injection-site and systemic adverse reactions (assessed as vaccine-related by the investigator) observed among recipients of either GARDASIL 9 or GARDASIL in Studies 1 and 3 at a frequency of at least 1% are shown in Table 2. Few individuals discontinued study participation due to adverse experiences after receiving either vaccine (GARDASIL 9 = 0.1% vs. GARDASIL &lt;0.1%).



 Table 2: Rates (%) of Unsolicited Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Occurring among &gt;=1.0% of Individuals after Any Vaccination with GARDASIL 9 Compared with GARDASIL (Studies 1 and 3) 
                       Girls and Women 16 through 26 Years of Age  Girls 9 through 15 Years of Age   
                         GARDASIL 9N=7071       GARDASILN=7078       GARDASIL 9N=299        GARDASILN=300       
  
 The data for girls and women 16 through 26 years of age are from Study 1 (NCT00543543), and the data for girls 9 through 15 years of age are from Study 3 (NCT01304498).   
 N=number of subjects vaccinated with safety follow-up   
  
   Injection-Site Adverse Reactions (1 to 5 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)     
 Pruritus                      5.5                   4.0                   4.0                   2.7            
 Bruising                      1.9                   1.9                    0                     0             
 Hematoma                      0.9                   0.6                   3.7                   4.7            
 Mass                          1.3                   0.6                    0                     0             
 Hemorrhage                    1.0                   0.7                   1.0                   2.0            
 Induration                    0.8                   0.2                   2.0                   1.0            
 Warmth                        0.8                   0.5                   0.7                   1.7            
 Reaction                      0.6                   0.6                   0.3                   1.0            
   Systemic Adverse Reactions (1 to 15 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)     
 Headache                      14.6                  13.7                  11.4                  11.3           
 Pyrexia                       5.0                   4.3                   5.0                   2.7            
 Nausea                        4.4                   3.7                   3.0                   3.7            
 Dizziness                     3.0                   2.8                   0.7                   0.7            
 Fatigue                       2.3                   2.1                    0                    2.7            
 Diarrhea                      1.2                   1.0                   0.3                    0             
 Oropharyngeal pain            1.0                   0.6                   2.7                   0.7            
 Myalgia                       1.0                   0.7                   0.7                   0.7            
 Abdominal pain, upper          0.7                   0.8                   1.7                   1.3            
 Upper respiratory tract infection          0.1                   0.1                   0.3                   1.0            
           In an uncontrolled clinical trial with 639 boys and 1,878 girls 9 through 15 years of age (Study 2), the rates and severity of solicited adverse reactions following each dose of GARDASIL 9 were similar between boys and girls. Rates of unsolicited injection-site and systemic adverse reactions in boys 9 through 15 years of age were similar to those among girls 9 through 15 years of age. Solicited and unsolicited adverse reactions reported by boys in this study are shown in Table 3.
 

 Table 3: Rates (%) of Solicited and UnsolicitedUnsolicited adverse reactions reported by &gt;=1% of individuals Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions among Boys 9 through 15 Years of Age who Received Gardasil 9 
                                                                                     GARDASIL 9N=639      
  
 The data for GARDASIL 9 are from Study 2 (NCT00943722).                            
 N=number of subjects vaccinated with safety follow-up                              
  
   Solicited Adverse Reactions (1-5 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)                                      
 Injection-Site Pain                                                                       71.5           
 Injection-Site Erythema                                                                   24.9           
 Injection-Site Swelling                                                                   26.9           
 Oral Temperature &gt;=100.0 degrees F                                                        10.4           
   Unsolicited Injection-Site Adverse Reactions (1-5 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)                           
 Injection-Site Hematoma                                                                   1.3            
 Injection-Site Induration                                                                 1.1            
   Unsolicited Systemic Adverse Reactions (1-15 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)                           
 Headache                                                                                  9.4            
 Pyrexia                                                                                   8.9            
 Nausea                                                                                    1.3            
            Serious Adverse Events in Clinical Studies  
 

 Serious adverse events were collected throughout the entire study period (range one month to 48 months post-last dose) for the six integrated clinical studies for GARDASIL 9. Out of the 13,236 individuals who were administered GARDASIL 9 and had safety follow-up, 305 reported a serious adverse event; representing 2.3% of the population. As a comparison, of the 7,378 individuals who were administered GARDASIL and had safety follow-up, 185 reported a serious adverse event; representing 2.5% of the population. Five GARDASIL 9 recipients each reported at least one serious adverse event that was determined to be vaccine-related. The vaccine-related serious adverse reactions were pyrexia, allergy to vaccine, asthmatic crisis, headache, and tonsillitis.



     Deaths in the Entire Study Population  



 Across the clinical studies, ten deaths occurred (five each in the GARDASIL 9 and GARDASIL groups); none were assessed as vaccine-related. Causes of death in the GARDASIL 9 group included one automobile accident, one suicide, one case of acute lymphocytic leukemia, one case of hypovolemic septic shock, and one unexplained sudden death 678 days following the last dose of GARDASIL 9. Causes of death in the GARDASIL control group included one automobile accident, one airplane crash, one cerebral hemorrhage, one gunshot wound, and one stomach adenocarcinoma.



     Systemic Autoimmune Disorders  



 In all of the clinical trials with GARDASIL 9 subjects were evaluated for new medical conditions potentially indicative of a systemic autoimmune disorder. In total, 2.4% (321/13,234) of GARDASIL 9 recipients and 3.3% (240/7,378) of GARDASIL recipients reported new medical conditions potentially indicative of systemic autoimmune disorders, which were similar to rates reported following GARDASIL, AAHS control, or saline placebo in historical clinical trials.



     Clinical Trials Experience for GARDASIL 9 in Individuals Who Have Been Previously Vaccinated with GARDASIL  



 A clinical study (Study 4) evaluated the safety of GARDASIL 9 in 12- through 26-year-old girls and women who had previously been vaccinated with three doses of GARDASIL. The time interval between the last injection of GARDASIL and the first injection of GARDASIL 9 ranged from approximately 12 to 36 months. Individuals were administered GARDASIL 9 or saline placebo and safety was evaluated using vaccination report card (VRC)-aided surveillance for 14 days after each injection of GARDASIL 9 or saline placebo in these individuals. The individuals who were monitored included 608 individuals who received GARDASIL 9 and 305 individuals who received saline placebo. Few (0.5%) individuals who received GARDASIL 9 discontinued due to adverse reactions. The vaccine-related adverse experiences that were observed among recipients of GARDASIL 9 at a frequency of at least 1.0% and also at a greater frequency than that observed among saline placebo recipients are shown in Table 4. Overall the safety profile was similar between individuals vaccinated with GARDASIL 9 who were previously vaccinated with GARDASIL and those who were naive to HPV vaccination with the exception of numerically higher rates of injection-site swelling and erythema among individuals who were previously vaccinated with GARDASIL (Tables 1 and 4).



 Table 4: Rates (%) of Solicited and UnsolicitedUnsolicited adverse reactions reported by &gt;=1% of individuals Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions among Individuals Previously Vaccinated with GARDASIL Who Received GARDASIL 9 or Saline Placebo (Girls and Women 12 through 26 Years of Age) 
                                                                         GARDASIL 9N=608  Saline PlaceboN=305   
  
 The data for GARDASIL 9 and saline placebo are from Study 4 (NCT01047345).   
 N=number of subjects vaccinated with safety follow-up                    
  
   Solicited Adverse Reactions (1-5 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)                                        
 Injection-Site Pain                                                          90.3             38.0         
 Injection-Site Erythema                                                      42.3              8.5         
 Injection-Site Swelling                                                      49.0              5.9         
 Oral Temperature &gt;=100.0 degrees F                                            6.5              3.0         
   Unsolicited Injection-Site Adverse Reactions (1-5 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)                                       
 Injection-Site Pruritus                                                       7.7              1.3         
 Injection-Site Hematoma                                                       4.8              2.3         
 Injection-Site Reaction                                                       1.3              0.3         
 Injection-Site Mass                                                           1.2              0.7         
   Unsolicited Systemic Adverse Reactions (1-15 Days Post-Vaccination, Any Dose)                                       
 Headache                                                                     19.6             18.0         
 Pyrexia                                                                       5.1              1.6         
 Nausea                                                                        3.9              2.0         
 Dizziness                                                                     3.0              1.6         
 Abdominal pain, upper                                                         1.5              0.7         
 Influenza                                                                     1.2              1.0         
             Safety in Concomitant Use with Menactra and Adacel  
 

 In Study 5, the safety of GARDASIL 9 when administered concomitantly with Menactra [Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine] and Adacel [Tetanus Toxoid, Reduced Diphtheria Toxoid and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed (Tdap)] was evaluated in a randomized study of 1,241 boys (n = 620) and girls (n = 621) with a mean age of 12.2 years  [see  Clinical Studies (14.5)  ]  .



 Of the 1,237 boys and girls vaccinated, 1,220 had safety follow-up for injection-site adverse reactions. The rates of injection-site adverse reactions were similar between the concomitant group and non-concomitant group (vaccination with GARDASIL 9 separated from vaccination with Menactra and Adacel by 1 month) with the exception of an increased rate of swelling reported at the injection site for GARDASIL 9 in the concomitant group (14.4%) compared to the non-concomitant group (9.4%). The majority of injection-site swelling adverse reactions were reported as being mild to moderate in intensity.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  There is no post-marketing experience following administration of GARDASIL 9. However, the post-marketing safety experience with GARDASIL is relevant to GARDASIL 9 since the vaccines are manufactured similarly and contain the same antigens from HPV types 6, 11, 16, and 18. Because these events were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or to establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure. The following adverse experiences have been spontaneously reported during post-approval use of GARDASIL and may also be seen in post-marketing experience with GARDASIL 9:



 Blood and lymphatic system disorders: Autoimmune hemolytic anemia, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, lymphadenopathy.



 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders: Pulmonary embolus.



 Gastrointestinal disorders: Nausea, pancreatitis, vomiting.



 General disorders and administration site conditions: Asthenia, chills, death, fatigue, malaise.



 Immune system disorders: Autoimmune diseases, hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions, bronchospasm, and urticaria.



 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders: Arthralgia, myalgia.



 Nervous system disorders: Acute disseminated encephalomyelitis, dizziness, Guillain-Barre syndrome, headache, motor neuron disease, paralysis, seizures, syncope (including syncope associated with tonic-clonic movements and other seizure-like activity) sometimes resulting in falling with injury, transverse myelitis.



 Infections and infestations: Cellulitis.



 Vascular disorders: Deep venous thrombosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Because vaccinees may develop syncope, sometimes resulting in falling with injury, observation for 15 minutes after administration is recommended. Syncope, sometimes associated with tonic-clonic movements and other seizure-like activity, has been reported following HPV vaccination. When syncope is associated with tonic-clonic movements, the activity is usually transient and typically responds to restoring cerebral perfusion by maintaining a supine or Trendelenburg position. (  5.1  )



 



   5.1 Syncope



  Because vaccinees may develop syncope, sometimes resulting in falling with injury, observation for 15 minutes after administration is recommended. Syncope, sometimes associated with tonic-clonic movements and other seizure-like activity, has been reported following HPV vaccination. When syncope is associated with tonic-clonic movements, the activity is usually transient and typically responds to restoring cerebral perfusion by maintaining a supine or Trendelenburg position.



    5.2 Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be readily available in case of anaphylactic reactions following the administration of GARDASIL 9.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
