<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gastrocrom" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS:  Most of the adverse events reported in mastocytosis patients have been transient and could represent symptoms of the disease. The most frequently reported adverse events in mastocytosis patients who have received GASTROCROM during clinical studies were headache and diarrhea, each of which occurred in 4 of the 87 patients. Pruritus, nausea, and myalgia were each reported in 3 patients and abdominal pain, rash, and irritability in 2 patients each. One report of malaise was also recorded.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Meda Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-877-999-8406 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



     Other Adverse Events:  Additional adverse events have been reported during studies in other clinical conditions and from worldwide postmarketing experience. In most cases the available information is incomplete and attribution to the drug cannot be determined. The majority of these reports involve the gastrointestinal system and include: diarrhea, nausea, abdominal pain, constipation, dyspepsia, flatulence, glossitis, stomatitis, vomiting, dysphagia, esophagospasm.



 Other less commonly reported events (the majority representing only a single report) include the following:



 Skin: pruritus, rash, urticaria/angioedema, erythema/ burning, photosensitivity



 Musculoskeletal: arthralgia, myalgia, stiffness/weakness of legs



 Neurologic: headache, dizziness, hypoesthesia, paresthesia, migraine, convulsions, flushing



 Psychiatric: psychosis, anxiety, depression, hallucinations, behavior change, insomnia, nervousness



 Heart Rate: tachycardia, premature ventricular contractions (PVCs), palpitations



 Respiratory: pharyngitis, dyspnea



 Miscellaneous: fatigue, edema, unpleasant taste, chest pain, postprandial lightheadedness and lethargy, dysuria, urinary frequency, purpura, hepatic function test abnormal, polycythemia, neutropenia, pancytopenia, tinnitus, lupus erythematosus (LE) syndrome
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
