<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gemzar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in another section of the label



 *  Schedule-dependent Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Myelosuppression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Pulmonary Toxicity and Respiratory Failure [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Hemolytic Uremic Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Hepatic Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Embryofetal Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ), and Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.1  )]  
 *  Exacerbation of Radiation Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Capillary Leak Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions for the single agent (&gt;=20%) are nausea/vomiting, anemia, hepatic transaminitis, neutropenia, increased alkaline phosphatase, proteinuria, fever, hematuria, rash, thrombocytopenia, dyspnea, and peripheral edema. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Single-Agent Use:  



 The data described below reflect exposure to Gemzar as a single agent administered at doses between 800 mg/m  2  to 1250 mg/m  2  over 30 minutes intravenously, once weekly, in 979 patients with a variety of malignancies. The most common (&gt;=20%) adverse reactions of single-agent Gemzar are nausea/vomiting, anemia, increased ALT, increased AST, neutropenia, increased alkaline phosphatase, proteinuria, fever, hematuria, rash, thrombocytopenia, dyspnea, and edema. The most common (&gt;=5%) Grade 3 or 4 adverse reactions were neutropenia, nausea/vomiting; increased ALT, increase alkaline phosphatase, anemia, increased AST, and thrombocytopenia. Approximately 10% of the 979 patients discontinued Gemzar due to adverse reactions. Adverse reactions resulting in discontinuation of Gemzar in 2% of 979 patients were cardiovascular adverse events (myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular accident, arrhythmia, and hypertension) and adverse reactions resulting in discontinuation of Gemzar in less than 1% of the 979 patients were anemia, thrombocytopenia, hepatic dysfunction, renal dysfunction, nausea/vomiting, fever, rash, dyspnea, hemorrhage, infection, stomatitis, somnolence, flu-like syndrome, and edema.



   Table 5  presents the incidence of adverse reactions reported in 979 patients with various malignancies receiving single-agent Gemzar across 5 clinical trials.  Table 5  includes all clinical adverse reactions, reported in at least 10% of patients. A listing of clinically significant adverse reactions is provided following the table.



 Table 5: Selected Per-Patient Incidence of Adverse Events in Patients Receiving Single-Agent Gemzara 
  a Grade based on criteria from the World Health Organization (WHO).    
  b N=699-974; all patients with laboratory or non-laboratory data.    
  c Regardless of causality.        
  d For approximately 60% of patients, non-laboratory adverse events were graded only if assessed to be possibly drug-related.    
  
                                     All Patients      b       
 All Grades                        Grade 3                  Grade 4                  
   Laboratory      c                                                                                        
      Hematologic                                                                                           
          Anemia                   68                       7                       1                       
          Neutropenia              63                       19                      6                       
          Thrombocytopenia         24                       4                       1                       
      Hepatic                                                                                               
          Increased ALT            68                       8                       2                       
          Increased AST            67                       6                       2                       
          Increased Alkaline Phosphatase  55                       7                       2                       
          Hyperbilirubinemia       13                       2                       &lt;1                      
      Renal                                                                                                 
          Proteinuria              45                       &lt;1                      0                       
          Hematuria                35                       &lt;1                      0                       
          Increased BUN            16                       0                       0                       
          Increased Creatinine     8                        &lt;1                      0                       
   Non-laboratory      d                                                                                    
      Nausea and Vomiting          69                       13                      1                       
      Fever                        41                       2                       0                       
      Rash                         30                       &lt;1                      0                       
      Dyspnea                      23                       3                       &lt;1                      
      Diarrhea                     19                       1                       0                       
      Hemorrhage                   17                       &lt;1                      &lt;1                      
      Infection                    16                       1                       &lt;1                      
      Alopecia                     15                       &lt;1                      0                       
      Stomatitis                   11                       &lt;1                      0                       
      Somnolence                   11                       &lt;1                      &lt;1                      
      Paresthesias                 10                       &lt;1                      0                       
         *  Transfusion requirements - Red blood cell transfusions (19%); platelet transfusions (&lt;1%) 
 *  Fever - Fever occurred in the absence of clinical infection and frequently in combination with other flu-like symptoms. 
 *  Pulmonary - Dyspnea unrelated to underlying disease and sometimes accompanied by bronchospasm. 
 *  Edema - Edema (13%), peripheral edema (20%), and generalized edema (&lt;1%); &lt;1% of patients. discontinued Gemzar due to edema. 
 *  Flu-like Symptoms - Characterized by fever, asthenia, anorexia, headache, cough, chills, myalgia, asthenia insomnia, rhinitis, sweating, and/or malaise (19%); &lt;1% of patients discontinued Gemzar due to flu-like symptoms 
 *  Infection - Sepsis (&lt;1%) 
 *  Extravasation - Injection-site reactions (4%) 
 *  Allergic - Bronchospasm (&lt;2%); anaphylactoid reactions [see Contraindications (  4  )] . 
        Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer:  
 

   Table 6  presents the incidence of selected adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;=10% of Gemzar-treated patients and at a higher incidence in the Gemzar plus cisplatin arm, reported in a randomized trial of Gemzar plus cisplatin (n=262) administered in 28-day cycles as compared to cisplatin alone (n=260) in patients receiving first-line treatment for locally advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC)  [see Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  .



 Patients randomized to Gemzar plus cisplatin received a median of 4 cycles of treatment and those randomized to cisplatin received a median of 2 cycles of treatment. In this trial, the requirement for dose adjustments (&gt;90% versus 16%), discontinuation of treatment for adverse reactions (15% versus 8%), and the proportion of patients hospitalized (36% versus 23%) were all higher for patients receiving Gemzar plus cisplatin arm compared to those receiving cisplatin alone. The incidence of febrile neutropenia (9/262 versus 2/260), sepsis (4% versus 1%), Grade 3 cardiac dysrhythmias (3% versus &lt;1%) were all higher in the Gemzar plus cisplatin arm compared to the cisplatin alone arm. The two-drug combination was more myelosuppressive with 4 (1.5%) possibly treatment-related deaths, including 3 resulting from myelosuppression with infection and one case of renal failure associated with pancytopenia and infection. No deaths due to treatment were reported on the cisplatin arm.



 Table 6: Per-Patient Incidence of Selected Adverse Reactions from Randomized Trial of Gemzar plus Cisplatin versus Single-Agent Cisplatin in Patients with NSCLC Occurring at Higher Incidence in Gemzar-Treated Patients [Between Arm Difference of &gt;=5% (All Grades) or &gt;=2% (Grades 3-4)]a 
  a National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) for severity grading.    
  b N=217-253; all Gemzar plus cisplatin patients with laboratory or non-laboratory data Gemzar at 1000 mg/m2 on Days 1, 8, and 15 and cisplatin at 100 mg/m2 on Day 1 every 28 days.    
  c N=213-248; all cisplatin patients with laboratory or non-laboratory data. Cisplatin at 100 mg/m2 on Day 1 every 28 days.    
  d Regardless of causality.    
  e Percent of patients receiving transfusions. Percent transfusions are not CTC-graded events.    
  f Non-laboratory events were graded only if assessed to be possibly drug-related.    
  
                             Gemzar plus Cisplatin      b        Cisplatin      c       
 All Grades                Grade 3       Grade 4       All Grades    Grade 3       Grade 4        
   Laboratory      d                                                                                            
        Hematologic                                                                                             
          Anemia           89            22            3             67            6             1              
          RBC Transfusion  e    39                                        13                                         
          Neutropenia      79            22            35            20            3             1              
          Thrombocytopenia  85            25            25            13            3             1              
          Platelet Transfusions  e    21                                        &lt;1                                         
          Lymphopenia      75            25            18            51            12            5              
      Hepatic                                                                                                   
          Increased Transaminases  22            2             1             10            1             0              
          Increased Alkaline Phosphatase  19            1             0             13            0             0              
      Renal                                                                                                     
          Proteinuria      23            0             0             18            0             0              
          Hematuria        15            0             0             13            0             0              
          Elevated creatinine  38            4             &lt;1            31            2             &lt;1             
      Other Laboratory                                                                                          
          Hyperglycemia    30            4             0             23            3             0              
          Hypomagnesemia   30            4             3             17            2             0              
          Hypocalcemia     18            2             0             7             0             &lt;1             
   Non-laboratory      f                                                                                           
      Nausea               93            25            2             87            20            &lt;1             
      Vomiting             78            11            12            71            10            9              
      Alopecia             53            1             0             33            0             0              
      Neuro Motor          35            12            0             15            3             0              
      Diarrhea             24            2             2             13            0             0              
      Neuro Sensory        23            1             0             18            1             0              
      Infection            18            3             2             12            1             0              
      Fever                16            0             0             5             0             0              
      Neuro Cortical       16            3             1             9             1             0              
      Neuro Mood           16            1             0             10            1             0              
      Local                15            0             0             6             0             0              
      Neuro Headache       14            0             0             7             0             0              
      Stomatitis           14            1             0             5             0             0              
      Hemorrhage           14            1             0             4             0             0              
      Hypotension          12            1             0             7             1             0              
      Rash                 11            0             0             3             0             0              
               Table 7  presents the incidence of selected adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;=10% of Gemzar-treated patients and at a higher incidence in the Gemzar plus cisplatin arm, reported in a randomized trial of Gemzar plus cisplatin (n=69) administered in 21-day cycles as compared to etoposide plus cisplatin alone (n=66) in patients receiving first-line treatment for locally advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC)  [see Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  . A listing of clinically significant adverse reactions is provided following the table.
 

 Patients in the Gemzar cisplatin (GC) arm received a median of 5 cycles and those in the etoposide/cisplatin (EC) arm received a median of 4 cycles. The majority of patients receiving more than one cycle of treatment required dose adjustments; 81% in the (GC) arm and 68% in the (EC) arm. The incidence of hospitalizations for treatment-related adverse events was 22% (GC) and 27% in the (EC) arm. The proportion of discontinuation of treatment for treatment-related adverse reactions was higher for patients in the (GC) arm (14% versus 8%). The proportion of patients hospitalized for febrile neutropenia was lower in the (GC) arm (7% versus 12%). There was one death attributed to treatment, a patient with febrile neutropenia and renal failure, which occurred in the Gemzar/cisplatin arm.



 Table 7: Per-Patient Incidence of Selected Adverse Reactions in Randomized Trial of Gemzar plus Cisplatin versus Etoposide plus Cisplatin in Patients with NSCLCa 
  a Grade based on criteria from the World Health Organization (WHO).    
  b N=67-69; all Gemzar plus cisplatin patients with laboratory or non-laboratory data. Gemzar at 1250 mg/m2 on Days 1 and 8 and cisplatin at 100 mg/m2 on Day 1 every 21 days.    
  c N=57-63; all cisplatin plus etoposide patients with laboratory or non-laboratory data. Cisplatin at 100 mg/m2 on Day 1 and intravenous etoposide at 100 mg/m2 on Days 1, 2, and 3 every 21 days.    
  d Regardless of causality.    
  e WHO grading scale not applicable to proportion of patients with transfusions.    
  f Non-laboratory events were graded only if assessed to be possibly drug-related. Pain data were not collected.    
  g Flu-like syndrome and edema were not graded.    
  
                              Gemzar plus Cisplatin      b        Etoposide plus Cisplatin      c       
 All Grades                 Grade 3       Grade 4       All Grades    Grade 3       Grade 4        
   Laboratory      d                                                                                             
      Hematologic                                                                                                
          Anemia            88            22            0             77            13            2              
          RBC Transfusions  e    29            -             -             21            -             -              
          Neutropenia       88            36            28            87            20            56             
          Thrombocytopenia  81            39            16            45            8             5              
          Platelet Transfusions  e    3             -             -             8             -             -              
      Hepatic                                                                                                    
          Increased ALT     6             0             0             12            0             0              
          Increased AST     3             0             0             11            0             0              
          Increased Alkaline Phosphatase  16            0             0             11            0             0              
          Bilirubin         0             0             0             0             0             0              
      Renal                                                                                                      
          Proteinuria       12            0             0             5             0             0              
          Hematuria         22            0             0             10            0             0              
          BUN               6             0             0             4             0             0              
          Creatinine        2             0             0             2             0             0              
   Non-laboratory      f                                                                                           
          Nausea and Vomiting  96            35            4             86            19            7              
          Fever             6             0             0             3             0             0              
          Rash              10            0             0             3             0             0              
          Dyspnea           1             0             1             3             0             0              
          Diarrhea          14            1             1             13            0             2              
          Hemorrhage        9             0             3             3             0             3              
          Infection         28            3             1             21            8             0              
          Alopecia          77            13            0             92            51            0              
          Stomatitis        20            4             0             18            2             0              
          Somnolence        3             0             0             3             2             0              
          Paresthesias      38            0             0             16            2             0              
          Flu-like syndrome  g    3             -             -             0             -             -              
          Edema  g          12            -             -             2             -             -              
                 Breast Cancer  
 

   Table 8  presents the incidence of selected adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;=10% of Gemzar-treated patients and at a higher incidence in the Gemzar plus paclitaxel arm, reported in a randomized trial of Gemzar plus paclitaxel (n=262) compared to paclitaxel alone (n=259) for the first-line treatment of metastatic breast cancer (MBC) in women who received anthracycline-containing chemotherapy in the adjuvant/neo-adjuvant setting or for whom anthracyclines were contraindicated  [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  .



 The requirement for dose reduction of paclitaxel were higher for patients in the Gemzar/paclitaxel arm (5% versus 2%). The number of paclitaxel doses omitted (&lt;1%), the proportion of patients discontinuing treatment for treatment-related adverse reactions (7% versus 5%), and the number of treatment-related deaths (1 patient in each arm) were similar between the two arms.



 Table 8: Per-Patient Incidence of Selected Adverse Reactions from Comparative Trial of Gemzar plus Paclitaxel versus Single-Agent Paclitaxel in Breast Cancera Occurring at Higher Incidence in Gemzar-Treated Patients [Between Arm Difference of &gt;=5% (All Grades) or &gt;=2% (Grades 3-4)] 
  a Severity grade based on National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) Version 2.0.    
  b Regardless of causality.    
  c Non-laboratory events were graded only if assessed to be possibly drug-related.    
  
                              Gemzar plus Paclitaxel    (N=262)      Paclitaxel    (N=259)     
 All Grades                 Grade 3       Grade 4       All Grades    Grade 3       Grade 4        
   Laboratory      b                                                                                             
      Hematologic                                                                                                
          Anemia            69            6             1             51            3             &lt;1             
          Neutropenia       69            31            17            31            4             7              
          Thrombocytopenia  26            5             &lt;1            7             &lt;1            &lt;1             
      Hepatobiliary                                                                                              
          Increased ALT     18            5             &lt;1            6             &lt;1            0              
          Increased AST     16            2             0             5             &lt;1            0              
   Non-laboratory      c                                                                                           
      Alopecia              90            14            4             92            19            3              
      Neuropathy-sensory    64            5             &lt;1            58            3             0              
      Nausea                50            1             0             31            2             0              
      Fatigue               40            6             &lt;1            28            1             &lt;1             
      Vomiting              29            2             0             15            2             0              
      Diarrhea              20            3             0             13            2             0              
      Anorexia              17            0             0             12            &lt;1            0              
      Neuropathy-motor      15            2             &lt;1            10            &lt;1            0              
      Stomatitis/pharyngitis  13            1             &lt;1            8             &lt;1            0              
      Fever                 13            &lt;1            0             3             0             0              
      Rash/desquamation     11            &lt;1            &lt;1            5             0             0              
     Febrile neutropenia    6             5             &lt;1            2             1             0              
             Clinically relevant Grade 3 or 4 dyspnea occurred with a higher incidence in the Gemzar plus paclitaxel arm compared with the paclitaxel arm (1.9% versus 0).
 

     Ovarian Cancer  



   Table 9  presents the incidence of selected adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;=10% of gemcitabine-treated patients and at a higher incidence in the Gemzar plus carboplatin arm, reported in a randomized trial of Gemzar plus carboplatin (n=175) compared to carboplatin alone (n=174) for the second-line treatment of ovarian cancer in women with disease that had relapsed more than 6 months following first-line platinum-based chemotherapy  [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  . Additional clinically significant adverse reactions, occurring in less than 10% of patients, are provided following  Table 9  .



 The proportion of patients with dose adjustments for carboplatin (1.8% versus 3.8%), doses of carboplatin omitted (0.2% versus 0), and discontinuing treatment for treatment-related adverse reactions (10.9% versus 9.8%), were similar between arms. Dose adjustment for Gemzar occurred in 10.4% of patients and Gemzar dose was omitted in 13.7% of patients in the Gemzar /carboplatin arm.



 Table 9: Per-Patient Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Randomized Trial of Gemzar plus Carboplatin versus Carboplatin in Ovarian Cancera Occurring at Higher Incidence in Gemzar-Treated Patients [Between Arm Difference of &gt;=5% (All Grades) or &gt;=2% (Grades 3-4)] 
  a Grade based on Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) Version 2.0.    
  b Regardless of causality.    
  c Percent of patients receiving transfusions. Transfusions are not CTC-graded events. Blood transfusions included both packed red blood cells and whole blood.    
  
                              Gemzar plus Carboplatin    (N=175)      Carboplatin    (N=174)     
 All Grades                 Grade 3       Grade 4       All Grades    Grade 3       Grade 4        
   Laboratory      b                                                                                             
      Hematologic                                                                                                
          Neutropenia       90            42            29            58            11            1              
          Anemia            86            22            6             75            9             2              
          Thrombocytopenia  78            30            5             57            10            1              
          RBC Transfusions  c    38                                        15                                         
          Platelet Transfusions  c    9                                         3                                          
   Non-laboratory      b                                                                                           
      Nausea                69            6             0             61            3             0              
      Alopecia              49            0             0             17            0             0              
      Vomiting              46            6             0             36            2             &lt;1             
      Constipation          42            6             1             37            3             0              
      Fatigue               40            3             &lt;1            32            5             0              
      Diarrhea              25            3             0             14            &lt;1            0              
      Stomatitis/pharyngitis  22            &lt;1            0             13            0             0              
             Hematopoietic growth factors were administered more frequently in the Gemzar-containing arm: granulocyte growth factors (23.6% and 10.1%) and erythropoietic agents (7.3% and 3.9%).
 

 The following clinically relevant, Grade 3 and 4 adverse reactions occurred more frequently in the Gemzar plus carboplatin arm: dyspnea (3.4% versus 2.9%), febrile neutropenia (1.1% versus 0), hemorrhagic event (2.3% versus 1.1 %), motor neuropathy (1.1% versus 0.6%), and rash/desquamation (0.6% versus 0).



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Gemzar. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Cardiovascular  - Congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction, arrhythmias, supraventricular arrhythmias



   Vascular Disorders  - Peripheral vasculitis, gangrene, and capillary leak syndrome  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  



   Skin  - Cellulitis, severe skin reactions, including desquamation and bullous skin eruptions



   Hepatic  - Hepatic failure, hepatic veno-occlusive disease



   Pulmonary  - Interstitial pneumonitis, pulmonary fibrosis, pulmonary edema, and adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS)



   Nervous System  - Posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES)  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Schedule-dependent toxicity: Increased toxicity with infusion time greater than 60 minutes or dosing more frequently than once weekly. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Myelosuppression: Monitor for myelosuppression prior to each cycle and reduce or withhold dose for severe myelosuppression. (  5.2  ,  5.7  ) 
 *  Pulmonary Toxicity and Respiratory Failure: Discontinue Gemzar immediately for unexplained new or worsening dyspnea or evidence of severe pulmonary toxicity. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hemolytic-Uremic Syndrome (HUS): Monitor renal function prior to initiation and during therapy. Discontinue Gemzar for HUS or severe renal impairment. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hepatic Toxicity: Monitor hepatic function prior to initiation and during therapy. Discontinue Gemzar for severe hepatic toxicity. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Embryofetal Toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise women of potential risk to the fetus. (  5.6  ,  8.1  ) 
 *  Exacerbation of Radiation Therapy Toxicity: May cause severe and life-threatening toxicity when administered during or within 7 days of radiation therapy. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Capillary Leak Syndrome: Discontinue Gemzar. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES): Discontinue Gemzar. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Schedule-dependent Toxicity



  In clinical trials evaluating the maximum tolerated dose of Gemzar, prolongation of the infusion time beyond 60 minutes or more frequent than weekly dosing resulted in an increased incidence of clinically significant hypotension, severe flu-like symptoms, myelosuppression, and asthenia. The half-life of Gemzar is influenced by the length of the infusion [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    5.2 Myelosuppression



  Myelosuppression manifested by neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and anemia occurs with Gemzar as a single agent and the risks are increased when Gemzar is combined with other cytotoxic drugs. In clinical trials, Grade 3-4 neutropenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia occurred in 25%, 8%, and 5%, respectively of patients receiving single-agent Gemzar. The frequencies of Grade 3-4 neutropenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia varied from 48% to 71%, 8 to 28%, and 5 to 55%, respectively, in patients receiving Gemzar in combination with another drug.



    5.3 Pulmonary Toxicity and Respiratory Failure



  Pulmonary toxicity, including interstitial pneumonitis, pulmonary fibrosis, pulmonary edema, and adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), has been reported. In some cases, these pulmonary events can lead to fatal respiratory failure despite discontinuation of therapy. The onset of pulmonary symptoms may occur up to 2 weeks after the last dose of Gemzar. Discontinue Gemzar in patients who develop unexplained dyspnea, with or without bronchospasm, or have any evidence of pulmonary toxicity [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  and  6.2  )]  .



    5.4 Hemolytic Uremic Syndrome



  Hemolytic uremic syndrome, including fatalities from renal failure or the requirement for dialysis, can occur in patients treated with Gemzar. In clinical trials, HUS was reported in 6 of 2429 patients (0.25%). Most fatal cases of renal failure were due to HUS [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  and  6.2  )]  . Assess renal function prior to initiation of Gemzar and periodically during treatment. Consider the diagnosis of HUS in patients who develops anemia with evidence of microangiopathic hemolysis, elevation of bilirubin or LDH, or reticulocytosis; severe thrombocytopenia; or evidence of renal failure (elevation of serum creatinine or BUN) [see Dosage and Administration (  2.5  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  )]  . Permanently discontinue Gemzar in patients with HUS or severe renal impairment. Renal failure may not be reversible even with discontinuation of therapy.



    5.5 Hepatic Toxicity



  Drug-induced liver injury, including liver failure and death, has been reported in patients receiving Gemzar alone or in combination with other potentially hepatotoxic drugs [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  and  6.2  )]  . Administration of Gemzar in patients with concurrent liver metastases or a pre-existing medical history or hepatitis, alcoholism, or liver cirrhosis can lead to exacerbation of the underlying hepatic insufficiency [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.7  )]  . Assess hepatic function prior to initiation of Gemzar and periodically during treatment. Discontinue Gemzar in patients that develop severe liver injury.



    5.6 Embryofetal Toxicity



  Gemzar can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman, based on its mechanism of action. Gemcitabine was teratogenic, embryotoxic, and fetotoxic in mice and rabbits. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if a woman becomes pregnant while taking Gemzar, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



    5.7 Exacerbation of Radiation Therapy Toxicity



  Gemzar is not indicated for use in combination with radiation therapy.



    Concurrent (given together or &lt;=7 days apart)  - Life-threatening mucositis, especially esophagitis and pneumonitis occurred in a trial in which Gemzar was administered at a dose of 1000 mg/m  2  to patients with non-small cell lung cancer for up to 6 consecutive weeks concurrently with thoracic radiation.



    Non-concurrent (given &gt;7 days apart)  - Excessive toxicity has not been observed when Gemzar is administered more than 7 days before or after radiation. Radiation recall has been reported in patients who receive Gemzar after prior radiation.



    5.8 Capillary Leak Syndrome



  Capillary leak syndrome (CLS) with severe consequences has been reported in patients receiving Gemzar as a single agent or in combination with other chemotherapeutic agents. Discontinue Gemzar if CLS develops during therapy.



    5.9 Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome



     Posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES) has been reported in patients receiving Gemzar as a single agent or in combination with other chemotherapeutic agents. PRES can present with headache, seizure, lethargy, hypertension, confusion, blindness, and other visual and neurologic disturbances. Confirm the diagnosis of PRES with magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and discontinue Gemzar if PRES develops during therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
