<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="generess" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions with the use of COCs are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Serious cardiovascular events and smoking [see Boxed Warning, and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Vascular events [see Warnings  and  Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Liver disease [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
    Adverse reactions commonly reported by COC users are:
 

 *  Irregular uterine bleeding 
 *  Nausea 
 *  Breast tenderness 
 *  Headache 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) are nausea/vomiting (8.8%), headaches/migraine (7.5%), depression/mood complaints (4.1%), dysmenorrhea (3.9%), acne (3.2%), anxiety symptoms (2.4%), breast pain/tenderness (2.4%), and increased weight (2.3%). (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Watson Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-272-5525 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 A phase 3 clinical trial evaluated the safety and efficacy of GENERESS Fe for pregnancy prevention.  The study was a multicenter, non-comparative, open-label study with a treatment duration of 12 months (thirteen 28-day cycles).  A total of 1,677 women aged 18-46 were enrolled and took at least one dose of GENERESS Fe.



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Study Discontinuation:    8.5% of the women discontinued from the clinical trial due to an adverse reaction. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were nausea (1.0%), weight increase (0.8%), acne (0.8%), metrorrhagia (0.7%), altered mood (0.4%), hypertension (0.4%), irritability (0.3%), migraine (0.3%), decreased libido (0.3%) and mood swings (0.3%).



     Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 2% of all treated subjects):      nausea/vomiting (8.8%), headaches/migraine (7.5%), depression/mood complaints (4.1%), dysmenorrhea (3.9%), acne (3.2%), anxiety symptoms (2.4%), breast pain/tenderness (2.4%), and increased weight (2.3%).



     Serious Adverse Reactions:      Hypertension, depression, cholecystitis, and deep vein thrombosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: BOXED WARNING

    BOXED WARNING  

    WARNING:  CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS   



   Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive (COC) use. This risk increases with age, particularly in women over 35 years of age, and with the number of cigarettes smoked.  For this reason, COCs should not be used by women who are over 35 years of age and smoke   [see   Contraindications  (4)  ].     



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS    See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Women over 35 years old who smoke should not use GENERESS Fe. (4) 
 *  Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive (COC) use. (4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Vascular risks: Stop GENERESS Fe if a thrombotic event occurs.  Stop at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery.  Start no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery in women who are not breastfeeding. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Liver disease: Discontinue if jaundice occurs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  High blood pressure: Do not prescribe for women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Carbohydrate and lipid metabolic effects: Monitor prediabetic and diabetic women taking GENERESS Fe.  Consider an alternate contraceptive method for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemia. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Headache: Evaluate significant change in headaches and discontinue if indicated. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Uterine bleeding: Evaluate irregular bleeding or amenorrhea. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thrombotic and Other Vascular Events



  Stop GENERESS Fe if an arterial or deep venous thrombotic (VTE) event occurs. Although the use of COCs increases the risk of venous thromboembolism, pregnancy increases the risk of venous thromboembolism as much or more than the use of COCs. The risk of venous thromboembolism in women using COCs is 3 to 9 per 10,000 woman-years. The excess risk is highest during the first year of use of a COC.  Use of COCs also increases the risk of arterial thromboses such as strokes and myocardial infarctions, especially in women with other risk factors for these events.  The risk of thromboembolic disease due to oral contraceptives gradually disappears after COC use is discontinued.



 If feasible, stop GENERESS Fe at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery or other surgeries known to have an elevated risk of thromboembolism.



 Start GENERESS Fe no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. The risk of postpartum thromboembolism decreases after the third postpartum week, whereas the risk of ovulation increases after the third postpartum week.



 COCs have been shown to increase both the relative and attributable risks of cerebrovascular events (thrombotic and hemorrhagic strokes), although, in general, the risk is greatest among older (&gt; 35 years of age), hypertensive women who also smoke. COCs also increase the risk for stroke in women with other underlying risk factors.



 Oral contraceptives must be used with caution in women with cardiovascular disease risk factors. 



 Stop GENERESS Fe if there is unexplained loss of vision, proptosis, diplopia, papilledema, or retinal vascular lesions. Evaluate for retinal vein thrombosis immediately.    



    5.2 Carcinoma of the Breasts and Reproductive Organs



  Women who currently have or have had breast cancer should not use GENERESS Fe because breast cancer is a hormonally-sensitive tumor. 



 There is substantial evidence that COCs do not increase the incidence of breast cancer. Although some past studies have suggested that COCs might increase the incidence of breast cancer, more recent studies have not confirmed such findings.



 Some studies suggest that COCs are associated with an increase in the risk of cervical cancer or intraepithelial neoplasia.  However, there is controversy about the extent to which these findings may be due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors.



    5.3 Liver Disease



  Discontinue GENERESS Fe if jaundice develops. Steroid hormones may be poorly metabolized in patients with impaired liver function. Acute or chronic disturbances of liver function may necessitate the discontinuation of COC use until markers of liver function return to normal and COC causation has been excluded.



 Hepatic adenomas are associated with COC use. An estimate of the attributable risk is 3.3 cases/100,000 COC users.  Rupture of hepatic adenomas may cause death through intra-abdominal hemorrhage.



 Studies have shown an increased risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in long-term (&gt; 8 years) COC users.  However, the attributable risk of liver cancers in COC users is less than one case per million users.



 Oral contraceptive-related cholestasis may occur in women with a history of pregnancy-related cholestasis. Women with a history of COC-related cholestasis may have the condition recur with subsequent COC use.



    5.4 High Blood Pressure



  For women with well-controlled hypertension, monitor blood pressure and stop GENERESS Fe if blood pressure rises significantly.  Women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease should not use COCs.



 An increase in blood pressure has been reported in women taking COCs, and this increase is more likely in older women and with extended duration of use. The incidence of hypertension increases with increasing concentration of progestin.



    5.5 Gallbladder Disease



  Studies suggest the relative risk of developing gallbladder disease may be increased among COC users.



    5.6 Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects



  Carefully monitor prediabetic and diabetic women who are taking GENERESS Fe. COCs may decrease glucose tolerance in a dose-related fashion. 



 Consider alternative contraception for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemia. A small proportion of women will have adverse lipid changes while on COCs.



 Women with hypertriglyceridemia, or a family history thereof, may be at an increased risk of pancreatitis when using COCs.



    5.7 Headache



  If a woman taking GENERESS Fe develops new headaches that are recurrent, persistent, or severe, evaluate the cause and discontinue GENERESS Fe if indicated.



 An increase in frequency or severity of migraine during COC use (which may be prodromal of a cerebrovascular event) may be a reason for immediate discontinuation of the COC.    



    5.8 Bleeding Irregularities



  Unscheduled (breakthrough or intracyclic) bleeding and spotting sometimes occur in patients on COCs, especially during the first three months of use.  If bleeding persists or occurs after previously regular cycles, check for causes such as pregnancy or malignancy. If pathology and pregnancy are excluded, bleeding irregularities may resolve over time or with a change to a different COC.



 Patient diaries from the clinical trial of GENERESS Fe showed that on the first cycle of use, 37% of subjects taking GENERESS Fe had unscheduled bleeding and/or spotting.  From Cycle 2-13, the percent of women with unscheduled bleeding/spotting ranged from 21-31% per cycle. For those women with unscheduled bleeding/spotting, the mean number of days of unscheduled bleeding/spotting was 5.2 in the first cycle of use and ranged from 3.6 - 4.2 in cycles 2-13. A total of 15 subjects out of 1,677 (0.9%) discontinued the study prematurely due to metrorrhagia or irregular menstruation.



 Women who are not pregnant and use GENERESS Fe may not have scheduled (withdrawal) bleeding every cycle or may experience amenorrhea (absence of any bleeding and spotting). The incidence of amenorrhea in the clinical trial increased from 8.1% of the subjects in Cycle 2 to 18.4% by Cycle 13.  For those women who had scheduled (withdrawal) bleeding, the average duration of bleeding per cycle in Cycles 2-13 was 3.7 days. 



 If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed dosing schedule (missed one or more active tablets or started taking them on a day later than she should have), consider the possibility of pregnancy at the time of the first missed period and take appropriate diagnostic measures. If the patient has adhered to the prescribed regimen and misses two consecutive periods, rule out pregnancy.



 Some women may encounter amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea after stopping COCs, especially when such a condition was pre-existent.



    5.9 COC Use Before or During Early Pregnancy



  Extensive epidemiological studies have revealed no increased risk of birth defects in women who have used oral contraceptives prior to pregnancy. Studies also do not suggest a teratogenic effect, particularly in so far as cardiac anomalies and limb-reduction defects are concerned, when taken inadvertently during early pregnancy. GENERESS Fe use should be discontinued if pregnancy is confirmed.



 The administration of oral contraceptives to induce withdrawal bleeding should not be used as a test for pregnancy [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



    5.10 Depression



  Women with a history of depression should be carefully observed and GENERESS Fe discontinued if depression recurs to a serious degree.



    5.11 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  The use of COCs may change the results of some laboratory tests, such as coagulation factors, lipids, glucose tolerance, and binding proteins. Women on thyroid hormone replacement therapy may need increased doses of thyroid hormone because serum concentrations of thyroid-binding globulin increase with use of COCs.



    5.12 Monitoring



  A woman who is taking COCs should have a yearly visit with her healthcare provider for a blood pressure check and for other indicated healthcare.



    5.13 Other Conditions



  In women with hereditary angioedema, exogenous estrogens may induce or exacerbate symptoms of angioedema.  Chloasma may occasionally occur, especially in women with a history of chloasma gravidarum. Women with a tendency to chloasma should avoid exposure to the sun or ultraviolet radiation while taking COCs.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
