<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="genotropin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Other common somatropin-related adverse reactions include injection site reactions/rashes and lipoatrophy (  6.1  ) and headaches (  6.3  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Most Serious and/or Most Frequently Observed Adverse Reactions

  This list presents the most serious  b  and/or most frequently observed  a  adverse reactions during treatment with somatropin:



 *    b  Sudden death in pediatric patients with Prader-Willi syndrome with risk factors including severe obesity, history of upper airway obstruction or sleep apnea and unidentified respiratory infection [see  Contraindications (4.2)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *    b  Intracranial tumors, in particular meningiomas, in teenagers/young adults treated with radiation to the head as children for a first neoplasm and somatropin [see  Contraindications (4.3)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *    a  ,  b  Glucose intolerance including impaired glucose tolerance/impaired fasting glucose as well as overt diabetes mellitus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *    b  Intracranial hypertension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *    b  Significant diabetic retinopathy [see  Contraindications (4.4)  ]  
 *    b  Slipped capital femoral epiphysis in pediatric patients [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *    b  Progression of preexisting scoliosis in pediatric patients [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *    a  Fluid retention manifested by edema, arthralgia, myalgia, nerve compression syndromes including carpal tunnel syndrome/paraesthesias [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *    a  Unmasking of latent central hypothyroidism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *    a  Injection site reactions/rashes and lipoatrophy (as well as rare generalized hypersensitivity reactions) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *    b  Pancreatitis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)  ]  
      6.2 Clinical Trials Experience
   Because clinical trials are conducted under varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed during the clinical trials performed with one somatropin formulation cannot always be directly compared to the rates observed during the clinical trials performed with a second somatropin formulation, and may not reflect the adverse reaction rates observed in practice.



     Clinical Trials in children with GHD  



 In clinical studies with GENOTROPIN in pediatric GHD patients, the following events were reported infrequently: injection site reactions, including pain or burning associated with the injection, fibrosis, nodules, rash, inflammation, pigmentation, or bleeding; lipoatrophy; headache; hematuria; hypothyroidism; and mild hyperglycemia.



     Clinical Trials in PWS  



 In two clinical studies with GENOTROPIN in pediatric patients with Prader-Willi syndrome, the following drug-related events were reported: edema, aggressiveness, arthralgia, benign intracranial hypertension, hair loss, headache, and myalgia.



     Clinical Trials in children with SGA  



 In clinical studies of 273 pediatric patients born small for gestational age treated with GENOTROPIN, the following clinically significant events were reported: mild transient hyperglycemia, one patient with benign intracranial hypertension, two patients with central precocious puberty, two patients with jaw prominence, and several patients with aggravation of preexisting scoliosis, injection site reactions, and self-limited progression of pigmented nevi. Anti-hGH antibodies were not detected in any of the patients treated with GENOTROPIN.



     Clinical Trials in children with Turner Syndrome  



 In two clinical studies with GENOTROPIN in pediatric patients with Turner syndrome, the most frequently reported adverse events were respiratory illnesses (influenza, tonsillitis, otitis, sinusitis), joint pain, and urinary tract infection. The only treatment-related adverse event that occurred in more than 1 patient was joint pain.



     Clinical Trials in children with Idiopathic Short Stature  



 In two open-label clinical studies with GENOTROPIN in pediatric patients with ISS, the most commonly encountered adverse events include upper respiratory tract infections, influenza, tonsillitis, nasopharyngitis, gastroenteritis, headaches, increased appetite, pyrexia, fracture, altered mood, and arthralgia. In one of the two studies, during Genotropin treatment, the mean IGF-1 standard deviation (SD) scores were maintained in the normal range. IGF-1 SD scores above +2 SD were observed as follows: 1 subject (3%), 10 subjects (30%) and 16 subjects (38%) in the untreated control, 0. 23 and the 0.47 mg/kg/week groups, respectively, had at least one measurement; while 0 subjects (0%), 2 subjects (7%) and 6 subjects (14%) had two or more consecutive IGF-1 measurements above +2 SD.



     Clinical Trials in adults with GHD  



 In clinical trials with GENOTROPIN in 1,145 GHD adults, the majority of the adverse events consisted of mild to moderate symptoms of fluid retention, including peripheral swelling, arthralgia, pain and stiffness of the extremities, peripheral edema, myalgia, paresthesia, and hypoesthesia. These events were reported early during therapy, and tended to be transient and/or responsive to dosage reduction.



 Table 1 displays the adverse events reported by 5% or more of adult GHD patients in clinical trials after various durations of treatment with GENOTROPIN. Also presented are the corresponding incidence rates of these adverse events in placebo patients during the 6-month double-blind portion of the clinical trials.



 Table 1 Adverse Events Reported by &gt;= 5% of 1,145 Adult GHD Patients During Clinical Trials of GENOTROPIN and Placebo, Grouped by Duration of Treatment 
                            Double Blind Phase  Open Label PhaseGENOTROPIN   
 Adverse Event              Placebo0-6 mo.n = 572% Patients  GENOTROPIN0-6 mo.n = 573% Patients  6-12 mo.n = 504% Patients  12-18 mo.n = 63% Patients  18-24 mo.n = 60% Patients   
  
   n = number of patients receiving treatment during the indicated period.% = percentage of patients who reported the event during the indicated period.     
  
 Swelling, peripheral             5.1             17.5              5.6               0               1.7         
 Arthralgia                       4.2             17.3              6.9              6.3              3.3         
 Upper respiratory infection       14.5             15.5             13.1             15.9             13.3         
 Pain, extremities                5.9             14.7              6.7              1.6              3.3         
 Edema, peripheral                2.6             10.8              3.0               0                0          
 Paresthesia                      1.9              9.6              2.2              3.2               0          
 Headache                         7.7              9.9              6.2               0                0          
 Stiffness of extremities         1.6              7.9              2.4              1.6               0          
 Fatigue                          3.8              5.8              4.6              6.3              1.7         
 Myalgia                          1.6              4.9              2.0              4.8              6.7         
 Back pain                        4.4              2.8              3.4              4.8              5.0         
                Post-Trial Extension Studies in Adults  
 

 In expanded post-trial extension studies, diabetes mellitus developed in 12 of 3,031 patients (0.4%) during treatment with GENOTROPIN. All 12 patients had predisposing factors, e.g., elevated glycated hemoglobin levels and/or marked obesity, prior to receiving GENOTROPIN. Of the 3,031 patients receiving GENOTROPIN, 61 (2%) developed symptoms of carpal tunnel syndrome, which lessened after dosage reduction or treatment interruption (52) or surgery (9). Other adverse events that have been reported include generalized edema and hypoesthesia.



     Anti-hGH Antibodies  



 As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to GENOTROPIN with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading. In the case of growth hormone, antibodies with binding capacities lower than 2 mg/mL have not been associated with growth attenuation. In a very small number of patients treated with somatropin, when binding capacity was greater than 2 mg/mL, interference with the growth response was observed.



 In 419 pediatric patients evaluated in clinical studies with GENOTROPIN lyophilized powder, 244 had been treated previously with GENOTROPIN or other growth hormone preparations and 175 had received no previous growth hormone therapy. Antibodies to growth hormone (anti-hGH antibodies) were present in six previously treated patients at baseline. Three of the six became negative for anti-hGH antibodies during 6 to 12 months of treatment with GENOTROPIN. Of the remaining 413 patients, eight (1.9%) developed detectable anti-hGH antibodies during treatment with GENOTROPIN; none had an antibody binding capacity &gt; 2 mg/L. There was no evidence that the growth response to GENOTROPIN was affected in these antibody-positive patients.



     Periplasmic Escherichia coli Peptides  



 Preparations of GENOTROPIN contain a small amount of periplasmic  Escherichia coli  peptides (PECP). Anti-PECP antibodies are found in a small number of patients treated with GENOTROPIN, but these appear to be of no clinical significance.



   6.3 Post-Marketing Experience

  Because these adverse events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The adverse events reported during post-marketing surveillance do not differ from those listed/discussed above in Sections 6.1 and 6.2 in children and adults.



 Leukemia has been reported in a small number of GHD children treated with somatropin, somatrem (methionylated rhGH) and GH of pituitary origin. It is uncertain whether these cases of leukemia are related to GH therapy, the pathology of GHD itself, or other associated treatments such as radiation therapy. On the basis of current evidence, experts have not been able to conclude that GH therapy  per se  was responsible for these cases of leukemia. The risk for children with GHD, if any, remains to be established  [see  Contraindications (4.3)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



 The following additional adverse reactions have been observed during the appropriate use of somatropin: headaches (children and adults), gynecomastia (children), and pancreatitis (children and adults,  see  Warnings and Precautions [5.14]    ).



 New-onset type 2 diabetes mellitus has been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Acute Critical Illness: Potential benefit of treatment continuation should be weighed against the potential risk (  5.1  ).



 *  Prader-Willi syndrome in Children: Evaluate for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiation of treatment.Discontinue treatment if these signs occur (  5.2  ). 
 *  Neoplasm: Monitor patients with preexisting tumors for progression or recurrence. Increased risk of a second neoplasm in childhood cancer survivors treated with somatropin in particular meningiomas in patients treated with radiation to the head for their first neoplasm (  5.3  ). 
 *  Impaired Glucose Tolerance and Diabetes Mellitus: May be unmasked.Periodically monitor glucose levels in all patients. Doses of concurrent antihyperglycemic drugs in diabetics may require adjustment (  5.4  ). 
 *  Intracranial Hypertension: Exclude preexisting papilledema. May develop and is usually reversible after discontinuation or dose reduction (  5.5  ). 
 *  Fluid Retention (i.e., edema, arthralgia, carpal tunnel syndrome - especially in adults): May occur frequently. Reduce dose as necessary (  5.6  ). 
 *  Hypopituitarism: Closely monitor other hormone replacement therapies (  5.7  ). 
 *  Hypothyroidism: May first become evident or worsen (  5.8  ). 
 *  Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis: May develop. Evaluate children with the onset of a limp or hip/knee pain (  5.9  ). 
 *  Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis: May develop (  5.10  ) 
 *  Pancreatitis: Consider pancreatitis in patients with persistent severe abdominal pain (  5.14  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Critical Illness



  Increased mortality in patients with acute critical illness due to complications following open heart surgery, abdominal surgery or multiple accidental trauma, or those with acute respiratory failure has been reported after treatment with pharmacologic  amounts of somatropin [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ].  The safety of continuing somatropin treatment in patients receiving replacement  doses for approved indications who concurrently develop these illnesses has not been established. Therefore, the potential benefit of treatment continuation with somatropin in patients having acute critical illnesses should be weighed against the potential risk.



    5.2 Prader-Willi Syndrome in Children



  There have been reports of fatalities after initiating therapy with somatropin in pediatric patients with Prader-Willi syndrome who had one or more of the following risk factors: severe obesity, history of upper airway obstruction or sleep apnea, or unidentified respiratory infection. Male patients with one or more of these factors may be at greater risk than females. Patients with Prader-Willi syndrome should be evaluated for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiation of treatment with somatropin. If during treatment with somatropin, patients show signs of upper airway obstruction (including onset of or increased snoring) and/or new onset sleep apnea, treatment should be interrupted. All patients with Prader-Willi syndrome treated with somatropin should also have effective weight control and be monitored for signs of respiratory infection, which should be diagnosed as early as possible and treated aggressively [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ].  



    5.3 Neoplasms



   In childhood cancer survivors who were treated with radiation to the brain/head for their first neoplasm and who developed subsequent GHD and were treated with somatropin, an increased risk of a second neoplasm has been reported. Intracranial tumors, in particular meningiomas, were the most common of these second neoplasms. In adults, it is unknown whether there is any relationship between somatropin replacement therapy and CNS tumor recurrence [ see  Contraindications (4.3)    ].  



  Monitor all patients with a history of GHD secondary to an intracranial neoplasm routinely while on somatropin therapy for progression or recurrence of the tumor.  



  Because children with certain rare genetic causes of short stature have an increased risk of developing malignancies, practitioners should thoroughly consider the risks and benefits of starting somatropin in these patients. If treatment with somatropin is initiated, these patients should be carefully monitored for development of neoplasms.  



  Monitor patients on somatropin therapy carefully for increased growth, or potential malignant changes, of preexisting nevi.  



    5.4 Impaired Glucose Tolerance and Diabetes Mellitus



  Treatment with somatropin may decrease insulin sensitivity, particularly at higher doses in susceptible patients. As a result, previously undiagnosed impaired glucose tolerance and overt diabetes mellitus may be unmasked during somatropin treatment. New-onset Type 2 diabetes mellitus has been reported. Therefore, glucose levels should be monitored periodically in all patients treated with somatropin, especially in those with risk factors for diabetes mellitus, such as obesity, Turner syndrome, or a family history of diabetes mellitus. Patients with preexisting type 1 or type 2 diabetes mellitus or impaired glucose tolerance should be monitored closely during somatropin therapy. The doses of antihyperglycemic drugs (i.e., insulin or oral/injectable agents) may require adjustment when somatropin therapy is instituted in these patients.



    5.5 Intracranial Hypertension



  Intracranial hypertension (IH) with papilledema, visual changes, headache, nausea and/or vomiting has been reported in a small number of patients treated with somatropin products. Symptoms usually occurred within the first eight (8) weeks after the initiation of somatropin therapy. In all reported cases, IH-associated signs and symptoms rapidly resolved after cessation of therapy or a reduction of the somatropin dose. Funduscopic examination should be performed routinely before initiating treatment with somatropin to exclude preexisting papilledema, and periodically during the course of somatropin therapy. If papilledema is observed by funduscopy during somatropin treatment, treatment should be stopped. If somatropin-induced IH is diagnosed, treatment with somatropin can be restarted at a lower dose after IH-associated signs and symptoms have resolved. Patients with Turner syndrome and Prader-Willi syndrome may be at increased risk for the development of IH.



    5.6 Fluid Retention



  Fluid retention during somatropin replacement therapy in adults may occur. Clinical manifestations of fluid retention are usually transient and dose dependent.



    5.7 Hypopituitarism



  Patients with hypopituitarism (multiple pituitary hormone deficiencies) should have their other hormonal replacement treatments closely monitored during somatropin treatment.



    5.8 Hypothyroidism



  Undiagnosed/untreated hypothyroidism may prevent an optimal response to somatropin, in particular, the growth response in children. Patients with Turner syndrome have an inherently increased risk of developing autoimmune thyroid disease and primary hypothyroidism. In patients with growth hormone deficiency, central (secondary) hypothyroidism may first become evident or worsen during somatropin treatment. Therefore, patients treated with somatropin should have periodic thyroid function tests and thyroid hormone replacement therapy should be initiated or appropriately adjusted when indicated.



    5.9 Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphyses in Pediatric Patients



  Slipped capital femoral epiphyses may occur more frequently in patients with endocrine disorders (including GHD and Turner syndrome) or in patients undergoing rapid growth. Any pediatric patient with the onset of a limp or complaints of hip or knee pain during somatropin therapy should be carefully evaluated.



    5.10 Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis in Pediatric Patients



  Progression of scoliosis can occur in patients who experience rapid growth. Because somatropin increases growth rate, patients with a history of scoliosis who are treated with somatropin should be monitored for progression of scoliosis. However, somatropin has not been shown to increase the occurrence of scoliosis. Skeletal abnormalities including scoliosis are commonly seen in untreated Turner syndrome patients. Scoliosis is also commonly seen in untreated patients with Prader-Willi syndrome. Physicians should be alert to these abnormalities, which may manifest during somatropin therapy.



    5.11 Otitis Media and Cardiovascular Disorders in Turner Syndrome



  Patients with Turner syndrome should be evaluated carefully for otitis media and other ear disorders since these patients have an increased risk of ear and hearing disorders. Somatropin treatment may increase the occurrence of otitis media in patients with Turner syndrome. In addition, patients with Turner syndrome should be monitored closely for cardiovascular disorders (e.g., stroke, aortic aneurysm/dissection, hypertension) as these patients are also at risk for these conditions.



    5.12 Local and Systemic Reactions



  When somatropin is administered subcutaneously at the same site over a long period of time, tissue atrophy may result. This can be avoided by rotating the injection site [see  Dosage and Administration. (2.3)  ].  



 As with any protein, local or systemic allergic reactions may occur. Parents/Patients should be informed that such reactions are possible and that prompt medical attention should be sought if allergic reactions occur.



    5.13 Laboratory Tests



  Serum levels of inorganic phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase, parathyroid hormone (PTH) and IGF-I may increase during somatropin therapy.



    5.14 Pancreatitis



  Cases of pancreatitis have been reported rarely in children and adults receiving somatropin treatment, with some evidence supporting a greater risk in children compared with adults. Published literature indicates that girls who have Turner syndrome may be at greater risk than other somatropin-treated children. Pancreatitis should be considered in any somatropin-treated patient, especially a child, who develops persistent severe abdominal pain.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
