<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="genvoya" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse drug reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Severe Acute Exacerbations of Hepatitis B [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Immune Reconstitution Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Bone Loss and Mineralization Defects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reaction (incidence greater than or equal to 10%, all grades) is nausea. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc. at 1-800-GILEAD-5 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Clinical Trials in Treatment Naive Adults  



 The primary safety assessment of GENVOYA was based on Week 96 pooled data from 1733 subjects in two randomized, double-blind, active-controlled trials, Study 104 and Study 111, in antiretroviral treatment-naive HIV-1 infected adult subjects. A total of 866 subjects received one tablet of GENVOYA once daily  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 The most common adverse reaction (all Grades) reported in at least 10% of subjects in the GENVOYA group was nausea. The proportion of subjects who discontinued treatment with GENVOYA or STRIBILD  (r)  due to adverse events, regardless of severity, was 1% and 2%, respectively. Table 2 displays the frequency of adverse reactions (all Grades) greater than or equal to 5% in the GENVOYA group.



 Table 2 Adverse ReactionsFrequencies of adverse reactions are based on all adverse events attributed to study drugs by the investigator. (All Grades) Reported in &gt;= 5% of HIV-1 Infected Treatment Naive Adults Receiving GENVOYA in Studies 104 and 111 (Week 96 analysis) 
                                                                   GENVOYAN=866         STRIBILDN=867       
  
 GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                                                                                 
   Diarrhea                                                             7%                    9%            
   Nausea                                                              10%                   13%            
 GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS                                                       
   Fatigue                                                              5%                    4%            
 NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                                   
   Headache                                                             6%                    5%            
         The majority of events presented in Table 2 occurred at severity Grade 1.
 

     Clinical Trials in Virologically Suppressed Adults  



 The safety of GENVOYA in virologically-suppressed adults was based on Week 48 data from 959 subjects in a randomized, open-label, active-controlled trial (Study 109) in which virologically-suppressed subjects were switched from a TDF-containing combination regimen to GENVOYA. Overall, the safety profile of GENVOYA in subjects in this study was similar to that of treatment naive subjects  [see  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .



     Clinical Trials in Adult Subjects with Renal Impairment  



 In an open-label trial (Study 112), 248 HIV-1 infected subjects with eGFR of 30 to 69 mL per minute (by Cockcroft-Gault method) were treated with GENVOYA for a median duration of 43 weeks. Of these subjects, 64% had previously been on a stable TDF-containing regimen. Among the 80 subjects with baseline eGFR less than 50 mL per minute receiving GENVOYA, two subjects developed worsening renal impairment and discontinued treatment. One subject with an eGFR over 50 mL per minute developed transient acute renal failure. Otherwise, the safety profile of GENVOYA in subjects in this study was similar to that of subjects with normal renal function  [see  Clinical Studies (14.4)  ]  .



     Renal Laboratory Tests  



     Treatment Naive Adults:  



 Cobicistat (a component of GENVOYA) has been shown to increase serum creatinine due to inhibition of tubular secretion of creatinine without affecting glomerular filtration  [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  . Increases in serum creatinine occurred by Week 2 of treatment and remained stable through 96 weeks.



 In two 96-week randomized, controlled trials in a total of 1733 treatment naive adults with a median baseline eGFR of 115 mL per minute, mean serum creatinine increased by less than 0.1 mg per dL in the GENVOYA group and by 0.1 mg per dL in the STRIBILD group from baseline to Week 96. Median urine protein-to-creatinine ratio (UPCR) was 44 mg per gram at baseline and 42 mg per gram at Week 96 in the GENVOYA group. Median UPCR was 44 mg per gram at baseline and 54 mg per gram at Week 96 in those receiving STRIBILD.



     Virologically Suppressed Adults:  



 In a study of 1436 virologically-suppressed TDF-treated adults with a mean baseline eGFR of 112 mL per minute who were randomized to continue their treatment regimen or switch to GENVOYA, at Week 48 mean serum creatinine was similar to baseline for both those continuing baseline treatment and those switching to GENVOYA. Median UPCR was 61 mg per gram at baseline and 46 mg per gram at Week 48 in subjects switching to GENVOYA. In subjects remaining on their initial regimen, UPCR was 60 mg per gram at baseline and 63 mg per gram at Week 48.



     Adult Subjects with Renal Impairment:  



 In a 24-week trial in 248 subjects with renal impairment (baseline eGFR 30 to 69 mL per minute) who received GENVOYA, mean serum creatinine was 1.5 mg per dL at both baseline and Week 24. Median UPCR was 161 mg per gram at baseline and 93 mg per gram at Week 24.



     Bone Mineral Density Effects  



     Treatment Naive Adults:  



 In the pooled analysis of Studies 104 and 111, bone mineral density (BMD) from baseline to Week 96 was assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) to compare the bone safety of TAF to that of TDF when administered as GENVOYA or STRIBILD, respectively. Mean BMD decreased from baseline to Week 96 by -0.96% with GENVOYA compared to -2.79% with STRIBILD at the lumbar spine and -0.67% compared to -3.28% at the total hip. BMD declines of 5% or greater at the lumbar spine were experienced by 12% of GENVOYA subjects and 26% of STRIBILD subjects. BMD declines of 7% or greater at the femoral neck were experienced by 11% of GENVOYA subjects and 26% of STRIBILD subjects. The long-term clinical significance of these BMD changes is not known.



     Virologically Suppressed Adults:  



 In Study 109, TDF-treated subjects were randomized to continue their TDF-based regimen or switch to GENVOYA; changes in BMD from baseline to Week 48 were assessed by DXA. Mean BMD increased in subjects who switched to GENVOYA (1.86% lumbar spine, 1.95% total hip) and decreased slightly in subjects who continued their baseline regimen (-0.11% lumbar spine, -0.14% total hip). BMD declines of 5% or greater at the lumbar spine were experienced by 1% of GENVOYA subjects and 6% of subjects who continued their TDF-based regimen. BMD declines of 7% or greater at the femoral neck were experienced by 1% of GENVOYA subjects and 4% of subjects who continued their TDF-based regimen.



     Laboratory Abnormalities:  



 The frequency of laboratory abnormalities (Grades 3-4) occurring in at least 2% of subjects receiving GENVOYA in Studies 104 and 111 are presented in Table 3.



 Table 3 Laboratory Abnormalities (Grades 3-4) Reported in &gt;= 2% of Subjects Receiving GENVOYA in Studies 104 and 111 (Week 96 analysis) 
 Laboratory Parameter Abnormality                          GENVOYAN=866               STRIBILDN=867         
  
 Amylase                                                        2%                         4%               
 AST                                                            2%                         2%               
 Creatine Kinase (&gt;=10.0 * ULN)                                 9%                         7%               
 Urine RBC (Hematuria) (&gt;75 RBC/HPF)                            3%                         3%               
 LDL-cholesterol (fasted) (&gt;190 mg/dL)                          8%                         4%               
 Total cholesterol (fasted) (&gt;300mg/dL)                         3%                         2%               
             Serum Lipids:  
 

 Subjects receiving GENVOYA experienced greater increases in serum lipids compared to those receiving STRIBILD.



 Changes from baseline in total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, triglycerides and total cholesterol to HDL ratio are presented in Table 4.



 Table 4 Lipid Values, Mean Change from Baseline, Reported in Subjects Receiving GENVOYA or STRIBILD in Studies 104 and 111Excludes subjects who received lipid lowering agents during the treatment period. 
                                  GENVOYAN=866       STRIBILDN=867      
 Baseline                           Week 96             Baseline            Week 96         
 mg/dL                               Change              mg/dL               Change         
  
 Total Cholesterol (fasted)        162[N=692]          +31[N=692]          166[N=679]          +15[N=679]       
 HDL-cholesterol (fasted)          46[N=692]           +7[N=692]           46[N=679]           +4[N=679]        
 LDL-cholesterol (fasted)          103[N=688]          +18[N=688]          107[N=680]          +7[N=680]        
 Triglycerides (fasted)            113[N=692]          +31[N=692]          115[N=679]          +13[N=679]       
 Total Cholesterol to HDL ratio      3.7[N=692]          0.2[N=692]          3.8[N=679]           0[N=679]        
               Clinical Trials in Pediatric Subjects:  
 

 The safety of GENVOYA in HIV-1 infected, treatment naive pediatric subjects aged 12 to less than 18 years was evaluated through 24 weeks in an open-label clinical trial (Study 106)  [see  Clinical Studies (14.5)  ]  . The safety profile in 23 adolescent subjects who received treatment with GENVOYA was similar to that in adults. One 13 year old female subject developed unexplained uveitis while receiving GENVOYA that resolved and did not require discontinuation of GENVOYA.



 Among the 23 pediatric subjects receiving GENVOYA for 24 weeks, mean BMD increased from baseline to Week 24, + 1.7% at the lumbar spine and + 0.8% for the total body less head. Mean changes from baseline BMD Z-scores were -0.10 for lumbar spine and -0.11 for total body less head at Week 24. Two GENVOYA subjects had significant (greater than 4%) lumbar spine BMD loss at Week 24.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B

    WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B  

    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs in combination with other antiretrovirals   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .  



   GENVOYA is not approved for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection and the safety and efficacy of GENVOYA have not been established in patients coinfected with human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV-1) and HBV. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and have discontinued products containing emtricitabine and/or tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF), and may occur with discontinuation of GENVOYA. Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and discontinue GENVOYA. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs. (5.1) 
 *  GENVOYA is not approved for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and have discontinued products containing emtricitabine and/or tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF), and may occur with discontinuation of GENVOYA. Hepatic function should be monitored closely in these patients. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Risk of adverse reactions or loss of virologic response due to drug interactions: The concomitant use of GENVOYA and other drugs may result in known or potentially significant drug interactions, some of which may lead to loss of therapeutic effect of GENVOYA and possible development of resistance; and possible clinically significant adverse reactions from greater exposures of concomitant drugs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat: Observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Immune reconstitution syndrome: May necessitate further evaluation and treatment. (  5.5  ) 
 *  New onset or worsening renal impairment: Assess creatinine clearance, urine glucose, and urine protein in all patients before initiating GENVOYA therapy and monitor during therapy. Monitor serum phosphorus in patients with chronic kidney disease. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Bone loss and mineralization defects: Consider monitoring BMD in patients with a history of pathologic fracture or other risk factors of osteoporosis or bone loss. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs in combination with other antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged nucleoside exposure may be risk factors. Particular caution should be exercised when administering nucleoside analogs to any patient with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors. Since TAF and emtricitabine are nucleos(t)ide analogs, treatment with GENVOYA should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.2 Severe Acute Exacerbation of Hepatitis B in Patients Coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV



  Patients with HIV-1 should be tested for the presence of hepatitis B virus (HBV) before initiating antiretroviral therapy [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ]  . GENVOYA is not approved for the treatment of chronic HBV infection and the safety and efficacy of GENVOYA have not been established in patients coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV.



 Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B (e.g., liver decompensation and liver failure) have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and have discontinued products containing emtricitabine and/or tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF), and may occur with discontinuation of GENVOYA. Patients coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV who discontinue GENVOYA should be closely monitored with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months after stopping treatment. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted, especially in patients with advanced liver disease or cirrhosis, since post-treatment exacerbation of hepatitis may lead to hepatic decompensation and liver failure.



    5.3 Risk of Adverse Reactions or Loss of Virologic Response Due to Drug Interactions



  The concomitant use of GENVOYA and other drugs may result in known or potentially significant drug interactions, some of which may lead to [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.5)  ]:  



 *  Loss of therapeutic effect of GENVOYA and possible development of resistance. 
 *  Possible clinically significant adverse reactions from greater exposures of concomitant drugs. 
    See  Table 5  for steps to prevent or manage these possible and known significant drug interactions, including dosing recommendations. Consider the potential for drug interactions prior to and during GENVOYA therapy; review concomitant medications during GENVOYA therapy; and monitor for the adverse reactions associated with the concomitant drugs.
 

    5.4 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution or accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.5 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including emtricitabine, a component of GENVOYA. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections [such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia (PCP), or tuberculosis], which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.6 New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment



  Renal impairment, including cases of acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome (renal tubular injury with severe hypophosphatemia), has been reported with the use of tenofovir prodrugs in both animal toxicology studies and human trials. In clinical trials of GENVOYA, there have been no cases of Fanconi syndrome or Proximal Renal Tubulopathy (PRT). In clinical trials of GENVOYA in treatment naive subjects and in virologically suppressed subjects switched to GENVOYA with eGFRs greater than 50 mL per minute, renal serious adverse events or discontinuations due to renal adverse reactions were encountered in less than 1% of participants treated with GENVOYA. In a study of virologically suppressed subjects with baseline eGFRs between 30 and 69 mL per minute treated with GENVOYA for a median duration of 43 weeks, GENVOYA was permanently discontinued due to worsening renal function in two of 80 (3%) subjects with a baseline eGFR between 30 and 50 mL per minute [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . GENVOYA is not recommended in patients with estimated creatinine clearance below 30 mL per minute because data in this population are insufficient.



 Patients taking tenofovir prodrugs who have impaired renal function and those taking nephrotoxic agents including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs are at increased risk of developing renal-related adverse reactions.



 Estimated creatinine clearance, urine glucose and urine protein should be assessed before initiating GENVOYA therapy and should be monitored during therapy in all patients. Serum phosphorus should be monitored in patients with chronic kidney disease because these patients are at greater risk of developing Fanconi syndrome on tenofovir prodrugs. Discontinue GENVOYA in patients who develop clinically significant decreases in renal function or evidence of Fanconi syndrome.



 Cobicistat, a component of GENVOYA, produces elevations of serum creatinine due to inhibition of tubular secretion of creatinine without affecting glomerular filtration [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . The elevation is typically seen within 2 weeks of starting therapy and is reversible after discontinuation. Patients who experience a confirmed increase in serum creatinine of greater than 0.4 mg per dL from baseline should be closely monitored for renal safety.



    5.7 Bone Loss and Mineralization Defects



   Bone Mineral Density (BMD):  



 In animal toxicology studies and human clinical trials, TAF and tenofovir have been associated with decreases in bone mineral density and increases in biochemical markers of bone metabolism suggestive of increased bone turnover. In clinical trials in HIV-1 infected treatment-naive adults, a significant decline in bone mineral density was observed in 15% of subjects treated with GENVOYA [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . The long-term clinical significance of these changes has not been established.



 Assessment of BMD should be considered for adults and pediatric patients treated with GENVOYA who have a history of pathologic bone fracture or other risk factors for osteoporosis or bone loss. Calcium and vitamin D supplementation may be beneficial for all patients. If bone abnormalities are suspected then appropriate consultation should be obtained.



    Mineralization Defects:  



 Cases of osteomalacia associated with proximal renal tubulopathy, manifested as bone pain or pain in extremities and which may contribute to fractures, have been reported in association with the use of TDF-containing products. Hypophosphatemia and osteomalacia secondary to proximal renal tubulopathy have occurred in patients at risk of renal dysfunction who present with persistent or worsening bone or muscle symptoms while receiving products containing TDF [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  . While not observed in clinical studies of GENVOYA, the risk of osteomalacia with GENVOYA is not known.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
