<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="geodon" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice the incidence for placebo) were  :  



 *  : Somnolence, respiratory tract infection. ( ) Schizophrenia   6.1   
 *  : Somnolence, extrapyramidal symptoms, dizziness, akathisia, abnormal vision, asthenia, vomiting. ( ) Manic and Mixed Episodes Associated with Bipolar Disorder   6.1   
 *  (&gt;=5% and at least twice the lowest intramuscular ziprasidone group): Headache, nausea, somnolence. ( ) Intramuscular administration   6.1   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Clinical trials for oral ziprasidone included approximately 5700 patients and/or normal subjects exposed to one or more doses of ziprasidone. Of these 5700, over 4800 were patients who participated in multiple-dose effectiveness trials, and their experience corresponded to approximately 1831 patient-years. These patients include: (1) 4331 patients who participated in multiple-dose trials, predominantly in schizophrenia, representing approximately 1698 patient-years of exposure as of February 5, 2000; and (2) 472 patients who participated in bipolar mania trials representing approximately 133 patient-years of exposure. An additional 127 patients with bipolar disorder participated in a long-term maintenance treatment study representing approximately 74.7 patient-years of exposure to ziprasidone. The conditions and duration of treatment with ziprasidone included open-label and double-blind studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, and short-term and longer-term exposure.



 Clinical trials for intramuscular ziprasidone included 570 patients and/or normal subjects who received one or more injections of ziprasidone. Over 325 of these subjects participated in trials involving the administration of multiple doses.



 Adverse reactions during exposure were obtained by collecting voluntarily reported adverse experiences, as well as results of physical examinations, vital signs, weights, laboratory analyses, ECGs, and results of ophthalmologic examinations.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse reaction of the type listed. A reaction was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



     Adverse Findings Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials with Oral Ziprasidone  



 The following findings are based on the short-term placebo-controlled premarketing trials for schizophrenia (a pool of two 6-week, and two 4-week fixed-dose trials) and bipolar mania (a pool of two 3-week flexible-dose trials) in which ziprasidone was administered in doses ranging from 10 to 200 mg/day.



     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Short Term-Placebo-Controlled Trials  



 The following adverse reactions were the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of ziprasidone (incidence of 5% or greater) and not observed at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients (ziprasidone incidence at least twice that for placebo):



 Schizophrenia trials  (see )  Table 11    



 *  Somnolence 
 *  Respiratory Tract Infection 
    Bipolar trials  (see )  Table 12    
 

 *  Somnolence 
 *  Extrapyramidal Symptoms which includes the following adverse reaction terms: extrapyramidal syndrome, hypertonia, dystonia, dyskinesia, hypokinesia, tremor, paralysis and twitching. None of these adverse reactions occurred individually at an incidence greater than 10% in bipolar mania trials. 
 *  Dizziness which includes the adverse reaction terms dizziness and lightheadedness. 
 *  Akathisia 
 *  Abnormal Vision 
 *  Asthenia 
 *  Vomiting 
        SCHIZOPHRENIA  
 

     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials of Oral Ziprasidone  



 Approximately 4.1% (29/702) of ziprasidone-treated patients in short-term, placebo-controlled studies discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction, compared with about 2.2% (6/273) on placebo. The most common reaction associated with dropout was rash, including 7 dropouts for rash among ziprasidone patients (1%) compared to no placebo patients  [see ].  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)    



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More Among Ziprasidone-Treated Patients in Short-Term, Oral, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



 Table 11 enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred during acute therapy (up to 6 weeks) in predominantly patients with schizophrenia, including only those reactions that occurred in 2% or more of patients treated with ziprasidone and for which the incidence in patients treated with ziprasidone was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 Table 11: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence In Short-Term Oral Placebo-Controlled Trials - Schizophrenia 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction   
 Body System/Adverse Reaction                   Ziprasidone (N=702)               Placebo (N=273)           
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Asthenia                                              5                               3                  
   Accidental Injury                                     4                               2                  
   Chest Pain                                            3                               2                  
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
   Tachycardia                                           2                               1                  
   Digestive                                                                                                
   Nausea                                                10                              7                  
   Constipation                                          9                               8                  
   Dyspepsia                                             8                               7                  
   Diarrhea                                              5                               4                  
   Dry Mouth                                             4                               2                  
   Anorexia                                              2                               1                  
   Nervous                                                                                                  
   Extrapyramidal Symptoms                               14                              8                  
   Somnolence                                            14                              7                  
   Akathisia                                             8                               7                  
   Dizziness                                             8                               6                  
   Respiratory                                                                                              
   Respiratory Tract Infection                           8                               3                  
   Rhinitis                                              4                               2                  
   Cough Increased                                       3                               1                  
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                      
   Rash                                                  4                               3                  
   Fungal Dermatitis                                     2                               1                  
   Special Senses                                                                                           
   Abnormal Vision                                       3                               2                  
             Dose Dependency of Adverse Reactions in Short-Term, Fixed-Dose, Placebo-Controlled Trials  
 

 An analysis for dose response in the schizophrenia 4-study pool revealed an apparent relation of adverse reaction to dose for the following reactions: asthenia, postural hypotension, anorexia, dry mouth, increased salivation, arthralgia, anxiety, dizziness, dystonia, hypertonia, somnolence, tremor, rhinitis, rash, and abnormal vision  .  



   - The incidence of reported EPS (which included the adverse reaction terms extrapyramidal syndrome, hypertonia, dystonia, dyskinesia, hypokinesia, tremor, paralysis and twitching) for ziprasidone-treated patients in the short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia trials was 14% vs. 8% for placebo. Objectively collected data from those trials on the Simpson-Angus Rating Scale (for EPS) and the Barnes Akathisia Scale (for akathisia) did not generally show a difference between ziprasidone and placebo.  Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS)  



   Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.  Dystonia    - Class Effect:  



   - Ziprasidone is associated with orthostatic hypotension [ ]  Vital Sign Changes    see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    



   Ziprasidone is associated with an increase in the QTc interval . In the schizophrenia trials, ziprasidone was associated with a mean increase in heart rate of 1.4 beats per minute compared to a 0.2 beats per minute decrease among placebo patients.  ECG Changes -    [see ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Oral Ziprasidone  



 Following is a list of COSTART terms that reflect treatment-emergent adverse reactions as defined in the introduction to the section reported by patients treated with ziprasidone in schizophrenia trials at multiple doses &gt;4 mg/day within the database of 3834 patients. All reported reactions are included except those already listed in Table 11 or elsewhere in labeling, those reaction terms that were so general as to be uninformative, reactions reported only once and that did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life-threatening, reactions that are part of the illness being treated or are otherwise common as background reactions, and reactions considered unlikely to be drug-related. It is important to emphasize that, although the reactions reported occurred during treatment with ziprasidone, they were not necessarily caused by it.  ADVERSE REACTIONS  



 Adverse reactions are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions:



 adverse reactions occurring in at least 1/100 patients (&gt;=1.0% of patients) (only those not already listed in the tabulated results from placebo-controlled trials appear in this listing);  Frequent -  



 adverse reactions occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients (in 0.1-1.0% of patients)  Infrequent -  



 - adverse reactions occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients (&lt;0.1% of patients).  Rare  




   Body as a Whole     
   Frequent       abdominal pain, flu syndrome, fever, accidental fall, face edema, chills, photosensitivity reaction, flank pain, hypothermia, motor vehicle accident   
   Cardiovascular System     
   Frequent       tachycardia, hypertension, postural hypotension                                         
   Infrequent     bradycardia, angina pectoris, atrial fibrillation                                       
   Rare           first degree AV block, bundle branch block, phlebitis, pulmonary embolus, cardiomegaly, cerebral infarct, cerebrovascular accident, deep thrombophlebitis, myocarditis, thrombophlebitis   
   Digestive System     
   Frequent       anorexia, vomiting                                                                      
   Infrequent     rectal hemorrhage, dysphagia, tongue edema                                              
   Rare           gum hemorrhage, jaundice, fecal impaction, gamma glutamyl transpeptidase increased, hematemesis, cholestatic jaundice, hepatitis, hepatomegaly, leukoplakia of mouth, fatty liver deposit, melena   
   Endocrine       
   Rare           hypothyroidism, hyperthyroidism, thyroiditis                                            
   Hemic and Lymphatic System     
   Infrequent     anemia, ecchymosis, leukocytosis, leukopenia, eosinophilia, lymphadenopathy             
   Rare           thrombocytopenia, hypochromic anemia, lymphocytosis, monocytosis, basophilia, lymphedema, polycythemia, thrombocythemia   
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders     
   Infrequent     thirst, transaminase increased, peripheral edema, hyperglycemia, creatine phosphokinase increased, alkaline phosphatase increased, hypercholesteremia, dehydration, lactic dehydrogenase increased, albuminuria, hypokalemia   
   Rare           BUN increased, creatinine increased, hyperlipemia, hypocholesteremia, hyperkalemia, hypochloremia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, hypoproteinemia, glucose tolerance decreased, gout, hyperchloremia, hyperuricemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemicreaction, hypomagnesemia, ketosis, respiratory alkalosis   
   Musculoskeletal System     
   Frequent       myalgia                                                                                 
   Infrequent     tenosynovitis                                                                           
   Rare           myopathy                                                                                
   Nervous System     
   Frequent       agitation, extrapyramidal syndrome, tremor, dystonia, hypertonia, dyskinesia, hostility, twitching, paresthesia, confusion, vertigo, hypokinesia, hyperkinesia, abnormal gait, oculogyric crisis, hypesthesia, ataxia, amnesia, cogwheel rigidity, delirium, hypotonia, akinesia, dysarthria, withdrawal syndrome, buccoglossal syndrome, choreoathetosis, diplopia, incoordination, neuropathy   
   Infrequent     paralysis                                                                               
   Rare           myoclonus, nystagmus, torticollis, circumoral paresthesia, opisthotonos, reflexes increased, trismus   
   Respiratory System     
   Frequent       dyspnea                                                                                 
   Infrequent     pneumonia, epistaxis                                                                    
   Rare           hemoptysis, laryngismus                                                                 
   Skin and Appendages     
   Infrequent     maculopapular rash, urticaria, alopecia, eczema, exfoliative dermatitis, contact dermatitis, vesiculobullous rash   
   Special Senses     
   Frequent       fungal dermatitis                                                                       
   Infrequent     conjunctivitis, dry eyes, tinnitus, blepharitis, cataract, photophobia                  
   Rare           eye hemorrhage, visual field defect, keratitis, keratoconjunctivitis                    
   Urogenital System     
   Infrequent     impotence, abnormal ejaculation, amenorrhea, hematuria, menorrhagia, female lactation, polyuria, urinary retention metrorrhagia, male sexual dysfunction, anorgasmia, glycosuria   
   Rare           gynecomastia, vaginal hemorrhage, nocturia, oliguria, female sexual dysfunction, uterine hemorrhage   
            BIPOLAR DISORDER  
 

     Acute Treatment of Manic or Mixed Episodes  



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in Short Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



 Approximately 6.5% (18/279) of ziprasidone-treated patients in short-term, placebo-controlled studies discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction, compared with about 3.7% (5/136) on placebo. The most common reactions associated with dropout in the ziprasidone-treated patients were akathisia, anxiety, depression, dizziness, dystonia, rash and vomiting, with 2 dropouts for each of these reactions among ziprasidone patients (1%) compared to one placebo patient each for dystonia and rash (1%) and no placebo patients for the remaining adverse reactions.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More Among Ziprasidone-Treated Patients in Short-Term, Oral, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



 Table 12 enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred during acute therapy (up to 3 weeks) in patients with bipolar mania, including only those reactions that occurred in 2% or more of patients treated with ziprasidone and for which the incidence in patients treated with ziprasidone was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 Table 12: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Incidence In Short-Term Oral Placebo-Controlled Trials - Manic and Mixed Episodes Associated with Bipolar Disorder 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction   
 Body System/Adverse Reaction                   Ziprasidone (N=279)               Placebo (N=136)           
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Headache                                              18                              17                 
   Asthenia                                              6                               2                  
   Accidental Injury                                     4                               1                  
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
   Hypertension                                          3                               2                  
   Digestive                                                                                                
   Nausea                                                10                              7                  
   Diarrhea                                              5                               4                  
   Dry Mouth                                             5                               4                  
   Vomiting                                              5                               2                  
   Increased Salivation                                  4                               0                  
   Tongue Edema                                          3                               1                  
   Dysphagia                                             2                               0                  
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                          
   Myalgia                                               2                               0                  
   Nervous                                                                                                  
   Somnolence                                            31                              12                 
   Extrapyramidal Symptoms                               31                              12                 
   Dizziness                                             16                              7                  
   Akathisia                                             10                              5                  
   Anxiety                                               5                               4                  
   Hypesthesia                                           2                               1                  
   Speech Disorder                                       2                               0                  
   Respiratory                                                                                              
   Pharyngitis                                           3                               1                  
   Dyspnea                                               2                               1                  
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                      
   Fungal Dermatitis                                     2                               1                  
   Special Senses                                                                                           
   Abnormal Vision                                       6                               3                  
         Explorations for interactions on the basis of gender did not reveal any clinically meaningful differences in the adverse reaction occurrence on the basis of this demographic factor.
 

     INTRAMUSCULAR ZIPRASIDONE  



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among Ziprasidone-Treated Patients in Short-Term Trials of Intramuscular Ziprasidone  



 Table 13 enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred during acute therapy with intramuscular ziprasidone in 1% or more of patients.



 In these studies, the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of intramuscular ziprasidone (incidence of 5% or greater) and observed at a rate on intramuscular ziprasidone (in the higher dose groups) at least twice that of the lowest intramuscular ziprasidone group were headache (13%), nausea (12%), and somnolence (20%).



 Table 13: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence In Short-Term Fixed-Dose Intramuscular Trials 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction   
 Body System/Adverse Reaction              Ziprasidone 2 mg (N=92)  Ziprasidone 10 mg (N=63)  Ziprasidone 20 mg (N=41)   
  
   Body as a Whole                                                
   Headache                                         3                     13                    5             
   Injection Site Pain                              9                     8                     7             
   Asthenia                                         2                     0                     0             
   Abdominal Pain                                   0                     2                     0             
   Flu Syndrome                                     1                     0                     0             
   Back Pain                                        1                     0                     0             
   Cardiovascular                                                 
   Postural Hypotension                             0                     0                     5             
   Hypertension                                     2                     0                     0             
   Bradycardia                                      0                     0                     2             
   Vasodilation                                     1                     0                     0             
   Digestive                                                      
   Nausea                                           4                     8                     12            
   Rectal Hemorrhage                                0                     0                     2             
   Diarrhea                                         3                     3                     0             
   Vomiting                                         0                     3                     0             
   Dyspepsia                                        1                     3                     2             
   Anorexia                                         0                     2                     0             
   Constipation                                     0                     0                     2             
   Tooth Disorder                                   1                     0                     0             
   Dry Mouth                                        1                     0                     0             
   Nervous                                                        
   Dizziness                                        3                     3                     10            
   Anxiety                                          2                     0                     0             
   Insomnia                                         3                     0                     0             
   Somnolence                                       8                     8                     20            
   Akathisia                                        0                     2                     0             
   Agitation                                        2                     2                     0             
   Extrapyramidal Syndrome                          2                     0                     0             
   Hypertonia                                       1                     0                     0             
   Cogwheel Rigidity                                1                     0                     0             
   Paresthesia                                      0                     2                     0             
   Personality Disorder                             0                     2                     0             
   Psychosis                                        1                     0                     0             
   Speech Disorder                                  0                     2                     0             
   Respiratory                                                    
   Rhinitis                                         1                     0                     0             
   Skin and Appendages                                            
   Furunculosis                                     0                     2                     0             
   Sweating                                         0                     0                     2             
   Urogenital                                                                           
   Dysmenorrhea                                     0                     2                     0             
   Priapism                                         1                     0                     0             
            6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of GEODON. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reaction reports not listed above that have been received since market introduction include rare occurrences of the following : Tachycardia, torsade de pointes (in the presence of multiple confounding factors), ; Swollen Tongue; Galactorrhea, priapism; Facial Droop, neuroleptic malignant syndrome, serotonin syndrome (alone or in combination with serotonergic medicinal products), tardive dyskinesia; Insomnia, mania/hypomania; Allergic reaction (such as allergic dermatitis, angioedema, orofacial edema, urticaria), rash; Enuresis, urinary incontinence; Postural hypotension, syncope.  Cardiac Disorders:    [see ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)      Digestive System Disorders:    Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:    Nervous System Disorders:    Psychiatric Disorders:    Skin and subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    Urogenital System Disorders:    Vascular Disorders:  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    WARNING:  INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  

    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of seventeen placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. GEODON (ziprasidone) is not approved for the treatment of patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis [ ]).

                                  see

                                      Warnings and Precautions (5.1)      



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death compared to placebo treatment ( ) 5.1 
 *  GEODON is not approved for elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis ( ) 5.1 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  : GEODON use should be avoided in patients with bradycardia, hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia, congenital prolongation of the QT interval, or in combination with other drugs that have demonstrated QT prolongation. ( ) QT Interval Prolongation   5.2   
 *  (NMS): Potentially fatal symptom complex has been reported with antipsychotic drugs. Manage with immediate discontinuation of drug and close monitoring. ( ) Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome   5.3   
 *  : May develop acutely or chronically. ( ) Tardive Dyskinesia   5.4   
 *  *  (DM): Monitor all patients for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients with DM risk factors should undergo blood glucose testing before and during treatment. ( ) Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus   5.5   
 *  Undesirable alterations have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. ( ) Dyslipidemia:   5.5   
 *  Weight gain has been reported. Monitor weight gain. ( ) Weight Gain:   5.5   
   : Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/ cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and weight gain. ( ) Metabolic Changes   5.5   
 *  : Discontinue in patients who develop a rash without an identified cause. ( ) Rash   5.6   
 *  : Use with caution in patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease. ( ) Orthostatic Hypotension   5.7   
 *  has been reported with antipsychotics. Patients with a pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) or a history of leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and should discontinue Geodon at the first sign of a decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors. ( ) Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis   5.8   
 *  : Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower seizure threshold. ( ) Seizures   5.9   
 *  : Patients should use caution when operating machinery. ( ) Potential for Cognitive and Motor impairment   5.12   
 *  : Closely supervise high-risk patients. ( ) Suicide   5.15   
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. GEODON is not approved for the treatment of dementia-related psychosis. [see ]  Boxed Warning      



    5.2 QT Prolongation and Risk of Sudden Death



  Ziprasidone use should be avoided in combination with other drugs that are known to prolong the QTc interval [ . Additionally, clinicians should be alert to the identification of other drugs that have been consistently observed to prolong the QTc interval. Such drugs should not be prescribed with ziprasidone. Ziprasidone should also be avoided in patients with congenital long QT syndrome and in patients with a history of cardiac arrhythmias see , ]  Contraindications (4.1)    Drug Interactions (7.4)     [see ].  Contraindications (4)    



 A study directly comparing the QT/QTc prolonging effect of oral ziprasidone with several other drugs effective in the treatment of schizophrenia was conducted in patient volunteers. In the first phase of the trial, ECGs were obtained at the time of maximum plasma concentration when the drug was administered alone. In the second phase of the trial, ECGs were obtained at the time of maximum plasma concentration while the drug was co-administered with an inhibitor of the CYP4503A4 metabolism of the drug.



 In the first phase of the study, the mean change in QTc from baseline was calculated for each drug, using a sample-based correction that removes the effect of heart rate on the QT interval. The mean increase in QTc from baseline for ziprasidone ranged from approximately 9 to 14 msec greater than for four of the comparator drugs (risperidone, olanzapine, quetiapine, and haloperidol), but was approximately 14 msec less than the prolongation observed for thioridazine.



 In the second phase of the study, the effect of ziprasidone on QTc length was not augmented by the presence of a metabolic inhibitor (ketoconazole 200 mg twice daily).



 In placebo-controlled trials, oral ziprasidone increased the QTc interval compared to placebo by approximately 10 msec at the highest recommended daily dose of 160 mg. In clinical trials with oral ziprasidone, the electrocardiograms of 2/2988 (0.06%) patients who received GEODON and 1/440 (0.23%) patients who received placebo revealed QTc intervals exceeding the potentially clinically relevant threshold of 500 msec. In the ziprasidone-treated patients, neither case suggested a role of ziprasidone. One patient had a history of prolonged QTc and a screening measurement of 489 msec; QTc was 503 msec during ziprasidone treatment. The other patient had a QTc of 391 msec at the end of treatment with ziprasidone and upon switching to thioridazine experienced QTc measurements of 518 and 593 msec.



 Some drugs that prolong the QT/QTc interval have been associated with the occurrence of torsade de pointes and with sudden unexplained death. The relationship of QT prolongation to torsade de pointes is clearest for larger increases (20 msec and greater) but it is possible that smaller QT/QTc prolongations may also increase risk, or increase it in susceptible individuals Although torsade de pointes has not been observed in association with the use of ziprasidone in premarketing studies and experience is too limited to rule out an increased risk, there have been rare post-marketing reports (in the presence of multiple confounding factors) . .   [see ]  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    



 A study evaluating the QT/QTc prolonging effect of intramuscular ziprasidone, with intramuscular haloperidol as a control, was conducted in patient volunteers. In the trial, ECGs were obtained at the time of maximum plasma concentration following two injections of ziprasidone (20 mg then 30 mg) or haloperidol (7.5 mg then 10 mg) given four hours apart. Note that a 30 mg dose of intramuscular ziprasidone is 50% higher than the recommended therapeutic dose. The mean change in QTc from baseline was calculated for each drug, using a sample-based correction that removes the effect of heart rate on the QT interval. The mean increase in QTc from baseline for ziprasidone was 4.6 msec following the first injection and 12.8 msec following the second injection. The mean increase in QTc from baseline for haloperidol was 6.0 msec following the first injection and 14.7 msec following the second injection. In this study, no patients had a QTc interval exceeding 500 msec.



 As with other antipsychotic drugs and placebo, sudden unexplained deaths have been reported in patients taking ziprasidone at recommended doses. The premarketing experience for ziprasidone did not reveal an excess risk of mortality for ziprasidone compared to other antipsychotic drugs or placebo, but the extent of exposure was limited, especially for the drugs used as active controls and placebo. Nevertheless, ziprasidone's larger prolongation of QTc length compared to several other antipsychotic drugs raises the possibility that the risk of sudden death may be greater for ziprasidone than for other available drugs for treating schizophrenia. This possibility needs to be considered in deciding among alternative drug products [see ].  Indications and Usage (1)    



 Certain circumstances may increase the risk of the occurrence of torsade de pointes and/or sudden death in association with the use of drugs that prolong the QTc interval, including (1) bradycardia; (2) hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia; (3) concomitant use of other drugs that prolong the QTc interval; and (4) presence of congenital prolongation of the QT interval.



 It is recommended that patients being considered for ziprasidone treatment who are at risk for significant electrolyte disturbances, hypokalemia in particular, have baseline serum potassium and magnesium measurements. Hypokalemia (and/or hypomagnesemia) may increase the risk of QT prolongation and arrhythmia. Hypokalemia may result from diuretic therapy, diarrhea, and other causes. Patients with low serum potassium and/or magnesium should be repleted with those electrolytes before proceeding with treatment. It is essential to periodically monitor serum electrolytes in patients for whom diuretic therapy is introduced during ziprasidone treatment. Persistently prolonged QTc intervals may also increase the risk of further prolongation and arrhythmia, but it is not clear that routine screening ECG measures are effective in detecting such patients. Rather, ziprasidone should be avoided in patients with histories of significant cardiovascular illness, e.g., QT prolongation, recent acute myocardial infarction, uncompensated heart failure, or cardiac arrhythmia. Ziprasidone should be discontinued in patients who are found to have persistent QTc measurements &gt;500 msec.



 For patients taking ziprasidone who experience symptoms that could indicate the occurrence of torsade de pointes, e.g., dizziness, palpitations, or syncope, the prescriber should initiate further evaluation, e.g., Holter monitoring may be useful.



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with administration of antipsychotic drugs. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatinine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to exclude cases where the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system (CNS) pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: (1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and (3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. The patient should be carefully monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4 Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients undergoing treatment with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses.



 There is no known treatment for established cases of tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome, and thereby may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, ziprasidone should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that (1) is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs, and (2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient on ziprasidone, drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with ziprasidone despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.5 Metabolic Changes



   Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and body weight gain. While all of the drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.  



    Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus  



 There have been few reports of hyperglycemia or diabetes in patients treated with GEODON. Although fewer patients have been treated with GEODON, it is not known if this more limited experience is the sole reason for the paucity of such reports. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions is not completely understood. Precise risk estimates for hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics are not available. Hyperglycemia and diabetes mellitus, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, have been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics.  



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of antidiabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



  Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled studies in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder are presented in Tables 1-4. Note that for the flexible dose studies in both schizophrenia and bipolar disorder, each subject is categorized as having received either low (20-40 mg BID) or high (60-80 mg BID) dose based on the subject's modal daily dose. In the tables showing categorical changes, the percentages (% column) are calculated as 100x(n/N).  



 Table 1: Glucose Mean Change from Baseline in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone, Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Schizophrenia "Random" glucose measurements-fasting/non-fasting status unknown 
  Mean Random Glucose Change from Baseline mg/dL (N)     
  Ziprasidone        Placebo       
    5 mg BID        20 mg BID       40 mg BID       60 mg BID       80 mg BID       100 mg BID     
  
  -1.1 (N=45)      +2.4 (N=179)    -0.2 (N=146)    -0.5 (N=119)    -1.7 (N=104)    +4.1 (N=85)     +1.4 (N=260)     
            Table 2: Glucose Categorical Changes in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone, Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Schizophrenia "Random" glucose measurements - fasting/non-fasting status unknown 
  Laboratory Analyte    Category Change (at least once) from Baseline   Treatment Arm        N            n (%)         
  
  Random Glucose    Normal to High (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)    Ziprasidone        438        77 (17.6%)       
 Placebo           169                                            26 (15.4%)      
 Borderline to High (&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;126 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                       159         54 (34.0%)   
 Placebo           66                                             22 (33.3%)      
            In long-term (at least 1 year), placebo-controlled, flexible-dose studies in schizophrenia, the mean change from baseline in random glucose for ziprasidone 20-40 mg BID was -3.4 mg/dL (N=122); for ziprasidone 60-80 mg BID was +1.3 mg/dL (N=10); and for placebo was +0.3 mg/dL (N=71).  
 

 Table 3: Glucose Mean Change from Baseline in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Flexible-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone, Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Bipolar Disorder Fasting 
  Mean Fasting Glucose Change from Baseline mg/dL (N)     
               Ziprasidone                                 Placebo                    
         Low Dose: 20-40 mg BID                    High Dose: 60-80 mg BID            
  
              +0.1 (N=206)                               +1.6 (N=166)                    +1.4 (N=287)       
        Table 4: Glucose Categorical Changes in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Flexible-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone, Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Bipolar Disorder Fasting 
  Laboratory Analyte    Category Change (at least once) from Baseline   Treatment Arm       N           n (%)           
  
  Fasting Glucose    Normal to High (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)    Ziprasidone         272        5 (1.8%)        
 Placebo             210                                           2 (1.0%)       
 Borderline to High (&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;126 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                        79             12 (15.2%)   
 Placebo           71                                              7 (9.9%)       
               Dyslipidemia    
 

  Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled studies in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder are presented in Tables 5-8.  



 Table 5: Lipid Mean Change from Baseline in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Schizophrenia Random" lipid measurements, fasting/non-fasting status unknown " 
  Mean Lipid Change from Baseline mg/dL (N)     
  Laboratory Analyte    Ziprasidone     Placebo      
 5 mg BID         20 mg BID     40 mg BID     60 mg BID     80 mg BID     100 mg BID    
  
  Triglycerides    -12.9 (N=45)  -9.6 (N=181)  -17.3 (N=146)  -0.05 (N=120)  -16.0 (N=104)  +0.8 (N=85)   -18.6 (N=260)    
  Total Cholesterol    -3.6 (N=45)   -4.4 (N=181)  -8.2 (N=147)  -3.6 (N=120)  -10.0 (N=104)  -3.6 (N=85)    -4.7 (N=261)    
             Table 6: Lipid Categorical Changes in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Schizophrenia Random" lipid measurements, fasting/non-fasting status unknown " 
  Laboratory Analyte    Category Change (at least once) from Baseline   Treatment Arm        N            n (%)         
  
  Triglycerides    Increase by &gt;=50 mg/dL                        Ziprasidone        681        232 (34.1%)      
 Placebo           260                                            53 (20.4%)      
 Normal to High (&lt;150 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                       429         63 (14.7%)   
 Placebo           152                                            12 (7.9%)       
 Borderline to High (&gt;=150 mg/dL and &lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                        92         43 (46.7%)   
 Placebo           41                                             12 (29.3%)      
  Total Cholesterol    Increase by &gt;=40 mg/dL                        Ziprasidone        682        76 (11.1%)       
 Placebo           261                                            26 (10.0%)      
 Normal to High (&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                       380         15 (3.9%)   
 Placebo           145                                             0 (0.0%)       
 Borderline to High (&gt;=200 mg/dL and &lt;240 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                       207         56 (27.1%)   
 Placebo           82                                             22 (26.8%)      
            In long-term (at least 1 year), placebo-controlled, flexible-dose studies in schizophrenia, the mean change from baseline in random triglycerides for ziprasidone 20-40 mg BID was +26.3 mg/dL (N=15); for ziprasidone 60-80 mg BID was -39.3 mg/dL (N=10); and for placebo was +12.9 mg/dL (N=9). In long-term (at least 1 year), placebo-controlled, flexible-dose studies in schizophrenia, the mean change from baseline in random total cholesterol for ziprasidone 20-40 mg BID was +2.5 mg/dL (N=14); for ziprasidone 60-80 mg BID was -19.7 mg/dL (N=10); and for placebo was -28.0 mg/dL (N=9).  
 

 Table 7: Lipid Mean Change from Baseline in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Flexible-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Bipolar Disorder Fasting 
  Laboratory Analyte        Mean Change from Baseline mg/dL (N)   
 Ziprasidone                           Placebo               
 Low Dose: 20-40 mg BID        High Dose: 60-80 mg BID       
  
  Fasting Triglycerides             +0.95 (N=206)                    -3.5 (N=165)            +8.6 (N=286)     
  Fasting Total Cholesterol             -2.8 (N=206)                    -3.4 (N=165)            -1.6 (N=286)     
  Fasting LDL Cholesterol             -3.0 (N=201)                    -3.1 (N=158)            -1.97 (N=270)    
  Fasting HDL cholesterol            -0.09 (N=206)                    +0.3 (N=165)            -0.9 (N=286)     
         Table 8: Lipid Categorical Changes in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Flexible-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Bipolar Disorder Fasting 
  Laboratory Analyte    Category Change (at least once) from Baseline  Treatment Arm         N            n (%)         
  
  Fasting Triglycerides    Increase by &gt;=50 mg/dL                      Ziprasidone          371        66 (17.8%)       
 Placebo           286                                         62 (21.7%)         
 Normal to High (&lt;150 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                 225               15 (6.7%)   
 Placebo           179                                         13 (7.3%)          
 Borderline to High (&gt;=150 mg/dL and &lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                 58                16 (27.6%)   
 Placebo           47                                          14 (29.8%)         
  Fasting Total Cholesterol    Increase by &gt;=40 mg/dL                      Ziprasidone          371         30 (8.1%)       
 Placebo           286                                         13 (4.5%)          
 Normal to High (&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                 204               5 (2.5%)    
 Placebo           151                                         2 (1.3%)           
 Borderline to High (&gt;=200 mg/dL and &lt;240 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                 106               10 (9.4%)   
 Placebo           87                                          15 (17.2%)         
  Fasting LDL Cholesterol    Increase by &gt;=30 mg/dL                      Ziprasidone          359        39 (10.9%)       
 Placebo           270                                         17 (6.3%)          
 Normal to High (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                 115                0 (0%)     
 Placebo           89                                          1 (1.1%)           
 Borderline to High (&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;160 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)  Ziprasidone                                 193               18 (9.3%)   
 Placebo           141                                         14 (9.9%)          
  Fasting HDL      Normal (&gt;=40 mg/dL) to Low (&lt;40 mg/dL)      Ziprasidone          283         22 (7.8%)       
 Placebo           220                                         24 (10.9%)         
               Weight Gain    
 

  Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Monitoring of weight is recommended. Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled studies in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder are presented in Tables 9-10.  



 Table 9: Weight Mean Changes in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Schizophrenia 
  Ziprasidone       Placebo       
   5 mg BID        20 mg BID       40 mg BID       60 mg BID       80 mg BID       100 mg BID     
  
  Mean Weight (kg) Changes from Baseline (N)     
  +0.3 (N=40)     +1.0 (N=167)    +1.0 (N=135)    +0.7 (N=109)    +1.1 (N=97)     +0.9 (N=74)       -0.4 (227)      
  Proportion of Patients with &gt;=7% Increase in Weight from Baseline (N)     
  0.0% (N=40)     9.0% (N=167)   10.4% (N=135)    7.3% (N=109)    15.5% (N=97)    10.8% (N=74)     4.0% (N=227)     
              In long-term (at least 1 year), placebo-controlled, flexible-dose studies in schizophrenia, the mean change from baseline weight for ziprasidone 20-40 mg BID was -2.3 kg (N=124); for ziprasidone 60-80 mg BID was +2.5 kg (N=10); and for placebo was -2.9 kg (N=72). In the same long-term studies, the proportion of subjects with 7% increase in weight from baseline for ziprasidone 20-40 mg BID was 5.6% (N=124); for ziprasidone 60-80 mg BID was 20.0% (N=10), and for placebo was 5.6% (N=72). In a long-term (at least 1 year), placebo-controlled, fixed-dose study in schizophrenia, the mean change from baseline weight for ziprasidone 20 mg BID was -2.6 kg (N=72); for ziprasidone 40 mg BID was -3.3 kg (N=69); for ziprasidone 80 mg BID was -2.8 kg (N=70) and for placebo was -3.8 kg (N=70). In the same long-term fixed-dose schizophrenia study, the proportion of subjects with 7% increase in weight from baseline for ziprasidone 20 mg BID was 5.6% (N=72); for ziprasidone 40 mg BID was 2.9% (N=69); for ziprasidone 80 mg BID was 5.7% (N=70) and for placebo was 2.9% (N=70). &gt;=   &gt;=    
 

 Table 10: Summary of Weight Change in Short-Term (up to 6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled, Flexible-Dose, Oral Ziprasidone Monotherapy Trials in Adult Patients with Bipolar Disorder: 
               Ziprasidone                                 Placebo                    
         Low Dose: 20-40 mg BID                    High Dose : 60-80 mg BID           
  
  Mean Weight (kg) Changes from Baseline (N)     
              +0.4 (N=295)                               +0.4 (N=388)                    +0.1 (N=451)       
  Proportion of Patients with &gt;= 7% Increase in Weight from Baseline (N)     
              2.4% (N=295)                               4.4% (N=388)                    1.8% (N=451)       
          - The proportions of patients meeting a weight gain criterion of &gt;= 7% of body weight were compared in a pool of four 4- and 6-week placebo-controlled schizophrenia clinical trials, revealing a statistically significantly greater incidence of weight gain for ziprasidone (10%) compared to placebo (4%). A median weight gain of 0.5 kg was observed in ziprasidone patients compared to no median weight change in placebo patients. In this set of clinical trials, weight gain was reported as an adverse reaction in 0.4% and 0.4% of ziprasidone and placebo patients, respectively. During long-term therapy with ziprasidone, a categorization of patients at baseline on the basis of body mass index (BMI) revealed the greatest mean weight gain and highest incidence of clinically significant weight gain (&gt; 7% of body weight) in patients with low BMI (&lt;23) compared to normal (23-27) or overweight patients (&gt;27). There was a mean weight gain of 1.4 kg for those patients with a "low" baseline BMI, no mean change for patients with a "normal" BMI, and a 1.3 kg mean weight loss for patients who entered the program with a "high" BMI. Schizophrenia    
 

  - During a 6-month placebo-controlled bipolar maintenance study in adults with ziprasidone as an adjunct to lithium or valproate, the incidence of clinically significant weight gain (&gt;= 7% of body weight) during the double-blind period was 5.6% for both ziprasidone and placebo treatment groups who completed the 6 months of observation for relapse. Interpretation of these findings should take into consideration that only patients who adequately tolerated ziprasidone entered the double-blind phase of the study, and there were substantial dropouts during the open label phase. Bipolar Disorder    



    5.6 Rash



  In premarketing trials with ziprasidone, about 5% of patients developed rash and/or urticaria, with discontinuation of treatment in about one-sixth of these cases. The occurrence of rash was related to dose of ziprasidone, although the finding might also be explained by the longer exposure time in the higher dose patients. Several patients with rash had signs and symptoms of associated systemic illness, e.g., elevated WBCs. Most patients improved promptly with adjunctive treatment with antihistamines or steroids and/or upon discontinuation of ziprasidone, and all patients experiencing these reactions were reported to recover completely. Upon appearance of rash for which an alternative etiology cannot be identified, ziprasidone should be discontinued.



    5.7 Orthostatic Hypotension



  Ziprasidone may induce orthostatic hypotension associated with dizziness, tachycardia, and, in some patients, syncope, especially during the initial dose-titration period, probably reflecting its alpha -adrenergic antagonist properties. Syncope was reported in 0.6% of the patients treated with ziprasidone.1



 Ziprasidone should be used with particular caution in patients with known cardiovascular disease (history of myocardial infarction or ischemic heart disease, heart failure or conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, or conditions which would predispose patients to hypotension (dehydration, hypovolemia, and treatment with antihypertensive medications).



    5.8 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



  In clinical trial and postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia/neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents. Agranulocytosis (including fatal cases) has also been reported.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) and history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a pre-existing low WBC or a history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and should discontinue Geodon at the first sign of decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Patients with neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm3) should discontinue Geodon and have their WBC followed until recovery.



    5.9 Seizures



  During clinical trials, seizures occurred in 0.4% of patients treated with ziprasidone. There were confounding factors that may have contributed to the occurrence of seizures in many of these cases. As with other antipsychotic drugs, ziprasidone should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold, e.g., Alzheimer's dementia. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in a population of 65 years or older.



    5.10 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in elderly patients, in particular those with advanced Alzheimer's dementia. Ziprasidone and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia . [see ]  Boxed Warning    



    5.11 Hyperprolactinemia



  As with other drugs that antagonize dopamine D receptors, ziprasidone elevates prolactin levels in humans. Increased prolactin levels were also observed in animal studies with this compound, and were associated with an increase in mammary gland neoplasia in mice; a similar effect was not observed in rats . Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin-dependent , a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is contemplated in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans; the available evidence is considered too limited to be conclusive at this time.2 [see ]  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)     in vitro  



  Although disturbances such as galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported with prolactin-elevating compounds, the clinical significance of elevated serum prolactin levels is unknown for most patients. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density.  



    5.12 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  Somnolence was a commonly reported adverse reaction in patients treated with ziprasidone. In the 4- and 6-week placebo-controlled trials, somnolence was reported in 14% of patients on ziprasidone compared to 7% of placebo patients. Somnolence led to discontinuation in 0.3% of patients in short-term clinical trials. Since ziprasidone has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills, patients should be cautioned about performing activities requiring mental alertness, such as operating a motor vehicle (including automobiles) or operating hazardous machinery until they are reasonably certain that ziprasidone therapy does not affect them adversely.



    5.13 Priapism



  One case of priapism was reported in the premarketing database. While the relationship of the reaction to ziprasidone use has not been established, other drugs with alpha-adrenergic blocking effects have been reported to induce priapism, and it is possible that ziprasidone may share this capacity. Severe priapism may require surgical intervention.



    5.14 Body Temperature Regulation



  Although not reported with ziprasidone in premarketing trials, disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing ziprasidone for patients who will be experiencing conditions which may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration.



    5.15 Suicide



  The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in psychotic illness or bipolar disorder, and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy. Prescriptions for ziprasidone should be written for the smallest quantity of capsules consistent with good patient management in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



    5.16 Patients with concomitant illnesses



  Clinical experience with ziprasidone in patients with certain concomitant systemic illnesses is limited [see , ]  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)    ( 8.7)    



 Ziprasidone has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were excluded from premarketing clinical studies. Because of the risk of QTc prolongation and orthostatic hypotension with ziprasidone, caution should be observed in cardiac patients [see , ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    (5.7)    



    5.17 Laboratory Tests



  Patients being considered for ziprasidone treatment that are at risk of significant electrolyte disturbances should have baseline serum potassium and magnesium measurements. Low serum potassium and magnesium should be replaced before proceeding with treatment. Patients who are started on diuretics during Ziprasidone therapy need periodic monitoring of serum potassium and magnesium. Ziprasidone should be discontinued in patients who are found to have persistent QTc measurements &gt;500 msec. [see ]  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
