<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="giazo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2%) in male UC patients are  anemia, diarrhea, pharyngolaryngeal pain, and urinary tract infection. (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Salix Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-508-0024 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure of GIAZO in 565 ulcerative colitis patients with mildly to moderately active disease.  GIAZO was evaluated in one placebo-controlled trial (168 treated with GIAZO), one active-controlled trial (210 treated with GIAZO); and a subset of these patients also participated in an uncontrolled, open-label, extension study (additional 187 treated with GIAZO).  The population studied had a mean age of 43.1 (range: 18-80) years; approximately 94% of patients were &lt; 65 years old, 49% were male, and 84% were white.



 In the placebo-controlled trial, the most common adverse reactions with GIAZO in male patients were headache, nasopharyngitis, anemia, diarrhea, fatigue, pharyngolaryngeal pain, and urinary tract infection.  10% of patients in the GIAZO group and 13% of patients in the placebo group discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction.  The majority of adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity. The most common serious adverse reactions in both the placebo and GIAZO groups were gastrointestinal disorders, which were mainly associated with symptoms of ulcerative colitis.



 Adverse reactions occurring in at least 2% of male patients and at a rate numerically higher than placebo in the placebo-controlled trial are listed in Table 1. 



   Table 1: Adverse Reactions Experienced by at Least 2% of GIAZO -Treated Male Patients and at a Rate Numerically Greater than Placebo in a Placebo-Controlled Trial  




  Adverse Reaction    GIAZO6.6 g/day  N=82    PLACEBO  N=37    
  Anemia           3.7%             0%               
  Diarrhea         3.7%             0%               
  Pharyngolaryngeal Pain    3.7%             0%               
  Urinary Tract Infection    3.7%             0%               
  Arthralgia       2.4%             0%               
  Insomnia         2.4%             0%               
  Musculoskeletal Pain    2.4%             0%               
         Data collected from all three trials (placebo-controlled, active-controlled, and open-label) showed that female patients reported adverse reactions more frequently than did male patients (76% and 66%, respectively).
 

 The following adverse reactions, presented by body system, were reported by less than 1% of GIAZO-treated ulcerative colitis patients in controlled trials.



   Cardiovascular and Vascular  : increased blood pressure, increased heart rate



   Dermatological  : erythema nodosum, rash



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  : dyspnea



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : abdominal pain, constipation, defecation urgency, diarrhea, dry mouth, hard feces, flatulence, gastroesophageal reflux disease, vomiting



   Hepatobiliary Disorders  : increased aspartate aminotransferase



   Infections and Infestations  : gastroenteritis, upper respiratory infection



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  : arthralgia, back pain, myalgia



   Nervous System Disorders  : dizziness, lethargy



   General Disorders and Administrative Site Disorders  : face edema, fatigue, malaise, pain, pyrexia, swelling



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These adverse reactions have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to products which contain or are metabolized to mesalamine, including balsalazide.



   Cardiovascular and Vascular  : myocarditis, pericarditis, vasculitis



   Respiratory  : alveolitis, pleural effusion, pneumonia (with and without eosinophilia)



   Gastrointestinal  : pancreatitis



   Renal  : interstitial nephritis, renal failure.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  elevated liver enzymes (AST, ALT, GGT, LDH, alkaline phosphatase), elevated bilirubin, jaundice, cholestatic jaundice, cirrhosis, hepatocellular damage including liver necrosis and liver failure, Kawasaki-like syndrome including hepatic dysfunction.  Some of these cases were fatal.



   Dermatological  : alopecia, pruritus
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Exacerbation of the symptoms of ulcerative colitis was reported.  Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Renal impairment may occur.  Assess renal function at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment.   (5.2)    
 *   Use with caution with pre-existing liver disease.   (5.3)   



 
    
 

   5.1 Exacerbations of Ulcerative Colitis



  Balsalazide is converted to mesalamine, which has been associated with an acute intolerance syndrome that may be difficult to distinguish from an exacerbation of ulcerative colitis.  In controlled clinical trials with GIAZO in adults with ulcerative colitis, 7% of male patients reported exacerbation of the symptoms of ulcerative colitis.  Symptoms include cramping, acute abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea, sometimes fever, headache, and rash.  Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment. If acute intolerance syndrome is suspected, promptly discontinue treatment with GIAZO.



    5.2 Renal Impairment



  Renal impairment, including minimal change nephropathy, acute and chronic interstitial nephritis and renal failure, has been reported in patients given products that release mesalamine in the gastrointestinal tract.  Evaluate renal function prior to initiation of GIAZO therapy and periodically while on therapy.  Exercise caution when using GIAZO in patients with known renal dysfunction or a history of renal disease. 



    5.3 Use in Hepatic Impairment



  There have been reports of hepatic failure in patients with pre-existing liver disease who have been administered mesalamine.  Because balsalazide is converted to mesalamine, use caution and consider liver function testing when administering GIAZO to patients with liver disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
