<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gleevec" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates on other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   EXCERPT:   The most frequently reported adverse reactions (  &gt;  30%) were edema, nausea, vomiting, muscle cramps, musculoskeletal pain, diarrhea, rash, fatigue and abdominal pain (  6.1  ,  6.9  )



  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .   

  6.1     Chronic Myeloid Leukemia

  The majority of Gleevec-treated patients experienced adverse reactions at some time, most adverse reactions were of mild-to-moderate grade. Gleevec was discontinued due to drug-related adverse reactions in 2.4% of patients receiving Gleevec in the randomized trial of newly diagnosed patients with Ph+ CML in chronic phase comparing Gleevec versus INF+Ara-C, and in 12.5% of patients receiving Gleevec in the randomized trial of newly diagnosed patients with Ph+ CML in chronic phase comparing Gleevec and nilotinib. Gleevec was discontinued due to drug-related adverse reactions in 4% of patients in chronic phase after failure of interferon-alpha therapy, in 4% of patients in accelerated phase and in 5% of patients in blast crisis.



 The most frequently reported drug-related adverse reactions were edema, nausea and vomiting, muscle cramps, musculoskeletal pain, diarrhea and rash (Table 2 and Table 3 for newly diagnosed CML, Table 4 for other CML patients). Edema was most frequently periorbital or in lower limbs and was managed with diuretics, other supportive measures, or by reducing the dose of Gleevec [  see Dosage and Administration (2.12)  ]. The frequency of severe superficial edema was 1.5%-6%.



 A variety of adverse reactions represent local or general fluid retention including pleural effusion, ascites, pulmonary edema and rapid weight gain with or without superficial edema. These reactions appear to be dose related, were more common in the blast crisis and accelerated phase studies (where the dose was 600 mg/day), and are more common in the elderly. These reactions were usually managed by interrupting Gleevec treatment and using diuretics or other appropriate supportive care measures. A few of these reactions may be serious or life threatening, and one patient with blast crisis died with pleural effusion, congestive heart failure, and renal failure.



 Adverse reactions, regardless of relationship to study drug, that were reported in at least 10% of the Gleevec treated patients are shown in Tables 2, 3, and 4.



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug Reported in Newly Diagnosed CML Clinical Trial in the Gleevec versus INF+Ara-C Study (&gt;=10% of Gleevec Treated Patients)(1) 
   (1)  All adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=10% of Gleevec treated patients are listed regardless of suspected relationship to treatment.  (2)  Other fluid retention reactions include pleural effusion, ascites, pulmonary edema, pericardial effusion, anasarca, edema aggravated, and fluid retention not otherwise specified.   
  
                    All Grades       CTC Grades 3/4     
                    Gleevec          IFN+Ara-C        Gleevec          IFN+Ara-C       
   Preferred Term      N=551 (%)        N=533 (%)        N=551 (%)        N=533 (%)       
 Fluid Retention  61.7             11.1             2.5              0.9               
 - Superficial Edema  59.9             9.6              1.5              0.4               
 - Other Fluid Retention Reactions  2    6.9              1.9              1.3              0.6               
 Nausea           49.5             61.5             1.3              5.1               
 Muscle Cramps    49.2             11.8             2.2              0.2               
 Musculoskeletal Pain  47.0             44.8             5.4              8.6               
 Diarrhea         45.4             43.3             3.3              3.2               
 Rash and Related Terms  40.1             26.1             2.9              2.4               
 Fatigue          38.8             67.0             1.8              25.1              
 Headache         37.0             43.3             0.5              3.8               
 Joint Pain       31.4             38.1             2.5              7.7               
 Abdominal Pain   36.5             25.9             4.2              3.9               
 Nasopharyngitis  30.5             8.8              0                0.4               
 Hemorrhage       28.9             21.2             1.8              1.7               
 - GI Hemorrhage  1.6              1.1              0.5              0.2               
 - CNS Hemorrhage  0.2              0.4              0                0.4               
 Myalgia          24.1             38.8             1.5              8.3               
 Vomiting         22.5             27.8             2.0              3.4               
 Dyspepsia        18.9             8.3              0                0.8               
 Cough            20.0             23.1             0.2              0.6               
 Pharyngolaryngeal Pain  18.1             11.4             0.2              0                 
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection  21.2             8.4              0.2              0.4               
 Dizziness        19.4             24.4             0.9              3.8               
 Pyrexia          17.8             42.6             0.9              3.0               
 Weight Increased  15.6             2.6              2.0              0.4               
 Insomnia         14.7             18.6             0                2.3               
 Depression       14.9             35.8             0.5              13.1              
 Influenza        13.8             6.2              0.2              0.2               
 Bone Pain        11.3             15.6             1.6              3.4               
 Constipation     11.4             14.4             0.7              0.2               
 Sinusitis        11.4             6.0              0.2              0.2               
          Table 3: Most Frequently Reported Non-hematologic Adverse Reactions (Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug) in Patients with Newly Diagnosed Ph+ CML-CP in the Gleevec versus nilotinib Study (&gt;=10% in Gleevec 400 mg Once-Daily or nilotinib 300 mg Twice-Daily Groups) 60-Month Analysisa 
   a  Excluding laboratory abnormalities  b  NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, Version 3.0   
  
                    Patients with Newly Diagnosed Ph+ CML-CP     
                    Gleevec400 mgonce-daily      nilotinib300 mgtwice-daily      Gleevec400 mgonce-daily      nilotinib300 mgtwice-daily     
                    N=280            N=279            N=280            N=279           
   Body System and Preferred Term      All Grades (%)      CTC Grades  b  3/4 (%)     
 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  Rash             19               38               2                &lt;1                
                  Pruritus         7                21               0                &lt;1                
                  Alopecia         7                13               0                0                 
                  Dry skin         6                12               0                0                 
 Gastrointestinal disorders  Nausea           41               22               2                2                 
                  Constipation     8                20               0                &lt;1                
                  Diarrhea         46               19               4                1                 
                  Vomiting         27               15               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Abdominal pain upper  14               18               &lt;1               1                 
                  Abdominal pain   12               15               0                2                 
                  Dyspepsia        12               10               0                0                 
 Nervous system disorders  Headache         23               32               &lt;1               3                 
                  Dizziness        11               12               &lt;1               &lt;1                
 General disorders and administration site conditions  Fatigue          20               23               1                1                 
                  Pyrexia          13               14               0                &lt;1                
                  Asthenia         12               14               0                &lt;1                
                  Peripheral edema  20               9                0                &lt;1                
                  Face edema       14               &lt;1               &lt;1               0                 
 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  Myalgia          19               19               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Arthralgia       17               22               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Muscle spasms    34               12               1                0                 
                  Pain in extremity  16               15               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Back pain        17               19               1                1                 
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  Cough            13               17               0                0                 
                  Oropharyngeal pain  6                12               0                0                 
                  Dyspnea          6                11               &lt;1               2                 
 Infections and infestations  Nasopharyngitis  21               27               0                0                 
                  Upper respiratory tract infection  14               17               0                &lt;1                
                  Influenza        9                13               0                0                 
                  Gastroenteritis  10               7                &lt;1               0                 
 Eye disorders    Eyelid edema     19               1                &lt;1               0                 
                  Periorbital edema  15               &lt;1               0                0                 
 Psychiatric disorders  Insomnia         9                11               0                0                 
 Vascular disorder  Hypertension     4                10               &lt;1               1                 
           Table 4 Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug Reported in Other CML Clinical Trials (&gt;=10% of All Patients in any Trial)(1) 
   (1)  All adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=10% of patients are listed regardless of suspected relationship to treatment.  (2)  Other fluid retention reactions include pleural effusion, ascites, pulmonary edema, pericardial effusion, anasarca, edema aggravated, and fluid retention not otherwise specified.   
  
                    Myeloid Blast Crisis    (n=260)      Accelerated Phase    (n=235)      Chronic Phase, IFN Failure    (n=532)     
                    %                %                %               
   Preferred Term      All Grades       Grade 3/4        All Grades       Grade 3/4        All Grades       Grade 3/4       
 Fluid Retention  72               11               76               6                69               4                 
 -Superficial Edema  66               6                74               3                67               2                 
 -Other Fluid Retention Reactions  (2)    22               6                15               4                7                2                 
 Nausea           71               5                73               5                63               3                 
 Muscle Cramps    28               1                47               0.4              62               2                 
 Vomiting         54               4                58               3                36               2                 
 Diarrhea         43               4                57               5                48               3                 
 Hemorrhage       53               19               49               11               30               2                 
 - CNS Hemorrhage  9                7                3                3                2                1                 
 - GI Hemorrhage  8                4                6                5                2                0.4               
 Musculoskeletal Pain  42               9                49               9                38               2                 
 Fatigue          30               4                46               4                48               1                 
 Skin Rash        36               5                47               5                47               3                 
 Pyrexia          41               7                41               8                21               2                 
 Arthralgia       25               5                34               6                40               1                 
 Headache         27               5                32               2                36               0.6               
 Abdominal Pain   30               6                33               4                32               1                 
 Weight Increased  5                1                17               5                32               7                 
 Cough            14               0.8              27               0.9              20               0                 
 Dyspepsia        12               0                22               0                27               0                 
 Myalgia          9                0                24               2                27               0.2               
 Nasopharyngitis  10               0                17               0                22               0.2               
 Asthenia         18               5                21               5                15               0.2               
 Dyspnea          15               4                21               7                12               0.9               
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection  3                0                12               0.4              19               0                 
 Anorexia         14               2                17               2                7                0                 
 Night Sweats     13               0.8              17               1                14               0.2               
 Constipation     16               2                16               0.9              9                0.4               
 Dizziness        12               0.4              13               0                16               0.2               
 Pharyngitis      10               0                12               0                15               0                 
 Insomnia         10               0                14               0                14               0.2               
 Pruritus         8                1                14               0.9              14               0.8               
 Hypokalemia      13               4                9                2                6                0.8               
 Pneumonia        13               7                10               7                4                1                 
 Anxiety          8                0.8              12               0                8                0.4               
 Liver Toxicity   10               5                12               6                6                3                 
 Rigors           10               0                12               0.4              10               0                 
 Chest Pain       7                2                10               0.4              11               0.8               
 Influenza        0.8              0.4              6                0                11               0.2               
 Sinusitis        4                0.4              11               0.4              9                0.4               
               Hematologic and Biochemistry Laboratory Abnormalities  
 

 Cytopenias, and particularly neutropenia and thrombocytopenia, were a consistent finding in all studies, with a higher frequency at doses &gt;=750 mg (Phase 1 study). The occurrence of cytopenias in CML patients was also dependent on the stage of the disease.



 In patients with newly diagnosed CML, cytopenias were less frequent than in the other CML patients (see Tables 5, 6, and 7). The frequency of Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia and thrombocytopenia was between 2- and 3-fold higher in blast crisis and accelerated phase compared to chronic phase (see Tables 4 and 5). The median duration of the neutropenic and thrombocytopenic episodes varied from 2 to 3 weeks, and from 2 to 4 weeks, respectively.



 These reactions can usually be managed with either a reduction of the dose or an interruption of treatment with Gleevec, but in rare cases require permanent discontinuation of treatment.



 Table 5 Laboratory Abnormalities in Newly Diagnosed CML Clinical Trial (Gleevec versus INF+Ara-C) 
 *p&lt;0.001 (difference in Grade 3 plus 4 abnormalities between the two treatment groups)   
  
                    Gleevec    N=551      IFN+Ara-C    N=533     
                    %                %               
   CTC Grades       Grade 3          Grade 4          Grade 3          Grade 4         
   Hematology Parameters*                                                                         
 - Neutropenia*   13.1             3.6              20.8             4.5               
 - Thrombocytopenia*  8.5              0.4              15.9             0.6               
 - Anemia         3.3              1.1              4.1              0.2               
   Biochemistry Parameters                                                                         
 - Elevated Creatinine  0                0                0.4              0                 
 - Elevated Bilirubin  0.9              0.2              0.2              0                 
 - Elevated Alkaline Phosphatase  0.2              0                0.8              0                 
 - Elevated SGOT /SGPT  4.7              0.5              7.1              0.4               
          Table 6 Percent Incidence of Clinically Relevant Grade 3/4* Laboratory Abnormalities in the Newly Diagnosed CML Clinical Trial (Gleevec versus nilotinib) 
 *NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.0   
  
                    Gleevec 400 mgonce-dailyN=280(%)      nilotinib 300 mgtwice-dailyN=279(%)     
   Hematologic Parameters                                       
 Thrombocytopenia  9                10                
 Neutropenia      22               12                
 Anemia           6                4                 
   Biochemistry Parameters                                       
 Elevated lipase  4                9                 
 Hyperglycemia    &lt;1               7                 
 Hypophosphatemia  10               8                 
 Elevated bilirubin (total)  &lt;1               4                 
 Elevated SGPT (ALT)  3                4                 
 Hyperkalemia     1                2                 
 Hyponatremia     &lt;1               1                 
 Hypokalemia      2                &lt;1                
 Elevated SGOT (AST)  1                1                 
 Decreased albumin  &lt;1               0                 
 Hypocalcemia     &lt;1               &lt;1                
 Elevated alkaline phosphatase  &lt;1               0                 
 Elevated creatinine  &lt;1               0                 
        Table 7 Laboratory Abnormalities in Other CML Clinical Trials 
   1  CTC Grades: neutropenia (Grade 3 &gt;=0.5-1.0 x 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;0.5 x 10  9  /L), thrombocytopenia (Grade 3 &gt;=10-50 x 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;10 x 10  9  /L), anemia (hemoglobin &gt;=65-80 g/L, Grade 4 &lt;65 g/L), elevated creatinine (Grade 3 &gt;3-6 x upper limit normal range [ULN], Grade 4 &gt;6 x ULN), elevated bilirubin (Grade 3 &gt;3-10 x ULN, Grade 4 &gt;10 x ULN), elevated alkaline phosphatase (Grade 3 &gt;5-20 x ULN, Grade 4 &gt;20 x ULN), elevated SGOT or SGPT (Grade 3 &gt;5-20 x ULN, Grade 4 &gt;20 x ULN)   
  
                    Myeloid Blast Crisis    (n=260)      Accelerated Phase    (n=235)      Chronic Phase, IFN Failure    (n=532)     
                    600 mg n=223    400 mg n=37      600 mg n=158    400 mg n=77      400 mg          
                    %                %                %               
   CTC Grades      1        Grade 3          Grade 4          Grade 3          Grade 4          Grade 3          Grade 4         
   Hematology Parameters                                                                                                           
 - Neutropenia    16               48               23               36               27               9                 
 - Thrombocytopenia  30               33               31               13               21               &lt;1                
 - Anemia         42               11               34               7                6                1                 
   Biochemistry Parameters                                                                                                           
 - Elevated Creatinine  1.5              0                1.3              0                0.2              0                 
 - Elevated Bilirubin  3.8              0                2.1              0                0.6              0                 
 - Elevated Alkaline Phosphatase  4.6              0                5.5              0.4              0.2              0                 
 - Elevated SGOT (AST)  1.9              0                3.0              0                2.3              0                 
 - Elevated SGPT (ALT)  2.3              0.4              4.3              0                2.1              0                 
               Hepatotoxicity  
 

 Severe elevation of transaminases or bilirubin occurred in approximately 5% of CML patients (see Tables 6 and 7) and were usually managed with dose reduction or interruption (the median duration of these episodes was approximately 1 week). Treatment was discontinued permanently because of liver laboratory abnormalities in less than 1.0% of CML patients. One patient, who was taking acetaminophen regularly for fever, died of acute liver failure. In the Phase 2 GIST trial, Grade 3 or 4 SGPT (ALT) elevations were observed in 6.8% of patients and Grade 3 or 4 SGOT (AST) elevations were observed in 4.8% of patients. Bilirubin elevation was observed in 2.7% of patients.



   6.2     Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Population

    Single agent therapy  



 The overall safety profile of pediatric patients treated with Gleevec in 93 children studied was similar to that found in studies with adult patients, except that musculoskeletal pain was less frequent (20.5%) and peripheral edema was not reported. Nausea and vomiting were the most commonly reported individual adverse reactions with an incidence similar to that seen in adult patients. Although most patients experienced adverse reactions at some time during the study, the incidence of Grade 3/4 adverse reactions was low.



   In combination with multi-agent chemotherapy  



 Pediatric and young adult patients with very high risk ALL, defined as those with an expected 5 year event-free survival (EFS) less than 45%, were enrolled after induction therapy on a multicenter, non-randomized cooperative group pilot protocol. The study population included patients with a median age of 10 years (1 to 21 years), 61% of whom were male, 75% were white, 7% were black and 6% were Asian/Pacific Islander. Patients with Ph+ ALL (n=92) were assigned to receive Gleevec and treated in 5 successive cohorts. Gleevec exposure was systematically increased in successive cohorts by earlier introduction and more prolonged duration.



 The safety of Gleevec given in combination with intensive chemotherapy was evaluated by comparing the incidence of grade 3 and 4 adverse events, neutropenia (&lt;750/mcL) and thrombocytopenia (&lt;75,000/mcL) in the 92 patients with Ph+ ALL compared to 65 patients with Ph- ALL enrolled on the trial who did not receive Gleevec. The safety was also evaluated comparing the incidence of adverse events in cycles of therapy administered with or without Gleevec. The protocol included up to 18 cycles of therapy. Patients were exposed to a cumulative total of 1425 cycles of therapy, 778 with Gleevec and 647 without Gleevec. The adverse events that were reported with a 5% or greater incidence in patients with Ph+ ALL compared to Ph- ALL or with a 1% or greater incidence in cycles of therapy that included Gleevec are presented in Table 8.



 Table 8 Adverse Reactions Reported More Frequently in Patients Treated with Study Drug (&gt;5%) or in Cycles with Study Drug (&gt;1%) 
 * Defined as the frequency of AEs per patient per treatment cycles that included Gleevec (includes patients with Ph+ ALL that received cycles with Gleevec   
 ** Defined as the frequency of AEs per patient per treatment cycles that did not include Gleevec (includes patients with Ph+ ALL that received cycles without Gleevec as well as all patients with Ph- ALL who did not receive Gleevec in any treatment cycle)   
  
   Adverse Event      Per PatientIncidencePh+ALLWith GleevecN=92n (%)      Per PatientIncidencePh- ALLNo GleevecN=65n (%)      Per PatientPer CycleIncidenceWith Gleevec*N=778n (%)      Per PatientPer CycleIncidenceNo Gleevec**N=647n (%)     
   Grade 3 and 4 Adverse Events                                                                         
 Nausea and/or Vomiting  15 (16)          6 (9)            28 (4)           8 (1)             
 Hypokalemia      31 (34)          16 (25)          72 (9)           32(5)             
 Pneumonitis      7 (8)            1 (1)            7(1)             1(&lt;1)             
 Pleural effusion  6 (7)            0                6 (1)            0                 
 Abdominal Pain   8 (9)            2 (3)            9 (1)            3(&lt;1)             
 Anorexia         10 (11)          3 (5)            19 (2)           4 (1)             
 Hemorrhage       11 (12)          4 (6)            17 (2)           8 (1)             
 Hypoxia          8 (9)            2 (3)            12 (2)           2 (&lt;1)            
 Myalgia          5 (5)            0                4 (1)            1 (&lt;1)            
 Stomatitis       15 (16)          8 (12)           22 (3)           14 (2)            
 Diarrhea         8 (9)            3 (5)            12 (2)           3 (&lt;1)            
 Rash / Skin Disorder  4 (4)            0                5 (1)            0                 
 Infection        49 (53)          32 (49)          131 (17)         92 (14)           
 Hepatic (transaminase and/or bilirubin)  52 (57)          38 (58)          172 (22)         113 (17)          
 Hypotension      10 (11)          5 (8)            16 (2)           6 (1)             
   Myelosuppression                                                                         
 Neutropenia (&lt;750/mcL)  92 (100)         63 (97)          556 (71)         218 (34)          
 Thrombocytopenia (&lt;75,000/mcL)  90 (92)          63 (97)          431 (55)         329 (51)          
             6.3     Adverse Reactions in Other Subpopulations
   In older patients (&gt;=65 years old), with the exception of edema, where it was more frequent, there was no evidence of an increase in the incidence or severity of adverse reactions. In women there was an increase in the frequency of neutropenia, as well as Grade 1/2 superficial edema, headache, nausea, rigors, vomiting, rash, and fatigue. No differences were seen that were related to race but the subsets were too small for proper evaluation.



   6.4     Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia

  The adverse reactions were similar for Ph+ ALL as for Ph+ CML. The most frequently reported drug-related adverse reactions reported in the Ph+ ALL studies were mild nausea and vomiting, diarrhea, myalgia, muscle cramps and rash, which were easily manageable. Superficial edema was a common finding in all studies and were described primarily as periorbital or lower limb edemas. These edemas were rarely severe and may be managed with diuretics, other supportive measures, or in some patients by reducing the dose of Gleevec.



   6.5     Myelodysplastic/Myeloproliferative Diseases

  Adverse reactions, regardless of relationship to study drug, that were reported in at least 10% of the patients treated with Gleevec for MDS/MPD in the phase 2 study, are shown in Table 9.



 Table 9 Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug Reported (More than One Patient) in MPD Patients in the Phase 2 Study (&gt;=10% All Patients) All Grades 
   Preferred Term      N=7    n (%)     
 Nausea           4 (57.1)          
 Diarrhea         3 (42.9)          
 Anemia           2 (28.6)          
 Fatigue          2 (28.6)          
 Muscle Cramp     3 (42.9)          
 Arthralgia       2 (28.6)          
 Periorbital Edema  2 (28.6)          
          6.6     Aggressive Systemic Mastocytosis
   All ASM patients experienced at least one adverse reaction at some time. The most frequently reported adverse reactions were diarrhea, nausea, ascites, muscle cramps, dyspnea, fatigue, peripheral edema, anemia, pruritus, rash and lower respiratory tract infection. None of the 5 patients in the phase 2 study with ASM discontinued Gleevec due to drug-related adverse reactions or abnormal laboratory values.



   6.7     Hypereosinophilic Syndrome and Chronic Eosinophilic Leukemia

  The safety profile in the HES/CEL patient population does not appear to be different from the safety profile of Gleevec observed in other hematologic malignancy populations, such as Ph+ CML. All patients experienced at least one adverse reaction, the most common being gastrointestinal, cutaneous and musculoskeletal disorders. Hematological abnormalities were also frequent, with instances of CTC Grade 3 leukopenia, neutropenia, lymphopenia, and anemia.



   6.8     Dermatofibrosarcoma Protuberans

  Adverse reactions, regardless of relationship to study drug, that were reported in at least 10% of the 12 patients treated with Gleevec for DFSP in the phase 2 study are shown in Table 10.



 Table 10 Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug Reported in DFSP Patients in the Phase 2 Study (&gt;=10% All Patients) All Grades 
   Preferred term      N=12    n (%)     
 Nausea           5 (41.7)          
 Diarrhea         3 (25.0)          
 Vomiting         3 (25.0)          
 Periorbital Edema  4 (33.3)          
 Face Edema       2 (16.7)          
 Rash             3 (25.0)          
 Fatigue          5 (41.7)          
 Edema Peripheral  4 (33.3)          
 Pyrexia          2 (16.7)          
 Eye Edema        4 (33.3)          
 Lacrimation Increased  3 (25.0)          
 Dyspnea Exertional  2 (16.7)          
 Anemia           3 (25.0)          
 Rhinitis         2 (16.7)          
 Anorexia         2 (16.7)          
        Clinically relevant or severe laboratory abnormalities in the 12 patients treated with Gleevec for DFSP in the phase 2 study are presented in Table 11.
 

 Table 11 Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in DFSP Patients in the Phase 2 Study 
   1  CTC Grades: neutropenia (Grade 3 &gt;=0.5-1.0 x 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;0.5 x 10  9  /L), thrombocytopenia (Grade 3 &gt;=10-50 x 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;10 x 10  9  /L), anemia (Grade 3 &gt;=65-80 g/L, Grade 4 &lt;65 g/L), elevated creatinine (Grade 3 &gt;3-6 x upper limit normal range [ULN], Grade 4 &gt;6 x ULN),   
  
                    N=12            
   CTC Grades  1        Grade 3%         Grade 4%        
   Hematology Parameters                                       
 - Anemia         17               0                 
 - Thrombocytopenia  17               0                 
 - Neutropenia    0                8                 
   Biochemistry Parameters                                       
 - Elevated Creatinine  0                8                 
           6.9     Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors
     Unresectable and/or Malignant Metastatic GIST  



 In the Phase 3 trials, the majority of Gleevec-treated patients experienced adverse reactions at some time. The most frequently reported adverse reactions were edema, fatigue, nausea, abdominal pain, diarrhea, rash, vomiting, myalgia, anemia, and anorexia. Drug was discontinued for adverse reactions in a total of 89 patients (5.4%). Superficial edema, most frequently periorbital or lower extremity edema was managed with diuretics, other supportive measures, or by reducing the dose of Gleevec [  see Dosage and Administration (2.    12    )  ]. Severe (CTC Grade 3/4) edema was observed in 182 patients (11.1%).



 Adverse reactions, regardless of relationship to study drug, that were reported in at least 10% of the patients treated with Gleevec are shown in Table 12.



 Overall the incidence of all grades of adverse reactions and the incidence of severe adverse reactions (CTC Grade 3 and above) were similar between the two treatment arms except for edema, which was reported more frequently in the 800 mg group.



 Table 12 Number (%) of Patients with Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug where Frequency is &gt;=10% in any One Group (Full Analysis Set) in the Phase 3 Unresectable and/or Malignant Metastatic GIST Clinical Trials 
   Reported or Specified Term      Imatinib 400 mg    N=818      Imatinib 800 mg    N=822     
                    All Grades %      Grades 3/4/5    %      All Grades %      Grades 3/4/5    %     
 Edema            76.7             9.0              86.1             13.1              
 Fatigue/lethargy, malaise, asthenia  69.3             11.7             74.9             12.2              
 Nausea           58.1             9.0              64.5             7.8               
 Abdominal pain/cramping  57.2             13.8             55.2             11.8              
 Diarrhea         56.2             8.1              58.2             8.6               
 Rash/desquamation  38.1             7.6              49.8             8.9               
 Vomiting         37.4             9.2              40.6             7.5               
 Myalgia          32.2             5.6              30.2             3.8               
 Anemia           32.0             4.9              34.8             6.4               
 Anorexia         31.1             6.6              35.8             4.7               
 Other GI toxicity  25.2             8.1              28.1             6.6               
 Headache         22.0             5.7              19.7             3.6               
 Other pain (excluding tumor related pain)  20.4             5.9              20.8             5.0               
 Other dermatology/skin toxicity  17.6             5.9              20.1             5.7               
 Leukopenia       17.0             0.7              19.6             1.6               
 Other constitutional symptoms  16.7             6.4              15.2             4.4               
 Cough            16.1             4.5              14.5             3.2               
 Infection (without neutropenia)  15.5             6.6              16.5             5.6               
 Pruritus         15.4             5.4              18.9             4.3               
 Other neurological toxicity  15.0             6.4              15.2             4.9               
 Constipation     14.8             5.1              14.4             4.1               
 Other renal/genitourinary toxicity  14.2             6.5              13.6             5.2               
 Arthralgia (joint pain)  13.6             4.8              12.3             3.0               
 Dyspnea (shortness of breath)  13.6             6.8              14.2             5.6               
 Fever in absence of neutropenia (ANC&lt;1.0 x 10  9  /L)  13.2             4.9              12.9             3.4               
 Sweating         12.7             4.6              8.5              2.8               
 Other hemorrhage  12.3             6.7              13.3             6.1               
 Weight gain      12.0             1.0              10.6             0.6               
 Alopecia         11.9             4.3              14.8             3.2               
 Dyspepsia/heartburn  11.5             0.6              10.9             0.5               
 Neutropenia/ granulocytopenia  11.5             3.1              16.1             4.1               
 Rigors/chills    11.0             4.6              10.2             3.0               
 Dizziness/lightheadedness  11.0             4.8              10.0             2.8               
 Creatinine increase  10.8             0.4              10.1             0.6               
 Flatulence       10.0             0.2              10.1             0.1               
 Stomatitis/pharyngitis (oral/pharyngeal mucositis)  9.2              5.4              10.0             4.3               
 Lymphopenia      6.0              0.7              10.1             1.9               
           Clinically relevant or severe abnormalities of routine hematologic or biochemistry laboratory values were not reported or evaluated in the Phase 3 GIST trials. Severe abnormal laboratory values reported in the Phase 2 GIST trial are presented in Table 13.
 

 Table 13 Laboratory Abnormalities in the Phase 2 Unresectable and/or Malignant Metastatic GIST Trial 
   1  CTC Grades: neutropenia (Grade 3 &gt;=0.5-1.0 x 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;0.5 x 10  9  /L), thrombocytopenia (Grade 3 &gt;=10-50 x 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;10 x 10  9  /L), anemia (Grade 3 &gt;=65-80 g/L, Grade 4 &lt;65 g/L), elevated creatinine (Grade 3 &gt;3-6 x upper limit normal range [ULN], Grade 4 &gt;6 x ULN), elevated bilirubin (Grade 3 &gt;3-10 x ULN, Grade 4 &gt;10 x ULN), elevated alkaline phosphatase, SGOT or SGPT (Grade 3 &gt;5-20 x ULN, Grade 4 &gt;20 x ULN), albumin (Grade 3 &lt;20 g/L)   
  
                    400 mg    (n=73)      600 mg    (n=74)     
                    %                %               
   CTC Grades      1        Grade 3          Grade 4          Grade 3          Grade 4         
   Hematology Parameters                                                                         
 - Anemia         3                0                8                1                 
 - Thrombocytopenia  0                0                1                0                 
 - Neutropenia    7                3                8                3                 
   Biochemistry Parameters                                                                         
 - Elevated Creatinine  0                0                3                0                 
 - Reduced Albumin  3                0                4                0                 
 - Elevated Bilirubin  1                0                1                3                 
 - Elevated Alkaline Phosphatase  0                0                3                0                 
 - Elevated SGOT (AST)  4                0                3                3                 
 - Elevated SGPT (ALT)  6                0                7                1                 
             Adjuvant Treatment of GIST  
 

 In Study 1, the majority of both Gleevec and placebo treated patients experienced at least one adverse reaction at some time. The most frequently reported adverse reactions were similar to those reported in other clinical studies in other patient populations and include diarrhea, fatigue, nausea, edema, decreased hemoglobin, rash, vomiting, and abdominal pain. No new adverse reactions were reported in the adjuvant GIST treatment setting that had not been previously reported in other patient populations including patients with unresectable and/or malignant metastatic GIST. Drug was discontinued for adverse reactions in 57 patients (17%) and 11 patients (3%) of the Gleevec and placebo treated patients respectively. Edema, gastrointestinal disturbances (nausea, vomiting, abdominal distention and diarrhea), fatigue, low hemoglobin, and rash were the most frequently reported adverse reactions at the time of discontinuation.



 In Study 2, discontinuation of therapy due to adverse reactions occurred in 15 patients (8%) and 27 patients (14%) of the Gleevec 12-month and 36-month treatment arms, respectively.  As in previous trials the most common adverse reactions were diarrhea, fatigue, nausea, edema, decreased hemoglobin, rash, vomiting, and abdominal pain.



 Adverse reactions, regardless of relationship to study drug, that were reported in at least 5% of the patients treated with Gleevec are shown in Table 14 (Study 1) and Table 15 (Study 2).  There were no deaths attributable to Gleevec treatment in either trial.



 Table 14: Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug Reported in Study 1 (&gt;=5% of Gleevec Treated Patients)(1) 
   (1)  All adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of patients are listed regardless of suspected relationship to treatment.A patient with multiple occurrences of an adverse reaction is counted only once in the adverse reaction category.   
  
                    All CTC Grades      CTC Grade 3 and above     
                    Gleevec    (n=337)      Placebo    (n=345)      Gleevec    (n=337)      Placebo    (n=345)     
   Preferred Term      %                %                %                %               
 Diarrhea         59.3             29.3             3.0              1.4               
 Fatigue          57.0             40.9             2.1              1.2               
 Nausea           53.1             27.8             2.4              1.2               
 Periorbital Edema  47.2             14.5             1.2              0                 
 Hemoglobin Decreased  46.9             27.0             0.6              0                 
 Peripheral Edema  26.7             14.8             0.3              0                 
 Rash (Exfoliative)  26.1             12.8             2.7              0                 
 Vomiting         25.5             13.9             2.4              0.6               
 Abdominal Pain   21.1             22.3             3.0              1.4               
 Headache         19.3             20.3             0.6              0                 
 Dyspepsia        17.2             13.0             0.9              0                 
 Anorexia         16.9             8.7              0.3              0                 
 Weight Increased  16.9             11.6             0.3              0                 
 Liver enzymes (ALT) Increased  16.6             13.0             2.7              0                 
 Muscle spasms    16.3             3.3              0                0                 
 Neutrophil Count Decreased  16.0             6.1              3.3              0.9               
 Arthralgia       15.1             14.5             0                0.3               
 White Blood Cell Count Decreased  14.5             4.3              0.6              0.3               
 Constipation     12.8             17.7             0                0.3               
 Dizziness        12.5             10.7             0                0.3               
 Liver Enzymes (AST) Increased  12.2             7.5              2.1              0                 
 Myalgia          12.2             11.6             0                0.3               
 Blood Creatinine Increased  11.6             5.8              0                0.3               
 Cough            11.0             11.3             0                0                 
 Pruritus         11.0             7.8              0.9              0                 
 Weight Decreased  10.1             5.2              0                0                 
 Hyperglycemia    9.8              11.3             0.6              1.7               
 Insomnia         9.8              7.2              0.9              0                 
 Lacrimation Increased  9.8              3.8              0                0                 
 Alopecia         9.5              6.7              0                0                 
 Flatulence       8.9              9.6              0                0                 
 Rash             8.9              5.2              0.9              0                 
 Abdominal Distension  7.4              6.4              0.3              0.3               
 Back Pain        7.4              8.1              0.6              0                 
 Pain in Extremity  7.4              7.2              0.3              0                 
 Hypokalemia      7.1              2.0              0.9              0.6               
 Depression       6.8              6.4              0.9              0.6               
 Facial Edema     6.8              1.2              0.3              0                 
 Blood Alkaline Phosphatase Increased  6.5              7.5              0                0                 
 Dry skin         6.5              5.2              0                0                 
 Dysgeusia        6.5              2.9              0                0                 
 Abdominal Pain Upper  6.2              6.4              0.3              0                 
 Neuropathy Peripheral  5.9              6.4              0                0                 
 Hypocalcemia     5.6              1.7              0.3              0                 
 Leukopenia       5.0              2.6              0.3              0                 
 Platelet Count Decreased  5.0              3.5              0                0                 
 Stomatitis       5.0              1.7              0.6              0                 
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection  5.0              3.5              0                0                 
 Vision Blurred   5.0              2.3              0                0                 
          Table 15: Adverse Reactions Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug by Preferred Term All Grades and 3/4 Grades (&gt;=5% of Gleevec Treated Patients) Study 2(1) 
   (1)  All adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of patients are listed regardless of suspected relationship to treatment.A patient with multiple occurrences of an adverse reaction is counted only once in the adverse reaction category.   
  
   Preferred Term      All CTC Grades      CTC Grades 3 and above     
                    Gleevec    12 Months    (N=194)    %      Gleevec    36 Months    (N=198)    %      Gleevec    12 Months    (N=194)    %      Gleevec    36 Months    (N=198)    %     
 Patients with at least one AE  99.0             100.0            20.1             32.8              
 Hemoglobin decreased  72.2             80.3             0.5              0.5               
 Periorbital edema  59.3             74.2             0.5              1.0               
 Blood lactate dehydrogenase increased  43.3             60.1             0                0                 
 Diarrhea         43.8             54.0             0.5              2.0               
 Nausea           44.8             51.0             1.5              0.5               
 Muscle spasms    30.9             49.0             0.5              1.0               
 Fatigue          48.5             48.5             1.0              0.5               
 White blood cell count decreased  34.5             47.0             2.1              3.0               
 Pain             25.8             45.5             1.0              3.0               
 Blood creatinine increased  30.4             44.4             0                0                 
 Edema peripheral  33.0             40.9             0.5              1.0               
 Dermatitis       29.4             38.9             2.1              1.5               
 Aspartate aminotransferase increased  30.9             37.9             1.5              3.0               
 Alanine aminotransferase increased  28.9             34.3             2.1              3.0               
 Neutrophil count decreased  24.2             33.3             4.6              5.1               
 Hypoproteinemia  23.7             31.8             0                0                 
 Infection        13.9             27.8             1.5              2.5               
 Weight increased  13.4             26.8             0                0.5               
 Pruritus         12.9             25.8             0                0                 
 Flatulence       19.1             24.7             1.0              0.5               
 Vomiting         10.8             22.2             0.5              1.0               
 Dyspepsia        17.5             21.7             0.5              1.0               
 Hypoalbuminemia  11.9             21.2             0                0                 
 Edema            10.8             19.7             0                0.5               
 Abdominal distension  11.9             19.2             0.5              0                 
 Headache         8.2              18.2             0                0                 
 Lacrimation increased  18.0             17.7             0                0                 
 Arthralgia       8.8              17.2             0                1.0               
 Blood alkaline phosphatase increased  10.8             16.7             0                0.5               
 Dyspnea          6.2              16.2             0.5              1.5               
 Myalgia          9.3              15.2             0                1.0               
 Platelet count decreased  11.3             14.1             0                0                 
 Blood bilirubin increased  11.3             13.1             0                0                 
 Dysgeusia        9.3              12.6             0                0                 
 Paresthesia      5.2              12.1             0                0.5               
 Vision blurred   10.8             11.1             1.0              0.5               
 Alopecia         11.3             10.6             0                0                 
 Decreased appetite  9.8              10.1             0                0                 
 Constipation     8.8              9.6              0                0                 
 Pyrexia          6.2              9.6              0                0                 
 Depression       3.1              8.1              0                0                 
 Abdominal pain   2.6              7.6              0                0                 
 Conjunctivitis   5.2              7.6              0                0                 
 Photosensitivity reaction  3.6              7.1              0                0                 
 Dizziness        4.6              6.6              0.5              0                 
 Hemorrhage       3.1              6.6              0                0                 
 Dry skin         6.7              6.1              0.5              0                 
 Nasopharyngitis  1.0              6.1              0                0.5               
 Palpitations     5.2              5.1              0                0                 
             6.10     Additional Data from Multiple Clinical Trials
   The following adverse reactions have been reported during clinical trials of Gleevec.



   Cardiac Disorders:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: palpitations, pericardial effusion



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: congestive cardiac failure, tachycardia, pulmonary edema



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, cardiac arrest, myocardial infarction, angina pectoris



   Vascular Disorders:   



 Estimated 1%-10%: flushing, hemorrhage



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: hypertension, hypotension, peripheral coldness, Raynauds phenomenon, hematoma, subdural hematoma



   Investigations:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: blood CPK increased, blood amylase increased



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: blood LDH increased



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  :



 Estimated 1%-10%: dry skin, alopecia, face edema, erythema, photosensitivity reaction, nail disorder, purpura



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: exfoliative dermatitis, bullous eruption, psoriasis, rash pustular, contusion, sweating increased, urticaria, ecchymosis, increased tendency to bruise, hypotrichosis, skin hypopigmentation, skin hyperpigmentation, onychoclasis, folliculitis, petechiae, erythema multiforme



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: vesicular rash, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis (Sweet's syndrome), nail discoloration, angioneurotic edema, leucocytoclastic vasculitis



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:   



 Estimated 1%-10%: abdominal distention, gastroesophageal reflux, dry mouth, gastritis



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: gastric ulcer, stomatitis, mouth ulceration, eructation, melena, esophagitis, ascites, hematemesis, chelitis, dysphagia, pancreatitis



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: colitis, ileus, inflammatory bowel disease



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: weakness, anasarca, chills



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: malaise



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: pancytopenia, febrile neutropenia, lymphopenia, eosinophila



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: thrombocythemia, bone marrow depression, lymphadenopathy



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: hepatitis, jaundice



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: hepatic failure and hepatic necrosis  1   



   Immune System Disorders:  



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: angioedema



   Infections and Infestations:  



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: sepsis, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, cellulitis, urinary tract infection, gastroenteritis



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: fungal infection



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:   



 Estimated 1%-10%: weight decreased, decreased appetite



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: dehydration, gout, increased appetite, hyperuricemia, hypercalcemia, hyperglycemia, hyponatremia, hyperkalemia, hypomagnesemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: joint swelling



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: joint and muscle stiffness, muscular weakness, arthritis



   Nervous System/Psychiatric Disorders:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: paresthesia, hypesthesia



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: syncope, peripheral neuropathy, somnolence, migraine, memory impairment, libido decreased, sciatica, restless leg syndrome, tremor



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: increased intracranial pressure  1  , confusional state, convulsions, optic neuritis



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: renal failure acute, urinary frequency increased, hematuria, renal pain



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: breast enlargement, menorrhagia, sexual dysfunction, gynecomastia, erectile dysfunction, menstruation irregular, nipple pain, scrotal edema



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: epistaxis



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: pleural effusion



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: interstitial pneumonitis, pulmonary fibrosis, pleuritic pain, pulmonary hypertension, pulmonary hemorrhage



   Eye, Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  



 Estimated 1%-10%: conjunctivitis, vision blurred, orbital edema, conjunctival hemorrhage, dry eye



 Estimated 0.1%-1%: vertigo, tinnitus, eye irritation, eye pain, scleral hemorrhage, retinal hemorrhage, blepharitis, macular edema, hearing loss, cataract



 Estimated 0.01%-0.1%: papilledema  1  , glaucoma



   1  Including some fatalities



   6.11     Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Gleevec. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Nervous System Disorders  : cerebral edema  1   



   Eye Disorders  : vitreous hemorrhage



   Cardiac Disorders  : pericarditis, cardiac tamponade  1  



   Vascular Disorders  : thrombosis/embolism, anaphylactic shock



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  : acute respiratory failure  1  , interstitial lung disease



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : ileus/intestinal obstruction, tumor hemorrhage/tumor necrosis, gastrointestinal perforation  1   [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ],     diverticulitis, gastric antral vascular ectasia



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  lichenoid keratosis, lichen planus, toxic epidermal necrolysis, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome, drug rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS)



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  avascular necrosis/hip osteonecrosis, rhabdomyolysis/myopathy, growth retardation in children



   Reproduction Disorders  : hemorrhagic corpus luteum/hemorrhagic ovarian cyst



   1  Including some fatalities
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Edema and severe fluid retention have occurred. Weigh patients regularly and manage unexpected rapid weight gain by drug interruption and diuretics (  5.1  ,  6.1  ,  6.9  ) 
 *  Cytopenias, particularly anemia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia, have occurred. Manage with dose reduction or dose interruption and in rare cases discontinuation of treatment. Perform complete blood counts weekly for the first month, biweekly for the second month, and periodically thereafter (  5.2  ) 
 *  Severe congestive heart failure and left ventricular dysfunction have been reported, particularly in patients with comorbidities and risk factors. Patients with cardiac disease or risk factors for cardiac failure should be monitored and treated (  5.3  ) 
 *  Severe hepatotoxicity including fatalities may occur. Assess liver function before initiation of treatment and monthly thereafter or as clinically indicated. Monitor liver function when combined with chemotherapy known to be associated with liver dysfunction (  5.4  ) 
 *  Grade 3/4 hemorrhage has been reported in clinical studies in patients with newly diagnosed CML and with GIST. GI tumor sites may be the source of GI bleeds in GIST (  5.5  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal perforations, some fatal, have been reported (  5.6  ) 
 *  Cardiogenic shock/left ventricular dysfunction has been associated with the initiation of Gleevec in patients with conditions associated with high eosinophil levels (e.g., HES, MDS/MPD and ASM) (  5.7  ) 
 *  Bullous dermatologic reactions (e.g., erythema multiforme and Stevens-Johnson syndrome) have been reported with the use of Gleevec (  5.8  ) 
 *  Hypothyroidism has been reported in thyroidectomy patients undergoing levothyroxine replacement. Closely monitor TSH levels in such patients (  5.9  ) 
 *  Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be apprised of the potential harm to the fetus (  5.10  ,  8.1  ) 
 *  Growth retardation occurring in children and pre-adolescents receiving Gleevec has been reported. Close monitoring of growth in children under Gleevec treatment is recommended (  5.11  ,  6.11  ) 
 *  Tumor lysis syndrome. Close monitoring is recommended (  5.12  ) 
 *  Reports of motor vehicle accidents have been received in patients receiving Gleevec. Caution patients about driving a car or operating machinery (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Fluid Retention and Edema



   Gleevec is often associated with edema and occasionally serious fluid retention [ see Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]. Patients should be weighed and monitored regularly for signs and symptoms of fluid retention. An unexpected rapid weight gain should be carefully investigated and appropriate treatment provided. The probability of edema was increased with higher Gleevec dose and age &gt;65 years in the CML studies. Severe superficial edema was reported in 1.5% of newly diagnosed CML patients taking Gleevec, and in 2%-6% of other adult CML patients taking Gleevec. In addition, other severe fluid retention (e.g., pleural effusion, pericardial effusion, pulmonary edema, and ascites) reactions were reported in 1.3% of newly diagnosed CML patients taking Gleevec, and in 2%-6% of other adult CML patients taking Gleevec. Severe fluid retention was reported in 9% to 13.1% of patients taking Gleevec for GIST [ see Adverse Reactions (6.9)  ]. In a randomized trial in patients with newly diagnosed Ph+CML in chronic phase comparing Gleevec and nilotinib, severe (Grade 3 or 4) fluid retention occurred in 2.5% of patients receiving Gleevec and in 3.9% of patients receiving nilotinib 300 mg bid. Effusions (including pleural effusion, pericardial effusion, ascites) or pulmonary edema were observed in 2.1% (none were Grade 3 or 4) of patients in the Gleevec arm and 2.2% (0.7% Grade 3 or 4) of patients in the nilotinib 300 mg bid arm.  



    5.2     Hematologic Toxicity



  Treatment with Gleevec is associated with anemia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia. Complete blood counts should be performed weekly for the first month, biweekly for the second month, and periodically thereafter as clinically indicated (for example, every 2-3 months). In CML, the occurrence of these cytopenias is dependent on the stage of disease and is more frequent in patients with accelerated phase CML or blast crisis than in patients with chronic phase CML. In pediatric CML patients the most frequent toxicities observed were Grade 3 or 4 cytopenias including neutropenia, thrombocytopenia and anemia. These generally occur within the first several months of therapy [ see Dosage and Administration (2.12)  ].



    5.3     Congestive Heart Failure and Left Ventricular Dysfunction



   Congestive heart failure and left ventricular dysfunction have been reported in patients taking Gleevec. Most of the patients with reported cardiac reactions have had other co-morbidities and risk factors, including advanced age and previous medical history of cardiac disease. In an international randomized phase 3 study in 1,106 patients with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML in chronic phase, severe cardiac failure and left ventricular dysfunction were observed in 0.7% of patients taking Gleevec compared to 0.9% of patients taking IFN + Ara-C. In another randomized trial with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML patients in chronic phase that compared Gleevec and nilotinib, cardiac failure was observed in 1.1% of patient in the Gleevec arm and 2.2% of patients in the nilotinib 300 mg bid arm and severe (Grade 3 or 4) cardiac failure occurred in 0.7% of patients in each group. Patients with cardiac disease or risk factors for cardiac or history of renal failure should be monitored carefully and any patient with signs or symptoms consistent with cardiac or renal failure should be evaluated and treated.  



    5.4     Hepatotoxicity



  Hepatotoxicity, occasionally severe, may occur with Gleevec [ see Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]. Cases of fatal liver failure and severe liver injury requiring liver transplants have been reported with both short-term and long-term use of Gleevec. Liver function (transaminases, bilirubin, and alkaline phosphatase) should be monitored before initiation of treatment and monthly, or as clinically indicated. Laboratory abnormalities should be managed with Gleevec interruption and/or dose reduction [ see Dosage and Administration (2.12)  ].



 When Gleevec is combined with chemotherapy, liver toxicity in the form of transaminase elevation and hyperbilirubinemia has been observed. Additionally, there have been reports of acute liver failure. Monitoring of hepatic function is recommended.



    5.5     Hemorrhage



   In a trial of Gleevec versus IFN+Ara-C in patients with the newly diagnosed CML, 1.8% of patients had Grade 3/4 hemorrhage. In the Phase 3 unresectable or metastatic GIST studies, 211 patients (12.9%) reported Grade 3/4 hemorrhage at any site. In the Phase 2 unresectable or metastatic GIST study, 7 patients (5%) had a total of 8 CTC Grade 3/4 hemorrhages; gastrointestinal (GI) (3 patients), intra-tumoral (3 patients) or both (1 patient). Gastrointestinal tumor sites may have been the source of GI hemorrhages. In a randomized trial in patients with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML in chronic phase comparing Gleevec and nilotinib, GI hemorrhage occurred in 1.4% of patients in the Gleevec arm, and in 2.9% of patients in the nilotinib 300 mg bid arm. None of these events were Grade 3 or 4 in the Gleevec arm; 0.7% were Grade 3 or 4 in the nilotinib 300 mg bid arm. In addition, gastric antral vascular ectasia has been reported in postmarketing experience.  



    5.6     Gastrointestinal Disorders



  Gleevec is sometimes associated with GI irritation. Gleevec should be taken with food and a large glass of water to minimize this problem. There have been rare reports, including fatalities, of gastrointestinal perforation.



    5.7     Hypereosinophilic Cardiac Toxicity



  In patients with hypereosinophilic syndrome with occult infiltration of HES cells within the myocardium, cases of cardiogenic shock/left ventricular dysfunction have been associated with HES cell degranulation upon the initiation of Gleevec therapy. The condition was reported to be reversible with the administration of systemic steroids, circulatory support measures and temporarily withholding Gleevec.



 Myelodysplastic/myeloproliferative disease and systemic mastocytosis may be associated with high eosinophil levels. Performance of an echocardiogram and determination of serum troponin should therefore be considered in patients with HES/CEL, and in patients with MDS/MPD or ASM associated with high eosinophil levels. If either is abnormal, the prophylactic use of systemic steroids (1-2 mg/kg) for one to two weeks concomitantly with Gleevec should be considered at the initiation of therapy.



    5.8     Dermatologic Toxicities



  Bullous dermatologic reactions, including erythema multiforme and Stevens-Johnson syndrome, have been reported with use of Gleevec. In some cases of bullous dermatologic reactions, including erythema multiforme and Stevens-Johnson syndrome reported during postmarketing surveillance, a recurrent dermatologic reaction was observed upon rechallenge. Several foreign postmarketing reports have described cases in which patients tolerated the reintroduction of Gleevec therapy after resolution or improvement of the bullous reaction. In these instances, Gleevec was resumed at a dose lower than that at which the reaction occurred and some patients also received concomitant treatment with corticosteroids or antihistamines.



    5.9     Hypothyroidism



  Clinical cases of hypothyroidism have been reported in thyroidectomy patients undergoing levothyroxine replacement during treatment with Gleevec. TSH levels should be closely monitored in such patients.



    5.10     Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  Gleevec can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Imatinib mesylate was teratogenic in rats when administered during organogenesis at doses approximately equal to the maximum human dose of 800 mg/day based on body surface area. Significant post-implantation loss was seen in female rats administered imatinib mesylate at doses approximately one-half the maximum human dose of 800 mg/day based on body surface area. Sexually active female patients of reproductive potential taking Gleevec should use highly effective contraception. If this drug is used during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].



    5.11     Children and Adolescents



  Growth retardation has been reported in children and pre-adolescents receiving Gleevec. The long term effects of prolonged treatment with Gleevec on growth in children are unknown. Therefore, close monitoring of growth in children under Gleevec treatment is recommended [ see Adverse Reactions (6.11)  ].



    5.12     Tumor Lysis Syndrome



  Cases of Tumor Lysis Syndrome (TLS), including fatal cases, have been reported in patients with CML, GIST, ALL and eosinophilic leukemia receiving Gleevec. The patients at risk of TLS are those with tumors having a high proliferative rate or high tumor burden prior to treatment. These patients should be monitored closely and appropriate precautions taken. Due to possible occurrence of TLS, correction of clinically significant dehydration and treatment of high uric acid levels are recommended prior to initiation of Gleevec. 



    5.13     Driving and Using Machinery



  Reports of motor vehicle accidents have been received in patients receiving Gleevec. While most of these reports are not suspected to be caused by Gleevec, patients should be advised that they may experience undesirable effects such as dizziness, blurred vision or somnolence during treatment with Gleevec. Therefore, caution should be recommended when driving a car or operating machinery.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
