<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="gliadel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the label:



 *  Seizures [(see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Intracranial Hypertension [(see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Impaired Neurosurgical Wound Healing [(see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Meningitis [(see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
   *  Newly-Diagnosed High-Grade Malignant Glioma: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;10% and between arm difference &gt;=4%) are cerebral edema, asthenia, nausea, vomiting, constipation, wound healing abnormalities and depression (  6.1  ). 
 *  Recurrent High-Grade Malignant Glioma: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;10% and between arm difference &gt;=4%) are urinary tract infection, wound healing abnormalities and fever (  6.1  ). 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Arbor Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-866-516-4950 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Newly-Diagnosed High-Grade Malignant Glioma  



 The safety of GLIADEL Wafers was evaluated in a multicenter, randomized (1:1), double-blind, placebo controlled trial of 240 adult patients with newly-diagnosed high-grade malignant glioma who received up to eight GLIADEL Wafers or matched placebo implanted against the resection surfaces after maximal tumor resection (Study 1).



 The population in Study 1 was 67% male and 97% White, and the median age was 53 years (range: 21-72). Eighty-seven percent had a Karnofsky performance status &gt;= 70 and 71% had a Karnofsky performance status of &gt;= 80%. Seventy-eight percent had a histologic subtype of glioblastoma multiforme as determined by central pathology review. Thirty-eight percent of patients received 8 wafers and 78% received &gt;= 6 wafers. Starting three weeks after surgery, 80% of patients received standard limited field radiation therapy (RT) described as 55-60 Gy delivered in 28 to 30 fractions over six weeks; an additional 11% received no radiotherapy and the remainder received non-standard radiotherapy or a combination of standard and non-standard radiotherapy. At the time of progression, 12% received systemic chemotherapy.



 Deaths occurred within 30 days of wafer implantation in 5 (4%) of patients receiving GLIADEL Wafers compared to 2 (2%) of patients receiving placebo. Deaths on the GLIADEL arm resulted from cerebral hematoma/edema (n=3), pulmonary embolism (n=1) and acute coronary event (n=1). Deaths on the placebo arm resulted from sepsis (n=1) and malignant disease (n=1).



 The incidence of common adverse reactions in GLIADEL Wafer-treated patients is listed in Table 1. The incidence of local adverse reactions is shown in Table 2.



 Table 1. Per-Patient Incidence of Adverse Reactions Occurring in Gliadel Wafer-Treated Patients with Newly-Diagnosed High Grade Malignant Glioma (Study 1) (Between Arm Difference of &gt;= 4%) 
 BODY SYSTEM                                                    GLIADEL WaferN=120       PlaceboN=120       
 %                                                                      %             
  
 GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                                     
   Nausea                                                               22                    17            
   Vomiting                                                             21                    16            
   Constipation                                                         19                    12            
   Abdominal pain                                                       8                     2             
 GENERAL DISORDERS ANDADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITION             
   Asthenia                                                             22                    15            
   Chest pain                                                           5                     0             
 INJURY, POISONING AND PROCEDURALCOMPLICATIONS                  
   Wound healing abnormalities                                          16                    12            
 MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVETISSUE DISORDERS                 
   Back pain                                                            7                     3             
 PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                                          
   Depression                                                           16                    10            
        Table 2. Incidence of Local Adverse Reactions, Study 1Not seen at baseline or worsened if present at baseline. 
 Local Adverse Reactions                                       GLIADEL Wafer N=120       PlaceboN=120       
 %                                                                      %             
  
 Intracranial hypertension                                              9                     2             
 Cerebral hemorrhage                                                    6                     4             
 Brain abscess                                                          6                     4             
 Brain cyst                                                             2                     3             
 Cerebral edema                                                         23                    19            
             Recurrent High-Grade Malignant Glioma  
 

 The safety of GLIADEL Wafers was evaluated in a multicenter, randomized (1:1), double-blind, placebo controlled trial of 222 patients with recurrent high-grade malignant glioma who received up to eight GLIADEL Wafers or matched placebo implanted against the resection surfaces after maximal tumor resection (Study 2). Patients were required to have had prior definitive external beam radiation therapy sufficient to disqualify them from additional radiation therapy. All patients were eligible to receive chemotherapy which was withheld at least four weeks (six weeks for nitrosoureas) prior to and two weeks after surgery.



 The population in Study 2 was 64% male, 92% White, and the median age was 49 years (range: 19-80). Sixty-five percent had a histologic subtype of glioblastoma multiforme, 26% had anaplastic astrocytoma or another anaplastic variant, 73% had a Karnofsky performance status &gt;= 70, 53% had a Karnofsky performance status of &gt;= 80%, 73% had only one prior surgery, and 46% had prior treatment with nitrosourea. Eighty-one percent of patients received 8 wafers and 96% received &gt;= 6 wafers.



 Sixty-four severe adverse reactions were reported in 43(39%) patients receiving GLIADEL Wafers. Adverse reactions in GLIADEL Wafer-treated patients are shown in Table 3. Meningitis occurred in four patients receiving GLIADEL Wafers and in no patients receiving placebo. Bacterial meningitis was confirmed in two patients: the first with onset four days following GLIADEL Wafer implantation; the second following resection for tumor recurrence 155 days following GLIADEL Wafer implantation. One case, attributed to chemical meningitis resolved following steroid treatment. The cause of the fourth case was undetermined but resolved following antibiotic treatment.



 Table 3. Per-Patient Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Gliadel Wafer-Treated Patients with Recurrent High-Grade Malignant Glioma (Study 2) (Between Arm Difference of &gt;= 4%) 
 BODY SYSTEM                                                   GLIADEL Wafer N=110       PlaceboN=112       
                                                                        %                     %             
  
 GENERAL                                                        
   Fever                                                                12                    8             
 INFECTIOUS                                                     
   Urinary tract infections                                             21                    17            
 INJURY, POISONING AND PROCEDURALCOMPLICATIONS                  
   Wound healing abnormalities                                          14                    5             
         The incidence of seizures is shown in Table 4. The incidence of hydrocephalus, cerebral edema and intracranial hypertension is shown in Table 5.
 

 Table 4. Incidence of Seizures, Study 2 
 Adverse Reaction                                               GLIADEL WaferN=110       PlaceboN=112       
                                                                        %                     %             
  
 Patients with seizures                                                               
   Any seizures after wafer implantation                                37                    29            
   New or worsening seizures                                            20                    20            
 Time to new or worsening seizures (days)                                             
   Mean (SD)                                                       26.09 (0.75)         62.36 (48.66)       
   Median                                                              3.5                   61.0           
        Table 5. Hydrocephalus and Cerebral Edema, Study 2Not seen at baseline or worsened if present at baseline. 
 Adverse Reaction                                              GLIADEL Wafer N=110       PlaceboN=112       
 %                                                                      %             
  
 Hydrocephalus                                                          5                     2             
 Cerebral edema                                                         4                     1             
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Seizures: Monitor patients for seizures following implantation (  5.1  ). 
 *  Intracranial hypertension: Monitor patients for signs of increased intracranial pressure (  5.2  ). 
 *  Impaired neurosurgical wound healing: Monitor patients for complications of craniotomy (  5.3  ). 
 *  Meningitis: Monitor patients for signs of bacterial or chemical meningitis (  5.4  ). 
 *  Wafer migration: Monitor patients for signs of obstructive hydrocephalus (  5.5  ). 
 *  Embryo-fetal toxicity: Can cause fetal harm (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Seizures



  Seizures occurred in 37% of patients treated with GLIADEL Wafers for recurrent glioma in Study 2. New or worsening (treatment emergent) seizures occurred in 20% of patients; 54% of treatment emergent seizures occurred within the first 5 post-operative days [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  The median time to onset of the first new or worsened post-operative seizure was four days. Institute optimal anti-seizure therapy prior to surgery. Monitor patients for seizures postoperatively.



    5.2 Intracranial Hypertension



  Brain edema occurred in 23% of patients with newly diagnosed glioma treated with GLIADEL Wafers in Study 1. Additionally, one GLIADEL-treated patient experienced intracerebral mass effect unresponsive to corticosteroids which led to brain herniation ( see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ). Monitor patients closely for intracranial hypertension related to brain edema, inflammation, or necrosis of the brain tissue surrounding the resection. In refractory cases, consider re-operation and removal of GLIADEL Wafers or Wafer remnants.



    5.3 Impaired Neurosurgical Wound Healing



  Impaired neurosurgical wound healing including wound dehiscence, delayed wound healing, and subdural, subgleal, or wound effusions occur with GLIADEL Wafer treatment. In Study 1, 16% of GLIADEL Wafer-treated patients with newly diagnosed glioma experienced impaired intracranial wound healing and 5% had cerebrospinal fluid leaks. In Study 2, 14% of GLIADEL Wafer-treated patients with recurrent glioma experienced wound healing abnormalities [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  Monitor patients post-operatively for impaired neurosurgical wound healing.



    5.4 Meningitis



  Meningitis occurred in 4% of patients with recurrent glioma receiving GLIADEL Wafers in Study 2. Two cases of meningitis were bacterial; one patient required removal of the Wafers four days after implantation; the other developed meningitis following reoperation for recurrent tumor. One case was diagnosed as chemical meningitis and resolved following steroid treatment. In one case the cause was unspecified, but meningitis resolved following antibiotic treatment. Monitor postoperatively for signs of meningitis and central nervous system infection.



    5.5 Wafer Migration



  GLIADEL Wafer migration can occur. To reduce the risk of obstructive hydrocephalus due to wafer migration into the ventricular system, close any communication larger than the diameter of a Wafer between the surgical resection cavity and the ventricular system prior to Wafer implantation. Monitor patients for signs of obstructive hydrocephalus.



    5.6 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  GLIADEL Wafers can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Carmustine, the active component of GLIADEL Wafer, is embryotoxic and teratogenic in rats at exposures less than the exposure at the recommended human dose on a mg/m  2  basis and embryotoxic in rabbits at exposures similar to the exposure at the recommended human dose on a mg/m  2  basis. Advise females of reproductive potential to avoid pregnancy after implantation of GLIADEL Wafers. If the patient becomes pregnant after GLIADEL Wafer implantation, warn the patient about the potential hazard to the fetus [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  and  8.6)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
