<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="glucophage" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In a US double-blind clinical study of GLUCOPHAGE in patients with type 2 diabetes, a total of 141 patients received GLUCOPHAGE therapy (up to 2550 mg per day) and 145 patients received placebo. Adverse reactions reported in greater than 5% of the GLUCOPHAGE patients, and that were more common in GLUCOPHAGE- than placebo-treated patients, are listed in  Table 11  .



 Table 11: Most Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;5.0 Percent) in a Placebo-Controlled Clinical Study of GLUCOPHAGE Monotherapy* 
   Adverse Reaction                         GLUCOPHAGE    Monotherapy    (n=141)      Placebo    (n=145)            
                                            % of Patients                 
  
 *  Reactions that were more common in GLUCOPHAGE- than placebo-treated patients.   
  
  Diarrhea                                 53.2                           11.7                           
  Nausea/Vomiting                          25.5                           8.3                            
  Flatulence                               12.1                           5.5                            
  Asthenia                                 9.2                            5.5                            
  Indigestion                              7.1                            4.1                            
  Abdominal Discomfort                     6.4                            4.8                            
  Headache                                 5.7                            4.8                            
         Diarrhea led to discontinuation of study medication in 6% of patients treated with GLUCOPHAGE. Additionally, the following adverse reactions were reported in &gt;=1.0% to &lt;=5.0% of GLUCOPHAGE patients and were more commonly reported with GLUCOPHAGE than placebo: abnormal stools, hypoglycemia, myalgia, lightheaded, dyspnea, nail disorder, rash, sweating increased, taste disorder, chest discomfort, chills, flu syndrome, flushing, palpitation.
 

 In worldwide clinical trials over 900 patients with type 2 diabetes have been treated with GLUCOPHAGE XR in placebo- and active-controlled studies. In placebo-controlled trials, 781 patients were administered GLUCOPHAGE XR and 195 patients received placebo. Adverse reactions reported in greater than 5% of the GLUCOPHAGE XR patients, and that were more common in GLUCOPHAGE XR- than placebo-treated patients, are listed in  Table 12  .



 Table 12: Most Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;5.0 Percent) in Placebo-Controlled Studies of GLUCOPHAGE XR* 
   Adverse Reaction                         GLUCOPHAGE XR    (n=781)       Placebo    (n=195)            
                                            % of Patients                 
  
 *  Reactions that were more common in GLUCOPHAGE XR- than placebo-treated patients.   
  
  Diarrhea                                 9.6                            2.6                            
  Nausea/Vomiting                          6.5                            1.5                            
         Diarrhea led to discontinuation of study medication in 0.6% of patients treated with GLUCOPHAGE XR. Additionally, the following adverse reactions were reported in &gt;=1.0% to &lt;=5.0% of GLUCOPHAGE XR patients and were more commonly reported with GLUCOPHAGE XR than placebo: abdominal pain, constipation, distention abdomen, dyspepsia/heartburn, flatulence, dizziness, headache, upper respiratory infection, taste disturbance.
 

 Liver function test abnormalities or hepatitis, resolving upon metformin discontinuation, have been reported very rarely.



   Pediatric Patients

  In clinical trials with GLUCOPHAGE in pediatric patients with type 2 diabetes, the profile of adverse reactions was similar to that observed in adults.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
