<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="glucovance" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  GLUCOVANCE

  In double-blind clinical trials involving GLUCOVANCE as initial therapy or as second-line therapy, a total of 642 patients received GLUCOVANCE, 312 received metformin therapy, 324 received glyburide therapy, and 161 received placebo. The percent of patients reporting events and types of adverse events reported in clinical trials of GLUCOVANCE (all strengths) as initial therapy and second-line therapy are listed in  Table 6  .



 Table 6: Most Common Clinical Adverse Events (&gt;5%) in Double-Blind Clinical Studies of GLUCOVANCE Used as Initial or Second-Line Therapy 
   Adverse Event             Number (%) of Patients     
   PlaceboN=161              GlyburideN=324       MetforminN=312       GLUCOVANCEN=642     
  
 Upper respiratory infection  22 (13.7)            57 (17.6)            51 (16.3)            111 (17.3)            
 Diarrhea                  9 (5.6)              20 (6.2)             64 (20.5)            109 (17.0)            
 Headache                  17 (10.6)            37 (11.4)            29 (9.3)             57 (8.9)              
 Nausea/vomiting           10 (6.2)             17 (5.2)             38 (12.2)            49 (7.6)              
 Abdominal pain            6 (3.7)              10 (3.1)             25 (8.0)             44 (6.9)              
 Dizziness                 7 (4.3)              18 (5.6)             12 (3.8)             35 (5.5)              
      In a controlled clinical trial of rosiglitazone versus placebo in patients treated with GLUCOVANCE (n=365), 181 patients received GLUCOVANCE with rosiglitazone and 184 received GLUCOVANCE with placebo.
 

 Edema was reported in 7.7% (14/181) of patients treated with rosiglitazone compared to 2.2% (4/184) of patients treated with placebo. A mean weight gain of 3 kg was observed in rosiglitazone-treated patients.



 Disulfiram-like reactions have very rarely been reported in patients treated with glyburide tablets.



   Hypoglycemia

  In controlled clinical trials of GLUCOVANCE there were no hypoglycemic episodes requiring medical intervention and/or pharmacologic therapy; all events were managed by the patients. The incidence of reported symptoms of hypoglycemia (such as dizziness, shakiness, sweating, and hunger), in the initial therapy trial of GLUCOVANCE are summarized in  Table 7  . The frequency of hypoglycemic symptoms in patients treated with GLUCOVANCE 1.25 mg/250 mg was highest in patients with a baseline HbA1c&lt;7%, lower in those with a baseline HbA1cof between 7% and 8%, and was comparable to placebo and metformin in those with a baseline HbA1c&gt;8%. For patients with a baseline HbA1cbetween 8% and 11% treated with GLUCOVANCE 2.5 mg/500 mg as initial therapy, the frequency of hypoglycemic symptoms was 30% to 35%. As second-line therapy in patients inadequately controlled on sulfonylurea alone, approximately 6.8% of all patients treated with GLUCOVANCE experienced hypoglycemic symptoms. When rosiglitazone was added to GLUCOVANCE therapy, 22% of patients reported 1 or more fingerstick glucose measurements &lt;=50 mg/dL compared to 3.3% of placebo-treated patients. All hypoglycemic events were managed by the patients and only 1 patient discontinued for hypoglycemia. (See    PRECAUTIONS: General: Addition of Thiazolidinediones to GLUCOVANCE Therapy    .)



   Gastrointestinal Reactions

  The incidence of gastrointestinal (GI) side effects (diarrhea, nausea/vomiting, and abdominal pain) in the initial therapy trial are summarized in  Table 7  . Across all GLUCOVANCE trials, GI symptoms were the most common adverse events with GLUCOVANCE and were more frequent at higher dose levels. In controlled trials, &lt;2% of patients discontinued GLUCOVANCE therapy due to GI adverse events.



 Table 7: Treatment Emergent Symptoms of Hypoglycemia or Gastrointestinal Adverse Events in a Placebo- and Active-Controlled Trial of GLUCOVANCE as Initial Therapy 
   Variable                   PlaceboN=161      GlyburideTabletsN=160      MetforminTabletsN=159      GLUCOVANCE1.25 mg/250 mgTabletsN=158      GLUCOVANCE2.5 mg/500 mgTabletsN=162     
  
 Mean Final Dose            0 mg          5.3 mg        1317 mg       2.78 mg/557 mg      4.1 mg/824 mg        
 Number (%) of patients  with symptoms of  hypoglycemia  5 (3.1)       34 (21.3)     5 (3.1)       18 (11.4)           61 (37.7)            
 Number (%) of patients  with gastrointestinal  adverse events  39 (24.2)     38 (23.8)     69 (43.3)     50 (31.6)           62 (38.3)            
      In postmarketing reports cholestatic jaundice and hepatitis may occur rarely which may progress to liver failure; GLUCOVANCE should be discontinued if this occurs.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    PATIENT INFORMATION

ABOUT GLUCOVANCE  (r)   (Glyburide and Metformin

HCl) Tablets  



   

    WARNING: A small number of people

who have taken metformin hydrochloride have developed a serious condition

called lactic acidosis. Properly functioning kidneys are needed to help prevent

lactic acidosis. Most people with kidney problems should not take GLUCOVANCE.

(See Question Nos. 9-13.)  



     Q1. Why do I need to take GLUCOVANCE?  



 Your

doctor has prescribed GLUCOVANCE to treat your type 2 diabetes. This is also

known as non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus.



   Q2.

What is type 2 diabetes?  



 People with diabetes

are not able to make enough insulin and/or respond normally to the insulin

their body does make. When this happens, sugar (glucose) builds up in the

blood. This can lead to serious medical problems, including kidney damage,

amputations, and blindness. Diabetes is also closely linked to heart disease.

The main goal of treating diabetes is to lower your blood sugar to a normal

level.



   Q3. Why is it important to control type

2 diabetes?  



 The main goal of treating diabetes

is to lower your blood sugar to a normal level. Studies have shown that good

control of blood sugar may prevent or delay complications, such as heart disease,

kidney disease, or blindness.



   Q4. How is type

2 diabetes usually controlled?  



 High blood

sugar can be lowered by diet and exercise, a number of oral medications, and

insulin injections. Before taking GLUCOVANCE you should first try to control

your diabetes by exercise and weight loss. Even if you are taking GLUCOVANCE,

you should still exercise and follow the diet recommended for your diabetes.



   Q5.

Does GLUCOVANCE work differently from other glucose-control medications?  



 Yes,

it does. GLUCOVANCE combines 2 glucose-lowering drugs, glyburide and metformin.

These 2 drugs work together to improve the different metabolic defects found

in type 2 diabetes. Glyburide lowers blood sugar primarily by causing more

of the body's own insulin to be released, and metformin lowers blood sugar,

in part, by helping your body use your own insulin more effectively. Together,

they are efficient in helping you to achieve better glucose control.



   Q6.

What happens if my blood sugar is still too high?  



  When

blood sugar cannot be lowered enough by GLUCOVANCE your doctor may prescribe

injectable insulin or take other measures to control your diabetes.



   Q7.

Can GLUCOVANCE cause side effects?  



  GLUCOVANCE,

like all blood sugar-lowering medications, can cause side effects in some

patients. Most of these side effects are minor. However, there are also serious,

but rare, side effects related to GLUCOVANCE (see   Q9-Q13  ).



   Q8.

What are the most common side effects of GLUCOVANCE?  



  The

most common side effects of GLUCOVANCE are normally minor ones such as diarrhea,

nausea, and upset stomach. If these side effects occur, they usually occur

during the first few weeks of therapy. Taking your GLUCOVANCE with meals can

help reduce these side effects.



  Less frequently, symptoms

of hypoglycemia (low blood sugar), such as lightheadedness, dizziness, shakiness,

or hunger may occur. The risk of hypoglycemic symptoms increases when meals

are skipped, too much alcohol is consumed, or heavy exercise occurs without

enough food. Following the advice of your doctor can help you to avoid these

symptoms.



   Q9. Are there any serious

side effects that GLUCOVANCE can cause?  



 People

who have a condition known as glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency

and who take GLUCOVANCE may develop hemolytic anemia (fast breakdown of red

blood cells). G6PD deficiency usually runs in families. Tell your doctor if

you or any members of your family have been diagnosed with G6PD deficiency

before you start taking GLUCOVANCE.



  GLUCOVANCE rarely

causes serious side effects. The most serious side effect that GLUCOVANCE

can cause is called lactic acidosis.



   Q10. What

is lactic acidosis and can it happen to me?  



 Lactic

acidosis is caused by a buildup of lactic acid in the blood. Lactic acidosis

associated with metformin is rare and has occurred mostly in people whose

kidneys were not working normally. Lactic acidosis has been reported in about

1 in 33,000 patients taking metformin over the course of a year. Although

rare, if lactic acidosis does occur, it can be fatal in up to half the cases.



 It's

also important for your liver to be working normally when you take GLUCOVANCE.

Your liver helps remove lactic acid from your bloodstream.



 Your

doctor will monitor your diabetes and may perform blood tests on you from

time to time to make sure your kidneys and your liver are functioning normally.



 There

is no evidence that GLUCOVANCE causes harm to the kidneys or liver.



   Q11.

Are there other risk factors for lactic acidosis?  



 Your

risk of developing lactic acidosis from taking GLUCOVANCE is very low as long

as your kidneys and liver are healthy. However, some factors can increase

your risk because they can affect kidney and liver function. You should discuss

your risk with your doctor.



  You should not take GLUCOVANCE

if:



 *  You have chronic kidney or liver problems 
 *  You have congestive heart failure which is treated with medications, eg, digoxin (Lanoxin(r)) or furosemide (Lasix(r)) 
 *  You drink alcohol excessively (all the time or short-term "binge" drinking) 
 *  You are seriously dehydrated (have lost a large amount of body fluids) 
 *  You are going to have certain x-ray procedures with injectable contrast agents 
 *  You are going to have surgery 
 *  You develop a serious condition, such as a heart attack, severe infection, or stroke 
 *  You are &gt;=80 years of age and have NOT had your kidney function tested 
      Q12. What are the symptoms of lactic acidosis?  
 

 Some

of the symptoms include: feeling very weak, tired or uncomfortable; unusual

muscle pain; trouble breathing; unusual or unexpected stomach discomfort;

feeling cold; feeling dizzy or lightheaded; or suddenly developing a slow

or irregular heartbeat.



 If you notice these symptoms,

or if your medical condition has suddenly changed, stop taking GLUCOVANCE

tablets and call your doctor right away. Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency

that must be treated in a hospital.



   Q13. What

does my doctor need to know to decrease my risk of lactic acidosis?  



 Tell

your doctor if you have an illness that results in severe vomiting, diarrhea,

and/or fever, or if your intake of fluids is significantly reduced. These

situations can lead to severe dehydration, and it may be necessary to stop

taking GLUCOVANCE temporarily.



 You should let your

doctor know if you are going to have any surgery or specialized x-ray procedures

that require injection of contrast agents. GLUCOVANCE therapy will need to

be stopped temporarily in such instances.



   Q14.

Can I take GLUCOVANCE with other medications?  



 Remind

your doctor that you are taking GLUCOVANCE when any new drug is prescribed

or a change is made in how you take a drug already prescribed. GLUCOVANCE

may interfere with the way some drugs work and some drugs may interfere with

the action of GLUCOVANCE.



 Do not take GLUCOVANCE if you are taking bosentan used for pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH), which is high blood pressure in the vessels of the lungs.



   Q15. What if I become

pregnant while taking GLUCOVANCE?  



 Tell your

doctor if you plan to become pregnant or have become pregnant. As with other

oral glucose-control medications, you should not take GLUCOVANCE during pregnancy.



 Usually

your doctor will prescribe insulin while you are pregnant. As with all medications,

you and your doctor should discuss the use of GLUCOVANCE if you are nursing

a child.



   Q16. How do I take GLUCOVANCE?  



 Your

doctor will tell you how many GLUCOVANCE tablets to take and how often. This

should also be printed on the label of your prescription. You will probably

be started on a low dose of GLUCOVANCE and your dosage will be increased gradually

until your blood sugar is controlled.



   Q17. Where

can I get more information about GLUCOVANCE?  



 This

leaflet is a summary of the most important information about GLUCOVANCE. If

you have any questions or problems, you should talk to your doctor or other

healthcare provider about type 2 diabetes as well as GLUCOVANCE and its side

effects. There is also a leaflet (package insert) written for health professionals

that your pharmacist can let you read.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
