<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="glumetza" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The incidence and type of adverse reactions reported by &gt; 5% of patients for the combined GLUMETZA group versus placebo group are hypoglycemia, diarrhea, and nausea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Depomed, Inc. at 1-866-458-6389 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In clinical trials conducted in the U.S., over 1000 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus have been treated with GLUMETZA 1500-2000 mg/day in active-controlled and placebo-controlled studies with the 500 mg dosage form.



 In the 24-week monotherapy trial comparing GLUMETZA to immediate-release metformin, serious adverse reactions were reported in 3.6% (19/528) of the GLUMETZA-treated patients compared to 2.9% (5/174) of the patients treated with immediate-release metformin. In the add-on to sulfonylurea study, patients receiving background glyburide therapy were randomized to receive add-on treatment of either one of three different regimens of GLUMETZA or placebo. In total, 431 patients received GLUMETZA and glyburide and 144 patients received placebo and glyburide. A serious adverse reaction was reported in 2.1% (9/431) of the GLUMETZA and glyburide-treated patients compared to 1.4% (2/144) of the placebo and glyburide-treated patients. When the data from the monotherapy and add-on to sulfonylurea clinical trials were combined, the most frequently (incidence &gt;= 0.5%) reported serious adverse reactions classified by system organ class were gastrointestinal disorders (1.0% of GLUMETZA-treated patients compared to 0% of patients not treated with GLUMETZA) and cardiac disorders (0.4% of GLUMETZA-treated patients compared to 0.5% of patients not treated with GLUMETZA). Only 2 serious adverse reactions (unstable angina [n = 2] and pancreatitis [n = 2]) were reported in more than one GLUMETZA-treated patient.



 Adverse reactions reported in greater than 5% of patients treated with GLUMETZA that were more common in the combined GLUMETZA and glyburide group than in the placebo and glyburide group are shown in Table 1.



 In 0.7% of patients treated with GLUMETZA and glyburide, diarrhea was responsible for discontinuation of study medication compared to no patients in the placebo and glyburide group.



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Reported By &gt; 5%* of Patients for the Combined GLUMETZA Groups Versus Placebo Group 
 Adverse Reaction                    GLUMETZA + Glyburide(n = 431)        Placebo + Glyburide(n = 144)      
  
 *AR's that were more common in the GLUMETZA-treated than in the placebo-treated patients.   
  
 Hypoglycemia                                    13.7%                                4.9%                  
 Diarrhea                                        12.5%                                5.6%                  
 Nausea                                           6.7%                                4.2%                  
         
 

   6.2 Laboratory Tests

    Vitamin B12concentrations  



 Metformin may lower serum vitamin B12concentrations. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on GLUMETZA and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. (See  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (  5.6  )  )
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

WARNING: Lactic Acidosis



  

WARNING: Lactic Acidosis



    Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious, complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure.  



   The onset of lactic acidosis is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress.  



   Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate.  



   If acidosis is suspected, GLUMETZA (metformin hydrochloride extended-release tablets), should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately. (See WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS (  5.1  ))  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic insufficiency, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap and elevated blood lactate. (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue GLUMETZA and hospitalize the patient immediately. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Lactic acidosis: Warn against excessive alcohol intake. GLUMETZA is not recommended in hepatic impairment and is contraindicated in renal impairment. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Temporarily discontinue in patients undergoing radiologic studies with intravascular administration of iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food and fluids. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Vitamin B12deficiency: Metformin may lower vitamin B12levels. Monitor hematologic parameters annually. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Macrovascular outcomes: No conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with GLUMETZA or any other antidiabetic drug. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



   Lactic acidosis is a serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with GLUMETZA and is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate concentrations (&gt; 5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels &gt; 5 mug/mL are generally found. The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin hydrochloride is approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years. In more than 20,000 patient-years exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal impairment, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, particularly when accompanied by hypoperfusion and hypoxemia due to unstable or acute failure, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking GLUMETZA. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. GLUMETZA treatment should not be initiated in any patient unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced. In addition, GLUMETZA should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, GLUMETZA should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic impairment. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake when taking GLUMETZA, because alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin on lactate metabolism. In addition, GLUMETZA should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure necessitating restricted intake of food or fluids. Use of topiramate, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, in epilepsy and migraine prophylaxis may frequently cause dose-dependent metabolic acidosis (In controlled trials, 32% and 67% for adjunctive treatment in adults and pediatric patients, respectively, and 15 to 25% for monotherapy of epilepsy, with decrease in serum bicarbonate to less than 20 mEq/L; 3% and 11% for adjunctive treatment in adults and pediatric patients, respectively, and 1 to 7% for monotherapy of epilepsy, with decrease in serum bicarbonate to less than 17 mEq/L) and may exacerbate the risk of metformin-induced lactic acidosis. (See  7.1  Drug Interactions and  12.5  Clinical Pharmacology) The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis.  



  Patients should be educated to promptly report these symptoms should they occur. If present, GLUMETZA should be withdrawn until lactic acidosis is ruled out. Serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, blood pH, lactate levels, and blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of GLUMETZA, gastrointestinal symptoms, which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to recur. Later occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease. Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking GLUMETZA do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explainable by other mechanisms, such as poorly-controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling. Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia). Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking GLUMETZA, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin hydrochloride is dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery. (See CONTRAINDICATIONS (  4  ))  



    5.2 Monitoring of Renal Function



  Metformin is substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal impairment. Therefore GLUMETZA is contraindicated in patients with renal impairment.



 Before initiation of GLUMETZA and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal dysfunction is anticipated (e.g., elderly), renal function should be assessed more frequently and GLUMETZA discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present. Metformin treatment should not be initiated in patients &gt;= 80 years of age unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced, as these patients are more susceptible to developing lactic acidosis.



  Use of concomitant medications that may affect renal function or metformin disposition -  Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or may interfere with the disposition of metformin, such as cationic drugs that are eliminated by renal tubular secretion (see DRUG INTERACTIONS (  7  )  ), should be used with caution.



 Radiological studies and surgical procedures:



 Radiologic studies involving the use of intravascular iodinated contrast materials (for example, intravenous urogram, intravenous cholangiography, angiography, and computed tomography) can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin. Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, GLUMETZA should be temporarily discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been re-evaluated and found to be normal.



 GLUMETZA therapy should be temporarily suspended for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.3 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause, acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients on GLUMETZA therapy, the drug should be promptly discontinued.



    5.4 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol is known to potentiate the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients, therefore, should be warned against excessive alcohol intake while receiving GLUMETZA.



    5.5 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Because impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis GLUMETZA should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease.



    5.6 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled, 29-week clinical trials of immediate release metformin, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum Vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of GLUMETZA or Vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on GLUMETZA and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. Certain individuals (those with inadequate Vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal Vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum Vitamin B12measurements at two- to three-year intervals may be useful.



    5.7 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation, or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as sulfonylureas and insulin) or ethanol. Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.



    5.8 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with GLUMETZA or any other oral anti-diabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
