<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="glyset" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Gastrointestinal

  Gastrointestinal symptoms are the most common reactions to GLYSET Tablets. In U.S. placebo-controlled trials, the incidences of abdominal pain, diarrhea, and flatulence were 11.7%, 28.7%, and 41.5% respectively in 962 patients treated with GLYSET 25 100 mg 3 times daily, whereas the corresponding incidences were 4.7%, 10.0%, and 12.0% in 603 placebo-treated patients. The incidence of diarrhea and abdominal pain tended to diminish with continued treatment.



   Dermatologic

  Skin rash was reported in 4.3% of patients treated with GLYSET compared to 2.4% of placebo-treated patients. Rashes were generally transient and most were assessed as unrelated to GLYSET by physician investigators.



   Abnormal Laboratory Findings

  Low serum iron occurred more often in patients treated with GLYSET (9.2%) than in placebo-treated patients (4.2%) but did not persist in the majority of cases and was not associated with reductions in hemoglobin or changes in other hematologic indices.



   Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of GLYSET. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  ileus (including paralytic ileus), subileus, gastrointestinal pain, nausea, abdominal distention.



 *  Pneumatosis Cystoides IntestinalisThere have been rare postmarketing reports of pneumatosis cystoides intestinalis associated with the use of alpha-glucosidase inhibitors, including GLYSET. Pneumatosis cystoides intestinalis may present with symptoms of diarrhea, mucus discharge, rectal bleeding, and constipation. Complications may include pneumoperitoneum, volvulus, intestinal obstruction, intussusception, intestinal hemorrhage, and intestinal perforation. If pneumatosis cystoides intestinalis is suspected, discontinue Glyset and perform the appropriate diagnostic imaging. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
