<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="glyxambi" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions associated with GLYXAMBI (a 5% or greater incidence) were urinary tract infections, nasopharyngitis, and upper respiratory tract infections. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-542-6257 or 1-800-459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Empagliflozin and Linagliptin  The safety of concomitantly administered empagliflozin (daily dose 10 mg or 25 mg) and linagliptin (daily dose 5 mg) has been evaluated in a total of 1363 patients with type 2 diabetes treated for up to 52 weeks in active-controlled clinical trials. The most common adverse reactions with concomitant administration of empagliflozin and linagliptin based on a pooled analyses of these studies are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients Treated with Empagliflozin and Linagliptin 
   a  Predefined adverse event grouping, including, but not limited to, urinary tract infection, asymptomatic bacteriuria, cystitis   
  
                    GLYXAMBI10 mg/5 mgn=272      GLYXAMBI25 mg/5 mgn=273     
                    n (%)            n (%)           
 Urinary tract infection  a    34 (12.5)        31 (11.4)         
 Nasopharyngitis  16 (5.9)         18 (6.6)          
 Upper respiratory tract infection  19 (7.0)         19 (7.0)          
        Empagliflozin  Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=2% of patients receiving empagliflozin and more commonly than in patients given placebo included (10 mg, 25 mg, and placebo): urinary tract infection (9.3%, 7.6%, and 7.6%), female genital mycotic infections (5.4%, 6.4%, and 1.5%), upper respiratory tract infection (3.1%, 4.0%, and 3.8%), increased urination (3.4%, 3.2%, and 1.0%), dyslipidemia (3.9%, 2.9%, and 3.4%), arthralgia (2.4%, 2.3%, and 2.2%), male genital mycotic infections (3.1%, 1.6%, and 0.4%), and nausea (2.3%, 1.1%, and 1.4%).
 

 Empagliflozin causes an osmotic diuresis, which may lead to intravascular volume contraction and adverse reactions related to volume depletion.



   Linagliptin  Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=2% of patients treated with linagliptin 5 mg and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo included: nasopharyngitis (7.0% and 6.1%), diarrhea (3.3% and 3.0%), and cough (2.1% and 1.4%).



 Other adverse reactions reported in clinical studies with treatment of linagliptin monotherapy were hypersensitivity (e.g., urticaria, angioedema, localized skin exfoliation, or bronchial hyperreactivity) and myalgia.



 In the clinical trial program, pancreatitis was reported in 15.2 cases per 10,000 patient year exposure while being treated with linagliptin compared with 3.7 cases per 10,000 patient year exposure while being treated with comparator (placebo and active comparator, sulfonylurea). Three additional cases of pancreatitis were reported following the last administered dose of linagliptin.



   Hypoglycemia  



 Table 2 summarizes the reports of hypoglycemia with empagliflozin and linagliptin over a treatment period of 52 weeks.



 Table 2 Incidence of Overalla and Severeb Hypoglycemic Adverse Reactions 
   a  Overall hypoglycemic events: plasma or capillary glucose of less than or equal to 70 mg/dL or requiring assistance   
   b  Severe hypoglycemic events: requiring assistance regardless of blood glucose                
  
   Add-on to Metformin(52 weeks)                                                                   GLYXAMBI10 mg/5 mgn=136                                                                         GLYXAMBI25 mg/5 mgn=137                                                               
 Overall (%)                                                                                     2.2%                                                                                            3.6%                                                                                    
 Severe (%)                                                                                      0%                                                                                              0%                                                                                      
        Laboratory Tests    Empagliflozin and Linagliptin  Changes in laboratory findings in patients treated with the combination of empagliflozin and linagliptin included increases in cholesterol and hematocrit compared to baseline.
 

   Empagliflozin    Increase in Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol (LDL-C):  Dose-related increases in low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) were observed in patients treated with empagliflozin. LDL-C increased by 2.3%, 4.6%, and 6.5% in patients treated with placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  . The range of mean baseline LDL-C levels was 90.3 to 90.6 mg/dL across treatment groups.



   Increase in Hematocrit:  Median hematocrit decreased by 1.3% in placebo and increased by 2.8% in empagliflozin 10 mg and 2.8% in empagliflozin 25 mg treated patients. At the end of treatment, 0.6%, 2.7%, and 3.5% of patients with hematocrits initially within the reference range had values above the upper limit of the reference range with placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively.



   Linagliptin  Changes in laboratory values that occurred more frequently in the linagliptin group and &gt;=1% more than in the placebo group were increases in uric acid (1.3% in the placebo group, 2.7% in the linagliptin group).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of linagliptin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  Acute pancreatitis, including fatal pancreatitis [see Indications and Usage (  1.1  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Severe and disabling arthralgia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Rash 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Pancreatitis: There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue GLYXAMBI. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Hypotension: Before initiating GLYXAMBI assess and correct volume status in patients with renal impairment, the elderly, in patients with low systolic blood pressure, and in patients on diuretics. Monitor for signs and symptoms during therapy. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Impairment in Renal Function: Monitor renal function during therapy. More frequent monitoring is recommended in patients with eGFR below 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  . (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia: Consider lowering the dose of insulin secretagogue or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia when initiating GLYXAMBI. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Genital Mycotic Infections: Monitor and treat as appropriate (  5.5  ) 
 *   Urinary Tract Infections: Monitor and treat as appropriate (  5.6  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity: There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with linagliptin (one of the components of GLYXAMBI) including anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions. In such cases, promptly discontinue GLYXAMBI, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment, and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Increased LDL-C: Monitor and treat as appropriate (  5.8  ) 
 *   Arthralgia: Severe and disabling arthralgia has been reported in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate. (  5.9  ) 
 *   Macrovascular Outcomes : There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with GLYXAMBI or any other antidiabetic drug. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Pancreatitis



  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal pancreatitis, in patients taking linagliptin. Take careful notice of potential signs and symptoms of pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue GLYXAMBI and initiate appropriate management. It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using GLYXAMBI.



    5.2 Hypotension



  Empagliflozin causes intravascular volume contraction. Symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiating empagliflozin [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  particularly in patients with renal impairment, the elderly, in patients with low systolic blood pressure, and in patients on diuretics. Before initiating GLYXAMBI, assess for volume contraction and correct volume status if indicated. Monitor for signs and symptoms of hypotension after initiating therapy and increase monitoring in clinical situations where volume contraction is expected [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )]  .



    5.3 Impairment in Renal Function



  Empagliflozin increases serum creatinine and decreases eGFR. The risk of impaired renal function with empagliflozin is increased in elderly patients and patients with moderate renal impairment. More frequent monitoring of renal function is recommended in these patients [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ,  8.6  )].  Renal function should be evaluated prior to initiating GLYXAMBI and periodically thereafter.



    5.4 Hypoglycemia with Concomitant Use with Insulin and Insulin Secretagogues



  Insulin and insulin secretagogues are known to cause hypoglycemia. The use of empagliflozin or linagliptin in combination with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin was associated with a higher rate of hypoglycemia compared with placebo in a clinical trial. Therefore, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with GLYXAMBI.



    5.5 Genital Mycotic Infections



  Empagliflozin increases the risk for genital mycotic infections [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Patients with a history of chronic or recurrent genital mycotic infections were more likely to develop mycotic genital infections. Monitor and treat as appropriate.



    5.6 Urinary Tract Infections



  Empagliflozin increases the risk for urinary tract infections [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Monitor and treat as appropriate.



    5.7 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with linagliptin (one of the components of GLYXAMBI). These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions. Onset of these reactions occurred within the first 3 months after initiation of treatment with linagliptin, with some reports occurring after the first dose. If a serious hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue GLYXAMBI, assess for other potential causes for the event, and institute alternative treatment for diabetes.



 Angioedema has also been reported with other dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitors. Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema to another DPP-4 inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with GLYXAMBI.



    5.8 Increased Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol (LDL-C)



  Increases in LDL-C can occur with empagliflozin [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Monitor and treat as appropriate.



    5.9 Severe and Disabling Arthralgia



   There have been postmarketing reports of severe and disabling arthralgia in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. The time to onset of symptoms following initiation of drug therapy varied from one day to years. Patients experienced relief of symptoms upon discontinuation of the medication. A subset of patients experienced a recurrence of symptoms when restarting the same drug or a different DPP-4 inhibitor. Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate.  



    5.10 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with GLYXAMBI or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
