<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="grastek" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients were: ear pruritus, oral pruritus, tongue pruritus, mouth edema, and throat irritation.



    EXCERPT:    *  Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients were: ear pruritus, oral pruritus, tongue pruritus, mouth edema, throat irritation. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Adults  



 The safety data described below are based on 6 clinical trials which randomized 3589 subjects 18 through 65 years of age with Timothy grass pollen induced rhinitis with or without conjunctivitis, including 1669 subjects who were exposed to at least one dose of GRASTEK. Of the subjects treated with GRASTEK, 25% had mild asthma and 80% were sensitized to other allergens in addition to grass. The subject population was 88% White, 7% African American, and 3% Asian. Subjects were 52% male, and 88% of subjects were between 18 and 50 years of age. Subject demographics in placebo-treated subjects were similar to the active group.



 The most common adverse reactions reported in subjects treated with GRASTEK were oral pruritus (26.7% vs 3.5% placebo), throat irritation (22.6% vs 2.8%), ear pruritus (12.5% vs 1.1%) and mouth edema (11.1% vs 0.8%). The percentage of subjects who discontinued from the clinical trials because of an adverse reaction while exposed to GRASTEK or placebo was 4.9% and 0.9%, respectively. The most common adverse reactions that led to study discontinuation in subjects who were exposed to GRASTEK were pharyngeal edema and oral pruritus.



 Seven adult subjects (7/1669; 0.4%) who received GRASTEK experienced treatment-related systemic allergic reactions that led to discontinuation of GRASTEK in four out of the seven subjects.



 *  Five of the seven subjects had reactions on Day 1 of treatment with GRASTEK. Symptoms included swelling of lips/mouth; oral/pharyngeal itching; ear itching, sneezing, rhinorrhea, throat irritation, dysphonia, dysphagia, chest discomfort, and rash. Three of the five subjects received treatment with epinephrine and antihistamines, and one of the three also received oral corticosteroids. One of the five subjects who had a reaction on Day 1 of treatment with GRASTEK also had a reaction on Day 2 of treatment with GRASTEK. Symptoms on Day 2 included oral burning sensation; rhinorrhea; and throat irritation. 
 *  One of the seven subjects had a reaction on Day 2 after tolerating treatment with GRASTEK on Day 1. Symptoms included edema of the lower lip, epigastric discomfort and dizziness. 
 *  One of the seven subjects developed chest tightness and shortness of breath on Day 42 of treatment with GRASTEK. 
    Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=1% of subjects treated with GRASTEK are shown in Table 1.
 

 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Adults Treated with GRASTEK 
 Adverse Reaction                              GRASTEK(N=1669)                    PLACEBO(N=1645)           
  
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
 Headache                                            2.1%                               1.3%                
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                                                                              
 Ear pruritus                                       12.5%                               1.1%                
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                                           
 Throat irritation                                  22.6%                               2.8%                
 Pharyngeal edema                                    3.4%                               0.1%                
 Dry throat                                          1.7%                               0.4%                
 Oropharyngeal pain                                  1.6%                               1.0%                
 Nasal discomfort                                    1.6%                               1.0%                
 Throat tightness                                    1.4%                               0.2%                
 Dyspnea                                             1.1%                               0.4%                
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
 Oral pruritus                                      26.7%                               3.5%                
 Mouth edema                                        11.1%                               0.8%                
 Paraesthesia oral                                   9.8%                               2.0%                
 Tongue pruritus                                     5.7%                               0.5%                
 Lip swelling                                        4.0%                               0.2%                
 Swollen tongue                                      2.8%                               0.1%                
 Dyspepsia                                           2.3%                               0.1%                
 Hypoesthesia oral                                   2.3%                               1.0%                
 Nausea                                              1.9%                               0.6%                
 Oral discomfort                                     1.6%                               0.3%                
 Oral mucosal erythema                               1.5%                               0.6%                
 Lip edema                                           1.3%                               0.1%                
 Glossitis                                           1.3%                               0.1%                
 Stomatitis                                          1.1%                               0.3%                
 Tongue disorder                                     1.1%                               0.2%                
 Tongue edema                                        1.1%                               0.4%                
 Glossodynia                                         1.0%                               0.3%                
 Dysphagia                                           1.0%                               0.2%                
 Palatal edema                                       1.0%                               0.1%                
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                           
 Pruritus                                            2.4%                               1.0%                
 Urticaria                                           1.7%                               0.9%                
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                           
 Chest discomfort                                    1.6%                               0.5%                
 Fatigue                                             1.4%                               0.4%                
         Adverse reactions of interest that occurred in &lt;=1% of GRASTEK recipients include abdominal pain and gastroesophageal reflux.
 

     Pediatrics  



 Safety data are based on 3 clinical trials which randomized 881 subjects between 5 and 17 years of age with grass pollen induced rhinitis with or without conjunctivitis. Overall, 445 subjects received at least one dose of GRASTEK. Of the subjects treated with GRASTEK, 31% had mild asthma and 86% were sensitized to other allergens in addition to grass. The subject population was 86% White, 7% African American and 3% multi-racial. The majority (66%) of subjects were male. The mean age of subjects was 11.7 years. Subject demographics in placebo-treated subjects were similar to the active group.



 The most common adverse reactions in pediatric subjects treated with GRASTEK were oral pruritus (24.4% vs 2.1% placebo), throat irritation (21.3% vs 2.5%) and mouth edema (9.8% vs 0.2%). The percentage of subjects who discontinued from the clinical trials because of an adverse reaction while exposed to GRASTEK or placebo was 6.3% and 0.7%, respectively.



 One pediatric subject (1/447; 0.2%) who received GRASTEK experienced a treatment-related systemic allergic reaction consisting of lip angioedema, slight dysphagia due to the sensation of a lump in the throat, and intermittent cough which was of moderate intensity on Day 1. The subject was treated with epinephrine, recovered, and was discontinued from the trial.



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=1% of subjects treated with GRASTEK are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Pediatric Subjects Treated with GRASTEK 
 Adverse Reaction                               GRASTEK(N=447)                     PLACEBO(N=434)           
  
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
 Headache                                            3.4%                               1.8%                
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                                                                              
 Ear pruritus                                        7.2%                               0.5%                
   Eye Disorders                                                                                            
 Eye pruritus                                        3.4%                               2.1%                
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                                          
 Throat irritation                                   21.3%                              2.5%                
 Oropharyngeal pain                                  4.0%                               1.4%                
 Pharyngeal erythema                                 3.6%                               0.7%                
 Pharyngeal edema                                    2.9%                                0%                 
 Cough                                               2.7%                               1.2%                
 Dyspnea                                             2.0%                               0.5%                
 Nasal discomfort                                    1.6%                               0.9%                
 Nasal congestion                                    1.6%                               0.5%                
 Sneezing                                            1.6%                               0.7%                
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
 Oral pruritus                                       24.4%                              2.1%                
 Mouth edema                                         9.8%                               0.2%                
 Tongue pruritus                                     9.2%                               0.9%                
 Lip swelling                                        7.2%                               0.5%                
 Paraesthesia oral                                   5.4%                               1.2%                
 Oral mucosal erythema                               4.9%                               0.9%                
 Lip pruritus                                        2.9%                               0.2%                
 Swollen tongue                                      2.5%                                0%                 
 Dysphagia                                           2.0%                                0%                 
 Nausea                                              1.6%                               0.5%                
 Oral discomfort                                     1.6%                               0.2%                
 Stomatitis                                          1.3%                                0%                 
 Hypoesthesia oral                                   1.1%                               0.2%                
 Glossodynia                                         1.1%                               0.2%                
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                          
 Urticaria                                           1.8%                               0.2%                
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                          
 Chest discomfort                                    2.0%                               0.5%                
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
     Postmarketing Safety Studies  



 In European post-approval studies which included 1,666 patients treated with GRASTEK (marketed under the name GRAZAX), reported serious adverse reactions assessed as related to GRASTEK use included anaphylactic reaction, asthma exacerbation, hoarseness, laryngitis, oral ulceration, and ulcerative colitis exacerbation.



     Spontaneous Postmarketing Reports  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of GRASTEK (marketed under the name GRAZAX in Europe). Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These include: altered state of consciousness, anaphylactic shock, angioedema, asthma exercise induced, chest pressure, diarrhea, difficulty speaking, dizziness, drowsiness, eosinophilic esophagitis, erythema facial, face edema, forced expiratory volume decreased, heart rate increased, heart rate irregular, hyperventilation, hypotension, laryngeal discomfort, oral pain, oxygen saturation decreased, peak expiratory flow rate decreased, pneumonia, rash, respiratory distress, sensation of foreign body, status asthmaticus, swelling of neck, throat pruritus, tremor, vital capacity decreased, vomiting, and wheezing. Included in these reports was an adult male with asthma who experienced anaphylactic shock within two minutes of administration of GRASTEK. The patient experienced depressed level of consciousness, hypotension, increased heart rate, wheezing, urticaria, and face edema.



 Eosinophilic esophagitis has been reported following treatment with GRASTEK (marketed under the name GRAZAX). The clinical details of some postmarketing reports are consistent with a drug-induced effect, including at least one case with resolution of symptoms upon discontinuation of GRASTEK, relapse after resuming GRASTEK and resolution again after discontinuation of GRASTEK.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SEVERE ALLERGIC REACTIONS

    WARNING: SEVERE ALLERGIC REACTIONS  

    *  GRASTEK can cause life-threatening allergic reactions such as anaphylaxis and severe laryngopharyngeal restriction. (5.1) 
 *  Do not administer GRASTEK to patients with severe, unstable or uncontrolled asthma. (4) 
 *  Observe patients in the office for at least 30 minutes following the initial dose. (5.1) 
 *  Prescribe auto-injectable epinephrine, instruct and train patients on its appropriate use, and instruct patients to seek immediate medical care upon its use. (5.2) 
 *  GRASTEK may not be suitable for patients with certain underlying medical conditions that may reduce their ability to survive a serious allergic reaction. (5.2) 
 *  GRASTEK may not be suitable for patients who may be unresponsive to epinephrine or inhaled bronchodilators, such as those taking beta-blockers. (5.2) 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: SEVERE ALLERGIC REACTIONS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  GRASTEK can cause life-threatening allergic reactions such as anaphylaxis and severe laryngopharyngeal restriction. (5.1) 
 *  Do not administer GRASTEK to patients with severe, unstable or uncontrolled asthma. (4) 
 *  Observe patients in the office for at least 30 minutes following the initial dose. (5.1) 
 *  Prescribe auto-injectable epinephrine, instruct and train patients on its appropriate use, and instruct patients to seek immediate medical care upon its use. (5.2) 
 *  GRASTEK may not be suitable for patients with certain underlying medical conditions that may reduce their ability to survive a serious allergic reaction. (5.2) 
 *  GRASTEK may not be suitable for patients who may be unresponsive to epinephrine or inhaled bronchodilators, such as those taking beta-blockers. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Inform patients of the signs and symptoms of serious allergic reactions and instruct them to seek immediate medical care and discontinue therapy should any of these occur. (  5.1  ) 
 *  In case of oral inflammation or wounds, stop treatment with GRASTEK to allow complete healing of the oral cavity. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Severe Allergic Reactions



  GRASTEK can cause systemic allergic reactions including anaphylaxis which may be life-threatening. In addition, GRASTEK can cause severe local reactions, including laryngopharyngeal swelling, which can compromise breathing and be life-threatening. Educate patients to recognize the signs and symptoms of these allergic reactions and instruct them to seek immediate medical care and discontinue therapy should any of these occur. Allergic reactions may require treatment with epinephrine. [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  



 Administer the initial dose of GRASTEK in a healthcare setting under the supervision of a physician with experience in the diagnosis and treatment of allergic diseases and prepared to manage a life-threatening systemic or local allergic reaction. Observe patients in the office for at least 30 minutes following the initial dose of GRASTEK.



    5.2 Epinephrine



  Prescribe auto-injectable epinephrine to patients receiving GRASTEK. Instruct patients to recognize the signs and symptoms of a severe allergic reaction and in the proper use of emergency auto-injectable epinephrine. Instruct patients to seek immediate medical care upon use of auto-injectable epinephrine and to stop treatment with GRASTEK. [See  Patient Counseling Information (17)  .]  



 See the epinephrine package insert for complete information.



 GRASTEK may not be suitable for patients with certain medical conditions that may reduce the ability to survive a serious allergic reaction or increase the risk of adverse reactions after epinephrine administration. Examples of these medical conditions include but are not limited to: markedly compromised lung function (either chronic or acute), unstable angina, recent myocardial infarction, significant arrhythmia, and uncontrolled hypertension.



 GRASTEK may not be suitable for patients who are taking medications that can potentiate or inhibit the effect of epinephrine. These medications include:



 *      Beta-adrenergic blockers : Patients taking beta-adrenergic blockers may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat serious systemic reactions, including anaphylaxis. Specifically, beta-adrenergic blockers antagonize the cardiostimulating and bronchodilating effects of epinephrine. 
 *      Alpha-adrenergic blockers, ergot alkaloids : Patients taking alpha-adrenergic blockers may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat serious systemic reactions, including anaphylaxis. Specifically, alpha-adrenergic blockers antagonize the vasoconstricting and hypertensive effects of epinephrine. Similarly, ergot alkaloids may reverse the pressor effects of epinephrine. 
 *      Tricyclic antidepressants, levothyroxine sodium, monoamine oxidase inhibitors and certain antihistamines : The adverse effects of epinephrine may be potentiated in patients taking tricyclic antidepressants, levothyroxine sodium, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, and the antihistamines chlorpheniramine, and diphenhydramine. 
 *      Cardiac glycosides, diuretics : Patients who receive epinephrine while taking cardiac glycosides or diuretics should be observed carefully for the development of cardiac arrhythmias. 
       5.3 Upper Airway Compromise
 

  GRASTEK can cause local reactions in the mouth or throat that could compromise the upper airway [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1  and  6.2)  ].  Consider discontinuation of GRASTEK in patients who experience persistent and escalating adverse reactions in the mouth or throat.



    5.4 Eosinophilic Esophagitis



  Eosinophilic esophagitis has been reported in association with sublingual tablet immunotherapy [See  Contraindications (4)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  Discontinue GRASTEK and consider a diagnosis of eosinophilic esophagitis in patients who experience severe or persistent gastro-esophageal symptoms including dysphagia or chest pain.



    5.5 Asthma



  GRASTEK has not been studied in subjects with moderate or severe asthma or any subjects who required daily medication to treat asthma.



 Withhold immunotherapy with GRASTEK if the patient is experiencing an acute asthma exacerbation. Reevaluate patients who have recurrent asthma exacerbations and consider discontinuation of GRASTEK.



    5.6 Concomitant Allergen Immunotherapy



  GRASTEK has not been studied in subjects who are receiving concomitant allergen immunotherapy. Concomitant dosing with other allergen immunotherapy may increase the likelihood of local or systemic adverse reactions to either subcutaneous or sublingual allergen immunotherapy.



    5.7 Oral Inflammation



  Stop treatment with GRASTEK to allow complete healing of the oral cavity in patients with oral inflammation (e.g., oral lichen planus, mouth ulcers or thrush) or oral wounds, such as those following oral surgery or dental extraction.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
