<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="havrix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    In studies of adults and children 2 years of age and older, the most common solicited adverse events were injection-site soreness (56% of adults and 21% of children) and headache (14% of adults and less than 9% of children). (6.1) 
 *    In studies of children 11 to 25 months of age, the most frequently reported solicited local reactions were pain (32%) and redness (29%). Common solicited general adverse events were irritability (42%), drowsiness (28%), and loss of appetite (28%). (6.1) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov  .    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of HAVRIX has been evaluated in 61 clinical trials involving approximately 37,000 individuals receiving doses of 360 EL.U. (n = 21,928 in 3- or 4-dose schedule), 720 EL.U. (n = 12,274 in 2- or 3-dose schedule), or 1440 EL.U. (n = 2,782 in 2- or 3-dose schedule).



 Of solicited adverse events in clinical trials of adults, who received HAVRIX 1440 EL.U., and children (2 years of age and older), who received either HAVRIX 360 EL.U. or 720 EL.U., the most frequently reported was injection-site soreness (56% of adults and 21% of children); less than 0.5% of soreness was reported as severe. Headache was reported by 14% of adults and less than 9% of children. Other solicited and unsolicited events occurring during clinical trials are listed below.



   Incidence 1% to 10% of Injections:    Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Anorexia.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Nausea.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Fatigue, fever &gt;99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C), induration, redness, and swelling of the injection site; malaise.



   Incidence &lt;1% of Injections:    Infections and Infestations:  Pharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infections.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Lymphadenopathy.



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Insomnia.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Dysgeusia, hypertonia.



   Eye Disorders:  Photophobia.



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  Vertigo.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Abdominal pain, diarrhea, vomiting.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Pruritus, rash, urticaria.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Arthralgia, myalgia.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Injection site hematoma.



   Investigations:  Creatine phosphokinase increased.



   Coadministration Studies of HAVRIX in Children 11 to 25 Months of Age:  In 4 studies, 3,152 children 11 to 25 months of age received at least one dose of HAVRIX 720 EL.U. administered alone or concomitantly with other routine childhood vaccinations  [see Clinical Studies (14.2, 14.5)]  . The studies included HAV 210 (N = 1,084), HAV 232 (N = 394), HAV 220 (N = 433), and HAV 231 (N = 1,241).



 In the largest of these studies (HAV 231) conducted in the US, 1,241 children 15 months of age were randomized to receive: Group 1) HAVRIX alone; Group 2) HAVRIX concomitantly with measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR) vaccine (manufactured by Merck and Co.) and varicella vaccine (manufactured by Merck and Co.); or Group 3) MMR and varicella vaccines. Subjects in Group 3 who received MMR and varicella vaccines received the first dose of HAVRIX 42 days later. A second dose of HAVRIX was administered to all subjects 6 to 9 months after the first dose of HAVRIX. Solicited local adverse reactions and general events were recorded by parents/guardians on diary cards for 4 days (days 0 to 3) after vaccination. Unsolicited adverse events were recorded on the diary card for 31 days after vaccination. Telephone follow-up was conducted 6 months after the last vaccination to inquire about serious adverse events, new onset chronic illnesses and medically significant events. A total of 1,035 children completed the 6-month follow-up. Among subjects in all groups combined, 53% were male; 69% of subjects were white, 16% were Hispanic, 9% were black and 6% were other racial/ethnic groups.



 Percentages of subjects with solicited local adverse reactions and general adverse events following HAVRIX administered alone (Group 1) or concomitantly with MMR and varicella vaccines (Group 2) are presented in Table 1. The solicited adverse events from the 3 additional coadministration studies conducted with HAVRIX were comparable to those from Study HAV 231.



 Table 1. Solicited Local Adverse Reactions and General Adverse Events Occurring Within 4 Days of Vaccinationa in Children 15 to 24 Months of Age With HAVRIX Administered Alone or Concomitantly With MMR and Varicella Vaccines (TVC) 
                             Group 1  HAVRIX  Dose 1  %    Group 2  HAVRIX+  MMR+Vb  Dose 1  %    Group 1  HAVRIX  Dose 2  %    Group 2  HAVRIX  Dose 2  %    
  Local (at injection site for HAVRIX)    
  N                          298           411            272           373           
  Pain, any                  23.8          23.6           24.3          30.3          
  Redness, any               20.1          20.0           22.8          23.9          
  Swelling, any              8.7           10.2           9.6           9.9           
  General                    
  N                          300           417            271           375           
  Irritability, any          33.3          43.9           31.0          27.2          
  Irritability, grade 3      0.3           1.9            1.5           0.3           
  Drowsiness, any            22.3          35.3           21.0          20.8          
  Drowsiness, grade 3        1.0           2.2            1.1           0.0           
  Loss of appetite, any      18.3          26.1           19.9          20.5          
  Loss of appetite, grade 3    1.0           1.4            0.4           0.3           
  Fever &gt;=100.6 degrees F (38.1 degrees C)    3.0           4.8            3.3           2.7           
  Fever &gt;=101.5 degrees F (38.6 degrees C)    2.0           2.6            1.8           1.6           
  Fever &gt;=102.4 degrees F (39.1 degrees C)    0.7           0.7            0.4           1.1           
           Total vaccinated cohort (TVC) = all subjects who received at least one dose of vaccine.
 

 N = number of subjects who received at least one dose of vaccine and for whom diary card information was available.



 Grade 3: drowsiness defined as prevented normal daily activities; irritability/fussiness defined as crying that could not be comforted/prevented normal daily activities; loss of appetite defined as no eating at all.



   a  Within 4 days of vaccination defined as day of vaccination and the next 3 days.



   b  MMR = measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine; V = varicella vaccine.



   Serious Adverse Events in Children 11 to 25 Months of Age:  Among these 4 studies, 0.9% (29/3,152) of subjects reported a serious adverse event within the 31-day period following vaccination with HAVRIX. Among subjects administered HAVRIX alone 1.0% (13/1,332) reported a serious adverse event. Among subjects who received HAVRIX concomitantly with other childhood vaccines, 0.9% (8/909) reported a serious adverse event. In these 4 studies, there were 4 reports of seizure within 31 days post-vaccination: these occurred 2, 9, and 27 days following the first dose of HAVRIX administered alone and 12 days following the second dose of HAVRIX. In one subject who received INFANRIX and Hib conjugate vaccine followed by HAVRIX 6 weeks later, bronchial hyperreactivity and respiratory distress were reported on the day of administration of HAVRIX alone.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to reports in clinical trials, worldwide voluntary reports of adverse events received for HAVRIX since market introduction of this vaccine are listed below. This list includes serious adverse events or events which have a suspected causal connection to components of HAVRIX or other vaccines or drugs. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine.



   Infections and Infestations:  Rhinitis.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Thrombocytopenia.



   Immune System Disorders:  Anaphylactic reaction, anaphylactoid reaction, serum sickness-like syndrome.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Convulsion, dizziness, encephalopathy, Guillain-Barre syndrome, hypoesthesia, multiple sclerosis, myelitis, neuropathy, paresthesia, somnolence, syncope.



   Vascular Disorders:  Vasculitis.



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  Dyspnea.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Hepatitis, jaundice.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Angioedema, erythema multiforme, hyperhidrosis.



   Congenital, Familial, and Genetic Disorders:  Congenital anomaly.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Musculoskeletal stiffness.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Chills, influenza-like symptoms, injection site reaction, local swelling.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    HAVRIX is available in vials and 2 types of prefilled syringes. One type of prefilled syringe has a tip cap which may contain natural rubber latex. The other type has a tip cap and a rubber plunger which contain dry natural latex rubber. Use of these syringes may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. (5.1, 16) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including HAVRIX. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (5.2) 
    
 

   5.1 Latex



  HAVRIX is available in vials and 2 types of prefilled syringes. One type of prefilled syringe has a tip cap which may contain natural rubber latex. The other type has a tip cap and a rubber plunger which contain dry natural latex rubber. Use of these syringes may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. The vial stopper does not contain latex. [See How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16).]  



    5.2 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including HAVRIX. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.



    5.3 Preventing and Managing Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine [see Contraindications (4)]  .



    5.4 Altered Immunocompetence



  Immunocompromised persons may have a diminished immune response to HAVRIX, including individuals receiving immunosuppressant therapy.



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Hepatitis A virus has a relatively long incubation period (15 to 50 days). HAVRIX may not prevent hepatitis A infection in individuals who have an unrecognized hepatitis A infection at the time of vaccination. Additionally, vaccination with HAVRIX may not protect all individuals.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
