<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hectorol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Hectorol Injection has been evaluated for safety in 70 patients with chronic renal disease on hemodialysis (who had been previously treated with oral Hectorol) from two 12-week, open-label, single-arm, multi-centered studies. (Dosage titrated to achieve target plasma iPTH levels, see      CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY          /          Clinical Studies      .)



 Because there was no placebo group included in the studies of Hectorol Injection,  Table 4  provides the adverse event incidence rates from placebo-controlled studies of oral Hectorol.



 Table 4:  Adverse Events Reported by &gt;=2% of Hectorol(r) Treated Patients and More Frequently Than Placebo During the Double-blind Phase of Two Clinical Studies 
 Adverse Event              Hectorol  (r)  (n=61)%     Placebo (n=61)%             
  
     Body as a Whole         
 Abscess                    3.3                        0.0                         
 Headache                   27.9                       18.0                        
 Malaise                    27.9                       19.7                        
     Cardiovascular System       
 Bradycardia                6.6                        4.9                         
     Digestive System        
 Anorexia                   4.9                        3.3                         
 Constipation               3.3                        3.3                         
 Dyspepsia                  4.9                        1.6                         
 Nausea/Vomiting            21.3                       19.7                        
     Musculo-Skeletal System       
 Arthralgia                 4.9                        0.0                         
     Metabolic and Nutritional       
 Edema                      34.4                       21.3                        
 Weight increase            4.9                        0.0                         
     Nervous System          
 Dizziness                  11.5                       9.8                         
 Sleep disorder             3.3                        0.0                         
     Respiratory System       
 Dyspnea                    11.5                       6.6                         
     Skin                    
 Pruritus                   8.2                        6.6                         
  A patient who reported the same medical term more than once was counted only once for that medical term.    
      Potential adverse effects of Hectorol are, in general, similar to those encountered with excessive vitamin D intake. The early and late signs and symptoms of vitamin D intoxication associated with hypercalcemia include:
 

   Early

  Weakness, headache, somnolence, nausea, vomiting, dry mouth, constipation, muscle pain, bone pain, metallic taste, and anorexia.



   Late

  Polyuria, polydipsia, anorexia, weight loss, nocturia, conjunctivitis (calcific), pancreatitis, photophobia, rhinorrhea, pruritus, hyperthermia, decreased libido, elevated blood urea nitrogen (BUN), albuminuria, hypercholesterolemia, elevated serum aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT), ectopic calcification, hypertension, cardiac arrhythmias, sensory disturbances, dehydration, apathy, arrested growth, urinary tract infections, and, rarely, overt psychosis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
