<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hemangeol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6    ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Hypoglycemia and related events, like hypoglycemic seizure [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  
 *  Bronchospasm [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions to HEMANGEOL (occurring &gt;= 10% of patients) were sleep disorders, aggravated respiratory tract infections, diarrhea, and vomiting. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact  P  ierre Fabre Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-855-PFPHARM (737-4276) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinicaltrials of a drug may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Clinical Trials Experience with HEMANGEOL in Infants with proliferating infantile hemangioma    In clinical trials for proliferating infantile hemangioma, the most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;10%) in infants treated with HEMANGEOL were sleep disorders, aggravated respiratory tract infections such as bronchitis and bronchiolitis associated with cough and fever, diarrhea, and vomiting.  Adverse reactions led to treatment discontinuation in fewer than 2% of treated patients.



 Overall, 479 patients in the pooled safety population were exposed to study drug in the clinical study program (456 in placebo-controlled trials). A total of 424 patients were treated with HEMANGEOL at doses 1.2 mg/kg/day or 3.4 mg/kg/day for 3 or 6 months. Of these, 63% of patients were aged 91-150 days and 37% were aged 35-90 days at randomization.



 The following table lists according to the dosage the most common adverse reactions (treatment-emergent adverse events with an incidence at least 3% greater on one of the two doses than on placebo).



   Table 2. Treatment-emergent adverse events occurring at least 3% more often on HEMANGEOL than on placebo  




  Reaction         PlaceboN=236     HEMANGEOL1.2 mg/kg/dayN=200    HEMANGEOL3.4 mg/kg/dayN=224    
  Sleep disorder    5.9%             17.5%            16.1%            
  Bronchitis       4.7              8.0              13.4             
  Peripheral coldness    0.4              8.0              6.7              
  Agitation        2.1              8.5              4.5              
  Diarrhea         1.3              4.5              6.3              
  Somnolence       0.4              5.0              0.9              
  Nightmare        1.7              2.0              6.3              
  Irritability     1.3              5.5              1.3              
  Decreased appetite    0.4              2.5              3.6              
  Abdominal pain    0.4              3.5              0.4              
          The following adverse events have been observed during clinical studies, with an incidence of less than 1%:
 

   Cardiac disorders:  Second degree atrioventricular heart block, in a patient with underlying conduction disorder, required definitive treatment discontinuation  [    see         Warnings and Precautions        (        5.4        )    ]  .



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Urticaria, alopecia



   Investigations:  Decreased blood glucose, decreased heart rate



   Compassionate Use Program  



 More than 600 infants received HEMANGEOL in a compassionate use program (CUP). Mean age at treatment initiation was 3.6 months. Mean dose of HEMANGEOL was 2.2 mg/kg/day and mean treatment duration was 7.1 months.



 The adverse reactions reported in the CUP were similar to the ADRs observed during clinical trials but some were more severe.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of propranolol. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 These adverse reactions are as follows:



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  Agranulocytosis



   Psychiatric disorders:  Hallucination



   Skin and subcutaneous tissues disorders:  Purpura
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypoglycemia: Administer during or after feeding. Do not use in patients who are not able to feed or are vomiting (  4  ,  5.1  ,  6  ,  10  ,  17  ) 
 *  Bradycardia and hypotension (  4  ,  5.2  ,  17  ) 
 *  Bronchospasm: Avoid use in patients with asthma or lower respiratory infection (  4  ,  5.3  ,  6  ,  10  ,  17  ) 
 *  Increased risk of stroke in PHACE syndrome (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypoglycemia



  HEMANGEOL prevents the response of endogenous catecholamines to correct hypoglycemia and masks the adrenergic warning signs of hypoglycemia, particularly tachycardia, palpitations and sweating. HEMANGEOL can cause hypoglycemia in children, especially when they are not feeding regularly or are vomiting; withhold the dose under these conditions. Hypoglycemia may present in the form of seizures, lethargy, or coma. If a child has clinical signs of hypoglycemia, discontinue HEMANGEOL and call their health care provider immediately or take the child to the emergency room.



 Concomitant treatment with corticosteroids may increase the risk of hypoglycemia [   see       Drug Interactions (7)    ]  .



    5.2 Bradycardia and Hypotension



  HEMANGEOL may cause or worsen bradycardia or hypotension. In the studies of HEMANGEOL for infantile hemangioma the mean decrease in heart rate was about 7 bpm with little effect on blood pressure. Monitor heart rate and blood pressure after treatment initiation or increase in dose. Discontinue treatment if severe (&lt;80 beats per minute) or symptomatic bradycardia or hypotension (systolic blood pressure &lt;50 mmHg) occurs.



    5.3 Bronchospasm



  HEMANGEOL can cause bronchospasm; do not use in patients with asthma or a history of bronchospasm. Interrupt treatment in the event of a lower respiratory tract infection associated with dyspnea and wheezing.



    5.4 Cardiac Failure



  Sympathetic stimulation supports circulatory function in patients with congestive heart failure, beta blockade may precipitate more severe failure.



    5.5 Increased Risk of Stroke in PHACE Syndrome



  By dropping blood pressure, HEMANGEOL may increase the risk of stroke in PHACE syndrome patients with severe cerebrovascular anomalies.



 Investigate infants with large facial infantile hemangioma for potential arteriopathy associated with PHACE syndrome prior to HEMANGEOL therapy. 



    5.6 Hypersensitivity



  Beta-blockers will interfere with epinephrine used to treat serious anaphylaxis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
