<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hemabate" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The adverse effects of HEMABATE Sterile Solution are generally transient and reversible when therapy ends. The most frequent adverse reactions observed are related to its contractile effect on smooth muscle.



 In patients studied, approximately two-thirds experienced vomiting and diarrhea, approximately one-third had nausea, one-eighth had a temperature increase greater than 2 degrees  F, and one-fourteenth experienced flushing.



 The pretreatment or concurrent administration of antiemetic and antidiarrheal drugs decreases considerably the very high incidence of gastrointestinal effects common with all prostaglandins used for abortion. Their use should be considered an integral part of the management of patients undergoing abortion with HEMABATE.



 Of those patients experiencing a temperature elevation, approximately one-sixteenth had a clinical diagnosis of endometritis. The remaining temperature elevations returned to normal within several hours after the last injection.



 Adverse effects observed during the use of HEMABATE for abortion and for hemorrhage, not all of which are clearly drug related, in decreasing order of frequency include:




 Vomiting                                       Nervousness                                               
 Diarrhea                                       Nosebleed                                                 
 Nausea                                         Sleep disorders                                           
 Flushing or hot flashes                        Dyspnea                                                   
 Chills or shivering                            Tightness in chest                                        
 Coughing                                       Wheezing                                                  
 Headaches                                      Posterior cervical perforation                            
 Endometritis                                   Weakness                                                  
 Hiccough                                       Diaphoresis                                               
 Dysmenorrhea-like pain                         Dizziness                                                 
 Paresthesia                                    Blurred vision                                            
 Backache                                       Epigastric pain                                           
 Muscular pain                                  Excessive thirst                                          
 Breast tenderness                              Twitching eyelids                                         
 Eye pain                                       Gagging, retching                                         
 Drowsiness                                     Dry throat                                                
 Dystonia                                       Sensation of choking                                      
 Asthma                                         Thyroid storm                                             
 Injection site pain                            Syncope                                                   
 Tinnitus                                       Palpitations                                              
 Vertigo                                        Rash                                                      
 Vaso-vagal syndrome                            Upper respiratory infection                               
 Dryness of mouth                               Leg cramps                                                
 Hyperventilation                               Perforated uterus                                         
 Respiratory distress                           Anxiety                                                   
 Hematemesis                                    Chest pain                                                
 Taste alterations                              Retained placental fragment                               
 Urinary tract infection                        Shortness of breath                                       
 Septic shock                                   Fullness of throat                                        
 Torticollis                                    Uterine sacculation                                       
 Lethargy                                       Faintness, light-headedness                               
 Hypertension                                   Uterine rupture                                           
 Tachycardia                                                                                              
 Pulmonary edema                                                                                          
 Endometritis from IUCD                                                                                   
        The most common complications when HEMABATE was utilized for abortion requiring additional treatment after discharge from the hospital were endometritis, retained placental fragments, and excessive uterine bleeding, occurring in about one in every 50 patients.
 

   Post-marketing experience

  Hypersensitivity reactions (e.g. Anaphylactic reaction, Anaphylactic shock, Anaphylactoid reaction, Angioedema).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
