<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="heparin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are hemorrhage, thrombocytopenia, HIT and HITTS, injection site irritation, general hypersensitivity reactions, and elevations of aminotransferase levels. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of HEPARIN SODIUM INJECTION. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency.



 *  *  -  Adrenal hemorrhage, with resultant acute adrenal insufficiency, has occurred with heparin therapy, including fatal cases. 
 *  -  Ovarian (corpus luteum) hemorrhage developed in a number of women of reproductive age receiving short- or long-term heparin therapy. 
 *  -  Retroperitoneal hemorrhage. 
   Hemorrhage - Hemorrhage is the chief complication that may result from heparin therapy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] . Gastrointestinal or urinary tract bleeding during anticoagulant therapy may indicate the presence of an underlying occult lesion. Bleeding can occur at any site but certain specific hemorrhagic complications may be difficult to detect including: 
 *  HIT and HITT, including delayed onset cases [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] . 
 *  Local irritation - Local irritation, erythema, mild pain, hematoma, or ulceration have occurred following deep subcutaneous (intrafat) injection of heparin sodium. Because such reactions occur more frequently after intramuscular administration, the IM route is not recommended. 
 *  Histamine-like reactions - Such reactions have been observed at the site of injection. Necrosis of the skin has been reported at the site of subcutaneous injection of heparin, occasionally requiring skin grafting [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] . 
 *  Hypersensitivity - Generalized hypersensitivity reactions have been reported with chills, fever, and urticaria as the most usual manifestations; asthma, rhinitis, lacrimation, headache, nausea and vomiting, and anaphylactoid reactions, including shock, occur less frequently. Itching and burning, especially on the plantar site of the feet, may occur. 
 *  Elevations of serum aminotransferases - Significant elevations of aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels have occurred in patients who have received heparin. 
 *  Others - Osteoporosis following long-term administration of high doses of heparin, cutaneous necrosis after systemic administration, suppression of aldosterone synthesis, delayed transient alopecia, priapism, and rebound hyperlipemia on discontinuation of heparin sodium have been reported. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Fatal Medication Errors: Confirm choice of correct strength prior to administration. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hemorrhage: Fatal cases have occurred. Use caution in conditions with increased risk of hemorrhage. (  5.2  ) 
 *  HIT and HITTS: Monitor for signs and symptoms and discontinue if indicative of HIT and HITTS. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Benzyl Alcohol Toxicity: Use preservative-free formulation in neonates and infants. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Monitoring: Blood coagulation tests guide therapy for full-dose heparin. Monitor platelet count and hematocrit in all patients receiving heparin. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Fatal Medication Errors



  Do not use HEPARIN SODIUM INJECTION as a "catheter lock flush" product. HEPARIN SODIUM INJECTION is supplied in vials containing various strengths of heparin, including vials that contain a highly concentrated solution of 10,000 units in 1 mL. Fatal hemorrhages have occurred in pediatric patients due to medication errors in which 1 mL HEPARIN SODIUM INJECTION vials were confused with 1 mL "catheter lock flush" vials. Carefully examine all HEPARIN SODIUM INJECTION vials to confirm the correct vial choice prior to administration of the drug.



    5.2 Hemorrhage



  Avoid using heparin in the presence of major bleeding, except when the benefits of heparin therapy outweigh the potential risks.



 Hemorrhage can occur at virtually any site in patients receiving heparin. Fatal hemorrhages have occurred. Adrenal hemorrhage (with resultant acute adrenal insufficiency), ovarian hemorrhage, and retroperitoneal hemorrhage have occurred during anticoagulant therapy with heparin [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1]  )  . A higher incidence of bleeding has been reported in patients, particularly women, over 60 years of age [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . An unexplained fall in hematocrit or fall in blood pressure should lead to serious consideration of a hemorrhagic event.



 Use heparin sodium with caution in disease states in which there is increased risk of hemorrhage, including:



 *  Cardiovascular - Subacute bacterial endocarditis, severe hypertension 
 *  Surgical - During and immediately following: (a) spinal puncture or spinal anesthesia or (b) major surgery, especially involving the brain, spinal cord, or eye 
 *  Hematologic - Conditions associated with increased bleeding tendencies, such as hemophilia, thrombocytopenia, and some vascular purpuras 
 *  Patients with hereditary antithrombin III deficiency receiving concurrent antithrombin III therapy - The anticoagulant effect of heparin is enhanced by concurrent treatment with antithrombin III (human) in patients with hereditary antithrombin III deficiency. To reduce the risk of bleeding, reduce the heparin dose during concomitant treatment with antithrombin III (human). 
 *  Gastrointestinal - Ulcerative lesions, continuous tube drainage of the stomach or small intestine, and clinical settings in which stress-induced gastrointestinal hemorrhage is possible. 
 *  Other - Menstruation, liver disease with impaired hemostasis, severe renal disease, or in patients with indwelling catheters. 
       5.3 Heparin-Induced Thrombocytopenia and Heparin-Induced Thrombocytopenia and Thrombosis
 

  Heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT) is a serious antibody-mediated reaction resulting from irreversible aggregation of platelets. HIT may progress to the development of venous and arterial thromboses, a condition known as heparin-induced thrombocytopenia and thrombosis (HITT). Thrombotic events may also be the initial presentation for HITT. These serious thromboembolic events include deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, cerebral vein thrombosis, limb ischemia, stroke, myocardial infarction, mesenteric thrombosis, renal arterial thrombosis, skin necrosis, gangrene of the extremities that may lead to amputation, and possibly death. Monitor thrombocytopenia of any degree closely. If the platelet count falls below 100,000/mm  3  or if recurrent thrombosis develops, promptly discontinue heparin, evaluate for HIT and HITT, and, if necessary, administer an alternative anticoagulant.



 HIT and HITT can occur up to several weeks after the discontinuation of heparin therapy. Patients presenting with thrombocytopenia or thrombosis after discontinuation of heparin should be evaluated for HIT and HITT.



    5.4 Benzyl Alcohol Toxicity



  Use preservative-free HEPARIN SODIUM INJECTION in neonates and infants. The preservative benzyl alcohol has been associated with serious adverse events and death in pediatric patients. The minimum amount of benzyl alcohol at which toxicity may occur is not known. Premature and low-birth weight infants may be more likely to develop toxicity [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].  



    5.5 Thrombocytopenia



  Thrombocytopenia in patients receiving heparin has been reported at frequencies up to 30%. It can occur 2 to 20 days (average 5 to 9) following the onset of heparin therapy. Obtain platelet counts before and periodically during heparin therapy. Monitor thrombocytopenia of any degree closely. If the count falls below 100,000/mm  3  or if recurrent thrombosis develops, promptly discontinue heparin, evaluate for HIT and HITT, and, if necessary, administer an alternative anticoagulant [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .



    5.6 Coagulation Testing and Monitoring



  When using a full dose heparin regimen, adjust the heparin dose based on frequent blood coagulation tests. If the coagulation test is unduly prolonged or if hemorrhage occurs, discontinue heparin promptly [see  Overdosage (10)  ]  . Periodic platelet counts and hematocrits are recommended during the entire course of heparin therapy, regardless of the route of administration [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  .



    5.7 Heparin Resistance



  Resistance to heparin is frequently encountered in fever, thrombosis, thrombophlebitis, infections with thrombosing tendencies, myocardial infarction, cancer, in postsurgical patients, and patients with antithrombin III deficiency. Close monitoring of coagulation tests is recommended in these cases. Adjustment of heparin doses based on anti-Factor Xa levels may be warranted.



    5.8 Hypersensitivity



  Patients with documented hypersensitivity to heparin should be given the drug only in clearly life-threatening situations.



 Because HEPARIN SODIUM INJECTION is derived from animal tissue, it should be used with caution in patients with a history of allergy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
