<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hepagam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The only adverse reactions observed in clinical trial subjects were hypotension and nausea (2% of clinical trial subjects).



   EXCERPT:   The only adverse reactions observed in clinical trial subjects were hypotension and nausea (2% of clinical trial subjects).  (6)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Cangene Corporation at 1-800-768-2304 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Hepatitis B-Related Liver Transplantation  



 In a clinical trial with 27 liver transplant patients, one adverse drug reaction was reported following the 578 (&lt;1%) HepaGam B infusions. This study utilized the recommended dosing regimen outlined in Table 1 [see Dosage and Administration  2.1 Prevention of Hepatitis B recurrence following Liver Transplantation  ]. The attributed adverse drug reaction of hypotension was reported in one patient. The reaction was associated with a single HepaGam B infusion during the first day post-transplant. The reaction resolved on the same day and did not recur with subsequent HepaGam B infusions.



   Healthy Volunteer Studies  



 Seventy healthy male and female volunteers received a single dose of HepaGam B intramuscularly in clinical trials  6  . Only one adverse drug reaction, an episode of nausea, was reported.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    The following adverse reactions have been identified during    postapproval    use of    HepaGam    B. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.  



     Postexposure        Prophylaxis:    



 Dizziness has been reported in the postmarketing surveillance of HepaGam B for the postexposure prophylaxis indication.



     Hepatitis B-Related Liver Transplantation:    



 The system organ classification of reported adverse reactions is provided below:




  Cardiac disorders:      Sinus tachycardia    
  Gastrointestinal disorders:       Abdominal pain upper    
  Nausea                  
  General disorders and administration site conditions:       Chills              
  Feeling cold            
  Influenza like illness    
  Pyrexia                 
  Immune system disorders:       Anaphylactoid reaction    
  Hypersensitivity        
  Investigations:         Lipase increased    
  Transaminases increased    
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:    Back pain           
  Nervous system disorders:    Dizziness  Headache    
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:    Dyspnoea            
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:    Cold sweat          
        Healthcare professionals should report adverse reactions following the administration of HepaGam B to Cangene Corporation at 1-800-768-2304 or FDA's MedWatch reporting system at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity  (5.1)   
 *    Interference with Blood Glucose Testing  (5.2)   
 *    Monitoring: Serum Anti-HBs Antibody Levels  (5.3)   
 *    Infusion Reactions  (5.4)   
 *    Transmissible Infectious Agents  (5.5)   
 *    Coagulation Disorders  (5.6)   
 *    Thrombotic Events  (5.7)   
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur with HepaGam B. HepaGam B should be administered in a setting with appropriate equipment, medication and personnel trained in the management of hypersensitivity, anaphylaxis and shock. In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue HepaGam B infusion immediately and begin appropriate emergency treatment. Medications such as epinephrine and antihistamines should be available for immediate treatment of acute hypersensitivity reactions.



 HepaGam B contains trace amounts of IgA (&lt;40 micrograms per milliliter). Patients with known antibodies to IgA may have a greater risk of severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. HepaGam B is contraindicated in IgA deficient patients with antibodies against IgA and history of hypersensitivity reaction. (see  4 CONTRAINDICATIONS  )



    5.2 Interference with Blood Glucose Testing



   The maltose contained in   HepaGam   B can interfere with some types of blood glucose monitoring systems, i.e., those based on the glucose   dehydrogenase      pyrroloquinequinone   (GDH-PQQ) method. This can result in falsely elevated glucose readings and, consequently, in the inappropriate administration of insulin, resulting in life-threatening hypoglycemia. Cases of true hypoglycemia may go untreated if the hypoglycemic state is masked by falsely elevated results.  



    5.3 Monitoring: Serum Anti-HBs Antibody Levels



  Liver transplant patients should be monitored regularly for serum anti-HBs antibody levels using a quantitative assay to ensure that adequate protective levels are maintained.



    5.4 Infusion reactions



   Certain adverse drug reactions may be related to the rate of infusion. The recommended infusion rate given under Dosage and Administration  (2.1)  must be closely followed. Patients must be closely monitored and carefully observed for any symptoms throughout the infusion period and immediately following an infusion.  



    5.5 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because HepaGam B is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g. viruses, and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have been associated with the use of HepaGam B. All infections suspected by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Cangene Corporation at 1-800-768-2304.



    5.6 Coagulation Disorders



  For postexposure prophylaxis indications, HepaGam B must be administered intramuscularly only. In patients who have severe thrombocytopenia or any coagulation disorder that would contraindicate intramuscular injections, HepaGam B should be given only if the expected benefits outweigh the potential risks.



    5.7 Thrombotic Events



  Thrombotic events may occur during or following treatment with IGIV products  4, 5  . Patients at risk include those with a history of atherosclerosis, multiple cardiovascular risk factors, advanced age, impaired cardiac output, coagulation disorders, prolonged periods of immobilization, and/or known/suspected hyperviscosity.



 Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients who are at risk of developing thrombotic events, administer HepaGam B at the minimum rate of infusion practicable.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
