<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hexalen" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Gastrointestinal  

  With continuous high-dose daily HEXALEN  (r)  capsules, nausea and vomiting of gradual onset occur frequently. Although in most instances these symptoms are controllable with anti-emetics, at times the severity requires HEXALEN  (r)  capsules dose reduction or, rarely, discontinuation of HEXALEN  (r)  capsules therapy. In some instances, a tolerance of these symptoms develops after several weeks of therapy. The incidence and severity of nausea and vomiting are reduced with moderate-dose administration of HEXALEN  (r)  capsules. In 2 clinical studies of single-agent HEXALEN  (r)  capsules utilizing a moderate, intermittent dose and schedule, only 1 patient (1%) discontinued HEXALEN  (r)  capsules due to severe nausea and vomiting.



     Neurotoxicity  

  Peripheral neuropathy and central nervous system symptoms (mood disorders, disorders of consciousness, ataxia, dizziness, vertigo) have been reported. They are more likely to occur in patients receiving continuous high-dose daily HEXALEN  (r)  (altretamine) capsules than moderate-dose HEXALEN  (r)  capsules administered on an intermittent schedule. Neurologic toxicity has been reported to be reversible when therapy is discontinued. Data from a randomized trial of HEXALEN  (r)  capsules and cisplatin plus or minus pyridoxine in ovarian cancer indicated that pyridoxine significantly reduced neurotoxicity; however, it adversely affected response duration suggesting that pyridoxine should not be administered with HEXALEN  (r)  capsules and/or cisplatin (1).



     Hematologic  

  HEXALEN  (r)  capsules causes mild to moderate dose-related myelosuppression. Leukopenia below 3000 WBC/mm  3  occurred in &lt;15% of patients on a variety of intermittent or continuous dose regimens. Less than 1% had leukopenia below 1000 WBC/mm  3  . Thrombocytopenia below 50,000 platelets/mm  3  was seen in &lt;10% of patients. When given in doses of 8-12 mg/kg/day over a 21 day course, nadirs of leukocyte and platelet counts were reached by 3-4 weeks, and normal counts were regained by 6 weeks. With continuous administration at doses of 6-8 mg/kg/day, nadirs are reached in 6-8 weeks (median).



 Data in the following table are based on the experience of 76 patients with ovarian cancer previously treated with a cisplatin-based combination regimen who received single-agent HEXALEN  (r)  capsules. In one study, HEXALEN  (r)  capsules, 260 mg/m  2  /day, was administered for 14 days of a 28 day cycle. In another study, HEXALEN  (r)  capsules, 6-8 mg/kg/day, was administered for 21 days of a 28 day cycle.



 ADVERSE EXPERIENCES IN 76 PREVIOUSLY TREATED OVARIAN CANCER PATIENTS RECEIVING SINGLE-AGENT HEXALEN(r) CAPSULES 
 Adverse Experiences                                                          % Patients                  
  
   Gastrointestinal  Nausea and Vomiting    Mild to Moderate    SevereIncreased Alkaline Phosphatase        33           32     19               
   Neurologic  Peripheral Sensory Neuropathy    Mild    Moderate to SevereAnorexia and FatigueSeizures     31           22     91     1            
   Hematologic  Leukopenia    WBC 2000-2999/mm  3      WBC &lt;2000/mm  3  Thrombocytopenia    Platelets 75,000-99,000/mm  3      Platelets &lt;75,000/mm  3  Anemia    Mild    Moderate to Severe  5          4     19          6     333           20       13   
   Renal  Serum Creatinine 1.6-3.75 mg/dlBUN    25-40 mg%    41-60 mg%    &gt;60 mg%       7     9          5     3     1        
        Additional adverse reaction information is available from 13 single-agent altretamine studies (total of 1014 patients) conducted under the auspices of the National Cancer Institute. The treated patients had a variety of tumors and many were heavily pretreated with other chemotherapies; most of these trials utilized high, continuous daily doses of altretamine (612 mg/kg/day). In general, adverse reaction experiences were similar in the two trials described above. Additional toxicities, not reported in the above table, included hepatic toxicity, skin rash, pruritus and alopecia, each occurring in &lt;1% of patients.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

WARNINGS



  

WARNINGS



    *  HEXALEN(r) capsules should only be given under the supervision of a physician experienced in the use of antineoplastic agents. 
 *  Peripheral blood counts should be monitored at least monthly, prior to the initiation of each course of HEXALEN(r) capsules, and as clinically indicated (see Adverse Reactions). 
 *  Because of the possibility of HEXALEN(r) capsules-related neurotoxicity, neurologic examination should be performed regularly during HEXALEN(r) capsules administration (see Adverse Reactions). 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
