<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hiberix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common solicited adverse events (&gt;=20%) were pain and redness at the injection site, fever, fussiness, loss of appetite, and restlessness. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or  www.vaers.hhs.gov  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. There is the possibility that broad use of HIBERIX could reveal adverse reactions not observed in clinical trials.



 In 7 clinical studies, 1,008 children received HIBERIX as a booster dose following primary vaccination with either HIBERIX (not approved for primary series in US, N = 530), Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA (N = 235), Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine manufactured by Merck &amp; Co., Inc. (N = 26), or Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine manufactured by Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc. (no longer licensed in the US, N = 217). None of the studies included a comparator group that received a booster dose with a US-licensed Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine. Studies were conducted in Europe, Canada, and Latin America. Across these studies, the mean age of subjects at the time of booster vaccination with HIBERIX ranged from 16 to 19 months. At the time of vaccination, 172 (17.1%) subjects were 11 to 14 months of age, 642 (63.7%) subjects were 15 to 18 months of age, and 194 (19.2%) subjects were 19 to 25 months of age. Approximately half of the subjects were male. Among subjects for whom information on race/ethnicity was available, nearly all subjects were white.



 In these 7 studies, HIBERIX was administered concomitantly with non-US formulations (containing 2.5 mg 2-phenoxyethanol per dose as preservative) of one of the following US-licensed vaccines: INFANRIX  (r)  (Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed) (DTaP), KINRIX  (r)  (Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids and Acellular Pertussis Adsorbed and Inactivated Poliovirus Vaccine) (DTaP-IPV), or PEDIARIX  (r)  [Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids and Acellular Pertussis Adsorbed, Hepatitis B (Recombinant) and Inactivated Poliovirus Vaccine] (DTaP-HBV-IPV). In the studies, DTaP-IPV and DTaP-HBV-IPV were administered in dosing regimens not approved in the US. Some subjects received DTaP-HBV (GlaxoSmithKline Biologicals, not licensed in US) concomitantly with HIBERIX.



   Solicited Adverse Events:  In an open-label, multicenter study conducted in Germany, 371 children received a booster dose of HIBERIX administered concomitantly with DTaP-HBV-IPV. The mean age at the time of vaccination was 16 months. Subjects in this study had previously received a primary series with either HIBERIX (not approved for primary series in US, N = 92), Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA (N = 96), or Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine manufactured by Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc. (no longer licensed in the US) (N = 183). All subjects previously received 3 doses of DTaP-HBV-IPV. Information on adverse events was collected by parents/guardians using standardized forms for 4 consecutive days following vaccination with HIBERIX (i.e., day of vaccination and the next 3 days). The reported frequencies of solicited local and general adverse events are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1. Percentage of Children With Solicited Local And General Adverse Events Within 4 Days of Vaccinationa With HIBERIXb Coadministered With DTaP-HBV-IPVc, Intent to Treat Cohort (N = 371) 
                     %  Any    %  Grade 3    
  Locald                                 
  Redness            24.5    2.4e        
  Pain               20.5    1.1f        
  Swelling           14.8    2.2e        
  General                                
  Feverg             34.8    3.8         
  Fussiness          25.9    0.8h        
  Loss of appetite    22.9    0.8i        
  Restlessness       21.8    0.5i        
  Sleepiness         19.9    1.1i        
  Diarrhea           14.6    0.8i        
  Vomiting           4.9     0.5i        
         N = all subjects for whom safety data were available.
 

   a  Within 4 days of vaccination defined as day of vaccination and the next 3 days.



   b  In this study, 92 subjects previously received 3 doses of HIBERIX (not approved for primary immunization in the US), 96 subjects previously received 3 doses of a US-licensed Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine (manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA), and 183 subjects previously received 3 doses of a Haemophilus b Conjugate Vaccine that is no longer licensed in the US.



   c  In this study, DTaP-HBV-IPV was given to subjects who previously received 3 doses of DTaP-HBV-IPV. In the US, PEDIARIX is approved for use as a 3-dose primary series; use as a fourth consecutive dose is not approved in the US.



   d  Local reactions at the injection site for HIBERIX.



   e  Grade 3 redness or swelling defined as &gt;20 mm.



   f  Grade 3 pain defined as causing crying when limb moved.



   g  Fever defined as &gt;=100.4 degrees F (&gt;=38.0 degrees C) rectally or &gt;=99.5 degrees F (&gt;=37.5 degrees C) axillary, oral or tympanic; Grade 3 fever defined as &gt;103.1 degrees F (&gt;39.5 degrees C) rectally or &gt;102.2 degrees F (&gt;39.0 degrees C) axillary, oral or tympanic.



   h  Grade 3 fussiness defined as persistent crying and could not be comforted.



   i  Grade 3 for these symptoms defined as preventing normal daily activity.



   Serious Adverse Events:  Two of 1,008 subjects reported a serious adverse event that occurred in the 31-day period following booster immunization with HIBERIX. One subject developed bilateral pneumonia 9 days post-vaccination and one subject experienced asthenia following accidental drug ingestion 18 days post-vaccination.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to reports in clinical trials, worldwide voluntary reports of adverse events received for HIBERIX since market introduction (1996) of this vaccine are listed below. This list includes serious events and/or events which have a plausible causal connection to HIBERIX. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccination.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Extensive swelling of the vaccinated limb, injection site induration.



   Immune System Disorders:  Allergic reactions (including anaphylactic and anaphylactoid reactions), angioedema.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Convulsions (with or without fever), hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode, somnolence, syncope or vasovagal responses to injection.



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  Apnea.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Rash, urticaria.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the decision to give HIBERIX should be based on potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
 *    The tip cap of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals. (  5.2  ,  16  ) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including HIBERIX. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome has occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the decision to give any tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine, including HIBERIX, should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and possible risks.



    5.2 Latex



   The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals  [see How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16)].



     5.3 Syncope  



   Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including HIBERIX. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.  



    5.4 Preventing and Managing Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Prior to administration, the healthcare provider should review the patient's immunization history for possible vaccine hypersensitivity. Epinephrine and other appropriate agents used for the control of immediate allergic reactions must be immediately available should an acute anaphylactic reaction occur.



    5.5 Altered Immunocompetence



  Safety and effectiveness of HIBERIX in immunosuppressed children have not been evaluated. If HIBERIX is administered to immunosuppressed children, including children receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained.



    5.6 Interference With Laboratory Tests



  Urine antigen detection may not have a diagnostic value in suspected disease due to H. influenzae type b within 1 to 2 weeks after receipt of a H. influenzae type b-containing vaccine, including HIBERIX [see Drug Interactions (7.1)].



    5.7 Tetanus Immunization



  Immunization with HIBERIX does not substitute for routine tetanus immunization.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
