<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hizentra" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions (ARs), observed in &gt;=5% of study subjects receiving Hizentra, were local reactions (e.g., swelling, redness, heat, pain, and itching at the injection site), headache, diarrhea, fatigue, back pain, nausea, pain in extremity, cough, rash, pruritus, vomiting, abdominal pain (upper), migraine, and pain.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions observed in &gt;=5% of study subjects were local reactions (i.e., swelling, redness, heat, pain, and itching at the injection site), headache, diarrhea, fatigue, back pain, nausea, pain in extremity, cough, rash, pruritus, vomiting, abdominal pain (upper), migraine, and pain (  6  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, AR rates observed in clinical studies of a product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another product and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     US Study  



 The safety of Hizentra was evaluated in a clinical study in the US for 15 months (3-month wash-in/wash-out period followed by a 12-month efficacy period) in subjects with PI who had been treated previously with IGIV every 3 or 4 weeks. The safety analyses included 49 subjects in the intention-to-treat (ITT) population. The ITT population consisted of all subjects who received at least one dose of Hizentra  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .



 Subjects were treated with Hizentra at weekly median doses ranging from 66 to 331 mg/kg body weight (mean: 181.4 mg/kg) during the wash-in/wash-out period and from 72 to 379 mg/kg (mean: 213.2 mg/kg) during the efficacy period. The 49 subjects received a total of 2264 weekly infusions of Hizentra.



 Table 2 summarizes the most frequent adverse reactions (ARs) (experienced by at least 2 subjects) occurring during or within 72 hours after the end of an infusion. Local reactions were assessed by the investigators 15 to 45 minutes post-infusion and by the subjects 24 hours post-infusion. The investigators then evaluated the ARs arising from the subject assessments. Local reactions were the most frequent ARs observed, with injection-site reactions (e.g., swelling, redness, heat, pain, and itching at the site of injection) comprising 98% of local reactions.



 Table 2: Incidence of Subjects with Adverse Reactions (ARs) (Experienced by 2 or More Subjects) and Rate per Infusion (ITT Population), US Study 
                                           ARsOccurring During or Within 72 Hours of Infusion   
 AR (&gt;=2 Subjects)                          Number (%) of Subjects(n=49)   Number (Rate) of ARs(n=2264 Infusions)   
  
 Local reactions                                      49 (100)                      1322 (0.584)            
 Other ARs:                                                                                                 
   Headache                                          12 (24.5)                       32 (0.014)             
   Diarrhea                                           5 (10.2)                       6 (0.003)              
   Fatigue                                            4 (8.2)                        4 (0.002)              
   Back pain                                          4 (8.2)                        5 (0.002)              
   Nausea                                             4 (8.2)                        4 (0.002)              
   Pain in extremity                                  4 (8.2)                        6 (0.003)              
   Cough                                              4 (8.2)                        4 (0.002)              
   Vomiting                                           3 (6.1)                        3 (0.001)              
   Abdominal pain, upper                              3 (6.1)                        3 (0.001)              
   Migraine                                           3 (6.1)                        4 (0.002)              
   Pain                                               3 (6.1)                        4 (0.002)              
   Arthralgia                                         2 (4.1)                        3 (0.001)              
   Contusion                                          2 (4.1)                        3 (0.001)              
   Rash                                               2 (4.1)                        3 (0.001)              
   Urticaria                                          2 (4.1)                       2 (&lt; 0.001)             
         The ratio of infusions with ARs  ,  including local reactions, to all infusions was 1303 to 2264 (57.6%). Excluding local reactions, the corresponding ratio was 56 to 2264 (2.5%).
 

 Table 3 summarizes injection-site reactions based on investigator assessments 15 to 45 minutes after the end of the 683 infusions administered during regularly scheduled visits (every 4 weeks).



 Table 3: Investigator Assessments15 to 45 minutes after the end of infusions administered at regularly scheduled visits (every 4 weeks). of Injection-Site Reactions by Infusion, US Study 
 Injection-Site Reaction                                 Number(Rate) of Reactions(n=683 Infusions)       
  
 Edema/induration                                                        467 (0.68)                       
 Erythema                                                                346 (0.51)                       
 Local heat                                                              108 (0.16)                       
 Local pain                                                              88 (0.13)                        
 Itching                                                                 64 (0.09)                        
        Most local reactions were either mild (93.4%) or moderate (6.3%) in intensity.
 

 No deaths or serious ARs occurred during the study. Two subjects withdrew from the study due to ARs. One subject experienced a severe injection-site reaction one day after the third weekly infusion, and the other subject experienced moderate myositis. Both reactions were judged to be "at least possibly related" to the administration of Hizentra.



     European Study  



 In a clinical study conducted in Europe, the safety of Hizentra was evaluated for 10 months (3-month wash-in/wash-out period followed by a 7-month efficacy period) in 51 subjects with PI who had been treated previously with IGIV every 3 or 4 weeks or with IGSC weekly.



 Subjects were treated with Hizentra at weekly median doses ranging from 59 to 267 mg/kg body weight (mean: 118.8 mg/kg) during the wash-in/wash-out period and from 59 to 243 mg/kg (mean: 120.1 mg/kg) during the efficacy period. The 51 subjects received a total of 1831 weekly infusions of Hizentra.



 Table 4 summarizes the most frequent ARs (experienced by at least 2 subjects) occurring during or within 72 hours after the end of an infusion. Local reactions were assessed by the subjects between 24 and 72 hours post-infusion. The investigators then evaluated the ARs arising from the subject assessments.



 Table 4: Incidence of Subjects with Adverse Reactions (ARs) Excluding infections. (Experienced by 2 or More Subjects) and Rate per Infusion, European Study 
                                           ARsOccurring During or Within 72 Hours of Infusion   
 AR (&gt;=2 Subjects)                          Number (%) of Subjects(n=51)   Number (Rate) of ARs(n=1831 Infusions)   
  
 Local reactions                                     24 (47.1)                      105 (0.057)             
 Other ARs:                                                                                                 
   Headache                                           9 (17.6)                       20 (0.011)             
   Rash                                               4 (7.8)                        4 (0.002)              
   Pruritus                                           4 (7.8)                        13 (0.007)             
   Fatigue                                            3 (5.9)                        5 (0.003)              
   Abdominal pain, upper                              2 (3.9)                        3 (0.002)              
   Arthralgia                                         2 (3.9)                        2 (0.001)              
   Erythema                                           2 (3.9)                        4 (0.002)              
   Abdominal discomfort                               2 (3.9)                        3 (0.002)              
   Back pain                                          2 (3.9)                        2 (0.001)              
   Hematoma                                           2 (3.9)                        3 (0.002)              
   Hypersensitivity                                   2 (3.9)                        4 (0.002)              
         The proportion of subjects reporting local reactions decreased over time from approximately 20% following the first infusion to &lt;5% by the end of the study.
 

 Three subjects withdrew from the study due to ARs of mild to moderate intensity. One subject experienced injection-site pain and injection-site pruritus; the second subject experienced injection-site reaction, fatigue, and feeling cold; and the third subject experienced injection-site reaction and hypersensitivity. All reactions were judged by the investigator to be "at least possibly related" to the administration of Hizentra.



     Biweekly (Every Two Weeks) or Frequent (2 To 7 Times per Week) Dosing  



 No data regarding ARs are available for these alternative Hizentra dosing regimens because no clinical trials using these regimens were conducted; however, it is unlikely that the safety profile is qualitatively different from that of weekly dosing.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



     Hizentra  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of Hizentra. This list does not include reactions already reported in clinical studies with Hizentra  [  see    Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 *   Infusion reactions: Allergic-anaphylactic reactions such as swollen face or tongue and pharyngeal edema, pyrexia, chills, dizziness, hypertension/changes in blood pressure, malaise. 
 *   Cardiovascular: Chest discomfort (including chest pain) 
 *   Respiratory: Dyspnea 
 *   Neurological: Tremor, burning sensation 
    The following adverse reactions have been reported during postmarketing use of immune globulin products  5  :
 

 *   Infusion reactions: Tachycardia, flushing, wheezing, rigors, myalgia 
 *   Renal: Osmotic nephropathy 
 *   Respiratory: Apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS), cyanosis, hypoxemia, pulmonary edema, bronchospasm 
 *   Cardiovascular: Cardiac arrest, vascular collapse, hypotension 
 *   Neurological: Coma, loss of consciousness, seizures, aseptic meningitis syndrome 
 *   Integumentary: Stevens-Johnson syndrome, epidermolysis, erythema multiforme, dermatitis (e.g., bullous dermatitis) 
 *   Hematologic: Pancytopenia, leukopenia, hemolysis, positive direct antiglobulin (Coombs') test 
 *   Gastrointestinal: Hepatic dysfunction 
    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  THROMBOSIS

    WARNING:  THROMBOSIS  

    *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products1-3, including Hizentra. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors (see Warnings and Precautions [5.2], Patient Counseling Information [17]). 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer Hizentra at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity (see Warnings and Precautions [5.2]). 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: THROMBOSIS  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including Hizentra. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer Hizentra at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  IgA-deficient patients with anti-IgA antibodies are at greater risk of severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions (  5.1  ). 
 *  Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products, including Hizentra (  5.2  ). 
 *  Aseptic meningitis syndrome has been reported with IGIV or IGSC treatment (  5.3  ). 
 *  Monitor renal function, including blood urea nitrogen, serum creatinine, and urine output in patients at risk of acute renal failure (  5.4  ). 
 *  Monitor for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis (  5.5  ). 
 *  Monitor for pulmonary adverse reactions (transfusion-related acute lung injury [TRALI]) (  5.6  ) .  
 *  Hizentra is made from human plasma and may contain infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent (  5.7  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur to human immune globulin or components of Hizentra, such as polysorbate 80. If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, discontinue the Hizentra infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment.



 Individuals with IgA deficiency can develop anti-IgA antibodies and anaphylactic reactions (including anaphylaxis and shock) after administration of blood components containing IgA. Patients with known antibodies to IgA may have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions with administration of Hizentra. Hizentra contains &lt;=50 mcg/mL IgA [   see     Description (11)  ]  .



    5.2 Thrombosis



  Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products  1-3  , including Hizentra. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors.



 Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer Hizentra at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity [see     Boxed Warning     ,     Patient Counseling Information (17)  ].  



    5.3 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



  AMS has been reported with use of IGIV  4  or IGSC. The syndrome usually begins within several hours to 2 days following immune globulin treatment. AMS is characterized by the following signs and symptoms: severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea, and vomiting. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies frequently show pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per cubic millimeter, predominantly from the granulocytic series, and elevated protein levels up to several hundred mg/dL. AMS may occur more frequently in association with high doses (&gt;=2 g/kg) and/or rapid infusion of immune globulin product.



 Patients exhibiting such signs and symptoms should receive a thorough neurological examination, including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis. Discontinuation of immune globulin treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae.



    5.4 Renal Dysfunction/Failure



   Acute renal dysfunction/failure, acute tubular necrosis, proximal tubular nephropathy, osmotic nephrosis and death may occur with use of human immune globulin products, especially those containing sucrose.  5  Hizentra does not contain sucrose. Ensure that patients are not volume depleted before administering Hizentra.  



  For patients judged to be at risk for developing renal dysfunction, including patients with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs, monitor renal function and consider lower, more frequent dosing [see  Dosing and Administration (2.3)  ]  .  



  Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to have a potential increased risk of developing acute renal failure.  6  Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of Hizentra and at appropriate intervals thereafter. If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuing Hizentra.  



    5.5 Hemolysis



  Hizentra can contain blood group antibodies that may act as hemolysins and induce in vivo  coating of red blood cells (RBCs) with immunoglobulin, causing a positive direct antiglobulin (Coombs') test result and hemolysis.  7-9  Delayed hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to immune globulin therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration, and acute hemolysis, consistent with intravascular hemolysis, has been reported.  10  



  Monitor recipients of Hizentra for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis. If signs and/or symptoms of hemolysis are present after Hizentra infusion, perform appropriate confirmatory laboratory testing.  



    5.6 Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Noncardiogenic pulmonary edema may occur in patients administered human immune globulin products.  11  TRALI is characterized by severe respiratory distress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function, and fever. Typically, it occurs within 1 to 6 hours following transfusion. Patients with TRALI may be managed using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



 Monitor Hizentra recipients for pulmonary adverse reactions. If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies in both the product and patient's serum.



    5.7 Transmissible Infectious Agents



   Because Hizentra is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. This also applies to unknown or emerging viruses and other pathogens. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have been associated with the use of Hizentra. All infections suspected by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by Hizentra should be reported to CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958.  



    5.8 Laboratory Tests



  Various passively transferred antibodies in immunoglobulin preparations may lead to misinterpretation of the results of serological testing.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
