<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="honey" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

 Physicians administering Hymenoptera Venom testing or treatment materials should be experienced in the treatment of severe systemic reactions (see  WARNINGS  Box at the beginning of this Instruction Sheet).  (1) Local Reactions    Some erythema, swelling or pruritis at the site of injection are common, the extent varying with the patient.  Excessively large, painful or persistent local reactions can occur from skin tests or immunotherapy. Frequent application of cold, wet dressings to the area and/or the use of oral antihistamines will ameliorate the discomfort. Reactions usually subside in 24-36 hours. Large local reactions occurred in approximately 60% of the patients given immunotherapy in a clinical study. None of the local reactions required specific treatment; however, subsequent injections in many instances were held to the previous dose or a reduced dose. Some patients had repeated large local reactions that slowed the increase in the immunotherapy dose.  (4)  See  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY  and  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  section. A mild burning immediately after the injection is to be expected. This usually leaves in 10 to 20 seconds. See also  WARNINGS  and  PRECAUTIONS  regarding proper method and route of injection.  (2) Systemic Reactions  Most severe systemic reactions usually will begin within a 30-minute time period, but systemic reactions may occur at any time after skin tests or immunotherapy. Symptoms may range from mild to life-threatening from anaphylaxis as described under  INDICATIONS AND USAGE  . With careful attention to dosage and administration, severe systemic reactions occur infrequently, but it cannot be overemphasized that in sensitive individuals, any injection could result in anaphylactic shock. Therefore, it is imperative that physicians administering allergenic extracts understand and be prepared for the treatment of severe reactions. See  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY  for clinical incidence of systemic reactions and course of action following these reactions.  If a systemic or anaphylactic reaction does occur, apply a tourniquet above the site of injection and inject 1:1000 epinephrine-hydrochloride intramuscularly or subcutaneously into the opposite arm. Loosen the tourniquet at least every 10 minutes. Do not obstruct arterial blood flow with the tourniquet.  EPINEPHRINE DOSAGEADULT: 0.3 to 0.5 mL should be injected. Repeat in 5 to 10 minutes if necessary.PEDIATRIC: The usual initial dose is 0.01 mg (mL) per kg body weight or 0.3 mg (mL) per square meter of body surface area. Suggested dosage for infants to 2 years of age is 0.05 mL to 0.1 mL; for children 2 to 6 years, 0.15 mL; and children 6 to 12 years, 0.2 mL. Single pediatric doses should not exceed 0.3 mg (mL). Doses may be repeated as frequently as every 20 minutes, depending on the severity of the condition and the response of the patient.After administration of epinephrine, profound shock or vasomotor collapse should be treated with intravenous fluids, and possibly vasoactive drugs. Airway patency should be insured. Oxygen should be given by mask. Intravenous antihistamines, inhaled bronchodilators, theophylline and/or corticosteroids may be used if necessary after adequate epinephrine and circulatory support have been given. Emergency resuscitation measures and personnel trained in their use should be available immediately in the event of a serious systemic or anaphylactic reaction not responsive to the above measures [Ref. J. Allergy and Clinical Immunology, 77(2): p.271-273, 1986].Rarely are all of the above measures necessary; the tourniquet and epinephrine usually produce prompt responses. However, the physician should be prepared in advance for all contingencies. Promptness in beginning emergency treatment measures is of utmost importance.For recommendations regarding how to proceed with venom extract dose following systemic reactions, see  WARNINGS  ,  PRECAUTIONS  and  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  sections.  (3) Adverse Event Reporting  Report all adverse events to Jubilant HollisterStier Customer Technical Services Department at 1(800) 992-1120. A voluntary adverse event reporting system for health professionals is available through the FDA MEDWATCH program. Preprinted forms (FDA Form 3500) are available from the FDA by calling 1(800) FDA-1088. Completed forms should be mailed to MEDWATCH, 5600 Fisher Lane, Rockville, MD 20852-9787 or Fax to: 1(800) FDA-0178. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS

  WARNINGS

 This product is intended for use only by licensed medical personnel experienced in administering allergenic extracts and trained to provide immediate emergency treatment in the event of a life-threatening reaction. Hymenoptera venom extracts may potentially elicit a severe life-threatening systemic reaction, rarely resulting in death.   (1)   Therefore, emergency measures and personnel trained in their use must be available immediately in the event of such a reaction. Patients should be instructed to recognize adverse reaction symptoms, observed in the office for at least 30 minutes after skin testing or treatment, and cautioned to contact the physician's office if symptoms occur. See    ADVERSE REACTION  , Section 3, of the instruction for information regarding adverse event reporting. All patients should have available an Emergency Anaphylaxis Kit containing epinephrine and be instructed in its use for emergency treatment of possible systemic reactions occurring at times after the patient has departed the testing or treatment premises. Patients with cardiovascular diseases and/or pulmonary diseases such as symptomatic unstable, steroid-dependent asthma, and/or those who are receiving cardiovascular drugs such as beta blockers, may be at higher risk for severe adverse reactions. These patients may also be more refractory to the normal allergy treatment regimen. Patients should be treated only if the benefit of treatment outweighs the risks.   (1)  Patients on beta blockers may be more reactive to allergens given for testing or treatment and may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reactions.   (2)  Immunotherapy for insect sting allergy should be given to those patients who have experienced significant systemic reactions (for detailed description of symptoms see    INDICATIONS AND USAGE   and    ADVERSE REACTIONS  ) from insect stings and who demonstrate hypersensitivity by skin testing with these products. The only approved method for diagnosing insect sting allergic patients for immunization is by skin testing. This product must never be injected intravenously. Refer also to    CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,    WARNINGS  ,   PRECAUTIONS  ,    ADVERSE REACTIONS   and    OVERDOSAGE   for further discussion. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
