<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="humatrope" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions reported in adult and pediatric patients receiving somatropin include injection site reactions, hypersensitivity to the diluent, and hypothyroidism (  6.1  ). Additional common adverse reactions in adults include edema, arthralgia, myalgia, carpal tunnel syndrome, paraesthesias, and hyperglycemia (  6.1  ,  6.2  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Most Serious and/or Most Frequently Observed Adverse Reactions

  This list presents the most serious  a  and/or most frequently observed  b  adverse reactions during treatment with somatropin (including events observed in patients who received brands of somatropin other than Humatrope):



 *    a  Sudden death in pediatric patients with Prader-Willi syndrome who had risk factors including severe obesity, history of upper airway obstruction or sleep apnea and unidentified respiratory infection [see Contraindications (  4.2  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    a  Intracranial tumors, in particular meningiomas, in teenagers/young adults treated with radiation to the head for a first neoplasm who subsequently receive somatropin [see Contraindications (  4.3  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    a  Pancreatitis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
 *    a,b  Glucose intolerance including impaired glucose tolerance/impaired fasting glucose as well as overt diabetes mellitus [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    a  Intracranial hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *    a  Significant diabetic retinopathy [see Contraindications (  4.4  )]  
 *    a  Slipped capital femoral epiphysis in pediatric patients [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *    a  Progression of preexisting scoliosis in pediatric patients [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *    b  Fluid retention manifested by edema, arthralgia, myalgia, nerve compression syndromes including carpal tunnel syndrome/paraesthesias [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *    a  Unmasking of latent central hypothyroidism [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *    a  Injection site reactions/rashes and lipoatrophy (as well as rare generalized hypersensitivity reactions) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.13  )]  
      6.2 Clinical Trials Experience
   Because clinical trials are conducted under varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed during the clinical trials performed with one somatropin formulation cannot always be directly compared to the rates observed during the clinical trials performed with a second somatropin formulation, and may not reflect the adverse reaction rates observed in practice.



     Pediatric Patients  



     GH Deficiency  



 As with all protein pharmaceuticals, a small percentage of patients may develop antibodies to the protein. During the first 6 months of Humatrope therapy in 314 naive patients, only 1.6% developed specific antibodies to Humatrope (binding capacity &gt;=0.02 mg/L). None had antibody concentrations which exceeded 2 mg/L. Throughout 8 years of this same study, two patients (0.6%) had binding capacity &gt;2 mg/L. Neither patient demonstrated a decrease in growth velocity at or near the time of increased antibody production. It has been reported that growth attenuation from pituitary-derived GH may occur when antibody concentrations are &gt;1.5 mg/L.



 In addition to an evaluation of compliance with the treatment program and of thyroid status, testing for antibodies to somatropin should be carried out in any patient who fails to respond to therapy.



 In studies with GH deficient pediatric patients, injection site pain was reported infrequently. A mild and transient edema, which appeared in 2.5% of patients, was observed early during the course of treatment.



     Turner Syndrome  



 In a randomized, concurrent-controlled, open-label trial, there was a statistically significant increase in the occurrence of otitis media (43% vs. 26%), ear disorders (18% vs. 5%) and surgical procedures (45% vs. 27%) in patients receiving Humatrope compared with untreated control patients (  Table 1  ). A similar increase in otitis media was observed in an 18-month placebo-controlled trial.



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions of Special Interest by Treatment Group in Turner Syndrome 
  a Open-label study.                    
  b Dose=0.3 mg/kg/wk.                   
  
                                          Treatment Group  a                             
   Adverse Reaction                       Untreated             Humatrope  b          Significance         
 Total Number of Patients               62                    74                                           
 Surgical procedure                     17 (27.4%)            33 (44.6%)            p&lt;=0.05                
 Otitis media                           16 (25.8%)            32 (43.2%)            p&lt;=0.05                
 Ear disorders                          3 (4.8%)              13 (17.6%)            p&lt;=0.05                
              Idiopathic Short Stature  
 

 In a randomized, placebo-controlled study of Humatrope treatment (0.22 mg/kg/week) to adult height in patients with idiopathic short stature, the adverse events reported in Humatrope-treated patients (  Table 2  ) were similar to those observed in other pediatric populations treated with Humatrope. Mean serum glucose concentration did not change during Humatrope treatment. Mean fasting serum insulin concentration increased 10% in the Humatrope treatment group at the end of treatment relative to baseline, but remained within the normal reference range. For the same duration of treatment, the mean fasting serum insulin concentration decreased by 2% in the placebo group. The occurrence rates of above-range values for glucose, insulin, and HbA1cwere similar in the Humatrope (somatropin)- and placebo-treated groups. No patient developed diabetes mellitus. Consistent with the known mechanism of growth hormone action, Humatrope-treated patients had greater mean increases, relative to baseline, in serum insulin-like growth factor-I (IGF-I) than placebo-treated patients at each study observation. However, there was no significant difference between the Humatrope and placebo treatment groups in the proportion of patients who had at least one serum IGF-I concentration more than 2.0 SD above the age- and gender-appropriate mean (Humatrope: 9 of 35 patients [26%]; placebo: 7 of 28 patients [25%]).



 Table 2: Non-serious Clinically Significant Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions by Treatment Group in Idiopathic Short Stature 
                                 Treatment Group               
   Adverse Reaction              Placebo                        Humatrope                                  
 Total Number of Patients      31                             37                                           
 Scoliosis                     4 (12.9%)                      7 (18.9%)                                    
 Otitis media                  2 (6.5%)                       6 (16.2%)                                    
 Hyperlipidemia                1 (3.2%)                       3 (8.1%)                                     
 Gynecomastia                  1 (3.2%)                       2 (5.4%)                                     
 Hip pain                      0                              1 (2.7%)                                     
 Arthralgia                    1 (3.2%)                       4 (10.8%)                                    
 Arthrosis                     2 (6.5%)                       4 (10.8%)                                    
 Myalgia                       4 (12.9%)                      9 (24.3%)                                    
 Hypertension                  0                              1 (2.7%)                                     
         The adverse events observed in the dose-response study (239 patients treated for 2 years) did not indicate a pattern suggestive of a somatropin dose effect. Among Humatrope dose groups, mean fasting blood glucose, mean glycosylated hemoglobin, and the incidence of elevated fasting blood glucose concentrations were similar. One patient developed abnormalities of carbohydrate metabolism (glucose intolerance and high serum HbA1c) on treatment.
 

     SHOX Deficiency  



 Clinically significant adverse events (adverse events previously observed in association with growth hormone treatment in general) were assessed prospectively during the 2-year randomized, open-label study; those observed are presented in  Table 3  . In both treatment groups, the mean fasting plasma glucose concentration at the end of the first year was similar to the baseline value and remained in the normal range. No patient developed diabetes mellitus or had an above normal value for fasting plasma glucose at the end of one-year of treatment. During the 2 year study period, the proportion of patients who had at least one IGF-I concentration greater than 2.0 SD above the age- and gender-appropriate mean was 10 of 27 [37.0%] for the Humatrope-treated group vs. 0 of 24 patients [0.0%] for the untreated group. The proportion of patients who had at least one IGFBP-3 concentration greater than 2.0 SD above the age and gender appropriate mean was 16 of 27 [59.3%] for the Humatrope treated group vs. 7 of 24 [29.2%] for the untreated group.



 Table 3: Clinically Significant Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactionsa,b by Treatment Group in Patients with SHOX Deficiency 
  a All events were non-serious.                  
  b Events are included only if reported for a greater number of Humatrope-treated than Untreated patients.    
  c Percentage calculated for males only (1/12).    
  
   Adverse Reaction                                Treatment Group             
   Untreated                                       Humatrope                   
 Total Number of Patients                        25                           27                          
 Patients with at least one event                2                            5                           
 Arthralgia                                      2 (8.0%)                     3 (11.1%)                   
 Gynecomastia  c                                 0 (0.0%)                     1 (8.3%)                    
 Excessive number of cutaneous nevi              0 (0.0%)                     2 (7.4%)                    
 Scoliosis                                       0 (0.0%)                     1 (3.7%)                    
             Small for Gestational Age  
 

     Study 1  - In a 2-year, multicenter, randomized study, 193 non-GH deficient children with short stature born SGA who failed to demonstrate catch-up growth were treated with 2 different Humatrope treatment regimens: a fixed dose of 0.067 mg/kg/day (FHD group) or an individually adjusted dose regimen (IAD group; starting dose 0.035 mg/kg/day which could be increased as early as Month 3 to 0.067 mg/kg/day based on a validated growth prediction model). The most frequently reported adverse events were common childhood infectious diseases. Adverse events possibly/probably related to Humatrope were otitis media and headaches (where there was a suggestion of a modest dose response), and slipped capital femoral epiphysis (1 child)  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  ) and Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . There were no clear cut cases of new-onset diabetes mellitus, no children treated for hyperglycemia, and no children whose fasting blood glucose exceeded 126 mg/dL at any time during the study. However, 6 children (4 in the FHD group and 2 in the IAD group whose dose was increased from 0.035 mg/kg/day to 0.067 mg/kg/day [one at Month 3 and one at Year 1]) manifested impaired fasting glucose at Year 2. Two of these six children displayed impaired fasting glucose during the study as well, and one of them was required to discontinue Humatrope at Month 15 as a consequence  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) and Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . A modestly dose-dependent increase in mean serum IGF-I SDS concentrations within the reference range was observed; of note, at study completion, 20-25% of these children had serum IGF-I SDS values &gt; +2.



     Study 2  - A 2-year, open-label, single-arm study of Humatrope at a dosage of 0.067 mg/kg/day in 35 non-GH deficient children with short stature born SGA who failed to demonstrate catch-up growth did not reveal further safety data of note.



     Study 3  - Additional safety information was obtained from 340 short children born SGA followed in an observational study who received an average Humatrope dosage of 0.041 mg/kg/day (maximum dose: 0.084 mg/kg/day) for an average of 3.0 years. Type 2 diabetes mellitus apparently precipitated by Humatrope therapy was reported in a single patient, but appeared to resolve after discontinuation of Humatrope treatment, as the child had a normal oral glucose tolerance test and was receiving no antihyperglycemic medications 9 months after the drug was discontinued. One patient manifested carpal tunnel syndrome  [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  and another developed an exacerbation of preexisting scoliosis  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  ) and Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  which may have been related to Humatrope treatment.



 In both Study 1 and Study 2, after treatment with Humatrope, bone maturation did not accelerate excessively, and the timing of puberty was age-appropriate in boys and girls.



 Therefore, it can be concluded that no novel adverse events potentially related to treatment with Humatrope were reported in either short-term study or were apparent after a review of the post-marketing, observational, safety database.



     Adult Patients  



 In clinical studies in which high doses of Humatrope were administered to healthy adult volunteers, the following events occurred infrequently: headache, localized muscle pain, weakness, mild hyperglycemia, and glucosuria.



     Adult-Onset GH Deficiency  



 In the first 6 months of controlled blinded trials during which patients received either Humatrope or placebo, adult-onset GH deficient adults who received Humatrope experienced a statistically significant increase in edema (Humatrope 17.3% vs. placebo 4.4%, p=0.043) and peripheral edema (11.5% vs. 0%, respectively, p=0.017). In patients with adult-onset GH deficiency, edema, muscle pain, joint pain, and joint disorder were reported early in therapy and tended to be transient or responsive to dosage titration.



 Two of 113 adult-onset patients developed carpal tunnel syndrome after beginning maintenance therapy without a low dose (0.00625 mg/kg/day) lead-in phase. Symptoms abated in these patients after dosage reduction.



 All treatment-emergent adverse events with &gt;=5% overall occurrence rate during 12 or 18 months of replacement therapy with Humatrope are shown in  Table 4  (adult-onset patients) and in  Table 5  (childhood-onset patients).



 Adult patients treated with Humatrope who had been diagnosed with GH deficiency in childhood reported side effects less frequently than those with adult-onset GH deficiency.



 Table 4: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions with &gt;=5% Overall Occurrence in Adult-Onset Growth Hormone-Deficient Patients Treated with Humatrope for 18 Months as Compared with 6-Month Placebo and 12-Month Humatrope Exposurea 
  a Abbreviations: GH=Humatrope; N=number of patients receiving treatment in the period stated; n=number of patients reporting each treatment-emergent adverse event.    
  b p=0.04 as compared to placebo (6 months).    
  c p=0.02 as compared to placebo (6 months).    
  
   Adverse Reaction          18 Months Exposure[Placebo (6 Months)/GH (12 Months)](N=46)      18 Months GH Exposure(N=52)     
   n                         %                       n                       %               
 Edema  b                  7                       15.2                    11               21.2              
 Arthralgia                7                       15.2                    9                17.3              
 Paresthesia               6                       13.0                    9                17.3              
 Myalgia                   6                       13.0                    7                13.5              
 Pain                      6                       13.0                    7                13.5              
 Rhinitis                  5                       10.9                    7                13.5              
 Peripheral edema  c       8                       17.4                    6                11.5              
 Back pain                 5                       10.9                    5                9.6               
 Headache                  5                       10.9                    4                7.7               
 Hypertension              2                       4.3                     4                7.7               
 Acne                      0                       0                       3                5.8               
 Joint disorder            1                       2.2                     3                5.8               
 Surgical procedure        1                       2.2                     3                5.8               
 Flu syndrome              3                       6.5                     2                3.9               
               Childhood-Onset GH Deficiency  
 

 Two double-blind, placebo-controlled trials were conducted in 67 adult patients with childhood-onset GH deficiency who had received previous somatropin treatment during childhood. Patients were randomized to receive either placebo injections or Humatrope (0.00625 mg/kg/day [6.25 mug/kg/day] for the first 4 weeks, then 0.0125 mg/kg/day [12.5 mug/kg/day] thereafter) for the first 6 months, followed by open-label Humatrope for the next 12 months for all patients. The patients in these studies reported side effects less frequently than those with adult-onset GH deficiency. During the placebo-controlled phase (first 6 months) of the study, elevations of serum glutamic oxaloacetic transferase were reported significantly more often for Humatrope-treated (12.5%) than placebo-treated patients (0.0%, p=0.031). No other events were reported significantly more often for Humatrope-treated patients during the placebo-controlled phase. The following events were reported for at least 5% of patients in either of the 2 treatment groups over the 18-month duration of the study, listed in descending order of maximum frequency for either group: aspartate aminotransferase increased 13%, headache 11%, edema 9%, pain 9%, alanine aminotransferase increased 6%, asthenia 6%, myalgia 6%, respiratory disorder 6%.



 Table 5: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions with &gt;=5% Overall Occurrence in Childhood-Onset Growth Hormone-Deficient Patients Treated with Humatrope for 18 Months as Compared with 6-Month Placebo and 12-Month Humatrope Exposurea 
  a Abbreviations: GH=Humatrope; N=number of patients receiving treatment in the period stated; n=number of patients reporting each treatment-emergent adverse event; ALT=alanine aminotransferase, formerly SGPT; AST=aspartate aminotransferase, formerly SGOT.    
  b p=0.03 as compared to placebo (6 months).    
  
   Adverse Reaction          18 Months Exposure[Placebo (6 Months)/GH (12 Months)](N=35)      18 Months GH Exposure    (N=32)     
   n                         %                       n                       %               
 Flu syndrome              8                       22.9                    5                15.6              
 AST increased  b          2                       5.7                     4                12.5              
 Headache                  4                       11.4                    3                9.4               
 Asthenia                  1                       2.9                     2                6.3               
 Cough increased           0                       0                       2                6.3               
 Edema                     3                       8.6                     2                6.3               
 Hypesthesia               0                       0                       2                6.3               
 Myalgia                   2                       5.7                     2                6.3               
 Pain                      3                       8.6                     2                6.3               
 Rhinitis                  2                       5.7                     2                6.3               
 ALT increased             2                       5.7                     2                6.3               
 Respiratory disorder      2                       5.7                     1                3.1               
 Gastritis                 2                       5.7                     0                0                 
 Pharyngitis               5                       14.3                    1                3.1               
             6.3 Post-Marketing Experience
   Because these adverse events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The adverse events reported during post-marketing surveillance do not differ from those listed/discussed above in Sections 6.1 and 6.2 in children and adults.



 Other adverse events that have been reported in somatropin-treated patients include the following:



 *      Neurologic - Headaches (common in children and occasional in adults). 
 *      Skin - Increase in size or number of cutaneous nevi, especially in patients with Turner syndrome and those with SHOX deficiency [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )] . 
 *      Endocrine - Gynecomastia. 
 *      Gastrointestinal - Pancreatitis. Cases of pancreatitis have been reported rarely in children and adults receiving somatropin treatment, with some evidence supporting a greater risk in children compared with adults. Published literature indicates that girls who have Turner syndrome may be at greater risk than other somatropin-treated children. Pancreatitis should be considered in any somatropin-treated patient, especially a child, who develops abdominal pain [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )] . 
 *      Metabolic - New-onset type 2 diabetes mellitus in patients. 
 *      Neoplasia - Leukemia has been reported in a small number of GH deficient children treated with somatropin, somatrem (methionylated rhGH), and GH of pituitary origin. It is uncertain whether these cases of leukemia are related to GH therapy, the pathology of GH deficiency itself, or other associated treatments such as radiation therapy. On the basis of current evidence, experts have not been able to conclude that GH therapy per se was responsible for these cases of leukemia. The risk for children with GH deficiency, if any, remains to be established [see Contraindications (  4.3  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )] . 
    In an ongoing post-marketing observational study of somatropin treatment in 3,102 GH-deficient adults, hypertension, dyspnea, and sleep apnea were reported by 1% to less than 10% of patients after various durations of treatment.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute Critical Illness: Evaluate potential benefit of treatment continuation against potential risk. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Prader-Willi Syndrome: Evaluate for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiation of treatment for GH deficiency. Discontinue treatment if these signs occur. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Neoplasm: Monitor patients with preexisting tumors for progression or recurrence. Increased risk of a second neoplasm in childhood cancer survivors treated with somatropin - in particular meningiomas in patients treated with radiation to the head for their first neoplasm. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Impaired Glucose Tolerance (IGT) and Diabetes Mellitus (DM): Periodically monitor glucose levels in all patients, as IGT or DM may be unmasked. Doses of concurrent antihyperglycemic drugs in patients with DM may require adjustment. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Intracranial Hypertension (IH): Exclude preexisting papilledema. IH may develop, but is usually reversible after discontinuation or dose reduction. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Fluid Retention (e.g., edema, arthralgia, carpal tunnel syndrome - especially in adults): Reduce dose as necessary if such signs develop. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypothyroidism: Monitor thyroid function periodically as hypothyroidism may first become evident or worsen after initiation of somatropin. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis (SCFE): Evaluate any child with onset of a limp or hip/knee pain for possible SCFE. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis: Monitor any child with scoliosis for progression of the curve. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Pancreatitis: Consider pancreatitis in patients with abdominal pain, especially children. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Critical Illness



  Increased mortality in patients with acute critical illness due to complications following open heart surgery, abdominal surgery or multiple accidental trauma, or those with acute respiratory failure has been reported after treatment with pharmacologic doses of somatropin [see Contraindications (  4.1  )]  . The safety of continuing somatropin treatment in patients receiving replacement doses for approved indications who concurrently develop these illnesses has not been established. Therefore, the potential benefit of treatment continuation with somatropin in patients experiencing acute critical illnesses should be weighed against the potential risk.



    5.2 Prader-Willi Syndrome in Children



  There have been reports of fatalities after initiating therapy with somatropin in pediatric patients with Prader-Willi syndrome who had one or more of the following risk factors: severe obesity, history of upper airway obstruction or sleep apnea, or unidentified respiratory infection. Male patients with one or more of these factors may be at greater risk than females. Patients with Prader-Willi syndrome should be evaluated for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiation of treatment with somatropin. If, during treatment with somatropin, patients show signs of upper airway obstruction (including onset of, or increased, snoring) and/or new onset sleep apnea, treatment should be interrupted. All patients with Prader-Willi syndrome treated with somatropin should also have effective weight control and be monitored for signs of respiratory infection, which should be diagnosed as early as possible and treated aggressively [see Contraindications (  4.2  )]  . Humatrope is not indicated for the treatment of pediatric patients who have growth failure due to genetically confirmed Prader-Willi syndrome.



    5.3 Neoplasms



     In childhood cancer survivors who were treated with radiation to the brain/head for their first neoplasm and who developed subsequent GH deficiency and were treated with somatropin, an increased risk of a second neoplasm has been reported. Intracranial tumors, in particular meningiomas, were the most common of these second neoplasms. In adults, it is unknown whether there is any relationship between somatropin replacement therapy and CNS tumor recurrence [see Contraindications (  4.3  )]  . Monitor all patients receiving somatropin therapy who have a history of GH deficiency secondary to an intracranial neoplasm for progression or recurrence of the tumor.



    Because children with certain rare genetic causes of short stature have an increased risk of developing malignancies, practitioners should thoroughly consider the risks and benefits of starting somatropin in these patients. If treatment with somatropin is initiated, these patients should be carefully monitored for development of neoplasms.



    Monitor patients receiving somatropin therapy carefully for increased growth, or potential malignant changes, of preexisting nevi.



    5.4 Glucose Intolerance and Diabetes Mellitus



  Treatment with somatropin may decrease insulin sensitivity, particularly at higher doses in susceptible patients. As a result, previously undiagnosed impaired glucose tolerance and overt diabetes mellitus may be unmasked, and new onset type 2 diabetes mellitus has been reported in patients taking somatropin. Therefore, glucose levels should be monitored periodically in all patients treated with somatropin, especially in those with risk factors for diabetes mellitus, such as obesity, Turner syndrome, or a family history of diabetes mellitus. Patients with preexisting type 1 or type 2 diabetes mellitus or impaired glucose tolerance should be monitored closely during somatropin therapy. The doses of antihyperglycemic drugs (e.g., insulin or oral agents) may require adjustment when somatropin therapy is instituted in these patients.



    5.5 Intracranial Hypertension



  Intracranial hypertension (IH) with papilledema, visual changes, headache, nausea, and/or vomiting has been reported in a small number of patients treated with somatropin products. Symptoms usually occurred within the first eight (8) weeks after the initiation of somatropin therapy. In all reported cases, IH-associated signs and symptoms rapidly resolved after cessation of therapy or a reduction of the somatropin dose. Funduscopic examination should be performed routinely before initiating treatment with somatropin to exclude preexisting papilledema, and periodically during the course of somatropin therapy. If papilledema is observed by funduscopy during somatropin treatment, treatment should be stopped. If somatropin-induced IH is diagnosed, treatment with somatropin can be restarted at a lower dose after IH-associated signs and symptoms have resolved. Patients with Turner syndrome may be at increased risk for the development of IH.



    5.6 Fluid Retention



  Fluid retention during somatropin replacement therapy in adults may frequently occur. Clinical manifestations of fluid retention are usually transient and dose dependent.



    5.7 Hypopituitarism



  Patients with hypopituitarism (multiple pituitary hormone deficiencies) should have their other hormonal replacement treatments closely monitored during somatropin treatment.



    5.8 Hypothyroidism



  Undiagnosed/untreated hypothyroidism may prevent an optimal response to somatropin, in particular, the growth response in children. Patients with Turner syndrome have an inherently increased risk of developing autoimmune thyroid disease and primary hypothyroidism. In patients with GH deficiency, central (secondary) hypothyroidism may first become evident or worsen during somatropin treatment. Therefore, patients treated with somatropin should have periodic thyroid function tests performed, and thyroid hormone replacement therapy should be initiated or appropriately adjusted when indicated.



    5.9 Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis in Pediatric Patients



  Slipped capital femoral epiphysis may occur more frequently in patients with endocrine disorders (including pediatric GH deficiency and Turner syndrome) or in patients undergoing rapid growth. Any pediatric patient with the onset of a limp or complaints of hip or knee pain during somatropin therapy should be carefully evaluated.



    5.10 Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis in Pediatric Patients



  Progression of scoliosis can occur in patients who experience rapid growth. Because somatropin increases growth rate, patients with a history of scoliosis who are treated with somatropin should be monitored for progression of scoliosis. However, somatropin has not been shown to increase the occurrence of scoliosis. Skeletal abnormalities including scoliosis are commonly seen in untreated patients with Turner syndrome. Scoliosis is also commonly seen in untreated patients with Prader-Willi syndrome. Physicians should be alert to these abnormalities, which may manifest during somatropin therapy.



    5.11 Otitis Media and Cardiovascular Disorders in Patients with Turner Syndrome



  Patients with Turner syndrome should be evaluated carefully for otitis media and other ear disorders, as these patients have an increased risk of ear and hearing disorders. Somatropin treatment may increase the occurrence of otitis media in patients with Turner syndrome. In addition, patients with Turner syndrome should be monitored closely for cardiovascular disorders (e.g., hypertension, aortic aneurysm or dissection, stroke) as patients with Turner syndrome are also at increased risk for these conditions.



    5.12 Pancreatitis



  Cases of pancreatitis have been reported rarely in children and adults receiving somatropin treatment, with some evidence supporting a greater risk in children compared with adults. Published literature indicates that girls who have Turner syndrome may be at greater risk than other somatropin-treated children. Pancreatitis should be considered in any somatropin-treated patient, especially a child, who develops abdominal pain.



    5.13 Local and Systemic Reactions



  When somatropin is administered subcutaneously at the same site over a long period of time, tissue atrophy may result. This can be avoided by rotating the injection site [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  . As with any protein, local or systemic allergic reactions may occur. Parents/patients should be informed that such reactions are possible and that prompt medical attention should be sought if allergic reactions occur.



    5.14 Laboratory Tests



  Serum levels of inorganic phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase, parathyroid hormone and IGF-I may increase after somatropin therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
