<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="humalog1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions associated with HUMALOG include hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, injection site reactions, lipodystrophy, pruritus, and rash. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    Observed with HUMALOG U-100  



 The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere:



 *  Hypoglycemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )] . 
 *  Hypokalemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )] . 
      6.1 Clinical Trial Experience
   Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying designs, the adverse reaction rates reported in one clinical trial may not be easily compared with those rates reported in another clinical trial, and may not reflect the rates actually observed in clinical practice.



 The frequencies of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events during HUMALOG clinical trials in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus are listed in the tables below.



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events in Patients with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus (adverse events with frequency &gt;=5%) 
   Events, n (%)             Lispro(n=81)               Regular human insulin(n=86)     
 Flu syndrome              28 (34.6)                  28 (32.6)                     
 Pharyngitis               27 (33.3)                  29 (33.7)                     
 Rhinitis                  20 (24.7)                  25 (29.1)                     
 Headache                  24 (29.6)                  19 (22.1)                     
 Pain                      16 (19.8)                  14 (16.3)                     
 Cough increased           14 (17.3)                  15 (17.4)                     
 Infection                 11 (13.6)                  18 (20.9)                     
 Nausea                    5 (6.2)                    13 (15.1)                     
 Accidental injury         7 (8.6)                    10 (11.6)                     
 Surgical procedure        5 (6.2)                    12 (14.0)                     
 Fever                     5 (6.2)                    10 (11.6)                     
 Abdominal pain            6 (7.4)                    7 (8.1)                       
 Asthenia                  6 (7.4)                    7 (8.1)                       
 Bronchitis                6 (7.4)                    6 (7.0)                       
 Diarrhea                  7 (8.6)                    5 (5.8)                       
 Dysmenorrhea              5 (6.2)                    6 (7.0)                       
 Myalgia                   6 (7.4)                    5 (5.8)                       
 Urinary tract infection   5 (6.2)                    4 (4.7)                       
        Table 2: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (adverse events with frequency &gt;=5%) 
   Events, n (%)             Lispro(n=714)              Regular human insulin(n=709)     
 Headache                  63 (11.6)                  66 (9.3)                      
 Pain                      77 (10.8)                  71 (10.0)                     
 Infection                 72 (10.1)                  54 (7.6)                      
 Pharyngitis               47 (6.6)                   58 (8.2)                      
 Rhinitis                  58 (8.1)                   47 (6.6)                      
 Flu syndrome              44 (6.2)                   58 (8.2)                      
 Surgical procedure        53 (7.4)                   48 (6.8)                      
             Insulin initiation and intensification of glucose control  
 

 Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with a transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. However, long-term glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.



     Lipodystrophy  



 Long-term use of insulin, including HUMALOG, can cause lipodystrophy at the site of repeated insulin injections or infusion. Lipodystrophy includes lipohypertrophy (thickening of adipose tissue) and lipoatrophy (thinning of adipose tissue), and may affect insulin absorption. Rotate insulin injection or infusion sites within the same region to reduce the risk of lipodystrophy  [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  .



     Weight gain  



 Weight gain can occur with insulin therapy, including HUMALOG, and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin and the decrease in glucosuria.



     Peripheral Edema  



 Insulin, including HUMALOG, may cause sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy.



     Adverse Reactions with Continuous Subcutaneous Insulin Infusion (CSII) - HUMALOG U-100  



 In a 12-week, randomized, crossover study in adult patients with type 1 diabetes (n=39), the rates of catheter occlusions and infusion site reactions were similar for HUMALOG U-100 and regular human insulin treated patients (  see    Table 3  ).



 Table 3: Catheter Occlusions and Infusion Site Reactions 
                                    HUMALOG U-100(n=38)                 Regular human insulin(n=39)         
 Catheter occlusions/month          0.09                                0.10                                
 Infusion site reactions            2.6% (1/38)                         2.6% (1/39)                         
         In a randomized, 16-week, open-label, parallel design study of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes, adverse event reports related to infusion-site reactions were similar for insulin lispro and insulin aspart (21% of 100 patients versus 17% of 198 patients, respectively). In both groups, the most frequently reported infusion site adverse events were infusion site erythema and infusion site reaction.
 

     Allergic Reactions  



     Local Allergy  - As with any insulin therapy, patients taking HUMALOG may experience redness, swelling, or itching at the site of the injection. These minor reactions usually resolve in a few days to a few weeks, but in some occasions, may require discontinuation of HUMALOG. In some instances, these reactions may be related to factors other than insulin, such as irritants in a skin cleansing agent or poor injection technique.



     Systemic Allergy  - Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, may occur with any insulin, including HUMALOG. Generalized allergy to insulin may cause whole body rash (including pruritus), dyspnea, wheezing, hypotension, tachycardia, or diaphoresis.



 In controlled clinical trials, pruritus (with or without rash) was seen in 17 patients receiving regular human insulin (n=2969) and 30 patients receiving HUMALOG (n=2944).



 Localized reactions and generalized myalgias have been reported with injected metacresol, which is an excipient in HUMALOG  [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



     Antibody Production  



 In large clinical trials with patients with type 1 (n=509) and type 2 (n=262) diabetes mellitus, anti-insulin antibody (insulin lispro-specific antibodies, insulin-specific antibodies, cross-reactive antibodies) formation was evaluated in patients receiving both regular human insulin and HUMALOG (including patients previously treated with human insulin and naive patients). As expected, the largest increase in the antibody levels occurred in patients new to insulin therapy. The antibody levels peaked by 12 months and declined over the remaining years of the study. These antibodies do not appear to cause deterioration in glycemic control or necessitate an increase in insulin dose. There was no statistically significant relationship between the change in the total daily insulin dose and the change in percent antibody binding for any of the antibody types.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    HUMALOG U-100  



 The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of HUMALOG. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Medication errors in which other insulins have been accidentally substituted for HUMALOG have been identified during postapproval use  [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.4  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Never share a HUMALOG KwikPen, cartridge, reusable pen compatible with Lilly 3 mL cartridges, or syringe between patients, even if the needle is changed. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Hyper- or Hypoglycemia with Changes in Insulin Regimen: Carry out under close medical supervision and increase frequency of blood glucose monitoring. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia: May be life-threatening. Monitor blood glucose and increase monitoring frequency with changes to insulin dosage, use of glucose lowering medications, meal pattern, physical activity; in patients with renal or hepatic impairment; and in patients with hypoglycemia unawareness. (  5.3  ,  7  ,  8.6  ,  8.7  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia Due to Medication Errors: Accidental mix-ups between insulin products can occur. Instruct patients to check insulin labels before injection. Do not transfer HUMALOG U-200 from the HUMALOG KwikPen to a syringe as overdosage and severe hypoglycemia can result. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity Reactions: May be life-threatening. Discontinue HUMALOG, monitor and treat if indicated. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Hypokalemia: May be life-threatening. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk of hypokalemia and treat if indicated. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Fluid Retention and Heart Failure with Concomitant Use of Thiazolidinediones (TZDs): Observe for signs and symptoms of heart failure; consider dosage reduction or discontinuation if heart failure occurs. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Hyperglycemia and Ketoacidosis Due to Insulin Pump Device Malfunction: Monitor glucose and administer HUMALOG U-100 by subcutaneous injection if pump malfunction occurs. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Never Share a HUMALOG KwikPen, Cartridge, Reusable Pen Compatible with Lilly 3 mL Cartridges  1  , or Syringe Between Patients



     HUMALOG KwikPens, cartridges, and reusable pens compatible with Lilly 3 mL cartridges must never be shared between patients, even if the needle is changed. Patients using HUMALOG vials must never share needles or syringes with another person. Sharing poses a risk for transmission of blood-borne pathogens.



    5.2 Hyper- or Hypoglycemia with Changes in Insulin Regimen



  Changes in insulin strength, manufacturer, type, or method of administration may affect glycemic control and predispose to hypoglycemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  or hyperglycemia. These changes should be made cautiously and under close medical supervision and the frequency of blood glucose monitoring should be increased.



    5.3 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction associated with insulins, including HUMALOG. Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening, or cause death. Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving or operating other machinery).



 Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual. Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic nerve disease, in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers) [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  , or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia.



    Risk Factors for Hypoglycemia  



 The risk of hypoglycemia after an injection is related to the duration of action of the insulin and, in general, is highest when the glucose lowering effect of the insulin is maximal. As with all insulin preparations, the glucose lowering effect time course of HUMALOG may vary in different individuals or at different times in the same individual and depends on many conditions, including the area of injection as well as the injection site blood supply and temperature [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  . Other factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content or timing of meals), changes in level of physical activity, or changes to co-administered medication [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  . Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  ,  8.7  )]  .



    Risk Mitigation Strategies for Hypoglycemia  



 Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia. In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended.



    5.4 Hypoglycemia Due to Medication Errors



     Accidental mix-ups between basal insulin products and other insulins, particularly rapid-acting insulins, have been reported. To avoid medication errors between HUMALOG and other insulins, instruct patients to always check the insulin label before each injection.



    Do not transfer HUMALOG U-200 from the HUMALOG KwikPen to a syringe. The markings on the insulin syringe will not measure the dose correctly and can result in overdosage and severe hypoglycemia [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .



    5.5 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur with insulin products, including HUMALOG. If hypersensitivity reactions occur, discontinue HUMALOG; treat per standard of care and monitor until symptoms and signs resolve [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . HUMALOG is contraindicated in patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to HUMALOG or any of its excipients [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



    5.6 Hypokalemia



  All insulin products, including HUMALOG, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia. Untreated hypokalemia may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia if indicated (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications, patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations).



    5.7 Fluid Retention and Heart Failure with Concomitant Use of PPAR-gamma Agonists



  Thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists, can cause dose-related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate heart failure. Patients treated with insulin, including HUMALOG, and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of heart failure. If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care, and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.



    5.8 Hyperglycemia and Ketoacidosis Due to Insulin Pump Device Malfunction



  Malfunction of the insulin pump or insulin infusion set or insulin degradation can rapidly lead to hyperglycemia and ketoacidosis. Prompt identification and correction of the cause of hyperglycemia or ketosis is necessary. Interim subcutaneous injections with HUMALOG may be required. Patients using continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion pump therapy must be trained to administer insulin by injection and have alternate insulin therapy available in case of pump failure [see How Supplied/Storage and Handling (  16.2  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17.7  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
