<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="humatep" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reaction observed in patients receiving Humate-P is anaphylaxis. Thromboembolic events have also been observed in patients receiving Humate-P for the treatment of VWD  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . Reports of thromboembolic events in VWD patients with other thrombotic risk factors receiving coagulation factor replacement therapy have been obtained from spontaneous reports, published literature, and a European clinical study. In some cases, inhibitors to coagulation factors may occur. However, no inhibitor formation was observed in any of the clinical studies.



 In patients receiving Humate-P in clinical studies for treatment of VWD, the most commonly reported adverse reactions observed by &gt;5% of subjects are allergic-anaphylactic reactions (including urticaria, chest tightness, rash, pruritus, and edema). For patients undergoing surgery, the most common adverse reactions are postoperative wound and injection-site bleeding, and epistaxis.



    EXCERPT:    *  Most common adverse reactions observed by &gt;5% of subjects after receiving Humate-P are allergic-anaphylactic reactions (e.g., urticaria, chest tightness, rash, pruritus, edema) and, in patients undergoing surgery, postoperative wound and injection-site bleeding, and epistaxis (  6  ). 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  



     Treatment of Bleeding Episodes in VWD  



 Allergic symptoms, including allergic reaction, urticaria, chest tightness, rash, pruritus, and edema, were reported in 6 of 97 (6%) subjects in a Canadian retrospective study  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  . Four of 97 (4%) subjects experienced seven adverse events that were considered to have a possible or probable relationship to Humate-P. These included chills, phlebitis, vasodilation, paresthesia, pruritus, rash, and urticaria. All were mild in intensity with the exception of a moderate case of pruritus.



 In a prospective, open-label safety and efficacy study of Humate-P in VWD subjects with serious life- or limb-threatening bleeding or undergoing emergency surgery, seven of 71 (10%) subjects experienced nine adverse reactions. These were one occurrence each of mild vasodilation and mild pruritis; two occurrences of mild paresthesia; and one occurrence each of moderate peripheral edema and extremity pain and severe pseudothrombocytopenia (platelet clumping with a false low reading). Humate-P was discontinued in the subject who experienced the peripheral edema and extremity pain.



     Prevention of Excessive Bleeding During and After Surgery in VWD  



 Among the 63 VWD subjects who received Humate-P for prevention of excessive bleeding during and after surgery, including one subject who underwent colonoscopy without the planned polypectomy, the most common adverse events were postoperative hemorrhage (35 events in 19 subjects with five subjects experiencing bleeding at up to three different sites), postoperative nausea (15 subjects), and postoperative pain (11 subjects). Table 5 presents the postoperative hemorrhagic adverse events.



 Table 5: Hemorrhagic Adverse Events in 63 Surgical Subjects 
 Adverse Event         Surgical Procedure Category  Number of Subjects/Events  Onset(Number of Events)  Severity(Number of Events)   
                                                             On         Post        Mild        Mod        Severe     
  
 Wound/injection site bleeding       Major            8/11            7           4           9           -           2        
 Minor                       2/2               2             -           1           1           -        
 Oral                        2/6               -             6           3           3           -        
 Epistaxis                  Major             4/4            2           2           3           1           -        
 Minor                       1/1               1             -           1           -           -        
 Cerebral hemorrhage/subdural hematoma       Major             1/2            2           -           -           2           -        
 Gastrointestinal bleeding       Major             1/3          3             -           -           2           1        
 Menorrhagia                Major             1/1            1           -           -           1           -        
 Groin bleed                Oral              1/1            -           1           1           -           -        
 Ear bleed                  Major             1/1            1           -           1           -           -        
 Hemoptysis                 Major             1/1            1           -           1           -           -        
 Hematuria                  Major             1/1            1           -           1           -           -        
 Shoulder bleed             Major             1/1            1           -           1           -           -        
              Table 6 lists the non-hemorrhagic adverse events reported in at least two subjects, regardless of causality, and the adverse events that were possibly related to Humate-P. Pulmonary embolus considered possibly related to Humate-P occurred in one elderly subject who underwent bilateral knee replacement.
 

 Table 6: Non-Hemorrhagic and Possibly Related Adverse Events in 63 Surgical Subjects 
 Body System                Adverse Event (AE)         Number of Subjects With an AE Possibly Related to Humate-P  Number of Subjects With an AE Regardless of Causality   
  
 Body as a whole            Pain                                   -                         11               
 Fever                      -                                      4               
 Abdominal pain             -                                      3               
 Infection                  -                                      3               
 Surgery                    -                                      3               
 Back pain                  -                                      2               
 Facial edema               -                                      2               
 Cardiovascular             Chest pain                             -                          3               
 Pulmonary embolus          1                                      1               
 Thrombophlebitis           1                                      1               
 Digestive                  Nausea                                 1                         15               
 Constipation               -                                      7               
 Vomiting                   1                                      3               
 Sore throat                -                                      2               
 Hemic and lymphatic system  Anemia/decreased hemoglobin              -                          2               
 Metabolic/nutritional      Increased SGPT                         1                          1               
 Nervous                    Dizziness                              1                          5               
 Headache                   1                                      4               
 Increased sweating         -                                      3               
 Insomnia                   -                                      2               
 Skin and appendages        Pruritus                               -                          3               
 Rash                       1                                      1               
 Urogenital                 Urinary retention                      -                          4               
 Urinary tract infection    -                                      2               
          Eight subjects experienced 10 postoperative serious adverse events: one with subdural hematoma and intracerebral bleeding following intracranial surgery related to an underlying cerebrovascular abnormality; one with two occurrences of gastrointestinal bleeding following gastrojejunal bypass; and one each with sepsis, facial edema, infection, menorrhagia requiring hysterectomy following hysteroscopy and dilation and curettage, pyelonephritis, and pulmonary embolus.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Humate-P. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to Humate-P exposure.  



 Adverse reactions reported in patients receiving Humate-P for treatment of VWD or hemophilia A are allergic-anaphylactic reactions (including urticaria, chest tightness, rash, pruritus, edema, and shock), development of inhibitors to FVIII, and hemolysis. Additional adverse reactions reported for VWD are thromboembolic complications, chills and fever, and hypervolemia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  VWD patients receiving Humate-P may be at risk of developing thromboembolic events (  5.1  ). 
 *  Monitor for intravascular hemolysis and decreasing hematocrit values in patients with A, B, and AB blood groups who are receiving large or frequent doses (  5.2  ). 
 *  Monitor VWF:RCo and FVIII levels in VWD patients, especially those undergoing surgery (  5.3  ). 
 *  Products made from human plasma may contain infectious agents (e.g., viruses, and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent (  5.4  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Thromboembolic Events (VWD Patients)



  Thromboembolic events have been reported in VWD patients receiving Antihemophilic Factor/von Willebrand Factor Complex replacement therapy, especially in the setting of known risk factors for thrombosis.  3,4  Early reports indicate a higher incidence may occur in females. Endogenous high levels of FVIII have also been associated with thrombosis, but no causal relationship has been established. Exercise caution and consider antithrombotic measures in all at-risk VWD patients who are receiving coagulation factor replacement therapy.



    5.2 Monitoring for Intravascular Hemolysis



  Humate-P contains blood group isoagglutinins (anti-A and anti-B). When doses are very large or need to be repeated frequently (for example, when inhibitors are present or when pre- and post-surgical care is involved), monitor patients of blood groups A, B, and AB for signs of intravascular hemolysis and decreasing hematocrit values and treat appropriately.



    5.3 Monitoring VWF:RCo and FVIII Levels



  Monitor the VWF:RCo and FVIII levels of VWD patients receiving Humate-P using standard coagulation tests, especially in cases of surgery. It is advisable to monitor trough VWF:RCo and FVIII:C levels at least once a day in order to adjust the dosage of Humate-P as needed to avoid excessive accumulation of coagulation factors [  s ee  Dosage and Administration [2.2  ,  2.3)  ]  .



    5.4 Transmission of Infectious Agents



  Humate-P is made from human plasma. Products made from human plasma may contain infectious agents (e.g., viruses and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease [CJD] agent) that can cause disease [see  Description (11)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . The risk that such products will transmit an infectious agent has been reduced by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, by testing for the presence of certain current virus infections, and by inactivating and/or removing certain viruses during manufacturing [see  Description (11)  ]  .



 Despite these measures, such products can still potentially transmit disease. There is also the possibility that unknown infectious agents may be present in such products. Thus the risk of transmission of infectious agents cannot be eliminated completely. Report all infections thought by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product to CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 Some viruses, such as Parvovirus B19 virus (B19V) or hepatitis A (HAV), are particularly difficult to remove or inactivate. B19V may most seriously affect pregnant women and immune-compromised individuals.



 Although the overwhelming number of B19V and HAV cases are community acquired, reports of these infections have been associated with the use of some plasma-derived products. Therefore, physicians should be alert to the potential symptoms of B19V and HAV infections [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  .



 Symptoms of B19V may include low-grade fever, rash, arthralgias, and transient symmetric, nondestructive arthritis. Diagnosis is often established by measuring B19V-specific IgM and IgG antibodies. Symptoms of HAV include low-grade fever, anorexia, nausea, vomiting, fatigue, and jaundice. A diagnosis may be established by measuring specific IgM antibodies.



 Physicians should strongly consider administration of hepatitis A and hepatitis B vaccines to individuals receiving plasma derivatives. Potential risks and benefits of vaccination should be weighed by the physician and discussed with the patient.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
