<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="humalog0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere:



 *  Hypoglycemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )] . 
 *  Hypokalemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )] . 
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions associated with HUMALOG include hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, injection site reactions, lipodystrophy, pruritus, and rash. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying designs, the adverse reaction rates reported in one clinical trial may not be easily compared with those rates reported in another clinical trial, and may not reflect the rates actually observed in clinical practice.



 The frequencies of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events during HUMALOG clinical trials in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus are listed in the tables below.



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events in Patients with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus (adverse events with frequency &gt;=5%) 
 Events, n (%)              Lispro(n=81)               Regular human insulin(n=86)  Total(n=167)              
  
 Flu syndrome               28 (34.6)                  28 (32.6)                   56 (33.5)                 
 Pharyngitis                27 (33.3)                  29 (33.7)                   56 (33.5)                 
 Rhinitis                   20 (24.7)                  25 (29.1)                   45 (26.9)                 
 Headache                   24 (29.6)                  19 (22.1)                   43 (25.7)                 
 Pain                       16 (19.8)                  14 (16.3)                   30 (18.0)                 
 Cough increased            14 (17.3)                  15 (17.4)                   29 (17.4)                 
 Infection                  11 (13.6)                  18 (20.9)                   29 (17.4)                 
 Nausea                     5 (6.2)                    13 (15.1)                   18 (10.8)                 
 Accidental injury          7 (8.6)                    10 (11.6)                   17 (10.2)                 
 Surgical procedure         5 (6.2)                    12 (14.0)                   17 (10.2)                 
 Fever                      5 (6.2)                    10 (11.6)                   15 (9.0)                  
 Abdominal pain             6 (7.4)                    7 (8.1)                     13 (7.8)                  
 Asthenia                   6 (7.4)                    7 (8.1)                     13 (7.8)                  
 Bronchitis                 6 (7.4)                    6 (7.0)                     12 (7.2)                  
 Diarrhea                   7 (8.6)                    5 (5.8)                     12 (7.2)                  
 Dysmenorrhea               5 (6.2)                    6 (7.0)                     11 (6.6)                  
 Myalgia                    6 (7.4)                    5 (5.8)                     11 (6.6)                  
 Urinary tract infection    5 (6.2)                    4 (4.7)                     9 (5.4)                   
         Table 2: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (adverse events with frequency &gt;=5%) 
 Events, n (%)              Lispro(n=714)              Regular human insulin(n=709)  Total(n=1423)             
  
 Headache                   63 (11.6)                  66 (9.3)                    149 (10.5)                
 Pain                       77 (10.8)                  71 (10.0)                   148 (10.4)                
 Infection                  72 (10.1)                  54 (7.6)                    126 (8.9)                 
 Pharyngitis                47 (6.6)                   58 (8.2)                    105 (7.4)                 
 Rhinitis                   58 (8.1)                   47 (6.6)                    105 (7.4)                 
 Flu syndrome               44 (6.2)                   58 (8.2)                    102 (7.2)                 
 Surgical procedure         53 (7.4)                   48 (6.8)                    101 (7.1)                 
              Insulin initiation and intensification of glucose control  
 

 Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with a transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. However, long-term glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.



     Lipodystrophy  



 Long-term use of insulin, including HUMALOG, can cause lipodystrophy at the site of repeated insulin injections or infusion. Lipodystrophy includes lipohypertrophy (thickening of adipose tissue) and lipoatrophy (thinning of adipose tissue), and may affect insulin absorption. Rotate insulin injection or infusion sites within the same region to reduce the risk of lipodystrophy  [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ,  2.3  )]  .



     Weight gain  



 Weight gain can occur with insulin therapy, including HUMALOG, and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin and the decrease in glucosuria.



     Peripheral Edema  



 Insulin, including HUMALOG, may cause sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy.



     Adverse Reactions with Continuous Subcutaneous Insulin Infusion (CSII)  



 In a 12-week, randomized, crossover study in adult patients with type 1 diabetes (n=39), the rates of catheter occlusions and infusion site reactions were similar for HUMALOG and regular human insulin treated patients (  see    Table 3  ).



 Table 3: Catheter Occlusions and Infusion Site Reactions 
                                    HUMALOG(n=38)                      Regular human insulin(n=39)         
 Catheter occlusions/month          0.09                               0.10                                
 Infusion site reactions            2.6% (1/38)                        2.6% (1/39)                         
         In a randomized, 16-week, open-label, parallel design study of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes, adverse event reports related to infusion-site reactions were similar for insulin lispro and insulin aspart (21% of 100 patients versus 17% of 198 patients, respectively). In both groups, the most frequently reported infusion site adverse events were infusion site erythema and infusion site reaction.
 

     Allergic Reactions  



     Local Allergy  - As with any insulin therapy, patients taking HUMALOG may experience redness, swelling, or itching at the site of the injection. These minor reactions usually resolve in a few days to a few weeks, but in some occasions, may require discontinuation of HUMALOG. In some instances, these reactions may be related to factors other than insulin, such as irritants in a skin cleansing agent or poor injection technique.



     Systemic Allergy  - Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, may occur with any insulin, including HUMALOG. Generalized allergy to insulin may cause whole body rash (including pruritus), dyspnea, wheezing, hypotension, tachycardia, or diaphoresis.



 In controlled clinical trials, pruritus (with or without rash) was seen in 17 patients receiving regular human insulin (n=2969) and 30 patients receiving HUMALOG (n=2944).



 Localized reactions and generalized myalgias have been reported with injected metacresol, which is an excipient in HUMALOG  [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



     Antibody Production  



 In large clinical trials with patients with type 1 (n=509) and type 2 (n=262) diabetes mellitus, anti-insulin antibody (insulin lispro-specific antibodies, insulin-specific antibodies, cross-reactive antibodies) formation was evaluated in patients receiving both regular human insulin and HUMALOG (including patients previously treated with human insulin and naive patients). As expected, the largest increase in the antibody levels occurred in patients new to insulin therapy. The antibody levels peaked by 12 months and declined over the remaining years of the study These antibodies do not appear to cause deterioration in glycemic control or necessitate an increase in insulin dose. There was no statistically significant relationship between the change in the total daily insulin dose and the change in percent antibody binding for any of the antibody types.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of HUMALOG. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Medication errors in which other insulins have been accidentally substituted for HUMALOG have been identified during postapproval use  [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Dose adjustment and monitoring: Closely monitor blood glucose in all patients treated with insulin. Change insulin regimens cautiously and only under medical supervision. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypoglycemia: Most common adverse reaction of insulin therapy and may be life-threatening. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Allergic reactions: Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur with any insulin, including HUMALOG. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hypokalemia: All insulins, including HUMALOG can cause hypokalemia, which if untreated, may result in respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Renal or hepatic impairment: Like all insulins, may require a reduction in the HUMALOG dose. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Mixing: HUMALOG for subcutaneous injection should not be mixed with insulins other than NPH insulin. Do not mix HUMALOG with any insulin for use in a continuous infusion pump. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Pump use: Select a new infusion site at least every 3 days and replace the HUMALOG in the pump reservoir at least every 7 days. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Dose Adjustment and Monitoring



  Glucose monitoring is essential for patients receiving insulin therapy. Changes to an insulin regimen should be made cautiously and only under medical supervision. Changes in insulin strength, manufacturer, type, or method of administration may result in the need for a change in insulin dose. Concomitant oral antidiabetic treatment may need to be adjusted.



 As with all insulin preparations, the time course of action for HUMALOG may vary in different individuals or at different times in the same individual and is dependent on many conditions, including the site of injection, local blood supply, or local temperature. Patients who change their level of physical activity or meal plan may require adjustment of insulin dosages.



    5.2 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse effect associated with insulins, including HUMALOG. The risk of hypoglycemia increases with tighter glycemic control. Patients must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may be different for each person and may change from time to time. Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures and may be life-threatening or cause death.



 The timing of hypoglycemia usually reflects the time-action profile of the administered insulin formulations. Other factors such as changes in food intake (e.g., amount of food or timing of meals), injection site, exercise, and concomitant medications may also alter the risk of hypoglycemia [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  .



 As with all insulins, use caution in patients with hypoglycemia unawareness and in patients who may be predisposed to hypoglycemia (e.g., the pediatric population and patients who fast or have erratic food intake). The patient's ability to concentrate and react may be impaired as a result of hypoglycemia. This may present a risk in situations where these abilities are especially important, such as driving or operating other machinery.



 Rapid changes in serum glucose levels may induce symptoms similar to hypoglycemia in persons with diabetes, regardless of the glucose value. Early warning symptoms of hypoglycemia may be different or less pronounced under certain conditions, such as longstanding diabetes, diabetic nerve disease, use of medications such as beta-blockers [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  , or intensified diabetes control. These situations may result in severe hypoglycemia (and, possibly, loss of consciousness) prior to the patient's awareness of hypoglycemia.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions



  Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur with insulin products, including HUMALOG [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  .



    5.4 Hypokalemia



  All insulin products, including HUMALOG, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia. Untreated hypokalemia may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Use caution in patients who may be at risk for hypokalemia (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications, patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations).



    5.5 Renal or Hepatic Impairment



  Frequent glucose monitoring and insulin dose reduction may be required in patients with renal or hepatic impairment [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    5.6 Mixing of Insulins



  HUMALOG for subcutaneous injection should not be mixed with insulin preparations other than NPH insulin. If HUMALOG is mixed with NPH insulin, HUMALOG should be drawn into the syringe first. Injection should occur immediately after mixing.



 Do not mix HUMALOG with other insulins for use in an external subcutaneous infusion pump.



    5.7 Subcutaneous Insulin Infusion Pumps



     When used in an external insulin pump for subcutaneous infusion, HUMALOG should not be diluted or mixed with any other insulin. Change the HUMALOG in the reservoir at least every 7 days, change the infusion sets and the infusion set insertion site at least every 3 days. HUMALOG should not be exposed to temperatures greater than 98.6 degrees F (37 degrees C).



 Malfunction of the insulin pump or infusion set or insulin degradation can rapidly lead to hyperglycemia and ketosis. Prompt identification and correction of the cause of hyperglycemia or ketosis is necessary. Interim subcutaneous injections with HUMALOG may be required. Patients using continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion pump therapy must be trained to administer insulin by injection and have alternate insulin therapy available in case of pump failure [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ), How Supplied/Storage and Handling (  16  ), and Patient Counseling Information (  17.2  )]  .



    5.8 Drug Interactions



  Some medications may alter insulin requirements and the risk for hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
