<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="humulin1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Hypoglycemia

  Hypoglycemia is one of the most frequent adverse events experienced by insulin users.



 Symptoms of mild to moderate hypoglycemia may occur suddenly and can include:




 sweating                                           
                                                                                                         drowsiness                                         
                                                                                                          
 dizziness                                          
                                                                                                         sleep disturbances                                 
                                                                                                          
 palpitation                                        
                                                                                                         anxiety                                            
                                                                                                          
 tremor                                             
                                                                                                         blurred vision                                     
                                                                                                          
 hunger                                             
                                                                                                         slurred speech                                     
                                                                                                          
 restlessness                                       
                                                                                                         depressed mood                                     
                                                                                                          
 tingling in the hands, feet, lips, or tongue       
                                                                                                         irritability                                       
                                                                                                          
 lightheadedness                                    
                                                                                                         abnormal behavior                                  
                                                                                                          
 inability to concentrate                           
                                                                                                         unsteady movement                                  
                                                                                                          
 headache                                           
                                                                                                         personality changes                                
                                                                                                          
        Signs of severe hypoglycemia can include:
 


 disorientation                                     
                                                                                                         seizures                                           
                                                                                                          
 unconsciousness                                    
                                                                                                         coma                                               
                                                                                                          
 death                                              
                                                                                                                                                              
        Early warning symptoms of hypoglycemia may be different or less pronounced under certain conditions, such as long duration of diabetes, autonomic diabetic neuropathy, use of medications such as beta-adrenergic blockers, changing insulin preparations, or intensified control (3 or more insulin injections per day) of diabetes.
 

 Without recognition of early warning symptoms, the patient may not be able to take steps to avoid more serious hypoglycemia. Patients who experience hypoglycemia without early warning symptoms should monitor their blood glucose more frequently, especially prior to activities such as driving. Mild to moderate hypoglycemia may be treated by eating foods or taking drinks that contain sugar. Patients should always carry a quick source of sugar, such as hard candy, non-diet carbohydrate-containing drinks or glucose tablets.



   Hypokalemia

    See    Precautions  



   Lipodystrophy

  Administration of insulin subcutaneously can result in lipoatrophy (depression in the skin) or lipohypertrophy (enlargement or thickening of tissue).



   Allergy

    Local Allergy  - Patients occasionally experience erythema, local edema, and pruritus at the site of injection. This condition usually is self-limiting. In some instances, this condition may be related to factors other than insulin, such as irritants in the skin cleansing agent or poor injection technique.



     Systemic Allergy  - Less common, but potentially more serious, is generalized allergy to insulin, which may cause rash over the whole body, shortness of breath, wheezing, reduction in blood pressure, fast pulse, or sweating. Severe cases of generalized allergy (anaphylaxis) may be life threatening.



   Weight Gain

  Weight gain can occur with some insulin therapies and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin and the decrease in glycosuria.



   Peripheral Edema

  Insulin may cause sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy.



   Drug Interactions

  A number of substances affect glucose metabolism and may require insulin dose adjustment and particularly close monitoring.



 Drugs that may increase the blood-glucose-lowering effect of Humulin R U-100 and susceptibility to hypoglycemia:



 *  Oral antihyperglycemic agents, salicylates, sulfa antibiotics, certain antidepressants (monoamine oxidase inhibitors, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [SSRIs]), pramlintide, disopyramide, fibrates, fluoxetine, propoxyphene, pentoxifylline, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin II receptor blocking agents, beta-adrenergic blockers, inhibitors of pancreatic function (e.g., octreotide), and alcohol. 
    Drugs that may reduce the blood-glucose-lowering effect:
 

 *  Corticosteroids, isoniazid, certain lipid-lowering drugs (e.g., niacin), estrogens, oral contraceptives, phenothiazines, danazol, diuretics, sympathomimetic agents, somatropin, atypical antipsychotics, glucagon, protease inhibitors and thyroid replacement therapy. 
    Drugs that may increase or decrease blood-glucose-lowering effect:
 

 *  Beta-adrenergic blockers, clonidine, lithium salts, and alcohol. 
 *  Pentamidine may cause hypoglycemia, which may sometimes be followed by hyperglycemia. 
    Drugs that may mask the signs of hypoglycemia:
 

 *  Beta-adrenergic blockers, clonidine, guanethidine, and reserpine. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
