<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hycamtin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Bone Marrow Suppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Neutropenic Enterocolitis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Interstitial Lung Disease [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *    Extravasation and Tissue Injury [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
      EXCERPT:   Ovarian cancer:
 

 *    The most common hematologic adverse reactions were: neutropenia (Grade 4: 80%), anemia (Grade 3/4: 41%), thrombocytopenia (Grade 4: 27%), and febrile neutropenia (23%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    The most common (&gt;5%) non-hematologic adverse reactions (all grades) were: nausea, vomiting, fatigue, diarrhea, and dyspnea. (  6.1  ) 
    Small cell lung cancer:
 

 *    The most common hematologic adverse reactions were: neutropenia (Grade 4: 70%), anemia (Grade 3/4: 42%), thrombocytopenia (Grade 4: 29%), and febrile neutropenia (28%). 
 *    The most common (&gt;5%) non-hematologic adverse reactions (all grades) were: asthenia, dyspnea, nausea, pneumonia, abdominal pain, and fatigue. 
    Cervical cancer (HYCAMTIN plus cisplatin):
 

 *    The most common hematologic adverse reactions were: neutropenia (Grade 3/4: 74%), anemia (Grade 3/4: 40%), and thrombocytopenia (Grade 3/4: 33%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    The most common (&gt;25% and greater than or equal to 2% more than cisplatin alone) non-hematologic adverse reactions (all grades) were: pain, vomiting, and infection/febrile neutropenia. (  6.1  ) 
 *      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
    
   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Ovarian Cancer  



 Table 1 shows the Grade 3/4 hematologic and major non-hematologic adverse reactions in the topotecan/paclitaxel comparator trial in ovarian cancer.



   Table 1. Adverse Reactions Experienced by &gt;=5% of Ovarian Cancer Patients Randomized to Receive HYCAMTIN or Paclitaxel  




  Adverse Reaction                                    HYCAMTIN  (n = 112)        Paclitaxel  (n = 114)      
  Hematologic Grade 3/4                               %                          %                          
  Grade 4 neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm3)                80                         21                         
  Grade 3/4 anemia (Hgb &lt;8 g/dL)                      41                         6                          
  Grade 4 thrombocytopenia (&lt;25,000 plts/mm3)         27                         3                          
  Febrile neutropenia                                 23                         4                          
  Non-hematologic Grade 3/4                           %                          %                          
  Infections and infestations                                                                               
  Sepsisa                                             5                          2                          
  Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                          
  Dyspnea                                             6                          5                          
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                
  Abdominal pain                                      5                          4                          
  Constipation                                        5                          0                          
  Diarrhea                                            6                          1                          
  Intestinal obstruction                              5                          4                          
  Nausea                                              10                         2                          
  Vomiting                                            10                         3                          
  General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                          
  Fatigue                                             7                          6                          
  Asthenia                                            5                          3                          
  Painb                                               5                          7                          
           a  Death related to sepsis occurred in 2% of patients receiving HYCAMTIN and 0% of patients receiving paclitaxel.
 

   b  Pain includes body pain, skeletal pain, and back pain.



   Small Cell Lung Cancer  



 Table 2 shows the Grade 3/4 hematologic and major non-hematologic adverse reactions in the topotecan/CAV (cyclophosphamide-doxorubicin-vincristine) comparator trial in small cell lung cancer.



   Table 2. Adverse Reactions Experienced by &gt;=5% of Small Cell Lung Cancer Patients Randomized to Receive HYCAMTIN or CAV  




  Adverse Reaction                             HYCAMTIN  (n = 107)    CAV  (n = 104)         
  Hematologic Grade 3/4                        %                      %                      
  Grade 4 neutropenia  (&lt;500 cells/mm3)        70                     72                     
  Grade 3/4 anemia  (Hgb &lt;8 g/dL)              42                     20                     
  Grade 4 thrombocytopenia  (&lt;25,000 plts/mm3)    29                     5                      
  Febrile neutropenia                          28                     26                     
  Non-hematologic Grade 3/4                    %                      %                      
  Infections and infestations                                                                
  Sepsis a                                     5                      5                      
  Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                  
  Dyspnea                                      9                      14                     
  Pneumonia                                    8                      6                      
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                 
  Abdominal pain                               6                      4                      
  Nausea                                       8                      6                      
  General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                  
  Fatigue                                      6                      10                     
  Asthenia                                     9                      7                      
  Pain b                                       5                      7                      
           a  Death related to sepsis occurred in 3% of patients receiving HYCAMTIN and 1% of patients receiving CAV.
 

   b  Pain includes body pain, skeletal pain, and back pain.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders in Ovarian and Small Cell Lung Cancer Patients Receiving HYCAMTIN:  Based on the combined experience of 453 patients with metastatic ovarian carcinoma, and 426 patients with small cell lung cancer treated with HYCAMTIN, Grade 1 transient elevations in hepatic enzymes occurred in 8% of patients. Grade 3/4 elevations occurred in 4%. Grade 3/4 elevated bilirubin occurred in less than 2% of patients.



   Cervical Cancer  



 In the comparative trial with HYCAMTIN plus cisplatin versus cisplatin in patients with cervical cancer, the most common dose-limiting adverse reaction was myelosuppression. Table 3 shows the hematologic and non-hematologic adverse reactions in patients with cervical cancer.



   Table 3. Adverse Reactions Experienced by &gt;=5% of Patients with Cervical Cancer Randomized to Receive HYCAMTIN plus Cisplatin or Cisplatin Monotherapy (Between-Arm Difference &gt;=2%)  a    




  Adverse Reaction                             HYCAMTIN  plus Cisplatin  (n = 140)  %    Cisplatin  (n = 144)  %    
  Hematologic                                                                                
  Neutropenia                                                                                
  Grade 3 (&lt;1,000-500 cells/mm3)               26                     1                      
  Grade 4 (&lt;500 cells/mm3)                     48                     1                      
  Anemia                                                                                     
  Grade 3 (Hgb &lt;8-6.5 g/dL)                    34                     19                     
  Grade 4 (Hgb &lt;6.5 g/dL)                      6                      3                      
  Thrombocytopenia                                                                           
  Grade 3 (&lt;50,000-10,000 cells/mm3)           26                     3                      
  Grade 4 (&lt;10,000 cells/mm3)                  7                      0                      
  Non-hematologicb, c                                                                        
  General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                  
  Constitutionald                              69                     62                     
  Paine                                        59                     50                     
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                 
  Vomiting                                     40                     37                     
  Stomatitis-pharyngitis                       6                      0                      
  Other                                        63                     56                     
  Dermatologyf                                 48                     20                     
  Infection-febrile neutropeniaf               28                     18                     
  Cardiovascularf                              25                     15                     
           a  Includes patients who were eligible and treated.
 

   b  Data were collected using NCI Common Toxicity Criteria, v. 2.0.



   c  Grades 1 through 4 only. There were 3 patients who experienced deaths with investigator-designated attribution. The first patient experienced a Grade 5 hemorrhage in which the drug-related thrombocytopenia aggravated the event. A second patient experienced bowel obstruction, cardiac arrest, pleural effusion, and respiratory failure which were not treatment-related but probably aggravated by treatment. A third patient experienced a pulmonary embolism and adult respiratory distress syndrome; the latter was indirectly treatment-related.



   d  Constitutional includes fatigue (lethargy, malaise, asthenia), fever (in the absence of neutropenia), rigors, chills, sweating, and weight gain or loss.



   e  Pain includes abdominal pain or cramping, arthralgia, bone pain, chest pain (non-cardiac and non-pleuritic), dysmenorrhea, dyspareunia, earache, headache, hepatic pain, myalgia, neuropathic pain, pain due to radiation, pelvic pain, pleuritic pain, rectal or perirectal pain, and tumor pain.



   f  High-level terms were included if the between-arm difference was &gt;=10%.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of HYCAMTIN. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These reactions have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to HYCAMTIN.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Severe bleeding (in association with thrombocytopenia)  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .



   Immune System Disorders  



 Allergic manifestations, anaphylactoid reactions.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  



 Abdominal pain potentially associated with neutropenic enterocolitis  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



   Pulmonary Disorders  



 Interstitial lung disease  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  .



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Angioedema, severe dermatitis, severe pruritus.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  



 Extravasation  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: BONE MARROW SUPPRESSION

  WARNING: BONE MARROW SUPPRESSION

    HYCAMTIN  (r)   can cause severe myelosuppression. Administer only to patients with baseline neutrophil counts of greater than or equal to 1,500 cells/mm  3   and platelet counts greater than or equal to 100,000 cells/mm  3  . Monitor blood cell counts   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: BONE MARROW SUPPRESSION



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   HYCAMTIN can cause severe myelosuppression. Administer only to patients with baseline neutrophil counts greater than or equal to 1,500 cells/mm  3   and platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm  3  . Monitor blood cell counts. (  5.1  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Bone marrow suppression: Administer HYCAMTIN only to patients with adequate bone marrow reserves. Monitor peripheral blood counts and adjust the dose as needed. (  2.4  ,  5.1  ) 
 *    Neutropenic enterocolitis: Fatal typhlitis can occur. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Interstitial lung disease (ILD): Fatal cases have occurred. Permanently discontinue for confirmed ILD. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Embryofetal toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise women of potential risk to the fetus. (  5.4  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ) 
 *    Extravasation and tissue injury: Severe cases have been reported. If extravasation occurs, immediately stop administration and institute recommended management procedures. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Bone Marrow Suppression



  Bone marrow suppression (primarily neutropenia) is the dose-limiting toxicity of HYCAMTIN. Neutropenia is not cumulative over time. Severe myelotoxicity has been reported when HYCAMTIN is used in combination with cisplatin [see Drug Interactions (7)]  .



 *    The following data on myelosuppression are based on an integrated safety database from 8 trials (N = 879) using HYCAMTIN injection at 1.5 mg/m  2  by intravenous infusion over 30 minutes daily for 5 consecutive days, starting on Day 1 of a 21-day course in patients with ovarian cancer and small cell lung cancer and from one trial in patients with cervical cancer (N = 147) using HYCAMTIN 0.75 mg/m  2  by intravenous infusion over 30 minutes daily on Days 1, 2, and 3 repeated every 21 days in combination with cisplatin 50 mg/m  2  on Day 1. 
     Neutropenia  
 

 *    Monotherapy: Grade 4 neutropenia (less than 500 cells/mm3) occurred in 78% of patients, with a median duration of 7 days and was most common during Course 1 of treatment (58% of patients). Grade 4 neutropenia associated with infection occurred in 13% of patients and febrile neutropenia occurred in 5% of patients. Sepsis occurred in 4% of patients and was fatal in 1% of patients. Pancytopenia has been reported. 
 *    Combination with cisplatin: Grade 4 neutropenia occurred in 48% of patients. 
     Thrombocytopenia  
 

 *    Monotherapy: Grade 4 thrombocytopenia (less than 25,000/mm  3  ) occurred in 27% of patients, with a median duration of 5 days. 
 *    Combination with cisplatin: Grade 4 thrombocytopenia occurred in 7% of patients. 
     Anemia  
 

 *    Monotherapy: Grade 3 or 4 anemia (less than 8 g/dL) occurred in 37% of patients. 
 *    Combination with cisplatin: Grade 3 or Grade 4 anemia occurred in 40% of patients. 
    Administer HYCAMTIN only to patients with a baseline neutrophil count of greater than or equal to 1,500 cells/mm  3  and a platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm  3  . Monitor peripheral blood counts frequently during treatment with HYCAMTIN. Refer to Section 2.4 for dose modification guidelines for hematological toxicities in subsequent courses. Do not treat patients with subsequent courses of HYCAMTIN until neutrophils recover to greater than 1,000 cells/mm  3  , platelets recover to greater than 100,000 cells/mm  3  , and hemoglobin levels recover to 9.0 g/dL (with transfusion if necessary).
 

    5.2 Neutropenic Enterocolitis



  Topotecan can cause fatal typhlitis (neutropenic enterocolitis). Consider the possibility of typhlitis in patients presenting with fever, neutropenia, and abdominal pain.



    5.3 Interstitial Lung Disease



  Interstitial lung disease (ILD), including fatalities, has occurred with HYCAMTIN. Underlying risk factors include history of ILD, pulmonary fibrosis, lung cancer, thoracic radiation, and use of pneumotoxic drugs and/or colony stimulating factors. Monitor patients for pulmonary symptoms indicative of ILD (e.g., cough, fever, dyspnea, and/or hypoxia), and discontinue HYCAMTIN if a new diagnosis of ILD is confirmed.



    5.4 Embryofetal Toxicity



  Based on animal data, HYCAMTIN can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Topotecan caused embryolethality, fetotoxicity, and teratogenicity in rats and rabbits when administered during organogenesis. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment and for at least 1 month after the last dose of HYCAMTIN. Advise women of the potential risk to a fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1, 8.3)].  



    5.5 Extravasation and Tissue Injury



  Extravasation with HYCAMTIN has been observed; severe cases have been reported. If signs or symptoms of extravasation occur, immediately stop administration of HYCAMTIN and institute recommended management procedures [see Adverse Reactions (6)].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
