<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hydroxyethyl" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Serious adverse reactions reported in clinical trials were increased mortality and need for renal replacement therapy in critically ill patients including sepsis.  
    Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;1%) are pruritus, elevated serum amylase, hemodilution (resulting in dilution of blood components, e.g., coagulation factors and other plasma proteins, and in a decrease in hematocrit).
 

 Anaphylactoid/hypersensitivity reactions can occur. (  6  )



     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact B. Braun Medical Inc. at 1-800-227-2862 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Overall Adverse Reaction Profile

  Serious adverse reactions reported in clinical trials include increased mortality and increased use of RRT in critically ill subjects including subjects with sepsis. 



 The most common adverse reactions after administration of 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection occurring in more than 1% of patients are: pruritus (itching;  &gt;  1% to &lt;10%), elevation of serum amylase (  &gt;  1% to &lt;10%; interference with the diagnosis of pancreatitis), and dilutional effects that may result in decreased levels of coagulation factors and other plasma proteins and in a decrease of hematocrit (  &gt;  1% to &lt;10%).



 Anaphylactoid reactions occur rarely in &lt;0.1% after administration of hydroxyethyl starch solutions. Disturbances of blood coagulation beyond dilution effects can occur rarely in &lt;0.1% depending on the dosage with the administration of hydroxyethyl starch solutions  1  .



   6.2 Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug or another patient population and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During clinical development, a total of 899 subjects received the hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 drug substance at different concentrations (2%, 4%, 6%, or 10%) and at cumulative doses of several mL up to 66 L  2  . Of these 899 subjects, 602 were exposed to 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4. The mean duration of treatment with hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 was 3.7 +/- 3.1 days, mean cumulative doses were 3185 +/- 3498 mL, and the longest follow-up period was 90 days.



 In a randomized controlled trial (RCT) of subjects (N=100) undergoing elective orthopedic surgery, 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection (N=49) or hetastarch (6% hydroxyethyl starch in 0.9% sodium chloride injection; N=51) were administered for intraoperative volume replacement.  3    Mean infusion volumes were 1613 +/- 778 mL for 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection and 1584 +/- 958 mL for hetastarch.



 Adverse reactions observed in at least 1% of subjects: In the orthopedic surgery trial conducted in the US, no significant differences in serious adverse reactions were noted overall between the two treatment arms. A possible relationship to 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection was reported in five cases among three subjects (aPTT elevated, PT prolonged, wound hemorrhage, anemia, pruritus); a possible relationship to hetastarch was reported in five subjects (three cases of coagulopathy; two cases of pruritus). The three coagulopathy cases in the hetastarch group were serious and occurred in subjects receiving more than the labeled ceiling dose (20 mL/kg), which is known to increase the risk of bleeding, whereas no serious coagulopathy occurred in the 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection group. Since calculated red blood cell loss for the two treatment arms was not statistically different (95% confidence interval included unity), the difference observed for Factor VIII (see Table 1, below) must be interpreted with caution. An exploratory analysis of total erythrocyte volume transfused (8.0 mL/kg vs. 13.8 mL/kg, 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection vs. hetastarch, respectively) also must be viewed with caution.



   Table 1: Safety Variables for the Orthopedic Surgery Trial conducted in the US  




                       Mean         Ratio6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection/Hetastarch    
   Variable         6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection N=49       HetastarchN=51       Estimate         95% CI         
  Calculated red blood cell loss [L]*   1.17             1.31             0.910            [0.720; 1.141]   
  Factor VIII [%]*   100.5            81.4             1.244            [1.000; 1.563]   
  von Willebrand factor [%]    97.7             88.7             1.128            [0.991; 1.285]   
  Fresh frozen plasma [mL]     72               144              0.723            [0.000; 2.437]   
           A safety profile of 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection at least as favorable as for pentastarch was also demonstrated in studies where 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection was administered at doses higher (up to 50 mL/kg or 3 g/kg) than for pentastarch (up to 33 mL/kg or 2 g/kg) in clinical settings where large or repetitive doses were administered.
 

   Trials in critically ill adult subjects

  Three RCTs followed critically ill adult subjects treated with different HES products for 90 days.



 One trial using 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection in severe sepsis subjects (N=196) reported no difference in mortality (relative risk, 1.20; 95% CI, 0.83 to 1.74; p=0.33) and a trend for increased use of RRT (relative risk, 1.83; 95% CI, 0.93 to 3.59; p=0.06) in HES subjects  4  .



 Another trial using 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection in a heterogeneous population of critically ill subjects admitted to the ICU (N=7000) reported no difference in mortality (relative risk, 1.06; 95% CI, 0.96 to 1.18; p=0.26) but increased use of RRT (relative risk, 1.21; 95% CI, 1.00 to 1.45; p=0.04) in HES subjects.  5    A third trial in severe sepsis subjects (N=804) using an HES product not licensed in the U.S. (HES 130/0.42) reported increased mortality (relative risk, 1.17; 95% CI, 1.01 to 1.36; p=0.03) and increased use of RRT (relative risk, 1.35; 95% CI, 1.01 to 1.80; p=0.04) in HES subjects.  6  



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  Because adverse reactions are reported voluntarily post-approval from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency or establish a causal relationship to product exposure. 



 Among the very rarely occurring serious adverse drug reactions in patients treated with 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection, anaphylactic/anaphylactoid/hypersensitivity reactions or hypotension/shock/circulatory collapse were most frequently reported.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during the post-approval use of different HES products in critically ill adult patients, including patients with sepsis:



 *  Mortality 
 *  Renal: use of RRT 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:     MORTALITY     RENAL REPLACEMENT THERAPY

  WARNING:     MORTALITY     RENAL REPLACEMENT THERAPY

    *  In critically ill adult patients, including patients with sepsis, use of hydroxyethyl starch (HES) products, including 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection, increases risk ofMortalityRenal replacement therapy 
 *  Do not use HES products, including 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection, in critically ill adult patients, including patients with sepsis. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING:     MORTALITY RENAL REPLACEMENT THERAP  Y    
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  In critically ill adult patients, including patients with sepsis, use of hydroxyethyl starch (HES) products, including 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection, increases risk ofMortalityRenal replacement therapy 
 *  Do not use HES products, including 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection, in critically ill adult patients, including patients with sepsis. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Anaphylactoid and hypersensitivity reactions (  5.1  ,  6  ) 
 
    

 item{ Avoid use in patients with pre-existing renal dysfunction. (  5.2  ) 
 

 item{ Discontinue use of 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection at the first sign of renal injury. (  5.2  )
 

 item{ Continue to monitor renal function in hospitalized patients for at least 90 days as use of renal replacement therapy has been reported up to 90 days after administration of HES products. (  5.2  )
 

 item{ Monitor the coagulation status of patients undergoing open heart surgery in association with cardiopulmonary bypass as excess bleeding has been reported with HES solutions in this population. Discontinue use of 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection at the first sign of coagulopathy. (  5.3  )
 

 item{ Avoid fluid overload; adjust dosage in patients with cardiac or renal dysfunction (  5.4  )
 

 item{ In severe dehydration, a crystalloid solution should be given first (  5.4  )
 

 item{ Monitor liver function in patients receiving HES products, including 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection. (  5.5  )
 

 item{ Monitor kidney function, fluid balance and serum electrolytes (  5.5  )
 

 item{ Elevated serum amylase values may occur and interfere with the diagnosis of pancreatitis (  5.5  )
 

 item{High dosages may cause dilution of blood components (  5.5  ) 
 

   5.1 Anaphylactoid Reactions



  Anaphylactoid reactions (mild influenza-like symptoms, bradycardia, tachycardia, bronchospasm, non-cardiac pulmonary edema) have been reported with solutions containing hydroxyethyl starch. If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, administration of the drug should be discontinued immediately and the appropriate treatment and supportive measures should be undertaken until symptoms have resolved.  [see     Adverse Reactions (6)      ]



    5.2 Renal Dysfunction



  Avoid use in patients with pre-existing renal dysfunction.



 Discontinue use of 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection at the first sign of renal injury.



 Continue to monitor renal function in hospitalized patients for at least 90 days as use of RRT has been reported up to 90 days after administration of HES products.



    5.3 Coagulopathy



  Monitor the coagulation status of patients undergoing open heart surgery in association with cardiopulmonary bypass as excess bleeding has been reported with HES solutions in this population. Discontinue use of 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection at the first sign of coagulopathy.



    5.4 Fluid Equilibrium



  Avoid fluid overload; adjust dosage in patients with cardiac or renal dysfunction. Fluid status and rate of infusion should be assessed regularly during treatment, especially in patients with cardiac insufficiency or severe kidney dysfunction.



 In cases of severe dehydration, a crystalloid solution should be given first. Generally, sufficient fluid should be administered in order to avoid dehydration.



    5.5 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  Clinical evaluation and periodic laboratory determinations are necessary to monitor fluid balance, serum electrolyte concentrations, kidney function, acid-base balance, and coagulation parameters during prolonged parenteral therapy or whenever the patient's condition warrants such evaluation. Monitor liver function in patients receiving HES products, including 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 in 0.9% sodium chloride injection.



    5.6 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  Elevated serum amylase levels may be observed temporarily following administration of the product and can interfere with the diagnosis of pancreatitis. 



 At high dosages the dilutional effects may result in decreased levels of coagulation factors and other plasma proteins and a decrease in hematocrit.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
