<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hydrochlorothiazide" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The adverse reactions associated with hydrochlorothiazide have been shown to be dose related. In controlled clinical trials, the adverse events reported with doses of 12.5 mg hydrochlorothiazide once daily were comparable to placebo. The following adverse reactions have been reported for doses of hydrochlorothiazide 25 mg and greater and, within each category, are listed in the order of decreasing severity.



   Body as a whole:  Weakness.



   Cardiovascular:  Hypotension including orthostatic hypotension (may be aggravated by alcohol, barbiturates, narcotics or antihypertensive drugs).



   Digestive:  Pancreatitis, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice), diarrhea, vomiting, sialadenitis, cramping, constipation, gastric irritation, nausea, anorexia.



   Hematologic:  Aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia.



   Hypersensitivity:  Anaphylactic reactions, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis and cutaneous vasculitis), respiratory distress including pneumonitis and pulmonary edema, photosensitivity, fever, urticaria, rash, purpura.



   Metabolic:  Electrolyte imbalance (see      PRECAUTIONS      ), hyperglycemia, glycosuria, hyperuricemia.



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle spasm.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Vertigo, paresthesia, dizziness, headache, restlessness.



   Renal:  Renal failure, renal dysfunction, interstitial nephritis (see      WARNINGS      ).



   Skin:  Erythema multiforme including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis including toxic epidermal necrolysis, alopecia.



   Special Senses:  Transient blurred vision, xanthopsia.



   Urogenital:  Impotence.



 Whenever adverse reactions are moderate or severe, thiazide dosage should be reduced or therapy withdrawn.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
