<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hyqvia" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Common adverse reactions observed in clinical trials in &gt;5% of subjects were: local reactions, headache, antibody formation against recombinant human hyaluronidase (rHuPH20), fatigue, nausea, pyrexia, and vomiting.



   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical studies of a product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another product and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) administered intravenously: Prior to initiation of treatment with HYQVIA, 87 patients received 365 infusions of immune globulin infusion 10% (Human) encompassing 22.2 patient-years. Among the 87 patients treated, 56 (64.4%) experienced 1 or more adverse reactions. Among the 365 intravenous infusions, 158 adverse reactions occurred for a rate per infusion of 0.43.



 A total of 1359 infusions of HYQVIA were administered during the trial; 230 of these infusions occurred during the ramp-up period and the other 1129 occurred during the observation period. During the observation period, 81 patients received 1129 infusions of HYQVIA, of those, 67 (82.7%) experienced one or more adverse reactions. Among the 1129 HYQVIA infusions, 456 adverse reactions occurred for a rate per infusion of 0.40. Seven of these adverse reactions were severe defined as marked impairment of function or can lead to temporary inability to resume normal life pattern; requires prolonged intervention or results in sequelae.



 Adverse reactions occurring in greater than 5% of subjects associated with infusions of HYQVIA vs. Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) given intravenously are shown in Table 4. The majority of these adverse reactions was mild to moderate in severity and did not necessitate discontinuing the infusions. Mild is defined as transient discomfort that resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention; moderate is defined as limited impairment of function and resolves spontaneously or with minimal intervention with no sequelae. No serious adverse reactions occurred during the HYQVIA clinical trials.



 Table 4 Adverse Reactionsa in greater than 5% of Subjects Associated with Infusions of HYQVIA vs. Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) (IGIV) Given Intravenously 
                    HYQVIA            IGIV Given Intravenously     
   Adverse Reactions  b        Number of Subjects (%)    N= 81      Number of Adverse Reactions per Infusion (Rate  c  )    N = 1129      Number of Subjects (%)    N=87      Number of Adverse Reactions per Infusion (Rate)    N = 365     
  
  Local ARs        42 (51.9%)        234 (0.21)                   4 (4.6%)          4 (0.01)                     
  Systemic ARs     55 (67.9%)        222 (0.20)                   54 (62.1%)        154 (0.42)                   
  Headache         17 (21%)          40 (0.04)                    22 (25.3%)        42 (0.12)                    
  Fatigue          9 (11.1%)         16 (0.01)                    8 (9.2%)          10 (0.03)                    
  Nausea           6 (7.4%)          12 (0.01)                    10 (11.5%)        10 (0.03)                    
  Pyrexia          6 (7.4%)          11 (0.01)                    6 (6.9%)          7 (0.02)                     
  Vomiting         6 (7.4%)          11 (0.01)                    5 (5.7%)          7 (0.02)                     
             a  Causally related adverse events and/or temporally associated adverse events occurring within 72 hours.  b  Excluding infections
 

   c  Rate = total number of events divided by total number of infusions.



 Six subjects, 2 children and 4 adults, withdrew from the trial during the efficacy treatment period with HYQVIA due to mild to moderate adverse reactions. One child withdrew due to local pain and one due to fever, vomiting, and headaches. Of the four adults, two withdrew due to local pain and swelling, one had moderate swelling that transiently extended from the abdominal infusion site to the genitalia, and one had back injury.



 Antibodies binding to rHuPH20: A total of 15 out of 83 subjects who were treated with HYQVIA developed an antibody capable of binding to recombinant human hyaluronidase in the clinical trials. These antibodies were not capable of neutralizing recombinant human hyaluronidase.



 In the clinical trial, no temporal association between adverse reactions and the presence of antibodies capable of binding to the Recombinant Human Hyaluronidase of HYQVIA could be demonstrated. There was no increase in incidence or severity of adverse reactions in subjects who developed antibodies to Recombinant Human Hyaluronidase of HYQVIA. In all subjects, antibody titers decreased despite continued treatment.



 The effect of exposure to antibodies capable of binding to Recombinant Human Hyaluronidase of HYQVIA for periods longer than this clinical trial has not been evaluated.



 The local adverse reactions are listed by frequency in Table 5.  Mild swelling around the infusion site was present in most infusions due to the large volumes infused, but in general was not considered to be an adverse reaction unless it caused discomfort.  Among the 234 local adverse reactions, three were severe (infusion site pain, infusion site swelling and infusion site edema that extended from the abdominal infusion site to the genitalia); all were transient and resolved without sequelae. More than 98% of local reactions were either mild (70.5%) or moderate (28.2%) in severity.



 Table 5 Most Frequent Local Adverse Reactions Reported in greater than 1% of Infusion During Treatment With HYQVIA 
   Infusion Site Reaction      Number and Rate of    Reactions per Infusion    N=1129     
  
  Discomfort/pain          122 (0.11)                
  Erythema                 32 (0.03)                 
  Swelling/Edema           35 (0.03)                 
  Pruritus                 22 (0.02)                 
        Rate per infusion = total number of events divided by total number of infusions
 

 During the combined efficacy and extension trials encompassing more than 3 years, the local adverse reaction rate was 2.6 per patient-year.  During the first 12 month period (months 1-12), the rate was 3.68 local adverse reactions per patient-year.  During the subsequent 12 month period (months 13-24), the rate declined to 2.12 local adverse reactions per-patient year.  Finally, during the third 12 month period (months 25-36), the rate further declined to 0.37 local adverse reactions per patient-year.



 Sixty-six of the 68 subjects who completed the efficacy clinical trial enrolled in a prospective, open-label, multicenter extension trial to assess the long-term safety and tolerability of HYQVIA. Sixty-three of 66 subjects enrolled received HYQVIA and 3 received IGIV. Of the 63 subjects who received HYQVIA, 48 completed the extension trial. The cumulative exposure of HYQVIA across the two trials was 188 subject-years and 2959 infusions, and a maximum exposure of 188 weeks or up to approximately 3.5 years. There were no clinically observable changes in the skin or subcutaneous tissue in either the efficacy or extension clinical trials.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.



   Postmarketing Experience of Immune Globulin Products  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during the postmarketing use of Immune Globulin products administered intravenously:




  Hematologic             Leukopenia, Pancytopenia                                          
  Neurological            Transient ischemic attack, Tremor, Burning sensation, Cerebral vascular accident, Coma, Seizures, Loss of consciousness    
  Cardiovascular          Hypotension, Hypertension, Myocardial infarction, Chest pain, Cardiac arrest, Vascular collapse    
  Respiratory             Pulmonary edema, Dyspnea, Oxygen saturation decreased, Cyanosis, Hypoxemia, Bronchospasm, Apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS)    
  Gastrointestinal        Abdominal pain, Hepatic dysfunction                               
  Integumentary           Hyperhidrosis, Allergic dermatitis, Bullous dermatitis, Epidermolysis, Erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome    
  Psychiatric             Anxiety, Insomnia                                                 
  Musculoskeletal         Back Pain                                                         
  General/Body as a Whole    Edema, Rigors                                                     
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: THROMBOSIS 

  WARNING: THROMBOSIS 

    *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including HYQVIA. Risk factors may include advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer HYQVIA at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. 
 *  Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk of hyperviscosity. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: THROMBOSIS 
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including HYQVIA. Risk factors may include advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity and cardiovascular risk factors. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer HYQVIA at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. 
 *  Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk of hyperviscosity. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    IgA-deficient patients with anti-IgA antibodies are at greater risk of severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products including HYQVIA. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Antibodies to PH20 (recombinant human hyaluronidase) can develop. The potential exists for such antibodies to cross-react with endogenous PH20 which is known to be expressed in the adult male testes, epididymis, and sperm. It is unknown whether these antibodies may interfere with fertilization in humans. The clinical significance of these antibodies is not known. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS) may occur. Discontinue treatment if AMS symptoms appear. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Acute intravascular hemolysis may occur. Monitor for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis and hemolytic anemia. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Infusion into or around an infected area can spread a localized infection. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Monitor for pulmonary adverse reactions (transfusion-related acute lung injury [TRALI]). (  5.8  ) 
 *    May carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur, even in patients who have tolerated previous treatment with IgG. In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue the HYQVIA infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment.



 Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) of HYQVIA contains trace amount of IgA (average concentration of 37mug/mL). Patients with antibodies to IgA potentially are at greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions.



    5.2 Thrombosis



  Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products, including HYQVIA. Risk factors may include advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors.



 Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, such as those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer HYQVIA at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity. [see Boxed Warning, Dosage and Administration  (  2  ) , Patient Counseling Information  (  17  )].



    5.3 Immunogenicity of Recombinant Human Hyaluronidase (PH20)



  Eighteen percent (15 of 83) of subjects receiving HYQVIA in clinical studies developed non-neutralizing antibodies to the recombinant human hyaluronidase component. The potential exists for such antibodies to cross-react with endogenous PH20, which is known to be expressed in the adult male testes, epididymis, and sperm. It is unknown whether these antibodies may interfere with fertilization in humans. The clinical significance of these antibodies is not known.



    5.4 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



  AMS has been reported to occur with IgG products, including Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) administered intravenously and subcutaneously. Discontinuation of IgG treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae. The syndrome usually begins within several hours to two days following intravenously administered IgG, perhaps more frequently in association with high dose (2 g/kg) intravenously administered IgG.



 AMS is characterized by the following signs and symptoms: severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea and vomiting [see Patient Counseling Information  (  17  )]. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies frequently reveal pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per mm  3  , predominantly from the granulocytic series, and elevated protein levels up to several hundred mg/dL, but negative culture results. Conduct a thorough neurological examination on patients exhibiting such symptoms and signs, including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis.



    5.5 Hemolysis



  IgG products, including HYQVIA, contain blood group antibodies which may act as hemolysins and induce in vivo  coating of red blood cells (RBC) with IgG. These antibodies may cause a positive direct antiglobulin reaction and hemolysis  6  .    Acute intravascular hemolysis has been reported following intravenously administered IgG, including Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) administered intravenously, and    delayed hemolytic anemia can develop due to enhanced RBC sequestration [see Adverse Reactions  (  6  )].



 Monitor patients for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis. If signs and/or symptoms of hemolysis are present after HYQVIA infusion, perform appropriate confirmatory laboratory testing [see Patient Counseling Information  (  17  )].



    5.6 Renal Dysfunction/Failure



  Acute renal dysfunction/failure, acute tubular necrosis, proximal tubular nephropathy, osmotic nephrosis and death may occur upon use of IgG products administered intravenously, especially those containing sucrose  4  . HYQVIA does not contain sucrose. Acute renal dysfunction/failure has been reported in association with Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) administered intravenously. Ensure that patients are not volume depleted prior to the initiation of infusion of HYQVIA. In patients who are at risk of developing renal dysfunction because of pre-existing renal insufficiency or predisposition to acute renal failure (such as diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs), monitor renal function and consider lower, more frequent dosing.



 Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk for developing acute renal failure. Assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of HYQVIA and again at appropriate intervals thereafter. If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuation of HYQVIA.



    5.7 Spread of Localized Infection



  Infusion into or around an infected area can spread a localized infection. Do not infuse HYQVIA into these areas due to potential risk of spreading a localized infection.



    5.8 Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Non-cardiogenic pulmonary edema (TRALI) may occur with intravenously administered IgG and has been reported to occur with Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) administered intravenously. TRALI is characterized by severe respiratory distress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function, and fever. Symptoms typically occur within 1 to 6 hours after treatment.



 Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions [see Patient Counseling Information  (  17  )]. If TRALI is suspected, conduct an evaluation, including appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil and anti-HLA antibodies in both the product and patient serum. TRALI may be managed using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



    5.9 Transmittable Infectious Agents



  Because Immune Globulin Infusion 10% (Human) of HYQVIA is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant CJD (vCJD) agent, and theoretically, the classic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent. This also applies to unknown or emerging viruses and other pathogens. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or vCJD have been associated with HYQVIA.



 Report all infections thought to be possibly transmitted by HYQVIA to Baxter Healthcare Corporation, at 1-800-423-2862 (in the U.S.).



    5.10 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  After infusion of IgG, the transitory rise of the various passively transferred antibodies in the patient's blood may yield false positive serological testing results, with the potential for misleading interpretation. Passive transmission of antibodies to erythrocyte antigens (e.g., A, B, and D) may cause a positive direct or indirect antiglobulin (Coombs') test.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
