<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hysingla" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  
 *  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)  ]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.3)  ]  
 *  Interactions with Other CNS Depressants [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)  ]  
 *  Hypotensive Effects [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)  ]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Effects [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.9  ,  5.10)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common treatment-emergent adverse events (&gt;=5%) are constipation, nausea, vomiting, fatigue, upper respiratory tract infection, dizziness, headache, and somnolence.  (6.1)  
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Purdue Pharma L.P. at 1-888-726-7535 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 1,827 patients were treated with HYSINGLA ER in controlled and open-label chronic pain clinical trials. Five hundred patients were treated for 6 months and 364 patients were treated for 12 months. The clinical trial population consisted of opioid-naive and opioid-experienced patients with persistent moderate to severe chronic pain.



 The common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) reported by patients in clinical trials comparing HYSINGLA ER (20-120 mg/day) with placebo are shown in Table 2 below:



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=2% of Patients during the Open-Label Titration Period and Double-Blind Treatment Period: Opioid-Naive and Opioid-Experienced Patients 
                        
   MedDRA Preferred Term     
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
      The adverse reactions seen in controlled and open-label chronic pain studies are presented below in the following manner: most common (&gt;=5%), common (&gt;=1% to &lt;5%), and less common (&lt;1%).
 

 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) reported by patients treated with HYSINGLA ER in the chronic pain clinical trials were constipation, nausea, vomiting, fatigue, upper respiratory tract infection, dizziness, headache, somnolence.



 The common (&gt;=1% to &lt;5%) adverse events reported by patients treated with HYSINGLA ER in the chronic pain clinical trials organized by MedDRA (Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities) System Organ Class were:




   Ear and labyrinth disorders    tinnitus          
   Gastrointestinal disorders    abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, gastroesophageal reflux disease   
   General disorders and administration site conditions    chest pain, chills, edema peripheral, pain, pyrexia   
   Infections and infestations    bronchitis, gastroenteritis, gastroenteritis viral, influenza, nasopharyngitis, sinusitis, urinary tract infection   
   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications    fall, muscle strain   
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders    decreased appetite   
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders    arthralgia, back pain, muscle spasms, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia, pain in extremity   
   Nervous system disorders    lethargy, migraine, sedation   
   Psychiatric disorders    anxiety, depression, insomnia   
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders    cough, nasal congestion, oropharyngeal pain   
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders    hyperhidrosis, pruritus, rash   
   Vascular disorders    hot flush, hypertension   
      Other less common adverse reactions that were seen in &lt;1% of the patients in the HYSINGLA ER chronic pain clinical trials include the following in alphabetical order: abdominal discomfort, abdominal distention, agitation, asthenia, choking, confusional state, depressed mood, drug hypersensitivity, drug withdrawal syndrome, dysphagia, dyspnea, esophageal obstruction, flushing, hypogonadism, hypotension, hypoxia, irritability, libido decreased, malaise, mental impairment, mood altered, muscle twitching, edema, orthostatic hypotension, palpitations, presyncope, retching, syncope, thinking abnormal, thirst, tremor, and urinary retention.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY

DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME;

AND CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION

  WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY

DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME;

AND CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION

      Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse  HYSINGLA ER exposes patients and other users to the risks of opioid

addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death.

Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing HYSINGLA ER, and monitor

all patients regularly for the development of these behaviors or conditions   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.1)  ]  .  



     Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression

may occur with use of HYSINGLA ER. Monitor for respiratory depression,

especially during initiation of HYSINGLA ER or following a dose increase.

Instruct patients to swallow HYSINGLA ER tablets whole; crushing,

chewing, or dissolving HYSINGLA ER tablets can cause rapid release

and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of hydrocodone   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.2)  ]  .  



     Accidental Ingestion  Accidental

ingestion of even one dose of HYSINGLA ER, especially by children,

can result in a fatal overdose of hydrocodone   [see Warnings

and Precautions   (5.2)  ]  .  



     Neonatal

Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome  Prolonged use of

HYSINGLA ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal

syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated,

and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology

experts.  If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant

woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal

syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.3)  ]  .  



     Cytochrome P450 3A4 Interaction  The concomitant use of HYSINGLA ER with all cytochrome P450 3A4

inhibitors may result in an increase in hydrocodone plasma concentrations,

which could increase or prolong adverse drug effects and may cause

potentially fatal respiratory depression.  In addition, discontinuation

of a concomitantly used cytochrome P450 3A4 inducer may result in

an increase in hydrocodone plasma concentration.  Monitor patients

receiving HYSINGLA ER and any CYP3A4 inhibitor or inducer   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  ), Drug Interactions (  7.1  ) and Clinical

Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING

RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL

SYNDROME; AND CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION



   See full prescribing information for complete

boxed warning.  



 *  HYSINGLATM ER exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors or conditions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients to swallow HYSINGLA ER whole to avoid exposure to a potentially fatal dose of hydrocodone. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental ingestion of HYSINGLA ER, especially by children, can result in fatal overdose of hydrocodone. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of HYSINGLA ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
 *  Initiation of CYP3A4 inhibitors (or discontinuation of CYP3A4 inducers) can result in a fatal overdose of hydrocodone from HYSINGLA ER. (5.11,7.1, 12.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Misuse, abuse, and diversion: HYSINGLA ER is an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance with a high potential for abuse similar to fentanyl, methadone, morphine, oxycodone, and oxymorphone.  (5.1)   
 *  Interactions with CNS depressants: Concomitant use may cause profound sedation, respiratory depression, and death. If co-administration is required, consider dose reduction of one or both drugs.  (5.4)   
 *  Elderly, cachectic, debilitated patients, and those with chronic pulmonary disease: Monitor closely because of increased risk for life-threatening respiratory depression.  (5.5  ,  5.6)   
 *  Patients with head injury or increased intracranial pressure: Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression. Avoid use of HYSINGLA ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention.  (5.7)   
 *  Risk of Choking/GI Obstruction: Use with caution in patients who have difficulty swallowing or have underlying GI disorders that may predispose them to obstruction.  (5.9  ,  5.10)   
 *  Concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors may increase opioid effects.  (5.11)   
 *  Impaired mental/physical abilities: Caution must be used with potentially hazardous activities.  (5.12)   
 *  QTc prolongation has been observed with HYSINGLA ER following daily doses of 160 mg. Avoid use in patients with congenital long QTc syndrome. This observation should be considered in making clinical decisions regarding patient monitoring when prescribing HYSINGLA ER in patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias electrolyte abnormalities, or who are taking medications that are known to prolong the QTc interval. In patients who develop QTc prolongation, consider reducing the dose.  (5.14,    12.2)   
    
 

   5.1 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  HYSINGLA ER contains hydrocodone, a Schedule II controlled substance. As an opioid, HYSINGLA ER exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse [see Drug Abuse and Dependence  (9.1)  ]  . As extended-release products such as HYSINGLA ER deliver the opioid over an extended period of time, there is a greater risk for overdose and death due to the larger amount of hydrocodone present.



 Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed HYSINGLA ER and in those who obtain the drug illicitly. Addiction can occur at recommended doses and if the drug is misused or abused.



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing HYSINGLA ER, and monitor all patients receiving HYSINGLA ER for the development of these behaviors or conditions. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol addiction or abuse) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the prescribing of HYSINGLA ER for the proper management of pain in any given patient.



 Abuse or misuse of HYSINGLA ER by crushing, chewing, snorting, or injecting the dissolved product will result in the uncontrolled delivery of the hydrocodone and can result in overdose and death [see Drug Abuse and Dependence  (9.1)  , and Overdosage  (10)  ]  .



 Opioid agonists are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing HYSINGLA ER. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper disposal of unused drug [see Patient Counseling Information  (17)  ]  . Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.2 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of modified-release opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression from opioid use, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see Overdosage  (10.2)  ]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.



 While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of HYSINGLA ER, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dose increase. Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression when initiating therapy with HYSINGLA ER and following dose increases.



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of HYSINGLA ER are essential [see Dosage and Administration  (2.1,    2.2)  ]  . Overestimating the HYSINGLA ER dose when converting patients from another opioid product can result in fatal overdose with the first dose.



 Accidental ingestion of even one dose of HYSINGLA ER, especially by children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of hydrocodone.



    5.3 Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Prolonged use of HYSINGLA ER during pregnancy can result in withdrawal signs in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available.



 Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome presents as irritability, hyperactivity and abnormal sleep pattern, high pitched cry, tremor, vomiting, diarrhea and failure to gain weight. The onset, duration, and severity of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome vary based on the specific opioid used, duration of use, timing and amount of last maternal use, and rate of elimination of the drug by the newborn.



    5.4 Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



  Hypotension, profound sedation, coma, respiratory depression, and death may result if HYSINGLA ER is used concomitantly with alcohol or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids).



 When considering the use of HYSINGLA ER in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin HYSINGLA ER is made, start with a lower HYSINGLA ER dose than usual (i.e., 20-30% less), monitor patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, and consider using a lower dose of the concomitant CNS depressant [see Drug Interactions  (7.2)  ]  .



    5.5 Use in Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



  Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating HYSINGLA ER and when HYSINGLA ER is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)  ]  .



    5.6 Use in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Monitor patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or preexisting respiratory depression for respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy and titrating with HYSINGLA ER, as in these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of HYSINGLA ER may decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)  ]  . Consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients if possible.



    5.7 Use in Patients with Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  In the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a preexisting increase in intracranial pressure, the possible respiratory depressant effects of opioid analgesics and their potential to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2retention) may be markedly exaggerated. Furthermore, opioid analgesics can produce effects on pupillary response and consciousness, which may obscure neurologic signs of further increases in intracranial pressure in patients with head injuries.



 Monitor patients closely who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention, such as those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or impaired consciousness. Opioids may obscure the clinical course of a patient with a head injury.



 Avoid the use of HYSINGLA ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.8 Hypotensive Effect



  HYSINGLA ER may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is an added risk to individuals whose ability to maintain blood pressure has been compromised by a depleted blood volume, or after concurrent administration with drugs such as phenothiazines or other agents which compromise vasomotor tone. Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dose of HYSINGLA ER. In patients with circulatory shock, HYSINGLA ER may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. Avoid the use of HYSINGLA ER in patients with circulatory shock.



    5.9 Gastrointestinal Obstruction, Dysphagia, and Choking



  In the clinical studies with specific instructions to take HYSINGLA ER with adequate water to swallow the tablet, 11 out of 2476 subjects reported difficulty swallowing HYSINGLA ER. These reports included esophageal obstruction, dysphagia, and choking, one of which had required medical intervention to remove the tablet [see Adverse Reactions  (6)  ].  



 Instruct patients not to pre-soak, lick, or otherwise wet HYSINGLA ER tablets prior to placing in the mouth, and to take one tablet at a time with enough water to ensure complete swallowing immediately after placing in the mouth [see Patient Counseling Information  (17)  ]  .



 Patients with underlying gastrointestinal disorders such as esophageal cancer or colon cancer with a small gastrointestinal lumen are at greater risk of developing these complications. Consider use of an alternative analgesic in patients who have difficulty swallowing and patients at risk for underlying gastrointestinal disorders resulting in a small gastrointestinal lumen.



    5.10 Decreased Bowel Motility



  HYSINGLA ER is contraindicated in patients with known or suspected gastrointestinal obstruction, including paralytic ileus. Opioids diminish propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and decrease bowel motility. Monitor for decreased bowel motility in post-operative patients receiving opioids. The administration of HYSINGLA ER may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal conditions. Hydrocodone may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis.



    5.11 Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  Since the CYP3A4 isoenzyme plays a major role in the metabolism of HYSINGLA ER, drugs that alter CYP3A4 activity may cause changes in clearance of hydrocodone which could lead to changes in hydrocodone plasma concentrations.



 The clinical results with CYP3A4 inhibitors show an increase in hydrocodone plasma concentrations and possibly increased or prolonged opioid effects, which could be more pronounced with concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors. The expected clinical result with CYP3A4 inducers is a decrease in hydrocodone plasma concentrations, lack of efficacy or, possibly, development of an abstinence syndrome in a patient who had developed physical dependence to hydrocodone.



 If co-administration is necessary, caution is advised when initiating HYSINGLA ER treatment in patients currently taking, or discontinuing, CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers. Evaluate these patients at frequent intervals and consider dose adjustments until stable drug effects are achieved [see Drug Interactions  (7.1)  ]  .



    5.12 Driving and Operating Machinery



  HYSINGLA ER may impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. Peak blood levels of hydrocodone may occur 14 - 16 hours (range 6 - 30 hours) after initial dosing of HYSINGLA ER tablet administration. Blood levels of hydrocodone, in some patients, may be high at the end of 24 hours after repeated-dose administration. Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to the effects of HYSINGLA ER and know how they will react to the medication [see Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)  ]  .



    5.13 Interaction with Mixed Agonist/Antagonist Opioid Analgesics



  Avoid the use of mixed agonist/antagonist analgesics (i.e., pentazocine, nalbuphine, and butorphanol) in patients who have received, or are receiving, a course of therapy with a full opioid agonist analgesic, including HYSINGLA ER. In these patients, mixed agonist/antagonist analgesics may reduce the analgesic effect and/or may precipitate withdrawal symptoms.



    5.14 QT Interval Prolongation



  QTc prolongation has been observed with HYSINGLA ER following daily doses of 160 mg [see Clinical Pharmacology  (12.2)  ]  . This observation should be considered in making clinical decisions regarding patient monitoring when prescribing HYSINGLA ER in patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, electrolyte abnormalities, or who are taking medications that are known to prolong the QTc interval.



 HYSINGLA ER should be avoided in patients with congenital long QT syndrome. In patients who develop QTc prolongation, consider reducing the dose by 33 - 50%, or changing to an alternate analgesic.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
