<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="hyzaar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Losartan potassium-hydrochlorothiazide has been evaluated for safety in 858 patients treated for essential hypertension and 3889 patients treated for hypertension and left ventricular hypertrophy. In clinical trials with losartan potassium-hydrochlorothiazide, no adverse experiences peculiar to this combination have been observed. Adverse experiences have been limited to those that were reported previously with losartan potassium and/or hydrochlorothiazide. The overall incidence of adverse experiences reported with the combination was comparable to placebo.



 In general, treatment with losartan potassium-hydrochlorothiazide was well tolerated. For the most part, adverse experiences have been mild and transient in nature and have not required discontinuation of therapy. In controlled clinical trials, discontinuation of therapy due to clinical adverse experiences was required in only 2.8% and 2.3% of patients treated with the combination and placebo, respectively.



 In these double-blind controlled clinical trials, the following adverse experiences reported with losartan-hydrochlorothiazide occurred in &gt;=1 percent of patients, and more often on drug than placebo, regardless of drug relationship:




                                      Losartan Potassium-Hydrochlorothiazide(n=858)  Placebo(n=173)                     
  
   Body as a Whole     Abdominal pain   Edema/swelling  1.21.3                            0.61.2                             
   Cardiovascular     Palpitation     1.4                               0.0                                
   Musculoskeletal     Back pain      2.1                               0.6                                
   Nervous/Psychiatric     Dizziness  5.7                               2.9                                
   Respiratory     Cough   Sinusitis   Upper respiratory infection  2.61.26.1                         2.30.64.6                          
   Skin     Rash                      1.4                               0.0                                
         The following adverse events were also reported at a rate of 1% or greater, but were as, or more, common in the placebo group in studies of essential hypertension: asthenia/fatigue, diarrhea, nausea, headache, bronchitis, pharyngitis.
 

 Adverse events occurred at about the same rates in men and women. Adverse events were somewhat more frequent in the elderly compared to non-elderly patients and somewhat more frequent in Blacks compared to non-Blacks for both the losartan-hydrochlorothiazide and the control groups.



 A patient with known hypersensitivity to aspirin and penicillin, when treated with losartan potassium, was withdrawn from study due to swelling of the lips and eyelids and facial rash, reported as angioedema, which returned to normal 5 days after therapy was discontinued.



 Superficial peeling of palms and hemolysis were reported in one subject treated with losartan potassium.



   Losartan Potassium

  Other adverse experiences that have been reported with losartan, without regard to causality, are listed below:



   Body as a Whole:  chest pain, facial edema, fever, orthostatic effects, syncope;  Cardiovascular:  angina pectoris, arrhythmias including atrial fibrillation, sinus bradycardia, tachycardia, ventricular tachycardia and ventricular fibrillation, CVA, hypotension, myocardial infarction, second degree AV block;  Digestive:  anorexia, constipation, dental pain, dry mouth, dyspepsia, flatulence, gastritis, vomiting;  General disorders and administration site conditions:  malaise;  Hematologic:  anemia;  Metabolic:  gout;  Musculoskeletal:  arm pain, arthralgia, arthritis, fibromyalgia, hip pain, joint swelling, knee pain, leg pain, muscle cramps, muscle weakness, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia, shoulder pain, stiffness;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  anxiety, anxiety disorder, ataxia, confusion, depression, dream abnormality, hypesthesia, insomnia, libido decreased, memory impairment, migraine, nervousness, panic disorder, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, sleep disorder, somnolence, tremor, vertigo;  Respiratory:  dyspnea, epistaxis, nasal congestion, pharyngeal discomfort, respiratory congestion, rhinitis, sinus disorder;  Skin:  alopecia, dermatitis, dry skin, ecchymosis, erythema, flushing, photosensitivity, pruritus, sweating, urticaria;  Special Senses:  blurred vision, burning/stinging in the eye, conjunctivitis, decrease in visual acuity, taste perversion, tinnitus;  Urogenital:  impotence, nocturia, urinary frequency, urinary tract infection.



   Hydrochlorothiazide

  Other adverse experiences that have been reported with hydrochlorothiazide, without regard to causality, are listed below:



   Body as a Whole:  weakness;  Digestive:  pancreatitis, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice), sialadenitis, cramping, gastric irritation;  Hematologic:  aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia;  Hypersensitivity:  purpura, photosensitivity, urticaria, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis and cutaneous vasculitis), fever, respiratory distress including pneumonitis and pulmonary edema;  Metabolic:  hyperglycemia, glycosuria, hyperuricemia;  Musculoskeletal:  muscle spasm;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  restlessness;  Renal:  renal failure, renal dysfunction, interstitial nephritis;  Skin:  erythema multiforme including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis including toxic epidermal necrolysis;  Special Senses:  transient blurred vision, xanthopsia.



 Persistent dry cough (with an incidence of a few percent) has been associated with ACE-inhibitor use and in practice can be a cause of discontinuation of ACE-inhibitor therapy. Two prospective, parallel-group, double-blind, randomized, controlled trials were conducted to assess the effects of losartan on the incidence of cough in hypertensive patients who had experienced cough while receiving ACE-inhibitor therapy. Patients who had typical ACE-inhibitor cough when challenged with lisinopril, whose cough disappeared on placebo, were randomized to losartan 50 mg, lisinopril 20 mg, or either placebo (one study, n=97) or 25 mg hydrochlorothiazide (n=135). The double-blind treatment period lasted up to 8 weeks. The incidence of cough is shown below.




 Study 1                    HCTZ                       Losartan                   Lisinopril                  
 Cough                      25%                        17%                        69%                         
                                                                                                              
 Study 2                    Placebo                    Losartan                   Lisinopril                  
                                                                                                              
  Cough                      35%                        29%                       62%                         
          These studies demonstrate that the incidence of cough associated with losartan therapy, in a population that all had cough associated with ACE-inhibitor therapy, is similar to that associated with hydrochlorothiazide or placebo therapy.
 

 Cases of cough, including positive re-challenges, have been reported with the use of losartan in post-marketing experience.



   Severe Hypertension

  In a clinical study in patients with severe hypertension (SiDBP &gt;=110 mmHg), the overall pattern of adverse events reported through six weeks of follow-up was similar in patients treated with HYZAAR as initial therapy and in patients treated with losartan as initial therapy. There were no reported cases of syncope in either treatment group. There were 2 (0.6%) and 0 (0.0%) cases of hypotension reported in the group treated with HYZAAR and the group treated with losartan, respectively. There were 3 (0.8%) and 2 (1.2%) cases of increased serum creatinine (&gt;0.5 mg/dL) in the group treated with HYZAAR and the group treated with losartan, respectively, during the same time period. (See  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Effects, Severe Hypertension  .)



   Post-Marketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been reported in post-marketing experience:



   Digestive:  Hepatitis has been reported rarely in patients treated with losartan.



   Hemic:  Thrombocytopenia.



   Hypersensitivity:  Angioedema, including swelling of the larynx and glottis, causing airway obstruction and/or swelling of the face, lips, pharynx, and/or tongue has been reported rarely in patients treated with losartan; some of these patients previously experienced angioedema with other drugs including ACE inhibitors. Vasculitis, including Henoch-Schonlein purpura, has been reported with losartan. Anaphylactic reactions have been reported.



   Metabolic and Nutrition:  Hyperkalemia, hyponatremia have been reported with losartan.



   Musculoskeletal:  Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers.



   Respiratory:  Dry cough (see above) has been reported with losartan.



   Skin:  Erythroderma has been reported with losartan.



   Laboratory Test Findings

  In controlled clinical trials, clinically important changes in standard laboratory parameters were rarely associated with administration of HYZAAR.



   Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen:  Minor increases in blood urea nitrogen (BUN) or serum creatinine were observed in 0.6 and 0.8 percent, respectively, of patients with essential hypertension treated with HYZAAR alone. No patient discontinued taking HYZAAR due to increased BUN. One patient discontinued taking HYZAAR due to a minor increase in serum creatinine.



   Hemoglobin and Hematocrit:  Small decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit (mean decreases of approximately 0.14 grams percent and 0.72 volume percent, respectively) occurred frequently in patients treated with HYZAAR alone, but were rarely of clinical importance. No patients were discontinued due to anemia.



   Liver Function Tests:  Occasional elevations of liver enzymes and/or serum bilirubin have occurred. In patients with essential hypertension treated with HYZAAR alone, no patients were discontinued due to these laboratory adverse experiences.



   Serum Electrolytes:  See  PRECAUTIONS  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    USE IN PREGNANCY  



   When used in pregnancy during the second and third trimesters, drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and even death to the developing fetus  . When pregnancy is detected, HYZAAR should be discontinued as soon as possible. See   WARNINGS, Fetal/Neonatal Morbidity and Mortality  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
