<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ibuprofen" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  



 The most frequently reported adverse events with Ibuprofen Lysine were as shown in Table 1.



 



 



 



 



 



 



 



 



 



   6.2 Renal Function  



 Compared to placebo, there was a small decrease in urinary output in the ibuprofen group on days 2-6 of life, with a compensatory increase in urine output on day 9. In other studies, adverse events classified as renal insufficiency including oliguria, elevated BUN, elevated creatinine, or renal failure were reported in ibuprofen treated infants.



   6.3 Additional Adverse Events  



 The adverse events reported in the multicenter study and of unknown association include tachycardia, cardiac failure, abdominal distension, gastroesophageal reflux, gastritis, ileus, inguinal hernia, injection site reactions, cholestasis, various infections, feeding problems, convulsions, jaundice, hypotension, and various laboratory abnormalities including neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and hyperglycemia.



   6.4 Post-marketing Experience  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified from spontaneous post-marketing reports or published literature: gastrointestinal perforation, necrotizing enterocolitis, and pulmonary hypertension. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency, or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) are sepsis, anemia, intraventricular bleeding, apnea, gastrointestinal disorders, impaired renal function, respiratory infection, skin lesions, hypoglycemia, hypocalcemia, respiratory failure.  (6)  



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Prasco Laboratories at 1-888-525-0888, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

 Table 1 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   5.1 General  



 There are no long-term evaluations of the infants treated with ibuprofen at durations greater than the 36 weeks post-conceptual age observation period. Ibuprofen's effects on neurodevelopmental outcome and growth as well as disease processes associated with prematurity (such as retinopathy of prematurity and chronic lung disease) have not been assessed.



  5.2 Infection  



 Ibuprofen Lysine may alter the usual signs of infection. The physician must be continually on the alert and should use the drug with extra care in the presence of controlled infection and in infants at risk of infection.



  5.3 Platelet Aggregation  



 Ibuprofen Lysine, like other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents, can inhibit platelet aggregation. Preterm infants should be observed for signs of bleeding. Ibuprofen has been shown to prolong bleeding time (but within the normal range) in normal adult subjects. This effect may be exaggerated in patients with underlying hemostatic defects (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ).



  5.4 Bilirubin Displacement  



 Ibuprofen has been shown to displace bilirubin from albumin binding-sites; therefore, it should be used with caution in patients with elevated total bilirubin.



  5.5 Administration  



 Ibuprofen Lysine should be administered carefully to avoid extravascular injection or leakage, as solution may be irritating to tissue.



 



    EXCERPT:    *  Ibuprofen Lysine has not been assessed for neurodevelopmental outcome and growth  (5.1)   
 *  Ibuprofen Lysine may alter the usual signs of infection  (5.2)   
 *  Ibuprofen Lysine can inhibit platelet aggregation, and has been shown to prolong bleeding time in normal adult subjects  (5.3)   
 *  Ibuprofen has been shown to displace bilirubin from albumin binding-sites  (5.4)   
 *  Ibuprofen Lysine should be administered carefully to avoid extravascular injection or leakage  (5.5)   
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
