<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="iluvien" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   In controlled studies, the most common adverse reactions reported were cataract development and increases in intraocular pressure.  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Alimera Sciences, Inc. at 1-844-445-8843 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



    



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reactions associated with ophthalmic steroids including  ILUVIEN  include cataract formation and subsequent cataract surgery, elevated intraocular pressure, which may be associated with optic nerve damage, visual acuity and field defects, secondary ocular infection from pathogens including herpes simplex, and perforation of the globe where there is thinning of the cornea or sclera.



   ILUVIEN  was studied in two multicenter, randomized, sham-controlled, masked trials in which patients with diabetic macular edema were treated with either ILUVIEN (n=375) or sham (n=185).



   Table 1  summarizes safety data available when the last subject completed the last 36 month follow up visit for the two primary  ILUVIEN  trials. In these trials, subjects were eligible for retreatment no earlier than 12 months after study entry. Over the three year follow up period, approximately 75% of the  ILUVIEN  treated subjects received only one  ILUVIEN  implant.



 The most common ocular (study eye) and non-ocular adverse reactions are shown in  Tables 1  and  2  :



 Table 1: Ocular Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=1% of Patients and Non-ocular Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=5% of Patients 
   1  Includes cataract, cataract nuclear, cataract subcapsular, cataract cortical and cataract diabetic in patients who were phakic at baseline. Among these patients, 80% of  ILUVIEN  subjects vs. 27% of sham-controlled subjects underwent cataract surgery.   
   2  235 of the 375  ILUVIEN  subjects were phakic at baseline; 121 of 185 sham-controlled subjects were phakic at baseline.   
  
   Adverse Reactions          ILUVIEN(N=375)n (%)        Sham(N=185)n (%)          
 Ocular                      
 Cataract  1                192/235  2  (82%)          61/121  2  (50%)            
 Myodesopsia                80 (21%)                   17 (9%)                     
 Eye pain                   57 (15%)                   25 (14%)                    
 Conjunctival hemorrhage    50 (13%)                   21 (11%)                    
 Posterior capsule opacification  35 (9%)                    6 (3%)                      
 Eye irritation             30 (8%)                    11 (6%)                     
 Vitreous detachment        26 (7%)                    12 (7%)                     
 Conjunctivitis             14 (4%)                    5 (3%)                      
 Corneal oedema             13 (4%)                    3 (2%)                      
 Foreign body sensation in eyes  12 (3%)                    4 (2%)                      
 Eye pruritus               10 (3%)                    3 (2%)                      
 Ocular hyperaemia          10 (3%)                    3 (2%)                      
 Optic atrophy              9 (2%)                     2 (1%)                      
 Ocular discomfort          8 (2%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Photophobia                7 (2%)                     2 (1%)                      
 Retinal exudates           7 (2%)                     0 (0%)                      
 Anterior chamber cell      6 (2%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Eye discharge              6 (2%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Non-ocular                  
 Anemia                     40 (11%)                   10 (5%)                     
 Headache                   33 (9%)                    11 (6%)                     
 Renal Failure              32 (9%)                    10 (5%)                     
 Pneumonia                  28 (7%)                    8 (4%)                      
      Increased intraocular Pressure
 

 Table 2: Summary of Elevated IOP Related Adverse Reactions 
   Event       ILUVIEN(N=375)n (%)      Sham(N=185)n (%)     
 IOP elevation &gt;= 10 mmHg from Baseline  127 (34%)  18 (10%)   
 IOP elevation &gt;= 30 mmHg  75 (20%)  8 (4%)   
 Any IOP-lowering medication  144 (38%)  26 (14%)   
 Any surgical intervention for elevated intraocular pressure  18 (5%)  1 (1%)   
        Figure 1: Mean IOP during the study   
 

 



   Cataracts and Cataract Surgery  At baseline, 235 of the 375  ILUVIEN  subjects were phakic; 121 of 185 sham-controlled subjects were phakic. The incidence of cataract development in patients who had a phakic study eye was higher in the  ILUVIEN  group (82%) compared with Sham (50%). The median time of cataract being reported as an adverse event was approximately 12 months in the  ILUVIEN  group and 19 months in the Sham group. Among these patients, 80% of  ILUVIEN  subjects vs. 27% of sham-controlled subjects underwent cataract surgery, generally within the first 18 months (Median Month 15 for both  ILUVIEN  group and for Sham) of the studies.



  iluvien-figure-1   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following reactions have been identified during post-marketing use of  ILUVIEN  in clinical practice. Because they are reported voluntarily estimates of frequency cannot be made. The reactions, which have been chosen for inclusion due to either their seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to  ILUVIEN  , or a combination of these factors, include reports of drug administration error and reports of the drug being ineffective.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Intravitreal injections have been associated with endophthalmitis, eye inflammation, increased intraocular pressure, and retinal detachments. Patients should be monitored following the injection.  (5.1)   
 *  Use of corticosteroids may produce posterior subcapsular cataracts, increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and may enhance the establishment of secondary ocular infections due to bacteria, fungi, or viruses.  (5.2)   
 *  The implant may migrate into the anterior chamber if the posterior lens capsule is not intact.  (5.3)   
    
 

   5.1 Intravitreal Injection-related Effects



  Intravitreal injections, including those with ILUVIEN  , have been associated with endophthalmitis, eye inflammation, increased intraocular pressure, and retinal detachments. Patients should be monitored following the intravitreal injection [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  .



    5.2 Steroid-related Effects



   Use of corticosteroids including ILUVIEN  may produce posterior subcapsular cataracts, increased intraocular pressure and glaucoma.  Use of corticosteroids may enhance the establishment of secondary ocular infections due to bacteria, fungi, or viruses.
 

 Corticosteroids are not recommended to be used in patients with a history of ocular herpes simplex because of the potential for reactivation of the viral infection.



    5.3 Risk of Implant Migration



  Patients in whom the posterior capsule of the lens is absent or has a tear are at risk of implant migration into the anterior chamber.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
