<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="imlygic" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6          ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The most commonly reported adverse drug reactions (&gt;= 25%) in IMLYGIC-treated patients were fatigue, chills, pyrexia, nausea, influenza-like illness, and injection site pain.



 The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in another section of the label:



 *  Herpetic Infection [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.2    )]  
 *  Injection Site Complications  [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.3    )]  
   *  The most commonly reported adverse drug reactions (&gt;= 25%) in IMLYGIC-treated patients were fatigue, chills, pyrexia, nausea, influenza-like illness, and injection site pain. (  6  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Amgen at 1-855-IMLYGIC (1-855-465-9442) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

    6.1          Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of IMLYGIC was evaluated in 419 patients who received at least 1 dose of either IMLYGIC (n = 292) or subcutaneously administered granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) (n = 127) in an open-label, randomized clinical study of patients with stage IIIB, IIIC, and IV melanoma that was not considered to be surgically resectable   [see Clinical Studies    (      14      )]  . The median duration of exposure to IMLYGIC was 23 weeks (5.3 months). Twenty-six patients were exposed to IMLYGIC for at least 1 year.



 Most adverse reactions reported were mild or moderate in severity and generally resolved within 72 hours. The most common grade 3 or higher adverse reaction was cellulitis  [see Warnings and Precautions (      5.3      )]  .



 Pyrexia, chills, and influenza-like illness can occur any time during IMLYGIC treatment but were more frequent during the first 3 months of treatment. 



 Table 4 below lists adverse reactions with a 5% or greater incidence in the IMLYGIC arm compared to the GM-CSF arm in the clinical study  [see Clinical Studies    (      14      )]  .



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions Reported with At Least a 5% Greater Incidence in Patients Treated with IMLYGIC Compared to GM-CSF 
                    IMLYGIC    (    n         =         292)      GM-CSF         (    n         =         127)     
   Adverse Reactions      Any Grade    n (%)      Grade 3    n (%)      Any Grade    n (%)      Grade 3    n (%)     
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
     Fatigue      147 (50.3)       6 (2.1)          46 (36.2)        1 (&lt; 1)           
     Chills       142 (48.6)                        11 (8.7)                           
     Pyrexia      125 (42.8)                        11 (8.7)                           
     Influenza-like illness  89 (30.5)        2 (&lt; 1)          19 (15.0)                          
     Injection site pain  81 (27.7)        2 (&lt; 1)          8 (6.3)                            
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
     Nausea       104 (35.6)       1 (&lt; 1)          25 (19.7)                          
     Vomiting     62 (21.2)        5 (1.7)          12 (9.5)                           
     Diarrhea     55 (18.8)        1 (&lt; 1)          14 (11.0)                          
     Constipation  34 (11.6)                         8 (6.3)          1 (&lt; 1)           
     Abdominal pain  26 (8.9)         2 (&lt; 1)          3 (2.4)                            
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
     Myalgia      51 (17.5)        1 (&lt; 1)          7 (5.5)                            
     Arthralgia   50 (17.1)        2 (&lt; 1)          11 (8.7)                           
     Pain in extremity  48 (16.4)        4 (1.4)          12 (9.5)         1 (&lt; 1)           
   Nervous system disorders     
     Headache     55 (18.8)        2 (&lt; 1)          12 (9.5)                           
     Dizziness    28 (9.6)                          4 (3.2)                            
   Respiratory, thoracic    ,    and mediastinal disorders     
     Oropharyngeal pain  17 (5.8)                          1 (&lt; 1)                            
   Investigations     
     Weight decreased  17 (5.8)         1 (&lt; 1)          1 (&lt; 1)                            
           Other adverse reactions associated with IMLYGIC in the open-label, randomized study include glomerulonephritis, vitiligo, cellulitis, and oral herpes.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5         WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Accidental Exposure to IMLYGIC: Accidental exposure may lead to transmission of IMLYGIC and herpetic infection. Healthcare providers and close contacts should avoid direct contact with injected lesions, dressings, or body fluids of treated patients. Healthcare providers who are immunocompromised or pregnant should not prepare or administer IMLYGIC. If accidental exposure occurs, exposed individuals should clean the affected area. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Herpetic Infection: Patients who develop herpetic infections should be advised to follow standard hygienic practices to prevent viral transmission. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Injection Site Complications: Consider the risks and benefits before continuing IMLYGIC treatment if persistent infection or delayed healing develops. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Immune-Mediated Events: Consider the risks and benefits of IMLYGIC before initiating treatment in patients who have underlying autoimmune disease or before continuing treatment in patients who develop immune-mediated events. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Plasmacytoma at Injection Site: Consider the risks and benefits in patients with multiple myeloma or in whom plasmacytoma develops during treatment. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

    5.   1         Accidental Exposure to   IMLYGIC  



  Accidental exposure may lead to transmission of IMLYGIC and herpetic infection. Accidental needle stick and splashback to the eyes have been reported in healthcare providers during preparation and administration of IMLYGIC.  



 Healthcare providers, close contacts (household members, caregivers, sex partners, or persons sharing the same bed), pregnant women, and newborns should avoid direct contact with injected lesions, dressings, or body fluids of treated patients  [   see Dosage and Administration (     2.2     )]  . Healthcare providers who are immunocompromised or pregnant should not prepare or administer IMLYGIC.



 Caregivers should wear protective gloves when assisting patients in applying or changing occlusive dressings and observe safety precautions for disposal of used dressings, gloves, and cleaning materials [   see Dosage and Administration (     2.2     )   ]  .



 In the event of an accidental exposure to IMLYGIC, exposed individuals should clean the affected area thoroughly with soap and water and/or a disinfectant. If signs or symptoms of herpetic infection develop, the exposed individuals should contact their healthcare provider for appropriate treatment [   see Warnings and Precautions (     5.2     )]  .



 Patients should avoid touching or scratching injection sites or their occlusive dressings, as doing so could lead to inadvertent transfer of IMLYGIC to other areas of the body.



     5.   2             Herpetic Infection  



  In clinical studies, herpetic infections (including cold sores and herpetic keratitis) have been reported in patients treated with IMLYGIC. Disseminated herpetic infection may also occur in immunocompromised patients  [   see Contraindications (     4.1     )]  .



 Patients who develop suspicious herpes-like lesions should follow standard hygienic practices to prevent viral transmission. Patients or close contacts with suspected herpetic infections should also contact their healthcare provider to evaluate the lesions. Suspected herpetic lesions should be reported to Amgen at 1-855-IMLYGIC (1-855-465-9442); patients or close contacts have the option of follow-up testing for further characterization of the infection.



 IMLYGIC is sensitive to acyclovir. Acyclovir or other antiviral agents may interfere with the effectiveness of IMLYGIC. Therefore, consider the risks and benefits of IMLYGIC treatment before administering antiviral agents to manage herpetic infection.



     5.   3         Injection Site Complications  



  Necrosis or ulceration of tumor tissue may occur during IMLYGIC treatment. Cellulitis and systemic bacterial infection have been reported in clinical studies. Careful wound care and infection precautions are recommended, particularly if tissue necrosis results in open wounds.



 In clinical studies, impaired healing at the injection site has been reported. IMLYGIC may increase the risk of impaired healing in patients with underlying risk factors (e.g., previous radiation at the injection site or lesions in poorly vascularized areas). One patient had an amputation of a lower extremity 6 months after IMLYGIC injection due to an infected non-healing wound. This wound area had been treated with surgery and radiation prior to IMLYGIC treatment and had previous wound complications.



 If there is persistent infection or delayed healing of the injection site(s), consider the risks and benefits of IMLYGIC before continuing treatment with IMLYGIC.



     5.   4         Immune-   M   ediated   Events  



  IMLYGIC may result in immune-mediated events. In clinical studies, immune-mediated events, including glomerulonephritis, vasculitis, pneumonitis, worsening psoriasis, and vitiligo have been reported in patients treated with IMLYGIC.



 Consider the risks and benefits of IMLYGIC before initiating treatment in patients who have underlying autoimmune disease or before continuing treatment in patients who develop immune-mediated events.



     5.   5         Plasmacytoma at Injection Site  



  In a clinical study, a plasmacytoma has been reported in proximity to the injection site after administration of IMLYGIC in a patient with smoldering multiple myeloma.



 Consider the risks and benefits of IMLYGIC in patients with multiple myeloma or in whom plasmacytoma develops during treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
