<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="imogam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic prophylactic treatments occasionally are complicated by adverse reaction. (1)



   Data From Clinical Studies

   The safety profile of Imogam  (r)  Rabies - HT (heat treated) was compared to Rabies Immune Globulin (Human), Imogam  (r)  Rabies (non-heat treated), in a clinical trial involving 16 volunteers in each of 4 treatment groups (64 total subjects). Local and systemic adverse reactions were classified by the description of the reaction and by its severity (Mild - aware of symptoms but easily tolerated [pain described as tenderness upon touch; erythema, bruising, induration/ swelling &lt;1 inch (2.5 cm); occasional site pruritis; fever (oral temperature 37.5-38.5 degrees C)]. Moderate - discomforting enough to interfere with normal daily activity [pain on movement; erythema, bruising, induration/swelling of 1-2 inches (2.5-5 cm) in diameter; frequent site pruritis; fever (oral temperature 38.5-40 degrees C)]. Severe - subject bed-ridden [disabling pain that limited motion; erythema, bruising, induration/ swelling &gt;2 inches (&gt;5 cm); continuous site pruritis, fever (oral temperature &gt;40 degrees C).) . Both Imogam  (r)  Rabies - HT and Imogam  (r)  Rabies were without reported serious adverse reactions or allergic reactions. Two subjects reported severe headaches, one in the Imogam  (r)  Rabies - HT + placebo group and one in the Imogam  (r)  Rabies + Imovax  (r)  Rabies group, and one third of the volunteers reported moderate systemic (headache and malaise) reactions. These were equally distributed among the 4 treatment groups with no significant differences between the groups. Three-quarters of the local adverse reactions (tenderness, pain, erythema, induration, pruritus, regional adenopathy) were mild. The safety profile did not differ between groups, although Imogam  (r)  Rabies - HT produced fewer and milder local reactions such as pain or tenderness at the injection site. (6)
 

   Data From Post-marketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Imogam  (r)  Rabies - HT. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to Imogam  (r)  Rabies - HT exposure.



   Cardiac Disorders  



 *     Hypotension, tachycardia 
      Gastrointestinal Disorders  
 

 *     Nausea, vomiting 
      General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  
 

 *     Fever, chills 
      Immune System Disorders  
 

 *     Anaphylaxis, allergic reaction 
      Skin and Subcutaneous System Disorders  
 

 *     Rash, pruritus 
      Data From Literature
   Although not reported specifically for Rabies Immune Globulin (Human), angioneurotic edema and nephrotic syndrome have been reported after injection of immune globulin (IG), a product similar in biochemical composition but without antirabies activity. (7)



   Reporting of Adverse Reactions

  Encourage reporting by patients, parents or guardians of all suspected adverse reactions occurring after Rabies Immune Globulin (Human) administration. Report suspected adverse reactions following treatment with Rabies Immune Globulin (Human) to the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.



 Also report these events to the Pharmacovigilance Department, Sanofi Pasteur Inc., Discovery Drive, Swiftwater, PA 18370 or call 1-800-822-2463.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
