<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="implanon" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions reported with the use of hormonal contraception are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Changes in Menstrual Bleeding Patterns [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Ectopic Pregnancies [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Thrombotic and Other Vascular Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Liver Disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common (&gt;=10%) adverse reactions reported in clinical trials were change in menstrual bleeding pattern, headache, vaginitis, weight increase, acne, breast pain, abdominal pain, and pharyngitis. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical trials including 942 women who were evaluated for safety, change in menstrual bleeding patterns (irregular menses) was the most common adverse reaction causing discontinuation of use of IMPLANON (11.1% of women).



 Adverse reactions that resulted in a rate of discontinuation of &gt;=1% are shown in  Table 3  .



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment in 1% or More of Subjects in Clinical Trials of IMPLANON 
 Adverse Reactions                                                               All StudiesN = 942       
  
 Bleeding Irregularities                                                                11.1%             
 Emotional Lability                                                                     2.3%              
 Weight Increase                                                                        2.3%              
 Headache                                                                               1.6%              
 Acne                                                                                   1.3%              
 Depression                                                                             1.0%              
        Other adverse reactions that were reported by at least 5% of subjects in clinical trials of IMPLANON are listed in  Table 4  .
 

 Table 4: Common Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=5% of Subjects in Clinical Trials with IMPLANON 
 Adverse Reaction                                                                 All StudiesN=942        
  
 Headache                                                                               24.9%             
 Vaginitis                                                                              14.5%             
 Weight increase                                                                        13.7%             
 Acne                                                                                   13.5%             
 Breast pain                                                                            12.8%             
 Abdominal pain                                                                         10.9%             
 Pharyngitis                                                                            10.5%             
 Leukorrhea                                                                             9.6%              
 Influenza-like symptoms                                                                7.6%              
 Dizziness                                                                              7.2%              
 Dysmenorrhea                                                                           7.2%              
 Back pain                                                                              6.8%              
 Emotional lability                                                                     6.5%              
 Nausea                                                                                 6.4%              
 Pain                                                                                   5.6%              
 Nervousness                                                                            5.6%              
 Depression                                                                             5.5%              
 Hypersensitivity                                                                       5.4%              
 Insertion site pain                                                                    5.2%              
        Implant site complications were reported by 3.6% of subjects during any of the assessments in clinical trials. Pain was the most frequent implant site complication, reported during and/or after insertion, occurring in 2.9% of subjects. Additionally, hematoma, redness, and swelling were reported by 0.1%, 0.3%, and 0.3% of patients, respectively  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of IMPLANON. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  constipation, diarrhea, flatulence, vomiting.



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  edema, fatigue, implant site reaction, pyrexia.



   Immune system disorders:  anaphylactic reactions



   Infections and infestations:  rhinitis, urinary tract infection.



   Investigations:  clinically relevant rise in blood pressure, weight decreased.



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  increased appetite.



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  arthralgia, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia.



   Nervous system disorders:  convulsions, migraine, somnolence.



   Pregnancy, puerperium and perinatal conditions:  ectopic pregnancy.



   Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety, insomnia, libido decreased.



   Renal and urinary disorders:  dysuria.



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  breast discharge, breast enlargement, ovarian cyst, pruritus genital, vulvovaginal discomfort.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  angioedema, aggravation of angioedema and/or aggravation of hereditary angioedema, alopecia, chloasma, hypertrichosis, pruritus, rash, seborrhea, urticaria.



   Vascular disorders:  hot flush.



 Complications related to insertion or removal of the implant reported include: bruising, slight local irritation, pain or itching, fibrosis at the implant site, paresthesia or paresthesia-like events, scarring and abscess. Expulsion or migration of the implant, have been reported, including rarely to the chest wall. In rare cases implants have been found within the vasculature including the pulmonary artery. Some cases of implants found within the pulmonary artery reported chest pain and/or dyspnea; others have been reported as asymptomatic  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . Surgical intervention might be necessary when removing the implant.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   The following information is based on experience with either IMPLANON, other progestin-only contraceptives, or experience with combination (estrogen plus progestin) oral contraceptives.  



    EXCERPT:    *  Insertion and removal complications: Pain, paresthesias, bleeding, hematoma, scarring or infection may occur. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Menstrual bleeding pattern: Counsel women regarding changes in bleeding frequency, intensity, or duration. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Ectopic pregnancies: Be alert to the possibility of an ectopic pregnancy in women using IMPLANON who become pregnant or complain of lower abdominal pain. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Thrombotic and other vascular events: The IMPLANON implant should be removed in the event of a thrombosis. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Liver disease: Remove the IMPLANON implant if jaundice occurs. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Elevated blood pressure: The IMPLANON implant should be removed if blood pressure rises significantly and becomes uncontrolled. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Carbohydrate and lipid metabolic effects: Monitor prediabetic and diabetic women using IMPLANON. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Complications of Insertion and Removal



  IMPLANON should be inserted subdermally so that it will be palpable after insertion, and this should be confirmed by palpation immediately after insertion. Failure to insert IMPLANON properly may go unnoticed unless it is palpated immediately after insertion. Undetected failure to insert the implant may lead to an unintended pregnancy. Complications related to insertion and removal procedures, such as pain, paresthesias, bleeding, hematoma, scarring or infection, may occur. Occasionally in post-marketing use, implant insertions have failed because the implant fell out of the needle or remained in the needle during insertion.



  If IMPLANON is inserted deeply (intramuscular or in the fascia), neural or vascular injury may occur. To reduce the risk of neural or vascular injury, IMPLANON should be inserted at the inner side of the non-dominant upper arm about 8-10 cm (3-4 inches) above the medial epicondyle of the humerus. IMPLANON should be inserted subdermally just under the skin, avoiding the sulcus (groove) between the biceps and triceps muscles and the large blood vessels and nerves that lie there in the neurovascular bundle deeper in the subcutaneous tissues. Deep insertions of IMPLANON have been associated with paraesthesia (due to neural injury) and migration of the implant (due to intramuscular or fascial insertion), and in a very few cases with intravascular insertion. If infection develops at the insertion site, start suitable treatment. If the infection persists, the implant should be removed. Incomplete insertions or infections may lead to expulsion.  



 Implant removal may be difficult or impossible if the implant is not inserted correctly, is inserted too deeply, not palpable, encased in fibrous tissue, or has migrated.



 There have been reports of migration of the implant within the arm from the insertion site, which may be related to a deep insertion. There also have been rare postmarketing reports of implants located within the vessels of the arm and the pulmonary artery, which may be related to deep insertions or intravascular insertion. In cases where the implant has migrated to the pulmonary artery, endovascular procedures may be needed for removal.



  If at any time the implant cannot be palpated, it should be localized and removal is recommended.  



  Exploratory surgery without knowledge of the exact location of the implant is strongly discouraged. Removal of deeply inserted implants should be conducted with caution in order to prevent injury to deeper neural or vascular structures in the arm and be performed by healthcare providers familiar with the anatomy of the arm. If the implant is located in the chest, healthcare providers familiar with the anatomy of the chest should be consulted. Failure to remove the implant may result in continued effects of etonogestrel, such as compromised fertility, ectopic pregnancy, or persistence or occurrence of a drug-related adverse event.  



    5.2 Changes in Menstrual Bleeding Patterns



  After starting IMPLANON, women are likely to have a change from their normal menstrual bleeding pattern. These may include changes in bleeding frequency (absent, less, more frequent or continuous), intensity (reduced or increased) or duration. In clinical trials, bleeding patterns ranged from amenorrhea (1 in 5 women) to frequent and/or prolonged bleeding (1 in 5 women). The bleeding pattern experienced during the first three months of IMPLANON use is broadly predictive of the future bleeding pattern for many women. Women should be counseled regarding the bleeding pattern changes they may experience so that they know what to expect. Abnormal bleeding should be evaluated as needed to exclude pathologic conditions or pregnancy.



 In clinical studies of IMPLANON, reports of changes in bleeding pattern were the most common reason for stopping treatment (11.1%). Irregular bleeding (10.8%) was the single most common reason women stopped treatment, while amenorrhea (0.3%) was cited less frequently. In these studies, women had an average of 17.7 days of bleeding or spotting every 90 days (based on 3,315 intervals of 90 days recorded by 780 patients). The percentages of patients having 0, 1-7, 8-21, or &gt;21 days of spotting or bleeding over a 90-day interval while using the IMPLANON implant are shown in  Table 1  .



 Table 1: Percentages of Patients with 0, 1 - 7, 8 - 21, or &gt;21 Days of Spotting or Bleeding Over a 90-Day Interval While Using IMPLANON 
 Total Days of Spotting or Bleeding   Percentage of Patients     
 Treatment Days 91-180(N = 745)  Treatment Days271-360(N = 657)  Treatment Days631-720(N = 547)   
  
 0 Days                                19%                        24%                        17%              
 1-7 Days                              15%                        13%                        12%              
 8-21 Days                             30%                        30%                        37%              
 &gt;21 Days                              35%                        33%                        35%              
          Bleeding patterns observed with use of IMPLANON for up to 2 years, and the proportion of 90-day intervals with these bleeding patterns, are summarized in  Table 2  .
 

 Table 2: Bleeding Patterns Using IMPLANON during the First 2 Years of UseBased on 3,315 recording periods of 90 day's duration in 780 women, excluding the first 90 days after implant insertion 
 BLEEDING PATTERNS     DEFINITIONS                                                            %             
  
 Infrequent            Less than three bleeding and/or spotting episodes in 90 days (excluding amenorrhea)          33.6           
 Amenorrhea            No bleeding and/or spotting in 90 days                                22.2           
 Prolonged             Any bleeding and/or spotting episode lasting more than 14 days in 90 days          17.7           
 Frequent              More than 5 bleeding and/or spotting episodes in 90 days              6.7            
         In case of undiagnosed, persistent, or recurrent abnormal vaginal bleeding, appropriate measures should be conducted to rule out malignancy.
 

    5.3 Ectopic Pregnancies



  As with all progestin-only contraceptive products, be alert to the possibility of an ectopic pregnancy among women using IMPLANON who become pregnant or complain of lower abdominal pain. Although ectopic pregnancies are uncommon among women using IMPLANON, a pregnancy that occurs in a woman using IMPLANON may be more likely to be ectopic than a pregnancy occurring in a woman using no contraception.



    5.4 Thrombotic and Other Vascular Events



  The use of combination hormonal contraceptives (progestin plus estrogen) increases the risk of vascular events, including arterial events (strokes and myocardial infarctions) or deep venous thrombotic events (venous thromboembolism, deep venous thrombosis, retinal vein thrombosis, and pulmonary embolism). IMPLANON is a progestin-only contraceptive. It is unknown whether this increased risk is applicable to etonogestrel alone. It is recommended, however, that women with risk factors known to increase the risk of venous and arterial thromboembolism be carefully assessed.



 There have been postmarketing reports of serious arterial thrombotic and venous thromboembolic events, including cases of pulmonary emboli (some fatal), deep vein thrombosis, myocardial infarction, and strokes, in women using IMPLANON. IMPLANON should be removed in the event of a thrombosis.



 Due to the risk of thromboembolism associated with pregnancy and immediately following delivery, IMPLANON should not be used prior to 21 days postpartum. Women with a history of thromboembolic disorders should be made aware of the possibility of a recurrence.



 Evaluate for retinal vein thrombosis immediately if there is unexplained loss of vision, proptosis, diplopia, papilledema, or retinal vascular lesions.



 Consider removal of the IMPLANON implant in case of long-term immobilization due to surgery or illness.



    5.5 Ovarian Cysts



  If follicular development occurs, atresia of the follicle is sometimes delayed, and the follicle may continue to grow beyond the size it would attain in a normal cycle. Generally, these enlarged follicles disappear spontaneously. On rare occasion, surgery may be required.



    5.6 Carcinoma of the Breast and Reproductive Organs



  Women who currently have or have had breast cancer should not use hormonal contraception because breast cancer may be hormonally sensitive [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . Some studies suggest that the use of combination hormonal contraceptives might increase the incidence of breast cancer; however, other studies have not confirmed such findings.



 Some studies suggest that the use of combination hormonal contraceptives is associated with an increase in the risk of cervical cancer or intraepithelial neoplasia. However, there is controversy about the extent to which such findings are due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors.



 Women with a family history of breast cancer or who develop breast nodules should be carefully monitored.



    5.7 Liver Disease



  Disturbances of liver function may necessitate the discontinuation of hormonal contraceptive use until markers of liver function return to normal. Remove IMPLANON if jaundice develops.



 Hepatic adenomas are associated with combination hormonal contraceptives use. An estimate of the attributable risk is 3.3 cases per 100,000 for combination hormonal contraceptives users. It is not known whether a similar risk exists with progestin-only methods like IMPLANON.



 The progestin in IMPLANON may be poorly metabolized in women with liver impairment. Use of IMPLANON in women with active liver disease or liver cancer is contraindicated [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.8 Weight Gain



  In clinical studies, mean weight gain in US IMPLANON users was 2.8 pounds after 1 year and 3.7 pounds after 2 years. How much of the weight gain was related to the implant is unknown. In studies, 2.3% of the users reported weight gain as the reason for having the implant removed.



    5.9 Elevated Blood Pressure



  Women with a history of hypertension-related diseases or renal disease should be discouraged from using hormonal contraception. For women with well-controlled hypertension, use of IMPLANON can be considered. Women with hypertension using IMPLANON should be closely monitored. lf sustained hypertension develops during the use of IMPLANON, or if a significant increase in blood pressure does not respond adequately to antihypertensive therapy, IMPLANON should be removed.



    5.10 Gallbladder Disease



  Studies suggest a small increased relative risk of developing gallbladder disease among combination hormonal contraceptive users. It is not known whether a similar risk exists with progestin-only methods like IMPLANON.



    5.11 Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects



  Use of IMPLANON may induce mild insulin resistance and small changes in glucose concentrations of unknown clinical significance. Carefully monitor prediabetic and diabetic women using IMPLANON.



 Women who are being treated for hyperlipidemia should be followed closely if they elect to use IMPLANON. Some progestins may elevate LDL levels and may render the control of hyperlipidemia more difficult.



    5.12 Depressed Mood



  Women with a history of depressed mood should be carefully observed. Consideration should be given to removing IMPLANON in patients who become significantly depressed.



    5.13 Return to Ovulation



  In clinical trials with IMPLANON, the etonogestrel levels in blood decreased below sensitivity of the assay by one week after removal of the implant. In addition, pregnancies were observed to occur as early as 7 to 14 days after removal. Therefore, a woman should re-start contraception immediately after removal of the implant if continued contraceptive protection is desired.



    5.14 Fluid Retention



  Hormonal contraceptives may cause some degree of fluid retention. They should be prescribed with caution, and only with careful monitoring, in patients with conditions which might be aggravated by fluid retention. It is unknown if IMPLANON causes fluid retention.



    5.15 Contact Lenses



  Contact lens wearers who develop visual changes or changes in lens tolerance should be assessed by an ophthalmologist.



    5.16 In Situ  Broken or Bent Implant



   There have been reports of broken or bent implants while in the patient's arm. Based on in vitro  data, when the implant is broken or bent, the release rate of etonogestrel may be slightly increased.  



  When an implant is removed, it is important to remove it in its entirety [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  .  



    5.17 Monitoring



  A woman who is using IMPLANON should have a yearly visit with her healthcare provider for a blood pressure check and for other indicated health care.



    5.18 Drug-Laboratory Test Interactions



  Sex hormone-binding globulin concentrations may be decreased for the first 6 months after IMPLANON insertion followed by a gradual recovery. Thyroxine concentrations may initially be slightly decreased followed by gradual recovery to baseline.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
