<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="increlex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    The following serious adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:  



 *  Hypoglycemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ,  Adverse Reaction (6.1)  ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions, including Anaphylaxis [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ,  Adverse Reaction (6.1)  ] 
 *  Intracranial hypertension (IH) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ,  Adverse Reaction (6.1  ] 
 *  Tonsillar and Adenoidal Hypertrophy and related complications [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ,  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ] 
      EXCERPT:   Common INCRELEX  (r)  -related adverse reactions in clinical trials include: hypoglycemia (  5.1  ,  6.1  ), local and systemic hypersensitivity (  5.2  ,  6.1  ,  6.2  ), tonsillar hypertrophy (  5.4  ,  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ipsen Biopharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-866-837-2422 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical studies of 71 subjects with Primary IGFD treated for a mean duration of 3.9 years and representing 274 subject-years, no subjects withdrew from any clinical study because of adverse reactions. Adverse reactions to INCRELEX  (r)  treatment that occurred in 5% or more of these study participants are listed below by organ class.



 *      Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders: hypoglycemia 
 *      General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions: lipohypertrophy, bruising 
 *      Infections and Infestations: otitis media, serous otitis media 
 *      Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders: snoring, tonsillar hypertrophy 
 *      Nervous System Disorders: headache, dizziness, convulsions 
 *      Gastrointestinal Disorders: vomiting 
 *      Ear and Labyrinth Disorders: hypoacusis, fluid in middle ear, ear pain, abnormal tympanometry 
 *      Cardiac Disorders: cardiac murmur 
 *      Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders: arthralgia, pain in extremity 
 *      Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders: thymus hypertrophy 
 *      Surgical and Medical Procedures: ear tube insertion 
    Hypoglycemia was reported by 30 subjects (42%) at least once during their course of therapy. Most cases of hypoglycemia were mild or moderate in severity. Five subjects had severe hypoglycemia (requiring assistance and treatment) on one or more occasion and 4 subjects experienced hypoglycemic seizures/loss of consciousness on one or more occasion. Of the 30 subjects reporting hypoglycemia, 14 (47%) had a history of hypoglycemia prior to treatment. The frequency of hypoglycemia was highest in the first month of treatment, and episodes were more frequent in younger children. Symptomatic hypoglycemia was generally avoided when a meal or snack was consumed either shortly (i.e., 20 minutes) before or after the administration of INCRELEX  (r)  .
 

 Tonsillar hypertrophy was noted in 11 (15%) subjects in the first 1 to 2 years of therapy with lesser tonsillar growth in subsequent years. Tonsillectomy or tonsillectomy/adenoidectomy was performed in 7 subjects; 3 of these had obstructive sleep apnea, which resolved after the procedure in all three cases.



 Intracranial hypertension occurred in three subjects. In two subjects the events resolved without interruption of INCRELEX  (r)  treatment. INCRELEX  (r)  treatment was discontinued in the third subject and resumed later at a lower dose without recurrence.



 Mild elevations in the serum AST and LDH were found in a significant proportion of patients before and during treatment. Rise in levels of these serum enzymes did not lead to treatment discontinuation. ALT elevations were occasionally noted during treatment.



 Renal and splenic lengths (measured by ultrasound) increased rapidly on INCRELEX  (r)  treatment during the first years of therapy. This lengthening slowed down subsequently; though in some patients, renal and/or splenic length reached or surpassed the 95  th  percentile. Renal function (as defined by serum creatinine and calculated creatinine clearance) was normal in all patients, irrespective of renal growth.



 Elevations in cholesterol and triglycerides to above the upper limit of normal were observed before and during treatment.



 Echocardiographic evidence of cardiomegaly/valvulopathy was observed in a few individuals without associated clinical symptoms. The relation of these cardiac changes to drug treatment cannot be assessed due to underlying disease and the lack of a control group.



 Thickening of the soft tissues of the face was observed in several patients and should be monitored during INCRELEX  (r)  treatment.



 As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. Anti-IGF-1 antibodies were present at one or more of the periodic assessments in 14 of 23 children with Primary IGFD treated for 2 years. However, no clinical consequences of these antibodies were observed (e.g., attenuation of growth). The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to INCRELEX  (r)  with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of INCRELEX  (r)  . Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Systemic hypersensitivity:  anaphylaxis, generalized urticaria, angioedema, dyspnea  



 In the post-marketing setting, the frequency of cases indicative of anaphylaxis was estimated to be 0.3%. Symptoms included hives, angioedema, and dyspnea, and some patients required hospitalization. Upon re-administration, symptoms did not re-occur in all patients.



 Local allergic reactions at the injection site:  pruritus, urticaria.  



 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  alopecia, hair texture abnormal.  



 General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions:  injection site reactions (e.g. erythema, pain, haematoma, haemorrhage, induration, rash, swelling).  



 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  osteonecrosis/avascular necrosis (occasionally associated with slipped capital femoral epiphysis)  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  INCRELEX  (r)  should be administered shortly before or after a meal or snack, because it has insulin-like hypoglycemic effects. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions, including Anaphylaxis: A low number of cases indicative of anaphylaxis requiring hospitalization have been reported. Parents and patients should be informed that such reactions are possible and that if a systemic allergic reaction occurs, treatment should be interrupted and prompt medical attention should be sought. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Intracranial Hypertension : Funduscopic examination is recommended at the initiation and periodically during the course of INCRELEX  (r)  therapy. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Lymphoid Tissue Hypertrophy (tonsillar/adenoidal hypertrophy): Patients should have periodic examinations to rule out potential complications and receive appropriate treatment if necessary. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis (SCFE): Evaluate any child with onset of a limp or hip/knee pain for possible SCFE. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Progression of Scoliosis: Monitor any child with scoliosis for progression of the spine curve. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypoglycemia



  Because INCRELEX  (r)  has insulin-like hypoglycemic effects it should be administered shortly before or after (+/- 20 minutes) a meal or snack. Glucose monitoring and INCRELEX  (r)  dose titration are recommended until a well tolerated dose is established (see  Dosage 2.1  ) and subsequently as medically indicated. Special attention should be paid to small children because their oral intake may not be consistent. Patients should avoid engaging in any high-risk activities (e.g., driving, etc.) within 2 to 3 hours after dosing, particularly during the initiation of INCRELEX  (r)  treatment until tolerability and a stable dose have been established [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]. INCRELEX  (r)  should not be administered when the meal or snack is omitted.  The dose of INCRELEX  (r)  should never be increased to make up for one or more omitted doses.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions, including Anaphylaxis



  Allergic reactions to INCRELEX  (r)  have been reported post-marketing. They range from localized (injection site) reactions to systemic reactions, including anaphylaxis requiring hospitalization. Parents and patients should be informed that such reactions are possible and that if a systemic allergic reaction occurs, treatment should be interrupted and prompt medical attention should be sought. [see  Contraindications (4.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1,    6.2)  ]



    5.3 Intracranial Hypertension



  Intracranial hypertension (IH) with papilledema, visual changes, headache, nausea and/or vomiting have occurred in patients treated with INCRELEX  (r)  . IH-associated signs and symptoms resolved after interruption of dosing. Funduscopic examination is recommended at the initiation and periodically during the course of INCRELEX  (r)  therapy. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]



    5.4 Lymphoid Tissue Hypertrophy



  Lymphoid tissue (e.g., tonsillar and adenoidal) hypertrophy associated with complications, such as snoring, sleep apnea, and chronic middle-ear effusions have been reported with the use of INCRELEX  (r)  . Patients should have periodic examinations to rule out such potential complications and receive appropriate treatment if necessary. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]



    5.5 Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis



  Slipped capital femoral epiphysis can occur in patients who experience rapid growth. Any pediatric patient with the onset of a limp or complaints of hip or knee pain during INCRELEX  (r)  therapy should be carefully evaluated.



    5.6 Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis



  Progression of scoliosis may occur in patients who experience rapid growth. Because INCRELEX  (r)  increases growth rate, patients with a history of scoliosis who are treated with INCRELEX  (r)  should be monitored for progression of scoliosis.



    5.7 Benzyl Alcohol



  Benzyl alcohol, a component of this product, has been associated with serious adverse events and death, particularly in pediatric patients. The "gasping syndrome," (characterized by central nervous system depression, metabolic acidosis, gasping respirations, and high levels of benzyl alcohol and its metabolites found in the blood and urine) has been associated with benzyl alcohol dosages &gt;99 mg/kg/day in neonates and low-birth weight neonates. Additional symptoms may include gradual neurological deterioration, seizures, intracranial hemorrhage, hematologic abnormalities, skin breakdown, hepatic and renal failure, hypotension, bradycardia, and cardiovascular collapse. Practitioners administering this and other medications containing benzyl alcohol should consider the combined daily metabolic load of benzyl alcohol from all sources.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
