<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="indocin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The adverse reactions for Capsules INDOCIN listed in the following table have been arranged into two groups: (1) incidence greater than 1%; and (2) incidence less than 1%. The incidence for group (1) was obtained from 33 double-blind controlled clinical trials reported in the literature (1,092 patients). The incidence for group (2) was based on reports in clinical trials, in the literature, and on voluntary reports since marketing. The probability of a causal relationship exists between INDOCIN and these adverse reactions, some of which have been reported only rarely.



 The adverse reactions reported with Capsules INDOCIN may also occur with use of the suspension. 




   Incidence greater than 1%           Incidence less than 1%            
  
   GASTROINTESTINAL                   
  nauseaReactions occurring in 3% to 9% of patients treated with INDOCIN. (Those reactions occurring in less than 3% of the patients are unmarked.) with or without vomiting  dyspepsia (including indigestion, heartburn and epigastric pain)  diarrhea  abdominal distress or pain  constipation    anorexia  bloating (includes distension)  flatulence  peptic ulcer  gastroenteritis  rectal bleeding  proctitis  single or multiple ulcerations, including perforation and hemorrhage of the esophagus, stomach, duodenum or small and large intestines  intestinal ulceration associated with stenosis and obstruction    gastrointestinal bleeding without obvious ulcer formation and perforation of pre-existing sigmoid lesions (diverticulum, carcinoma, etc.)  development of ulcerative colitis and regional ileitis  ulcerative stomatitis  toxic hepatitis and jaundice (some fatal cases have been reported)  intestinal strictures (diaphragms)    
   CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM             
  headache (11.7%)  dizziness  vertigo  somnolence  depression and fatigue (including malaise and listlessness)    anxiety (includes nervousness)  muscle weakness  involuntary muscle movements  insomnia  muzziness  psychic disturbances including psychotic episodes  mental confusion  drowsiness    light-headedness  syncope  paresthesia  aggravation of epilepsy and parkinsonism  depersonalization  coma  peripheral neuropathy  convulsion  dysarthria    
   SPECIAL SENSES                     
  tinnitus                            ocular - corneal deposits and retinal disturbances, including those of the macula, have been reported in some patients on prolonged therapy with INDOCIN    blurred vision  diplopia  hearing disturbances, deafness    
   CARDIOVASCULAR                     
  none                                hypertension  hypotension  tachycardia  chest pain    congestive heart failure  arrhythmia; palpitations    
   METABOLIC                          
  none                                edema  weight gain  fluid retention  flushing or sweating    hyperglycemia  glycosuria  hyperkalemia    
   INTEGUMENTARY                      
  none                                pruritus  rash; urticaria  petechiae or ecchymosis    exfoliative dermatitis  erythema nodosum  loss of hair  Stevens-Johnson syndrome  erythema multiforme  toxic epidermal necrolysis    
   HEMATOLOGIC                        
  none                                leukopenia  bone marrow depression  anemia secondary to obvious or occult gastrointestinal bleeding    aplastic anemia  hemolytic anemia  agranulocytosis  thrombocytopenic purpura  disseminated intravascular coagulation    
   HYPERSENSITIVITY                   
  none                                acute anaphylaxis  acute respiratory distress  rapid fall in blood pressure resembling a shock-like state  angioedema    dyspnea  asthma  purpura  angiitis  pulmonary edema  fever    
   GENITOURINARY                      
  none                                hematuria  vaginal bleeding  proteinuria  nephrotic syndrome  interstitial nephritis    BUN elevation  renal insufficiency, including renal failure    
   MISCELLANEOUS                      
  none                                epistaxis  breast changes, including enlargement and tenderness, or gynecomastia                                       
           Causal relationship unknown:  
 

 Other reactions have been reported but occurred under circumstances where a causal relationship could not be established. However, in these rarely reported events, the possibility cannot be excluded. Therefore, these observations are being listed to serve as alerting information to physicians:



   Cardiovascular  : Thrombophlebitis



   Hematologic  : Although there have been several reports of leukemia, the supporting information is weak



   Genitourinary  : Urinary frequency



 A rare occurrence of fulminant necrotizing fasciitis, particularly in association with Group Abeta hemolytic streptococcus, has been described in persons treated with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents, including indomethacin, sometimes with fatal outcome (see also  PRECAUTIONS, General  ).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at a greater risk. (See WARNINGS.) 
 *  INDOCIN is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery (see WARNINGS). 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events. (See WARNINGS.) 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
