<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="infanrix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Rates of injection site reactions (pain, redness, swelling) ranged from 10% to 53%, depending on reaction and dose number, and were highest following doses 4 and 5. Fever was common (20% to 30%) following doses 1-3. Other common solicited adverse events were drowsiness, irritability/fussiness, and loss of appetite, reported in approximately 15% to 60% of subjects, depending on event and dose number. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. There is the possibility that broad use of INFANRIX could reveal adverse reactions not observed in clinical trials.



 Approximately 95,000 doses of INFANRIX have been administered in clinical studies. In these studies, 29,243 infants have received INFANRIX in primary series studies, 6,081 children have received a fourth consecutive dose of INFANRIX, 1,764 children have received a fifth consecutive dose of INFANRIX, and 559 children have received a dose of INFANRIX following 3 doses of PEDIARIX.



   Solicited Adverse Events:  In a US study, 335 infants received INFANRIX, ENGERIX-B  (r)  [Hepatitis B Vaccine (Recombinant)], inactivated poliovirus vaccine (IPV, Sanofi Pasteur SA), Haemophilus b (Hib) conjugate vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.), and pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate (PCV7) vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.) concomitantly at separate sites. All vaccines were administered at 2, 4, and 6 months of age. Data on solicited local reactions and general adverse events were collected by parents using standardized diary cards for 4 consecutive days following each vaccine dose (i.e., day of vaccination and the next 3 days) (Table 1). Among subjects, 69% were White, 16% were Hispanic, 8% were Black, 4% were Asian, and 2% were of other racial/ethnic groups.



 Table 1. Solicited Local Reactions and General Adverse Events (%) Occurring Within 4 Days of Vaccinationa With Separate Concomitant Administration of INFANRIX, ENGERIX-B, IPV, Haemophilus  b (Hib) Conjugate Vaccine, and Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV7) (Modified Intent To Treat Cohort) 
                                     INFANRIX, ENGERIX-B, IPV, Hib Vaccine, &amp; PCV7    
                                     Dose 1               Dose 2               Dose 3               
  Localb                                                                                            
  N                                  335                  323                  315                  
  Pain, any                          31.9                 30.0                 29.8                 
  Pain, grade 2 or 3                 9.0                  8.7                  8.9                  
  Pain, grade 3                      2.7                  1.5                  1.3                  
  Redness, any                       18.2                 32.8                 39.0                 
  Redness, &gt;20 mm                    0.3                  0.0                  1.9                  
  Swelling, any                      9.6                  20.4                 24.8                 
  Swelling, &gt;20 mm                   0.6                  0.0                  1.3                  
  General                                                                                           
  N                                  333                  321                  311                  
  Feverc (&gt;=100.4 degrees F)         19.8                 30.2                 23.8                 
  Feverc (&gt;101.3 degrees F)          4.5                  9.7                  5.8                  
  Feverc (&gt;102.2 degrees F)          0.3                  3.1                  2.3                  
  Feverc (&gt;103.1 degrees F)          0.0                  0.3                  0.3                  
  N                                  335                  323                  315                  
  Drowsiness, any                    54.0                 48.3                 38.4                 
  Drowsiness, grade 2 or 3           17.6                 12.4                 11.1                 
  Drowsiness, grade 3                3.6                  0.6                  1.9                  
  Irritability/Fussiness, any        61.5                 61.6                 56.5                 
  Irritability/Fussiness, grade 2 or 3    19.4                 21.1                 19.4                 
  Irritability/Fussiness, grade 3    3.9                  3.4                  3.2                  
  Loss of appetite, any              27.8                 26.6                 23.8                 
  Loss of appetite, grade 2 or 3     5.1                  3.4                  5.4                  
  Loss of appetite, grade 3          0.6                  0.3                  0.0                  
          Hib conjugate vaccine and PCV7 manufactured by Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc. IPV manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA.
 

 Modified intent to treat cohort = all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.



 N = number of infants for whom at least one symptom sheet was completed; for fever, numbers exclude missing temperature recordings or tympanic measurements.



 Grade 2: pain defined as cried/protested on touch; drowsiness defined as interfered with normal daily activities; irritability/fussiness defined as crying more than usual/interfered with normal daily activities; loss of appetite defined as eating less than usual/interfered with normal daily activities.



 Grade 3: pain defined as cried when limb was moved/spontaneously painful; drowsiness defined as prevented normal daily activities; irritability/fussiness defined as crying that could not be comforted/prevented normal daily activities; loss of appetite defined as no eating at all.



   a  Within 4 days of vaccination defined as day of vaccination and the next 3 days.



   b  Local reactions at the injection site for INFANRIX.



   c  Axillary temperatures increased by 1 degrees C and oral temperatures increased by 0.5 degrees C to derive equivalent rectal temperature.



 In a US study, the safety of a booster dose of INFANRIX was evaluated in children 15 to 18 months of age whose previous 3 DTaP doses were with INFANRIX (N = 251) or PEDIARIX (N = 559). Vaccines administered concurrently with the fourth dose of INFANRIX included measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR) vaccine (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.), varicella vaccine (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.), pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate (PCV7) vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.), and any US-licensed Hib conjugate vaccine; these were given concomitantly in 13.2%, 6.3%, 37.4%, and 41.2% of subjects, respectively. Data on solicited adverse events were collected by parents using standardized diary cards for 4 consecutive days following each vaccine dose (i.e., day of vaccination and the next 3 days) (Table 2). Among subjects, 85% were White, 6% were Hispanic, 6% were Black, 1% were Asian, and 2% were of other racial/ethnic groups.



 Table 2. Solicited Local Reactions and General Adverse Events (%) Occurring Within 4 Days of Vaccinationa With INFANRIX Administered as the Fourth Dose Following 3 Previous Doses of INFANRIX or PEDIARIX (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                           Group Primed With INFANRIXb  N = 247    Group Primed With PEDIARIXc  N = 553    
  Locald                                                                                                    
  Pain, any                                44.5                             48.3                            
  Pain, grade 2 or 3                       19.0                             18.6                            
  Pain, grade 3                            3.6                              3.4                             
  Redness, any                             48.2                             49.9                            
  Redness, &gt;20 mm                          6.1                              6.0                             
  Swelling, any                            32.8                             32.7                            
  Swelling, &gt;20 mm                         3.6                              5.2                             
  Increase in mid-thigh circumference, any    33.2                             26.2                            
  Increase in mid-thigh circumference, &gt;40 mm    0.0                              1.3                             
  General                                                                                                   
  Fevere (&gt;99.5 degrees F)                 8.9                              15.4                            
  Fevere (&gt;100.4 degrees F)                4.5                              6.7                             
  Fevere (&gt;101.3 degrees F)                2.0                              2.0                             
  Drowsiness, any                          35.6                             31.3                            
  Drowsiness, grade 2 or 3                 9.3                              6.7                             
  Drowsiness, grade 3                      2.4                              1.3                             
  Irritability, any                        52.2                             53.9                            
  Irritability, grade 2 or 3               18.2                             19.7                            
  Irritability, grade 3                    3.2                              1.4                             
  Loss of appetite, any                    24.7                             23.3                            
  Loss of appetite, grade 2 or 3           5.3                              4.9                             
  Loss of appetite, grade 3                2.4                              0.5                             
         Total Vaccinated Cohort = all subjects who received a dose of study vaccine.
 

 N = number of subjects for whom at least one symptom sheet was completed.



 Grade 2: pain defined as cried/protested on touch; drowsiness defined as interfered with normal daily activities; irritability defined as crying more than usual/interfered with normal daily activities; loss of appetite defined as eating less than usual/no effect on normal daily activities.



 Grade 3: pain defined as cried when limb was moved/spontaneously painful; drowsiness defined as prevented normal daily activities; irritability defined as crying that could not be comforted/prevented normal daily activities; loss of appetite defined as eating less than usual/interfered with normal daily activities.



   a  Within 4 days of vaccination defined as day of vaccination and the next 3 days.



   b  Received INFANRIX, ENGERIX-B, IPV (Sanofi Pasteur SA), PCV7 vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.), and Hib conjugate vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.) at 2, 4, and 6 months of age.



   c  Received PEDIARIX, PCV7 vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.), and Hib conjugate vaccine (Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc.) at 2, 4, and 6 months of age or PCV7 vaccine 2 weeks later.



   d  Local reactions at the injection site for INFANRIX.



   e  Axillary temperatures.



 In a US study, the safety of a fifth consecutive dose of INFANRIX coadministered at separate sites with a fourth dose of IPV (Sanofi Pasteur SA) and a second dose of MMR vaccine (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.) was evaluated in 1,053 children 4 to 6 years of age. Data on solicited adverse events were collected by parents using standardized diary cards for 4 consecutive days following each vaccine dose (i.e., day of vaccination and the next 3 days) (Table 3). Among subjects, 43% were White, 18% Hispanic, 15% Asian, 7% Black, and 17% were of other racial/ethnic groups.



 Table 3. Solicited Local Reactions and General Adverse Events (%) Occurring Within 4 Days of Vaccinationa With a Fifth Consecutive Dose of INFANRIX When Coadministered With IPV and MMR Vaccine (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
  Localb                                 N = 1,039-1,043     
  Pain, any                              53.3                
  Pain, grade 2 or 3c                    12.0                
  Pain, grade 3c                         0.6                 
  Redness, any                           36.6                
  Redness, &gt;=50 mm                       20.0                
  Redness, &gt;=110 mm                      4.1                 
  Arm circumference increase, any        37.8                
  Arm circumference increase, &gt;20 mm     7.4                 
  Arm circumference increase, &gt;30 mm     3.2                 
  Swelling, any                          27.0                
  Swelling, &gt;=50 mm                      11.5                
  Swelling, &gt;=110 mm                     1.8                 
  General                                N = 993-1,036       
  Drowsiness, any                        17.5                
  Drowsiness, grade 3d                   0.8                 
  Fever, &gt;=99.5 degrees F                14.8                
  Fever, &gt;100.4 degrees F                4.4                 
  Fever, &gt;102.2 degrees F                1.1                 
  Fever, &gt;104 degrees F                  0.0                 
  Loss of appetite, any                  16.0                
  Loss of appetite, grade 3e             0.6                 
         IPV manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur SA. MMR vaccine manufactured by Merck &amp; Co., Inc.
 

 Total Vaccinated Cohort = all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available.



 N = number of children with evaluable data for the events listed.



   a  Within 4 days of vaccination defined as day of vaccination and the next 3 days.



   b  Local reactions at the injection site for INFANRIX.



   c  Grade 2 defined as painful when the limb was moved; Grade 3 defined as preventing normal daily activities.



   d  Grade 3 defined as preventing normal daily activities.



   e  Grade 3 defined as not eating at all.



 In the US booster immunization studies in which INFANRIX was administered as the fourth or fifth dose in the DTaP series following previous doses with INFANRIX or PEDIARIX, large swelling reactions of the limb injected with INFANRIX were assessed.



 In the fourth dose study, a large swelling reaction was defined as injection site swelling with a diameter of &gt;50 mm, a &gt;50 mm increase in the mid-thigh circumference compared to the pre-vaccination measurement, and/or any diffuse swelling that interfered with or prevented daily activities. The overall incidence of large swelling reactions occurring within 4 days (Day 0-Day 3) following INFANRIX was 2.3%.



 In the fifth dose study, a large swelling reaction was defined as swelling that involved &gt;50% of the injected upper arm length and that was associated with a &gt;30 mm increase in mid-upper arm circumference within 4 days following vaccination. The incidence of large swelling reactions following the fifth consecutive dose of INFANRIX was 1.0%.



   Less Common and Serious General Adverse Events:  Selected adverse events reported from a double-blind, randomized Italian clinical efficacy trial involving 4,696 children administered INFANRIX or 4,678 children administered whole-cell DTP vaccine (DTwP) (manufactured by Connaught Laboratories, Inc.) as a 3-dose primary series are shown in Table     4. The incidence of rectal temperature &gt;=104 degrees F, hypotonic-hyporesponsive episodes and persistent crying &gt;=3 hours following administration of INFANRIX was significantly less than that following administration of whole-cell DTP vaccine.



 Table 4. Selected Adverse Events Occurring Within 48 Hours Following Vaccination With INFANRIX or Whole-Cell DTP in Italian Infants at 2, 4, or 6 Months of Age 
  Event                                 INFANRIX  (N = 13,761 Doses)    Whole-Cell DTP Vaccine  (N = 13,520 Doses)    
  Number                                Rate/1,000 Doses    Number               Rate/1,000 Doses    
  Fever (&gt;=104 degrees F)ab             5           0.36                 32          2.4                  
  Hypotonic-hyporesponsive episodec     0           0                    9           0.67                 
  Persistent crying &gt;=3 hoursa          6           0.44                 54          4.0                  
  Seizuresd                             1e          0.07                 3f          0.22                 
             a    P   &lt;0.001.
 

   b  Rectal temperatures.



   c    P   = 0.002.



   d  Not statistically significant at  P   &lt;0.05.



   e  Maximum rectal temperature within 72 hours of vaccination = 103.1 degrees F.



   f  Maximum rectal temperature within 72 hours of vaccination = 99.5 degrees F, 101.3 degrees F, and 102.2 degrees F.



 In a German safety study that enrolled 22,505 infants (66,867 doses of INFANRIX administered as a 3-dose primary series at 3, 4, and 5 months of age), all subjects were monitored for unsolicited adverse events that occurred within 28 days following vaccination using report cards. In a subset of subjects (N = 2,457), these cards were standardized diaries which solicited specific adverse events that occurred within 8 days of each vaccination in addition to unsolicited adverse events which occurred from enrollment until approximately 30 days following the third vaccination. Cards from the whole cohort were returned at subsequent visits and were supplemented by spontaneous reporting by parents and a medical history after the first and second doses of vaccine. In the subset of 2,457, adverse events following the third dose of vaccine were reported via standardized diaries and spontaneous reporting at a follow-up visit. Adverse events in the remainder of the cohort were reported via report cards which were returned by mail approximately 28 days after the third dose of vaccine. Adverse events (rates per 1,000 doses) occurring within 7 days following any of the first 3 doses included: unusual crying (0.09), febrile seizure (0.0), afebrile seizure (0.13), and hypotonic-hyporesponsive episodes (0.01).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to reports in clinical trials, worldwide voluntary reports of adverse events received for INFANRIX since market introduction are listed below. This list includes serious events and events which have a plausible causal connection to INFANRIX. These adverse events were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size; therefore, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccination.



   Infections and Infestations:  Bronchitis, cellulitis, respiratory tract infection.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Lymphadenopathy, thrombocytopenia.



   Immune System Disorders:  Anaphylactic reaction, hypersensitivity.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Encephalopathy, headache, hypotonia, syncope.



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  Ear pain.



   Cardiac Disorders:  Cyanosis.



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  Apnea, cough.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Angioedema, erythema, pruritus, rash, urticaria.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Fatigue, injection site induration, injection site reaction, Sudden Infant Death Syndrome.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurs within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the decision to give INFANRIX should be based on potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
 *    The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including INFANRIX. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (  5.3  ) 
 *    If temperature &gt;=105 degrees F, collapse or shock-like state, or persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours have occurred within 48 hours after receipt of a pertussis-containing vaccine, or if seizures have occurred within 3 days after receipt of a pertussis-containing vaccine, the decision to give INFANRIX should be based on potential benefits and risks. (  5.4  ) 
 *    For children at higher risk for seizures, an antipyretic may be administered at the time of vaccination with INFANRIX. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. Decisions about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including INFANRIX, to infants born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status, and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurs within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the decision to give any tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine, including INFANRIX, should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and possible risks. When a decision is made to withhold tetanus toxoid, other available vaccines should be given, as indicated.



    5.2 Latex



  The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals.



    5.3 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including INFANRIX. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.



    5.4 Adverse Events Following Prior Pertussis Vaccination



  If any of the following events occur in temporal relation to receipt of a pertussis-containing vaccine, the decision to give any pertussis-containing vaccine, including INFANRIX, should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and possible risks:



 *    Temperature of &gt;=40.5 degrees C (105 degrees F) within 48 hours not due to another identifiable cause; 
 *    Collapse or shock-like state (hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode) within 48 hours; 
 *    Persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours, occurring within 48 hours; 
 *    Seizures with or without fever occurring within 3 days. 
       5.5 Children at Risk for Seizures
 

  For children at higher risk for seizures than the general population, an appropriate antipyretic may be administered at the time of vaccination with a pertussis-containing vaccine, including INFANRIX, and for the ensuing 24 hours to reduce the possibility of post-vaccination fever.



    5.6 Apnea in Premature Infants



  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. Decisions about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including INFANRIX, to infants born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status, and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination.



    5.7 Preventing and Managing Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Prior to administration, the healthcare provider should review the patient's immunization history for possible vaccine hypersensitivity. Epinephrine and other appropriate agents used for the control of immediate allergic reactions must be immediately available should an acute anaphylactic reaction occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
