<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="infumorph" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

   
  IMPROPER OR ERRONEOUS SUBSTITUTION OF INFUMORPH 200 or 500 (10 or 25 mg/mL, respectively) FOR REGULAR DURAMORPH (0.5 or 1 mg/mL) IS LIKELY TO RESULT IN SERIOUS OVERDOSAGE, LEADING TO SEIZURES, RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION AND, POSSIBLY, FATAL OUTCOME.    
       The most serious adverse experiences encountered during continuous intrathecal or epidural infusion of INFUMORPH are respiratory depression, myoclonus, and formation of inflammatory masses.
 

 *  Single-dose neuraxial administration may result in acute or delayed respiratory depression for periods at least as long as 24 hours. Severe respiratory depression, potentially life-threatening, can result from technical errors during refill, e.g., injection of INFUMORPH outside the filling port, unintentional injection into the direct bypass-dosing port featured on some devices or local infiltration.  
 *   Tolerance and myoclonus: See    WARNINGS   for discussion of these and related hazards. 
 *   Inflammatory masses: See   WARNINGS   . 
    While low doses of intravenously administered morphine have little effect on cardiovascular stability, high doses are excitatory, resulting from  sympathetic hyperactivity  and increase in circulating catecholamines. Excitation of the central nervous system, resulting in  convulsions  , may accompany high doses of morphine given intravenously.  Dysphoric reactions  may occur after any size dose and  toxic psychoses  have been reported.
 

     Pruritus:  

  Single-dose epidural or intrathecal administration is accompanied by a high incidence of  pruritus  that is dose-related but not confined to the site of administration. Pruritus, following continuous infusion of epidural or intrathecal morphine, is occasionally reported in the literature; these reactions are poorly understood as to their cause.



     Urinary Retention:  

  Urinary retention, which may persist 10 to 20 hours following single epidural or intrathecal administration, is a frequent side effect and must be anticipated primarily in male patients, with a somewhat lower incidence in females. Also frequently reported in the literature is the occurrence of urinary retention during the first several days of hospitalization for the initiation of continuous intrathecal or epidural morphine therapy. Patients who develop urinary retention have responded to cholinomimetic treatment and/or judicious use of catheters (see    PRECAUTIONS    ).



     Constipation:  

  Constipation is frequently encountered during continuous infusion of morphine; this can usually be managed by conventional therapy.



     Headache:  

  Lumbar puncture-type headache is encountered in a significant minority of cases for several days following intrathecal catheter implantation; this, generally, responds to bed rest and/or other conventional therapy.



     Peripheral Edema:  

  There are several reports of peripheral edema, including unexplained genital swelling in male patients, following infusion-device implant surgery.



     Other:  

  Other adverse experiences reported following morphine therapy include -  Dizziness, euphoria, anxiety, depression of cough reflex, interference with thermal regulation  and  oliguria.  Evidence of histamine release such as  urticaria, wheals  and/or  local tissue irritation  may occur.



 Pruritus, nausea/vomiting and urinary retention, if associated with continuous infusion therapy, may respond to intravenous administration of a low dose of naloxone (0.2 mg). The risks of using narcotic antagonists in patients chronically receiving narcotic therapy should be considered.




  NALOXONE INJECTION AND RESUSCITATIVE EQUIPMENT SHOULD BE IMMEDIATELY AVAILABLE FOR USE IN CASE OF LIFE-THREATENING OR INTOLERABLE SIDE EFFECTS AND WHENEVER INFUMORPH THERAPY IS BEING INITIATED, THE RESERVOIR IS BEING REFILLED OR ANY MANIPULATION OF THE RESERVOIR SYSTEM IS TAKING PLACE.    
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
