<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="integrilin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reaction is also discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Bleeding [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Bleeding and hypotension are the most commonly reported adverse reactions. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 A total of 16,782 patients were treated in the Phase III clinical trials (PURSUIT, ESPRIT, and IMPACT II)  [see  Clinical Trials (14)  ]  . These 16,782 patients had a mean age of 62 years (range: 20-94 years). Eighty-nine percent of the patients were Caucasian, with the remainder being predominantly Black (5%) and Hispanic (5%). Sixty-eight percent were men. Because of the different regimens used in PURSUIT, IMPACT II, and ESPRIT, data from the 3 studies were not pooled.



 Bleeding and hypotension were the most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and greater than placebo) in the INTEGRILIN controlled clinical trial database.



       Bleeding    



 The incidence of bleeding and transfusions in the PURSUIT and ESPRIT studies are shown in Table 2. Bleeding was classified as major or minor by the criteria of the TIMI study group. Major bleeding consisted of intracranial hemorrhage and other bleeding that led to decreases in hemoglobin greater than 5 g/dL. Minor bleeding included spontaneous gross hematuria, spontaneous hematemesis, other observed blood loss with a hemoglobin decrease of more than 3 g/dL, and other hemoglobin decreases that were greater than 4 g/dL but less than 5 g/dL. In patients who received transfusions, the corresponding loss in hemoglobin was estimated through an adaptation of the method of Landefeld et al.



 Table 2: Bleeding and Transfusions in the PURSUIT and ESPRIT Studies 
 PURSUIT (ACS)                              
                                                      Placebo                     INTEGRILIN180/2           
                                                       n (%)                           n (%)                
  
 Note: Denominator is based on patients for whom data are available.   
  
 Patients                                               4696                            4679                
 Major bleeding                                      425 (9.3%)                     498 (10.8%)             
 Minor bleeding                                      347 (7.6%)                     604 (13.1%)             
 Requiring transfusions                             490 (10.4%)                     601 (12.8%)             
   ESPRIT (PCI)                             
                                                      Placebo                 INTEGRILIN    180/2/180       
                                                       n (%)                           n (%)                
 Patients                                               1024                            1040                
 Major bleeding                                       4 (0.4%)                       13 (1.3%)              
 Minor bleeding                                       18 (2%)                         29 (3%)               
 Requiring transfusions                              11 (1.1%)                       16 (1.5%)              
         The majority of major bleeding reactions in the ESPRIT study occurred at the vascular access site (1 and 8 patients, or 0.1% and 0.8% in the placebo and INTEGRILIN groups, respectively). Bleeding at "other" locations occurred in 0.2% and 0.4% of patients, respectively.
 

 In the PURSUIT study, the greatest increase in major bleeding in INTEGRILIN-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients was also associated with bleeding at the femoral artery access site (2.8% versus 1.3%). Oropharyngeal (primarily gingival), genitourinary, gastrointestinal, and retroperitoneal bleeding were also seen more commonly in INTEGRILIN-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients.



 Among patients experiencing a major bleed in the IMPACT II study, an increase in bleeding on INTEGRILIN versus placebo was observed only for the femoral artery access site (3.2% versus 2.8%).



 Table 3 displays the incidence of TIMI major bleeding according to the cardiac procedures carried out in the PURSUIT study. The most common bleeding complications were related to cardiac revascularization (CABG-related or femoral artery access site bleeding). A corresponding table for ESPRIT is not presented, as every patient underwent PCI in the ESPRIT study and only 11 patients underwent CABG.



 Table 3: Major Bleeding by Procedures in the PURSUIT Study 
                                                      Placebo                        INTEGRILIN             
                                                                                       180/2                
                                                       n (%)                           n (%)                
  
 Note: Denominators are based on the total number of patients whose TIMI classification was resolved.   
  
 Patients                                               4577                            4604                
 Overall incidence of major bleeding                 425 (9.3%)                     498 (10.8%)             
 Breakdown by procedure:                                                                                    
   CABG                                              375 (8.2%)                      377 (8.2%)             
   Angioplasty without CABG                          27 (0.6%)                       64 (1.4%)              
   Angiography without angioplasty or CABG            11 (0.2%)                       29 (0.6%)              
   Medical therapy only                              12 (0.3%)                       28 (0.6%)              
         In the PURSUIT and ESPRIT studies, the risk of major bleeding with INTEGRILIN increased as patient weight decreased. This relationship was most apparent for patients weighing less than 70 kg.
 

 Bleeding resulting in discontinuation of the study drug was more frequent among patients receiving INTEGRILIN than placebo (4.6% versus 0.9% in ESPRIT, 8% versus 1% in PURSUIT, 3.5% versus 1.9% in IMPACT II).



       Intracranial Hemorrhage and Stroke    



 Intracranial hemorrhage was rare in the PURSUIT, IMPACT II, and ESPRIT clinical studies. In the PURSUIT study, 3 patients in the placebo group, 1 patient in the group treated with INTEGRILIN 180/1.3, and 5 patients in the group treated with INTEGRILIN 180/2 experienced a hemorrhagic stroke. The overall incidence of stroke was 0.5% in patients receiving INTEGRILIN 180/1.3, 0.7% in patients receiving INTEGRILIN 180/2, and 0.8% in placebo patients.



 In the IMPACT II study, intracranial hemorrhage was experienced by 1 patient treated with INTEGRILIN 135/0.5, 2 patients treated with INTEGRILIN 135/0.75, and 2 patients in the placebo group. The overall incidence of stroke was 0.5% in patients receiving 135/0.5 INTEGRILIN, 0.7% in patients receiving INTEGRILIN 135/0.75, and 0.7% in the placebo group.



 In the ESPRIT study, there were 3 hemorrhagic strokes, 1 in the placebo group and 2 in the INTEGRILIN group. In addition there was 1 case of cerebral infarction in the INTEGRILIN group.



       Immunogenicity/Thrombocytopenia    



 The potential for development of antibodies to eptifibatide has been studied in 433 subjects. INTEGRILIN was nonantigenic in 412 patients receiving a single administration of INTEGRILIN (135-mcg/kg bolus followed by a continuous infusion of either 0.5 mcg/kg/min or 0.75 mcg/kg/min), and in 21 subjects to whom INTEGRILIN (135-mcg/kg bolus followed by a continuous infusion of 0.75 mcg/kg/min) was administered twice, 28 days apart. In both cases, plasma for antibody detection was collected approximately 30 days after each dose. The development of antibodies to eptifibatide at higher doses has not been evaluated.



 In patients with suspected INTEGRILIN-related immune-mediated thrombocytopenia, IgG antibodies that react with the GP IIb/IIIa complex were identified in the presence of eptifibatide and in INTEGRILIN-naive patients. These findings suggest acute thrombocytopenia after the administration of INTEGRILIN can develop as a result of naturally occurring drug-dependent antibodies or those induced by prior exposure to INTEGRILIN. Similar antibodies were identified with other GP IIb/IIIa ligand-mimetic agents. Immune-mediated thrombocytopenia with INTEGRILIN may be associated with hypotension and/or other signs of hypersensitivity.



 In the PURSUIT and IMPACT II studies, the incidence of thrombocytopenia (&lt;100,000/mm  3  or &gt;=50% reduction from baseline) and the incidence of platelet transfusions were similar between patients treated with INTEGRILIN and placebo. In the ESPRIT study, the incidence was 0.6% in the placebo group and 1.2% in the INTEGRILIN group.



       Other Adverse Reactions    



 In the PURSUIT and ESPRIT studies, the incidence of serious nonbleeding adverse reactions was similar in patients receiving placebo or INTEGRILIN (19% and 19%, respectively, in PURSUIT; 6% and 7%, respectively, in ESPRIT). In PURSUIT, the only serious nonbleeding adverse reaction that occurred at a rate of at least 1% and was more common with INTEGRILIN than placebo (7% versus 6%) was hypotension. Most of the serious nonbleeding adverse reactions consisted of cardiovascular reactions typical of a UA population. In the IMPACT II study, serious nonbleeding adverse reactions that occurred in greater than 1% of patients were uncommon and similar in incidence between placebo- and INTEGRILIN-treated patients.



 Discontinuation of study drug due to adverse reactions other than bleeding was uncommon in the PURSUIT, IMPACT II, and ESPRIT studies, with no single reaction occurring in &gt;0.5% of the study population (except for "other" in the ESPRIT study).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because the reactions below are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following adverse reactions have been reported in postmarketing experience, primarily with INTEGRILIN in combination with heparin and aspirin: cerebral, GI, and pulmonary hemorrhage. Fatal bleeding reactions have been reported. Acute profound thrombocytopenia, as well as immune-mediated thrombocytopenia, has been reported  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  INTEGRILIN can cause serious bleeding. If bleeding cannot be controlled, discontinue INTEGRILIN immediately. Minimize vascular and other traumas. If heparin is given concomitantly, monitor aPTT or ACT. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Thrombocytopenia: Discontinue INTEGRILIN and heparin. Monitor and treat condition appropriately. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Bleeding



  Bleeding is the most common complication encountered during INTEGRILIN therapy. Administration of INTEGRILIN is associated with an increase in major and minor bleeding, as classified by the criteria of the Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction Study group (TIMI) [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Most major bleeding associated with INTEGRILIN has been at the arterial access site for cardiac catheterization or from the gastrointestinal or genitourinary tract. Minimize the use of arterial and venous punctures, intramuscular injections, and the use of urinary catheters, nasotracheal intubation, and nasogastric tubes. When obtaining intravenous access, avoid non-compressible sites (e.g., subclavian or jugular veins).



    Use of Thrombolytics, Anticoagulants, and Other Antiplatelet Agents  



 Risk factors for bleeding include older age, a history of bleeding disorders, and concomitant use of drugs that increase the risk of bleeding (thrombolytics, oral anticoagulants, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and P2Y12inhibitors). Concomitant treatment with other inhibitors of platelet receptor glycoprotein (GP) IIb/IIIa should be avoided. In patients treated with heparin, bleeding can be minimized by close monitoring of the aPTT and ACT [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  .



    Care of the Femoral Artery Access Site in Patients Undergoing Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PCI)  



 In patients undergoing PCI, treatment with INTEGRILIN is associated with an increase in major and minor bleeding at the site of arterial sheath placement. After PCI, INTEGRILIN infusion should be continued until hospital discharge or up to 18 to 24 hours, whichever comes first. Heparin use is discouraged after the PCI procedure. Early sheath removal is encouraged while INTEGRILIN is being infused. Prior to removing the sheath, it is recommended that heparin be discontinued for 3 to 4 hours and an aPTT of &lt;45 seconds or ACT &lt;150 seconds be achieved. In any case, both heparin and INTEGRILIN should be discontinued and sheath hemostasis should be achieved at least 2 to 4 hours before hospital discharge. If bleeding at access site cannot be controlled with pressure, infusion of INTEGRILIN and heparin should be discontinued immediately.



    5.2 Thrombocytopenia



  There have been reports of acute, profound thrombocytopenia (immune-mediated and non-immune mediated) with INTEGRILIN. In the event of acute profound thrombocytopenia or a confirmed platelet decrease to &lt;100,000/mm  3  , discontinue INTEGRILIN and heparin (unfractionated or low-molecular weight). Monitor serial platelet counts, assess the presence of drug-dependent antibodies, and treat as appropriate [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 There has been no clinical experience with INTEGRILIN initiated in patients with a baseline platelet count &lt;100,000/mm  3  . If a patient with low platelet counts is receiving INTEGRILIN, their platelet count should be monitored closely.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
