<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="intuniv" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labelling:  



 *  Hypotension, bradycardia, and syncope [ ]  see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    
 *  Sedation and somnolence [ ]  see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and at least twice placebo rate) in the monotherapy trials: somnolence, fatigue, nausea, lethargy, and hypotension ( ). Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and at least twice placebo rate) in the adjunctive trial: somnolence, fatigue, insomnia, dizziness, and abdominal pain ( ).  6    6    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Shire US Inc. at 1-800-828-2088 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch      .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 A total of 2,028 subjects have been exposed to INTUNIV while participating in clinical trials. This includes 1,533 patients from completed studies in children and adolescents, and 495 subjects in completed studies in adult healthy volunteers.  (r)  



 The mean duration of exposure of 446 patients that previously participated in two 2-year, open-label long-term studies was approximately 10 months.



   Monotherapy Trials  



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate for placebo) in the monotherapy trials (Studies 1 and 2) with INTUNIV were: somnolence, fatigue, nausea, lethargy, and hypotension.  Most Common Adverse Reactions -    (r)  



 Twelve percent (12%) of patients receiving INTUNIV discontinued from the monotherapy clinical studies (Studies 1 and 2) due to adverse reactions, compared to 4% in the placebo group. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of INTUNIV -treated patients from the studies were somnolence/sedation (6%) and fatigue (2%). Less common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation (occurring in approximately 1% of patients) included: hypotension, headache, and dizziness.  Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation -    (r)    (r)  



   Adjunctive Trial  



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate for placebo) in the adjunctive trial with INTUNIV were: somnolence, fatigue, insomnia, dizziness, and abdominal pain.  Most Common Adverse Reactions -    (r)  



 In the adjunctive clinical study, 3% of patients receiving INTUNIV discontinued due to adverse reactions, compared to 1% in the placebo group.  Each adverse reaction leading to discontinuation occurred in less than 1% of INTUNIV -treated patients.  Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation -    (r)    (r)  



   Short Term Monotherapy Clinical Studies  



 - Two short-term, placebo-controlled, double-blind pivotal studies (Studies 1 and 2) were conducted in children and adolescents with ADHD, using fixed doses of INTUNIV (1 mg, 2 mg, 3 mg, and 4 mg/day).  The most commonly reported adverse reactions (occurring in &gt;= 2% of patients) that were considered drug-related and reported in a greater percentage of patients taking INTUNIV compared to patients taking placebo are shown in Table 2. Adverse reactions that were dose-related include: somnolence/sedation, abdominal pain, dizziness, hypotension, dry mouth and constipation.  Common Adverse Reactions    (r)    (r)  




     Table 2:  Percentage of Patients Experiencing Common (&gt;= 2%)    Adverse Reactions in Short-Term Monotherapy Studies 1 and 2    
   Adverse Reaction Term      All Doses of INTUNIV (N=513)  (r)            Placebo       (N=149)     
   Somnolence  a                 38%              12%             
   Headache         24%              19%             
   Fatigue          14%              3%              
   Abdominal pain  b      11%              9%              
   Hypotension  c      7%               3%              
   Nausea           6%               2%              
   Lethargy         6%               3%              
   Dizziness        6%               4%              
   Irritability     6%               4%              
   Decreased appetite    5%               3%              
   Dry mouth        4%               1%              
   Constipation     3%               1%              
 a: The somnolence term includes somnolence, sedation, and hypersomnia. b: The abdominal pain term includes abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, and abdominal pain lower. c: The hypotension term includes hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, and decreased blood pressure.   
         In an 8-week, placebo-controlled study in children 6-12 years of age with ADHD in which INTUNIV was dosed once (1-4 mg/day) in the morning or evening (Study 4), the safety profile was consistent with the once daily morning dosing of INTUNIV .  (r)    (r)  
 

   Short Term Adjunctive Clinical Study  



 - A 8-week, placebo-controlled, double-blind, dose-optimized pivotal study (Study 3) was conducted in children and adolescents aged 6-17 years with a diagnosis of ADHD who were identified as having a sub-optimal response to psychostimulants. Patients received INTUNIV (1 mg, 2 mg, 3 mg, and 4 mg/day) or placebo, dosed in the morning or in the evening, in combination with their morning dose of psychostimulant. The most commonly reported adverse reactions (occurring in &gt;= 2% of patients in the overall INTUNIV group) that were reported in a greater percentage of patients taking INTUNIV compared to patients taking placebo are shown in Table 3.  Common Adverse Reactions    (r)    (r)    (r)  




     Table 3:  Percentage of Patients Experiencing Common (&gt;= 2%) Adverse Reactions in Short-Term Adjunctive Study 3       
    Adverse Reaction Term       All Doses of INTUNIV  (r)      (N=302)  a            Placebo   (N=153)     
   Headache         21%              13%             
   Somnolence  b      18%              7%              
   Insomnia  c      12%              6%              
   Fatigue          10%              3%              
   Abdominal pain  d      10%              3%              
   Dizziness        8%               4%              
   Decreased appetite    7%               4%              
   Nausea           5%               3%              
   Diarrhea         4%               1%              
   Hypotension  e      3%               0%              
   Affect lability    2%               1%              
   Bradycardia      2%               0%              
   Constipation     2%               0%              
   Dry mouth        2%               0%              
 a: The morning and evening dose groups of INTUNIV are combined. b: The somnolence term includes somnolence, sedation, and hypersomnia. c: The insomnia term includes insomnia, initial insomnia, and middle insomnia. d: The abdominal pain term includes abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, and abdominal pain lower. e: The hypotension term includes hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, and decreased blood pressure.  (r)     
           Effects on Blood Pressure and Heart Rate  
 

 In the monotherapy pediatric, short-term, controlled trials (Studies 1 and 2), the maximum mean changes from baseline in systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, and pulse were -5 mmHg, -3 mmHg, and -6 bpm, respectively, for all dose groups combined (generally one week after reaching target doses of 1 mg/day, 2 mg/day, 3 mg/day or 4 mg/day). These changes were dose dependent. Decreases in blood pressure and heart rate were usually modest and asymptomatic; however, hypotension and bradycardia can occur. Hypotension was reported as an adverse reaction for 7% of the INTUNIV group and 3% of the placebo group. This includes orthostatic hypotension, which was reported for 1% of the INTUNIV group and none in the placebo group. In the adjunctive trial, hypotension (3%) and bradycardia (2%) were observed in patients treated with INTUNIV as compared to none in the placebo group.  In long-term, open label studies, (mean exposure of approximately 10 months), maximum decreases in systolic and diastolic blood pressure occurred in the first month of therapy. Decreases were less pronounced over time. Syncope occurred in 1% of pediatric subjects in the clinical program. The majority of these cases occurred in the long-term, open-label studies.  (r)    (r)    (r)  



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed in Clinical Studies  



 Table 4 includes additional adverse reactions observed in short-term, placebo-controlled and long-term, open-label clinical studies not included elsewhere in section 6.1, listed by organ system.




   Table 4: Other adverse reactions observed in clinical studies       
    Body System         Adverse Reaction     
   Cardiac          Atrioventricular block, sinus arrhythmia   
   Gastrointestinal      Dyspepsia, stomach discomfort, vomiting   
   General          Asthenia, chest pain   
   Immune System            Disorders           Hypersensitivity   
   Investigations      Increased alanine amino transferase, increased weight   
   Nervous system      Convulsion      
   Psychiatric      Agitation, anxiety, depression, nightmare   
   Renal            Increased urinary frequency, enuresis   
   Respiratory      Asthma          
   Vascular         Hypertension, pallor   
          6.2 Post-marketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of guanfacine.  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 An open-label post-marketing study involving 21,718 patients was conducted to assess the safety of guanfacine (as the hydrochloride) 1 mg/day given at bedtime for 28 days. Guanfacine was administered with or without other antihypertensive agents. Adverse events reported in the post-marketing study at an incidence greater than 1% included dry mouth, dizziness, somnolence, fatigue, headache and nausea. The most commonly reported adverse events in this study were the same as those observed in controlled clinical trials.



 Less frequent, possibly guanfacine-related events observed in the post-marketing study and/or reported spontaneously, not included in , include:  section 6.1  



 edema, malaise, tremor    General:    



 palpitations, tachycardia    Cardiovascular:    



 paresthesias, vertigo    Central Nervous System:    



 blurred vision    Eye Disorders:    



 arthralgia, leg cramps, leg pain, myalgia    Musculo-Skeletal System:    



 confusion, hallucinations    Psychiatric:    



 impotence    Reproductive System, Male:    



 dyspnea    Respiratory System:    



 alopecia, dermatitis, exfoliative dermatitis, pruritus, rash    Skin and Appendages:    



 alterations in taste    Special Senses:    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypotension, bradycardia, and syncope: Use INTUNIV with caution in patients at risk for hypotension, bradycardia, heart block, or syncope (e.g., those taking antihypertensives). Measure heart rate and blood pressure prior to initiation of therapy, following dose increases, and periodically while on therapy. Advise patients to avoid becoming dehydrated or overheated ( ).  (r)    5.1   
 *  Sedation and somnolence: Occur commonly with INTUNIV .  Consider the potential for additive sedative effects with CNS depressant drugs. Caution patients against operating heavy equipment or driving until they know how they respond to INTUNIV ( ).   (r)      (r)     5.2   
    
 

   5.1 Hypotension, Bradycardia, and Syncope



  Treatment with INTUNIV can cause dose-dependent decreases in blood pressure and heart rate. Decreases were less pronounced over time of treatment. Orthostatic hypotension and syncope have been reported .  (r)   [   ]   see Adverse Reactions       (6.1)      



 Measure heart rate and blood pressure prior to initiation of therapy, following dose increases, and periodically while on therapy. Use INTUNIV with caution in patients with a history of hypotension, heart block, bradycardia, cardiovascular disease, or who have a history of syncope or may have a condition that predisposes them to syncope, such as hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, bradycardia, or dehydration. Use INTUNIV with caution in patients treated concomitantly with antihypertensives or other drugs that can reduce blood pressure or heart rate or increase the risk of syncope. Advise patients to avoid becoming dehydrated or overheated.  (r)    (r)  



    5.2 Sedation and Somnolence



  Somnolence and sedation were commonly reported adverse reactions in clinical studies [ . Before using INTUNIV with other centrally active depressants (such as phenothiazines, barbiturates, or benzodiazepines), consider the potential for additive sedative effects.  Caution patients against operating heavy equipment or driving until they know how they respond to treatment with INTUNIV Advise patients to avoid use with alcohol. ]   see Adverse Reactions (6.1)        (r)    (r)   .  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
