<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="invanz" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are described in greater detail in the Warnings and Precautions section.



 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Seizure Potential [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Interaction with Valproic Acid [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *   Clostridium difficile -Associated Diarrhea (CDAD) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Caution with Intramuscular Administration [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Laboratory Tests [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Adults:
 

 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) in patients treated with INVANZ, including those who were switched to therapy with an oral antimicrobial, were diarrhea, nausea, headache and infused vein complication. (  6.1  )



 In the prophylaxis indication the overall adverse experience profile was generally comparable to that observed for ertapenem in other clinical trials. (  6.1  )



 Pediatrics:



 Adverse reactions in this population were comparable to adults. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) in pediatric patients treated with INVANZ, including those who were switched to therapy with an oral antimicrobial, were diarrhea, vomiting and infusion site pain. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adults Receiving INVANZ as a Treatment Regimen  



 Clinical trials enrolled 1954 patients treated with INVANZ; in some of the clinical trials, parenteral therapy was followed by a switch to an appropriate oral antimicrobial  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . Most adverse experiences reported in these clinical trials were described as mild to moderate in severity. INVANZ was discontinued due to adverse experiences in 4.7% of patients.  Table 3  shows the incidence of adverse experiences reported in &gt;=2.0% of patients in these trials. The most common drug-related adverse experiences in patients treated with INVANZ, including those who were switched to therapy with an oral antimicrobial, were diarrhea (5.5%), infused vein complication (3.7%), nausea (3.1%), headache (2.2%), and vaginitis in females (2.1%).



 Table 3: Incidence (%) of Adverse Experiences Reported During Study Therapy Plus 14-Day Follow-Up in &gt;=2.0% of Adult Patients Treated With INVANZ in Clinical Trials 
                                 INVANZ1 g daily   Piperacillin/ Tazobactam3.375 g q6h  INVANZ1 g daily   Ceftriaxone1 or 2 g daily   
 Adverse Events                  (N=802)           (N=774)            (N=1152)          (N=942)             
  
   Local:                                                                                                   
   Infused vein complication     7.1               7.9                5.4               6.7                 
   Systemic:                                                                                                
   Death                         2.5               1.6                1.3               1.6                 
   Edema/swelling                3.4               2.5                2.9               3.3                 
   Fever                         5.0               6.6                2.3               3.4                 
   Abdominal pain                3.6               4.8                4.3               3.9                 
   Hypotension                   2.0               1.4                1.0               1.2                 
   Constipation                  4.0               5.4                3.3               3.1                 
   Diarrhea                      10.3              12.1               9.2               9.8                 
   Nausea                        8.5               8.7                6.4               7.4                 
   Vomiting                      3.7               5.3                4.0               4.0                 
   Altered mental status         5.1               3.4                3.3               2.5                 
   Dizziness                     2.1               3.0                1.5               2.1                 
   Headache                      5.6               5.4                6.8               6.9                 
   Insomnia                      3.2               5.2                3.0               4.1                 
   Dyspnea                       2.6               1.8                1.0               2.4                 
   Pruritus                      2.0               2.6                1.0               1.9                 
   Rash                          2.5               3.1                2.3               1.5                 
   Vaginitis                     1.4               1.0                3.3               3.7                 
           In patients treated for complicated intra-abdominal infections, death occurred in 4.7% (15/316) of patients receiving INVANZ and 2.6% (8/307) of patients receiving comparator drug. These deaths occurred in patients with significant co-morbidity and/or severe baseline infections. Deaths were considered unrelated to study drugs by investigators.
 

 In clinical trials, seizure was reported during study therapy plus 14-day follow-up period in 0.5% of patients treated with INVANZ, 0.3% of patients treated with piperacillin/tazobactam and 0% of patients treated with ceftriaxone  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



 Additional adverse experiences that were reported with INVANZ with an incidence &gt;0.1% within each body system are listed below



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal distention, pain, chills, septicemia, septic shock, dehydration, gout, malaise, asthenia/fatigue, necrosis, candidiasis, weight loss, facial edema, injection site induration, injection site pain, extravasation, phlebitis/thrombophlebitis, flank pain, syncope



   Cardiovascular System:  heart failure, hematoma, chest pain, hypertension, tachycardia, cardiac arrest, bradycardia, arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, heart murmur, ventricular tachycardia, asystole, subdural hemorrhage



   Digestive System:  acid regurgitation, oral candidiasis, dyspepsia, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, anorexia, flatulence,  C. difficile  -associated diarrhea, stomatitis, dysphagia, hemorrhoids, ileus, cholelithiasis, duodenitis, esophagitis, gastritis, jaundice, mouth ulcer, pancreatitis, pyloric stenosis



   Musculoskeletal System:  leg pain



   Nervous System &amp; Psychiatric:  anxiety, nervousness, seizure  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  , tremor, depression, hypesthesia, spasm, paresthesia, aggressive behavior, vertigo



   Respiratory System:  cough, pharyngitis, rales/rhonchi, respiratory distress, pleural effusion, hypoxemia, bronchoconstriction, pharyngeal discomfort, epistaxis, pleuritic pain, asthma, hemoptysis, hiccups, voice disturbance



   Skin &amp; Skin Appendage:  erythema, sweating, dermatitis, desquamation, flushing, urticaria



   Special Senses:  taste perversion



   Urogenital System:  renal impairment, oliguria/anuria, vaginal pruritus, hematuria, urinary retention, bladder dysfunction, vaginal candidiasis, vulvovaginitis.



 In a clinical trial for the treatment of diabetic foot infections in which 289 adult diabetic patients were treated with INVANZ, the adverse experience profile was generally similar to that seen in previous clinical trials.



   Prophylaxis of Surgical Site Infection following Elective Colorectal Surgery  



 In a clinical trial in adults for the prophylaxis of surgical site infection following elective colorectal surgery in which 476 patients received a 1 g dose of INVANZ 1 hour prior to surgery and were then followed for safety 14 days post surgery, the overall adverse experience profile was generally comparable to that observed for INVANZ in previous clinical trials.  Table 4  shows the incidence of adverse experiences other than those previously described above for INVANZ that were reported regardless of causality in &gt;=2.0% of patients in this trial.



 Table 4: Incidence (%) of Adverse Experiences Reported During Study Therapy Plus 14-Day Follow-Up in &gt;=2.0% of Adult Patients Treated With INVANZ for Prophylaxis of Surgical Site Infections Following Elective Colorectal Surgery 
 Adverse Events                                       INVANZ1 g(N = 476)        Cefotetan2 g(N = 476)       
  
 Anemia                                               5.7                       6.9                         
 Small intestinal obstruction                         2.1                       1.9                         
 Pneumonia                                            2.1                       4.0                         
 Postoperative infection                              2.3                       4.0                         
 Urinary tract infection                              3.8                       5.5                         
 Wound infection                                      6.5                       12.4                        
 Wound complication                                   2.9                       2.3                         
 Atelectasis                                          3.4                       1.9                         
         Additional adverse experiences that were reported in this prophylaxis trial with INVANZ, regardless of causality, with an incidence &gt;0.5% within each body system are listed below:
 

   Gastrointestinal Disorders:    C. difficile  infection or colitis, dry mouth, hematochezia



   General Disorders and Administration Site Condition:  crepitations



   Infections and Infestations:  cellulitis, abdominal abscess, fungal rash, pelvic abscess



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  incision site complication, incision site hemorrhage, intestinal stoma complication, anastomotic leak, seroma, wound dehiscence, wound secretion



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  muscle spasms



   Nervous System Disorders:  cerebrovascular accident



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  dysuria, pollakiuria



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  crackles lung, lung infiltration, pulmonary congestion, pulmonary embolism, wheezing.



   Pediatric Patients Receiving INVANZ as a Treatment Regimen  



 Clinical trials enrolled 384 patients treated with INVANZ; in some of the clinical trials, parenteral therapy was followed by a switch to an appropriate oral antimicrobial  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . The overall adverse experience profile in pediatric patients is comparable to that in adult patients.  Table 5  shows the incidence of adverse experiences reported in &gt;=2.0% of pediatric patients in clinical trials. The most common drug-related adverse experiences in pediatric patients treated with INVANZ, including those who were switched to therapy with an oral antimicrobial, were diarrhea (6.5%), infusion site pain (5.5%), infusion site erythema (2.6%), vomiting (2.1%).



 Table 5: Incidence (%) of Adverse Experiences Reported During Study Therapy Plus 14-Day Follow-Up in &gt;=2.0% of Pediatric Patients Treated With INVANZ in Clinical Trials 
                                              INVANZ  ,            Ceftriaxone       Ticarcillin/ Clavulanate   
 Adverse Events                               (N=384)              (N=100)           (N=24)                 
  
   Local:                                      
   Infusion Site Erythema                     3.9                  3.0               8.3                    
   Infusion Site Pain                         7.0                  4.0               20.8                   
   Systemic:                                   
   Abdominal Pain                             4.7                  3.0               4.2                    
   Constipation                               2.3                  0.0               0.0                    
   Diarrhea                                   11.7                 17.0              4.2                    
   Loose Stools                               2.1                  0.0               0.0                    
   Vomiting                                   10.2                 11.0              8.3                    
   Pyrexia                                    4.9                  6.0               8.3                    
   Upper Respiratory Tract Infection          2.3                  3.0               0.0                    
   Headache                                   4.4                  4.0               0.0                    
   Cough                                      4.4                  3.0               0.0                    
   Diaper Dermatitis                          4.7                  4.0               0.0                    
   Rash                                       2.9                  2.0               8.3                    
          Additional adverse experiences that were reported with INVANZ with an incidence &gt;0.5% within each body system are listed below:
 

   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  nausea



   General Disorders and Administration Site Condition:  hypothermia, chest pain, upper abdominal pain; infusion site pruritus, induration, phlebitis, swelling, and warmth



   Infections and Infestations:  candidiasis, oral candidiasis, viral pharyngitis, herpes simplex, ear infection, abdominal abscess



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  decreased appetite



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  arthralgia



   Nervous System Disorders:  dizziness, somnolence



   Psychiatric Disorders:  insomnia



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  genital rash



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  wheezing, nasopharyngitis, pleural effusion, rhinitis, rhinorrhea



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  dermatitis, pruritus, rash erythematous, skin lesion



   Vascular Disorders:  phlebitis.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during the post-approval use of INVANZ. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  teeth staining



   Immune System Disorders:  anaphylaxis including anaphylactoid reactions



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  muscular weakness



   Nervous System Disorders:  coordination abnormal, depressed level of consciousness, dyskinesia, gait disturbance, myoclonus, tremor



   Psychiatric Disorders:  altered mental status (including aggression, delirium), hallucinations



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Drug Rash with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS syndrome)



   6.3 Adverse Laboratory Changes in Clinical Trials

    Adults Receiving INVANZ as Treatment Regimen  



 Laboratory adverse experiences that were reported during therapy in &gt;=2.0% of adult patients treated with INVANZ in clinical trials are presented in  Table 6  . Drug-related laboratory adverse experiences that were reported during therapy in &gt;=2.0% of adult patients treated with INVANZ, including those who were switched to therapy with an oral antimicrobial, in clinical trials were ALT increased (6.0%), AST increased (5.2%), serum alkaline phosphatase increased (3.4%), and platelet count increased (2.8%). INVANZ was discontinued due to laboratory adverse experiences in 0.3% of patients.



 Table 6: IncidenceNumber of patients with laboratory adverse experiences/Number of patients with the laboratory test (%) of Laboratory Adverse Experiences Reported During Study Therapy Plus 14-Day Follow-Up in &gt;=2.0% of Adult Patients Treated With INVANZ in Clinical Trials 
                                             INVANZ1 g daily  Piperacillin/Tazobactam3.375 g q6h  INVANZ1 g daily  Ceftriaxone1 or 2 g daily   
 Adverse laboratory experiences              (n=766)        (n=755)          (n=1122)        (n=920)          
  
 ALT increased                               8.8            7.3              8.3             6.9              
 AST increased                               8.4            8.3              7.1             6.5              
 Serum alkaline phosphatase increased        6.6            7.2              4.3             2.8              
 Eosinophils increased                       1.1            1.1              2.1             1.8              
 Hematocrit decreased                        3.0            2.9              3.4             2.4              
 Hemoglobin decreased                        4.9            4.7              4.5             3.5              
 Platelet count increased                    6.5            6.3              4.3             3.5              
 Urine RBCs increased                        2.5            2.9              1.1             1.0              
 Urine WBCs increased                        2.5            3.2              1.6             1.1              
           Additional laboratory adverse experiences that were reported during therapy in &gt;0.1% of patients treated with INVANZ in clinical trials include: increases in serum creatinine, serum glucose, BUN, total, direct and indirect serum bilirubin, serum sodium and potassium, PT and PTT; decreases in serum potassium, serum albumin, WBC, platelet count, and segmented neutrophils.
 

 In a clinical trial for the treatment of diabetic foot infections in which 289 adult diabetic patients were treated with INVANZ, the laboratory adverse experience profile was generally similar to that seen in previous clinical trials.



   Prophylaxis of Surgical Site Infection following Elective Colorectal Surgery  



 In a clinical trial in adults for the prophylaxis of surgical site infection following elective colorectal surgery in which 476 patients received a 1 g dose of INVANZ 1 hour prior to surgery and were then followed for safety 14 days post surgery, the overall laboratory adverse experience profile was generally comparable to that observed for INVANZ in previous clinical trials.



   Pediatric Patients Receiving INVANZ as a Treatment Regimen  



 Laboratory adverse experiences that were reported during therapy in &gt;=2.0% of pediatric patients treated with INVANZ in clinical trials are presented in  Table 7  . Drug-related laboratory adverse experiences that were reported during therapy in &gt;=2.0% of pediatric patients treated with INVANZ, including those who were switched to therapy with an oral antimicrobial, in clinical trials were neutrophil count decreased (3.0%), ALT increased (2.2%), and AST increased (2.1%).



 Table 7: IncidenceNumber of patients with laboratory adverse experiences/Number of patients with the laboratory test; where at least 300 patients had the test (%) of Specific Laboratory Adverse Experiences Reported During Study Therapy Plus 14-Day Follow-Up in &gt;=2.0% of Pediatric Patients Treated With INVANZ in Clinical Trials 
                                              INVANZ              Ceftriaxone         Ticarcillin/Clavulanate   
 Adverse laboratory experiences               (n=379)             (n=97)              (n=24)                
  
 ALT Increased                                3.8                 1.1                 4.3                   
 AST Increased                                3.8                 1.1                 4.3                   
 Neutrophil Count Decreased                   5.8                 3.1                 0.0                   
          Additional laboratory adverse experiences that were reported during therapy in &gt;0.5% of patients treated with INVANZ in clinical trials include: alkaline phosphatase increased, eosinophil count increased, platelet count increased, white blood cell count decreased and urine protein present.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions have been reported in patients receiving beta-lactams. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Seizures and other central nervous system adverse experiences have been reported during treatment. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Co-administration of INVANZ with valproic acid or divalproex sodium reduces the serum concentration of valproic acid potentially increasing the risk of breakthrough seizures. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea (ranging from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis): Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Caution should be taken when administering INVANZ intramuscularly to avoid inadvertent injection into a blood vessel. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious and occasionally fatal hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions have been reported in patients receiving therapy with beta-lactams. These reactions are more likely to occur in individuals with a history of sensitivity to multiple allergens. There have been reports of individuals with a history of penicillin hypersensitivity who have experienced severe hypersensitivity reactions when treated with another beta-lactam. Before initiating therapy with INVANZ, careful inquiry should be made concerning previous hypersensitivity reactions to penicillins, cephalosporins, other beta-lactams and other allergens. If an allergic reaction to INVANZ occurs, discontinue the drug immediately. Serious anaphylactic reactions require immediate emergency treatment as clinically indicated.



    5.2 Seizure Potential



  Seizures and other central nervous system (CNS) adverse experiences have been reported during treatment with INVANZ [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . During clinical investigations in adult patients treated with INVANZ (1 g once a day), seizures, irrespective of drug relationship, occurred in 0.5% of patients during study therapy plus 14-day follow-up period [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . These experiences have occurred most commonly in patients with CNS disorders (e.g., brain lesions or history of seizures) and/or compromised renal function. Close adherence to the recommended dosage regimen is urged, especially in patients with known factors that predispose to convulsive activity. Anticonvulsant therapy should be continued in patients with known seizure disorders. If focal tremors, myoclonus, or seizures occur, patients should be evaluated neurologically, placed on anticonvulsant therapy if not already instituted, and the dosage of INVANZ re-examined to determine whether it should be decreased or discontinued.



    5.3 Interaction with Valproic Acid



  Case reports in the literature have shown that co-administration of carbapenems, including ertapenem, to patients receiving valproic acid or divalproex sodium results in a reduction in valproic acid concentrations. The valproic acid concentrations may drop below the therapeutic range as a result of this interaction, therefore increasing the risk of breakthrough seizures. Increasing the dose of valproic acid or divalproex sodium may not be sufficient to overcome this interaction. The concomitant use of ertapenem and valproic acid/divalproex sodium is generally not recommended. Anti-bacterials other than carbapenems should be considered to treat infections in patients whose seizures are well controlled on valproic acid or divalproex sodium. If administration of INVANZ is necessary, supplemental anti-convulsant therapy should be considered [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



    5.4 Clostridium difficile  -Associated Diarrhea (CDAD)



  CDAD has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including ertapenem, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of Clostridium difficile  .



  Clostridium difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of Clostridium difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against Clostridium difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of Clostridium difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.5 Caution with Intramuscular Administration



  Caution should be taken when administering INVANZ intramuscularly to avoid inadvertent injection into a blood vessel [see  Dosage and Administration (2.7)  ]  .



    5.6 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  As with other antibiotics, prolonged use of INVANZ may result in overgrowth of non-susceptible organisms. Repeated evaluation of the patient's condition is essential. If superinfection occurs during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.



 Prescribing INVANZ in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.



    5.7 Laboratory Tests



  While INVANZ possesses toxicity similar to the beta-lactam group of antibiotics, periodic assessment of organ system function, including renal, hepatic, and hematopoietic, is advisable during prolonged therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
