<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="invega0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Increased mortality in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Cerebrovascular adverse reactions, including stroke, in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Neuroleptic malignant syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  QT prolongation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Tardive dyskinesia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Metabolic changes [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Orthostatic hypotension and syncope [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Leukopenia, neutropenia, and agranulocytosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Hyperprolactinemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Potential for cognitive and motor impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Dysphagia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Priapism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
 *  Disruption of body temperature regulation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and occurring at least twice as often as placebo) were injection site reaction, weight increased, headache, upper respiratory tract infection, akathisia, and parkinsonism. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-JANSSEN (1-800-526-7736) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Patient Exposure



 The data described in this section include data from two clinical trials. One is a long-term maintenance trial, in which 506 subjects with schizophrenia received several doses of the 1-month paliperidone palmitate extended-release injectable suspension during the open-label phase, of which 379 subjects continued to receive a single injection of INVEGA TRINZATM during the open-label phase, and 160 subjects were subsequently randomized to receive at least one dose of INVEGA TRINZATM and 145 subjects received placebo during the double-blind placebo-controlled phase. The mean (SD) duration of exposure during the double-blind phase was 150 (79) days in the placebo group and 175 (90) days in the INVEGA TRINZATM group. The other is a Phase 1 study (N=308), which included patients with schizophrenia who received a single injection of INVEGA TRINZATM concomitantly with other oral antipsychotics.



   Adverse Reactions in a Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled (Long-Term Maintenance) Clinical Trial



     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions:  The most common adverse reactions (incidence at least 5% in the open-label phase, or in the INVEGA TRINZATM group and at least twice the incidence in the placebo group during the double-blind phase) were injection site reaction, weight increased, headache, upper respiratory tract infection, akathisia, and parkinsonism.



     Discontinuation of Treatment Due to Adverse Events:  The percentages of subjects who discontinued due to adverse events in the long-term maintenance trial were 5.1% during the open-label phase. During the double-blind phase, no INVEGA TRINZATM-treated subject and one placebo-treated subject discontinued due to adverse events.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More in INVEGA TRINZATM-Treated Patients:  The safety profile of INVEGA TRINZATM was similar to that seen with the 1-month paliperidone extended-release injectable suspension. Table 8 lists the adverse reactions reported in a long-term maintenance trial in subjects with schizophrenia.



 Table 8. Incidences of Adverse Reactions 2% or More of INVEGA TRINZATM-Treated Patients (and Greater than Placebo) for the Open-Label and Double-Blind Phases of a Long-Term Maintenance Trial in Patients with Schizophrenia 
                                           --- Open Label-----   ------------ Double Blind -------------   
                                           Paliperidone Palmitate        Placebo           INVEGA TRINZATM      
 System Organ Class                              (N=506)               (N=145)               (N=160)          
   Adverse Reaction                                 %                     %                     %             
  
 Table includes adverse reactions that were reported in 2% or more of subjects in the INVEGA TRINZATM group during the double-blind phase and which occurred at greater incidence than in the placebo group.   
  
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                       
   Injection site reaction                          12                    0                     3             
   Infections and infestations                                                                                
   Upper respiratory tract infection                5                     4                     10            
   Urinary tract infection                          &lt;1                    1                     3             
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                         
   Weight increased                                 10                    3                     9             
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                   
   Akathisia                                        5                     2                     5             
   Headache                                         7                     4                     9             
   Parkinsonism                                     5                     0                     4             
            Demographic Differences
 

 An examination of population subgroups in the long-term maintenance trial did not reveal any evidence of differences in safety on the basis of age, gender, or race alone; however, there were few subjects 65 years of age and older.



   Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS)



 Data from the long-term maintenance trial provided information regarding EPS. Several methods were used to measure EPS: (1) the Simpson-Angus global score which broadly evaluates parkinsonism, (2) the Barnes Akathisia Rating Scale global clinical rating score which evaluates akathisia, (3) the Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale scores which evaluates dyskinesia, and (4) use of anticholinergic medications to treat EPS (Table 9), and (5) incidence of spontaneous reports of EPS (Table 10).



 Table 9. Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS) Assessed by Incidence of Rating Scales and Use of Anticholinergic Medication 
                                                                 Percentage of Subjects   
                                             Open-label Phase     Double-blind Phase    
                                           Paliperidone Palmitate        Placebo           INVEGA TRINZATM      
 Scale                                           (N=506)%              (N=145)%              (N=160)%         
  
 Parkinsonism                                       6                     3                     6             
 Akathisia                                          3                     1                     4             
 Dyskinesia                                         1                     3                     3             
 Use of Anticholinergic Medications                 11                    9                     11            
         Table 10. Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS)-Related Events by MedDRA Preferred Term 
                                                             Percentage of Subjects   
                                      Open-label Phase        Double-blind Phase     
                                   Paliperidone Palmitate           Placebo             INVEGA TRINZATM       
 EPS Group                                (N=506)%                 (N=145)%                (N=160)%           
  
 Parkinsonism group includes: Cogwheel rigidity, drooling, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, muscle tightness, musculoskeletal stiffness, parkinsonism   
 Hyperkinesia group includes: Akathisia, restlessness   
 Dystonia group includes: Blepharospasm, dystonia, muscle spasms   
  
 Overall percentage of subjects with EPS-related adverse events             10                        3                       8              
 Parkinsonism                                 4                        0                       4              
 Hyperkinesia                                 5                        2                       5              
 Tremor                                       2                        0                       1              
 Dyskinesia                                  &lt;1                        1                       1              
 Dystonia                                     1                        0                       1              
          After injection of INVEGA TRINZATM in the open-label phase, 12 (3.2%) subjects had EPS that were new or worsened in severity, with events under the groupings of hyperkinesia (1.6%) and parkinsonism (1.3%) being the most common. After injection of INVEGA TRINZATM in the open-label or double-blind phases, one subject discontinued from the open-label phase due to restlessness.
 

 An examination of the time to EPS during the double-blind phase showed no clustering of these events at visits that would be expected to correspond to median peak plasma concentrations of paliperidone for subjects randomized to INVEGA TRINZATM.



   Dystonia



 Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



   Pain Assessment and Local Injection Site Reactions



     Investigator ratings of injection site.  Redness and swelling were observed in 2% or less of subjects in the INVEGA TRINZATM and placebo groups during the double-blind phase of the long-term maintenance study, and were rated mild based on investigator ratings using a 4-point scale (0=absent; 1=mild; 2=moderate; 3=severe). There were no reports of induration in either group during the double-blind phase and no subjects discontinued due to INVEGA TRINZATM injection.



     Subject ratings of injection site pain.  Subject evaluations of injection pain during the double-blind phase also were similar for placebo and INVEGA TRINZATM.



 Subject ratings of injection site pain in the single-dose Phase 1 study allowed for assessment of the temporal course of injection site pain. Residual injection pain peaked 1 or 6 hours after injection, and trended downward 3 days after the injection. Deltoid injections were numerically more painful than gluteal injections, although most pain ratings were below 10 mm on a 100-mm scale.



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Trial Evaluation of INVEGA TRINZATM



 The following additional adverse reactions were identified in the long-term maintenance trial. The following list does not include reactions: 1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, 2) for which a drug cause was remote, 3) which were so general as to be uninformative, 4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or 5) occurred at an incidence lower than that of placebo-treated patients.



   Cardiac disorders:  tachycardia



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  nausea, vomiting



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  hyperinsulinemia



   Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety



   Additional Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with the 1-Month Paliperidone Palmitate Extended-Release Injectable Suspension



 The following is a list of additional adverse reactions that have been reported in clinical trials with the 1-month paliperidone palmitate extended-release injectable suspension:



   Cardiac disorders:  atrioventricular block first degree, bradycardia, bundle branch block, palpitations, postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  vertigo



   Eye disorders:  eye movement disorder, eye rolling, oculogyric crisis, vision blurred



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal discomfort/abdominal pain upper, diarrhea, dry mouth, toothache



   General disorders and administration site conditions  : asthenia, fatigue



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Investigations:  electrocardiogram abnormal



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  decreased appetite, increased appetite



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  back pain, myalgia, pain in extremity, joint stiffness, muscle spasms, muscle twitching, nuchal rigidity



   Nervous system disorders:  bradykinesia, cerebrovascular accident, convulsion, dizziness, dizziness postural, dysarthria, hypertonia, lethargy, oromandibular dystonia, psychomotor hyperactivity, syncope



   Psychiatric disorders:  agitation, nightmare



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  breast discharge, erectile dysfunction, gynecomastia, menstrual disorder, menstruation delayed, menstruation irregular, sexual dysfunction



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  cough



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  drug eruption, pruritus, pruritus generalized, rash, urticaria



   Vascular disorders  : hypertension



   Additional Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with Oral Paliperidone



 The following is a list of additional adverse reactions that have been reported in clinical trials with oral paliperidone:



   Cardiac disorders  : bundle branch block left, sinus arrhythmia



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : abdominal pain, constipation, flatulence, small intestinal obstruction



   General disorders and administration site conditions  : edema, edema peripheral



   Immune system disorders  : anaphylactic reaction



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  : arthralgia, musculoskeletal pain, torticollis, trismus



   Nervous system disorders  : grand mal convulsion, parkinsonian gait, transient ischemic attack



   Psychiatric disorders:  sleep disorder



   Reproductive system and breast disorders  : breast engorgement, breast tenderness/breast pain, retrograde ejaculation



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  nasal congestion, pharyngolaryngeal pain, pneumonia aspiration



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  rash papular



   Vascular disorders  : hypotension, ischemia



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of paliperidone; because these reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: angioedema, ileus, swollen tongue, thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura, urinary incontinence, and urinary retention.



 Cases of anaphylactic reaction after injection with the 1-month paliperidone palmitate extended-release suspension have been reported during postmarketing experience in patients who have previously tolerated oral risperidone or oral paliperidone.



 Paliperidone is the major active metabolite of risperidone. Adverse reactions reported with oral risperidone and risperidone long-acting injection can be found in the  Adverse Reactions (6)  sections of the package inserts for those products.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  

    *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  INVEGA TRINZATM is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. (5.1) 
 *  INVEGA TRINZATM is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (e.g. stroke, transient ischemic attack, including fatalities). INVEGA TRINZATM is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis (  5.2  ) 
 *   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation of drug and close monitoring (  5.3  ) 
 *   QT Prolongation: Avoid use with drugs that also increase QT interval and in patients with risk factors for prolonged QT interval (  5.4  ) 
 *   Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue drug if clinically appropriate (  5.5  ) 
 *  *   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus: Monitor for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Monitor glucose regularly in patients with diabetes or at risk for diabetes. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Dyslipidemia: Undesirable alterations have been observed. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Weight Gain: Significant weight gain has been reported. Monitor weight gain. (  5.6  ) 
    Metabolic Changes: Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cer e brovascular risk. These metabolic changes include: 
 *   Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope: Use with caution in patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease and patients predisposed to hypotension (  5.7  ) 
 *   Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis: Monitor complete blood count in patients with a history of a clinically significant low white blood cell count (WBC) or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Consider discontinuation if clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors (  5.8  ) 
 *   Hyperprolactinemia: Prolactin elevations occur and persist during chronic administration (  5.9  ) 
 *   Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment: Use caution when operating machinery (  5.10  ) 
 *   Seizures: Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. INVEGA TRINZATM is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



    5.2 Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  In placebo-controlled trials with risperidone, aripiprazole, and olanzapine in elderly subjects with dementia, there was a higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (cerebrovascular accidents and transient ischemic attacks) including fatalities compared to placebo-treated subjects. No studies have been conducted with oral paliperidone, the 1-month paliperidone palmitate extended-release injectable suspension, or INVEGA TRINZATM in elderly patients with dementia. These medications are not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with antipsychotic drugs, including paliperidone. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to identify cases in which the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: (1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and (3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. Consideration should be given to the long-acting nature of INVEGA TRINZATM. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for uncomplicated NMS.



 If a patient appears to require antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, reintroduction of drug therapy should be closely monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4 QT Prolongation



  Paliperidone causes a modest increase in the corrected QT (QTc) interval. The use of paliperidone should be avoided in combination with other drugs that are known to prolong QTc including Class 1A (e.g., quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic medications, antipsychotic medications (e.g., chlorpromazine, thioridazine), antibiotics (e.g., gatifloxacin, moxifloxacin), or any other class of medications known to prolong the QTc interval. Paliperidone should also be avoided in patients with congenital long QT syndrome and in patients with a history of cardiac arrhythmias.



 Certain circumstances may increase the risk of the occurrence of Torsades de pointes and/or sudden death in association with the use of drugs that prolong the QTc interval, including (1) bradycardia; (2) hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia; (3) concomitant use of other drugs that prolong the QTc interval; and (4) presence of congenital prolongation of the QT interval.



 The effects of paliperidone on the QT interval were evaluated in a double-blind, active-controlled (moxifloxacin 400 mg single dose), multicenter Thorough QT study with oral paliperidone in adult patients, and in four fixed-dose efficacy studies and one maintenance study of the 1-month paliperidone palmitate injectable product.



 In the Thorough QT study (n=141), the 8 mg dose of immediate-release oral paliperidone (n=50) showed a mean placebo-subtracted increase from baseline in QTcLD (QT interval corrected for heart rate using the population specified linear derived method) of 12.3 msec (90% CI: 8.9; 15.6) on day 8 at 1.5 hours post-dose. The mean steady-state peak plasma concentration for this 8 mg dose of paliperidone immediate release (Cmax ss=113 ng/mL) was approximately 2-fold the exposure with the maximum recommended 819 mg dose of INVEGA TRINZATM administered in the deltoid muscle (predicted median Cmax ss=56 ng/mL). In this same study, a 4 mg dose of the immediate-release oral formulation of paliperidone, for which Cmax ss=35 ng/mL, showed an increased placebo-subtracted QTcLD of 6.8 msec (90% CI: 3.6; 10.1) on day 2 at 1.5 hours post-dose.



 In the four fixed-dose efficacy studies of the 1-month paliperidone palmitate injectable product, no subject had a change in QTcLD exceeding 60 msec and no subject had a QTcLD value of &gt; 500 msec at any time point. In the maintenance study, no subject had a QTcLD change &gt; 60 msec, and one subject had a QTcLD value of 507 msec (Bazett's QT corrected interval [QTcB] value of 483 msec); this latter subject also had a heart rate of 45 beats per minute.



 In the long-term maintenance trial of INVEGA TRINZATM in subjects with schizophrenia, an increase in QTcLD exceeding 60 msec was observed in 1 subject (&lt; 1%) in the open-label phase, no subject had an increase in QTcLD exceeding 60 msec after treatment with INVEGA TRINZATM in the double-blind phase, and no subject had a QTcLD value of &gt; 480 msec at any point in the study.



    5.5 Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to predict which patients will develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible appear to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase, but the syndrome can develop after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses, although this is uncommon.



 There is no known treatment for established tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment itself may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and may thus mask the underlying process. The effect of symptomatic suppression on the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, INVEGA TRINZATM should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient treated with INVEGA TRINZATM, drug discontinuation should be considered. Consideration should be given to the long-acting nature of INVEGA TRINZATM. However, some patients may require treatment with INVEGA TRINZATM despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.6 Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and body weight gain. While all of the drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus



 Hyperglycemia and diabetes mellitus, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, have been reported in patients treated with all atypical antipsychotics. These cases were, for the most part, seen in post-marketing clinical use and epidemiologic studies, not in clinical trials. Hyperglycemia and diabetes have been reported in trial subjects treated with INVEGA TRINZATM. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse events is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



 Data from the long-term maintenance trial with INVEGA TRINZATM in subjects with schizophrenia are presented in Table 5.



 Table 5. Change in Fasting Glucose from the Long-Term Maintenance Trial with INVEGA TRINZATM in Subjects with Schizophrenia 
                            Open-Label Phase (relative to open-label baseline)  Double-Blind Phase (relative to double-blind baseline)   
                             Paliperidone Palmitate             Placebo                INVEGA TRINZATM        
  
                             Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
                                     n=397                      n=120                      n=138              
  Serum GlucoseChange from baseline               1.2                       -1.6                       -1.2              
                             Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
                                     n=397                      n=128                      n=148              
  Serum GlucoseNormal to High              2.3%                       2.3%                       4.1%              
  (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)             (9/397)                    (3/128)                    (6/148)            
            Dyslipidemia
 

 Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics.



 Data from the long-term maintenance trial with INVEGA TRINZATM in subjects with schizophrenia are presented in Table 6.



 Table 6. Change in Fasting Lipids from the Long-Term Maintenance Trial with INVEGA TRINZATM in Subjects with Schizophrenia 
                            Open-Label Phase (relative to open-label baseline)  Double-Blind Phase (relative to double-blind baseline)   
                             Paliperidone Palmitate             Placebo                INVEGA TRINZATM        
  
                             Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
  Cholesterol                        n=400                      n=120                      n=138              
  Change from baseline                 0.5                       -0.4                        0.9              
  LDL                                n=396                      n=119                      n=138              
  Change from baseline                 1.1                       -0.4                        1.1              
  HDL                                n=397                      n=119                      n=138              
  Change from baseline                -0.2                       -0.5                       -1.3              
  Triglycerides                      n=400                      n=120                      n=138              
  Change from baseline                 0.1                       -2.0                        5.1              
                             Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
  Cholesterol Normal to High              2.0%                       3.9%                       1.4%              
  (&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)             (8/400)                    (5/128)                    (2/148)            
  LDL Normal to High                  0.3%                       0.8%                        0%               
  (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)             (1/396)                    (1/127)                    (0/148)            
  HDL Normal to Low                   8.6%                       9.4%                       13.5%             
  (&gt;=40 mg/dL to &lt;40 mg/dL)            (34/397)                   (12/127)                   (20/148)            
  Triglycerides Normal to High              4.5%                       1.6%                       8.1%              
  (&lt;150 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)            (18/400)                    (2/128)                   (12/148)            
            Weight Gain
 

 Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Clinical monitoring of weight is recommended.



 Data on mean changes in body weight and the proportion of subjects meeting a weight gain criterion of &gt;= 7% of body weight from the long-term maintenance trial with INVEGA TRINZATM in subjects with schizophrenia are presented in Table 7.



 Table 7. Change in Body Weight (kg) and the Proportion of Subjects with &gt;= 7% Gain in Body Weight from the Long-Term Maintenance Trial with INVEGA TRINZATM in Subjects with Schizophrenia 
                            Open-Label Phase (relative to open-label baseline)  Double-Blind Phase (relative to double-blind baseline)   
                             Paliperidone Palmitate             Placebo                INVEGA TRINZATM        
                                      n=466                      n=142                      n=157             
  
  Weight (kg)Change from baseline              1.42                       -1.28                      0.94              
  Weight Gain &gt;= 7% increase from baseline              15.2%                      0.7%                       9.6%              
             5.7 Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope
 

  Paliperidone can induce orthostatic hypotension and syncope in some patients because of its alpha-adrenergic blocking activity. In the long-term maintenance trial, syncope was reported in &lt; 1% (1/506) of subjects treated with the 1-month paliperidone palmitate extended-release injectable suspension during the open-label phase; there were no cases reported during the double-blind phase in either treatment group. In the long-term maintenance trial, orthostatic hypotension was reported as an adverse event by &lt; 1% (1/506) of subjects treated with the 1-month paliperidone palmitate extended-release injectable suspension and &lt; 1% (1/379) of subjects after receiving a single-dose of INVEGA TRINZATM during the open-label phase; there were no cases reported during the double-blind phase in either treatment group.



 INVEGA TRINZATM should be used with caution in patients with known cardiovascular disease (e.g., heart failure, history of myocardial infarction or ischemia, conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, or conditions that predispose the patient to hypotension (e.g., dehydration, hypovolemia, and treatment with antihypertensive medications). Monitoring of orthostatic vital signs should be considered in patients who are vulnerable to hypotension.



    5.8 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



  In clinical trial and/or postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia and neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents, including INVEGA TRINZATM. Agranulocytosis has also been reported.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC)/absolute neutrophil count (ANC) and history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. In patients with a history of a clinically significant low WBC/ANC or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia, perform a complete blood count (CBC) frequently during the first few months of therapy. In such patients, consider discontinuation of INVEGA TRINZATM at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Monitor patients with clinically significant neutropenia for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Discontinue INVEGA TRINZATM in patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm  3  ) follow their WBC until recovery.



    5.9 Hyperprolactinemia



  Like other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2receptors, paliperidone elevates prolactin levels and the elevation persists during chronic administration. Paliperidone has a prolactin-elevating effect similar to that seen with risperidone, a drug that is associated with higher levels of prolactin than other antipsychotic drugs.



 Hyperprolactinemia, regardless of etiology, may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotrophin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported in patients receiving prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male subjects.



 Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin dependent in vitro  , a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is considered in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. An increase in the incidence of pituitary gland, mammary gland, and pancreatic islet cell neoplasia (mammary adenocarcinomas, pituitary and pancreatic adenomas) was observed in the risperidone carcinogenicity studies conducted in mice and rats [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans, but the available evidence is too limited to be conclusive.



 In a long-term maintenance trial of INVEGA TRINZATM, elevations of prolactin to above the reference range (&gt;13.13 ng/mL in males and &gt;26.72 ng/mL in females) relative to open-label baseline at any time during the double-blind phase were noted in a higher percentage of males in the INVEGA TRINZATM group than in the placebo group (46% vs. 25%) and in a higher percentage of females in the INVEGA TRINZATM group than in the placebo group (32% vs. 15%). During the double-blind phase, 1 female (2.4%) in the INVEGA TRINZATM group experienced an adverse reaction of amenorrhea, while no potentially prolactin-related adverse reactions were noted among females in the placebo group. There were no potentially prolactin-related adverse reactions among males in either group.



 Prior to the double-blind phase (during the 29-week open-label phase of the long-term maintenance trial), the mean (SD) serum prolactin values at baseline in males (N=368) were 17.1 (13.55) ng/mL and 51.6 (40.85) ng/mL in females (N=122). Twelve weeks after a single injection of INVEGA TRINZATM at the end of the open-label phase, mean (SD) prolactin values were 25.8 (13.49) ng/mL in males (N=322) and 70.6 (40.23) ng/mL in females (N=107). During the open-label phases 27% of females and 42% of males experienced elevations of prolactin above the reference range relative to baseline, and a higher proportion of females experienced potentially prolactin-related adverse reactions compared to males (7.9% vs. 3.7%). Amenorrhea (4.7%) and galactorrhea (3.1%) were the most commonly observed (&gt;=3%) potentially prolactin-related adverse reactions in females. Among males in the open-label phase, no potentially prolactin-related adverse reaction was observed with a rate greater than 3%.



    5.10 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  Somnolence, sedation, and dizziness were reported as adverse reactions in subjects treated with INVEGA TRINZATM [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Antipsychotics, including INVEGA TRINZATM, have the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about performing activities requiring mental alertness, such as operating hazardous machinery or operating a motor vehicle, until they are reasonably certain that paliperidone therapy does not adversely affect them.



    5.11 Seizures



  In the long-term maintenance trial there were no reports of seizures or convulsions. In the pivotal clinical studies with the 1-month paliperidone palmitate extended-release injectable suspension which included four fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies in subjects with schizophrenia, &lt;1% (1/1293) of subjects treated with the 1-month injection experienced an adverse event of convulsion compared with &lt;1% (1/510) of placebo-treated subjects who experienced an adverse event of grand mal convulsion.



 Like other antipsychotic drugs, INVEGA TRINZATM should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or other conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in patients 65 years or older.



    5.12 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. INVEGA TRINZATM and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia.



    5.13 Priapism



  Drugs with alpha-adrenergic blocking effects have been reported to induce priapism. Although no cases of priapism have been reported in clinical trials with INVEGA TRINZATM, priapism has been reported with oral paliperidone during postmarketing surveillance. Severe priapism may require surgical intervention.



    5.14 Disruption of Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing INVEGA TRINZATM to patients who will be experiencing conditions which may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
