<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="invega1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Increased mortality in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [see    Boxed Warning    and    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Cerebrovascular adverse reactions, including stroke, in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [  see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Neuroleptic malignant syndrome [  see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  QT prolongation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Tardive dyskinesia [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Metabolic changes [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Orthostatic hypotension and syncope [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Leukopenia, neutropenia, and agranulocytosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Hyperprolactinemia [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Potential for cognitive and motor impairment [  see    Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Dysphagia [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Priapism [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
 *  Disruption of body temperature regulation [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.14)  ]  
    The most common (at least 5% in any INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  group) and likely drug-related (adverse events for which the drug rate is at least twice the placebo rate) adverse reactions from the double-blind, placebo-controlled trials in subjects with schizophrenia were injection site reactions, somnolence/sedation, dizziness, akathisia, and extrapyramidal disorder  .  No occurrences of adverse events reached this threshold in the long-term double-blind, placebo-controlled study in subjects with schizoaffective disorder.
 

 The data described in this section are derived from a clinical trial database consisting of a total of 3817 subjects (approximately 1705 patient-years exposure) with schizophrenia who received at least one dose of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  in the recommended dose range of 39 mg to 234 mg and a total of 510 subjects with schizophrenia who received placebo. Among the 3817 INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  -treated subjects, 1293 received INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  in four fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials (one 9-week and three 13-week studies), 849 received INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  in the maintenance trial (median exposure 229 days during the initial 33-week open-label phase of this study, of whom 205 continued to receive INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  during the double-blind placebo-controlled phase of this study [median exposure 171 days]), and 1675 received INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  in five non-placebo controlled trials (three noninferiority active-comparator trials, one long-term open-label pharmacokinetic and safety study, and an injection site [deltoid-gluteal] cross-over trial). One of the 13-week studies included a 234 mg INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  initiation dose followed by treatment with either 39 mg, 156 mg, or 234 mg every 4 weeks.



 The safety of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was also evaluated in a long-term study in adult subjects with schizoaffective disorder. A total of 667 subjects received INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  during the initial 25-week open-label period of this study (median exposure 147 days); 164 subjects continued to receive INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  during the 15-month double-blind placebo-controlled period of this study (median exposure 446 days). Adverse reactions that occurred more frequently in the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  than the placebo group (a 2% difference or more between groups) were weight increased, nasopharyngitis, headache, hyperprolactinemia, and pyrexia.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and occurring at least twice as often as placebo) were injection site reactions, somnolence/sedation, dizziness, akathisia, and extrapyramidal disorder. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-JANSSEN (1-800-526-7736) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials



 Table 10 lists the adverse reactions reported in 2% or more of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  -treated subjects and at a greater proportion than in the placebo group with schizophrenia in the four fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials.



 Table 10. Incidence of Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 2% of INVEGA SUSTENNA(r)-Treated Subjects (and greater than Placebo) with Schizophrenia in Four Fixed-Dose, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                                             INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)     
 System Organ Class               Placebo      39 mg       78 mg       156 mg    234/39 mg   234/156 mg  234/234 mg   
   Adverse Event                  (N=510)     (N=130)     (N=302)     (N=312)     (N=160)     (N=165)     (N=163)     
  
 Percentages are rounded to whole numbers. Table includes adverse events that were reported in 2% or more of subjects in any of the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  dose groups and which occurred at greater incidence than in the placebo group.   
 Adverse events for which the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  incidence was equal to or less than placebo are not listed in the table, but included the following: dyspepsia, psychotic disorder, schizophrenia, and tremor. The following terms were combined: somnolence/sedation, breast tenderness/breast pain, abdominal discomfort/abdominal pain upper/stomach discomfort, and tachycardia/sinus tachycardia/heart rate increased. All injection site reaction-related adverse events were collapsed and are grouped under "Injection site reactions".   
  
 Total percentage of subjects with adverse event      70          75          68          69          63          60          63       
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
   Abdominal discomfort/abdominal pain upper      2           2           4           4           1           2           4        
   Diarrhea                          2           0           3           2           1           2           2        
   Dry mouth                         1           3           1           0           1           1           1        
   Nausea                            3           4           4           3           2           2           2        
   Toothache                         1           1           1           3           1           2           3        
   Vomiting                          4           5           4           2           3           2           2        
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
   Asthenia                          0           2           1           &lt;1          0           1           1        
   Fatigue                           1           1           2           2           1           2           1        
   Injection site reactions          2           0           4           6           9           7           10       
   Infections and infestations     
   Nasopharyngitis                   2           0           2           2           4           2           2        
   Upper respiratory tract infection      2           2           2           2           1           2           4        
   Urinary tract infection           1           0           1           &lt;1          1           1           2        
   Investigations                 
   Weight increased                  1           4           4           1           1           1           2        
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
   Back pain                         2           2           1           3           1           1           1        
   Musculoskeletal stiffness         1           1           &lt;1          &lt;1          1           1           2        
   Myalgia                           1           2           1           &lt;1          1           0           2        
   Pain in extremity                 1           0           2           2           2           3           0        
   Nervous system disorders       
   Akathisia                         3           2           2           3           1           5           6        
   Dizziness                         1           6           2           4           1           4           2        
   Extrapyramidal disorder           1           5           2           3           1           0           0        
   Headache                          12          11          11          15          11          7           6        
   Somnolence/sedation               3           5           7           4           1           5           5        
   Psychiatric disorders          
   Agitation                         7           10          5           9           8           5           4        
   Anxiety                           7           8           5           3           5           6           6        
   Nightmare                         &lt;1          2           0           0           0           0           0        
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
   Cough                             1           2           3           1           0           1           1        
   Vascular disorders             
   Hypertension                      1           2           1           1           1           1           0        
                Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Trial Evaluation of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  
 

 The following list does not include reactions: 1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, 2) for which a drug cause was remote, 3) which were so general as to be uninformative, or 4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications.



   Cardiac disorders:  atrioventricular block first degree, bradycardia, bundle branch block, palpitations, postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome, tachycardia



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  vertigo



   Eye disorders:  eye movement disorder, eye rolling, oculogyric crisis, vision blurred



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  constipation, dyspepsia, flatulence, salivary hypersecretion



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Investigations:  alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, electrocardiogram abnormal



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  decreased appetite, hyperinsulinemia, increased appetite



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  arthralgia, joint stiffness, muscle rigidity, muscle spasms, muscle tightness, muscle twitching, nuchal rigidity



   Nervous system disorders:  bradykinesia, cerebrovascular accident, convulsion, dizziness postural, drooling, dysarthria, dyskinesia, dystonia, hypertonia, lethargy, oromandibular dystonia, parkinsonism, psychomotor hyperactivity, syncope



   Psychiatric disorders:  insomnia, restlessness



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  amenorrhea, breast discharge, erectile dysfunction, galactorrhea, gynecomastia, menstrual disorder, menstruation delayed, menstruation irregular, sexual dysfunction



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  nasal congestion



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  drug eruption, pruritus, pruritus generalized, rash, urticaria



   Discontinuations Due to Adverse Events



 The percentage of subjects who discontinued due to adverse events in the four fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled schizophrenia trials were similar for INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  - and placebo-treated subjects.



 The percentage of subjects who discontinued due to adverse events in the open-label period of the long-term study in subjects with schizoaffective disorder was 7.5%. During the double-blind, placebo-controlled period of that study, the percentages of subjects who discontinued due to adverse events were 5.5% and 1.8% in INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  - and placebo-treated subjects, respectively.



   Dose-Related Adverse Reactions



 Based on the pooled data from the four fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials in subjects with schizophrenia, among the adverse reactions that occurred at &gt;= 2% incidence in the subjects treated with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  , only akathisia increased with dose. Hyperprolactinemia also exhibited a dose relationship, but did not occur at &gt;= 2% incidence in INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  -treated subjects from the four fixed-dose studies.



   Demographic Differences



 An examination of population subgroups in the double-blind placebo-controlled trials did not reveal any evidence of differences in safety on the basis of age, gender, or race alone; however, there were few subjects &gt;= 65 years of age.



   Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS)



 Pooled data from the two double-blind, placebo-controlled, 13-week, fixed-dose trials in adult subjects with schizophrenia provided information regarding EPS. Several methods were used to measure EPS: (1) the Simpson-Angus global score (mean change from baseline or score at the end of trial) which broadly evaluates Parkinsonism, (2) the Barnes Akathisia Rating Scale global clinical rating score (mean change from baseline or score at the end of trial) which evaluates akathisia, (3) use of anticholinergic medications to treat EPS, (4) the Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale scores (mean change from baseline or scores at the end of trial) (Table 11), and (5) incidence of spontaneous reports of EPS (Table 12).



 Table 11. Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS) Assessed by Incidence of Rating Scales and Use of Anticholinergic Medication - Schizophrenia Studies in Adults 
                                           Percentage of Subjects   
                                                            INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)     
                                               Placebo           39 mg            78 mg           156 mg        
 Scale                                         (N=262)          (N=130)          (N=223)          (N=228)       
  
 Parkinsonism                                     9               12               10                6          
 Akathisia                                        5                5                6                5          
 Dyskinesia                                       3                4                6                4          
 Use of Anticholinergic Medications              12               10               12               11          
          Table 12. Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS)-Related Events by MedDRA Preferred Term - Schizophrenia Studies in Adults 
                                           Percentage of Subjects   
                                                            INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)     
                                               Placebo           39 mg            78 mg           156 mg        
 EPS Group                                     (N=262)          (N=130)          (N=223)          (N=228)       
  
 Parkinsonism group includes: Extrapyramidal disorder, hypertonia, musculoskeletal stiffness, parkinsonism, drooling, masked facies, muscle tightness, hypokinesiaHyperkinesia group includes: Akathisia, restless legs syndrome, restlessnessDyskinesia group includes: Dyskinesia, choreoathetosis, muscle twitching, myoclonus, tardive dyskinesiaDystonia group includes: Dystonia, muscle spasms   
  
 Overall percentage of subjects with EPS-related adverse events        10               12               11               11          
 Parkinsonism                                     5                6                6                4          
 Hyperkinesia                                     2                2                2                4          
 Tremor                                           3                2                2                3          
 Dyskinesia                                       1                2                3                1          
 Dystonia                                         0                1                1                2          
           The results across all phases of the maintenance trial in subjects with schizophrenia exhibited comparable findings. In the 9-week, fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, the proportions of Parkinsonism and akathisia assessed by incidence of rating scales were higher in the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  156 mg group (18% and 11%, respectively) than in the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  78 mg group (9% and 5%, respectively) and placebo group (7% and 4%, respectively).
 

 In the 13-week study in subjects with schizophrenia involving 234 mg initiation dosing, the incidence of any EPS was similar to that of the placebo group (8%), but exhibited a dose-related pattern with 6%, 10%, and 11% in the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  234/39 mg, 234/156 mg, and 234/234 mg groups, respectively. Hyperkinesia was the most frequent category of EPS-related adverse events in this study, and was reported at a similar rate between the placebo (4.9%) and INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  234/156 mg (4.8%) and 234/234 mg (5.5%) groups, but at a lower rate in the 234/39 mg group (1.3%).



 In the long-term study in subjects with schizoaffective disorder, the EPS during the 25-week open-label INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  treatment were hyperkinesia (12.3%), parkinsonism (8.7%), tremor (3.4%), dyskinesia (2.5%), and dystonia (2.1%). During the 15-month double-blind treatment, the incidence of any EPS was similar to that of the placebo group (8.5% and 7.1% respectively). The most commonly reported treatment-emergent EPS-related adverse events (&gt;2%) in any treatment group in the double-blind phase of the study (INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  versus placebo) were hyperkinesia (3.7% vs. 2.9%), parkinsonism (3.0% vs. 1.8%), and tremor (1.2% vs. 2.4%).



   Dystonia



 Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



   Laboratory Test Abnormalities



 In the pooled data from the two double-blind, placebo-controlled, 13-week, fixed-dose trials in subjects with schizophrenia, a between-group comparison revealed no medically important differences between INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  and placebo in the proportions of subjects experiencing potentially clinically significant changes in routine serum chemistry, hematology, or urinalysis parameters. Similarly, there were no differences between INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  and placebo in the incidence of discontinuations due to changes in hematology, urinalysis, or serum chemistry, including mean changes from baseline in fasting glucose, insulin, c-peptide, triglycerides, HDL, LDL, and total cholesterol measurements. However, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was associated with increases in serum prolactin  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ].  The results from the 13-week study involving 234 mg initiation dosing, the 9-week, fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, and the double-blind phase of the maintenance trial in subjects with schizophrenia exhibited comparable findings.



   Pain Assessment and Local Injection Site Reactions



 In the pooled data from the two 13-week, fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials in subjects with schizophrenia, the mean intensity of injection pain reported by subjects using a visual analog scale (0 = no pain to 100 = unbearably painful) decreased in all treatment groups from the first to the last injection (placebo: 10.9 to 9.8; 39 mg: 10.3 to 7.7; 78 mg: 10.0 to 9.2; 156 mg: 11.1 to 8.8). The results from both the 9-week, fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial and the double-blind phase of the maintenance trial exhibited comparable findings.



 In the 13-week study involving 234 mg initiation dosing in subjects with schizophrenia, occurrences of induration, redness, or swelling, as assessed by blinded study personnel, were infrequent, generally mild, decreased over time, and similar in incidence between the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  and placebo groups. Investigator ratings of injection pain were similar for the placebo and INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  groups. Investigator evaluations of the injection site after the first injection for redness, swelling, induration, and pain were rated as absent for 69-100% of subjects in both the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  and placebo groups. At Day 92, investigators rated absence of redness, swelling, induration, and pain in 95-100% of subjects in both the INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  and placebo groups.



   Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with Oral Paliperidone



 The following is a list of additional adverse reactions that have been reported in clinical trials with oral paliperidone:



   Cardiac disorders  : bundle branch block left, sinus arrhythmia



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : abdominal pain, small intestinal obstruction



   General disorders and administration site conditions  : edema, edema peripheral



   Immune system disorders  : anaphylactic reaction



   Infections and infestations:  rhinitis



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  : musculoskeletal pain, torticollis, trismus



   Nervous system disorders  : cogwheel rigidity, grand mal convulsion, parkinsonian gait, transient ischemic attack



   Psychiatric disorders:  sleep disorder



   Reproductive system and breast disorders  : breast engorgement, breast tenderness/breast pain, retrograde ejaculation



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  pharyngolaryngeal pain, pneumonia aspiration



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  rash papular



   Vascular disorders  : hypotension, ischemia



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of paliperidone; because these reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Reactions already listed in other parts of    ADVERSE REACTIONS (6)    , or those considered in    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (5)    are not listed here.



   Blood disorders:  thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : ileus



   Genitourinary disorders:  urinary incontinence, urinary retention



   Immune system disorders  : angioedema, swollen tongue



 Cases of anaphylactic reaction after injection with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  have been reported during postmarketing experience in patients who have previously tolerated oral risperidone or oral paliperidone.



   6.3 Adverse Reactions Reported With Risperidone

  Paliperidone is the major active metabolite of risperidone. Adverse reactions reported with oral risperidone and risperidone long-acting injection can be found in the  ADVERSE REACTIONS  sections of the package inserts for those products.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  

    *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  INVEGA SUSTENNA(r) is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. (5.1) 
 *  INVEGA SUSTENNA(r) is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (e.g. stroke, transient ischemic attack, including fatalities). INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis (  5.2  ) 
 *   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation of drug and close monitoring (  5.3  ) 
 *   QT Prolongation: Avoid use with drugs that also increase QT interval and in patients with risk factors for prolonged QT interval (  5.4  ) 
 *   Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue drug if clinically appropriate (  5.5  ) 
 *  *   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus: Monitor for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Monitor glucose regularly in patients with diabetes or at risk for diabetes. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Dyslipidemia: Undesirable alterations have been observed. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Weight Gain: Significant weight gain has been reported. Monitor weight gain. (  5.6  ) 
    Metabolic Changes: Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cer e brovascular risk. These metabolic changes include: 
 *   Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope: Use with caution in patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease and patients predisposed to hypotension (  5.7  ) 
 *   Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis: Monitor complete blood count in patients with a history of a clinically significant low white blood cell count (WBC) or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Consider discontinuation if clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors (  5.8  ) 
 *   Hyperprolactinemia: Prolactin elevations occur and persist during chronic administration (  5.9  ) 
 *   Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment: Use caution when operating machinery (  5.10  ) 
 *   Seizures: Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  (paliperidone palmitate) is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  ]  .



    5.2 Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  In placebo-controlled trials with risperidone, aripiprazole, and olanzapine in elderly subjects with dementia, there was a higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (cerebrovascular accidents and transient ischemic attacks) including fatalities compared to placebo-treated subjects. Oral paliperidone and INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  were not marketed at the time these studies were performed and are not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with antipsychotic drugs, including INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  .



 Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to identify cases in which the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: (1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and (3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for uncomplicated NMS.



 If a patient appears to require antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, reintroduction of drug therapy should be closely monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4 QT Prolongation



  Paliperidone causes a modest increase in the corrected QT (QTc) interval. The use of paliperidone should be avoided in combination with other drugs that are known to prolong QTc including Class 1A (e.g., quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic medications, antipsychotic medications (e.g., chlorpromazine, thioridazine), antibiotics (e.g., gatifloxacin, moxifloxacin), or any other class of medications known to prolong the QTc interval. Paliperidone should also be avoided in patients with congenital long QT syndrome and in patients with a history of cardiac arrhythmias.



 Certain circumstances may increase the risk of the occurrence of Torsades de pointes and/or sudden death in association with the use of drugs that prolong the QTc interval, including (1) bradycardia; (2) hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia; (3) concomitant use of other drugs that prolong the QTc interval; and (4) presence of congenital prolongation of the QT interval.



 The effects of oral paliperidone on the QT interval were evaluated in a double-blind, active-controlled (moxifloxacin 400 mg single dose), multicenter QT study in adults with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder, and in three placebo- and active-controlled 6-week, fixed-dose efficacy trials in adults with schizophrenia.



 In the QT study (n=141), the 8 mg dose of immediate-release oral paliperidone (n=50) showed a mean placebo-subtracted increase from baseline in QTcLD of 12.3 msec (90% CI: 8.9; 15.6) on day 8 at 1.5 hours post-dose. The mean steady-state peak plasma concentration for this 8 mg dose of paliperidone immediate release (Cmax ss= 113 ng/mL) was more than 2-fold the exposure observed with the maximum recommended 234 mg dose of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  administered in the deltoid muscle (predicted median Cmax ss= 50 ng/mL). In this same study, a 4 mg dose of the immediate-release oral formulation of paliperidone, for which Cmax ss= 35 ng/mL, showed an increased placebo-subtracted QTcLD of 6.8 msec (90% CI: 3.6; 10.1) on day 2 at 1.5 hours post-dose.



 In the three fixed-dose efficacy studies of oral paliperidone extended release in subjects with schizophrenia, electrocardiogram (ECG) measurements taken at various time points showed only one subject in the oral paliperidone 12 mg group had a change exceeding 60 msec at one time-point on Day 6 (increase of 62 msec).



 In the four fixed-dose efficacy studies of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  in subjects with schizophrenia and in the long-term study in subjects with schizoaffective disorder, no subject experienced a change in QTcLD exceeding 60 msec and no subject had a QTcLD value of &gt; 500 msec at any time point. In the maintenance study in subjects with schizophrenia, no subject had a QTcLD change &gt; 60 msec, and one subject had a QTcLD value of 507 msec (Bazett's QT corrected interval [QTcB] value of 483 msec); this latter subject also had a heart rate of 45 beats per minute.



    5.5 Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to predict which patients will develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible appear to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase, but the syndrome can develop after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses, although this is uncommon.



 There is no known treatment for established tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment itself may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and may thus mask the underlying process. The effect of symptomatic suppression on the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient treated with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  , drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.6 Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and body weight gain. While all of the drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus



 Hyperglycemia and diabetes mellitus, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, have been reported in patients treated with all atypical antipsychotics. These cases were, for the most part, seen in post-marketing clinical use and epidemiologic studies, not in clinical trials, and there have been few reports of hyperglycemia or diabetes in trial subjects treated with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  . Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. Because INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was not marketed at the time these studies were performed, it is not known if INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  is associated with this risk.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



 Pooled data from the four placebo-controlled (one 9-week and three 13-week), fixed-dose studies in subjects with schizophrenia are presented in Table 5.



 Table 5. Change in Fasting Glucose from Four Placebo-Controlled, 9- to 13-Week, Fixed-Dose Studies in Subjects with Schizophrenia 
                          INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)     
                            Placebo       39 mg        78 mg       156 mg      234/39 mg   234/156 mg   234/234 mg    
  
                           Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
                            n=367         n=86        n=244        n=238        n=110        n=126        n=115       
  Serum GlucoseChange from baseline       -1.3          1.3          3.5          0.1          3.4          1.8         -0.2       
                           Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
  Serum GlucoseNormal to High       4.6%         6.3%         6.4%         3.9%         2.5%         7.0%         6.6%       
  (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)     (11/241)      (4/64)      (11/173)      (6/154)      (2/79)       (6/86)       (5/76)      
              In a long-term open-label pharmacokinetic and safety study in subjects with schizophrenia in which the highest dose available (234 mg) was evaluated, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was associated with a mean change in glucose of -0.4 mg/dL at Week 29 (n=109) and +6.8 mg/dL at Week 53 (n=100).
 

 During the initial 25-week open-label period of a long-term study in subjects with schizoaffective disorder, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was associated with mean change in glucose of +5.3 mg/dL (n=518). At the endpoint of the subsequent 15-month double-blind period of the study, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was associated with a mean change in glucose of +0.3 mg/dL (n=131) compared with a mean change of +4.0 mg/dL in the placebo group (n=120).



   Dyslipidemia



 Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics.



 Pooled data from the four placebo-controlled (one 9-week and three 13-week), fixed-dose studies in subjects with schizophrenia are presented in Table 6.



 Table 6. Change in Fasting Lipids from Four Placebo-Controlled, 9- to 13-Week, Fixed-Dose Studies in Subjects with Schizophrenia 
                          INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)     
                            Placebo       39 mg        78 mg       156 mg      234/39 mg   234/156 mg   234/234 mg    
  
                           Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
  Cholesterol               n=366         n=89        n=244        n=232        n=105        n=119        n=120       
  Change from baseline       -6.6         -6.4         -5.8         -7.1         -0.9         -4.2          9.4       
  LDL                       n=275         n=80        n=164        n=141        n=104        n=117        n=108       
  Change from baseline       -6.0         -4.8         -5.6         -4.8          0.9         -2.4          5.2       
  HDL                       n=286         n=89        n=165        n=150        n=105        n=118        n=115       
  Change from baseline        0.7          2.1          0.6          0.3          1.5          1.1          0.0       
  Triglycerides             n=366         n=89        n=244        n=232        n=105        n=119        n=120       
  Change from baseline       -16.7         7.6         -9.0         -11.5        -14.1        -20.0        11.9       
                           Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
  Cholesterol                                                                                                         
  Normal to High             3.2%         2.0%         2.0%         2.1%          0%          3.1%         7.1%       
  (&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)      (7/222)      (1/51)       (3/147)      (3/141)      (0/69)       (2/65)       (6/84)      
  LDL                                                                                                                 
  Normal to High             1.1%          0%           0%           0%           0%           0%           0%        
  (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)      (1/95)       (0/29)       (0/67)       (0/46)       (0/41)       (0/37)       (0/44)      
  HDL                                                                                                                 
  Normal to Low              13.8%        14.8%        9.6%         14.2%        12.7%        10.5%        16.0%      
  (&gt;=40 mg/dL to &lt;40 mg/dL)     (28/203)      (9/61)      (11/115)     (15/106)      (9/71)       (8/76)       (13/81)     
  Triglycerides                                                                                                       
  Normal to High             3.6%         6.1%         9.2%         7.2%         1.3%         3.7%         10.7%      
  (&lt;150 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)      (8/221)      (3/49)      (14/153)     (10/139)      (1/79)       (3/82)       (9/84)      
              In a long-term open-label pharmacokinetic and safety study in subjects with schizophrenia in which the highest dose available (234 mg) was evaluated, the mean changes from baseline in lipid values are presented in Table 7.
 

 Table 7. Change in Fasting Lipids from Long-term Open-label Pharmacokinetic and Safety Study in Subjects with Schizophrenia 
                                         INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  234 mg     
                                                   Week 29                           Week 53                
  
                                        Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
  Cholesterol                                       n=112                             n=100                 
    Change from baseline                             -1.2                              0.1                  
  LDL                                               n=107                             n=89                  
    Change from baseline                             -2.7                              -2.3                 
  HDL                                               n=112                             n=98                  
    Change from baseline                             -0.8                              -2.6                 
  Triglycerides                                     n=112                             n=100                 
    Change from baseline                             16.2                              37.4                 
         The mean changes from baseline in lipid values during the initial 25-week open-label period and at the endpoint of the subsequent 15-month double-blind period in a long-term study in subjects with schizoaffective disorder are presented in Table 8.
 

 Table 8. Change in Fasting Lipids from an Open-Label and Double-Blind Periods of a Long-Term Study in Subjects with Schizoaffective Disorder 
                             Open-Label Period         Double-Blind Period       
                          INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)               Placebo              INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)        
  
                           Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
  Cholesterol                     n=198                      n=119                        n=132               
  Change from baseline             -3.9                       -4.2                          2.3               
  LDL                             n=198                      n=117                        n=130               
  Change from baseline             -2.7                       -2.8                          5.9               
  HDL                             n=198                      n=119                        n=131               
  Change from baseline             -2.7                       -0.9                         -0.7               
  Triglycerides                   n=198                      n=119                        n=132               
  Change from baseline              7.0                        2.5                         -12.3              
            Weight Gain
 

 Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Clinical monitoring of weight is recommended.



 Data on mean changes in body weight and the proportion of subjects meeting a weight gain criterion of &gt;= 7% of body weight from the four placebo-controlled (one 9-week and three 13-week), fixed-dose studies in subjects with schizophrenia are presented in Table 9.



 Table 9. Mean Change in Body Weight (kg) and the Proportion of Subjects with &gt;= 7% Gain in Body Weight from Four Placebo-Controlled, 9- to 13-Week, Fixed-Dose Studies in Subjects with Schizophrenia 
                                       INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)     
                            Placebo       39 mg        78 mg       156 mg      234/39 mg   234/156 mg   234/234 mg    
  
                            n=451        n=116        n=280        n=267        n=137        n=144        n=145       
  Weight (kg)Change from baseline       -0.4          0.4          0.8          1.4          0.4          0.7          1.4       
  Weight Gain&gt;= 7% increase from baseline       3.3%         6.0%         8.9%         9.0%         5.8%         8.3%         13.1%      
              In a long-term open-label pharmacokinetic and safety study in which the highest dose available (234 mg) was evaluated, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was associated with a mean change in weight of +2.4 kg at Week 29 (n=134) and +4.3 kg at Week 53 (n=113).
 

 During the initial 25-week open-label period of a long-term study in subjects with schizoaffective disorder, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was associated with a mean change in weight of +2.2 kg and 18.4% of subjects had an increase in body weight of &gt;= 7% (n=653). At the endpoint of the subsequent 15-month double-blind period of the study, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  was associated with a mean change in weight of -0.2 kg and 13.0% of subjects had an increase in body weight of &gt;= 7% (n=161); the placebo group had a mean change in weight of -0.8 kg and 6.0% of subjects had an increase in body weight of &gt;= 7% (n=168).



    5.7 Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope



  Paliperidone can induce orthostatic hypotension and syncope in some patients because of its alpha-blocking activity. Syncope was reported in &lt; 1% (4/1293) of subjects treated with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  in the recommended dose range of 39 mg to 234 mg in the four fixed-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials compared with 0% (0/510) of subjects treated with placebo. In the four fixed-dose efficacy studies in subjects with schizophrenia, orthostatic hypotension was reported as an adverse event by &lt; 1% (2/1293) of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  -treated subjects compared to 0% (0/510) with placebo. Incidences of orthostatic hypotension and syncope in the long-term studies in subjects with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder were similar to those observed in the short-term studies.



 INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  should be used with caution in patients with known cardiovascular disease (e.g., heart failure, history of myocardial infarction or ischemia, conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, or conditions that predispose the patient to hypotension (e.g., dehydration, hypovolemia, and treatment with antihypertensive medications). Monitoring of orthostatic vital signs should be considered in patients who are vulnerable to hypotension.



    5.8 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



  In clinical trial and/or postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia/neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents, including INVEGA  (r)  , an oral form of paliperidone. Agranulocytosis has also been reported.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) and history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a history of a clinically significant low WBC or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and discontinuation of INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  should be considered at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Patients with clinically significant neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm  3  ) should discontinue INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  and have their WBC followed until recovery.



    5.9 Hyperprolactinemia



  Like other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2receptors, paliperidone elevates prolactin levels and the elevation persists during chronic administration. Paliperidone has a prolactin-elevating effect similar to that seen with risperidone, a drug that is associated with higher levels of prolactin than other antipsychotic drugs.



 Hyperprolactinemia, regardless of etiology, may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotrophin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported in patients receiving prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male subjects.



 Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin dependent in vitro  , a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is considered in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. An increase in the incidence of pituitary gland, mammary gland, and pancreatic islet cell neoplasia (mammary adenocarcinomas, pituitary and pancreatic adenomas) was observed in the risperidone carcinogenicity studies conducted in mice and rats [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans, but the available evidence is too limited to be conclusive.



    5.10 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  Somnolence, sedation, and dizziness were reported as adverse reactions in subjects treated with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)   [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Antipsychotics, including INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  , have the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about performing activities requiring mental alertness, such as operating hazardous machinery or operating a motor vehicle, until they are reasonably certain that paliperidone therapy does not adversely affect them.



    5.11 Seizures



  In the four fixed-dose double-blind placebo-controlled studies in subjects with schizophrenia, &lt;1% (1/1293) of subjects treated with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  in the recommended dose range of 39 mg to 234 mg experienced an adverse event of convulsion compared with &lt;1% (1/510) of placebo-treated subjects who experienced an adverse event of grand mal convulsion.



 Like other antipsychotic drugs, INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or other conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in patients 65 years or older.



    5.12 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in patients with advanced Alzheimer's dementia. INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia.



    5.13 Priapism



  Drugs with alpha-adrenergic blocking effects have been reported to induce priapism. Although no cases of priapism have been reported in clinical trials with INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  , priapism has been reported with oral paliperidone during postmarketing surveillance. Severe priapism may require surgical intervention.



    5.14 Disruption of Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing INVEGA SUSTENNA  (r)  to patients who will be experiencing conditions which may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
