<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="invirase0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  PR Interval Prolongation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  QT Interval Prolongation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions are nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, fatigue, pneumonia, lipodystrophy and abdominal pain. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genentech at 1-800-835-2555 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience in Adult Subjects

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The original INVIRASE safety database consisted of a total of 574 adult subjects who received saquinavir 600 mg alone or in combination with ZDV or ddC. Combination dosing with ritonavir is based on 352 HIV-1 infected subjects and 166 healthy subjects who received various combinations of either saquinavir (hard gel or soft-gel capsules) with ritonavir.



 The recommended dose of INVIRASE is 1000 mg twice daily co-administered with ritonavir 100 mg twice daily, in combination with other antiretroviral agents.    Table 2    lists grade 2, 3 and 4 adverse events that occurred in &gt;=2% of subjects receiving saquinavir soft gel capsules with ritonavir (1000/100 mg bid).



 Table 2 Grade 2, 3 and 4 Adverse Events (All CausalityIncludes events with unknown relationship to study drug) Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Subjects in the MaxCmin 1 Study of Saquinavir Soft Gel Capsules in Combination with Ritonavir 1000/100 mg twice a day 
 Adverse Events                                      Saquinavir soft gel capsules 1000 mg plus Ritonavir 100 mg bid (48 weeks)N=148n (%=n/N)   
  
   Endocrine Disorders                                                                                    
   Diabetes mellitus/hyperglycemia                                         4 (3)                          
   Lipodystrophy                                                           8 (5)                          
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                             
   Nausea                                                                 16 (11)                         
   Vomiting                                                                11 (7)                         
   Diarrhea                                                                12 (8)                         
   Abdominal Pain                                                          9 (6)                          
   Constipation                                                            3 (2)                          
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                         
   Fatigue                                                                 9 (6)                          
   Fever                                                                   5 (3)                          
   Musculoskeletal Disorders                                                                              
   Back Pain                                                               3 (2)                          
   Respiratory Disorders                                                                                  
   Pneumonia                                                               8 (5)                          
   Bronchitis                                                              4 (3)                          
   Influenza                                                               4 (3)                          
   Sinusitis                                                               4 (3)                          
   Dermatological Disorders                                                                               
   Rash                                                                    5 (3)                          
   Pruritus                                                                5 (3)                          
   Dry lips/skin                                                           3 (2)                          
   Eczema                                                                  3 (2)                          
        Limited experience is available from three trials investigating the pharmacokinetics of the INVIRASE 500 mg film-coated tablet compared to the INVIRASE 200 mg capsule in healthy volunteers (n=140). In two of these trials saquinavir was boosted with ritonavir; in the other trial, saquinavir was administered as single drug. The INVIRASE tablet and the capsule formulations were similarly tolerated. The most common adverse events were gastrointestinal disorders (such as nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea). Similar bioavailability was demonstrated and no clinically significant differences in saquinavir exposures were seen. Thus, similar safety profiles are expected between the two INVIRASE formulations.
 

 A study investigating the drug-drug interaction of rifampin 600 mg/day daily and INVIRASE 1000 mg/ritonavir 100 mg twice daily enrolled 28 healthy volunteers. Eleven of 17 healthy volunteers (65%) exposed concomitantly to rifampin and ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE developed severe hepatocellular toxicity which presented as increased hepatic transaminases. In some subjects, transaminases increased up to &gt;20-fold the upper limit of normal and were associated with gastrointestinal symptoms, including abdominal pain, gastritis, nausea, and vomiting. Following discontinuation of all three drugs, clinical symptoms abated and the increased hepatic transaminases normalized  [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



     Additional Adverse Reactions Reported During Clinical Trials with Saquinavir  



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  anemia, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, neutropenia, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenia



   Cardiac disorders:  heart murmur, syncope



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  tinnitus



   Eye disorders:  visual impairment



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal discomfort, ascites, dyspepsia, dysphagia, eructation, flatulence, gastritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, intestinal obstruction, mouth dry, mucosal ulceration, pancreatitis



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  anorexia, asthenia, chest pain, edema, lethargy, wasting syndrome, weight increased



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  chronic active hepatitis, hepatitis, hepatomegaly, hyperbilirubinemia, jaundice, portal hypertension



   Immune system disorders:  allergic reaction



   Investigations:  ALT increase, AST increase, blood creatine phosphokinase increased, increased alkaline phosphatase, GGT increase, raised amylase, raised LDH



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  increased or decreased appetite, dehydration, hypertriglyceridemia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  arthralgia, muscle spasms, myalgia, polyarthritis



   Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (incl cysts and polyps):  acute myeloid leukemia, papillomatosis



   Nervous system disorders:  confusion, convulsions, coordination abnormal, dizziness, dysgeusia, headache, hypoaesthesia, intracranial hemorrhage leading to death, loss of consciousness, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, somnolence, tremor



   Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety, depression, insomnia, libido disorder, psychotic disorder, sleep disorder, suicide attempt



   Renal and urinary disorders:  nephrolithiasis



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  cough, dyspnea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  acne, alopecia, dermatitis bullous, drug eruption, erythema, severe cutaneous reaction associated with increased liver function tests, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, sweating increased, urticaria



   Vascular disorders:  hypertension, hypotension, thrombophlebitis, peripheral vasoconstriction



   6.2 Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Subjects

  Limited safety data are available from two pediatric clinical trials of saquinavir hard gel capsules (approximately 50 mg per kg twice daily) used in combination with either low dose ritonavir or lopinavir/ritonavir. These trials enrolled pediatric subjects aged 4 months to 16 years old. In the HIVNAT 017 study (INVIRASE + lopinavir/ritonavir), adverse events were reported in 90% of the 50 subjects enrolled. The most commonly reported adverse events considered related to study treatment were diarrhea (18%) and vomiting (10%). In the NV20911 study (INVIRASE + ritonavir), 4 subjects (22% of 18 enrolled) experienced adverse events that were considered related to INVIRASE + ritonavir. These events (n) were vomiting (3), abdominal pain (1) and diarrhea (1). All reported adverse events were mild or moderate in intensity. The adverse reaction profile of INVIRASE in the pediatric trials is similar to that observed in adult trials.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  Additional adverse events identified during postmarketing use are similar to those observed in clinical trials with INVIRASE and saquinavir soft gel capsules alone or in combination with ritonavir. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to INVIRASE exposure. In addition, torsades de pointes has been reported rarely [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ].
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   INVIRASE must be used in combination with ritonavir.  Please refer to the ritonavir full prescribing information for additional precautionary measures.



 If a serious or severe toxicity occurs during treatment with INVIRASE, INVIRASE should be interrupted until the etiology of the event is identified or the toxicity resolves. At that time, resumption of treatment with full-dose INVIRASE may be considered. For antiretroviral agents used in combination with INVIRASE, physicians should refer to the complete product information for these drugs for dose adjustment recommendations and for information regarding drug-associated adverse reactions.



    EXCERPT:    *  The concomitant use of INVIRASE/ritonavir and certain other drugs may result in known or potentially significant drug interactions. Consult the full prescribing information prior to and during treatment for potential drug interactions (  5.1  ,  7.3  ) 
 *  QT and PR interval prolongations have been observed in a healthy volunteer study. Use with caution in patients with preexisting conduction system abnormalities and certain heart diseases. (  5.2  ,  5.3  ,  12.2  ) 
 *  Patients on INVIRASE therapy may develop new onset or exacerbations of diabetes mellitus (  5.4  ), hyperglycemia (  5.4  ), elevated cholesterol and/or triglyceride concentrations (  5.7  ), redistribution/accumulation of body fat (  5.9  ), and immune reconstitution syndrome (  5.10  ). Monitor cholesterol and triglycerides prior to therapy and periodically thereafter. (  5.7  ) 
 *  In patients with underlying hepatitis B or C, cirrhosis, chronic alcoholism and/or other underlying liver abnormalities there have been reports of worsening liver disease. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hemophilia: Spontaneous bleeding may occur and additional factor VII may be required. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Various degrees of cross-resistance have been observed. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Serious Adverse Reactions Due to Drug Interactions



   Initiation of INVIRASE/ritonavir, a CYP3A inhibitor, in patients receiving medications metabolized by CYP3A or initiation of medications metabolized by CYP3A in patients already receiving INVIRASE/ritonavir, may increase plasma concentrations of medications metabolized by CYP3A. Initiation of medications that inhibit or induce CYP3A may increase or decrease concentrations of INVIRASE/ritonavir, respectively. These interactions may lead to:  



 *   Clinically significant adverse reactions potentially leading to severe, life threatening, or fatal events from greater exposures of concomitant medications.  
 *   Clinically significant adverse reactions from greater exposures of INVIRASE/ritonavir.  
 *   Loss of therapeutic effect of INVIRASE/ritonavir and possible development of resistance.  
    See   Table 3    for steps to prevent or manage these possible and known significant drug interactions, including dosing recommendations [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  . Consider the potential for drug interactions prior to and during INVIRASE/ritonavir therapy; review concomitant medications during INVIRASE/ritonavir therapy; and monitor for adverse reactions associated with concomitant medications [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  
 

    5.2 PR Interval Prolongation



  Saquinavir/ritonavir prolongs the PR interval in a dose-dependent fashion. Cases of second or third degree atrioventricular block have been reported rarely. Patients with underlying structural heart disease, pre-existing conduction system abnormalities, cardiomyopathies and ischemic heart disease may be at increased risk for developing cardiac conduction abnormalities. ECG monitoring is recommended in these patients [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .



 The impact on the PR interval of co-administration of saquinavir/ritonavir with other drugs that prolong the PR interval (including calcium channel blockers, beta-adrenergic blockers, digoxin and atazanavir) has not been evaluated. As a result, co-administration of saquinavir/ritonavir with these drugs should be undertaken with caution, particularly with those drugs metabolized by CYP3A, and clinical monitoring is recommended [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .



    5.3 QT Interval Prolongation



  Saquinavir/ritonavir causes dose-dependent QT prolongation. Torsades de pointes has been reported rarely post-marketing. Avoid saquinavir/ritonavir in patients with long QT syndrome. ECG monitoring is recommended if therapy is initiated in patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, hepatic impairment and electrolyte abnormalities. Correct hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia prior to initiating saquinavir/ritonavir and monitor these electrolytes periodically during therapy. Do not use in combination with drugs that both increase saquinavir plasma concentrations and prolong the QT interval (see   Tables 1    and   3    ) [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .



    Patients initiating therapy with ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE:  



 An ECG should be performed prior to initiation of treatment. Patients with a QT interval &gt; 450 msec should not receive ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE. For patients with a QT interval &lt; 450 msec, an on-treatment ECG is suggested after approximately 3 to 4 days of therapy; patients with a QT interval &gt; 480 msec or prolongation over pre-treatment by &gt; 20 msec should discontinue ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE.



    Patients requiring treatment with medications with the potential to increase the QT interval and concomitant ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE:  



 Such combinations should only be used where no alternative therapy is available and the potential benefits outweigh the potential risks. An ECG should be performed prior to initiation of the concomitant therapy, and patients with a QT interval &gt; 450 msec should not initiate the concomitant therapy. If baseline QT interval &lt; 450 msec, an on-treatment ECG should be performed after 3-4 days of therapy. For patients demonstrating a subsequent increase in QT interval to &gt; 480 msec or increase by &gt; 20 msec after commencing concomitant therapy, the physician should use best clinical judgment to discontinue either ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE or the concomitant therapy or both.



 A cardiology consult is recommended if drug discontinuation or interruption is being considered on the basis of ECG assessment.



    5.4 Diabetes Mellitus / Hyperglycemia



  New onset diabetes mellitus, exacerbation of preexisting diabetes mellitus and hyperglycemia have been reported during postmarketing surveillance in HIV-1-infected patients receiving protease-inhibitor therapy. Some patients required either initiation or dose adjustments of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents for the treatment of these events. In some cases diabetic ketoacidosis has occurred. In those patients who discontinued protease-inhibitor therapy, hyperglycemia persisted in some cases. Because these events have been reported voluntarily during clinical practice, estimates of frequency cannot be made and a causal relationship between protease-inhibitor therapy and these events has not been established.



    5.5 Hepatotoxicity



  In patients with underlying hepatitis B or C, cirrhosis, chronic alcoholism and/or other underlying liver abnormalities, there have been reports of worsening liver disease.



    5.6 Hemophilia



  There have been reports of spontaneous bleeding in patients with hemophilia A and B treated with protease inhibitors. In some patients additional factor VIII was required. In the majority of reported cases treatment with protease inhibitors was continued or restarted. A causal relationship between protease inhibitor therapy and these episodes has not been established.



    5.7 Hyperlipidemia



  Elevated cholesterol and/or triglyceride levels have been observed in some patients taking saquinavir in combination with ritonavir. Marked elevation in triglyceride levels is a risk factor for development of pancreatitis. Cholesterol and triglyceride levels should be monitored prior to initiating combination dosing regimen of INVIRASE with ritonavir, and at periodic intervals while on such therapy. In these patients, lipid disorders should be managed as clinically appropriate.



    5.8 Lactose Intolerance



  Each capsule contains lactose (anhydrous) 63.3 mg. This quantity should not induce specific symptoms of intolerance.



    5.9 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), facial wasting, peripheral wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.10 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including INVIRASE. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jiroveci  pneumonia [PCP], or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.11 Resistance/Cross-resistance



  Varying degrees of cross-resistance among HIV-1 protease inhibitors have been observed. Continued administration of INVIRASE therapy following loss of viral suppression may increase the likelihood of cross resistance to other protease inhibitors [see  Microbiology (12.4)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
