<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="invirase1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Concomitant Therapy with Ritonavir Adverse Reactions

  In combination with ritonavir the recommended dose of INVIRASE is 1000 mg two times daily with ritonavir 100 mg two times daily in combination with other antiretroviral agents.    Table 6    lists grade 2, 3 and 4 adverse events that occurred in &gt;=2% of patients receiving saquinavir soft gel capsules with ritonavir (1000/100 mg bid).



 Table 6 Grade 2, 3 and 4 Adverse Events (All CausalityIncludes events with unknown relationship to study drug) Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Patients in the MaxCmin 1 Study of saquinavir soft gel capsules in Combination with Ritonavir 1000/100 mg bid 
 Adverse Events                                      Saquinavir soft gel capsules 1000 mg plus Ritonavir 100 mg bid (48 weeks)N=148n (%=n/N)   
  
   Endocrine Disorders                                                                                    
   Diabetes mellitus/hyperglycemia                                        4 (2.7)                         
   Lipodystrophy                                                          8 (5.4)                         
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                             
   Nausea                                                                16 (10.8)                        
   Vomiting                                                               11 (7.4)                        
   Diarrhea                                                               12 (8.1)                        
   Abdominal Pain                                                         9 (6.1)                         
   Constipation                                                           3 (2.0)                         
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                         
   Fatigue                                                                9 (6.1)                         
   Fever                                                                  5 (3.4)                         
   Musculoskeletal Disorders                                                                              
   Back Pain                                                              3 (2.0)                         
   Respiratory Disorders                                                                                  
   Pneumonia                                                              8 (5.4)                         
   Bronchitis                                                             4 (2.7)                         
   Influenza                                                              4 (2.7)                         
   Sinusitis                                                              4 (2.7)                         
   Dermatological Disorders                                                                               
   Rash                                                                   5 (3.4)                         
   Pruritus                                                               5 (3.4)                         
   Dry lips/skin                                                          3 (2.0)                         
   Eczema                                                                 3 (2.0)                         
        Limited experience is available from three studies investigating the pharmacokinetics of the INVIRASE 500 mg film-coated tablet compared to the INVIRASE 200 mg capsule in healthy volunteers (n=140). In two of these studies saquinavir was boosted with ritonavir; in the other study, saquinavir was administered as single drug. The INVIRASE tablet and the capsule formulations were similarly tolerated. The most common adverse events were gastrointestinal disorders (such as diarrhea). Similar bioavailability was demonstrated and no clinically significant differences in saquinavir exposures were seen. Thus, similar safety profiles are expected between the two INVIRASE formulations.
 

 In a study investigating the drug-drug interaction of rifampin 600 mg/day daily and INVIRASE 1000 mg/ritonavir 100 mg twice daily (ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE) involving 28 healthy volunteers, 11 of 17 healthy volunteers (65%) exposed concomitantly to rifampin and ritonavir-boosted INVIRASE developed severe hepatocellular toxicity which presented as increased hepatic transaminases. In some subjects, transaminases increased up to &gt;20-fold the upper limit of normal and were associated with gastrointestinal symptoms, including abdominal pain, gastritis, nausea, and vomiting. Following discontinuation of all three drugs, clinical symptoms abated and the increased hepatic transaminases normalized (see    CONTRAINDICATIONS    ).



   Additional Adverse Reactions Reported with Saquinavir

  Additionally, adverse experiences of any intensity, at least remotely related to saquinavir, that were reported from clinical trials using INVIRASE or saquinavir soft gel capsules with or without ritonavir, are listed below by body system:



 Body as a Whole: allergic reaction, anorexia, asthenia, chest pain, drug fever, edema, fatigue, fever, intoxication, mucosa damage, parasites external, retrosternal pain, shivering, wasting syndrome, weakness generalized, weight decrease, redistribution/accumulation of body fat (see    PRECAUTIONS: Fat Redistribution    )



 Cardiovascular: cyanosis, heart murmur, heart valve disorder, hypertension, hypotension, peripheral vasoconstriction, syncope, thrombophlebitis, vein distended



 Endocrine/Metabolic: appetite decrease, appetite disturbance, dehydration, diabetes mellitus, dry eye syndrome, hypercalcemia, hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia, hypernatremia, hyperphosphatemia, hypertriglyceridemia, hypocalcemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, weight increase, xerophthalmia



 Gastrointestinal: ascites, abdominal discomfort, buccal mucosa ulceration, cheilitis, colic abdominal, constipation, dyspepsia, dysphagia, esophagitis, eructation, exacerbation of chronic liver disease with grade 4 LFT, feces bloodstained, feces discolored, flatulence, gastralgia, gastritis, gastrointestinal inflammation, intestinal obstruction, gingivitis, glossitis, hemorrhage rectum, hemorrhoids, hepatitis, hepatomegaly, hepatosplenomegaly, hyperbilirubinemia, infectious diarrhea, jaundice, liver enzyme disorder, melena, pain pelvic, painful defecation, pancreatitis, parotid disorder, portal hypertension, right and left upper quadrant abdominal pain, salivary glands disorder, stomach upset, stomatitis, toothache, tooth disorder, vomiting, frequent bowel movements



 Hematologic: anemia, bleeding dermal, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, microhemorrhages, neutropenia, pancytopenia, splenomegaly, thrombocytopenia, lymphadenopathy



 Infections and Infestations: abscess, angina tonsillaris, candidiasis, cellulitis, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, infection bacterial, infection mycotic, infection staphylococcal, influenza, moniliasis



 Investigations: ALT increase, AST increase, GGT increase, increased alkaline phosphatase, increased creatine phosphokinase, increased gamma GT, isolated increase in transaminase, raised amylase, raised LDH, TSH increase



 Musculoskeletal: arthralgia, arthritis, back pain, cramps leg, cramps muscle, creatine phosphokinase increased, musculoskeletal disorders, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia, stiffness, tissue changes, trauma



 Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified: acute myeloblastic leukemia



 Neurological: ataxia, confusion, convulsions, dizziness, dysarthria, dysesthesia, extremity numbness, headache, heart rate disorder, hyperesthesia, hyperreflexia, hyporeflexia, light-headed feeling, mouth dry, myelopolyradiculoneuritis, numbness face, pain facial, paresis, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, poliomyelitis, prickly sensation, progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy, seizures, spasms, intracranial hemorrhage leading to death, tremor, unconsciousness



 Psychological: agitation, amnesia, anxiety, anxiety attack, depression, dreaming excessive, euphoria, hallucination, insomnia, intellectual ability reduced, irritability, lethargy, libido disorder, overdose effect, psychic disorder, psychosis, somnolence, speech disorder, suicide attempt



 Reproductive System: impotence, prostate enlarged, vaginal discharge



 Respiratory: bronchitis, cough, dyspnea, epistaxis, hemoptysis, laryngitis, pharyngitis, pneumonia, pulmonary disease, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, sinusitis, upper respiratory tract infection



 Skin and Appendages: acne, alopecia, bullous skin eruption and polyarthritis, chalazion, dermatitis, dermatitis seborrheic, eczema, erythema, folliculitis, furunculosis, hair changes, hot flushes, nail disorder, night sweats, papillomatosis, photosensitivity reaction, pigment changes skin, rash maculopapular, severe cutaneous reaction associated with increased liver function tests, skin disorder, skin nodule, skin ulceration, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, sweating increased, urticaria, verruca, xeroderma



 Special Senses: blepharitis, earache, ear pressure, eye irritation, hearing decreased, otitis, taste alteration, tinnitus, visual disturbance



 Urinary System: micturition disorder, nephrolithiasis, renal calculus, urinary tract bleeding, urinary tract infection



   Postmarketing Experience

  Additional adverse events that have been observed during the postmarketing period are similar to those seen in clinical trials with INVIRASE and saquinavir soft gel capsules alone or in combination with ritonavir.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
