<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="invokamet1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are also discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Lactic Acidosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ,  (5.3)  ,  (5.5)  ,  (5.11)  ,  (5.12)  ]  
 *  Hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Impairment in Renal Function [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hyperkalemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Impaired Hepatic Function [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hypoglycemia with Concomitant Use of Sulfonylurea or Insulin [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Genital Mycotic Infections [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Bone Fracture [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Vitamin B12Deficiency [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Increases in Low-Density Lipoprotein (LDL-C) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
   *  Most common adverse reactions associated with canagliflozin (5% or greater incidence): female genital mycotic infections, urinary tract infection, and increased urination (  6.1  ) 
 *  Most common adverse reactions associated with metformin (5% or greater incidence) are diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, flatulence, asthenia, indigestion, abdominal discomfort, and headache (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-526-7736 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Pool of Placebo-Controlled Trials



     Canagliflozin  



 The data in Table 1 is derived from four 26-week placebo-controlled trials. In one trial canagliflozin was used as monotherapy and in three trials canagliflozin was used as add-on therapy with metformin (with or without other agents)  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . These data reflect exposure of 1667 patients to canagliflozin and a mean duration of exposure to canagliflozin of 24 weeks with 1275 subjects exposed to a combination of canagliflozin and metformin. Patients received canagliflozin 100 mg (N=833), canagliflozin 300 mg (N=834) or placebo (N=646) once daily. The mean daily dose of metformin was 2138 mg (SD 337.3) for the 1275 subjects in the three placebo-controlled metformin add-on studies. The mean age of the population was 56 years and 2% were older than 75 years of age. Fifty percent (50%) of the population was male and 72% were Caucasian, 12% were Asian, and 5% were Black or African American. At baseline the population had diabetes for an average of 7.3 years, had a mean HbA1C of 8.0% and 20% had established microvascular complications of diabetes. Baseline renal function was normal or mildly impaired (mean eGFR 88 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ).



 Table 1 shows common adverse reactions associated with the use of canagliflozin. These adverse reactions were not present at baseline, occurred more commonly on canagliflozin than on placebo, and occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with either canagliflozin 100 mg or canagliflozin 300 mg.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions From Pool of Four 26-Week Placebo-Controlled Studies Reported in &gt;= 2% of Canagliflozin-Treated PatientsThe four placebo-controlled trials included one monotherapy trial and three add-on combination trials with metformin, metformin and sulfonylurea, or metformin and pioglitazone. 
 Adverse Reaction                              PlaceboN=646      Canagliflozin100 mgN=833  Canagliflozin300 mgN=834   
  
 Female genital mycotic infections                 3.2%                 10.4%                 11.4%           
 Urinary tract infections                          4.0%                  5.9%                  4.3%           
 Increased urination                               0.8%                  5.3%                  4.6%           
 Male genital mycotic infections                   0.6%                  4.2%                  3.7%           
 Vulvovaginal pruritus                             0.0%                  1.6%                  3.0%           
 Thirst                                            0.2%                  2.8%                  2.3%           
 Constipation                                      0.9%                  1.8%                  2.3%           
 Nausea                                            1.5%                  2.2%                  2.3%           
          Abdominal pain was also more commonly reported in patients taking canagliflozin 100 mg (1.8%), 300 mg (1.7%) than in patients taking placebo (0.8%).
 

     Canagliflozin and Metformin  



 The incidence and type of adverse reactions in the three 26-week placebo-controlled metformin add-on studies, representing a majority of data from the four 26-week placebo-controlled trials, was similar to the adverse reactions described in Table 1. There were no additional adverse reactions identified in the pooling of these three placebo-controlled studies that included metformin relative to the four placebo-controlled studies.



     Pool of Placebo- and Active-Controlled Trials - Canagliflozin  



 The occurrence of adverse reactions for canagliflozin was evaluated in a larger pool of patients participating in placebo- and active-controlled trials.



 The data combined eight clinical trials and reflect exposure of 6177 patients to canagliflozin. The mean duration of exposure to canagliflozin was 38 weeks with 1832 individuals exposed to canagliflozin for greater than 50 weeks. Patients received canagliflozin 100 mg (N=3092), canagliflozin 300 mg (N=3085) or comparator (N=3262) once daily. The mean age of the population was 60 years and 5% were older than 75 years of age. Fifty-eight percent (58%) of the population was male and 73% were Caucasian, 16% were Asian, and 4% were Black or African American. At baseline, the population had diabetes for an average of 11 years, had a mean HbA1C of 8.0% and 33% had established microvascular complications of diabetes. Baseline renal function was normal or mildly impaired (mean eGFR 81 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ).



 The types and frequency of common adverse reactions observed in the pool of eight clinical trials were consistent with those listed in Table 1. In this pool, canagliflozin was also associated with the adverse reactions of fatigue (1.7% with comparator, 2.2% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 2.0% with canagliflozin 300 mg) and loss of strength or energy (i.e., asthenia) (0.6% with comparator, 0.7% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 1.1% with canagliflozin 300 mg).



 In the pool of eight clinical trials, the incidence rate of pancreatitis (acute or chronic) was 0.9, 2.7, and 0.9 per 1000 patient-years of exposure to comparator, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively.



 In the pool of eight clinical trials, hypersensitivity-related adverse reactions (including erythema, rash, pruritus, urticaria, and angioedema) occurred in 3.0%, 3.8%, and 4.2% of patients receiving comparator, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively. Five patients experienced serious adverse reactions of hypersensitivity with canagliflozin, which included 4 patients with urticaria and 1 patient with a diffuse rash and urticaria occurring within hours of exposure to canagliflozin. Among these patients, 2 patients discontinued canagliflozin. One patient with urticaria had recurrence when canagliflozin was re-initiated.



 Photosensitivity-related adverse reactions (including photosensitivity reaction, polymorphic light eruption, and sunburn) occurred in 0.1%, 0.2%, and 0.2% of patients receiving comparator, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively.



 Other adverse reactions occurring more frequently on canagliflozin than on comparator were:



     Volume Depletion-Related Adverse Reactions  



 Canagliflozin results in an osmotic diuresis, which may lead to reductions in intravascular volume. In clinical studies, treatment with canagliflozin was associated with a dose-dependent increase in the incidence of volume depletion-related adverse reactions (e.g., hypotension, postural dizziness, orthostatic hypotension, syncope, and dehydration). An increased incidence was observed in patients on the 300 mg dose. The three factors associated with the largest increase in volume depletion-related adverse reactions were the use of loop diuretics, moderate renal impairment (eGFR 30 to less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ), and age 75 years and older (Table 2)  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  , and  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  ,  (8.6)  ]  .



 Table 2: Proportion of Patients With at Least One Volume Depletion-Related Adverse Reaction (Pooled Results from 8 Clinical Trials) 
 Baseline Characteristic         Comparator Group%       Canagliflozin 100 mg%      Canagliflozin 300 mg%     
  
 Overall population                     1.5%                     2.3%                       3.4%              
 75 years of age and older              2.6%                     4.9%                       8.7%              
 eGFR less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2             2.5%                     4.7%                       8.1%              
 Use of loop diuretic                   4.7%                     3.2%                       8.8%              
              Falls  
 

 In a pool of nine clinical trials with mean duration of exposure to canagliflozin of 85 weeks, the proportion of patients who experienced falls was 1.3%, 1.5%, and 2.1% with comparator, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively. The higher risk of falls for patients treated with canagliflozin was observed within the first few weeks of treatment.



     Impairment in Renal Function  



 Canagliflozin is associated with a dose-dependent increase in serum creatinine and a concomitant fall in estimated GFR (Table 3). Patients with moderate renal impairment at baseline had larger mean changes.



 Table 3: Changes in Serum Creatinine and eGFR Associated with Canagliflozin in the Pool of Four Placebo-Controlled Trials and Moderate Renal Impairment Trial 
                     PlaceboN=646       Canagliflozin 100 mgN=833      Canagliflozin 300 mgN=834     
 Pool of Four Placebo-Controlled Trials  Baseline           Creatinine (mg/dL)        0.84             0.82               0.82          
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  87.0               88.3                      88.8        
 Week 6 Change     Creatinine (mg/dL)  0.01                      0.03             0.05          
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  -1.6               -3.8                      -5.0        
 End of Treatment Change  Creatinine (mg/dL)  0.01                      0.02             0.03          
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  -1.6               -2.3                      -3.4        
                     PlaceboN=90        Canagliflozin 100 mgN=90      Canagliflozin 300 mgN=89     
 Moderate Renal Impairment Trial  Baseline           Creatinine (mg/dL)        1.61             1.62               1.63          
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  40.1               39.7                      38.5        
 Week 3 Change     Creatinine (mg/dL)  0.03                      0.18             0.28          
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  -0.7               -4.6                      -6.2        
 End of Treatment Change  Creatinine (mg/dL)  0.07                      0.16             0.18          
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  -1.5               -3.6                      -4.0        
            In the pool of four placebo-controlled trials where patients had normal or mildly impaired baseline renal function, the proportion of patients who experienced at least one event of significant renal function decline, defined as an eGFR below 80 mL/min/1.73 m  2  and 30% lower than baseline, was 2.1% with placebo, 2.0% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 4.1% with canagliflozin 300 mg. At the end of treatment, 0.5% with placebo, 0.7% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 1.4% with canagliflozin 300 mg had a significant renal function decline.
 

 In a trial carried out in patients with moderate renal impairment with a baseline eGFR of 30 to less than 50 mL/min/1.73 m  2  (mean baseline eGFR 39 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ), the proportion of patients who experienced at least one event of significant renal function decline, defined as an eGFR 30% lower than baseline, was 6.9% with placebo, 18% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 22.5% with canagliflozin 300 mg. At the end of treatment, 4.6% with placebo, 3.4% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 2.2% with canagliflozin 300 mg had a significant renal function decline.



 In a pooled population of patients with moderate renal impairment (N=1085) with baseline eGFR of 30 to less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  (mean baseline eGFR 48 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ), the overall incidence of these events was lower than in the dedicated trial but a dose-dependent increase in incident episodes of significant renal function decline compared to placebo was still observed. Use of canagliflozin has been associated with an increased incidence of renal-related adverse reactions (e.g., increased blood creatinine, decreased glomerular filtration rate, renal impairment, and acute renal failure), particularly in patients with moderate renal impairment.



 In the pooled analysis of patients with moderate renal impairment, the incidence of renal-related adverse reactions was 3.7% with placebo, 8.9% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 9.3% with canagliflozin 300 mg. Discontinuations due to renal-related adverse events occurred in 1.0% with placebo, 1.2% with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 1.6% with canagliflozin 300 mg  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



     Genital Mycotic Infections  



 In the pool of four placebo-controlled clinical trials, female genital mycotic infections (e.g., vulvovaginal mycotic infection, vulvovaginal candidiasis, and vulvovaginitis) occurred in 3.2%, 10.4%, and 11.4% of females treated with placebo, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively. Patients with a history of genital mycotic infections were more likely to develop genital mycotic infections on canagliflozin. Female patients who developed genital mycotic infections on canagliflozin were more likely to experience recurrence and require treatment with oral or topical antifungal agents and anti-microbial agents. In females, discontinuation due to genital mycotic infections occurred in 0% and 0.7% of patients treated with placebo and canagliflozin, respectively  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  .



 In the pool of four placebo-controlled clinical trials, male genital mycotic infections (e.g., candidal balanitis, balanoposthitis) occurred in 0.6%, 4.2%, and 3.7% of males treated with placebo, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively. Male genital mycotic infections occurred more commonly in uncircumcised males and in males with a prior history of balanitis or balanoposthitis. Male patients who developed genital mycotic infections on canagliflozin were more likely to experience recurrent infections (22% on canagliflozin versus none on placebo), and require treatment with oral or topical antifungal agents and anti-microbial agents than patients on comparators. In males, discontinuations due to genital mycotic infections occurred in 0% and 0.5% of patients treated with placebo and canagliflozin, respectively. In the pooled analysis of 8 controlled trials, phimosis was reported in 0.3% of uncircumcised male patients treated with canagliflozin and 0.2% required circumcision to treat the phimosis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  .



     Hypoglycemia  



 In canagliflozin clinical trials, hypoglycemia was defined as any event regardless of symptoms, where biochemical hypoglycemia was documented (any glucose value below or equal to 70 mg/dL). Severe hypoglycemia was defined as an event consistent with hypoglycemia where the patient required the assistance of another person to recover, lost consciousness, or experienced a seizure (regardless of whether biochemical documentation of a low glucose value was obtained). In individual clinical trials  [see  Clinical Studies (14.6)  ]  , episodes of hypoglycemia occurred at a higher rate when canagliflozin was co-administered with insulin or sulfonylureas (Table 4)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  .



 Table 4: Incidence of HypoglycemiaNumber of patients experiencing at least one event of hypoglycemia based on either biochemically documented episodes or severe hypoglycemic events in the intent-to-treat population in Controlled Clinical Studies 
                                            
  
   Monotherapy(26 weeks)                     Placebo(N=192)      Canagliflozin 100 mg(N=195)      Canagliflozin 300 mg(N=197)     
 Overall [N (%)]                                5 (2.6)               7 (3.6)                6 (3.0)          
   In Combination with Metformin(26 weeks)      Placebo + Metformin(N=183)      Canagliflozin 100 mg + Metformin(N=368)      Canagliflozin 300 mg + Metformin(N=367)     
 Overall [N (%)]                                3 (1.6)               16 (4.3)               17 (4.6)         
 Severe [N (%)]                                  0 (0)                1 (0.3)                1 (0.3)          
   In Combination with Metformin(18 weeks)      Placebo(N=93)       Canagliflozin 100 mg(N=93)      Canagliflozin 300 mg(N=93)     
 Overall [N (%)]                                3 (3.2)               4 (4.3)                3 (3.2)          
   In Combination with Metformin + Sulfonylurea(26 weeks)      Placebo + Metformin + Sulfonylurea(N=156)      Canagliflozin 100 mg + Metformin + Sulfonylurea(N=157)      Canagliflozin 300 mg + Metformin + Sulfonylurea(N=156)     
 Overall [N (%)]                               24 (15.4)             43 (27.4)              47 (30.1)         
 Severe [N (%)]                                 1 (0.6)               1 (0.6)                   0             
   In Combination with Metformin + Pioglitazone(26 weeks)      Placebo + Metformin + Pioglitazone(N=115)      Canagliflozin 100 mg + Metformin + Pioglitazone(N=113)      Canagliflozin 300 mg + Metformin + Pioglitazone(N=114)     
 Overall [N (%)]                                3 (2.6)               3 (2.7)                6 (5.3)          
   In Combination with Insulin(18 weeks)      Placebo(N=565)      Canagliflozin 100 mg(N=566)      Canagliflozin 300 mg(N=587)     
 Overall [N (%)]                               208 (36.8)            279 (49.3)             285 (48.6)        
 Severe [N (%)]                                 14 (2.5)              10 (1.8)               16 (2.7)         
   In Combination with Insulin and Metformin (18 weeks)      Placebo(N=145)      Canagliflozin 100 mg(N=139)      Canagliflozin 300 mg(N=148)     
 Overall [N (%)]                               66 (45.5)             58 (41.7)              70 (47.3)         
 Severe [N (%)]                                 4 (2.8)               1 (0.7)                3 (2.0)          
              Bone Fracture  
 

 The occurrence of bone fractures was evaluated in a pool of nine clinical trials with a mean duration of exposure to canagliflozin of 85 weeks. The incidence rates of adjudicated bone fractures were 1.1, 1.4, and 1.5 per 100 patient-years of exposure in the comparator, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg groups, respectively. Fractures were observed as early as 12 weeks after treatment initiation and were more likely to be low trauma (e.g., fall from no more than standing height), and affect the upper extremities  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  .



   Metformin



 The most common adverse reactions (5% or greater incidence) due to initiation of metformin are diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, flatulence, asthenia, indigestion, abdominal discomfort, and headache.



 Long-term treatment with metformin has been associated with a decrease in vitamin B12, which may very rarely result in clinically significant vitamin B12deficiency (e.g., megaloblastic anemia)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  .



   Laboratory and Imaging Tests



     Increases in Serum Potassium  



 In a pooled population of patients (N=723) with moderate renal impairment (eGFR 45 to less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ), increases in serum potassium to greater than 5.4 mEq/L and 15% above baseline occurred in 5.3%, 5.0%, and 8.8% of patients treated with placebo, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively. Severe elevations (greater than or equal to 6.5 mEq/L) occurred in 0.4% of patients treated with placebo, no patients treated with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 1.3% of patients treated with canagliflozin 300 mg.



 In these patients, increases in potassium were more commonly seen in those with elevated potassium at baseline. Among patients with moderate renal impairment, approximately 84% were taking medications that interfere with potassium excretion, such as potassium-sparing diuretics, angiotensin-converting-enzyme inhibitors, and angiotensin-receptor blockers  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ,  (5.4)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ].  



     Increases in Serum Magnesium  



 Dose-related increases in serum magnesium were observed early after initiation of canagliflozin (within 6 weeks) and remained elevated throughout treatment. In the pool of four placebo-controlled trials, the mean percent change in serum magnesium levels was 8.1% and 9.3% with canagliflozin 100 mg and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively, compared to -0.6% with placebo. In a trial of patients with moderate renal impairment, serum magnesium levels increased by 0.2%, 9.2%, and 14.8% with placebo, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively.



     Increases in Serum Phosphate  



 Dose-related increases in serum phosphate levels were observed with canagliflozin. In the pool of four placebo-controlled trials, the mean percent change in serum phosphate levels were 3.6% and 5.1% with canagliflozin 100 mg and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively, compared to 1.5% with placebo. In a trial of patients with moderate renal impairment, the mean serum phosphate levels increased by 1.2%, 5.0%, and 9.3% with placebo, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively.



     Increases in Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol (LDL-C) and non-High-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol (non-HDL-C)  



 In the pool of four placebo-controlled trials, dose-related increases in LDL-C with canagliflozin were observed. Mean changes (percent changes) from baseline in LDL-C relative to placebo were 4.4 mg/dL (4.5%) and 8.2 mg/dL (8.0%) with canagliflozin 100 mg and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively. The mean baseline LDL-C levels were 104 to 110 mg/dL across treatment groups  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  .



 Dose-related increases in non-HDL-C with canagliflozin were observed. Mean changes (percent changes) from baseline in non-HDL-C relative to placebo were 2.1 mg/dL (1.5%) and 5.1 mg/dL (3.6%) with canagliflozin 100 mg and 300 mg, respectively. The mean baseline non-HDL-C levels were 140 to 147 mg/dL across treatment groups.



     Increases in Hemoglobin  



 In the pool of four placebo-controlled trials, mean changes (percent changes) from baseline in hemoglobin were -0.18 g/dL (-1.1%) with placebo, 0.47 g/dL (3.5%) with canagliflozin 100 mg, and 0.51 g/dL (3.8%) with canagliflozin 300 mg. The mean baseline hemoglobin value was approximately 14.1 g/dL across treatment groups. At the end of treatment, 0.8%, 4.0%, and 2.7% of patients treated with placebo, canagliflozin 100 mg, and canagliflozin 300 mg, respectively, had hemoglobin levels above the upper limit of normal.



     Decreases in Bone Mineral Density  



 Bone mineral density (BMD) was measured by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry in a clinical trial of 714 older adults (mean age 64 years). At 2 years, patients randomized to canagliflozin 100 mg and canagliflozin 300 mg had placebo-corrected declines in BMD at the total hip of 0.9% and 1.2%, respectively, and at the lumbar spine of 0.3% and 0.7%, respectively. Additionally, placebo-adjusted BMD declines were 0.1% at the femoral neck for both canagliflozin doses and 0.4% at the distal forearm for patients randomized to canagliflozin 300 mg. The placebo-adjusted change at the distal forearm for patients randomized to canagliflozin 100 mg was 0%.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS  

    *  Lactic acidosis is a rare but serious complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as renal impairment, sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. 
 *  The onset is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. 
 *  Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate. 
 *  If lactic acidosis is suspected, INVOKAMET(r) should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as renal impairment, sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, and acute congestive heart failure (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue INVOKAMET and hospitalize the patient immediately (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Lactic acidosis : Warn against excessive alcohol use. INVOKAMET is not recommended in hepatic impairment or hypoxic states. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter (  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.5  ,  5.11  ,  5.12  ) 
 *   Hypotension : Before initiating INVOKAMET, assess volume status and correct hypovolemia in patients with renal impairment, the elderly, in patients with low systolic blood pressure, or on diuretics, ACEi, or ARB. Monitor for signs and symptoms during therapy (  5.2  ) 
 *   Impairment in Renal Function : Monitor renal function during therapy (  5.3  ) 
 *   Radiological Studies and Surgical Procedures : Temporarily discontinue for radiologic studies with intravascular administration of iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food and fluids (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hyperkalemia : Monitor potassium levels in patients with impaired renal function and in patients predisposed to hyperkalemia (  2.2  ,  5.4  ,  6.1  ,  8.6  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia : Consider a lower dose of insulin or the insulin secretagogue to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with INVOKAMET (  5.6  ) 
 *   Genital mycotic infections : Monitor and treat if indicated (  5.7  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions : Discontinue INVOKAMET and monitor until signs and symptoms resolve (  5.8  ) 
 *   Bone fracture : Consider factors that contribute to fracture risk before initiating INVOKAMET (  5.9  ) 
 *   Vitamin B12deficiency : Metformin may lower vitamin B12levels. Monitor hematologic parameters annually (  5.10  ) 
 *   Increased LDL-C : Monitor LDL-C and treat if appropriate (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



  Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with INVOKAMET and is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate levels (greater than 5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels greater than 5 mcg/mL are generally found.



 The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin is approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years (with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years). In more than 20,000 patient-years exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal insufficiency, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, particularly when accompanied by hypoperfusion and hypoxemia due to unstable or acute failure, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis.



 The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking metformin. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. Metformin treatment should not be initiated in any patients unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced. In addition, metformin should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis.



 Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, metformin should be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic impairment. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake when taking metformin, since alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin on lactate metabolism. In addition, metformin should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure necessitating restricted intake of food or fluids [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ,  (5.5)  ,  (5.11)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



 The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. More severe acidosis may be associated with signs such as hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias. Patients should be educated to recognize and promptly report these symptoms. If present, INVOKAMET should be discontinued until lactic acidosis is ruled out. Gastrointestinal symptoms in patients on a chronic, stable dose of metformin could be caused by lactic acidosis or other serious disease.



 To rule out lactic acidosis, serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, blood pH, lactate levels, and blood metformin levels may be useful. Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking metformin do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be due to other mechanisms, such as poorly controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling .  



 Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia). Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking metformin, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Metformin is dialyzable (clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions) and prompt hemodialysis is recommended to remove the accumulated metformin and correct the metabolic acidosis. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery [see  Boxed Warning  and  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.2 Hypotension



  Canagliflozin causes intravascular volume contraction. Symptomatic hypotension can occur after initiating INVOKAMET [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  particularly in patients with eGFR less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  , elderly patients, patients on either diuretics or medications that interfere with the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., angiotensin-converting-enzyme [ACE] inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers [ARBs]), or patients with low systolic blood pressure. Before initiating INVOKAMET in patients with one or more of these characteristics who were not already on canagliflozin, volume status should be assessed and corrected. Monitor for signs and symptoms after initiating therapy.



    5.3 Impairment in Renal Function



  Canagliflozin increases serum creatinine and decreases eGFR. Patients with hypovolemia may be more susceptible to these changes. Renal function abnormalities can occur after initiating INVOKAMET [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Metformin is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney. The risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of impairment of renal function. Therefore, INVOKAMET is contraindicated in patients with renal impairment [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  , and  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ]  .



 Before initiation of INVOKAMET therapy and at least annually thereafter, assess renal function [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . In patients in whom development of renal impairment is anticipated (e.g., elderly), assess renal function more frequently and discontinue INVOKAMET if evidence of renal impairment is present (e.g. serum creatinine levels greater than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL for males or 1.4 mg/dL for females, or eGFR is less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ).



    Use of Concomitant Medications That May Affect Renal Function or Metformin Disposition  



 Monitor and adjust dose of INVOKAMET or concomitant drug in patients taking medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in a significant hemodynamic change or interfere with the disposition of metformin [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    Radiological Studies and Surgical Procedures  



 Radiologic studies involving the use of intravascular iodinated contrast materials (e.g., intravenous urogram, intravenous cholangiography, angiography, and computed tomography) can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin. Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, temporarily discontinue INVOKAMET at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withhold for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstitute only after renal function has been confirmed to be normal.



 Temporarily discontinue INVOKAMET for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and restart after the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.4 Hyperkalemia



  Canagliflozin can lead to hyperkalemia. Patients with moderate renal impairment who are taking medications that interfere with potassium excretion, such as potassium-sparing diuretics, or medications that interfere with the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system are at an increased risk of developing hyperkalemia [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Monitor serum potassium levels periodically after initiating INVOKAMET in patients with impaired renal function and in patients predisposed to hyperkalemia due to medications or other medical conditions.



    5.5 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Metformin use in patients with impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis. Therefore, INVOKAMET is not recommended in patients with hepatic impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



    5.6 Hypoglycemia with Concomitant Use of Sulfonylurea or Insulin



  Canagliflozin



 Insulin and insulin secretagogues are known to cause hypoglycemia. Canagliflozin can increase the risk of hypoglycemia when combined with insulin or an insulin secretagogue [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Therefore, a lower dose of insulin or insulin secretagogue may be required to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with INVOKAMET.



   Metformin



 Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation, or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as sulfonylureas and insulin) or ethanol. Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication, are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs. Monitor for a need to lower the dose of INVOKAMET to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia in these patients.



    5.7 Genital Mycotic Infections



  Canagliflozin increases the risk of genital mycotic infections. Patients with a history of genital mycotic infections and uncircumcised males were more likely to develop genital mycotic infections [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Monitor and treat appropriately.



    5.8 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., generalized urticaria), some serious, were reported with canagliflozin treatment; these reactions generally occurred within hours to days after initiating canagliflozin. If hypersensitivity reactions occur, discontinue use of INVOKAMET; treat and monitor until signs and symptoms resolve [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.9 Bone Fracture



   An increased risk of bone fracture, occurring as early as 12 weeks after treatment initiation, was observed in patients using canagliflozin. Consider factors that contribute to fracture risk prior to initiating INVOKAMET [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .  



    5.10 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled, 29-week clinical trials of metformin, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of metformin-treated patients. Such decreases, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia or neurologic manifestations due to the short duration (less than 1 year) of the clinical trials. This risk may be more relevant to patients receiving long-term treatment with metformin and adverse hematologic and neurologic reactions have been reported postmarketing. The decrease in vitamin B12levels appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or vitamin B12supplementation. Measure hematologic parameters on an annual basis in patients on INVOKAMET and investigate and treat if abnormalities occur. Patients with inadequate vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption may be predisposed to developing subnormal vitamin B12levels, and routine serum vitamin B12measurement at 2- to 3-year intervals is recommended in these patients.



    5.11 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol is known to potentiate the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Warn patients against excessive alcohol intake while receiving INVOKAMET [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



    5.12 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause (e.g., acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia) have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur, promptly discontinue INVOKAMET [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



    5.13 Increases in Low-Density Lipoprotein (LDL-C)



  Dose-related increases in LDL-C occur with canagliflozin [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Monitor LDL-C and treat if appropriate after initiating INVOKAMET.



    5.14 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with INVOKAMET or any other antidiabetic drug [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
