<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ionsys" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Life-threatening respiratory depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Addiction, abuse, and misuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Interactions with other CNS depressants [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Hypotensive effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.13  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common (frequency &gt;= 2%) adverse reactions were headache, hypotension, nausea, vomiting, anemia, dizziness, application site reaction-erythema, pruritus, and urinary retention. (  6  )
 

 



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact The Medicines Company at 1-877-488-6835 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 



 



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In controlled and uncontrolled studies, the safety of IONSYS 40 mcg was evaluated in a total of 2114 patients with acute postoperative pain requiring opioid analgesia.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) in the placebo-controlled studies, regardless of relationship to study medication, are listed in Table 1.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions with Incidence &gt;= 2% in Placebo-controlled Studies 1, 2, and 3 (N=791; 24 Hour Duration) 
   Adverse Reactions         IONSYS (n=475)              Placebo(n=316)            
   Body as a Whole           
 Headache                    9%                        7%                          
   Cardiovascular System     
  Hypotension                2%                         &lt;1%                        
   Digestive System          
 Nausea                      39%                        22%                        
  Vomiting                   12%                        6%                         
   Hemic and Lymphatic System     
  Anemia                     3%                         &lt;1%                        
   Nervous System            
 Dizziness                   3%                         1%                         
   Skin System               
 Application site reaction- Erythema   14%                       2%                          
  Pruritus                   6%                         &lt;1%                        
   Urogenital System         
 Urinary retention           3%                           &lt;1%                      
      NOTE: Patients reported as having "Nausea and vomiting" are included in "Nausea" and "Vomiting" in Table 1.
 

   Other Adverse Reactions  



 Other adverse reactions that were reported (excluding adverse reactions listed in Table 1) in 4 active comparator trials vs. IV PCA morphine in patients treated with IONSYS (n=1288) are described below:



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain, back pain, extremity pain, chest pain, chills, abdomen enlarged, asthenia, abscess, hypothermia



   Cardiovascular System:  syncope, postural hypotension, vasodilation, hypertension, atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, tachycardia, bigeminy, arrhythmia, myocardial infarct



   Digestive System:  constipation, flatulence, dyspepsia, ileus, dry mouth, diarrhea



   Metabolic and Nutritional System:  peripheral edema, healing abnormal, edema, dehydration



   Musculoskeletal System:  leg cramps and myalgia



   Nervous System:  insomnia, anxiety, somnolence, confusion, paresthesia, hypesthesia, nervousness, agitation, abnormal dreams, tremor



   Respiratory System:  hypoxia, hypoventilation, dyspnea, apnea, cough increased, asthma, hiccup, atelectasis, rhinitis, hyperventilation



   Skin System:  application site reactions including: itching, vesicles, papules/pustules, edema, pain, burning, dry and flaky skin, and vesiculobullous rash, wound site oozing/bleeding, wound site inflammation/erythema, rash, sweating



   Special Senses:  abnormal vision-blurred vision



   Urogenital System:  urination impaired, hematuria, urinary tract infection, urinary urgency, dysuria



 Scheduled observation of the skin approximately 24 hours after IONSYS removal was included in several studies. Some redness at the skin sites was observed in approximately 60% of patients at this observation. The skin findings included erythema, edema, and papules. The majority of these events were categorized as mild. Two patients were noted to have hyperpigmentation lasting 2 - 3 weeks at the application site. Three patients noted a rectangular mark at the application site, which persisted for up to 3 months after study completion.



   6.2 Post Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of IONSYS. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 



 The most commonly observed events were related to application site reactions which included urticaria, application site discharge, erosion, hyperesthesia, pustules, rash and scab, application site bleeding, application site infection, and necrosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    WARNING: HOSPITAL USE ONLY; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; IONSYS REMS; ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION  



     Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression    



 *  Use of IONSYS may result in potentially life-threatening respiratory depression and death as a result of the active drug, fentanyl. Only the patient should activate IONSYS dosing [see Dosage and Administration (2.1) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Accidental exposure to an intact IONSYS or to the hydrogel component, especially by children, through contact with skin or contact with mucous membranes, can result in a fatal overdose of fentanyl [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  IONSYS is for use only in patients in the hospital. Discontinue treatment with IONSYS before patients leave the hospital [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
        IONSYS Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) Program    
 

 *  Because of potentially life-threatening respiratory depression resulting from accidental exposure, IONSYS is available only through a restricted program under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) called the IONSYS REMS Program [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
        Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse    
 

 *  IONSYS exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors or conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]. 
        Cytochrome P450 3A4 Interaction    
 

 *  The concomitant use of IONSYS with all cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentrations, which could increase or prolong adverse drug effects and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression. In addition, discontinuation of a concomitantly used cytochrome P450 3A4 inducer may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentration. Monitor patients receiving IONSYS and any CYP3A4 inhibitor or inducer [see Warnings and Precautions (5.15), Drug Interactions (7.3), and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: HOSPITAL USE ONLY; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; IONSYS REMS; ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION
        See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Use of IONSYS may result in potentially life-threatening respiratory depression and death. Only the patient should activate dosing. (2.1, 5.1) 
 *  Accidental exposure to an intact IONSYS or to the hydrogel component, especially by children, through contact with skin or mucous membranes, can result in a fatal overdose of fentanyl. (5.1) 
 *  IONSYS is for use only in patients in the hospital.Discontinue IONSYS before patients leave the hospital. (5.1) 
 *  Because of potentially life-threatening respiratory depression resulting from accidental exposure, IONSYS is only available through a restricted program called the IONSYS REMS Program. (5.2) 
 *  IONSYS exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for these behaviors or conditions. (5.3) 
 *  Initiation of CYP 3A4 inhibitors or discontinuation of CYP 3A4 inducers can result in a fatal overdose of fentanyl from IONSYS. (5.15, 7.3, 12.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Interactions with CNS depressants : Concomitant use may cause hypotension, profound sedation, respiratory depression, and death. Monitor patients closely if co-administration is required. (  5.1  ,  5.4  ,  7.1  ) 
 *   Risk of injury during MRI : IONSYS contains metal parts and must be removed before an MRI. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Risk of use during other procedures (cardioversion, defibrillation, X-ray, CT, diathermy) : Remove IONSYS before these procedures. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Topical skin reactions : If reaction is severe, discontinue IONSYS. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Elderly, cachectic, and debilitated patients, and those with chronic pulmonary disease : Monitor closely because of increased risk of life-threatening respiratory depression. (  5.8  ,  5.9  ) 
 *   Hypotension : Monitor during dose initiation. Avoid use of IONSYS in patients with circulatory shock. (  5.10  ) 
 *   Patients with head injury or increased intracranial pressure : Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression. Avoid use of IONSYS in patients with impaired consciousness or coma. Opioids may obscure clinical course in patients with head injury. (  5.11  ) 
 *   Patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis : Monitor for worsening symptoms. (  5.12  ) 
 *   Increased risk of seizures in patients with seizure disorders : Monitor for worsened seizure control during IONSYS therapy. (  5.13  ) 
 *   Bradycardia : Closely monitor patients with bradyarrhythmias. (  5.14  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of opioids, including fentanyl, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression from opioid use, including fentanyl, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see Overdosage (  10.2  )].  Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.



 



 The use of concomitant CNS-active drugs increases the risk of respiratory depression and requires special patient care and observation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )].  



 



 Keep IONSYS out of reach of children at all times.



 



 Accidental exposure to an intact IONSYS or to its components, through contact with skin or mucous membranes can result in a fatal overdose of fentanyl. Following accidental contact with IONSYS or its components, immediately rinse the affected area thoroughly with water. Do not use soap, alcohol, or other solvent because they may enhance the drug's ability to penetrate the skin. The individual exposed should be monitored for signs of respiratory or central nervous system depression.



 



 If IONSYS is not handled correctly using gloves, healthcare professionals are at risk of accidental exposure to a fatal overdose of fentanyl.



 



 IONSYS is for hospital use only. Use of IONSYS outside of the hospital setting can lead to accidental exposure in others for whom it is not prescribed, causing fatal respiratory depression. Prior to the patient leaving the hospital, medical personnel must remove IONSYS and dispose of it properly.



    5.2 IONSYS Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) Program



  IONSYS is available only through a restricted program under a REMS called the IONSYS REMS Program because of the risk of respiratory depression resulting from accidental exposure [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



 



 Notable requirements of the IONSYS REMS Program include the following:



 



 *  Healthcare facilities that dispense and administer IONSYS must be certified in the IONSYS REMS program and comply with the REMS requirements. 
 *  Hospitals must only dispense IONSYS for hospital use. 
    
 

 Further information about the IONSYS REMS Program is available at www.ionsysrems.com, or by calling 1-877-488-6835.



    5.3 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  IONSYS contains fentanyl, an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance. Fentanyl can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. Opioid agonists are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing IONSYS in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of addiction, abuse, and misuse. Concerns about addiction, abuse, and misuse, however, should not prevent the proper management of pain.



 



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid abuse or addiction prior to prescribing IONSYS. The risk for opioid abuse is increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). Patients at increased risk may still be appropriately treated with opioids; however these patients will require intensive monitoring for signs of misuse, abuse, or addiction. Routinely monitor all patients receiving opioids for signs of misuse, abuse, and addiction because these drugs carry a risk for addiction even under appropriate medical use.



 



 Contact local State Professional Licensing Board or State Controlled Substances Authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.4 Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



  Hypotension, profound sedation, coma, respiratory depression, and death may result if IONSYS is used concomitantly with alcohol or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids).



 



 When considering the use of IONSYS in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration of use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that cause CNS depression    [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )].  



    5.5 Risk of Injury during Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) Procedure



  The IONSYS device is considered MR Unsafe. IONSYS contains metal parts and must be removed and properly disposed of before an MRI procedure to avoid injury to the patient and damage to IONSYS. It is unknown if exposure to an MRI procedure increases release of fentanyl from IONSYS. Monitor any patients wearing IONSYS with inadvertent exposure to an MRI for signs of central nervous system and respiratory depression.



    5.6 Risk of IONSYS Use during Other Procedures or Near Certain Equipment



   Cardioversion, Defibrillation, Radiographic Imaging Procedures other than MRI, or Diathermy  



 Use of IONSYS during cardioversion, defibrillation, X-ray, CT, or diathermy can damage IONSYS from the strong electromagnetic fields set up by these procedures. IONSYS contains radio-opaque components and may interfere with an X-ray image or CT scan. Remove and properly dispose of IONSYS prior to cardioversion, defibrillation, X-ray, CT, or diathermy [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ,  2.4  )].  



  Synthetic Materials and Electronic Security Systems  



 Avoid contact with synthetic materials (such as carpeted flooring) to reduce the possibility of electrostatic discharge and damage to IONSYS. Avoid exposing IONSYS to electronic security systems to reduce the possibility of damage to IONSYS. See   IONSYS Important Device Instructions    for additional details.



  Communications Equipment and Radio Frequency Identification Transmitters  



 Use of IONSYS near communications equipment (e.g., base stations for radio telephones and land mobile radios, amateur radio, AM and FM radio broadcast and TV broadcast Radio) and Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) transmitters can damage IONSYS. Depending on the rated maximum output power and frequency of the transmitter, the recommended separation distance between IONSYS and communications equipment or the RFID transmitter ranges between 0.12 and 23 meters. See   IONSYS Important Device Instructions    for detailed instructions regarding recommended separation distances.



  Other Electromechanical Devices Including Pacemakers or Electrical Monitoring Equipment  



 The low-level electrical current provided by IONSYS does not result in electromagnetic interference with other electromechanical devices like pacemakers or electrical monitoring equipment.



 If exposure to the procedures listed above, electronic security systems, electrostatic discharge, communications equipment, or RFID transmitters occurs, and if IONSYS does not appear to function normally [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )],  remove IONSYS and replace with a new IONSYS. See   IONSYS Important Device Instructions    for additional details including information on troubleshooting device malfunction and electromagnetic compatibility.



    5.7 Topical Skin Reactions



  Topical skin reactions (erythema, sweating, vesicles, papules/pustules) may occur with use of IONSYS and are typically limited to the application site area. If a severe skin reaction is observed, remove IONSYS and discontinue further use.



    5.8 Use in Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



  Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely; especially when IONSYS is used concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



    5.9 Use in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Monitor patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression for respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with IONSYS, as in these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of IONSYS may decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  Consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients if possible.



    5.10 Hypotensive Effect



  IONSYS may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is increased risk in patients whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a reduced blood volume, or concurrent administration of certain CNS depressant drugs (e.g., phenothiazines or general anesthetics) [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )].  Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating IONSYS. Avoid the use of IONSYS in patients with circulatory shock as IONSYS may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure.



 



    5.11 Use in Patients with Head Injury or Increased Intracranial Pressure



  IONSYS is not suitable for use in patients who are not alert and able to follow directions. Monitor patients using IONSYS who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors) for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with IONSYS. IONSYS may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2retention can further increase intracranial pressure. Opioids, including IONSYS, may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury.



 



 Avoid the use of IONSYS in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.12 Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  IONSYS is contraindicated in patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, including paralytic ileus. Fentanyl may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis for worsening symptoms. Opioids, including IONSYS, may cause increases in serum amylase.



 



    5.13 Use in Patients with Convulsive or Seizure Disorders



  IONSYS may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings. Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during IONSYS therapy.



    5.14 Bradycardia



  IONSYS may produce bradycardia in some patients. Monitor patients with bradyarrhythmias closely for changes in heart rate, particularly when initiating therapy with IONSYS.



 



    5.15 Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  Since the CYP3A4 isoenzyme plays a major role in the metabolism of fentanyl, drugs that alter CYP3A4 activity may cause changes in clearance of fentanyl which could lead to changes in fentanyl plasma concentrations.



 



 The concomitant use of IONSYS with a CYP3A4 inhibitor (such as ritonavir, ketoconazole, itraconazole, troleandomycin, clarithromycin, nelfinavir, nefazadone, amiodarone, amprenavir, aprepitant, diltiazem, erythromycin, fluconazole, fosamprenavir, verapamil) may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentrations, which could increase or prolong adverse drug effects and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression. Carefully monitor patients receiving IONSYS and any CYP3A4 inhibitor for signs of sedation and respiratory depression for an extended period of time, and make dosage adjustments as needed.



 



 If co-administration is necessary, caution is advised when initiating IONSYS treatment in patients currently taking, or discontinuing, CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers. Evaluate these patients at frequent intervals and consider dose adjustments until stable drug effects are achieved [see Drug Interactions (  7.3  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )].  



    5.16 Hepatic Impairment



  Insufficient data are available on the use of IONSYS in patients with impaired hepatic function. Since fentanyl is eliminated by hepatic metabolism and fentanyl clearance may decrease in patients with hepatic disease, monitor patients with hepatic impairment for signs of sedation and respiratory depression    [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )].  



    5.17 Renal Impairment



  A clinical pharmacology study with intravenous fentanyl in patients undergoing kidney transplantation has shown that patients with high blood urea nitrogen level had low fentanyl clearance. Monitor for signs of sedation and respiratory depression in patients with renal impairment    [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.7  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
