<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ipol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Body System As A Whole

  In earlier studies with the vaccine grown in primary monkey kidney cells, transient local reactions at the site of injection were observed. (3) Erythema, induration and pain occurred in 3.2%, 1% and 13%, respectively, of vaccinees within 48 hours post-vaccination. Temperatures of &gt;=39 degrees C (&gt;=102 degrees F) were reported in 38% of vaccinees. Other symptoms included irritability, sleepiness, fussiness, and crying. Because IPV was given in a different site but concurrently with Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids and Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed (DTP), these systemic reactions could not be attributed to a specific vaccine. However, these systemic reactions were comparable in frequency and severity to that reported for DTP given alone without IPV. (12) Although no causal relationship has been established, deaths have occurred in temporal association after vaccination of infants with IPV. (37)



 Four additional US studies using IPOL vaccine in more than 1,300 infants, (12) between 2 to 18 months of age administered with DTP at the same time at separate sites or combined have demonstrated that local and systemic reactions were similar when DTP was given alone.



 Table 2 (12): Percentage of Infants Presenting with Local or Systemic Reactions at 6, 24, and 48 Hours of Immunization with IPOL Vaccine Administered Intramuscularly Concomitantly at Separate Sites with SanofiSanofi Pasteur Inc. formerly known as Aventis Pasteur Inc. Whole-Cell DTP Vaccine at 2 and 4 Months of Age and with Sanofi Acellular Pertussis Vaccine (Tripedia(r)) at 18 Months of Age 
                               AGE AT IMMUNIZATION   
 REACTION                      2 Months(n=211)  4 Months(n=206)  18 Months(n=74)   
 6 Hrs.                         24 Hrs.   48 Hrs.    6 Hrs.   24 Hrs.   48 Hrs.    6 Hrs.   24 Hrs.   48 Hrs.   
  
   Local, IPOL vaccine alone                                                                                               
   Erythema &gt;1"                    0.5%      0.5%      0.5%      1.0%      0.0%      0.0%      1.4%      0.0%      0.0%   
   Swelling                       11.4%      5.7%      0.9%     11.2%      4.9%      1.9%      2.7%      0.0%      0.0%   
   Tenderness                     29.4%      8.5%      2.8%     22.8%      4.4%      1.0%     13.5%      4.1%      0.0%   
   Systemic                                                                                                               
   Fever &gt;102.2 degrees F          1.0%      0.5%      0.5%      2.0%      0.5%      0.0%      0.0%      0.0%      4.2%   
   Irritability                   64.5%     24.6%     17.5%     49.5%     25.7%     11.7%     14.7%      6.7%      8.0%   
   Tiredness                      60.7%     31.8%      7.1%     38.8%     18.4%      6.3%      9.3%      5.3%      4.0%   
   Anorexia                       16.6%      8.1%      4.3%      6.3%      4.4%      2.4%      2.7%      1.3%      2.7%   
   Vomiting                        1.9%      2.8%      2.8%      1.9%      1.5%      1.0%      1.3%      1.3%      0.0%   
   Persistent Crying           Percentage of infants within 72 hours after immunization was 0.0% after dose one, 1.4% after dose two, and 0.0% after dose three.   
                  Digestive System
   Anorexia and vomiting occurred with frequencies not significantly different as reported when DTP was given alone without IPV or OPV. (12)



   Nervous System

  Although no causal relationship between IPOL vaccine and GBS has been established, (28) GBS has been temporally related to administration of another inactivated poliovirus vaccine.



   Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been identified during postapproval use of IPOL vaccine. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it may not be possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure. Adverse events were included based on one or more of the following factors: severity, frequency of reporting or strength of evidence for a causal relationship.



 *   Blood and lymphatic system disorders : lymphadenopathy 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions : agitation, injection site reaction including injection site rash and mass 
 *   Immune system disorders : type I hypersensitivity including allergic reaction, anaphylactic reaction, and anaphylactic shock 
 *   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders : arthralgia, myalgia 
 *   Nervous system disorders : convulsion, febrile convulsion, headache, paresthesia, and somnolence 
 *   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders : rash, urticaria 
      Reporting of Adverse Events
   The National Vaccine Injury Compensation Program, established by the National Childhood Vaccine Injury Act of 1986, requires physicians and other healthcare providers who administer vaccines to maintain permanent vaccination records and to report occurrences of certain adverse events to the US Department of Health and Human Services. Reportable events include those listed in the Act for each vaccine and events specified in the package insert as contraindications to further doses of that vaccine. (38) (39) (40)



 Reporting by parents or guardians of all adverse events after vaccine administration should be encouraged. Adverse events following immunization with vaccine should be reported by healthcare providers to the US Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS) Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS). Reporting forms and information about reporting requirements or completion of the form can be obtained from VAERS through a toll-free number 1-800-822-7967. (38) (39) (40)



   Healthcare providers also should report these events to the Pharmacovigilance Department, Sanofi Pasteur Inc., Discovery Drive, Swiftwater, PA 18370 or call 1-800-822-2463.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
