<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="isopto" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Clinical Studies Experience  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.The safety data described below reflect exposure in four controlled clinical trials of 90 days to 2 years duration in 317 patients diagnosed with open-angle glaucoma or ocular hypertension. In the four clinical trials, patients were treated with Isopto(r) Carpine 2%, two to four times daily or with pilocarpine 1%, 1.75% or 2% in fixed combination with betaxolol 0.25%, two or three times daily.The most frequently reported adverse reactions occurring in &gt;= 5% of patients in the pilocarpine 2% populations were: headache/browache, accommodative change, blurred vision, eye irritation, visual impairment (dim, dark, or "jumping" vision), and eye pain.The adverse reaction profile reported for the use of Isopto(r) Carpine in pediatric patients is comparable to that seen in adult patients.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are headache/browache, accommodative change, eye irritation, eye pain, blurred vision, and/or visual impairment (    6.1    ).



        



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Alcon Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-757-9195 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Poor illumination: Exercise caution in night driving and other hazardous occupations in poor illumination (   5.1   ). 
 *  Pre-existing retinal disease: Rare cases of retinal detachment have been reported; a thorough examination of the retina including funduscopy is advised in all patients prior to the initiation of therapy (   5.2   ). 
 *  Iritis: Caution is advised in patients with iritis. (   5.3   ) 
 *  Congenital glaucoma: Caution is advised in pediatric patients with primary congenital glaucoma for control of IOP as cases of a paradoxical increase in IOP have been reported. (   5.4   ) 
    
 

   5.1 Poor Illumination



  Patients should be advised to exercise caution in night driving and other hazardous occupations in poor illumination. In addition, miotics may cause accommodative spasm. Patients should be advised not to drive or use machinery if vision is not clear.



    5.2 Pre-existing Retinal Disease



  As with all miotics, rare cases of retinal detachment have been reported when used in certain susceptible individuals and those with pre-existing retinal disease; therefore, a thorough examination of the retina including funduscopy is advised in all patients prior to the initiation of therapy.



    5.3 Iritis



  Isopto(r) Carpine is not recommended to be used when iritis is present.



    5.4 Primary Congenital Glaucoma



  Caution is advised when using Isopto(r) Carpine in pediatric patients with primary congenital glaucoma for control of intraocular pressure (IOP) as cases of a paradoxical increase in IOP have been reported. In addition, the use of Isopto(r) Carpine is not recommended in pediatric patients diagnosed with glaucoma secondary to anterior segment dysgenesis or uveitis (especially if uveitis is active).



    5.5 Contact Lens Wear



  Contact lens wearers should be advised to remove their lenses prior to the instillation of Isopto(r) Carpine ophthalmic solution and to wait 10 minutes after dosing before reinserting their contact lenses.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
