<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="istalol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most frequently reported adverse reactions have been burning and stinging upon instillation in 38% of patients treated with Istalol. Additional reactions reported with Istalol at a frequency of 4 to 10% include: blurred vision, cataract, conjunctival injection, headache, hypertension, infection, itching and decreased visual acuity  .  (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bausch &amp; Lomb, a division of Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-323-0000, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions have been burning and stinging upon instillation in 38% of patients treated with Istalol. Additional reactions reported with Istalol at a frequency of 4 to 10% include: blurred vision, cataract, conjunctival injection, headache, hypertension, infection, itching and decreased visual acuity.



 The following additional adverse reactions have been reported less frequently with ocular administration of this or other timolol maleate formulations.



   Timolol (Ocular Administration)  



   Body as a whole:  Asthenia/fatigue and chest pain;  Cardiovascular:  Bradycardia, arrhythmia, hypotension, syncope, heart block, cerebral vascular accident, cerebral ischemia, cardiac failure, worsening of angina pectoris, palpitation, cardiac arrest, pulmonary edema, edema, claudication, Raynaud's phenomenon and cold hands and feet;  Digestive:  Nausea, diarrhea, dyspepsia, anorexia, and dry mouth;  Immunologic:  Systemic lupus erythematosus;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Dizziness, increase in signs and symptoms of myasthenia gravis, paresthesia, somnolence, insomnia, nightmares, behavioral changes and psychic disturbances including depression, confusion, hallucinations, anxiety, disorientation, nervousness and memory loss;  Skin:  Alopecia and psoriasiform rash or exacerbation of psoriasis;  Hypersensitivity:  Signs and symptoms of systemic allergic reactions, including angioedema, urticaria, and localized and generalized rash;  Respiratory:  Bronchospasm (predominantly in patients with pre-existing bronchospastic disease), respiratory failure, dyspnea, nasal congestion, cough and upper respiratory infections;  Endocrine:  Masked symptoms of hypoglycemia in diabetic patients (see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  ,  5.6  );  Special Senses:  Signs and symptoms of ocular irritation including conjunctivitis, blepharitis, keratitis, ocular pain, discharge (e.g., crusting), foreign body sensation, itching and tearing, and dry eyes; ptosis, decreased corneal sensitivity; cystoid macular edema; visual disturbances including refractive changes and diplopia; pseudopemphigoid; choroidal detachment following filtration surgery (see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  ,  5.12  );  Urogenital:  Retroperitoneal fibrosis, decreased libido, impotence, and Peyronie's disease.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

    Oral Timolol/Oral Beta-blockers  



 The following additional adverse effects have been reported in clinical experience with ORAL timolol maleate or other ORAL beta-blocking agents and may be considered potential effects of ophthalmic timolol maleate:  Allergic:  Erythematous rash, fever combined with aching and sore throat, laryngospasm with respiratory distress;  Body as a Whole:  Extremity pain, decreased exercise tolerance, weight loss;  Cardiovascular:  Worsening of arterial insufficiency, vasodilatation;  Digestive  : Gastrointestinal pain, hepatomegaly, vomiting, mesenteric arterial thrombosis, ischemic colitis;  Hematologic  : Nonthrombocytopenic purpura; thrombocytopenic purpura, agranulocytosis;  Endocrine:  Hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia;  Skin:  Pruritus, skin irritation, increased pigmentation, sweating;  Musculoskeletal:  Arthralgia;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Vertigo, local weakness, diminished concentration, reversible mental depression progressing to catatonia, an acute reversible syndrome characterized by disorientation for time and place, emotional lability, slightly clouded sensorium and decreased performance on neuropsychometrics;  Respiratory:  Rales, bronchial obstruction;  Urogenital:  Urination difficulties.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Potentiation of Respiratory Reactions Including Asthma  (  5.1  ) 
 *    Cardiac Failure (  5.2  ) 
 *    Obstructive Pulmonary Disease  (  5.3  ) 
 *    Increased Reactivity to Allergens  (  5.4  ) 
 *    Potentiation of Muscle Weakness  (  5.5  ) 
 *    Masking of Hypoglycemic Symptoms in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus (  5.6  ) 
 *    Masking of Thyrotoxicosis (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Potentiation of Respiratory Reactions Including Asthma



  Istalol contains timolol maleate; and although administered topically, it can be absorbed systemically. Therefore, the same adverse reactions found with systemic administration of beta-adrenergic blocking agents may occur with topical administration. For example, severe respiratory reactions and cardiac reactions including death due to bronchospasm in patients with asthma, and rarely death in association with cardiac failure, have been reported following systemic or ophthalmic administration of timolol maleate (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  4.1  ).



    5.2 Cardiac Failure



  Sympathetic stimulation may be essential for support of the circulation in individuals with diminished myocardial contractility, and its inhibition of beta-adrenergic receptor blockade may precipitate more severe failure.



 In patients without a history of cardiac failure, continued depression of the myocardium with beta-blocking agents over a period of time can, in some cases, lead to cardiac failure. At the first sign or symptom of cardiac failure, Istalol should be discontinued (see also  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  4.2  ).



    5.3 Obstructive Pulmonary Disease



  Patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (e.g., chronic bronchitis, emphysema) of mild or moderate severity, bronchospastic disease, or a history of bronchospastic disease [other than bronchial asthma or a history of bronchial asthma in which Istalol is contraindicated (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  4.2   )] should, in general, not receive beta-blocking agents, including Istalol.



    5.4 Increased Reactivity to Allergens



  While taking beta-blockers, patients with a history of atopy or a history of severe anaphylactic reactions to a variety of allergens may be more reactive to repeated accidental, diagnostic, or therapeutic challenge with such allergens. Such patients may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat anaphylactic reactions.



    5.5 Potentiation of Muscle Weakness



  Beta-adrenergic blockade has been reported to potentiate muscle weakness consistent with certain myasthenic symptoms (e.g., diplopia, ptosis, and generalized weakness). Timolol has been reported rarely to increase muscle weakness in some patients with myasthenia gravis or myasthenic symptoms.



    5.6 Masking of Hypoglycemic Symptoms in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus



  Beta-adrenergic blocking agents should be administered with caution in patients subject to spontaneous hypoglycemia or to diabetic patients (especially those with labile diabetes) who are receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents. Beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agents may mask the signs and symptoms of acute hypoglycemia.



    5.7 Masking of Thyrotoxicosis



  Beta-adrenergic blocking agents may mask certain clinical signs (e.g., tachycardia) of hyperthyroidism. Patients suspected of developing thyrotoxicosis should be managed carefully to avoid abrupt withdrawal of beta-adrenergic blocking agents that might precipitate a thyroid storm.



    5.8 Contamination of Topical Ophthalmic Products After Use



  There have been reports of bacterial keratitis associated with the use of multiple-dose containers of topical ophthalmic products. These containers had been inadvertently contaminated by patients who, in most cases, had a concurrent corneal disease or a disruption of the ocular epithelial surface (see  PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION  ,  17  ).



    5.9 Impairment of Beta-adrenergically Mediated Reflexes During Surgery



  The necessity or desirability of withdrawal of beta-adrenergic blocking agents prior to major surgery is controversial. Beta-adrenergic receptor blockade impairs the ability of the heart to respond to beta-adrenergically mediated reflex stimuli. This may augment the risk of general anesthesia in surgical procedures. Some patients receiving beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agents have experienced protracted severe hypotension during anesthesia. Difficulty in restarting and maintaining the heartbeat has also been reported. For these reasons, in patients undergoing elective surgery, some authorities recommend gradual withdrawal of beta-adrenergic receptor blocking agents. If necessary during surgery, the effects of beta-adrenergic blocking agents may be reversed by sufficient doses of adrenergic agonists.



    5.10 Angle-Closure Glaucoma



  In patients with angle-closure glaucoma, the immediate objective of treatment is to reopen the angle. This may require constricting the pupil. Timolol maleate has little or no effect on the pupil. Istalol should not be used alone in the treatment of angle-closure glaucoma.



    5.11 Cerebrovascular Insufficiency



  Because of potential effects of beta-adrenergic blocking agents on blood pressure and pulse, these agents should be used with caution in patients with cerebrovascular insufficiency. If signs or symptoms suggesting reduced cerebral blood flow develop following initiation of therapy with Istalol, alternative therapy should be considered.



    5.12 Choroidal Detachment



  Choroidal detachment after filtration procedures has been reported with the administration of aqueous suppressant therapy (e.g. timolol).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
