<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="janumet0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients simultaneously started on sitagliptin and metformin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo were diarrhea, upper respiratory tract infection, and headache. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients treated with sitagliptin in combination with sulfonylurea and metformin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo in combination with sulfonylurea and metformin were hypoglycemia and headache. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Hypoglycemia was the only adverse reaction reported in &gt;=5% of patients treated with sitagliptin in combination with insulin and metformin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo in combination with insulin and metformin. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Sitagliptin and Metformin Immediate-Release Coadministration in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Inadequately Controlled on Diet and Exercise  



   Table 1  summarizes the most common (&gt;=5% of patients) adverse reactions reported (regardless of investigator assessment of causality) in a 24-week placebo-controlled factorial study in which sitagliptin and metformin immediate-release were coadministered to patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on diet and exercise.



 Table 1: Sitagliptin and Metformin Immediate-Release Coadministered to Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Inadequately Controlled on Diet and Exercise: Adverse Reactions Reported (Regardless of Investigator Assessment of Causality) in &gt;=5% of Patients Receiving Combination Therapy (and Greater than in Patients Receiving Placebo) Intent-to-treat population. 
                       Number of Patients (%)   
                          Placebo     Sitagliptin100 mg oncedaily  Metformin Immediate-Release 500 mg or1000 mg twice daily  Sitagliptin50 mg twice daily +Metformin Immediate-Release 500 mg or 1000mg twice daily   
                          N = 176        N = 179               N = 364                      N = 372             
  
 Diarrhea                 7 (4.0)        5 (2.8)              28 (7.7)                     28 (7.5)             
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection     9 (5.1)        8 (4.5)              19 (5.2)                     23 (6.2)             
 Headache                 5 (2.8)        2 (1.1)              14 (3.8)                     22 (5.9)             
               Sitagliptin Add-on Therapy in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Inadequately Controlled on Metformin Immediate-Release Alone  
 

 In a 24-week placebo-controlled trial of sitagliptin 100 mg administered once daily added to a twice daily metformin immediate-release regimen, there were no adverse reactions reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality in &gt;=5% of patients and more commonly than in patients given placebo. Discontinuation of therapy due to clinical adverse reactions was similar to the placebo treatment group (sitagliptin and metformin immediate-release, 1.9%; placebo and metformin immediate-release, 2.5%).



     Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions  



 The incidences of pre-selected gastrointestinal adverse experiences in patients treated with sitagliptin and metformin immediate-release were similar to those reported for patients treated with metformin immediate-release alone. See  Table 2  .



 Table 2: Pre-selected Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions (Regardless of Investigator Assessment of Causality) Reported in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Receiving Sitagliptin and Metformin Immediate-Release 
        Number of Patients (%)   
        Study of Sitagliptin and Metformin Immediate-Release in Patients Inadequately Controlled on Diet and Exercise  Study of Sitagliptin Add-on in Patients Inadequately Controlled on Metformin Immediate-Release Alone   
         Placebo    Sitagliptin100 mgonce daily  MetforminImmediate-Release500 mg or 1000 mgtwice daily  Sitagliptin 50 mg bid +Metformin Immediate-Release 500 mg or1000 mg twice daily  Placebo andMetforminImmediate-Release&gt;=1500 mgdaily  Sitagliptin 100 mgonce daily andMetforminImmediate-Release&gt;=1500 mg daily   
         N = 176     N = 179          N = 364               N = 372             N = 237            N = 464          
  
 Diarrhea   7 (4.0)     5 (2.8)          28 (7.7)              28 (7.5)            6 (2.5)            11 (2.4)         
 Nausea   2 (1.1)     2 (1.1)          20 (5.5)              18 (4.8)            2 (0.8)            6 (1.3)          
 Vomiting   1 (0.6)     0 (0.0)          2 (0.5)               8 (2.2)             2 (0.8)            5 (1.1)          
 Abdominal Pain   4 (2.3)     6 (3.4)          14 (3.8)              11 (3.0)            9 (3.8)            10 (2.2)         
                 Sitagliptin in Combination with Metformin Immediate-Release and Glimepiride  
 

 In a 24-week placebo-controlled study of sitagliptin 100 mg as add-on therapy in patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on metformin immediate-release and glimepiride (sitagliptin, N=116; placebo, N=113), the adverse reactions reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality in &gt;=5% of patients treated with sitagliptin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo were: hypoglycemia (  Table 3  ) and headache (6.9%, 2.7%).



     Sitagliptin in Combination with Metformin Immediate-Release and Rosiglitazone  



 In a placebo-controlled study of sitagliptin 100 mg as add-on therapy in patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on metformin immediate-release and rosiglitazone (sitagliptin, N=181; placebo, N=97), the adverse reactions reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality through Week 18 in &gt;=5% of patients treated with sitagliptin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo were: upper respiratory tract infection (sitagliptin, 5.5%; placebo, 5.2%) and nasopharyngitis (6.1%, 4.1%). Through Week 54, the adverse reactions reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality in &gt;=5% of patients treated with sitagliptin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo were: upper respiratory tract infection (sitagliptin, 15.5%; placebo, 6.2%), nasopharyngitis (11.0%, 9.3%), peripheral edema (8.3%, 5.2%), and headache (5.5%, 4.1%).



     Sitagliptin in Combination with Metformin Immediate-Release and Insulin  



 In a 24-week placebo-controlled study of sitagliptin 100 mg as add-on therapy in patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on metformin immediate-release and insulin (sitagliptin, N=229; placebo, N=233), the only adverse reaction reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality in &gt;=5% of patients treated with sitagliptin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo was hypoglycemia (  Table 3  ).



     Hypoglycemia  



 In all (N=5) studies, adverse reactions of hypoglycemia were based on all reports of symptomatic hypoglycemia; a concurrent glucose measurement was not required although most (77%) reports of hypoglycemia were accompanied by a blood glucose measurement &lt;=70 mg/dL. When the combination of sitagliptin and metformin immediate-release was coadministered with a sulfonylurea or with insulin, the percentage of patients reporting at least one adverse reaction of hypoglycemia was higher than that observed with placebo and metformin immediate-release coadministered with a sulfonylurea or with insulin (  Table 3  ).



 Table 3: Incidence and Rate of HypoglycemiaAdverse reactions of hypoglycemia were based on all reports of symptomatic hypoglycemia; a concurrent glucose measurement was not required: Intent-to-treat population. (Regardless of Investigator Assessment of Causality) in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Studies of Sitagliptin in Combination with Metformin Immediate-Release Coadministered with Glimepiride or Insulin 
   Add-On to Glimepiride +  Metformin Immediate-Release    (24 weeks)    Sitagliptin 100 mg+ Metformin Immediate-Release+ Glimepiride      Placebo+ Metformin Immediate-Release+ Glimepiride     
                                                  N = 116                            N = 113                
   Overall (%)                                   19 (16.4)                           1 (0.9)                
   Rate (episodes/patient-year)                    0.82                               0.02                  
   Severe (%)                                     0 (0.0)                            0 (0.0)                
   Add-On to Insulin  + Metformin Immediate-Release    (24 weeks)    Sitagliptin 100 mg+ Metformin Immediate-Release+ Insulin      Placebo+ Metformin Immediate-Release+ Insulin     
                                                  N = 229                            N = 233                
   Overall (%)                                   35 (15.3)                          19 (8.2)                
   Rate (episodes/patient-year)                    0.98                               0.61                  
   Severe (%)                                     1 (0.4)                            1 (0.4)                
         The overall incidence of reported adverse reactions of hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on diet and exercise was 0.6% in patients given placebo, 0.6% in patients given sitagliptin alone, 0.8% in patients given metformin immediate-release alone, and 1.6% in patients given sitagliptin in combination with metformin immediate-release. In patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on metformin immediate-release alone, the overall incidence of adverse reactions of hypoglycemia was 1.3% in patients given add-on sitagliptin and 2.1% in patients given add-on placebo.
 

 In the study of sitagliptin and add-on combination therapy with metformin immediate-release and rosiglitazone, the overall incidence of hypoglycemia was 2.2% in patients given add-on sitagliptin and 0.0% in patients given add-on placebo through Week 18. Through Week 54, the overall incidence of hypoglycemia was 3.9% in patients given add-on sitagliptin and 1.0% in patients given add-on placebo.



     Vital Signs and Electrocardiograms  



 With the combination of sitagliptin and metformin immediate-release, no clinically meaningful changes in vital signs or in electrocardiogram parameters (including the QTc interval) were observed.



     Pancreatitis  



 In a pooled analysis of 19 double-blind clinical trials that included data from 10,246 patients randomized to receive sitagliptin 100 mg/day (N=5429) or corresponding (active or placebo) control (N=4817), the incidence of acute pancreatitis was 0.1 per 100 patient-years in each group (4 patients with an event in 4708 patient-years for sitagliptin and 4 patients with an event in 3942 patient-years for control).  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  .]  



     Sitagliptin  



 The most common adverse experience in sitagliptin monotherapy reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality in &gt;=5% of patients and more commonly than in patients given placebo was nasopharyngitis.



     Metformin Extended-Release  



 In a 24-week clinical trial in which extended-release metformin or placebo was added to glyburide therapy, the most common (&gt;5% and greater than placebo) adverse reactions in the combined treatment group were hypoglycemia (13.7% vs. 4.9%), diarrhea (12.5% vs. 5.6%), and nausea (6.7% vs. 4.2%).



     Laboratory Tests  



     Sitagliptin  



 The incidence of laboratory adverse reactions was similar in patients treated with sitagliptin and metformin immediate-release (7.6%) compared to patients treated with placebo and metformin (8.7%). In most but not all studies, a small increase in white blood cell count (approximately 200 cells/microL difference in WBC vs. placebo; mean baseline WBC approximately 6600 cells/microL) was observed due to a small increase in neutrophils. This change in laboratory parameters is not considered to be clinically relevant.



     Metformin hydrochloride  



 In controlled clinical trials of metformin of 29 weeks duration, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum Vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or Vitamin B12supplementation.  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  .]  



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of sitagliptin with or without metformin, and/or in combination with other antidiabetic medications. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, rash, urticaria, cutaneous vasculitis, and exfoliative skin conditions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)  ];  upper respiratory tract infection; hepatic enzyme elevations; acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic and necrotizing pancreatitis  [see  Indications and Usage (1)  ;  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ];  worsening renal function, including acute renal failure (sometimes requiring dialysis)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  ; severe and disabling arthralgia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ]  ; constipation; vomiting; headache; myalgia; pain in extremity; back pain; pruritus.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS  

    Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure.  



   The onset of lactic acidosis is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress.  



   Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap and elevated blood lactate.  



   If acidosis is suspected, JANUMET XR (sitagliptin and metformin HCl extended-release) tablets should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately.   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  .]    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    .  



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic insufficiency, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap and elevated blood lactate. (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue JANUMET XR and hospitalize the patient immediately. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Lactic acidosis: Warn against excessive alcohol intake. JANUMET XR is not recommended in hepatic impairment and is contraindicated in renal impairment. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter. (  4  ,  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Temporarily discontinue JANUMET XR in patients undergoing radiologic studies with intravascular administration of iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food or fluids. (  5.1  ,  5.4  ,  5.7  ,  5.11  ) 
 *  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis in patients treated with sitagliptin (one of the components of JANUMET XR) with or without metformin. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue JANUMET XR. (  5.2  ) 
 *  There have been postmarketing reports of acute renal failure in patients treated with sitagliptin with or without metformin, sometimes requiring dialysis. Before initiating JANUMET XR and at least annually thereafter, assess renal function and verify as normal. (  4  ,  5.1  ,  5.4  ,  5.10  ,  6.2  ) 
 *  Vitamin B12deficiency: Metformin may lower Vitamin B12levels. Measure hematologic parameters annually. (  5.5  ,  6.1  ) 
 *  When used with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or with insulin, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia. (  2.1  ,  5.9  ) 
 *  There have been postmarketing reports of serious allergic and hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with sitagliptin, such as anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome. In such cases, promptly stop JANUMET XR, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment, and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes. (  5.14  ,  6.2  ) 
 *  Severe and disabling arthralgia has been reported in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate. (  5.15  ) 
 *  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with JANUMET XR or any other anti-diabetic drug. (  5.16  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



   Metformin hydrochloride  



 Lactic acidosis is a serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with JANUMET XR and is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate concentrations (&gt;5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels &gt;5 mug/mL are generally found. The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin hydrochloride is approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years. In more than 20,000 patient-years exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal impairment, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, in particular those with unstable or acute congestive heart failure who are at risk of hypoperfusion and hypoxemia, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking JANUMET XR. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. JANUMET XR treatment should not be initiated in any patient unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced. In addition, JANUMET XR should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, JANUMET XR should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic impairment. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake when taking JANUMET XR, because alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin on lactate metabolism. In addition, JANUMET XR should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure necessitating restricted intake of food or fluids. Use of topiramate, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, in epilepsy and migraine prophylaxis may frequently cause dose-dependent metabolic acidosis (in controlled trials, 32% and 67% for adjunctive treatment in adults and pediatric patients, respectively, and 15 to 25% for monotherapy of epilepsy, with decrease in serum bicarbonate to less than 20 mEq/L; 3% and 11% for adjunctive treatment in adults and pediatric patients, respectively, and 1 to 7% for monotherapy of epilepsy, with decrease in serum bicarbonate to less than 17 mEq/L) and may exacerbate the risk of metformin-induced lactic acidosis. [See  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ;  Clinical Pharmacology (12)  .]  The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis.



 Patients should be educated to promptly report these symptoms to their physician should they occur. If present, JANUMET XR should be withdrawn until lactic acidosis is ruled out. Serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, blood pH, lactate levels, and blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of JANUMET XR, gastrointestinal symptoms, which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to recur. Later occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease. Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking JANUMET XR do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explainable by other mechanisms, such as poorly-controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling. Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia). Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking JANUMET XR, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin hydrochloride is dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery. [See  Contraindications (4)  .]  



    5.2 Pancreatitis



  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis, in patients taking sitagliptin with or without metformin. After initiation of JANUMET XR, patients should be observed carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, JANUMET XR should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated. It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using JANUMET XR.



    5.3 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Since impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis, JANUMET XR should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease.



    5.4 Assessment of Renal Function



  Metformin and sitagliptin are substantially excreted by the kidney.



    Metformin hydrochloride  



 The risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of impairment of renal function. Therefore, JANUMET XR is contraindicated in patients with renal impairment.



 Before initiation of JANUMET XR and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal dysfunction is anticipated (e.g., elderly), renal function should be assessed more frequently and JANUMET XR discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present.



    Sitagliptin  



 There have been postmarketing reports of worsening renal function in patients taking sitagliptin with or without metformin, including acute renal failure, sometimes requiring dialysis. Before initiation of therapy with JANUMET XR and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal dysfunction is anticipated, particularly in elderly patients, renal function should be assessed more frequently and JANUMET XR discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present.



    5.5 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled clinical trials of metformin of 29 weeks duration, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum Vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or Vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on JANUMET XR and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  .]  



 Certain individuals (those with inadequate Vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal Vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum Vitamin B12measurements at two- to three-year intervals may be useful.



    5.6 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol potentiates the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients should be warned against excessive alcohol intake while receiving JANUMET XR.



    5.7 Surgical Procedures



  Use of JANUMET XR should be temporarily suspended for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.8 Change in Clinical Status of Patients with Previously Controlled Type 2 Diabetes



  A patient with type 2 diabetes previously well controlled on JANUMET XR who develops laboratory abnormalities or clinical illness (especially vague and poorly defined illness) should be evaluated promptly for evidence of ketoacidosis or lactic acidosis. Evaluation should include serum electrolytes and ketones, blood glucose and, if indicated, blood pH, lactate, pyruvate, and metformin levels. If acidosis of either form occurs, JANUMET XR must be stopped immediately and other appropriate corrective measures initiated.



    5.9 Use with Medications Known to Cause Hypoglycemia



     Sitagliptin  



 When sitagliptin was used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin, medications known to cause hypoglycemia, the incidence of hypoglycemia was increased over that of placebo used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ].  Therefore, patients also receiving an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin may require a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ]  .



    Metformin hydrochloride  



 Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation, or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as sulfonylureas and insulin) or ethanol. Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.



    5.10 Concomitant Medications Affecting Renal Function or Metformin Disposition



  Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or may interfere with the disposition of metformin, such as cationic drugs that are eliminated by renal tubular secretion [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  , should be used with caution.



    5.11 Radiologic Studies with Intravascular Iodinated Contrast Materials



  Intravascular contrast studies with iodinated materials (for example, intravenous urogram, intravenous cholangiography, angiography, and computed tomography (CT) scans with intravascular contrast materials) can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin [see     Contraindications (4)  ].  Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, JANUMET XR should be temporarily discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been re-evaluated and found to be normal.



    5.12 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause, acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients on JANUMET XR therapy, the drug should be promptly discontinued.



    5.13 Loss of Control of Blood Glucose



  When a patient stabilized on any diabetic regimen is exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a temporary loss of glycemic control may occur. At such times, it may be necessary to withhold JANUMET XR and temporarily administer insulin. JANUMET XR may be reinstituted after the acute episode is resolved.



    5.14 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with sitagliptin, one of the components of JANUMET XR. These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome. Onset of these reactions occurred within the first 3 months after initiation of treatment with sitagliptin, with some reports occurring after the first dose. If a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue JANUMET XR, assess for other potential causes for the event, and institute alternative treatment for diabetes. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  .]  



 Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema to another dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP4) inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with JANUMET XR.



    5.15 Severe and Disabling Arthralgia



   There have been postmarketing reports of severe and disabling arthralgia in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. The time to onset of symptoms following initiation of drug therapy varied from one day to years. Patients experienced relief of symptoms upon discontinuation of the medication. A subset of patients experienced a recurrence of symptoms when restarting the same drug or a different DPP-4 inhibitor. Consider DPP-4 inhibitors as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate.  



    5.16 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with JANUMET XR or any other anti-diabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
