<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="jentadueto0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients treated with linagliptin and metformin coadministered and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo are nasopharyngitis and diarrhea (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-542-6257 or 1-800-459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Linagliptin/Metformin  



 The safety of concomitantly administered linagliptin (daily dose 5 mg) and metformin (mean daily dose of approximately 1800 mg) has been evaluated in 2816 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated for &gt;=12 weeks in clinical trials.



 Three placebo-controlled studies with linagliptin + metformin were conducted: 2 studies were 24 weeks in duration, 1 study was 12 weeks in duration. In the 3 placebo-controlled clinical studies, adverse reactions which occurred in &gt;=5% of patients receiving linagliptin + metformin (n=875) and were more common than in patients given placebo + metformin (n=539) included nasopharyngitis (5.7% vs 4.3%).



 In a 24-week factorial design study, adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients receiving linagliptin + metformin and were more common than in patients given placebo are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients Treated with Linagliptin + Metformin and Greater than with Placebo in a 24-week Factorial-Design Study 
                    Placebon=72      LinagliptinMonotherapyn=142      MetforminMonotherapyn=291      Combination ofLinagliptin with Metforminn=286     
                    n (%)            n (%)            n (%)            n (%)           
 Nasopharyngitis  1 (1.4)          8 (5.6)          8 (2.7)          18 (6.3)          
 Diarrhea         2 (2.8)          5 (3.5)          11 (3.8)         18 (6.3)          
      Other adverse reactions reported in clinical studies with treatment of linagliptin + metformin were hypersensitivity (e.g., urticaria, angioedema, or bronchial hyperreactivity), cough, decreased appetite, nausea, vomiting, pruritus, and pancreatitis.
 

   Linagliptin  



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=2% of patients treated with linagliptin 5 mg and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo included: nasopharyngitis (7.0% vs 6.1%), diarrhea (3.3% vs 3.0%), and cough (2.1% vs 1.4%).



 Rates for other adverse reactions for linagliptin 5 mg vs placebo when linagliptin was used in combination with specific anti-diabetic agents were: urinary tract infection (3.1% vs 0%) and hypertriglyceridemia (2.4% vs 0%) when linagliptin was used as add-on to sulfonylurea; hyperlipidemia (2.7% vs 0.8%) and weight increased (2.3% vs 0.8%) when linagliptin was used as add-on to pioglitazone; and constipation (2.1% vs 1%) when linagliptin was used as add-on to basal insulin therapy.



 Other adverse reactions reported in clinical studies with treatment of linagliptin monotherapy were hypersensitivity (e.g., urticaria, angioedema, localized skin exfoliation, or bronchial hyperreactivity) and myalgia. In the clinical trial program, pancreatitis was reported in 15.2 cases per 10,000 patient year exposure while being treated with linagliptin compared with 3.7 cases per 10,000 patient year exposure while being treated with comparator (placebo and active comparator, sulfonylurea). Three additional cases of pancreatitis were reported following the last administered dose of linagliptin.



   Metformin  



 The most common adverse reactions due to initiation of metformin are diarrhea, nausea/vomiting, flatulence, asthenia, indigestion, abdominal discomfort, and headache.



 In a 24-week clinical trial in which extended-release metformin or placebo was added to glyburide therapy, the most common (&gt;5% and greater than placebo) adverse reactions in the combined treatment group were hypoglycemia (13.7% vs 4.9%), diarrhea (12.5% vs 5.6%), and nausea (6.7% vs 4.2%).



   Hypoglycemia  



   Linagliptin/Metformin  



 In a 24-week factorial design study, hypoglycemia was reported in 4 (1.4%) of 286 subjects treated with linagliptin + metformin, 6 (2.1%) of 291 subjects treated with metformin, and 1 (1.4%) of 72 subjects treated with placebo. When linagliptin was administered in combination with metformin and a sulfonylurea, 181 (22.9%) of 792 patients reported hypoglycemia compared with 39 (14.8%) of 263 patients administered placebo in combination with metformin and sulfonylurea. Adverse reactions of hypoglycemia were based on all reports of hypoglycemia. A concurrent glucose measurement was not required or was normal in some patients. Therefore, it is not possible to conclusively determine that all these reports reflect true hypoglycemia.



   Laboratory Tests  



   Metformin  



 Long-term treatment with metformin has been associated with a decrease in vitamin B12absorption which may very rarely result in clinically significant vitamin B12deficiency (e.g., megaloblastic anemia)  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  .



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of linagliptin with or without metformin, and/or in combination with other antidiabetic medications. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  Acute pancreatitis, including fatal pancreatitis [see Indications and Usage (  1.2  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Severe and disabling arthralgia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Rash 
 *  Mouth ulceration, stomatitis 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF LACTIC ACIDOSIS

  WARNING: RISK OF LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    Postmarketing cases of metformin-associated

lactic acidosis have resulted in death, hypothermia, hypotension,

and resistant bradyarrhythmias. The onset of metformin-associated

lactic acidosis is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms

such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, somnolence, and abdominal

pain. Metformin-associated lactic acidosis was characterized by elevated

blood lactate levels (&gt;5 mmol/Liter), anion gap acidosis (without

evidence of ketonuria or ketonemia), an increased lactate/pyruvate

ratio; and metformin plasma levels generally &gt;5 mcg/mL   [see

Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   Risk

factors for metformin-associated lactic acidosis include renal impairment,

concomitant use of certain drugs (e.g., cationic drugs such as topiramate),

age 65 years old or greater, having a radiological study with contrast,

surgery and other procedures, hypoxic states (e.g., acute congestive

heart failure), excessive alcohol intake, and hepatic impairment.  



   Steps to reduce

the risk of and manage metformin-associated lactic acidosis in these

high risk groups are provided in the full prescribing information   [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ), Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings

and Precautions (  5.1  ), Drug Interactions

(  7.1  ), and Use in Specific Populations

(  8.6  ,   8.7  )].    



   If metformin-associated lactic acidosis is suspected, immediately

discontinue JENTADUETO XR and institute general supportive measures

in a hospital setting.  Prompt hemodialysis is recommended   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: RISK OF LACTIC ACIDOSIS  



   See full prescribing information

for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Postmarketing cases of metformin-associated lactic acidosis have resulted in death, hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias. Symptoms included malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, somnolence, and abdominal pain. Laboratory abnormalities included elevated blood lactate levels, anion gap acidosis, increased lactate/pyruvate ratio; and metformin plasma levels generally &gt;5 mcg/mL. (5.1) 
 *  Risk factors include renal impairment, concomitant use of certain drugs, age &gt;= 65 years old, radiological studies with contrast, surgery and other procedures, hypoxic states, excessive alcohol intake, and hepatic impairment. Steps to reduce the risk of and manage metformin-associated lactic acidosis in these high risk groups are provided in the Full Prescribing Information. (5.1) 
 *  If lactic acidosis is suspected, discontinue JENTADUETO XR and institute general supportive measures in a hospital setting. Prompt hemodialysis is recommended. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Lactic acidosis: See boxed warning (  5.1  ) 
 *  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue JENTADUETO XR. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hypoglycemia: When used with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea (SU)) or insulin, consider lowering the dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions: There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with linagliptin (one of the components of JENTADUETO XR) including anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions. In such cases, promptly discontinue JENTADUETO XR, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment, and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Vitamin B12deficiency: Metformin may lower vitamin B12levels. Monitor hematologic parameters annually. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Arthralgia: Severe and disabling arthralgia has been reported in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. Consider as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Macrovascular outcomes: No conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with JENTADUETO XR or any other antidiabetic drug (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



   Metformin  



 There have been postmarketing cases of metformin-associated lactic acidosis, including fatal cases. These cases had a subtle onset and were accompanied by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, abdominal pain, respiratory distress, or increased somnolence; however, hypothermia, hypotension and resistant bradyarrhythmias have occurred with severe acidosis. Metformin-associated lactic acidosis was characterized by elevated blood lactate concentrations (&gt;5 mmol/Liter), anion gap acidosis (without evidence of ketonuria or ketonemia), and an increased lactate pyruvate ratio; metformin plasma levels generally &gt;5 mcg/mL. Metformin decreases liver uptake of lactate increasing lactate blood levels which may increase risk of lactic acidosis, especially in patients at risk.



 If metformin-associated lactic acidosis is suspected, general supportive measures should be instituted promptly in a hospital setting, along with immediate discontinuation of JENTADUETO XR. In JENTADUETO XR-treated patients with a diagnosis or strong suspicion of lactic acidosis, prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove accumulated metformin (metformin hydrochloride is dialyzable, with clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions). Hemodialysis has often resulted in reversal of symptoms and recovery.



 Educate patients and their families about the symptoms of lactic acidosis and if these symptoms occur instruct them to discontinue JENTADUETO XR and report these symptoms to their healthcare provider.



 For each of the known and possible risk factors for metformin-associated lactic acidosis, recommendations to reduce the risk of and manage metformin-associated lactic acidosis are provided below:



  Renal Impairment:  The postmarketing metformin-associated lactic acidosis cases primarily occurred in patients with significant renal impairment. The risk of metformin accumulation and metformin-associated lactic acidosis increases with the severity of renal impairment because metformin is substantially excreted by the kidney [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )].  



 *  Before initiating JENTADUETO XR, obtain an estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR). 
 *  JENTADUETO XR is contraindicated in patients with an eGFR less than 30 mL/min/1.73 m  2  . Initiation of JENTADUETO XR is not recommended in patients with eGFR between 30 - 45 mL/min/1.73 m  2  . 
 *  Obtain an eGFR at least annually in all patients taking JENTADUETO XR. In patients at increased risk for the development of renal impairment (e.g., the elderly), renal function should be assessed more frequently. 
 *  In patients taking JENTADUETO XR whose eGFR later falls below 45 mL/min/1.73 m  2  , assess the benefit and risk of continuing therapy [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ), Contraindications (  4  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )] . 
     Drug Interactions:  The concomitant use of JENTADUETO XR with specific drugs may increase the risk of metformin-associated lactic acidosis: those that impair renal function, result in significant hemodynamic change, interfere with acid-base balance or increase metformin accumulation (e.g., cationic drugs) [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  . Therefore, consider more frequent monitoring of patients.
 

  Age 65 or Greater:  The risk of metformin-associated lactic acidosis increases with the patient's age because elderly patients have a greater likelihood of having hepatic, renal, or cardiac impairment than younger patients. Assess renal function more frequently in elderly patients [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )].  



  Radiological Studies with Contrast:  Administration of intravascular iodinated contrast agents in metformin-treated patients has led to an acute decrease in renal function and the occurrence of lactic acidosis. Stop JENTADUETO XR at the time of, or prior to, an iodinated contrast imaging procedure in patients with an eGFR between 30 and 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ; in patients with a history of hepatic impairment, alcoholism, or heart failure; or in patients who will be administered intra-arterial iodinated contrast. Re-evaluate eGFR 48 hours after the imaging procedure, and restart JENTADUETO XR if renal function is stable.



  Surgery and Other Procedures:  Withholding of food and fluids during surgical or other procedures may increase the risk for volume depletion, hypotension and renal impairment. JENTADUETO XR should be temporarily discontinued while patients have restricted food and fluid intake.



  Hypoxic States:  Several of the postmarketing cases of metformin-associated lactic acidosis occurred in the setting of acute congestive heart failure (particularly when accompanied by hypoperfusion and hypoxemia). Cardiovascular collapse (shock), acute myocardial infarction, sepsis, and other conditions associated with hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur, discontinue JENTADUETO XR.



  Excessive Alcohol Intake:  Alcohol potentiates the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism and this may increase the risk of metformin-associated lactic acidosis. Warn patients against excessive alcohol intake while receiving JENTADUETO XR.



  Hepatic Impairment:  Patients with hepatic impairment have developed cases of metformin-associated lactic acidosis. This may be due to impaired lactate clearance resulting in higher lactate blood levels. Therefore, avoid use of JENTADUETO XR in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease.



    5.2 Pancreatitis



  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis, including fatal pancreatitis, in patients taking linagliptin. Take careful notice of potential signs and symptoms of pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue JENTADUETO XR and initiate appropriate management. It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using JENTADUETO XR.



    5.3 Use with Medications Known to Cause Hypoglycemia



   Linagliptin  



 Insulin secretagogues and insulin are known to cause hypoglycemia. The use of linagliptin in combination with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) was associated with a higher rate of hypoglycemia compared with placebo in a clinical trial [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Therefore, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with JENTADUETO XR [see Drug Interactions (  7.3  )].  



  Metformin  



 Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation, or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as SUs and insulin) or ethanol. Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.



    5.4 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with linagliptin (one of the components of JENTADUETO XR). These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions. Onset of these reactions occurred within the first 3 months after initiation of treatment with linagliptin, with some reports occurring after the first dose. If a serious hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue JENTADUETO XR, assess for other potential causes for the event, and institute alternative treatment for diabetes.



 Angioedema has also been reported with other dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitors. Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema to another DPP-4 inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with JENTADUETO XR.



    5.5 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled, 29-week clinical trials of metformin a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of metformin-treated patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia or neurologic manifestations due to the short duration (&lt;1 year) of the clinical trials. This risk may be more relevant to patients receiving long-term treatment with metformin, and adverse hematologic and neurologic reactions have been reported postmarketing. The decrease in vitamin B12levels appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on JENTADUETO XR and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. Certain individuals (those with inadequate vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum vitamin B12measurement at 2- to 3-year intervals may be useful.



    5.6 Severe and Disabling Arthralgia



  There have been postmarketing reports of severe and disabling arthralgia in patients taking DPP-4 inhibitors. The time to onset of symptoms following initiation of drug therapy varied from one day to years. Patients experienced relief of symptoms upon discontinuation of the medication. A subset of patients experienced a recurrence of symptoms when restarting the same drug or a different DPP-4 inhibitor. Consider DPP-4 inhibitors as a possible cause for severe joint pain and discontinue drug if appropriate.



    5.7 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with linagliptin or metformin or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
