<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="jevtana" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in another section of the label:



 *  Bone Marrow Suppression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ] . 
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] . 
 *  Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] . 
 *  Renal Failure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ] . 
 *  Use in Elderly Patients [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ] . 
 *  Use in Patients with Hepatic Impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ] . 
 *  Embryo-Fetal Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ] . 
      EXCERPT:   Most common all grades adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) are neutropenia, anemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, diarrhea, fatigue, nausea, vomiting, constipation, asthenia, abdominal pain, hematuria, back pain, anorexia, peripheral neuropathy, pyrexia, dyspnea, dysgeusia, cough, arthralgia, and alopecia. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi-aventis U.S. LLC at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of JEVTANA in combination with prednisone was evaluated in 371 patients with hormone-refractory metastatic prostate cancer treated in a single randomized trial, compared to mitoxantrone plus prednisone.



 Deaths due to causes other than disease progression within 30 days of last study drug dose were reported in 18 (5%) JEVTANA-treated patients and 3 (&lt; 1%) mitoxantrone-treated patients. The most common fatal adverse reactions in JEVTANA-treated patients were infections (n=5) and renal failure (n=4). The majority (4 of 5 patients) of fatal infection-related adverse reactions occurred after a single dose of JEVTANA. Other fatal adverse reactions in JEVTANA-treated patients included ventricular fibrillation, cerebral hemorrhage, and dyspnea.



 The most common (&gt;= 10%) grade 1-4 adverse reactions were anemia, leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, diarrhea, fatigue, nausea, vomiting, constipation, asthenia, abdominal pain, hematuria, back pain, anorexia, peripheral neuropathy, pyrexia, dyspnea, dysguesia, cough, arthralgia, and alopecia.



 The most common (&gt;= 5%) grade 3-4 adverse reactions in patients who received JEVTANA were neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, febrile neutropenia, diarrhea, fatigue, and asthenia.



 Treatment discontinuations due to adverse drug reactions occurred in 18% of patients who received JEVTANA and 8% of patients who received mitoxantrone. The most common adverse reactions leading to treatment discontinuation in the JEVTANA group were neutropenia and renal failure. Dose reductions were reported in 12% of JEVTANA-treated patients and 4% of mitoxantrone-treated patients. Dose delays were reported in 28% of JEVTANA-treated patients and 15% of mitoxantrone-treated patients.



 Table 2 - Incidence of Reported Adverse ReactionsGraded using NCI CTCAE version 3 and Hematologic Abnormalities in &gt;= 5% of Patients Receiving JEVTANA in Combination with Prednisone or Mitoxantrone in Combination with Prednisone 
                                           JEVTANA 25 mg/m  2  every 3 weeks with prednisone 10 mg dailyn=371  Mitoxantrone 12 mg/m  2  every 3 weeks with prednisone 10 mg dailyn=371   
                                           Grade 1-4n (%)   Grade 3-4n (%)   Grade 1-4n (%)   Grade 3-4n (%)    
  
   Any Adverse Reaction                                                                                         
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders                                                        
   Neutropenia                                347 (94%)        303 (82%)        325 (87%)        215 (58%)      
   Febrile Neutropenia                         27 (7%)          27 (7%)          5 (1%)           5 (1%)        
   Anemia                                     361 (98%)        39 (11%)         302 (82%)         18 (5%)       
   Leukopenia                                 355 (96%)        253 (69%)        343 (93%)        157 (42%)      
   Thrombocytopenia                           176 (48%)         15 (4%)         160 (43%)         6 (2%)        
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                                            
   Arrhythmia                                  18 (5%)          4 (1%)           6 (2%)          1 (&lt; 1%)       
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                   
   Diarrhea                                   173 (47%)         23 (6%)         39 (11%)         1 (&lt; 1%)       
   Nausea                                     127 (34%)         7 (2%)          85 (23%)         1 (&lt; 1%)       
   Vomiting                                   83 (22%)          6 (2%)          38 (10%)             0          
   Constipation                               76 (20%)          4 (1%)          57 (15%)         2 (&lt; 1%)       
   Abdominal Pain                             64 (17%)          7 (2%)           23 (6%)             0          
   Dyspepsia                                  36 (10%)             0             9 (2%)              0          
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions     
   Fatigue                                    136 (37%)         18 (5%)         102 (27%)         11 (3%)       
   Asthenia                                   76 (20%)          17 (5%)         46 (12%)          9 (2%)        
   Pyrexia                                    45 (12%)          4 (1%)           23 (6%)         1 (&lt; 1%)       
   Peripheral Edema                            34 (9%)         2 (&lt; 1%)          34 (9%)         2 (&lt; 1%)       
   Mucosal Inflammation                        22 (6%)         1 (&lt; 1%)          10 (3%)         1 (&lt; 1%)       
   Pain                                        20 (5%)          4 (1%)           18 (5%)          7 (2%)        
   Infections and Infestations                                                                                  
   Urinary Tract Infection                     29 (8%)          6 (2%)           12 (3%)          4 (1%)        
   Investigations                                                                                               
   Weight Decreased                            32 (9%)             0             28 (8%)         1 (&lt; 1%)       
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders       
   Anorexia                                   59 (16%)         3 (&lt; 1%)         39 (11%)         3 (&lt; 1%)       
   Dehydration                                 18 (5%)          8 (2%)           10 (3%)         3 (&lt; 1%)       
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
   Back Pain                                  60 (16%)          14 (4%)         45 (12%)          11 (3%)       
   Arthralgia                                 39 (11%)          4 (1%)           31 (8%)          4 (1%)        
   Muscle Spasms                               27 (7%)             0             10 (3%)             0          
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                     
   Peripheral Neuropathy                      50 (13%)         3 (&lt; 1%)         12 (3.2%)        3 (&lt; 1%)       
   Dysgeusia                                  41 (11%)             0             15 (4%)             0          
   Dizziness                                   30 (8%)             0             21 (6%)         2 (&lt; 1%)       
   Headache                                    28 (8%)             0             19 (5%)             0          
   Renal and Urinary Tract Disorders        
   Hematuria                                  62 (17%)          7 (2%)           13 (4%)         1 (&lt; 1%)       
   Dysuria                                     25 (7%)             0             5 (1%)              0          
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders     
   Dyspnea                                    43 (12%)          4 (1%)           16 (4%)         2 (&lt; 1%)       
   Cough                                      40 (11%)             0             22 (6%)             0          
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders     
   Alopecia                                   37 (10%)             0             18 (5%)             0          
   Vascular Disorders                                                                                           
   Hypotension                                 20 (5%)         2 (&lt;1 %)          9 (2%)          1 (&lt; 1%)       
                                                                                                                
   Median Duration of Treatment               6 cycles         4 cycles       
             Neutropenia and Associated Clinical Events:
 

 Five patients experienced fatal infectious adverse events (sepsis or septic shock). All had grade 4 neutropenia and one had febrile neutropenia. One additional patient's death was attributed to neutropenia without a documented infection. Twenty-two (6%) patients discontinued JEVTANA treatment due to neutropenia, febrile neutropenia, infection, or sepsis. The most common adverse reaction leading to treatment discontinuation in the JEVTANA group was neutropenia (2%).



   Hematuria:



 Adverse events of hematuria, including those requiring medical intervention, were more common in JEVTANA-treated patients. The incidence of grade &gt;= 2 hematuria was 6% in JEVTANA-treated patients and 2% in mitoxantrone-treated patients. Other factors associated with hematuria were well-balanced between arms and do not account for the increased rate of hematuria on the JEVTANA arm.



   Hepatic Laboratory Abnormalities:



 The incidences of grade 3-4 increased AST, increased ALT, and increased bilirubin were each &lt;= 1%.



   Elderly Population:



 The following grade 1-4 adverse reactions were reported at rates &gt;= 5% higher in patients 65 years of age or greater compared to younger patients: fatigue (40% vs. 30%), neutropenia (97% vs. 89%), asthenia (24% vs. 15%), pyrexia (15% vs. 8%), dizziness (10% vs. 5%), urinary tract infection (10% vs. 3%) and dehydration (7% vs. 2%), respectively.



 The incidence of the following grade 3-4 adverse reactions were higher in patients &gt;= 65 years of age compared to younger patients; neutropenia (87% vs. 74%), and febrile neutropenia (8% vs. 6%)  [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  ]  .



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified from clinical trials and/or post-marketing surveillance. Because they are reported from a population of unknown size, precise estimates of frequency cannot be made.



 Gastrointestinal: Gastritis, intestinal obstruction.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: NEUTROPENIA AND HYPERSENSITIVITY

    WARNING: NEUTROPENIA AND HYPERSENSITIVITY  

  EXCERPT:     WARNING: NEUTROPENIA AND HYPERSENSITIVITY  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    .  



 *  Neutropenic deaths have been reported. Obtain frequent blood counts to monitor for neutropenia. Do not give JEVTANA if neutrophil counts are &lt;=1,500 cells/mm3. (2.2)(4) 
 *  Severe hypersensitivity can occur and may include generalized rash/erythema, hypotension and bronchospasm. Discontinue JEVTANA immediately if severe reactions occur and administer appropriate therapy. (2.1)(5.2) 
 *  Contraindicated if history of severe hypersensitivity reactions to JEVTANA or to drugs formulated with polysorbate 80. (4) 
    
 

      Neutropenia:   Neutropenic deaths have been reported. In order to monitor the occurrence of neutropenia, frequent blood cell counts should be performed on all patients receiving JEVTANA. JEVTANA is contraindicated in patients with neutrophil counts of &lt;=1,500 cells/mm  3       [see   Contraindications (4)   and   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]    .  



       Severe hypersensitivity:   Severe hypersensitivity reactions can occur and may include generalized rash/erythema, hypotension and bronchospasm. Severe hypersensitivity reactions require immediate discontinuation of the JEVTANA infusion and administration of appropriate therapy. Patients should receive premedication. JEVTANA is contraindicated in patients who have a history of severe hypersensitivity reactions to cabazitaxel or to other drugs formulated with polysorbate 80     [see   Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ,   Contraindications (4)  , and   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Bone marrow suppression (particularly neutropenia) and its clinical consequences (febrile neutropenia, neutropenic infections): Monitor blood counts frequently to determine if dosage modification or initiation of G-CSF is needed. Primary prophylaxis with G-CSF should be considered in patients with high-risk clinical features. Use caution in patients with hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dL. (  2.2  )(  4  )(  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity: Severe hypersensitivity reactions can occur. Premedicate with corticosteroids and H2 antagonists. Discontinue infusion immediately if hypersensitivity is observed and treat as indicated. (  4  )(  5.2  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal disorders: Nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea may occur. Mortality related to diarrhea has been reported. Rehydrate and treat with anti-emetics and anti-diarrheals as needed. If experiencing Grade &gt;= 3 diarrhea, dosage should be modified. (  2.2  ) Deaths have occurred due to gastrointestinal hemorrhage, perforation and neutropenic enterocolitis. Delay or discontinue JEVTANA. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Renal failure, including cases with fatal outcomes, has been reported. Identify cause and manage aggressively. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Elderly patients: Patients &gt;= 65 years of age were more likely to experience fatal outcomes not related to disease progression and certain adverse reactions, including neutropenia and febrile neutropenia. Monitor closely. (  5.5  )(  6  )(  8.5  ) 
 *  Hepatic impairment: Reduce the JEVTANA dose to 20 mg/m  2  in patients with mild hepatic impairment and to 15 mg/m  2  in patients with moderate hepatic impairment. (  2.3  ) 
 *  JEVTANA can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. (  5.7  )(  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Bone Marrow Suppression



   Bone marrow suppression manifested as neutropenia, anemia, thrombocytopenia and/or pancytopenia may occur. Neutropenic deaths have been reported. In the randomized trial, five patients (1.3%) experienced fatal infectious adverse events (sepsis or septic shock). All had grade 4 neutropenia and one had febrile neutropenia. One additional patient's death was attributed to neutropenia without a documented infection. Grade 3-4 neutropenia has been observed in 82% of patients treated with JEVTANA in the randomized trial.  



 G-CSF may be administered to reduce the risks of neutropenia complications associated with JEVTANA use. Primary prophylaxis with G-CSF should be considered in patients with high-risk clinical features (age &gt; 65 years, poor performance status, previous episodes of febrile neutropenia, extensive prior radiation ports, poor nutritional status, or other serious comorbidities) that predispose them to increased complications from prolonged neutropenia. Therapeutic use of G-CSF and secondary prophylaxis should be considered in all patients considered to be at increased risk for neutropenia complications.



 Monitoring of complete blood counts is essential on a weekly basis during cycle 1 and before each treatment cycle thereafter so that the dose can be adjusted, if needed [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  .



 JEVTANA is contraindicated in patients with neutrophils &lt;= 1,500/mm  3   [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



  Caution is recommended in patients with hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dl.  



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions may occur within a few minutes following the initiation of the infusion of JEVTANA, thus facilities and equipment for the treatment of hypotension and bronchospasm should be available. Severe hypersensitivity reactions can occur and may include generalized rash/erythema, hypotension and bronchospasm.



 Premedicate all patients prior to the initiation of the infusion of JEVTANA [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ]  . Observe patients closely for hypersensitivity reactions, especially during the first and second infusions. Severe hypersensitivity reactions require immediate discontinuation of the JEVTANA infusion and appropriate therapy. JEVTANA is contraindicated in patients with a history of severe hypersensitivity reactions to cabazitaxel or to other drugs formulated with polysorbate 80 [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.3 Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions



  Nausea, vomiting and severe diarrhea, at times, may occur. Death related to diarrhea and electrolyte imbalance occurred in the randomized clinical trial. Intensive measures may be required for severe diarrhea and electrolyte imbalance. Antiemetic prophylaxis is recommended. Treat patients with rehydration, anti-diarrheal or anti-emetic medications as needed. Treatment delay or dosage reduction may be necessary if patients experience Grade &gt;= 3 diarrhea [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ].  



 Gastrointestinal (GI) hemorrhage and perforation, ileus, enterocolitis, neutropenic enterocolitis, including fatal outcome, have been reported in patients treated with JEVTANA [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . Risk may be increased with neutropenia, age, steroid use, concomitant use of NSAIDs, anti-platelet therapy or anti-coagulants, and patients with a prior history of pelvic radiotherapy, adhesions, ulceration and GI bleeding.



 Abdominal pain and tenderness, fever, persistent constipation, diarrhea, with or without neutropenia, may be early manifestations of serious gastrointestinal toxicity and should be evaluated and treated promptly. JEVTANA treatment delay or discontinuation may be necessary.



    5.4 Renal Failure



  In the randomized clinical trial, renal failure of any grade occurred in 4% of the patients being treated with JEVTANA, including four cases with fatal outcome. Most cases occurred in association with sepsis, dehydration, or obstructive uropathy [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Some deaths due to renal failure did not have a clear etiology. Appropriate measures should be taken to identify causes of renal failure and treat aggressively.



    5.5 Use in Elderly Patients



  In the randomized clinical trial, 3 of 131 (2%) patients &lt; 65 years of age and 15 of 240 (6%) &gt;= 65 years of age died of causes other than disease progression within 30 days of the last cabazitaxel dose. Patients &gt;= 65 years of age are more likely to experience certain adverse reactions, including neutropenia and febrile neutropenia [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  ]  .



    5.6 Use in Patients with Hepatic Impairment



   Cabazitaxel is extensively metabolized in the liver.  



  JEVTANA is contraindicated in patients with severe hepatic impairment (total bilirubin &gt; 3 * ULN) [  see   Contraindications (4)  ]  . Dose should be reduced for patients with mild (total bilirubin &gt; 1 to &lt;= 1.5 * ULN or AST &gt; 1.5 * ULN) and moderate (total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 to &lt;= 3.0 * ULN and any AST) hepatic impairment, based on tolerability data in these patients [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  ]  . Administration of cabazitaxel to patients with mild and moderate hepatic impairment should be undertaken with caution and close monitoring of safety.  



    5.7 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  JEVTANA is not indicated for use in female patients.



 JEVTANA can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. In non-clinical studies in rats and rabbits, cabazitaxel was embryotoxic, fetotoxic, and abortifacient at exposures significantly lower than those expected at the recommended human dose level.



 There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women using JEVTANA. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Females of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant during treatment with JEVTANA [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
