<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="karbinal" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Use of Karbinal ER may result in decreased mental alertness with impaired mental or physical abilities [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].



 The most frequent adverse reactions include: sedation, sleepiness, dizziness, disturbed coordination, epigastric distress, and thickening of bronchial secretions. In clinical use, younger children and older adults may be particularly sensitive to adverse reactions [  see  Pediatric Use (8.4)  and  Geriatric Use (8.5)    ].



 The following adverse reactions, listed by body system, have been identified in case reports and during the use of carbinoxamine in observational studies. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole  : Urticaria, drug rash, anaphylactic shock, photosensitivity, excessive perspiration, chills, dryness of mouth, nose and throat.



   Cardiovascular  : Hypotension, headache, palpitations, tachycardia, extrasystoles.



   Central Nervous System  : Fatigue, confusion, restlessness, excitation, nervousness, tremor, irritability, insomnia, euphoria, paresthesia, blurred vision, diplopia, vertigo, tinnitus, acute labyrinthitis, hysteria, neuritis, convulsions.



   Gastrointestinal  : Anorexia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, constipation.



   Hematologic  : Hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, agranulocytosis.



   Laboratory  : Increase in uric acid levels.



   Respiratory  : Tightness of chest and wheezing, nasal stuffiness.



   Urogenital  : Urinary frequency, difficult urination, urinary retention, early menses.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are: sedation, sleepiness, dizziness, disturbed coordination, epigastric distress, and thickening of bronchial secretions. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact FSC Laboratories, Inc., at 1-866-764-7822 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Activities requiring mental alertness: Avoid engaging in hazardous tasks requiring complete mental alertness such as driving or operating machinery. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Anticholinergic actions: Use with caution in patients with increased intraocular pressure, narrow angle glaucoma, hyperthyroidism, cardiovascular disease, hypertension, stenosing peptic ulcer, symptomatic prostatic hypertrophy, bladder neck obstruction, pyloroduodenal obstruction. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfite that may cause anaphylaxis including life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in susceptible individuals. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Pediatric Mortality



  Deaths have been reported in children less than 2 years of age who were taking carbinoxamine-containing drug products; therefore, Karbinal ER is contraindicated in children younger than 2 years of age.



    5.2 Activities Requiring Mental Alertness



  Karbinal ER may produce marked drowsiness and impair the mental or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery. Advise patients to avoid engaging in hazardous tasks requiring mental alertness and motor coordination after ingestion of Karbinal ER. Avoid concurrent use of Karbinal ER with alcohol or other central nervous system depressants because additional impairment of central nervous system performance may occur.



    5.3 Concomitant Medical Conditions



  Karbinal ER has anticholinergic (atropine-like) properties and, therefore, should be used with caution in patients with: increased intraocular pressure, narrow angle glaucoma, hyperthyroidism, cardiovascular disease, hypertension, stenosing peptic ulcer, symptomatic prostatic hypertrophy, bladder neck obstruction, or pyloroduodenal obstruction.



    5.4 Allergic Reactions due to Sulfites



  Karbinal ER contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfite that may cause allergic-type reactions, including anaphylaxis and life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes, in susceptible individuals. The overall prevalence of sulfite sensitivity in the general population is unknown and probably low. Sulfite sensitivity is seen more frequently in asthmatic than in nonasthmatic individuals.



    5.5 Dosing



  Advise patients to measure Karbinal ER with an accurate milliliter measuring device. A household teaspoon is not an accurate measuring device and could lead to overdosage. A pharmacist can recommend an appropriate measuring device and can provide instructions for measuring the correct dose.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
