<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kcentra" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions (ARs) (frequency &gt;= 2.8%) observed in subjects receiving Kcentra were headache, nausea/vomiting, hypotension, and anemia.



 The most serious ARs were thromboembolic events including stroke, pulmonary embolism, and deep vein thrombosis.



 The following serious adverse reactions are described below and/or elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Arterial and venous thromboembolic complications [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Possible transmission of infectious agents [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
   *  The most common adverse reactions (ARs) (frequency &gt;= 2.8%) observed in subjects receiving Kcentra were headache, nausea/vomiting, hypotension, and anemia. (  6  ) 
 *  The most serious ARs were thromboembolic events including stroke, pulmonary embolism, and deep vein thrombosis. (  6  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact CSL Behring at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Randomized, Plasma-Controlled Trial in Acute Major Bleeding  



 In a prospective, randomized, open-label, active-controlled multicenter non-inferiority trial, 212 subjects who required urgent reversal of VKA therapy due to acute major bleeding were enrolled and randomized to treatment; 103 were treated with Kcentra and 109 with plasma. Subjects with a history of a thrombotic event, myocardial infarction, cerebral vascular accident, transient ischemic attack, unstable angina pectoris, severe peripheral vascular disease, or disseminated intravascular coagulation, within the previous 3 months were excluded from participating. Subjects ranged in age from 26 years to 96 years.



     Randomized, Plasma-Controlled Trial in Urgent Surgery/Invasive Procedures  



 In a prospective, randomized, open-label, active-controlled, multicenter non-inferiority trial, 176 subjects who required urgent reversal of VKA therapy due to the need for an urgent surgical or urgent invasive procedure were enrolled; 88 were treated with Kcentra and 88 with plasma. Subjects ranged in age from 27 years to 94 years.



 Adverse reactions are summarized for Kcentra and plasma in the Acute Major Bleeding and Urgent Surgery/Invasive Procedures RCTs (  see  Table 3    ).



 Adverse Reactions are defined as adverse events that began during or within 72 hours of test product infusion plus adverse events considered possibly/probably related or related to study treatment according to the investigator, sponsor, or the blinded safety adjudication board (SAB), and with at least a 1.3-fold difference between treatments.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Reported in more than 5 Subjects (&gt;= 2.8%) Following Kcentra or Plasma Administration in RCTs 
                                                               No. (%) of subjects    
                                                                 Kcentra(N = 191)      Plasma(N = 197)      
  
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
   Headache                                                         14 (7.3%)              7 (3.6%)         
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                         
   Pleural effusion                                                  8 (4.2%)              3 (1.5%)         
   Respiratory distress/dyspnea/hypoxia                              7 (3.7%)             10 (5.1%)         
   Pulmonary edema                                                   3 (1.6%)             10 (5.1%)         
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
   Nausea/vomiting                                                  12 (6.3%)              8 (4.1%)         
   Diarrhea                                                          4 (2.1%)              7 (3.6%)         
   Cardiac disorders                                                                                        
   Tachycardia                                                       9 (4.7%)              2 (1.0%)         
   Atrial fibrillation                                               8 (4.2%)              6 (3.0%)         
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                       
   Fluid overload                                                    5 (2.6%)             16 (8.1%)         
   Hypokalemia                                                       9 (4.7%)             14 (7.1%)         
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                                          9 (4.7%)              6 (3.0%)         
   Vascular disorders                                                                                       
   Hypotension                                                      14 (7.3%)             10 (5.1%)         
   Injury, poisoning, and procedural complications                                                          
   Skin laceration/contusion/subcutaneous hematoma                   8 (4.2%)              5 (2.5%)         
   Blood and lymphatic disorders                                                                            
   Anemia                                                           11 (5.8%)             16 (8.1%)         
         Serious adverse reactions in subjects receiving Kcentra in both RCTs included ischemic cerebrovascular accident (stroke), DVT, thrombosis, and venous insufficiency. Serious adverse reactions in both RCTs for plasma included myocardial ischemia, myocardial infarction, fluid overload, embolic cerebral infarction, pulmonary edema, respiratory failure, and DVT.
 

 There were a total of 10 subjects (9.7%) who died in the Kcentra group (1 additional death occurred on day 46 just after completion of the study reporting period) and 5 (4.6%) who died in the plasma group in the plasma-controlled RCT in acute major bleeding. The 95% confidence interval for the Kcentra minus plasma between-group difference in deaths ranged from -2.7% to 13.5%. From the plasma-controlled RCT in urgent surgery/invasive procedures, there were a total of 3 subjects (3.4%) who died in the Kcentra group (1 additional death occurred on day 48 after completion of the study reporting period) and 8 (9.1%) who died in the Plasma group. The 95% confidence interval for the Kcentra minus plasma between-group difference in deaths in this trial ranged from -14.6% to 2.7%. One death in the Kcentra group in the RCT in Acute Major Bleeding and one death in the plasma group in the RCT in urgent surgery/invasive procedures were considered possibly related to study treatment according to an assessment of masked data by an independent safety adjudication board. No factors common to all deaths were identified, except for the frequent findings of a high comorbidity burden, advanced age, and death after being placed on comfort care. Although, a greater proportion of subjects in the RCT in acute major bleeding than in the RCT in surgery/invasive procedure received the highest two recommended doses of Kcentra because more subjects in the trial in acute major bleeding had a baseline INR in the ranges of 4-6 and &gt; 6.0, an analysis of deaths and factor levels in subjects with major bleeding revealed that subjects who died had similar median factor levels to subjects that did not die. Additionally, outliers with supraphysiologic factor levels did not have a mortality rate out of proportion to the overall population.



     Fluid Overload  



 There were 9 subjects (4.7%, all non-related by investigator assessment) in the Kcentra group who experienced fluid overload in the plasma-controlled RCTs in acute major bleeding and urgent surgery/invasive procedures and 25 (12.7%, 13 events related by investigator assessment) who had fluid overload in the plasma group. The 95% confidence interval for the Kcentra minus Plasma between-group difference in fluid overload event incidence ranged from -14.1% to -2.0%.



 Subgroup analyses of the RCTs in acute major bleeding and urgent surgery/invasive procedures according to whether subjects with fluid overload events had a prior history of congestive heart failure are presented in Table 4.



 Table 4: Subjects with Fluid Overload Events by Prior History of Congestive Heart Failure in RCTs 
 Subgroup        Acute Major Bleeding Study  Urgent Surgery/Invasive Procedures Study   
 Kcentra         Plasma     Kcentra      Plasma   
 N               Fluid OverloadN (%)        N         Fluid OverloadN (%)        N         Fluid OverloadN (%)       N        Fluid OverloadN (%)   
 All subjects     103      6 (5.8)       109     14 (12.8)          88         3 (3.4)          88        11 (12.5)     
  
   With history of CHF   46       4 (8.7)       44      11 (25.0)          24         1 (4.2)          36         6 (16.7)     
   Without history of CHF   57       2 (3.5)       65       3 (4.6)           64         2 (3.1)          52         5 (9.6)      
                   Thromboembolic Events  
 

 In RCTs, there were 13 subjects (6.8%) in the Kcentra group who experienced possible thromboembolic events (TEEs) and 14 (7.1%) who had TEEs in the plasma group. The incidence of thromboembolic (TE) adverse reactions assessed as at least possibly related to study treatment by the Investigator or, in the case of serious thromboembolic events, the blinded safety adjudication board (SAB) was 9 (4.7%) in the Kcentra group and 7 (3.6%) in the plasma group. When also considering the events which began during or within 72 hours of test product infusion, the incidence was 9 (4.7%) in the Kcentra group and 8 (4.1%) in the plasma group.



 TE events observed in the acute major bleeding and the urgent surgery/invasive procedures RCTs are shown in Table 5.



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions (TEEs only) Following Kcentra or Plasma Administration in RCTs 
                                                       No. (%) of subjects   
 System Organ Class                                    Acute Major Bleeding Study  Urgent Surgery/Invasive Procedures Study   
                                                       Kcentra(N = 103)  Plasma(N = 109)  Kcentra(N = 88)  Plasma(N = 88)   
  
   Any possible TEE                                      9 (8.7%)      6 (5.5%)      4 (4.5)       8 (9.1)      
     TEE Adverse reactions                               6 (5.5%)      4 (3.7%)      4 (4.5)       4 (4.5)      
   Cardiac disorders                                                                                            
   Myocardial infarction                                    0          1 (0.9%)         0          2 (2.3)      
   Myocardial ischemia                                      0          2 (1.8%)         0             0         
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                     
   Ischemic cerebrovascular accident (stroke)            2 (1.9%)         0          1 (1.1)          0         
   Embolic cerebral infarction                              0             0             0          1 (1.1)      
   Cerebrovascular disorder                                 0          1 (0.9%)         0             0         
   Vascular disorders                                                                                           
   Venous thrombosis calf                                1 (1.0%)         0             0             0         
   Venous thrombosis radial vein                            0             0          1 (1.1)          0         
   Thrombosis (microthrombosis of toes)                     0             0          1 (1.1)          0         
   Deep vein thrombosis (DVT)                            1 (1.0%)         0          1 (1.1)       1 (1.1)      
   Fistula Clot                                          1 (1.0%)         0             0             0         
   Unknown Cause of Death (not confirmed TEE)                                                                   
   Sudden death                                          1 (1.0%)         0             0             0         
           Subgroup analyses of the RCTs according to whether subjects with thromboembolic events had a prior history of a thromboembolic event are presented in Table 6.
 

 Table 6: Subjects with Thromboembolic Events by Prior History of TE Event in RCTs 
                 Acute Major Bleeding Study  Urgent Surgery/Invasive Procedures Study   
 Kcentra         Plasma     Kcentra      Plasma   
 N               TE EventsN (%)        N         TE EventsN (%)        N         TE EventsN (%)       N        TE EventsN (%)   
 All subjects     103      9 (8.7)       109      6 (5.5)           88         4 (4.5)          88         8 (9.1)      
  
   With history of TE event   69       8 (11.6)      79       3 (3.8)           55         3 (5.5)          62         5 (8.1)      
   Without history of TE event   34       1 (2.9)       30       3 (10.0)          33         1 (3.0)          26         3 (11.5)     
                   The European Bleeding and Surgical Study:  In a prospective, open label, single-arm, multicenter safety and efficacy trial, 17 subjects who required urgent reversal of VKA due to acute bleeding were enrolled and 26 subjects who required urgent reversal of Vitamin K antagonist due to the need for an urgent surgical/invasive procedure were enrolled, all were treated with Kcentra. Subjects ranged in age from 22 years to 85 years. Serious adverse reactions considered possibly related to Kcentra included a suspected pulmonary embolism which occurred in one subject following a second dose of Kcentra. A single non-fatal TE event occurred in another Kcentra-treated subject in that trial.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    No adverse reactions other than those addressed in  Warnings And Precautions (5)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)  have been observed in the postmarketing use of Kcentra outside the US since 1996.  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ARTERIAL AND VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLIC COMPLICATIONS

    WARNING: ARTERIAL AND VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLIC COMPLICATIONS  

    Patients being treated with Vitamin K antagonists (VKA) therapy have underlying disease states that predispose them to thromboembolic events. Potential benefits of reversing VKA should be weighed against the potential risks of thromboembolic events (TE), especially in patients with the history of a thromboembolic event. Resumption of anticoagulation should be carefully considered as soon as the risk of thromboembolic events outweighs the risk of acute bleeding.  



 *  Both fatal and non-fatal arterial and venous thromboembolic complications have been reported with Kcentra in clinical trials and post marketing surveillance. Monitor patients receiving Kcentra for signs and symptoms of thromboembolic events. (5.2) 
 *  Kcentra was not studied in subjects who had a thromboembolic event, myocardial infarction, disseminated intravascular coagulation, cerebral vascular accident, transient ischemic attack, unstable angina pectoris, or severe peripheral vascular disease within the prior 3 months. Kcentra may not be suitable in patients with thromboembolic events in the prior 3 months. (5.2) 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: ARTERIAL AND VENOUS THROMBOEMBOLIC COMPLICATIONS  
 

   Patients being treated with Vitamin K antagonists (VKA) therapy have underlying disease states that predispose them to thromboembolic events. Potential benefits of reversing VKA should be weighed against the potential risks of thromboembolic events, especially in patients with the history of a thromboembolic event. Resumption of anticoagulation should be carefully considered as soon as the risk of thromboembolic events outweighs the risk of acute bleeding.  



 *  Both fatal and non-fatal arterial and venous thromboembolic complications have been reported with Kcentra in clinical trials and post marketing surveillance. Monitor patients receiving Kcentra for signs and symptoms of thromboembolic events. 
 *  Kcentra was not studied in subjects who had a thromboembolic event, myocardial infarction, disseminated intravascular coagulation, cerebral vascular accident, transient ischemic attack, unstable angina pectoris, or severe peripheral vascular disease within the prior 3 months. Kcentra may not be suitable in patients with thromboembolic events in the prior 3 months. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions may occur. If necessary, discontinue administration and institute appropriate treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Arterial and venous thromboembolic complications have been reported in patients receiving Kcentra. Monitor patients receiving Kcentra for signs and symptoms of thromboembolic events. Kcentra was not studied in subjects who had a thrombotic or thromboembolic (TE) event within the prior 3 months. Kcentra may not be suitable in patients with thromboembolic events in the prior 3 months. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Kcentra is made from human blood and may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions including flushing, urticaria, tachycardia, anxiety, angioedema, wheezing, nausea, vomiting, hypotension, tachypnea, dyspnea, pulmonary edema, and bronchospasm have been observed with Kcentra.



 If severe allergic reaction or anaphylactic type reactions occur, immediately discontinue administration, and institute appropriate treatment.



    5.2 Thromboembolic Risk/Complications



   Both fatal and non-fatal arterial thromboembolic events (including acute myocardial infarction and arterial thrombosis), and venous thromboembolic events (including pulmonary embolism and venous thrombosis) and disseminated intravascular coagulation have been reported with Kcentra in clinical trials and post marketing surveillance [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  and  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . Patients being treated with VKA therapy have underlying disease states that predispose them to thromboembolic events. Reversing VKA therapy exposes patients to the thromboembolic risk of their underlying disease. Resumption of anticoagulation should be carefully considered following administration of Kcentra and Vitamin K once the risk of thromboembolic events outweighs the risk of bleeding.  



 Thromboembolic events occurred more frequently following Kcentra compared to plasma in a randomized, plasma controlled trial in subjects requiring urgent reversal of VKA anticoagulation due to acute major bleeding, and the excess in thromboembolic events was more pronounced among subjects who had a history of prior thromboembolic event, although these differences were not statistically significant [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ,  Clinical Studies (14)  ].  Potential benefits of treatment with Kcentra should be weighed against the potential risks of thromboembolic events [  see   Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  . Patients with a history of thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, cerebral vascular accident, transient ischemic attack, unstable angina pectoris, severe peripheral vascular disease, or disseminated intravascular coagulation, within the previous 3 months were excluded from participating in the plasma-controlled RCT. Kcentra may not be suitable in patients with thromboembolic events in the prior 3 months. Because of the risk of thromboembolism associated with reversal of VKA, closely monitor patients for signs and symptoms of thromboembolism during and after administration of Kcentra. [see  17 Patient Counseling Information  ]  



    5.3 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because Kcentra is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, the variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD) agent, and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent. There is also the possibility that unknown infectious agents may be present in such products. Despite the use of two dedicated virus reduction steps in manufacturing to reduce risks, such products may still potentially transmit disease.



 Reports of suspected virus transmission of hepatitis A, B, C, and HIV were generally confounded by concomitant administration of blood/blood components and/or other plasma-derived products. No causal relationship to Kcentra administration was established for any of these reports since introduction of a virus filtration step in 1996.



 All infections thought by a physician to have been possibly transmitted by Kcentra should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to the CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance Department at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
