<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kedbumin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions include fever, chills, rash, nausea, vomiting, tachycardia, and hypotension  (6)  .



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact KEDRION at 1-855-427-6378 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 General

  The most common adverse reactions include flushing, urticaria, fever, chills, nausea, vomiting, tachycardia and hypotension. These reactions normally disappear when the infusion rate is slowed or stopped.



 If a severe reaction such as shock or anaphylaxis occurs, the infusion should be stopped and appropriate treatment initiated.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Risk of transmission of infectious agents  (5.1)  . 
 *  Caution where hypervolemia and its consequences or hemodilution could represent a special risk  (5.2)   
 *  Do not dilute with water for injections  (5.2)   
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Hypersensitivity or allergic reactions have been observed, and may in some cases progress to severe anaphylaxis. Epinephrine should be available immediately to treat any acute hypersensitivity reaction.



    5.2 Hypovolemia



  KEDBUMINTM should be used with caution in conditions where hypervolemia and its consequences or hemodilution could represent a special risk  (10)  . Examples of such conditions may include but are not limited to:



 *  Heart failure 
 *  Arterial hypertension 
 *  Esophageal varices 
 *  Pulmonary edema 
 *  Hemorrhagic diathesis 
 *  Severe anemia 
 *  Renal and post-renal anuria 
       5.3 Hemolysis
 

  Do not dilute KEDBUMINTM with Sterile Water for Injection, as this may cause hemolysis in recipients. There is a risk of potentially fatal hemolysis and acute renal failure from the use of Sterile Water for Injection as a diluent for 25% albumin  12  . Suitable solutions for dilution include 5% glucose and 0.9% sodium chloride  (2.2)  .



    5.4 Large Volumes



  When replacing comparatively large volumes of albumin, control of coagulation and hematocrit is essential. Ensure adequate substitution of other blood constituents as coagulation factors, electrolytes, platelets, and erythrocytes.



    5.5 Hydration



  The colloid osmotic effect of KEDBUMINTM 25% is approximately four times that of human blood. Therefore, when concentrated albumin is administered, ensure adequate hydration of the patient. Carefully monitor to guard against circulatory overload  (10)  .



 Hemodynamic performance should be monitored regularly. This may include arterial blood pressure and pulse rate, central venous pressure, pulmonary artery occlusion pressure, urine output, electrolyte levels, and hematocrit/hemoglobin.



    5.6 Infectious Diseases



  Because KEDBUMINTM is derived from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. No cases of transmission of viral diseases or CJD have ever been identified for KEDBUMIN.



 ALL infections suspected by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Kedrion at 1-855-427-6378.



 See also PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION    (17)  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
