<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="keflex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious events are described in greater detail in the Warning and Precautions section:



 *  Hypersensitivity reactions [ see Warning and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated diarrhea [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Direct Coombs' Test Seroconversion [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Seizure Potential [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) ] 
 *  Effect on Prothrombin Activity [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ) ] 
 *  Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions associated with KEFLEX include diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, dyspepsia and abdominal pain. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pragma Pharmaceuticals, LLC at (414) 434-6604 Monday-Friday 9am-5pm EST, or to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical trials, the most frequent adverse reaction was diarrhea. Nausea and vomiting, dyspepsia, gastritis, and abdominal pain have also occurred. As with penicillins and other cephalosporins, transient hepatitis and cholestatic jaundice have been reported.



 Other reactions have included hypersensitivity reactions, genital and anal pruritus, genital candidiasis, vaginitis and vaginal discharge, dizziness, fatigue, headache, agitation, confusion, hallucinations, arthralgia, arthritis, and joint disorder. Reversible interstitial nephritis has been reported. Eosinophilia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, hemolytic anemia, and slight elevations in aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) have been reported.



 In addition to the adverse reactions listed above that have been observed in patients treated with KEFLEX, the following adverse reactions and other altered laboratory tests have been reported for cephalosporin class antibacterial drugs:



   Other Adverse Reactions  : Fever, colitis, aplastic anemia, hemorrhage, renal dysfunction, and toxic nephropathy.



   Altered Laboratory Tests  : Prolonged prothrombin time, increased blood urea nitrogen (BUN), increased creatinine, elevated alkaline phosphatase, elevated bilirubin, elevated lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), pancytopenia, leukopenia, and agranulocytosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Serious hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions: Prior to use, inquire regarding history of hypersensitivity to beta-lactam antibacterial drugs. Discontinue the drug if signs or symptoms of an allergic reaction occur and institute supportive measures. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile-  associated diarrhea (CDAD): Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Direct Coomb's Test Seroconversion: If anemia develops during or after cephalexin therapy, evaluate for drug-induced hemolytic anemia. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Seizure Potential: Use lower dose in patients with renal impairment. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Allergic reactions in the form of rash, urticaria, angioedema, anaphylaxis, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, or toxic epidermal necrolysis have been reported with the use of KEFLEX. Before therapy with KEFLEX is instituted, inquire whether the patient has a history of hypersensitivity reactions to cephalexin, cephalosporins, penicillins, or other drugs. Cross-hypersensitivity among beta-lactam antibacterial drugs may occur in up to 10% of patients with a history of penicillin allergy.



 If an allergic reaction to KEFLEX occurs, discontinue the drug and institute appropriate treatment.



    5.2 Clostridium difficile-  Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including KEFLEX, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B, which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin-producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.3 Direct Coombs' Test Seroconversion



  Positive direct Coombs' tests have been reported during treatment with the cephalosporin antibacterial drugs including cephalexin. Acute intravascular hemolysis induced by cephalexin therapy has been reported. If anemia develops during or after cephalexin therapy, perform a diagnostic work-up for drug-induced hemolytic anemia, discontinue cephalexin and institute appropriate therapy.



    5.4 Seizure Potential



  Several cephalosporins have been implicated in triggering seizures, particularly in patients with renal impairment when the dosage was not reduced. If seizures occur, discontinue KEFLEX. Anticonvulsant therapy can be given if clinically indicated.



    5.5 Prolonged Prothrombin Time



  Cephalosporins may be associated with prolonged prothrombin time. Those at risk include patients with renal or hepatic impairment, or poor nutritional state, as well as patients receiving a protracted course of antibacterial therapy, and patients receiving anticoagulant therapy. Monitor prothrombin time in patients at risk and manage as indicated.



    5.6 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing KEFLEX in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.



 Prolonged use of KEFLEX may result in the overgrowth of nonsusceptible organisms. Careful observation of the patient is essential. If superinfection occurs during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
