<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="keppra1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more details in other sections of labeling:



 *  Behavioral abnormalities and Psychotic Symptoms [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Suicidal Behavior And Ideation [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Somnolence And Fatigue [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Serious Dermatological Reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Coordination Difficulties [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Hematologic Abnormalities [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% more than placebo) include: somnolence and irritability (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact UCB, Inc. at 866-822-0068 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     KEPPRA XR Tablets  



 In the controlled clinical study in patients with partial onset seizures, the most common adverse reactions in patients receiving KEPPRA XR in combination with other AEDs, for events with rates greater than placebo, were irritability and somnolence.



 Table 3 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of epilepsy patients receiving KEPPRA XR in the placebo-controlled study and were numerically more common than in patients treated with placebo. In this study, either KEPPRA XR or placebo was added to concurrent AED therapy.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions in the Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Study in Patients Experiencing Partial Onset Seizures 
                                                  KEPPRA XR(N=77)%                 Placebo(N=79)%           
  
 Influenza                                               8                               4                  
 Somnolence                                              8                               3                  
 Irritability                                            7                               0                  
 Nasopharyngitis                                         7                               5                  
 Dizziness                                               5                               3                  
 Nausea                                                  5                               3                  
             Discontinuation or Dose Reduction in the KEPPRA XR Controlled Clinical Study  
 

 In the controlled clinical study, 5% of patients receiving KEPPRA XR and 3% receiving placebo discontinued as a result of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions that resulted in discontinuation and that occurred more frequently in KEPPRA XR-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients were asthenia, epilepsy, mouth ulceration, rash, and respiratory failure. Each of these adverse reactions led to discontinuation in a KEPPRA XR-treated patient and no placebo-treated patients.



     Immediate-Release KEPPRA Tablets  



 Table 4 lists the adverse reactions in the controlled studies of immediate-release KEPPRA tablets in adult patients experiencing partial onset seizures. Although the pattern of adverse reactions in the KEPPRA XR study seems somewhat different from that seen in partial onset seizure controlled studies for immediate-release KEPPRA tablets, this is possibly due to the much smaller number of patients in this study compared to the immediate-release tablet studies. The adverse reactions for KEPPRA XR are expected to be similar to those seen with immediate-release KEPPRA tablets.



     Adults  



 In controlled clinical studies of immediate-release KEPPRA tablets as adjunctive therapy to other AEDs in adults with partial onset seizures, the most common adverse reactions, for events with rates greater than placebo, were somnolence, asthenia, infection, and dizziness.



 Table 4 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of adult epilepsy patients receiving immediate-release KEPPRA tablets in placebo-controlled studies and were numerically more common than in patients treated with placebo. In these studies, either immediate-release KEPPRA tablets or placebo was added to concurrent AED therapy.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions in Pooled Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Studies in Adults Experiencing Partial Onset Seizures 
                                                   KEPPRA(N=769)%                 Placebo(N=439)%           
  
 Asthenia                                                15                              9                  
 Somnolence                                              15                              8                  
 Headache                                                14                              13                 
 Infection                                               13                              8                  
 Dizziness                                               9                               4                  
 Pain                                                    7                               6                  
 Pharyngitis                                             6                               4                  
 Depression                                              4                               2                  
 Nervousness                                             4                               2                  
 Rhinitis                                                4                               3                  
 Anorexia                                                3                               2                  
 Ataxia                                                  3                               1                  
 Vertigo                                                 3                               1                  
 Amnesia                                                 2                               1                  
 Anxiety                                                 2                               1                  
 Cough Increased                                         2                               1                  
 Diplopia                                                2                               1                  
 Emotional Lability                                      2                               0                  
 Hostility                                               2                               1                  
 Paresthesia                                             2                               1                  
 Sinusitis                                               2                               1                  
             Pediatric Patients 4 Years to &lt;16 Years  
 

 In a pooled analysis of two controlled pediatric clinical studies in children 4 to 16 years of age with partial onset seizures, the adverse reactions most frequently reported with the use of immediate-release KEPPRA in combination with other AEDs, and with greater frequency than in patients on placebo, were fatigue, aggression, nasal congestion, decreased appetite, and irritability.



 Table 5 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of pediatric patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA and were more common than in pediatric patients on placebo. In these studies, either immediate-release KEPPRA or placebo was added to concurrent AED therapy. Adverse reactions were usually mild to moderate in intensity.



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions in Pooled Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Studies in Pediatric Patients Ages 4 to 16 Years Experiencing Partial Onset Seizures 
                                                   KEPPRA(N=165)%                 Placebo(N=131)%           
  
 Headache                                                19                              15                 
 Nasopharyngitis                                         15                              12                 
 Vomiting                                                15                              12                 
 Somnolence                                              13                              9                  
 Fatigue                                                 11                              5                  
 Aggression                                              10                              5                  
 Abdominal Pain Upper                                    9                               8                  
 Cough                                                   9                               5                  
 Nasal Congestion                                        9                               2                  
 Decreased Appetite                                      8                               2                  
 Abnormal Behavior                                       7                               4                  
 Dizziness                                               7                               5                  
 Irritability                                            7                               1                  
 Pharyngolaryngeal Pain                                  7                               4                  
 Diarrhea                                                6                               2                  
 Lethargy                                                6                               5                  
 Insomnia                                                5                               3                  
 Agitation                                               4                               1                  
 Anorexia                                                4                               3                  
 Head Injury                                             4                               0                  
 Constipation                                            3                               1                  
 Contusion                                               3                               1                  
 Depression                                              3                               1                  
 Fall                                                    3                               2                  
 Influenza                                               3                               1                  
 Mood Altered                                            3                               1                  
 Affect Lability                                         2                               1                  
 Anxiety                                                 2                               1                  
 Arthralgia                                              2                               0                  
 Confusional State                                       2                               0                  
 Conjunctivitis                                          2                               0                  
 Ear Pain                                                2                               1                  
 Gastroenteritis                                         2                               0                  
 Joint Sprain                                            2                               1                  
 Mood Swings                                             2                               1                  
 Neck Pain                                               2                               1                  
 Rhinitis                                                2                               0                  
 Sedation                                                2                               1                  
         In controlled pediatric clinical studies in patients 4-16 years of age, 7% of patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA tablets and 9% of patients on placebo discontinued as a result of an adverse event.
 

 In addition, the following adverse reactions were seen in other controlled studies of immediate-release KEPPRA tablets: balance disorder, disturbance in attention, eczema, hyperkinesia, memory impairment, myalgia, personality disorders, pruritus, and blurred vision.



     Comparison of Gender, Age and Race  



 There are insufficient data for KEPPRA XR to support a statement regarding the distribution of adverse reactions by gender, age, and race.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of immediate-release KEPPRA tablets. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The listing is alphabetized: abnormal liver function test, choreoathetosis, drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), dyskinesia, erythema multiforme, hepatic failure, hepatitis, hyponatremia, muscular weakness, pancreatitis, pancytopenia (with bone marrow suppression identified in some of these cases), panic attack, thrombocytopenia, and weight loss. Alopecia has been reported with immediate-release KEPPRA use; recovery was observed in majority of cases where immediate-release KEPPRA was discontinued.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Behavioral abnormalities including psychotic symptoms, suicidal ideation, irritability, and aggressive behavior have been observed; monitor patients for psychiatric signs and symptoms (  5.1  ) 
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor patients for new or worsening depression, suicidal thoughts/behavior, and/or unusual changes in mood or behavior (  5.2   )  
 *  Monitor for somnolence and fatigue and advise patients not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on KEPPRA XR (  5.3  ) 
 *  Withdrawal Seizures: KEPPRA XR must be gradually withdrawn (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Behavioral Abnormalities and Psychotic Symptoms



   KEPPRA XR may cause behavioral abnormalities and psychotic symptoms. Patients treated with KEPPRA XR should be monitored for psychiatric signs and symptoms.  



     Behavioral abnormalities    



     KEPPRA XR Tablets    



  A total of 7% of KEPPRA XR-treated patients experienced non-psychotic behavioral disorders (reported as irritability and aggression) compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients. Irritability was reported in 7% of KEPPRA XR-treated patients. Aggression was reported in 1% of KEPPRA XR-treated patients.  



  No patient discontinued treatment or had a dose reduction as a result of these adverse reactions.  



  The number of patients exposed to KEPPRA XR was considerably smaller than the number of patients exposed to immediate-release KEPPRA tablets in controlled trials. Therefore, certain adverse reactions observed in the immediate-release KEPPRA controlled trials will likely occur in patients receiving KEPPRA XR.  



     Immediate-Release KEPPRA Tablets    



  A total of 13% of adult patients and 38% of pediatric patients (4 to 16 years of age) treated with immediate-release KEPPRA experienced non-psychotic behavioral symptoms (reported as aggression, agitation, anger, anxiety, apathy, depersonalization, depression, emotional lability, hostility, hyperkinesias, irritability, nervousness, neurosis, and personality disorder), compared to 6% and 19% of adult and pediatric patients on placebo. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study was performed to assess the neurocognitive and behavioral effects of immediate-release KEPPRA tablets as adjunctive therapy in pediatric patients (4 to 16 years of age). An exploratory analysis suggested a worsening in aggressive behavior in patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA tablets in that study [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ].  



  A total of 1.7% of adult patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA discontinued treatment due to behavioral adverse reactions, compared to 0.2% of placebo-treated patients. The treatment dose was reduced in 0.8% of adult patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA, compared to 0.5% of placebo-treated patients. Overall, 11% of pediatric patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA experienced behavioral symptoms associated with discontinuation or dose reduction, compared to 6.2% of placebo-treated pediatric patients.  



  One percent of adult patients and 2% of pediatric patients (4 to 16 years of age) treated with immediate-release KEPPRA experienced psychotic symptoms, compared to 0.2% and 2%, respectively, in adult and placebo-treated pediatric patients. In the controlled study that assessed the neurocognitive and behavioral effects of immediate-release KEPPRA in pediatric patients 4 to 16 years of age, 1.6% KEPPRA-treated patients experienced paranoia, compared to no placebo-treated patients. There were 3.1% patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA who experienced confusional state, compared to no placebo-treated patients [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ].  



     Psychotic symptoms    



     Immediate-Release KEPPRA tablets    



  One percent of KEPPRA-treated adult patients experienced psychotic symptoms compared to 0.2% of placebo-treated patients.  



  Two (0.3%) KEPPRA-treated adult patients were hospitalized and their treatment was discontinued due to psychosis. Both events, reported as psychosis, developed within the first week of treatment and resolved within 1 to 2 weeks following treatment discontinuation. There was no difference between drug and placebo-treated patients in the incidence of pediatric patients who discontinued treatment due to psychotic and non-psychotic adverse reactions.  



    5.2 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including KEPPRA XR, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed. Table 2 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 2: Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis 
 Indication       Placebo Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients  Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients  Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients  Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients   
  
 Epilepsy         1.0                   3.4                   3.5                        2.4                    
 Psychiatric      5.7                   8.5                   1.5                        2.9                    
 Other            1.0                   1.8                   1.9                        0.9                    
 Total            2.4                   4.3                   1.8                        1.9                    
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing KEPPRA XR or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.3 Somnolence and Fatigue



   KEPPRA XR may cause somnolence and fatigue. Patients should be monitored for these signs and symptoms and advised not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on KEPPRA XR to gauge whether it adversely affects their ability to drive or operate machinery.  



    Somnolence  



    KEPPRA XR Tablets  



 In the KEPPRA XR double-blind, controlled trial in patients experiencing partial onset seizures, 8% of KEPPRA XR-treated patients experienced somnolence compared to 3% of placebo-treated patients.



 No patient discontinued treatment or had a dose reduction as a result of these adverse reactions.



 The number of patients exposed to KEPPRA XR was considerably smaller than the number of patients exposed to immediate-release KEPPRA tablets in controlled trials. Therefore, certain adverse reactions observed in the immediate-release KEPPRA controlled trials will likely occur in patients receiving KEPPRA XR.



    Immediate-Release KEPPRA Tablets  



 In controlled trials of adult patients with epilepsy experiencing partial onset seizures, 15% of KEPPRA-treated patients reported somnolence, compared to 8% of placebo-treated patients. There was no clear dose response up to 3000 mg/day. In a study where there was no titration, about 45% of patients receiving 4000 mg/day reported somnolence. The somnolence was considered serious in 0.3% of the KEPPRA-treated patients, compared to 0% in the placebo group. About 3% of KEPPRA-treated patients discontinued treatment due to somnolence, compared to 0.7% of placebo-treated patients. In 1.4% of KEPPRA-treated patients and in 0.9% of placebo-treated patients the dose was reduced, while 0.3% of the treated patients were hospitalized due to somnolence.



    Asthenia  



    Immediate-Release KEPPRA Tablets  



 In controlled trials of adult patients with epilepsy experiencing partial onset seizures, 15% of KEPPRA-treated patients reported asthenia, compared to 9% of placebo-treated patients. Treatment was discontinued due to asthenia in 0.8% of KEPPRA-treated patients as compared to 0.5% of placebo-treated patients. In 0.5% of KEPPRA-treated patients and in 0.2% of placebo-treated patients, the dose was reduced due to asthenia.



 Somnolence and asthenia occurred most frequently within the first 4 weeks of treatment.



    5.4 Serious Dermatological Reactions



  Serious dermatological reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have been reported in patients treated with levetiracetam. The median time of onset is reported to be 14 to 17 days, but cases have been reported at least four months after initiation of treatment. Recurrence of the serious skin reactions following rechallenge with levetiracetam has also been reported. KEPPRA XR should be discontinued at the first sign of a rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related. If signs or symptoms suggest SJS/TEN, use of this drug should not be resumed and alternative therapy should be considered.



    5.5 Coordination Difficulties



  Coordination difficulties were not observed in the KEPPRA XR controlled trial, however, the number of patients exposed to KEPPRA XR was considerably smaller than the number of patients exposed to immediate-release KEPPRA tablets in controlled trials. However, adverse reactions observed in the immediate-release KEPPRA controlled trials may also occur in patients receiving KEPPRA XR.



    Immediate-Release KEPPRA Tablets  



 A total of 3.4% of adult KEPPRA-treated patients experienced coordination difficulties, (reported as either ataxia, abnormal gait, or incoordination) compared to 1.6% of placebo-treated patients. A total of 0.4% of patients in controlled trials discontinued KEPPRA treatment due to ataxia, compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients. In 0.7% of KEPPRA-treated patients and in 0.2% of placebo-treated patients, the dose was reduced due to coordination difficulties, while one of the KEPPRA-treated patients was hospitalized due to worsening of pre-existing ataxia. These events occurred most frequently within the first 4 weeks of treatment.



 Patients should be monitored for these signs and symptoms and advised not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on KEPPRA to gauge whether it could adversely affect their ability to drive or operate machinery.



    5.6 Withdrawal Seizures



  Antiepileptic drugs, including KEPPRA XR, should be withdrawn gradually to minimize the potential of increased seizure frequency.



    5.7 Hematologic Abnormalities



   KEPPRA XR can cause hematologic abnormalities. Hematologic abnormalities occurred in clinical trials and included decreases in red blood cell (RBC) counts, hemoglobin, and hematocrit, and increases in eosinophil counts. Decreased white blood cell (WBC) and neutrophil counts also occurred in clinical trials. Cases of agranulocytosis have been reported in the postmarketing setting.  



 In controlled trials of immediate-release KEPPRA tablets in patients experiencing partial onset seizures, minor, but statistically significant, decreases compared to placebo in total mean RBC count (0.03 * 10  6  /mm  3  ), mean hemoglobin (0.09 g/dL), and mean hematocrit (0.38%), were seen in immediate-release KEPPRA-treated patients.



 A total of 3.2% of KEPPRA-treated and 1.8% of placebo-treated patients had at least one possibly significant (&lt;=2.8 * 10  9  /L) decreased WBC, and 2.4% of KEPPRA-treated and 1.4% of placebo-traeted patients had at least one possibly significant (&lt;=1.0 * 10  9  /L) decreased neutrophil count. Of the KEPPRA-treated patients with a low neutrophil count, all but one rose towards or to baseline with continued treatment. No patient was discontinued secondary to low neutrophil counts.



  In pediatric patients (4 to &lt;16 years of age), statistically significant decreases in WBC and neutrophil counts were seen in patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA, as compared to placebo. The mean decreases from baseline in the immediate-release KEPPRA group were -0.4 * 10  9  /L and -0.3 * 10  9  /L, respectively, whereas there were small increases in the placebo group. A significant increase in mean relative lymphocyte counts was observed in 1.7% of patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA compared to a decrease of 4% in patients on placebo.  



  In the controlled pediatric trial, a possibly clinically significant abnormal low WBC value was observed in 3% of patients treated with immediate-release KEPPRA, compared to no patients on placebo. However, there was no apparent difference between treatment groups with respect to neutrophil count. No patient was discontinued secondary to low WBC or neutrophil counts.  



  In the controlled pediatric cognitive and neuropsychological safety study, two subjects (6.1%) in the placebo group and 5 subjects (8.6%) in the immediate-release KEPPRA-treated group had high eosinophil count values that were possibly clinically significant (&gt;=10% or &gt;=0.7*10  9  /L).  



    5.8 Seizure Control During Pregnancy



  Physiological changes may gradually decrease plasma levels of levetiracetam throughout pregnancy. This decrease is more pronounced during the third trimester. It is recommended that patients be monitored carefully during pregnancy. Close monitoring should continue through the postpartum period especially if the dose was changed during pregnancy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
