<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="keytruda" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling.



 *  Immune-mediated pneumonitis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  
 *  Immune-mediated colitis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] . 
 *  Immune-mediated hepatitis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] . 
 *  Immune-mediated endocrinopathies [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ] . 
 *  Renal failure and immune-mediated nephritis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ] . 
 *  Other immune-mediated adverse reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ] . 
 *  Infusion-related reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ].  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (reported in &gt;=20% of patients) included fatigue, cough, nausea, pruritus, rash, decreased appetite, constipation, arthralgia, and diarrhea. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described in the WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS section reflect exposure to KEYTRUDA in Trial 1, an uncontrolled, open-label, multiple cohort trial in which 411 patients with unresectable or metastatic melanoma received KEYTRUDA at either 2 mg/kg every 3 weeks or 10 mg/kg every 2 or 3 weeks. The median duration of exposure to KEYTRUDA was 6.2 months (range 1 day to 24.6 months) with a median of 10 doses (range 1 to 51). The study population characteristics were: median age of 61 years (range 18 to 94), 39% age 65 years or older, 60% male, 97% white, 73% with M1c disease, 8% with brain metastases, 35% with elevated LDH, 54% with prior exposure to ipilimumab, and 47% with two or more prior systemic therapies for advanced or metastatic disease.



 KEYTRUDA was discontinued for adverse reactions in 9% of the 411 patients. Adverse reactions, reported in at least two patients, that led to discontinuation of KEYTRUDA were: pneumonitis, renal failure, and pain. Serious adverse reactions occurred in 36% of patients receiving KEYTRUDA. The most frequent serious adverse drug reactions reported in 2% or more of patients in Trial 1 were renal failure, dyspnea, pneumonia, and cellulitis.



 Table 1 presents adverse reactions identified from analyses of the 89 patients with unresectable or metastatic melanoma who received KEYTRUDA 2 mg/kg every three weeks in one cohort of Trial 1. Patients had documented disease progression following treatment with ipilimumab and, if BRAF V600 mutation positive, a BRAF inhibitor. This cohort of Trial 1 excluded patients with severe immune-related toxicity related to ipilimumab, defined as any Grade 4 toxicity requiring treatment with corticosteroids or Grade 3 toxicity requiring corticosteroid treatment (greater than 10 mg/day prednisone or equivalent dose) for greater than 12 weeks; a medical condition that required systemic corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive medication; a history of pneumonitis or interstitial lung disease; or any active infection requiring therapy, including HIV or hepatitis B or C. Of the 89 patients in this cohort, the median age was 59 years (range 18 to 88), 33% were age 65 years or older, 53% were male, 98% were white, 44% had an elevated LDH, 84% had Stage M1c disease, 8% had brain metastases, and 70% received two or more prior therapies for advanced or metastatic disease. The median duration of exposure to KEYTRUDA was 6.2 months (range 1 day to 15.3 months) with a median of nine doses (range 1 to 23). Fifty-one percent of patients were exposed to KEYTRUDA for greater than 6 months and 21% for greater than 1 year.



 KEYTRUDA was discontinued for adverse reactions in 6% of the 89 patients. The most common adverse reactions (reported in at least 20% of patients) were fatigue, cough, nausea, pruritus, rash, decreased appetite, constipation, arthralgia, and diarrhea.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions in &gt;=10% of Patients with Unresectable or Metastatic Melanoma 
                                                                         KEYTRUDA2 mg/kg every 3 weeksN=89   
  
   Adverse Reaction                                                       All Grades(%)     Grade 3(%)      
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                   
   Fatigue                                                                     47                7          
   Peripheral Edema                                                            17                1          
   Chills                                                                      14                0          
   Pyrexia                                                                     11                0          
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                             
   Nausea                                                                      30                0          
   Constipation                                                                21                0          
   Diarrhea                                                                    20                0          
   Vomiting                                                                    16                0          
   Abdominal pain                                                              12                0          
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                          
   Cough                                                                       30                1          
   Dyspnea                                                                     18                2          
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                   
   Pruritus                                                                    30                0          
   Rash                                                                        29                0          
   Vitiligo                                                                    11                0          
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                       
   Decreased appetite                                                          26                0          
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                          
   Arthralgia                                                                  20                0          
   Pain in extremity                                                           18                1          
   Myalgia                                                                     14                1          
   Back pain                                                                   12                1          
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
   Headache                                                                    16                0          
   Dizziness                                                                   11                0          
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders                                   
   Anemia                                                                      14                5          
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                                                    14                0          
   Infections and Infestations                                                                              
   Upper respiratory tract infection                                           11                1          
         Other clinically important adverse reactions observed in up to 10% of patients treated with KEYTRUDA were:
 

   Infections and infestations:  sepsis



 Table 2: Laboratory Abnormalities Increased from Baseline in &gt;=20% of Patients with Unresectable or Metastatic Melanoma 
                                           KEYTRUDA2 mg/kg every 3 weeksN=89   
  
   Laboratory Test                                  All Grades%                     Grades 3-4%             
   Chemistry                                
   Hyperglycemia                                         40                              2                  
   Hyponatremia                                          35                              9                  
   Hypoalbuminemia                                       34                              0                  
   Hypertriglyceridemia                                  25                              0                  
   Increased Aspartate Aminotransferase                  24                              2                  
   Hypocalcemia                                          24                              1                  
   Hematology                               
   Anemia                                                55                              8                  
           6.2 Immunogenicity
   As with all therapeutic proteins, there is the potential for immunogenicity. Because trough levels of pembrolizumab interfere with the electrochemiluminescent (ECL) assay results, a subset analysis was performed in the patients with a concentration of pembrolizumab below the drug tolerance level of the anti-product antibody assay. In this analysis, none of the 97 patients who were treated with 2 mg/kg every 3 weeks tested positive for treatment-emergent anti-pembrolizumab antibodies.



 The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of incidence of antibodies to KEYTRUDA with the incidences of antibodies to other products may be misleading.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  *  Immune-mediated pneumonitis: Withhold for moderate, and permanently discontinue for severe or life-threatening pneumonitis. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Immune-mediated colitis: Withhold for moderate or severe, and permanently discontinue for life-threatening colitis. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Immune-mediated hepatitis: Monitor for changes in hepatic function. Based on severity of liver enzyme elevations, withhold or discontinue. (  5.3  ) 
 *  *  Hypophysitis: Withhold for moderate, withhold or discontinue for severe, and permanently discontinue for life-threatening hypophysitis. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Thyroid disorders: Monitor for changes in thyroid function. Withhold for severe and permanently discontinue for life-threatening hyperthyroidism. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Type 1 diabetes mellitus: Monitor for hyperglycemia. Administer insulin for type 1 diabetes and withhold KEYTRUDA in cases of severe hyperglycemia until metabolic control is achieved. (  5.4  ) 
   Immune-mediated endocrinopathies: 
 *  Immune-mediated nephritis: Monitor for changes in renal function. Withhold for moderate, and permanently discontinue for severe or life-threatening nephritis. (  5.5  ) 
   Immune-mediated adverse reactions: Administer corticosteroids based on the severity of the reaction. (  5.1  ,  5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Infusion-related reactions: Stop infusion and permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA for severe or life-threatening infusion reactions. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Embryofetal toxicity: KEYTRUDA may cause fetal harm. Advise females of reproductive potential of the potential risk to a fetus. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Immune-Mediated Pneumonitis



  Pneumonitis occurred in 12 (2.9%) of 411 melanoma patients, including Grade 2 or 3 cases in 8 (1.9%) and 1 (0.2%) patients, respectively, receiving KEYTRUDA in Trial 1. The median time to development of pneumonitis was 5 months (range 0.3 weeks to 9.9 months). The median duration was 4.9 months (range 1 week to 14.4 months). Five of eight patients with Grade 2 and the one patient with Grade 3 pneumonitis required initial treatment with high-dose systemic corticosteroids (greater than or equal to 40 mg prednisone or equivalent per day) followed by a corticosteroid taper. The median initial dose of high-dose corticosteroid treatment was 63.4 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent with a median duration of treatment of 3 days (range 1 to 34) followed by a corticosteroid taper. Pneumonitis led to discontinuation of KEYTRUDA in 3 (0.7%) patients. Pneumonitis completely resolved in seven of the nine patients with Grade 2-3 pneumonitis.



 Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of pneumonitis. Evaluate patients with suspected pneumonitis with radiographic imaging and administer corticosteroids for Grade 2 or greater pneumonitis. Withhold KEYTRUDA for moderate (Grade 2) pneumonitis, and permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA for severe (Grade 3) or life-threatening (Grade 4) pneumonitis [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.2 Immune-Mediated Colitis



  Colitis (including microscopic colitis) occurred in 4 (1%) of 411 patients, including Grade 2 or 3 cases in 1 (0.2%) and 2 (0.5%) patients, respectively, receiving KEYTRUDA in Trial 1. The median time to onset of colitis was 6.5 months (range 2.3 to 9.8). The median duration was 2.6 months (range 0.6 weeks to 3.6 months). All three patients with Grade 2 or 3 colitis were treated with high-dose corticosteroids (greater than or equal to 40 mg prednisone or equivalent per day) with a median initial dose of 70 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent; the median duration of initial treatment was 7 days (range 4 to 41), followed by a corticosteroid taper. One patient (0.2%) required permanent discontinuation of KEYTRUDA due to colitis. All four patients with colitis experienced complete resolution of the event.



 Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of colitis. Administer corticosteroids for Grade 2 or greater colitis. Withhold KEYTRUDA for moderate (Grade 2) or severe (Grade 3) colitis, and permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA for life-threatening (Grade 4) colitis [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.3 Immune-Mediated Hepatitis



  Hepatitis (including autoimmune hepatitis) occurred in 2 (0.5%) of 411 patients, including a Grade 4 case in 1 (0.2%) patient, receiving KEYTRUDA in Trial 1. The time to onset was 22 days for the case of Grade 4 hepatitis which lasted 1.1 months. The patient with Grade 4 hepatitis permanently discontinued KEYTRUDA and was treated with high-dose (greater than or equal to 40 mg prednisone or equivalent per day) systemic corticosteroids followed by a corticosteroid taper. Both patients with hepatitis experienced complete resolution of the event.



 Monitor patients for changes in liver function. Administer corticosteroids for Grade 2 or greater hepatitis and, based on severity of liver enzyme elevations, withhold or discontinue KEYTRUDA [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.4 Immune-Mediated Endocrinopathies



    Hypophysitis    



  Hypophysitis occurred in 2 (0.5%) of 411 patients, consisting of one Grade 2 and one Grade 4 case (0.2% each), in patients receiving KEYTRUDA in Trial 1. The time to onset was 1.7 months for the patient with Grade 4 hypophysitis and 1.3 months for the patient with Grade 2 hypophysitis. Both patients were treated with high-dose (greater than or equal to 40 mg prednisone or equivalent per day) corticosteroids followed by a corticosteroid taper and remained on a physiologic replacement dose.  



  Monitor for signs and symptoms of hypophysitis (including hypopituitarism and adrenal insufficiency). Administer corticosteroids for Grade 2 or greater hypophysitis. Withhold KEYTRUDA for moderate (Grade 2) hypophysitis, withhold or discontinue KEYTRUDA for severe (Grade 3) hypophysitis, and permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA for life-threatening (Grade 4) hypophysitis [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].    



     Thyroid Disorders    



  Hyperthyroidism occurred in 5 (1.2%) of 411 patients, including Grade 2 or 3 cases in 2 (0.5%) and 1 (0.2%) patients, respectively, receiving KEYTRUDA in Trial 1. The median time to onset was 1.5 months (range 0.5 to 2.1). The median duration was 2.8 months (range 0.9 to 6.1). One of two patients with Grade 2 and the one patient with Grade 3 hyperthyroidism required initial treatment with high-dose corticosteroids (greater than or equal to 40 mg prednisone or equivalent per day) followed by a corticosteroid taper. One patient (0.2%) required permanent discontinuation of KEYTRUDA due to hyperthyroidism. All five patients with hyperthyroidism experienced complete resolution of the event.  



  Hypothyroidism occurred in 34 (8.3%) of 411 patients, including a Grade 3 case in 1 (0.2%) patient, receiving KEYTRUDA in Trial 1. The median time to onset of hypothyroidism was 3.5 months (range 0.7 weeks to 19 months). All but two of the patients with hypothyroidism were treated with long-term thyroid hormone replacement therapy. The other two patients only required short-term thyroid hormone replacement therapy. No patient received corticosteroids or discontinued KEYTRUDA for management of hypothyroidism.  



  Thyroid disorders can occur at any time during treatment. Monitor patients for changes in thyroid function (at the start of treatment, periodically during treatment, and as indicated based on clinical evaluation) and for clinical signs and symptoms of thyroid disorders.  



  Administer corticosteroids for Grade 3 or greater hyperthyroidism, withhold KEYTRUDA for severe (Grade 3) hyperthyroidism, and permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA for life-threatening (Grade 4) hyperthyroidism. Isolated hypothyroidism may be managed with replacement therapy without treatment interruption and without corticosteroids [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].    



     Type 1 Diabetes mellitus    



  Type 1 diabetes mellitus, including diabetic ketoacidosis, has occurred in patients receiving KEYTRUDA. Monitor patients for hyperglycemia and other signs and symptoms of diabetes. Administer insulin for type 1 diabetes, and withhold KEYTRUDA in cases of severe hyperglycemia until metabolic control is achieved [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].    



    5.5 Renal Failure and Immune-Mediated Nephritis



  Nephritis occurred in 3 (0.7%) patients, consisting of one case of Grade 2 autoimmune nephritis (0.2%) and two cases of interstitial nephritis with renal failure (0.5%), one Grade 3 and one Grade 4. The time to onset of autoimmune nephritis was 11.6 months after the first dose of KEYTRUDA (5 months after the last dose) and lasted 3.2 months; this patient did not have a biopsy. Acute interstitial nephritis was confirmed by renal biopsy in two patients with Grades 3-4 renal failure. All three patients fully recovered renal function with treatment with high-dose corticosteroids (greater than or equal to 40 mg prednisone or equivalent per day) followed by a corticosteroid taper.



 Monitor patients for changes in renal function. Administer corticosteroids for Grade 2 or greater nephritis. Withhold KEYTRUDA for moderate (Grade 2) nephritis, and permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA for severe (Grade 3), or life-threatening (Grade 4) nephritis [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.6 Other Immune-Mediated Adverse Reactions



  Other clinically important immune-mediated adverse reactions can occur.



 The following clinically significant, immune-mediated adverse reactions occurred in less than 1% of patients treated with KEYTRUDA in Trial 1: exfoliative dermatitis, uveitis, arthritis, myositis, pancreatitis, hemolytic anemia, and partial seizures arising in a patient with inflammatory foci in brain parenchyma.



  Across clinical studies with KEYTRUDA, the following clinically significant, immune-mediated adverse reactions have occurred: severe dermatitis including bullous pemphigoid, myasthenic syndrome, optic neuritis, and rhabdomyolysis.  



  For suspected immune-mediated adverse reactions, ensure adequate evaluation to confirm etiology or exclude other causes. Based on the severity of the adverse reaction, withhold KEYTRUDA and administer corticosteroids. Upon improvement to Grade 1 or less, initiate corticosteroid taper and continue to taper over at least 1 month. Restart KEYTRUDA if the adverse reaction remains at Grade 1 or less. Permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA for any severe or Grade 3 immune-mediated adverse reaction that recurs and for any life-threatening immune-mediated adverse reaction [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].    



    5.7 Infusion-Related Reactions



   Infusion-related reactions, including severe and life-threatening reactions, have occurred in patients receiving KEYTRUDA. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of infusion-related reactions including rigors, chills, wheezing, pruritis, flushing, rash, hypotension, hypoxemia, and fever. For severe (Grade 3) or life-threatening (Grade 4) infusion-related reactions, stop infusion and permanently discontinue KEYTRUDA [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  .  



    5.8 Embryofetal Toxicity



  Based on its mechanism of action, KEYTRUDA may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Animal models link the PD-1/PD-L1 signaling pathway with maintenance of pregnancy through induction of maternal immune tolerance to fetal tissue. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, apprise the patient of the potential hazard to a fetus. Advise females of reproductive potential to use highly effective contraception during treatment with KEYTRUDA and for 4 months after the last dose of KEYTRUDA [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  ,  8.8)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
