<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kinrix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    The most frequently reported solicited local reaction (&gt;50%) was injection site pain. Other common solicited local reactions (&gt;=25%) were redness, increase in arm circumference, and swelling. (  6.1  ) 
 *    Common solicited general adverse events (&gt;=15%) were drowsiness, fever (&gt;=99.5 degrees F), and loss of appetite. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 4,013 children were vaccinated with a single dose of KINRIX in 4 clinical trials. Of these, 381 children received a non-US formulation of KINRIX (containing &lt;=2.5 mg 2-phenoxyethanol per dose as preservative).



 The primary study (Study 048), conducted in the United States, was a randomized, controlled clinical trial in which children 4 to 6 years of age were vaccinated with KINRIX (N = 3,156) or control vaccines (INFANRIX and IPOL  (r)  vaccine [IPV, Sanofi Pasteur SA]; N = 1,053) as a fifth DTaP vaccine dose following 4 doses of INFANRIX and as a fourth IPV dose following 3 doses of IPOL. Subjects also received the second dose of US-licensed measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR) vaccine (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.) administered concomitantly, at separate sites.



 Data on adverse events were collected by parents/guardians using standardized forms for 4 consecutive days following vaccination with KINRIX or control vaccines (i.e., day of vaccination and the next 3 days). The reported frequencies of solicited local reactions and general adverse events in Study 048 are presented in Table 1.



 In 3 studies (Studies 046, 047, and 048), children were monitored for unsolicited adverse events, including serious adverse events, that occurred in the 31-day period following vaccination and in 2 studies (Studies 047 and 048), parents/guardians were actively queried about changes in the child's health status, including the occurrence of serious adverse events, through 6 months post-vaccination.



 Table 1. Percentage of Children 4 to 6 Years of Age Reporting Solicited Local Reactions or General Adverse Events Within 4 Days of Vaccinationa With KINRIX or Separate Concomitant Administration of INFANRIX and IPV When Coadministered With MMR Vaccine (Study 048) (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                                      KINRIX                   INFANRIX + IPV               
  Localb                                              N = 3,121-3,128          N = 1,039-1,043              
  Pain, any                                           57.0c                    53.3                         
  Pain, grade 2 or 3d                                 13.7                     12.0                         
  Pain, grade 3d                                      1.6c                     0.6                          
  Redness, any                                        36.6                     36.6                         
  Redness, &gt;=50 mm                                    17.6                     20.0                         
  Redness, &gt;=110 mm                                   2.9                      4.1                          
  Arm circumference increase, any                     36.0                     37.8                         
  Arm circumference increase, &gt;20 mm                  6.9                      7.4                          
  Arm circumference increase, &gt;30 mm                  2.4                      3.2                          
  Swelling, any                                       26.0                     27.0                         
  Swelling, &gt;=50 mm                                   10.2                     11.5                         
  Swelling, &gt;=110 mm                                  1.4                      1.8                          
  General                                             N = 3,037-3,120          N = 993-1,036                
  Drowsiness, any                                     19.1                     17.5                         
  Drowsiness, grade 3e                                0.8                      0.8                          
  Fever, &gt;=99.5 degrees F                             16.0                     14.8                         
  Fever, &gt;100.4 degrees F                             6.5c                     4.4                          
  Fever, &gt;102.2 degrees F                             1.1                      1.1                          
  Fever, &gt;104 degrees F                               0.1                      0.0                          
  Loss of appetite, any                               15.5                     16.0                         
  Loss of appetite, grade 3f                          0.8                      0.6                          
        *     IPV = inactivated poliovirus vaccine (Sanofi Pasteur SA); MMR = measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine (Merck &amp; Co., Inc.). 
 *     Total Vaccinated Cohort = all vaccinated subjects for whom safety data were available. 
 *     N = number of children with evaluable data for the events listed. 
 *       a  Within 4 days of vaccination defined as day of vaccination and the next 3 days. 
 *       b  Local reactions at the injection site for KINRIX or INFANRIX. 
 *       c  Statistically higher than comparator group ( P  &lt;0.05). 
 *       d  Grade 2 defined as painful when the limb was moved; Grade 3 defined as preventing normal daily activities. 
 *       e  Grade 3 defined as preventing normal daily activities. 
 *       f  Grade 3 defined as not eating at all. 
    In Study 048, KINRIX was non-inferior to INFANRIX with regard to swelling that involved &gt;50% of the injected upper arm length and that was associated with a &gt;30-mm increase in mid-upper arm circumference within 4 days following vaccination (upper limit of two-sided 95% Confidence Interval for difference in percentage of KINRIX [0.6%, n = 20] minus INFANRIX [1.0%, n = 11] &lt;=2%).
 

   Serious Adverse Events:  Within the 31-day period following study vaccination in 3 studies (Studies 046, 047, and 048), in which all subjects received concomitant MMR vaccine (US-licensed MMR vaccine [Merck &amp; Co., Inc.] in Studies 047 and 048; non-US-licensed MMR vaccine in Study 046), 3 subjects (0.1% [3/3,537]) who received KINRIX reported serious adverse events (dehydration and hypernatremia; cerebrovascular accident; dehydration and gastroenteritis) and 4 subjects (0.3% [4/1,434]) who received INFANRIX and inactivated poliovirus vaccine (Sanofi Pasteur SA) reported serious adverse events (cellulitis, constipation, foreign body trauma, fever without identified etiology).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to reports in clinical trials, the following adverse events, for which a causal relationship to components of KINRIX is plausible, have been reported since market introduction. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccination.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Injection site vesicles.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Syncope.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Pruritus.



 Additional adverse events reported following postmarketing use of INFANRIX, for which a causal relationship to vaccination is plausible, are: Allergic reactions, including anaphylactoid reactions, anaphylaxis, angioedema, and urticaria; apnea; collapse or shock-like state (hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode); convulsions (with or without fever); lymphadenopathy; and thrombocytopenia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurs within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the decision to give KINRIX should be based on potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
 *    The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including KINRIX. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (  5.3  ) 
 *    If adverse events (i.e., temperature &gt;=105  o  F, collapse or shock-like state, persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours, occurring within 48 hours of vaccination; seizures within 3 days of vaccination) have occurred in temporal relation to receipt of a pertussis-containing vaccine, the decision to give KINRIX should be based on potential benefits and risks. (  5.4  ) 
 *    For children at higher risk for seizures, an antipyretic may be administered at the time of vaccination with KINRIX. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurs within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the decision to give any tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine, including KINRIX, should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and possible risks. When a decision is made to withhold tetanus toxoid, other available vaccines should be given, as indicated.



    5.2 Latex



  The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals.



    5.3 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including KINRIX. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.



    5.4 Adverse Events Following Prior Pertussis Vaccination



  If any of the following events occur in temporal relation to receipt of a pertussis-containing vaccine, the decision to give any pertussis-containing vaccine, including KINRIX, should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and possible risks:



 *    Temperature of &gt;=40.5 degrees C (105 degrees F) within 48 hours not due to another identifiable cause; 
 *    Collapse or shock-like state (hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode) within 48 hours; 
 *    Persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours, occurring within 48 hours; 
 *    Seizures with or without fever occurring within 3 days. 
    When a decision is made to withhold pertussis vaccination, other available vaccines should be given, as indicated.
 

    5.5 Children at Risk for Seizures



  For children at higher risk for seizures than the general population, an appropriate antipyretic may be administered at the time of vaccination with a pertussis-containing vaccine, including KINRIX, and for the ensuing 24 hours to reduce the possibility of post-vaccination fever.



    5.6 Preventing and Managing Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Prior to administration, the healthcare provider should review the patient's immunization history for possible vaccine sensitivity and previous vaccination-related adverse reactions to allow an assessment of benefits and risks. Epinephrine and other appropriate agents used for the control of immediate allergic reactions must be immediately available should an acute anaphylactic reaction occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
