<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="klonopin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The adverse experiences for Klonopin are provided separately for patients with seizure disorders and with panic disorder.



   Seizure Disorders

  The most frequently occurring side effects of Klonopin are referable to CNS depression. Experience in treatment of seizures has shown that drowsiness has occurred in approximately 50% of patients and ataxia in approximately 30%. In some cases, these may diminish with time; behavior problems have been noted in approximately 25% of patients. Others, listed by system, are:



   Neurologic:  Abnormal eye movements, aphonia, choreiform movements, coma, diplopia, dysarthria, dysdiadochokinesis, "glassy-eyed" appearance, headache, hemiparesis, hypotonia, nystagmus, respiratory depression, slurred speech, tremor, vertigo



   Psychiatric:  Confusion, depression, amnesia, hallucinations, hysteria, increased libido, insomnia, psychosis (the behavior effects are more likely to occur in patients with a history of psychiatric disturbances). The following paradoxical reactions have been observed: excitability, irritability, aggressive behavior, agitation, nervousness, hostility, anxiety, sleep disturbances, nightmares and vivid dreams



   Respiratory:  Chest congestion, rhinorrhea, shortness of breath, hypersecretion in upper respiratory passages



   Cardiovascular:  Palpitations



   Dermatologic:  Hair loss, hirsutism, skin rash, ankle and facial edema



   Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia, coated tongue, constipation, diarrhea, dry mouth, encopresis, gastritis, increased appetite, nausea, sore gums



   Genitourinary:  Dysuria, enuresis, nocturia, urinary retention



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle weakness, pains



   Miscellaneous:  Dehydration, general deterioration, fever, lymphadenopathy, weight loss or gain



   Hematopoietic:  Anemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, eosinophilia



   Hepatic:  Hepatomegaly, transient elevations of serum transaminases and alkaline phosphatase



   Panic Disorder

  Adverse events during exposure to Klonopin were obtained by spontaneous report and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of events into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and tabulations that follow, CIGY dictionary terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events, except in certain cases in which redundant terms were collapsed into more meaningful terms, as noted below.



 The stated frequencies of adverse events represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



   Adverse Findings Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials

  Adverse Events Associated With Discontinuation of Treatment

  Overall, the incidence of discontinuation due to adverse events was 17% in Klonopin compared to 9% for placebo in the combined data of two 6- to 9-week trials. The most common events (&gt;=1%) associated with discontinuation and a dropout rate twice or greater for Klonopin than that of placebo included the following:



 Table 2 Most Common Adverse Events (&gt;=1%) Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment 
 Adverse Event                                    Klonopin (N=574)                Placebo (N=294)           
  
 Somnolence                                              7%                              1%                 
 Depression                                              4%                              1%                 
 Dizziness                                               1%                             &lt;1%                 
 Nervousness                                             1%                              0%                 
 Ataxia                                                  1%                              0%                 
 Intellectual Ability Reduced                            1%                              0%                 
           Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among Klonopin-Treated Patients
     Table 3  enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse events that occurred during acute therapy of panic disorder from a pool of two 6- to 9-week trials. Events reported in 1% or more of patients treated with Klonopin (doses ranging from 0.5 to 4 mg/day) and for which the incidence was greater than that in placebo-treated patients are included.



 The prescriber should be aware that the figures in  Table 3  cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the side effect incidence in the population studied.



 Table 3 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in 6- to 9-Week Placebo-Controlled Clinical TrialsEvents reported by at least 1% of patients treated with Klonopin and for which the incidence was greater than that for placebo. 
 Clonazepam Maximum Daily Dose   
 Adverse Eventby Body System    &lt;1mgn=96%    1-&lt;2mgn=129%  2-&lt;3mgn=113%  &gt;=3mgn=235%   All Klonopin GroupsN=574%  PlaceboN=294%   
  
 Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System                                                                                       
   Somnolence                       26            35            50            36            37            10        
   Dizziness                        5             5             12            8             8             4         
   Coordination Abnormal            1             2             7             9             6             0         
   Ataxia                           2             1             8             8             5             0         
   Dysarthria                       0             0             4             3             2             0         
 Psychiatric                                                                                                        
   Depression                       7             6             8             8             7             1         
   Memory Disturbance               2             5             2             5             4             2         
   Nervousness                      1             4             3             4             3             2         
   Intellectual Ability Reduced       0             2             4             3             2             0         
   Emotional Lability               0             1             2             2             1             1         
   Libido Decreased                 0             1             3             1             1             0         
   Confusion                        0             2             2             1             1             0         
 Respiratory System                                                                                                 
   Upper Respiratory Tract Infection       10            10            7             6             8             4         
   Sinusitis                        4             2             8             4             4             3         
   Rhinitis                         3             2             4             2             2             1         
   Coughing                         2             2             4             0             2             0         
   Pharyngitis                      1             1             3             2             2             1         
   Bronchitis                       1             0             2             2             1             1         
 Gastrointestinal System                                                                                            
   Constipation                     0             1             5             3             2             2         
   Appetite Decreased               1             1             0             3             1             1         
   Abdominal Pain                   2             2             2             0             1             1         
 Body as a Whole                                                                                                    
   Fatigue                          9             6             7             7             7             4         
   Allergic Reaction                3             1             4             2             2             1         
 Musculoskeletal                                                                                                    
   Myalgia                          2             1             4             0             1             1         
 Resistance Mechanism Disorders                                                                                       
   Influenza                        3             2             5             5             4             3         
 Urinary System                                                                                                     
   Micturition Frequency            1             2             2             1             1             0         
   Urinary Tract Infection          0             0             2             2             1             0         
 Vision Disorders                                                                                                   
   Blurred Vision                   1             2             3             0             1             1         
 Reproductive Disorders                                                                                             
   Female                                                                                                           
   Dysmenorrhea                     0             6             5             2             3             2         
   Colpitis                         4             0             2             1             1             1         
   Male                                                                                                             
   Ejaculation Delayed              0             0             2             2             1             0         
   Impotence                        3             0             2             1             1             0         
               Commonly Observed Adverse Events
     Table 4 Incidence of Most Commonly Observed Adverse EventsTreatment-emergent events for which the incidence in the clonazepam patients was &gt;=5% and at least twice that in the placebo patients. in Acute Therapy in Pool of 6- to 9-Week Trials 
 Adverse Event(Genentech Preferred Term)         Clonazepam(N=574)                 Placebo(N=294)           
  
 Somnolence                                             37%                             10%                 
 Depression                                              7%                              1%                 
 Coordination Abnormal                                   6%                              0%                 
 Ataxia                                                  5%                              0%                 
           Treatment-Emergent Depressive Symptoms
   In the pool of two short-term placebo-controlled trials, adverse events classified under the preferred term "depression" were reported in 7% of Klonopin-treated patients compared to 1% of placebo-treated patients, without any clear pattern of dose relatedness. In these same trials, adverse events classified under the preferred term "depression" were reported as leading to discontinuation in 4% of Klonopin-treated patients compared to 1% of placebo-treated patients. While these findings are noteworthy, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D) data collected in these trials revealed a larger decline in HAM-D scores in the clonazepam group than the placebo group suggesting that clonazepam-treated patients were not experiencing a worsening or emergence of clinical depression.



   Other Adverse Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Klonopin in Panic Disorder

  Following is a list of modified CIGY terms that reflect treatment-emergent adverse events reported by patients treated with Klonopin at multiple doses during clinical trials. All reported events are included except those already listed in  Table 3  or elsewhere in labeling, those events for which a drug cause was remote, those event terms which were so general as to be uninformative, and events reported only once and which did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life-threatening. It is important to emphasize that, although the events occurred during treatment with Klonopin, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency. These adverse events were reported infrequently, which is defined as occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients.



   Body as a Whole:  weight increase, accident, weight decrease, wound, edema, fever, shivering, abrasions, ankle edema, edema foot, edema periorbital, injury, malaise, pain, cellulitis, inflammation localized



   Cardiovascular Disorders:  chest pain, hypotension postural



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders:  migraine, paresthesia, drunkenness, feeling of enuresis, paresis, tremor, burning skin, falling, head fullness, hoarseness, hyperactivity, hypoesthesia, tongue thick, twitching



   Gastrointestinal System Disorders:  abdominal discomfort, gastrointestinal inflammation, stomach upset, toothache, flatulence, pyrosis, saliva increased, tooth disorder, bowel movements frequent, pain pelvic, dyspepsia, hemorrhoids



   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders:  vertigo, otitis, earache, motion sickness



   Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders:  palpitation



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  thirst, gout



   Musculoskeletal System Disorders:  back pain, fracture traumatic, sprains and strains, pain leg, pain nape, cramps muscle, cramps leg, pain ankle, pain shoulder, tendinitis, arthralgia, hypertonia, lumbago, pain feet, pain jaw, pain knee, swelling knee



   Platelet, Bleeding and Clotting Disorders:  bleeding dermal



   Psychiatric Disorders:  insomnia, organic disinhibition, anxiety, depersonalization, dreaming excessive, libido loss, appetite increased, libido increased, reactions decreased, aggressive reaction, apathy, attention lack, excitement, feeling mad, hunger abnormal, illusion, nightmares, sleep disorder, suicide ideation, yawning



   Reproductive Disorders, Female:  breast pain, menstrual irregularity



   Reproductive Disorders, Male:  ejaculation decreased



   Resistance Mechanism Disorders:  infection mycotic, infection viral, infection streptococcal, herpes simplex infection, infectious mononucleosis, moniliasis



   Respiratory System Disorders:  sneezing excessive, asthmatic attack, dyspnea, nosebleed, pneumonia, pleurisy



   Skin and Appendages Disorders:  acne flare, alopecia, xeroderma, dermatitis contact, flushing, pruritus, pustular reaction, skin burns, skin disorder



   Special Senses Other, Disorders:  taste loss



   Urinary System Disorders:  dysuria, cystitis, polyuria, urinary incontinence, bladder dysfunction, urinary retention, urinary tract bleeding, urine discoloration



   Vascular (Extracardiac) Disorders:  thrombophlebitis leg



   Vision Disorders:  eye irritation, visual disturbance, diplopia, eye twitching, styes, visual field defect, xerophthalmia
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
