<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kogenate" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions seen with Kogenate FS are systemic hypersensitivity reactions, including bronchospastic reactions and/or hypotension and anaphylaxis, and the development of high-titer inhibitors necessitating alternative treatments to factor VIII.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 4%) observed in clinical trials were inhibitor formation in previously untreated patients (PUPs) and minimally treated patients (MTPs), skin-related hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., rash, pruritus), infusion site reactions (e.g., inflammation, pain), and central venous access device (CVAD) associated infections.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=4%) in clinical trials are inhibitor formation (neutralizing antibodies) in previously untreated and minimally treated patients (PUPs and MTPs), skin-associated hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., rash, pruritus, urticaria), infusion site reactions (e.g., inflammation, pain), and central venous access device (CVAD) associated infections.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bayer HealthCare at 1-888-842-2937 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Previously Treated Patients (PTPs)  

  During the open-label clinical studies conducted in 73 PTPs, there were 24 adverse reactions reported in the course of 24,936 infusions.



 Adverse reactions reported by &gt;= 4% of the patients are listed in  Table 3  below.



 Table 3 Adverse Reactions (AR) in Previously Treated Patients with Frequency of &gt;= 4% (Age Range 12-59 years) 
  MedDRA Primary SOC                       Preferred Term                    N = 73  AR (%)                
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    Rash, pruritus                    6 (8.2%)                      
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    Infusion site reactions           3 (4.1%)                      
  SOC = System Organ Class                 
             Previously Untreated Patients (PUPs) and Minimally Treated Patients (MTPs)  
   In clinical studies with pediatric PUPs and MTPs, there were 29 adverse reactions reported in the course of 9,389 infusions.



 Adverse reactions reported by &gt;= 4% of the patients are listed in  Table 4  below.



 Table 4 Adverse Reactions (AR) in Previously Untreated Patients and Minimally Treated Patients with Frequency of &gt;= 4% (Age Range 2-27 months) 
  MedDRA Primary SOC                       Preferred Term                    N = 61  AR (%)                
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    Rash, pruritus, urticaria         10 (16%)                      
  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders     Factor VIII inhibition (neutralizing antibodies)    9 (15%)Denominator for de novo inhibitors is N = 60, since one patient had a pre-existing inhibitor.    
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    Infusion site reactions           4 (7%)                        
  SOC = System Organ Class                 
             Minimally Treated Patients (MTPs) in the Joint Outcome Study  
   In the Joint Outcome Study with pediatric MTPs treated with routine prophylaxis or episodic enhanced treatment for 5.5 years, 46 of the 65 randomized patients experienced adverse events over the study duration.



 Table 5 Adverse Reactions in Minimally Treated Patients in the Joint Outcome Study (Age Range 0-6 years) 
  MedDRA Primary SOC             Preferred Term           Prophylaxis Arm  N = 32AR (%)    Enhanced Episodic Arm  N = 33AR (%)    
  Surgical and Medical Procedures    Central venous catheterization, Catheter removal    19 (59%)              18 (55%)Three patients from the enhanced episodic arm had catheter removal.    
  Infections and Infestations    Central line infection    6 (19%)               6 (18%)                       
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    Pyrexia                  1 (3%)                4 (12%)                       
  SOC = System Organ Class       
              Immunogenicity  
   In clinical studies with 73 PTPs (defined as having more than 100 exposure days), one patient had a pre-existing inhibitor. In the other 72 patients, followed over 4 years, no  de novo  inhibitors were observed.



 In clinical studies with pediatric PUPs and MTPs, inhibitor development was observed in 9 out of 60 patients (15%), 6 were high titer  1  (&gt; 5 BU) and 3 were low-titer inhibitors. Inhibitors were detected at a median number of 7 exposure days (range 2 to 16 exposure days).



 In the Joint Outcome Study with Kogenate FS,  5    de novo  inhibitor development was observed in 8 of 64 patients with negative baseline values (12.5%), 2 patients developed high titer  1  (&gt; 5 BU) and were withdrawn from the study. Six patients developed low-titer inhibitors. Inhibitors were detected at a median number of 44 exposure days (range 5 to 151 exposure days).



 Inhibitor data in PUPs have been collected in several postmarketing registries  [see Postmarketing Experience (  6.2  )]  .



 The detection of antibody formation is dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to Kogenate FS with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because adverse reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The following adverse reaction has been identified during post approval use of Kogenate FS:



 Sensory System - Dysgeusia



     Immunogenicity - Postmarketing Registries  

  Data from the Research of Determinants of Inhibitor Development (RODIN) study  7  , French National Registry (FranceCoag)  8  and United Kingdom Haemophilia Centre Doctors' Organisation (UKHCDO)  9  registry reported an inhibitor development rate in PUPs for Kogenate FS of 38%, 50% and 35%, respectively, which is comparable to previously-reported inhibitor rates  10  for FVIII products. These registry studies show a trend towards an increased risk of inhibitor development in PUPs, as compared to the reference rFVIII product. A survey of Canadian hemophilia centers  11  (2005 to 2012) and available data from the European Haemophilia Safety Surveillance (EUHASS)  12  registry from 2009 to 2013, reported an inhibitor development rate in PUPs for Kogenate FS of 42% and 31%, respectively, with no statistically significant differences observed across FVIII products.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, are possible. Should symptoms occur, discontinue treatment with Kogenate FS and administer appropriate treatment (  5.1  ). 
 *    Development of activity-neutralizing antibodies can occur in patients receiving factor VIII-containing products, including Kogenate FS. If expected plasma factor VIII activity levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with an expected dose, perform an assay that measures factor VIII inhibitor concentration (  5.2  ). 
 *    When clotting is normalized by treatment with factor VIII, development of cardiovascular risk factors may be the same as the risk for non-hemophilic patients (  5.3  ). 
 *    Monitor plasma factor VIII levels during infusions when indicated (  5.4  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis have been reported with Kogenate FS. Reported symptoms included facial swelling, flushing, hives, decrease in blood pressure, nausea, rash, restlessness, shortness of breath, tachycardia, tightness of the chest, tingling, urticaria, and vomiting.



 Kogenate FS contains trace amounts of mouse immunoglobulin G (MuIgG) and hamster (BHK) proteins [see Description (  11  )].  Patients treated with this product may develop hypersensitivity to these non-human mammalian proteins.



 Discontinue Kogenate FS if symptoms occur and seek immediate emergency treatment.



    5.2 Neutralizing Antibodies



  Neutralizing antibodies (inhibitors) have been reported following administration of Kogenate FS, predominantly in previously untreated patients (PUPs) [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  . Carefully monitor patients for the development of factor VIII inhibitors, using appropriate clinical observations and laboratory tests.  6  If expected plasma factor VIII activity levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled with an expected dose, perform an assay that measures factor VIII inhibitor concentration [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  .



    5.3 Cardiovascular Risk Factors



  Hemophilic patients with cardiovascular risk factors or diseases may be at the same risk to develop cardiovascular events as non-hemophilic patients when clotting has been normalized by treatment with factor VIII.



    5.4 Monitoring Laboratory Tests



    *    Monitor plasma factor VIII activity levels by the one-stage clotting assay to confirm the adequate factor VIII levels have been achieved and maintained, when clinically indicated [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )].  
 *    Monitor for development of factor VIII inhibitors. Perform assay to determine if factor VIII inhibitor is present. If expected factor VIII activity plasma levels are not attained or if bleeding is not controlled with the expected dose of Kogenate FS, use Bethesda Units (BU) to titer inhibitors. 
 *  o  If the inhibitor is less than 10 BU per mL, the administration of additional Kogenate FS concentrate may neutralize the inhibitor and may permit an appropriate hemostatic response. 
   *  o  If inhibitor titers are above 10 BU per mL, adequate hemostasis may not be achieved. The inhibitor titer may rise following Kogenate FS infusion as a result of an anamnestic response to factor VIII. The treatment or prevention of bleeding in such patients requires the use of alternative therapeutic approaches and agents. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
