<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kombiglyze" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    Adverse reactions reported in &gt;5% of patients treated with metformin extended-release and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo are: diarrhea and nausea/vomiting.  (6.1)   
 *    Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients treated with saxagliptin and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo are: upper respiratory tract infection, urinary tract infection, and headache.  (6.1)   
 *    Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of treatment-naive patients treated with coadministered saxagliptin and metformin and more commonly than in patients treated with metformin alone are: headache and nasopharyngitis.  (6.1)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adverse Reactions with Monotherapy and with Add-On Combination Therapy

    Metformin hydrochloride  



 In placebo-controlled monotherapy trials of metformin extended-release, diarrhea and nausea/vomiting were reported in &gt;5% of metformin-treated patients and more commonly than in placebo-treated patients (9.6% versus 2.6% for diarrhea and 6.5% versus 1.5% for nausea/vomiting). Diarrhea led to discontinuation of study medication in 0.6% of the patients treated with metformin extended-release.



     Saxagliptin  



 In two placebo-controlled monotherapy trials of 24-week duration, patients were treated with saxagliptin 2.5 mg daily, saxagliptin 5 mg daily, and placebo. Three 24-week, placebo-controlled, add-on combination therapy trials were also conducted: one with metformin immediate-release, one with a thiazolidinedione (pioglitazone or rosiglitazone), and one with glyburide. In these three trials, patients were randomized to add-on therapy with saxagliptin 2.5 mg daily, saxagliptin 5 mg daily, or placebo. A saxagliptin 10 mg treatment arm was included in one of the monotherapy trials and in the add-on combination trial with metformin immediate-release. The 10 mg saxagliptin dosage is not an approved dosage.



 In a prespecified pooled analysis of the 24-week data (regardless of glycemic rescue) from the two monotherapy trials, the add-on to metformin immediate-release trial, the add-on to thiazolidinedione (TZD) trial, and the add-on to glyburide trial, the overall incidence of adverse events in patients treated with saxagliptin 2.5 mg and saxagliptin 5 mg was similar to placebo (72% and 72.2% versus 70.6%, respectively). Discontinuation of therapy due to adverse events occurred in 2.2%, 3.3%, and 1.8% of patients receiving saxagliptin 2.5 mg, saxagliptin 5 mg, and placebo, respectively. The most common adverse events (reported in at least 2 patients treated with saxagliptin 2.5 mg or at least 2 patients treated with saxagliptin 5 mg) associated with premature discontinuation of therapy included lymphopenia (0.1% and 0.5% versus 0%, respectively), rash (0.2% and 0.3% versus 0.3%), blood creatinine increased (0.3% and 0% versus 0%), and blood creatine phosphokinase increased (0.1% and 0.2% versus 0%). The adverse reactions in this pooled analysis reported (regardless of investigator assessment of causality) in &gt;=5% of patients treated with saxagliptin 5 mg, and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Trials* Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients Treated with Saxagliptin 5 mg and More Commonly than in Patients Treated with Placebo 
                                                Number (%) of Patients       
                                                Saxagliptin 5 mg    N=882      Placebo    N=799             
  
 *  The 5 placebo-controlled trials include two monotherapy trials and one add-on combination therapy trial with each of the following: metformin, thiazolidinedione, or glyburide. Table shows 24-week data regardless of glycemic rescue.   
  
  Upper respiratory tract infection            68 (7.7)                      61 (7.6)                      
  Urinary tract infection                      60 (6.8)                      49 (6.1)                      
  Headache                                     57 (6.5)                      47 (5.9)                      
         In patients treated with saxagliptin 2.5 mg, headache (6.5%) was the only adverse reaction reported at a rate &gt;=5% and more commonly than in patients treated with placebo.
 

 In this pooled analysis, adverse reactions that were reported in &gt;=2% of patients treated with saxagliptin 2.5 mg or saxagliptin 5 mg and &gt;=1% more frequently compared to placebo included: sinusitis (2.9% and 2.6% versus 1.6%, respectively), abdominal pain (2.4% and 1.7% versus 0.5%), gastroenteritis (1.9% and 2.3% versus 0.9%), and vomiting (2.2% and 2.3% versus 1.3%).



 The incidence rate of fractures was 1.0 and 0.6 per 100 patient-years, respectively, for saxagliptin (pooled analysis of 2.5 mg, 5 mg, and 10 mg) and placebo. The 10 mg saxagliptin dosage is not an approved dosage. The incidence rate of fracture events in patients who received saxagliptin did not increase over time. Causality has not been established and nonclinical studies have not demonstrated adverse effects of saxagliptin on bone.



 An event of thrombocytopenia, consistent with a diagnosis of idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, was observed in the clinical program. The relationship of this event to saxagliptin is not known.



   Adverse Reactions with Concomitant Use with Insulin

  In the add-on to insulin trial [see    Clinical Studies (14.4)    ], the incidence of adverse events, including serious adverse events and discontinuations due to adverse events, was similar between saxagliptin and placebo, except for confirmed hypoglycemia [see    Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



   Adverse Reactions Associated with Saxagliptin Coadministered with Metformin Immediate-Release in Treatment-Naive Patients with Type 2 Diabetes

  Table 2 shows the adverse reactions reported (regardless of investigator assessment of causality) in &gt;=5% of patients participating in an additional 24-week, active-controlled trial of coadministered saxagliptin and metformin in treatment-naive patients.



 Table 2: Coadministration of Saxagliptin and Metformin Immediate-Release in Treatment-Naive Patients: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients Treated with Combination Therapy of Saxagliptin 5 mg Plus Metformin Immediate-Release (and More Commonly than in Patients Treated with Metformin Immediate-Release Alone) 
                           Number (%) of Patients                  
                           Saxagliptin 5 mg + Metformin*    N=320      Placebo + Metformin*    N=328          
  
 *  Metformin immediate-release was initiated at a starting dose of 500 mg daily and titrated up to a maximum of 2000 mg daily.   
  
  Headache                24 (7.5)                                 17 (5.2)                                
  Nasopharyngitis         22 (6.9)                                 13 (4.0)                                
         In patients treated with the combination of saxagliptin and metformin immediate-release, either as saxagliptin add-on to metformin immediate-release therapy or as coadministration in treatment-naive patients, diarrhea was the only gastrointestinal-related event that occurred with an incidence &gt;=5% in any treatment group in both studies. In the saxagliptin add-on to metformin immediate-release trial, the incidence of diarrhea was 9.9%, 5.8%, and 11.2% in the saxagliptin 2.5 mg, 5 mg, and placebo groups, respectively. When saxagliptin and metformin immediate-release were coadministered in treatment-naive patients, the incidence of diarrhea was 6.9% in the saxagliptin 5 mg + metformin immediate-release group and 7.3% in the placebo + metformin immediate-release group.
 

   Hypoglycemia

  In the saxagliptin clinical trials, adverse reactions of hypoglycemia were based on all reports of hypoglycemia. A concurrent glucose measurement was not required or was normal in some patients. Therefore, it is not possible to conclusively determine that all these reports reflect true hypoglycemia.



 The incidence of reported hypoglycemia for saxagliptin 2.5 mg and saxagliptin 5 mg versus placebo given as monotherapy was 4% and 5.6% versus 4.1%, respectively. In the add-on to metformin immediate-release trial, the incidence of reported hypoglycemia was 7.8% with saxagliptin 2.5 mg, 5.8% with saxagliptin 5 mg, and 5% with placebo. When saxagliptin and metformin immediate-release were coadministered in treatment-naive patients, the incidence of reported hypoglycemia was 3.4% in patients given saxagliptin 5 mg + metformin immediate-release and 4% in patients given placebo + metformin immediate-release.



 In the active-controlled trial comparing add-on therapy with saxagliptin 5 mg to glipizide in patients inadequately controlled on metformin alone, the incidence of reported hypoglycemia was 3% (19 events in 13 patients) with saxagliptin 5 mg versus 36.3% (750 events in 156 patients) with glipizide. Confirmed symptomatic hypoglycemia (accompanying fingerstick blood glucose &lt;=50 mg/dL) was reported in none of the saxagliptin-treated patients and in 35 glipizide-treated patients (8.1%) (p&lt;0.0001).



 In the saxagliptin add-on to insulin trial, the overall incidence of reported hypoglycemia was 18.4% for saxagliptin 5 mg and 19.9% for placebo. However, the incidence of confirmed symptomatic hypoglycemia (accompanying fingerstick blood glucose &lt;=50 mg/dL) was higher with saxagliptin 5 mg (5.3%) versus placebo (3.3%). Among the patients using insulin in combination with metformin, the incidence of confirmed symptomatic hypoglycemia was 4.8% with saxagliptin versus 1.9% with placebo.



 In the saxagliptin add-on to metformin plus sulfonylurea trial, the overall incidence of reported hypoglycemia was 10.1% for saxagliptin 5 mg and 6.3% for placebo. Confirmed hypoglycemia was reported in 1.6% of the saxagliptin-treated patients and in none of the placebo-treated patients [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.9)    ].



   Hypersensitivity Reactions

    Saxagliptin  



 Hypersensitivity-related events, such as urticaria and facial edema in the 5-study pooled analysis up to Week 24 were reported in 1.5%, 1.5%, and 0.4% of patients who received saxagliptin 2.5 mg, saxagliptin 5 mg, and placebo, respectively. None of these events in patients who received saxagliptin required hospitalization or were reported as life-threatening by the investigators. One saxagliptin-treated patient in this pooled analysis discontinued due to generalized urticaria and facial edema.



   Infections

    Saxagliptin  



 In the unblinded, controlled, clinical trial database for saxagliptin to date, there have been 6 (0.12%) reports of tuberculosis among the 4959 saxagliptin-treated patients (1.1 per 1000 patient-years) compared to no reports of tuberculosis among the 2868 comparator-treated patients. Two of these six cases were confirmed with laboratory testing. The remaining cases had limited information or had presumptive diagnoses of tuberculosis. None of the six cases occurred in the United States or in Western Europe. One case occurred in Canada in a patient originally from Indonesia who had recently visited Indonesia. The duration of treatment with saxagliptin until report of tuberculosis ranged from 144 to 929 days. Post-treatment lymphocyte counts were consistently within the reference range for four cases. One patient had lymphopenia prior to initiation of saxagliptin that remained stable throughout saxagliptin treatment. The final patient had an isolated lymphocyte count below normal approximately four months prior to the report of tuberculosis. There have been no spontaneous reports of tuberculosis associated with saxagliptin use. Causality has not been established and there are too few cases to date to determine whether tuberculosis is related to saxagliptin use.



 There has been one case of a potential opportunistic infection in the unblinded, controlled clinical trial database to date in a saxagliptin-treated patient who developed suspected foodborne fatal salmonella sepsis after approximately 600 days of saxagliptin therapy. There have been no spontaneous reports of opportunistic infections associated with saxagliptin use.



   Vital Signs

    Saxagliptin  



 No clinically meaningful changes in vital signs have been observed in patients treated with saxagliptin alone or in combination with metformin.



   Laboratory Tests

  Absolute Lymphocyte Counts

    Saxagliptin  



 There was a dose-related mean decrease in absolute lymphocyte count observed with saxagliptin. From a baseline mean absolute lymphocyte count of approximately 2200 cells/microL, mean decreases of approximately 100 and 120 cells/microL with saxagliptin 5 mg and 10 mg, respectively, relative to placebo were observed at 24 weeks in a pooled analysis of five placebo-controlled clinical studies. Similar effects were observed when saxagliptin 5 mg and metformin were coadministered in treatment-naive patients compared to placebo and metformin. There was no difference observed for saxagliptin 2.5 mg relative to placebo. The proportion of patients who were reported to have a lymphocyte count &lt;=750 cells/microL was 0.5%, 1.5%, 1.4%, and 0.4% in the saxagliptin 2.5 mg, 5 mg, 10 mg, and placebo groups, respectively. In most patients, recurrence was not observed with repeated exposure to saxagliptin although some patients had recurrent decreases upon rechallenge that led to discontinuation of saxagliptin. The decreases in lymphocyte count were not associated with clinically relevant adverse reactions. The 10 mg saxagliptin dosage is not an approved dosage.



 The clinical significance of this decrease in lymphocyte count relative to placebo is not known. When clinically indicated, such as in settings of unusual or prolonged infection, lymphocyte count should be measured. The effect of saxagliptin on lymphocyte counts in patients with lymphocyte abnormalities (e.g., human immunodeficiency virus) is unknown.



   Vitamin B12Concentrations

    Metformin hydrochloride  



 Metformin may lower serum vitamin B12concentrations. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on KOMBIGLYZE XR and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. [See    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    .]



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of saxagliptin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *    Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions. [See   Contraindications (4)   and   Warnings and Precautions (5.13)   .] 
 *    Acute pancreatitis. [See   Indications and Usage (1.1)   and   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   .] 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

  WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious, complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure.  



   The onset of lactic acidosis is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress.  



   Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate.  



   If acidosis is suspected, KOMBIGLYZE XR should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately. [See     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    .]  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS



      See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate. (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue KOMBIGLYZE XR and hospitalize the patient immediately. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Lactic Acidosis: Warn patients against excessive alcohol intake. KOMBIGLYZE XR not recommended in hepatic impairment and contraindicated in renal impairment. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter. Temporarily discontinue KOMBIGLYZE XR in patients undergoing radiologic studies with intravascular administration of iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food and fluids.  (4  ,  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.7  ,  5.10  ,  5.11)   
 *     Acute Pancreatitis (postmarketing reports): If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue KOMBIGLYZE XR.  (5.2  ,  6.2)   
 *     Vitamin B12Deficiency: Metformin may lower vitamin B12levels. Measure hematological parameters annually.  (5.5  ,  6.1)   
 *     Hypoglycemia: In the saxagliptin add-on to sulfonylurea, add-on to insulin, and add-on to metformin plus sulfonylurea trials, confirmed hypoglycemia was reported more commonly in patients treated with saxagliptin compared to placebo. When used with an insulin secretagogue (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia.  (5.9  ,  6.1)   
 *     Hypersensitivity-Related Events (e.g., urticaria, facial edema): More common in patients treated with saxagliptin than in patients treated with placebo; and postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions, such as anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions in patients treated with saxagliptin. Promptly discontinue KOMBIGLYZE XR, assess for other potential causes, institute appropriate monitoring and treatment, and initiate alternative treatment for diabetes.  (5.13  ,  6.1  ,  6.2)   
 *     Macrovascular Outcomes: No conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with KOMBIGLYZE XR or any other antidiabetic drug.  (5.14)   
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



  Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with KOMBIGLYZE XR; when it occurs, it is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate levels (&gt;5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels &gt;5 ug/mL are generally found.



 The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin hydrochloride is very low (approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years). In more than 20,000 patient-years exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal insufficiency, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, in particular those with unstable or acute congestive heart failure who are at risk of hypoperfusion and hypoxemia, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking metformin and by use of the minimum effective dose of metformin. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. Metformin treatment should not be initiated in patients &gt;=80 years of age unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced, as these patients are more susceptible to developing lactic acidosis. In addition, metformin should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, metformin should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake when taking metformin since alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin hydrochloride on lactate metabolism. In addition, metformin should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3  ,  5.6  ,  5.7  ,  5.11)    ].



 The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis. The patient and the patient's physician must be aware of the possible importance of such symptoms and the patient should be instructed to notify the physician immediately if they occur [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.12)    ]. Metformin should be withdrawn until the situation is clarified. Serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, and if indicated, blood pH, lactate levels, and even blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of metformin, gastrointestinal symptoms, which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to be drug related. Later occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease.



 Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal, but less than 5 mmol/L, in patients taking metformin do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explainable by other mechanisms, such as poorly controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling. [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.8)    .]



 Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia).



 Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking metformin, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin hydrochloride is dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery [see   Contraindications (4)    and   Warnings and Precautions (5.6  ,  5.7  ,  5.10  ,  5.11  ,  5.12)    ].



    5.2 Pancreatitis



  There have been postmarketing reports of acute pancreatitis in patients taking saxagliptin. After initiation of KOMBIGLYZE XR, patients should be observed carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis. If pancreatitis is suspected, KOMBIGLYZE XR should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated. It is unknown whether patients with a history of pancreatitis are at increased risk for the development of pancreatitis while using KOMBIGLYZE XR.



    5.3 Assessment of Renal Function



  Metformin is substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of impairment of renal function. Therefore, KOMBIGLYZE XR is contraindicated in patients with renal impairment [see   Contraindications (4)    ].



 Before initiation of KOMBIGLYZE XR, and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal impairment is anticipated (e.g., elderly), renal function should be assessed more frequently and KOMBIGLYZE XR discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present.



    5.4 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Metformin use in patients with impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis. Therefore, KOMBIGLYZE XR is not recommended in patients with hepatic impairment.



    5.5 Vitamin B12Concentrations



  In controlled clinical trials of metformin of 29-week duration, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on KOMBIGLYZE XR and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



 Certain individuals (those with inadequate vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum vitamin B12measurements at 2- to 3-year intervals may be useful.



    5.6 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol potentiates the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients should be warned against excessive alcohol intake while receiving KOMBIGLYZE XR.



    5.7 Surgical Procedures



  Use of KOMBIGLYZE XR should be temporarily suspended for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.8 Change in Clinical Status of Patients with Previously Controlled Type 2 Diabetes



  A patient with type 2 diabetes previously well controlled on KOMBIGLYZE XR who develops laboratory abnormalities or clinical illness (especially vague and poorly defined illness) should be evaluated promptly for evidence of ketoacidosis or lactic acidosis. Evaluation should include serum electrolytes and ketones, blood glucose and, if indicated, blood pH, lactate, pyruvate, and metformin levels. If acidosis of either form occurs, KOMBIGLYZE XR must be stopped immediately and other appropriate corrective measures initiated.



    5.9 Hypoglycemia with Concomitant Use of Sulfonylurea or Insulin



   Saxagliptin  



 When saxagliptin was used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin, medications known to cause hypoglycemia, the incidence of confirmed hypoglycemia was increased over that of placebo used in combination with a sulfonylurea or with insulin. [See   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    .] Therefore, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with KOMBIGLYZE XR. [See   Dosage and Administration (2.3)    .]



    Metformin hydrochloride  



 Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation, or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as sulfonylureas and insulin) or ethanol. Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.



    5.10 Concomitant Medications Affecting Renal Function or Metformin Disposition



  Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or may interfere with the disposition of metformin, such as cationic drugs that are eliminated by renal tubular secretion [see   Drug Interactions (7.2)    ], should be used with caution.



    5.11 Radiologic Studies with Intravascular Iodinated Contrast Materials



  Intravascular contrast studies with iodinated materials can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin. Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, KOMBIGLYZE XR should be temporarily discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been re-evaluated and found to be normal.



    5.12 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock), acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction, and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients on KOMBIGLYZE XR therapy, the drug should be promptly discontinued.



    5.13 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions in patients treated with saxagliptin. These reactions include anaphylaxis, angioedema, and exfoliative skin conditions. Onset of these reactions occurred within the first 3 months after initiation of treatment with saxagliptin, with some reports occurring after the first dose. If a serious hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, discontinue KOMBIGLYZE XR, assess for other potential causes for the event, and institute alternative treatment for diabetes. [See   Adverse Reactions (6.2)    .]



 Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema to another dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP4) inhibitor because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with KOMBIGLYZE XR.



    5.14 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with KOMBIGLYZE XR or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
