<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="korlym" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions in Cushing's syndrome (&gt;= 20%): nausea, fatigue, headache, decreased blood potassium, arthralgia, vomiting, peripheral edema, hypertension, dizziness, decreased appetite, endometrial hypertrophy



   To report suspected adverse reactions, contact Corcept Therapeutics at 1-855-844-3270 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Safety data on the use of Korlym are available from 50 patients with Cushing's syndrome enrolled in an uncontrolled, open-label, multi-center trial (Study 400). Forty-three patients had Cushing's disease and all except one had previously undergone pituitary surgery. Four patients had ectopic ACTH secretion, and three had adrenal carcinoma. Patients were treated for up to 24 weeks. A dose of 300 mg per day was administered for the initial 14 days; thereafter, the dose could be escalated in increments of 300 mg per day based on assessments of tolerability and clinical response. Doses were escalated up to 900 mg per day for patients &lt;60 kg, or 1200 mg per day for patients &gt;60 kg.



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions (reported in &gt;=20% of patients, regardless of relationship to Korlym) were nausea, fatigue, headache, decreased blood potassium, arthralgia, vomiting, peripheral edema, hypertension, dizziness, decreased appetite, and endometrial hypertrophy. Drug-related adverse events resulted in dose interruption or reduction in study drug in 40% of patients.



 The adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=10% of the Cushing's syndrome patients receiving Korlym, regardless of relationship to Korlym, are shown in  Table 1  .



 Table 1. Treatment Emergent Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;=10% of Cushing's Syndrome Patients Receiving Korlym 
   Body System/Adverse Reaction                                         Percent (%) of Patients Reporting Event    (n = 50)     
  
  *The denominator was 26 females who had baseline and end-of-trial transvaginal ultrasound    
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                          
 Nausea                                                               48                                 
 Vomiting                                                             26                                 
 Dry mouth                                                            18                                 
 Diarrhea                                                             12                                 
 Constipation                                                         10                                 
   General disorders and administration/site conditions                
 Fatigue                                                              48                                 
 Edema peripheral                                                     26                                 
 Pain                                                                 14                                 
   Nervous system disorders                                            
 Headache                                                             44                                 
 Dizziness                                                            22                                 
 Somnolence                                                           10                                 
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                     
 Arthralgia                                                           30                                 
 Back pain                                                            16                                 
 Myalgia                                                              14                                 
 Pain in extremity                                                    12                                 
   Investigations                                                      
 Blood potassium decreased                                            34                                 
 Thyroid function test abnormal                                       18                                 
   Infections and infestations                                         
 Sinusitis                                                            14                                 
 Nasopharyngitis                                                      12                                 
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                  
 Decreased appetite                                                   20                                 
 Anorexia                                                             10                                 
   Vascular disorders                                                  
 Hypertension                                                         24                                 
   Reproductive system and breast disorders                            
 Endometrial hypertrophy                                              38*                                
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                    
 Dyspnea                                                              16                                 
   Psychiatric disorders                                               
 Anxiety                                                              10                                 
          6.2 Laboratory Tests
   Reductions in high density lipoprotein-cholesterol (HDL-C) levels have been observed following treatment with Korlym. In study subjects that experienced declines in HDL-C, levels returned to baseline following discontinuation of drug. The clinical significance of the treatment-related reduction in HDL-C levels in patients with Cushing's syndrome is not known.



 In a study of patients with Cushing's syndrome, hypokalemia was observed in 44% of subjects during treatment with Korlym. In these cases, hypokalemia responded to treatment with potassium supplementation and/or mineralocorticoid antagonist therapy (e.g., spironolactone or eplerenone). Hypokalemia should be corrected prior to initiating Korlym.  [See Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  



 Elevations of thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) were seen in subjects treated with Korlym. Of the 42 subjects with detectable TSH at baseline, eight (19%) had increases in TSH above the normal range, while remaining asymptomatic. The TSH levels returned to normal in most patients without intervention when Korlym was discontinued at the end of the study.



   6.3 Vaginal Bleeding and Endometrial Changes

  In Study 400, the thickness of the endometrium increased from a mean of 6.14 mm at baseline (n=23) to 15.7 mm at end-of-trial (n=18) in premenopausal women; in postmenopausal women the increase was from 2.75 mm (n=6) to 7.35 mm (n=8). Endometrial thickness above the upper limit of normal was reported in 10/26 females who had baseline and end-of-trial transvaginal ultrasound (38%). The endometrial thickness returned to the normal range in 3 out of 10 patients 6 weeks after treatment cessation at the end of the study. Vaginal bleeding occurred in 5 out of 35 females (14%). Two of five subjects with vaginal bleeding had normal endometrial thickness. Endometrial biopsies were performed in six patients; five of these patients had endometrial thickening. No endometrial carcinoma was detected in the sampled cases.



   6.4 Additional Data from Clinical Trials

  The following are adverse events that were reported in Study 400 at frequencies of &gt;= 5% to 10%, and may be related to Korlym's mechanism of action:



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  gastroesophageal reflux, abdominal pain



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  asthenia, malaise, edema, pitting edema, thirst



   Investigations:  blood triglycerides increased



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  hypoglycemia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  muscular weakness, flank pain, musculoskeletal chest pain



   Psychiatric disorders:  insomnia



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  vaginal hemorrhage, metrorrhagia  [See Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  



   6.4.1 Adrenal Insufficiency

  Adrenal insufficiency was reported in two subjects (4%) in Study 400. The most typical symptoms of adrenal insufficiency were nausea and decreased appetite. No hypotension or hypoglycemia was reported during the events. Adrenal insufficiency resolved in both cases with Korlym interruption and /or dexamethasone administration.



   6.4.2 Rash

  Generalized, maculo-papular rash was reported in 2 subjects (4%) in Study 400. Two additional subjects developed pruritus (4%). None resulted in discontinuation of Korlym, and all the events resolved by the end of the study.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY



  WARNING:  TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY



    Mifepristone is a potent antagonist of progesterone and cortisol via the progesterone and glucocorticoid (GR-II) receptors, respectively.  The antiprogestational effects will result in the termination of pregnancy. Pregnancy must therefore be excluded before the initiation of treatment with Korlym and prevented during treatment and for one month after stopping treatment by the use of a non-hormonal medically acceptable method of contraception unless the patient has had a surgical sterilization, in which case no additional contraception is needed. Pregnancy must also be excluded if treatment is interrupted for more than 14 days in females of reproductive potential.  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:  TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Mifepristone has potent antiprogestational effects and will result in the termination of pregnancy. Pregnancy must therefore be excluded before the initiation of treatment with Korlym, or if treatment is interrupted for more than 14 days in females of reproductive potential.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Adrenal insufficiency : Patients should be closely monitored for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency (  5.1  ). 
 *   Hypokalemia : Hypokalemia should be corrected prior to treatment and monitored for during treatment (  5.2  ). 
 *   Vaginal bleeding and endometrial changes : Women may experience endometrial thickening or unexpected vaginal bleeding. Use with caution if patient also has a hemorrhagic disorder or is on anti-coagulant therapy (  5.3  ). 
 *   QT interval prolongation : Avoid use with QT interval-prolonging drugs, or in patients with potassium channel variants resulting in a long QT interval (  5.4  ). 
 *   Use of Strong CYP3A Inhibitors: Concomitant use can increase mifepristone plasma levels significantly. Use only when necessary and limit mifepristone dose to 300 mg (  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Adrenal Insufficiency



  Patients receiving mifepristone may experience adrenal insufficiency. Because serum cortisol levels remain elevated and may even increase during treatment with Korlym, serum cortisol levels do not provide an accurate assessment of hypoadrenalism in patients receiving Korlym. Patients should be closely monitored for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency, including weakness, nausea, increased fatigue, hypotension, and hypoglycemia. If adrenal insufficiency is suspected, discontinue treatment with Korlym immediately and administer glucocorticoids without delay. High doses of supplemental glucocorticoids may be needed to overcome the glucocorticoid receptor blockade produced by mifepristone. Factors considered in deciding on the duration of glucocorticoid treatment should include the long half-life of mifepristone (85 hours).



 Treatment with Korlym at a lower dose can be resumed after resolution of adrenal insufficiency. Patients should also be evaluated for precipitating causes of hypoadrenalism (infection, trauma, etc.).



    5.2 Hypokalemia



  In a study of patients with Cushing's syndrome, hypokalemia was observed in 44% of subjects during treatment with Korlym. Hypokalemia should be corrected prior to initiating Korlym. During Korlym administration, serum potassium should be measured 1 to 2 weeks after starting or increasing the dose of Korlym and periodically thereafter. Hypokalemia can occur at any time during Korlym treatment. Mifepristone-induced hypokalemia should be treated with intravenous or oral potassium supplementation based on event severity. If hypokalemia persists in spite of potassium supplementation, consider adding mineralocorticoid antagonists.



    5.3 Vaginal Bleeding and Endometrial Changes



  Being an antagonist of the progesterone receptor, mifepristone promotes unopposed endometrial proliferation that may result in endometrium thickening, cystic dilatation of endometrial glands, and vaginal bleeding. Korlym should be used with caution in women who have hemorrhagic disorders or are receiving concurrent anticoagulant therapy. Women who experience vaginal bleeding during Korlym treatment should be referred to a gynecologist for further evaluation.



    5.4 QT Interval Prolongation



  Mifepristone and its metabolites block IKr. Korlym prolongs the QTc interval in a dose-related manner. There is little or no experience with high exposure, concomitant dosing with other QT-prolonging drugs, or potassium channel variants resulting in a long QT interval. [See Warnings &amp; Precautions (  5.6  )]  To minimize risk, the lowest effective dose should always be used.



    5.5 Exacerbation/Deterioration of Conditions Treated with Corticosteroids



  Use of Korlym in patients who receive corticosteroids for other conditions (e.g., autoimmune disorders) may lead to exacerbation or deterioration of such conditions, as Korlym antagonizes the desired effects of glucocorticoid in these clinical settings. For medical conditions in which chronic corticosteroid therapy is lifesaving (e.g., immunosuppression in organ transplantation), Korlym is contraindicated. [See Contraindications (  4.3  )]  



    5.6 Use of Strong CYP3A Inhibitors



  Korlym should be used with extreme caution in patients taking ketoconazole and other strong inhibitors of CYP3A, such as itraconazole, nefazodone, ritonavir, nelfinavir, indinavir, atazanavir, amprenavir, fosamprenavir, boceprevir, clarithromycin, conivaptan, lopinavir, posaconazole, saquinavir, telaprevir, telithromycin, or voriconazole, as these could substantially increase the concentration of mifepristone in the blood. The benefit of concomitant use of these agents should be carefully weighed against the potential risks. Mifepristone should be used in combination with strong CYP3A inhibitors only when necessary, and in such cases the dose should be limited to 300 mg per day. [See Warnings &amp; Precautions (  5.4  ), Drug Interactions (  7.2  ), and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  



    5.7 Pneumocystis jiroveci  Infection



  Patients with endogenous Cushing's syndrome are at risk for opportunistic infections such as Pneumocystis jiroveci  pneumonia during Korlym treatment. Patients may present with respiratory distress shortly after initiation of Korlym. Appropriate diagnostic tests should be undertaken and treatment for Pneumocystis jiroveci  should be considered.



    5.8 Potential Effects of Hypercortisolemia



  Korlym does not reduce serum cortisol levels. Elevated cortisol levels may activate mineralocorticoid receptors which are also expressed in cardiac tissues. Caution should be used in patients with underlying heart conditions including heart failure and coronary vascular disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
