<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kovaltry" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most frequently reported adverse reactions in clinical trials (&gt;=3%) were headache, pyrexia, and pruritus (see  Table 3  ).



   EXCERPT:   The most frequently reported adverse reactions in clinical trials (&gt;=3%) were headache, pyrexia, and pruritus (  6  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    Bayer HealthCare at 1-888-842-2937    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety profile of KOVALTRY was evaluated in 193 previously treated patients (PTPs) (inclusive of 51 pediatric patients &lt;12 years of age) with at least three months of exposure to KOVALTRY. The safety analysis was done using a pooled database from three multi-center, prospective, open-label clinical studies. The median time on study for patients &gt;=12 years of age was 372 days with a median of 159 exposure days (EDs). The median time on study for patients &lt;12 years of age was 182 days with a median of 73 EDs. Subjects who received KOVALTRY for perioperative management (n=5) with treatment period of 2 to 3 weeks and those who received single doses of KOVALTRY for PK studies (n=6) were excluded from safety analysis.  Table 3  lists the adverse reactions reported during clinical studies. The frequency, type, and severity of adverse reactions in children are similar to those in adults.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions in PTPs (N=193) 
   MedDRA Primary System Organ Class  Preferred term          FrequencyN (%)     
  
  Blood and the Lymphatic System Disorders                                     
  Lymphadenopathy                                            2 (1.0%)          
  Cardiac Disorders                                                            
  Palpitation  Sinus tachycardia                             2 (1.0%)  2 (1.0%)    
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                   
  Abdominal pain  Abdominal discomfort  Dyspepsia            4 (2.1%)  3 (1.6%)  4 (2.1%)    
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                         
  Pyrexia  Chest discomfort  Injection site reactionsIncludes injection site extravasation and hematoma, infusion site pain, pruritus, and swelling    8 (4.1%)  2 (1.0%)  5 (2.6%)    
  Immune System Disorders                                                      
  Hypersensitivity                                           1 (0.5%)          
  Nervous System Disorders                                                     
  Dizziness  Dysgeusia  Headache                             2 (1.0%)  1 (0.5%)  14 (7.3%)    
  Psychiatric Disorders                                                        
  Insomnia                                                   5 (2.6%)          
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                       
  Dermatitis allergic  Pruritus  RashIncludes rash, rash erythematous, and rash pruritic  Urticaria    2 (1.0%)  6 (3.1%)  5 (2.6%)  1 (0.5%)    
  Vascular disorders                                                           
  Flushing                                                   1 (0.5%)          
          Immunogenicity  
 

 All clinical trial subjects were monitored for neutralizing antibodies (inhibitors) to Factor VIII by the modified Bethesda assay using blood samples obtained prior to the first infusion of KOVALTRY, at defined intervals during the studies and at the completion visit.



 Clinical trials (Phases 1 through 3) with KOVALTRY evaluated a total of 204 pediatric and adult patients diagnosed with severe hemophilia A (Factor VIII &lt;1%) with previous exposure to Factor VIII concentrates &gt;=50 EDs, and no history of inhibitors.



 In the completed studies, no PTP developed neutralizing antibodies to Factor VIII. In an ongoing extension study, a 13 year old PTP had a titer of 0.6 BU after 550 EDs concurrent with an acute infection and positive IgG anticardiolipin antibodies. The Factor VIII recovery was 2.2 IU/dL per IU/kg, annualized bleeding rate (ABR) was zero, and no change in therapy was required.



 In an actively enrolling clinical trial in PUPs, 6 of 14 treated subjects (42.9% with a 95% Confidence Interval of 17.7-71.1%) developed an inhibitor. Of these, 3 subjects (21.4%) had high titer inhibitors, and 3 subjects (21.4%) had transient low titer inhibitors for which no change in therapy was required.



 The detection of antibody formation is dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, it may be misleading to compare the incidence of antibodies to KOVALTRY with the incidence of antibodies to other products.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, are possible. Should symptoms occur, discontinue treatment with KOVALTRY and administer appropriate treatment (  5.1  ). 
 *    Development of Factor VIII-neutralizing antibodies can occur. Perform an assay that measures Factor VIII inhibitor concentration if expected plasma Factor VIII activity levels are not attained, or if bleeding is not controlled as expected with administered dose (  5.2  ,  5.5  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, are possible with KOVALTRY. Early signs of hypersensitivity reactions, which can progress to anaphylaxis, may include chest or throat tightness, dizziness, mild hypotension and nausea. Discontinue KOVALTRY if symptoms occur and seek immediate emergency treatment.



 KOVALTRY may contain trace amounts of mouse and hamster proteins [see Description (  11  )]  . Patients treated with this product may develop hypersensitivity to these non-human mammalian proteins.



    5.2 Neutralizing Antibodies



  Neutralizing antibody (inhibitor) formation can occur following administration of KOVALTRY. Previously untreated patients (PUPs) are at greatest risk for inhibitor development with all Factor VIII products [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Carefully monitor patients for the development of Factor VIII inhibitors, using appropriate clinical observations and laboratory tests. If expected plasma Factor VIII activity levels are not attained or if bleeding is not controlled as expected with administered dose, suspect the presence of an inhibitor (neutralizing antibody) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  .



    5.3 Cardiovascular Risk Factors



  Hemophilic patients with cardiovascular risk factors or diseases may be at the same risk to develop cardiovascular events as non-hemophilic patients when clotting has been normalized by treatment with Factor VIII.



    5.4 Catheter-related Infections



  Catheter-related infections may be observed when KOVALTRY is administered via central venous access devices (CVADs). These infections have not been associated with the product itself.



    5.5 Monitoring Laboratory Tests



    *    Monitor plasma Factor VIII activity levels using a validated test to confirm that adequate Factor VIII levels have been achieved and maintained [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )] . 
 *    Monitor for development of Factor VIII inhibitors. Perform a Bethesda inhibitor assay if expected Factor VIII plasma levels are not attained or if bleeding is not controlled with the expected dose of KOVALTRY. Use Bethesda Units (BU) to report inhibitor titers. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
