<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kovanaze" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Epistaxis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Dysphagia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Methemoglobinemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Anaphylatic Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions occurring in &gt;10% of patients include rhinorrhea, nasal congestion, nasal discomfort, oropharyngeal pain, and lacrimation increased (  6  ).
 

 Transient, asymptomatic elevations in systolic blood pressure (&gt;= 25 mm Hg from baseline) and diastolic blood pressures (&gt;= 15 mm Hg from baseline) have been reported (  6  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact St. Renatus, LLC at 800-865-4925 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The adverse reactions information described below is from Phase 3 randomized, controlled clinical trials  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  . These data reflect exposure to KOVANAZE in 154 adult dental patients and 20 pediatric dental patients (aged 7 to 17 years) with a need for an operative restorative dental procedure requiring local anesthesia for a single vital maxillary tooth (other than a maxillary first, second, or third molar) with no evidence of pulpal pathology.  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )].  



     Common Adverse Reactions in Adult Dental Patients and Pediatric Patients Weighing 40 kg or More  



 The most common adverse reactions to occur in Phase 3 trials with KOVANAZE in adult dental patients and pediatric dental patients weighing 40 kg or more were rhinorrhea, nasal congestion, nasal discomfort, oropharyngeal pain, and lacrimation increased  [  Table 1  ]  .



 No serious adverse events with KOVANAZE have occurred  [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  .



 



 Table 1: Common Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 2% of Phase 3 Adult Dental Patients and Pediatric Patients Weighing 40 kg or More 
   SOC / Preferred Term       KOVANAZE (N=174)           Active Comparator* (N=54)      Placebo (N=88)            
   Respiratory System Disorders    141 (81%)                  50 (93%)                   18 (21%)                    
 Rhinorrhea (runny nose)    91 (52%)                   20 (37%)                   3 (3%)                      
 Nasal congestion           56 (32%)                   34 (63%)                   6 (7%)                      
 Nasal discomfort           45 (26%)                   7 (13%)                    5 (6%)                      
 Oropharyngeal pain (sore throat)  25 (14%)                   5 (9%)                     0 (0%)                      
 Intranasal hypoesthesia    18 (10%)                   8 (15%)                    5 (6%)                      
 Pharyngeal hypesthesia (numb throat)  17 (10%)                   10 (19%)                   0 (0%)                      
 Throat Irritation          15 (9%)                    1 (2%)                     0 (0%)                      
 Rhinalgia                  10 (6%)                    3 (6%)                     2 (2%)                      
 Sneezing                   7 (4%)                     2 (4%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Epistaxis                  4 (2%)                     2 (4%)                     0 (0%)                      
 Nasal Dryness              4 (2%)                     0 (0%)                     1 (1%)                      
   Nervous System Disorders    39 (22%)                   5 (9%)                     6 (7%)                      
 Headache                   18 (10%)                   3 (6%)                     4 (5%)                      
 Dysgeusia                  14 (8%)                    1 (2%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Sinus headache             5 (3%)                     0 (0%)                     0 (0%)                      
 Dizziness                  5 (3%)                     0 (0%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Sensory Disturbance        4 (2%)                     0 (0%)                     0 (0%)                      
   Eye Disorders            29 (17%)                   8 (15%)                    4 (5%)                      
 Lacrimation increased (watery eye)  23 (13%)                   6 (11%)                    4 (5%)                      
   Gastrointestinal Disorders    16 (9%)                    5 (9%)                     3 (3%)                      
 Oral Discomfort            4 (2%)                     0 (0%)                     0 (0%)                      
   Investigations           12 (7%)                    0 (0%)                     4 (5%)                      
 BP systolic increased      8 (5%)                     0 (0%)                     2 (2%)                      
 BP diastolic increased     6 (3%)                     0 (0%)                     1 (1%)                      
   Cardiac Disorders        8 (5%)                     5 (9%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Bradycardia                5 (3%)                     3 (6%)                     1 (1%)                      
   Vascular Disorders       6 (3%)                     2 (4%)                     1 (1%)                      
 Hypertension               5 (3%)                     1 (2%)                     1 (1%)                      
 * Active Comparator was tetracaine only spray used in two clinical studies in adults.   
      Intranasal ulcerations, some of which were transient, were noted to have occurred following treatment with KOVANAZE. In Phase 3 trials, 6 (3%) patients who received KOVANAZE, but no patients who received placebo, developed nasal ulcers that were present on exam the same day as KOVANAZE dosing. Three (2%) KOVANAZE and 2 (2%) placebo-treated patients without nasal ulcerations on the day of KOVANAZE or placebo dosing were observed to have nasal ulcerations at the next day follow-up visit.
 

     Less Common Adverse Reactions in Phase 3 Clinical Trials Adult Dental Patients and Pediatric Dental Patients Weighing 40 kg or More  



 Dysphagia (i.e., the sensation of difficult swallowing) is a notable adverse reaction reported in Phase 3 trials, occurring in 1.15% of patients.



   For medical advice about adverse reactions, contact your medical professional.  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact St. Renatus, LLC at 800-865-4925 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch/  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:    Hypertension and Thyroid Disease  : Shown to increase blood pressure in some clinical trial patients. Monitor blood pressure. Use in patients with inadequately controlled hypertension or active thyroid disease is not advised (  5.1  ).



  Epistaxis  : Use is not recommended in patients with a history of frequent nose bleeds (&gt;=5 per month). If a decision to use is made, monitor these patients carefully (  5.2  ).



  Dysphagia  : Carefully monitor patients for dysphagia (  5.3  ).



  Methemoglobinemia  : May cause methemoglobinemia, particularly when used with methemoglobin-inducing agents. Use in patients with history of congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia not advised. If central cyanosis unresponsive to oxygen therapy occurs, suspect methemoglobinemia, confirm diagnosis with CO-oximetry, and treat with a standard clinical regimen (  5.4  ).



  Anaphylactic Reactions  : Seek emergency help if an anaphylactic reaction occurs (  5.5  ).



 



   5.1 Risk of Hypertension



  KOVANAZE has not been studied in Phase 3 trials in adult dental patients with blood pressure greater than 150/100 or in those with inadequately controlled active thyroid disease. KOVANAZE has been shown to increase blood pressure in some patients in clinical trials. Monitor patients for increased blood pressure. Use in patients with uncontrolled hypertension or inadequately controlled active thyroid disease of any type is not advised [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  .



    5.2 Epistaxis



  In clinical trials, epistaxis occurred more frequently with KOVANAZE than placebo. Either do not use KOVANAZE in patients with a history of frequent nose bleeds (&gt;= 5 per month) or monitor patients with frequent nose bleeds more carefully if KOVANAZE is used. [see Adverse Reactions (    6.1   )]  .



    5.3 Dysphagia



  In clinical trials, dysphagia occurred more frequently with KOVANAZE than placebo. Carefully monitor patients for this adverse reaction.



    5.4 Methemoglobinemia



  Tetracaine may cause methemoglobinemia, particularly in conjunction with methemoglobin-inducing agents. Based on the literature, patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency or congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia are more susceptible to drug-induced methemoglobinemia. Use of KOVANAZE in patients with a history of congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia is not advised.



 Patients taking concomitant drugs associated with drug-induced methemoglobinemia, such as sulfonamides, acetaminophen, acetanilide, aniline dyes, benzocaine, chloroquine, dapsone, naphthalene, nitrates and nitrites, nitrofurantoin, nitroglycerin, nitroprusside, pamaquine, p  -aminosalicylic acid, phenacetin, phenobarbital, phenytoin, primaquine, and quinine, may be at greater risk for developing methemoglobinemia.



 Initial signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia (which may be delayed for up to several hours following exposure) are characterized by a slate grey cyanosis seen in, e.g., buccal mucous membranes, lips and nail beds. In severe cases, symptoms may include central cyanosis, headache, lethargy, dizziness, fatigue, syncope, dyspnea, CNS depression, seizures, dysrythmia and shock. Methemoglobinemia should be considered if central cyanosis unresponsive to oxygen therapy occurs, especially if methemoglobinemia-inducing agents have been used. Calculated oxygen saturation and pulse oximetry are inaccurate in the identification of methemoglobinemia. Confirm diagnosis by measuring methemoglobin level with co-oximetry. Normally, methemoglobinemia levels are &lt;1%, and cyanosis may not be evident until a level of at least 10% is present.



 Treat clinically significant symptoms of methemoglobinemia with a standard clinical regimen such as a slow intravenous infusion of methylene blue at a dosage of 1-2 mg/kg given over a 5 minute period.



    5.5 Anaphylactic Reactions



  Allergic or anaphylactic reactions have been associated with tetracaine, and may occur with other components of KOVANAZE. They are characterized by urticaria, angioedema, bronchospasm, and shock. If an allergic reaction occurs, seek emergency help immediately.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
