<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kuvan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6.  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=4%) in patients treated with Kuvan are headache, rhinorrhea, pharyngolaryngeal pain, diarrhea, vomiting, cough, and nasal congestion (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact BioMarin Pharmaceutical Inc. at 1-866-906-6100, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch        .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. 



   PKU Clinical Studies  



 The safety of Kuvan was evaluated in 6 clinical studies in patients with PKU (aged 1 month to 50 years)  [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  . 



 In Studies1-4 (controlled and uncontrolled studies), 579 patients with PKU aged 4 to 49 years received Kuvan in doses ranging from 5 to 20 mg/kg per day for lengths of treatment ranging from 1 to 164 weeks. The patient population was evenly distributed in gender, and approximately 95% of patients were Caucasian.  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=4% of patients) were headache, rhinorrhea, pharyngolaryngeal pain, diarrhea, vomiting, cough, and nasal congestion.



 The data described in Table 3 reflect exposure of 74 patients with PKU to Kuvan at doses of 10 to 20 mg/kg per day for 6 to 10 weeks in two double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trials (Studies 2 and 4).



 Table 3 enumerates adverse reactions occurring in at least 4% of patients treated with Kuvan in the double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trials described above.



   Table 3: Summary of Adverse Reactions  Occurring in &gt;=4% of Patients in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Studies with Kuvan  




  MedDRA Preferred Term    Treatment        
  Kuvan  (N=74)    Placebo  (N=59)    
                   No. Patients (%)    No. Patients (%)    
  Headache         11 (15)          8 (14)           
  Rhinorrhea       8 (11)           0                
  Pharyngolaryngeal pain    7(10)            1 (2)            
  Diarrhea         6 (8)            3 (5)            
  Vomiting         6 (8)            4 (7)            
  Cough            5 (7)            3 (5)            
  Nasal congestion    3 (4)            0                
         In open-label, uncontrolled clinical trials (Studies 1 and 3)  all patients received Kuvan in doses of 5 to 20 mg/kg per day, adverse reactions were similar in type and frequency to those reported in the double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trials  [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  .
 

 In Study 5, 65 pediatric patients with PKU aged 1 month to 6 years received Kuvan 20 mg/kg per day for 6 months.  Adverse reactions in these patients were similar in frequency and type as those seen in other Kuvan clinical trials except for an increased incidence of low Phe levels. Twenty-five percent (16 out of 65) of patients developed Phe levels below normal for age  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ), Pediatric Use (  8.4  ), and Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  .



 In Study 6, a long term, open-label, extension study of 111 patients aged 4 to 50 years, receiving Kuvan in doses ranging from 5 to 20 mg/kg per day, adverse reactions were similar in type and frequency to those reported in the previous clinical studies.  Fifty-five patients received Kuvan both as dissolved and intact tablets.  There were no notable differences in the incidence or severity of adverse reactions between the two methods of administration.     The mean (+/- SD) exposure to sapropterin for the entire study population was 659 +/- 221 days (maximum 953 days).



   Safety Experience from Clinical Studies for Non-PKU Indications  



 Approximately 800 healthy volunteers and patients with disorders other than PKU, some of whom had underlying neurologic disorders or cardiovascular disease, have been administered a different formulation of the same active ingredient (sapropterin) in approximately 19 controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials. In these clinical trials, subjects were administered sapropterin at doses ranging from 1 to 100 mg/kg per day for lengths of exposure from 1 day to 2 years. Serious and severe adverse reactions (regardless of causality) during sapropterin administration were convulsions, exacerbation of convulsions  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  , dizziness, gastrointestinal bleeding, post-procedural bleeding, headache, irritability, myocardial infarction, overstimulation, and respiratory failure. Common adverse reactions were headache, peripheral edema, arthralgia, polyuria, agitation, dizziness, nausea, pharyngitis, abdominal pain, upper abdominal pain, and upper respiratory tract infection.



   6.2  Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Kuvan. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish causal relationship to drug exposure.



 In worldwide marketing experience, the most common adverse reactions due to Kuvan are oropharyngeal pain, pharyngitis, esophageal pain, gastritis, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting. Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis and rash have been reported. Most hypersensitivity reactions occurred within several days of initiating treatment. Two cases of hyperactivity have been reported, including one case in a patient who received an accidental overdose of Kuvan  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,  5.11  )].   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5.  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis have occurred (  5.1  ). 
 *  Gastritis was reported in clinical trials. Monitor patients for signs of gastritis (  5.2  ). 
 *  Children younger than 7 years treated with Kuvan doses of 20 mg/kg per day are at increased risk for low levels of blood Phe compared with children 7 years and older (  5.3  ). 
 *  Monitor blood Phe levels during treatment to ensure adequate blood Phe control (  5.4  ). 
 *  Identify non-responders to Kuvan treatment: Not all patients with PKU respond to treatment with Kuvan (  5.5  ). 
 *  Treat all patients with a Phe-restricted diet: The initiation of Kuvan therapy does not eliminate the need for ongoing dietary management (  5.6  ). 
 *  Monitor liver function tests in patients with liver impairment who are receiving Kuvan (  5.7  ). 
 *  Monitor patients when co-administering Kuvan with medications known to inhibit folate metabolism, or with levodopa. Monitor patients for hypotension when co-administering Kuvan with medications known to affect nitric oxide-mediated vasorelaxation (  5.8  ,  5.9  ,  5.10  ). 
 *  There have been post-marketing reports of hyperactivity with administration of Kuvan. Monitor patients for hyperactivity (  5.11  ). 
    
 

   5.1  Hypersensitivity Reactions Including Anaphylaxis



  Kuvan is not recommended in patients with a history of anaphylaxis to Kuvan. Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis and rash, have occurred [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )].  Signs of anaphylaxis include wheezing, dyspnea, coughing, hypotension, flushing, nausea, and rash. Discontinue treatment with Kuvan in patients who experience anaphylaxis and initiate appropriate medical treatment. Continue dietary Phe restrictions in patients who experience anaphylaxis.



    5.2 Gastritis



  During clinical studies, gastritis was reported as a serious adverse reaction. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of gastritis.



    5.3 Hypophenylalaninemia



  In clinical trials, some patients have experienced low blood Phe levels. Children younger than 7 years treated with Kuvan doses of 20 mg/kg per day are at increased risk for low levels of blood Phe compared with patients 7 years and older [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )].  



    5.4 Monitor Blood Phe Levels During Treatment



  Treatment with Kuvan should be directed by physicians knowledgeable in the management of PKU. Prolonged elevations in blood Phe levels in patients with PKU can result in severe neurologic damage, including severe mental retardation, microcephaly, delayed speech, seizures, and behavioral abnormalities. Conversely, prolonged levels of blood Phe that are too low have been associated with catabolism and protein breakdown. Active management of dietary Phe intake while taking Kuvan is required to ensure adequate Phe control and nutritional balance. Monitor blood Phe levels during treatment to ensure adequate blood Phe level control. Frequent blood monitoring is recommended in the pediatric population [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



    5.5 Identify Non-Responders to Kuvan Treatment



  Not all patients with PKU respond to treatment with Kuvan. In two clinical trials at a dose of 20 mg/kg per day, 56% to 75% of pediatric PKU patients responded to treatment with Kuvan, and in one clinical trial at a dose of 10 mg/kg per day, 20% of adult and pediatric PKU patients responded to treatment with Kuvan [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  . 



 Response to treatment cannot be pre-determined by laboratory testing (e.g., molecular testing), and can only be determined by a therapeutic trial of Kuvan [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )]  .



    5.6 Treat All Patients with  a Phe-restricted Diet



  All patients with PKU who are being treated with Kuvan should also be treated with a Phe-restricted diet.



    5.7 Monitor Patients with Hepatic Impairment



  Patients with liver impairment have not been evaluated in clinical trials with Kuvan. Monitor liver function tests in patients with liver impairment who are receiving Kuvan because hepatic damage has been associated with impaired Phe metabolism.



    5.8 Monitor Patients when Co-administering Kuvan and Medications Known to Inhibit Folate Metabolism



  Co-administering Kuvan with drugs known to affect folate metabolism (e.g., methotrexate) and their derivatives may require more frequent monitoring of blood Phe levels because these drugs can decrease endogenous BH4 levels by inhibiting the enzyme dihydropteridine reductase (DHPR).



    5.9 Monitor Patients for Hypotension when Co-administering Kuvan and Drugs Known to Affect Nitric Oxide-Mediated Vasorelaxation



  Monitor blood pressure when administering Kuvan with drugs that affect nitric oxide-mediated vasorelaxation (e.g., PDE-5 inhibitors such as sildenafil, vardenafil, or tadalafil), because both sapropterin dihydrochloride and PDE-5 inhibitors may induce vasorelaxation. The additive effect of sapropterin and PDE-5 inhibitor co-administration could lead to a reduction in blood pressure; however, the combined use of these medications has not been evaluated in humans. In animal studies, orally administered Kuvan in combination with a PDE-5 inhibitor had no effect on blood pressure.



    5.10 Monitor Patients when Co-administering Kuvan and Levodopa



  Caution should be used with the administration of Kuvan to patients who are receiving levodopa. In a 10-year post-marketing safety surveillance program for a non-PKU indication using another formulation of the same active ingredient (sapropterin), 3 patients with underlying neurologic disorders experienced convulsions, exacerbation of convulsions, over-stimulation, or irritability during co-administration of levodopa and sapropterin. Monitor for change in neurologic status.



    5.11 Monitor Patients for Hyperactivity



  In the post-marketing safety surveillance program for PKU, 2 patients experienced hyperactivity with administration of Kuvan. Monitor patients for hyperactivity.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
