<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kybella" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;20% of subjects) include injection site edema/swelling, hematoma, pain, numbness, erythema and induration. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    Kythera Biopharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-844-KYTHERA (1-844-598-4372)    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In two double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trials 513 subjects were treated with KYBELLA and 506 subjects were treated with placebo. The population was 19-65 years old, 85% were women, 87% Caucasian, 8% African American. At baseline the population had a mean BMI of 29 kg/m  2  , moderate to severe submental convexity (graded as 2 or 3 on a 0 to 4 scale) and without excessive skin laxity. Subjects received up to 6 treatments at least 1 month apart and were followed for up to 6 months after the last received treatment.



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions are listed below (  Table 1  ).



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions in the Pooled Trials 1 and 2a 
   a  Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 2% KYBELLA treated subjects and at greater incidence than placebo  b  Marginal mandibular nerve paresis   
  
      Adverse reactions      KYBELLA  (N=513)  n (%)    Placebo  (N=506)  n (%)    
  Injection site reactions    492 (96%)          411 (81%)             
           edema/swelling    448 (87%)          218 (43%)             
           hematoma/bruising    368 (72%)          353 (70%)             
            pain             356 (70%)          160 (32%)             
           numbness          341 (66%)          29 (6%)               
           erythema          136 (27%)          91 (18%)              
           induration        120 (23%)          13 (3%)               
           paresthesia       70 (14%)           20 (4%)               
           nodule            68 (13%)           14 (3%)               
           pruritus          64 (12%)           30 (6%)               
           skin tightness    24 (5%)            6 (1%)                
           site warmth       22 (4%)            8 (2%)                
           nerve injury b    20 (4 %)           1 (&lt;1%)               
  Headache                   41 (8%)            20 (4%)               
  Oropharyngeal pain         15 (3%)            7 (1%)                
  Hypertension               13 (3%)            7 (1%)                
  Nausea                     12 (2%)            3 (1%)                
  Dysphagia                  10 (2%)            1 (&lt;1%)               
         Other adverse reactions associated with the use of KYBELLA include: injection site hemorrhage, injection site discoloration, pre-syncope/syncope, lymphadenopathy, injection site urticaria and neck pain.
 

 Adverse reactions that lasted more than 30 days and occurred in more than 10% of subjects were injection site numbness (42%), injection site edema/swelling (20%), injection site pain (16%), and injection site induration (13%).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Marginal mandibular nerve (MMN) injury: Follow injection technique to avoid this injury. (  2.3  ,  5.1  ) 
 *    Dysphagia may occur with KYBELLA use. Use in patients with pre-existing dysphagia may exacerbate the condition. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Submental hematoma/bruising occurs frequently after KYBELLA administration. Use with caution in patients who are being treated with antiplatelet or anticoagulant therapy or have coagulation abnormalities. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Avoid injecting in proximity to vulnerable anatomic structures due to the increased risk of tissue damage. (  2.3  ,  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Marginal mandibular nerve injury



  Cases of marginal mandibular nerve injury, manifested as an asymmetric smile or facial muscle weakness (paresis), were reported during clinical trials. To avoid the potential for nerve injury, KYBELLA should not be injected into or in close proximity to the marginal mandibular branch of the facial nerve. All marginal mandibular nerve injuries reported from the trials resolved spontaneously (range 1-298 days, median 44 days).



    5.2 Dysphagia



  Difficulty swallowing (dysphagia) occurred in clinical trials in the setting of administration site reactions, e.g., pain, swelling, and induration of the submental area. Cases of dysphagia spontaneously resolved (range 1-81 days, median 3 days).



 Subjects with current or prior history of dysphagia were excluded from clinical trials. Avoid use of KYBELLA in these patients as current or prior history of dysphagia may exacerbate the condition.



    5.3 Injection site hematoma/bruising



  In clinical trials, 72% of subjects treated with KYBELLA experienced injection site hematoma/bruising [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  .



 KYBELLA should be used with caution in patients with bleeding abnormalities or who are currently being treated with antiplatelet or anticoagulant therapy as excessive bleeding or bruising in the treatment area may occur.



    5.4 Risk of injecting in proximity to vulnerable anatomic structures



  To avoid potential tissue damage, KYBELLA should not be injected into or in close proximity (1-1.5 cm) to salivary glands, lymph nodes and muscles.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
