<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="kyleena" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious or otherwise important adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Ectopic Pregnancy [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Intrauterine Pregnancy [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    Group A Streptococcal Sepsis (GAS) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    Pelvic Inflammatory Disease [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    Perforation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *    Expulsion [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  ]  
 *    Ovarian Cysts [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *    Bleeding Pattern Alterations [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions reported (&gt;= 5% users) were vulvovaginitis, ovarian cysts, abdominal pain/pelvic pain, headache/migraine, acne/seborrhea, dysmenorrhea/uterine spasm, breast pain/breast discomfort, and increased bleeding. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-888-842-2937    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure of 1,697 healthy 18- to 41-year-old women (mean age 27.8 +/- 5.2 years) to Kyleena. These data come from two multi-center contraceptive trials: A phase 2 study with a 3-year duration was conducted in Europe. The Kyleena population was generally healthy, 21 to 41-year old women; 217 subjects were exposed to Kyleena for one year and 174 completed three years. The data in this trial cover approximately 8,000 cycles of exposure. A phase 3 study with a 3-year duration and an optional extension of Kyleena use up to 5 years was conducted in the US, Canada, Europe, and Latin America. The population was generally healthy, 18 to 35-year old women. A total of 1,208 subjects were exposed to Kyleena for one year; 707 women entered to the optional extension phase after 3 years and 550 completed five years. The data in this trial cover more than 60,000 cycles. In total for both studies, 1,425 subjects were exposed for 1 year, and 550 subjects completed 5 years of use. Of the total of 1,697 subjects, 563 were from the US and 1,134 were from Europe and Latin America; 623 (36.7%) were nulliparous (mean age 24.6 +/- 4.5years) and 1,074 (63.3%) were parous (mean age 29.7 +/- 4.7 years). Most women who received Kyleena were Caucasian (83.0%) or Black/African American (4.4%); 9.4% of women were of Hispanic ethnicity. The clinical trials had no upper or lower weight or BMI limit. Mean BMI of Kyleena subjects was 25.2 kg/m  2  (range 15.2 - 57.6 kg/m2); 16.3% had a BMI &gt;= 30 kg/m2, and 2.0% had a BMI &gt;= 40 kg/m  2  . The data in both trials cover approximately 68.000 28-day cycles of Kyleena exposure. The frequencies of reported adverse drug reactions represent crude incidences.



 Most common adverse reactions (occurring in &gt;=5% users) were vulvovaginitis (24.3%), ovarian cyst (22.2%), abdominal pain/pelvic pain (20.7%), headache/migraine (15.4%), acne/seborrhea (15.4%), dysmenorrhea/uterine spasm (10.0%), breast pain/breast discomfort (9.7%), and increased bleeding (7.9%).



 In the studies, 22.1% discontinued prematurely due to an adverse reaction. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were increased bleeding (4.5%), abdominal pain/pelvic pain (4.2%), device expulsion (2.7%), acne/seborrhea (2.2%), dysmenorrhea/uterine spasm (1.3%).



 Other common adverse reactions (occurring in &gt;=1% users) by System Organ Class (SOC): The frequencies of adverse reactions observed in clinical trials are summarized in Table 3 by SOC (presented as crude incidences).



   Table 3: Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of Kyleena users in clinical trials by SOC  




   System Organ Class              Adverse Reaction                               Incidence (%)(N=1,697)     
  
  Reproductive System and Breast Disorders    Vulvovaginitis                                 24.3                      
  Ovarian cysta                   22.2                                           
  Dysmenorrhea/uterine spasm      8.0/2.4                                        
  Increased bleedingb             7.9                                            
  Breast pain/discomfort          7.1/3.5                                        
  Genital discharge               4.5                                            
  Device expulsion (complete and partial)    3.5                                            
  Upper genital tract infection    1.5                                            
  Gastrointestinal Disorders      Abdominal pain/pelvic pain                     13.3/8.2                  
  Nausea                          4.7                                            
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    Acne/Seborrhoea                                14.1/1.8                  
  Alopecia                        1.0                                            
  Nervous System Disorders        Headache/Migraine                              12.9/3.3                  
  Psychiatric Disorders           Depression/ Depressed mood                     4.3/0.2                   
           a  Ovarian cysts were reported as AEs if they were abnormal, non-functional cysts and/or had a diameter &gt;3 cm on ultrasound examination
 

   b  Not all bleeding alterations were captured as adverse reactions  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  .



 In the clinical trials, serious adverse reactions included: ectopic pregnancy; ruptured ectopic pregnancy; pelvic inflammatory disease; missed abortion; incomplete spontaneous abortion; spontaneous abortions; uterine perforation; embedded device (myometrial perforation); ovarian cyst; and abdominal pain.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of LNG-releasing IUSs. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *    Arterial thrombotic and venous thromboembolic events, including cases of pulmonary emboli, deep vein thrombosis and stroke 
 *    Device breakage 
 *    Hypersensitivity (including rash, urticaria, and angioedema) 
 *    Increased blood pressure 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Remove Kyleena if pregnancy occurs with Kyleena in place. If pregnancy occurs, there is increased risk of ectopic pregnancy including loss of fertility, pregnancy loss, septic abortion (including septicemia, shock and death), and premature labor and delivery. (  5.1  ,  5.2  ) 
 *    Group A streptococcal infection has been reported; strict aseptic technique is essential during insertion. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Before using Kyleena, consider the risks of PID. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Perforation may occur and may reduce contraceptive effectiveness. Risk is increased if inserted in lactating women and may be increased if inserted in women with fixed retroverted uteri and postpartum. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Partial or complete expulsion may occur. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Evaluate persistent enlarged ovarian follicles or ovarian cysts. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Bleeding patterns become altered, may remain irregular and amenorrhea may ensue. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Kyleena can be safely scanned with MRI only under certain conditions. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Ectopic Pregnancy



  Evaluate women for ectopic pregnancy if they become pregnant with Kyleena in place because the likelihood of a pregnancy being ectopic is increased with Kyleena. Approximately one-half of pregnancies that occur with Kyleena in place are likely to be ectopic. Also consider the possibility of ectopic pregnancy in the case of lower abdominal pain, especially in association with missed menses or if an amenorrheic woman starts bleeding.



 The incidence of ectopic pregnancy in clinical trials with Kyleena, which excluded women with a history of ectopic pregnancy, was approximately 0.2% per year. The risk of ectopic pregnancy in women who have a history of ectopic pregnancy and use Kyleena is unknown. Women with a previous history of ectopic pregnancy, tubal surgery or pelvic infection carry a higher risk of ectopic pregnancy. Ectopic pregnancy may result in loss of fertility.



    5.2 Risks with Intrauterine Pregnancy



  If pregnancy occurs while using Kyleena, remove Kyleena because leaving it in place may increase the risk of spontaneous abortion and preterm labor. Removal of Kyleena or probing of the uterus may also result in spontaneous abortion. In the event of an intrauterine pregnancy with Kyleena, consider the following:



    Septic abortion



  In patients becoming pregnant with an IUS in place, septic abortion - with septicemia, septic shock, and death - may occur.



    Continuation of pregnancy



  If a woman becomes pregnant with Kyleena in place and if Kyleena cannot be removed or the woman chooses not to have it removed, warn her that failure to remove Kyleena increases the risk of miscarriage, sepsis, premature labor and premature delivery. Follow her pregnancy closely and advise her to report immediately any symptom that suggests complications of the pregnancy.



    5.3 Sepsis



  Severe infection or sepsis, including Group A streptococcal sepsis (GAS), have been reported following insertion of a LNG-releasing IUS. In some cases, severe pain occurred within hours of insertion followed by sepsis within days. Because death from GAS is more likely if treatment is delayed, it is important to be aware of these rare but serious infections. Aseptic technique during insertion of Kyleena is essential in order to minimize serious infections such as GAS.



    5.4 Pelvic Infection



  Promptly examine users with complaints of lower abdominal or pelvic pain, odorous discharge, unexplained bleeding, fever, genital lesions or sores. Remove Kyleena in cases of recurrent endometritis or pelvic inflammatory disease, or if an acute pelvic infection is severe or does not respond to treatment.



    Pelvic Inflammatory Disease (PID)



  Kyleena is contraindicated in the presence of known or suspected PID or in women with a history of PID unless there has been a subsequent intrauterine pregnancy [see Contraindications (4)]  . IUDs have been associated with an increased risk of PID, most likely due to organisms being introduced into the uterus during insertion.  1  In clinical trials, PID was observed in 0.5% of women overall and occurred more frequently within the first year and most often within the first month after insertion of Kyleena.



    Women at increased risk for PID



  PID is often associated with a sexually transmitted infection (STI), and Kyleena does not protect against STI. The risk of PID is greater for women who have multiple sexual partners, and also for women whose sexual partner(s) have multiple sexual partners. Women who have had PID are at increased risk for a recurrence or re-infection. In particular, ascertain whether the woman is at increased risk of infection (for example, leukemia, acquired immune deficiency syndrome [AIDS], intravenous drug abuse).



    Subclinical PID



  PID may be asymptomatic but still result in tubal damage and its sequelae.



    Treatment of PID



  Following a diagnosis of PID, or suspected PID, bacteriologic specimens should be obtained and antibiotic therapy should be initiated promptly. Removal of Kyleena after initiation of antibiotic therapy is usually appropriate.  2  



    Actinomycosis



  Actinomycosis has been associated with IUDs Remove Kyleena from symptomatic women and treat with antibiotics. The significance of actinomyces-like organisms on Pap smear in an asymptomatic IUD user is unknown, and so this finding alone does not always require Kyleena removal and treatment. When possible, confirm a Pap smear diagnosis with cultures.



    5.5 Perforation



  Perforation (total or partial, including penetration/embedment of Kyleena in the uterine wall or cervix) may occur most often during insertion, although the perforation may not be detected until sometime later. Perforation may reduce contraceptive efficacy and result in pregnancy. The incidence of perforation during clinical trials was &lt; 0.1%.



 If perforation occurs, locate and remove Kyleena. Surgery may be required. Delayed detection or removal of Kyleena in case of perforation may result in migration outside the uterine cavity, adhesions, peritonitis, intestinal perforations, intestinal obstruction, abscesses and erosion of adjacent viscera.



 Clinical trials with Kyleena excluded breast-feeding women. An analysis from a large postmarketing safety study with other IUDs shows an increased risk of perforation in lactating women. The risk of perforation may be increased if Kyleena is inserted when the uterus is fixed retroverted or not completely involuted during the postpartum period. Delay Kyleena insertion a minimum of six weeks or until involution is complete following a delivery or a second trimester abortion.



    5.6 Expulsion



  Partial or complete expulsion of Kyleena may occur resulting in the loss of contraceptive protection. Expulsion may be associated with symptoms of bleeding or pain, or it may be asymptomatic and go unnoticed. Kyleena typically decreases menstrual bleeding over time; therefore, an increase of menstrual bleeding may be indicative of an expulsion. The risk of expulsion may be increased when the uterus is not completely involuted. In clinical trials, a 5-year expulsion rate of 3.5% (59 out of 1,690 subjects) was reported.



 Delay Kyleena insertion a minimum of six weeks or until uterine involution is complete following a delivery or a second trimester abortion. Remove a partially expelled Kyleena. If expulsion has occurred, Kyleena may be replaced within 7 days after the onset of a menstrual period after pregnancy has been ruled out.



    5.7 Ovarian Cysts



  Because the contraceptive effect of Kyleena is mainly due to its local effects within the uterus, ovulatory cycles with follicular rupture usually occur in women of fertile age using Kyleena. Ovarian cysts (reported as adverse reactions if they were abnormal, non-functional cysts and/or had a diameter &gt;3 cm on ultrasound examination) were reported at least once over the course of clinical trials in 22% of women using Kyleena, and 0.6% of subjects discontinued because of an ovarian cyst. Most ovarian cysts are asymptomatic, although some may be accompanied by pelvic pain or dyspareunia. In most cases the ovarian cysts disappear spontaneously during two to three months observation. Evaluate persistent ovarian cysts. Surgical intervention is not usually required.



    5.8 Bleeding Pattern Alterations



  Kyleena can alter the bleeding pattern and result in spotting, irregular bleeding, heavy bleeding, oligomenorrhea and amenorrhea. During the first 3-6 months of Kyleena use, the number of bleeding and spotting days may be higher and bleeding patterns may be irregular. Thereafter, the number of bleeding and spotting days usually decreases but bleeding may remain irregular.



 In Kyleena clinical trials, amenorrhea developed by the end of the first year of use in approximately 12% of Kyleena users. A total of 81 subjects out of 1,697 (4.8%) discontinued due to uterine bleeding complaints. Table 1 shows the bleeding patterns as documented in the Kyleena clinical trials based on 90-day reference periods. Table 2 shows the number of bleeding and spotting days based on 28-day cycle equivalents.



  Table 1: Bleeding Patterns Reported with Kyleena in Contraception Studies (by 90-day reference periods)  




  Kyleena               First 90 daysN=1,566    Second 90 daysN=1,511    End of year 1N=1,371    End of year 3N=975    End of year 5  N=530    
  Amenorrhea1           &lt; 1%            5%                  12%                20%              23%              
  Infrequent bleeding2    10%             20%                 26%                26%              26%              
  Frequent bleeding3    25%             10%                 4%                 2%               2%               
  Prolonged bleeding4    57%             14%                 6%                 2%               1%               
  Irregular bleeding5    43%             25%                 17%                10%              9%               
              1  Defined as subjects with no bleeding/spotting throughout the 90-day reference period
 

   2  Defined as subjects with 1 or 2 bleeding/spotting episodes in the 90-day reference period



   3  Defined as subjects with more than 5 bleeding/spotting episodes in the 90-day reference period



   4  Defined as subjects with bleeding/spotting episodes lasting more than 14 days in the 90-day reference period. Subjects with prolonged bleeding may also be included in one of the other categories (excluding amenorrhea)



   5  Defined as subjects with 3 to 5 bleeding/spotting episodes and less than 3 bleeding/spotting-free intervals of 14 or more days



  Table 2:   Mean number of Bleeding and Spotting Days per 28-day Cycle Equivalent  




  28-day Cycle Equivalent    Cycle 1  N=1,619    Cycle 4  N=1,575    Cycle 7  N=1,518    Cycle 13  N=1,394    Cycle 39  N=913    Cycle 65  N=322    
  Days on treatment    1-28     85-112    169-196    337-364    1065-1092    1793-1820    
                                                                                                                                
                                                                                                                                
                                                                                                                                
                    Mean(SD)    Mean(SD)    Mean(SD)    Mean(SD)    Mean(SD)    Mean(SD)    
  Number of bleeding days    7.2(5.9)    3.2(3.6)    2.2(3.0)    1.5(2.4)    1.0(2.0)    0.9(1.8)    
  Number of spotting days    8.6(6.0)    4.6(4.4)    3.5(3.4)    2.9(3.0)    2.2(2.6)    2.1(2.4)    
                   Because irregular bleeding/spotting is common during the first months of Kyleena use, exclude endometrial pathology (polyps or cancer) prior to the insertion of Kyleena in women with persistent or uncharacteristic bleeding. If a significant change in bleeding develops during prolonged use, take appropriate diagnostic measures to rule out endometrial pathology .  Consider the possibility of pregnancy if menstruation does not occur within six weeks of the onset of a previous menstruation. Once pregnancy has been excluded, repeated pregnancy tests are generally not necessary in amenorrheic women unless indicated, for example, by other signs of pregnancy or by pelvic pain.
 

    5.9 Breast Cancer



  Women who currently have or have had breast cancer, or have a suspicion of breast cancer, should not use hormonal contraception, including Kyleena, because some breast cancers are hormone-sensitive [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



 Spontaneous reports of breast cancer have been received during postmarketing experience with another LNG-releasing IUS. Observational studies of the risk of breast cancer with use of a LNG-releasing IUS do not provide conclusive evidence of increased risk.



    5.10 Clinical Considerations for Use and Removal



  Use Kyleena with caution after careful assessment if any of the following conditions exist, and consider removal of the system if any of them arise during use:



 *    Coagulopathy or use of anticoagulants 
 *    Migraine, focal migraine with asymmetrical visual loss or other symptoms indicating transient cerebral ischemia 
 *    Exceptionally severe headache 
 *    Marked increase of blood pressure 
 *    Severe arterial disease such as stroke or myocardial infarction 
    In addition, consider removing Kyleena if any of the following conditions arise during use:
 

 *    Uterine or cervical malignancy 
 *    Jaundice 
    If the threads are not visible or are significantly shortened, they may have broken or retracted into the cervical canal or uterus. Consider the possibility that the system may have been displaced, (for example, expelled or perforated the uterus) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ,  5.6  )].  Exclude pregnancy and verify the location of Kyleena, for example, by sonography, X-ray, or by gentle exploration of the cervical canal with a suitable instrument. If Kyleena is displaced, remove it. A new Kyleena may be inserted at that time or during the next menses if it is certain that conception has not occurred. If Kyleena is in place with no evidence of perforation, no intervention is indicated.
 

    5.11 Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) Safety Information



  Non-clinical testing has demonstrated that Kyleena is MR Conditional. A patient with Kyleena can be safely scanned in an MR system meeting the following conditions:



 *    Static magnetic field of 3.0 T or less 
 *    Maximum spatial field gradient of 36,000 gauss/cm (360 T/m) 
 *    Maximum MR system reported, whole body averaged specific absorption rate (SAR) of 4W/kg (First Level Controlled Operating Mode) 
    Under the scan conditions defined above, the Kyleena IUS is expected to produce a maximum temperature rise of less than 2 degrees C after 15 minutes of continuous scanning.
 

 In non-clinical testing, the image artifact caused by the IUS extended up to 5 mm from the IUS when imaged with a gradient echo pulse sequence and a 3.0 T MRI system.



  MRI   
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
