<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lamisil1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common (&gt;3% in patients treated with Lamisil Oral Granules) reported adverse events include: nasopharyngitis, headache, pyrexia, cough, vomiting, upper respiratory tract infection, nausea, upper abdominal pain, and diarrhea. (  6.1  )     



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Lamisil (terbinafine hydrochloride) Oral Granules  



 The data described below reflect exposure to terbinafine including 1042 subjects exposed for a median of 42 days. Lamisil Oral Granules was studied in 2 active-controlled trials (n=1042). The population was children aged 4 to 12 years old, 64% male and 36% female, 21% Caucasian, 47% Black, 32% Other. Baseline disease (dermatophyte) characteristics of subjects included 49% having  T.    tonsurans,  15%  T. violaceum,  15%  M. canis,  2%  M. audouinii,  and 1% others. Subjects received once daily, for 6 weeks, oral doses of Lamisil Oral Granules based on body weight: &lt;25 kg 125 mg/day, 25-35 kg 187.5 mg/day, and &gt;35 kg 250 mg/day.



 Adverse events reported in the 2 trials are listed in the table below.



 Table 2: Adverse Events (&gt;=1%) in the Tinea Capitis Trials 
                  LamisilOral Granules (%)N=1042  Griseofulvin Oral Suspension (%)N=507   
 Nasopharyngitis  10               11                
 Headache         7                8                 
 Pyrexia          7                6                 
 Cough            6                5                 
 Vomiting         5                5                 
 Upper respiratory tract infection  5                5                 
 Upper abdominal pain  4                4                 
 Diarrhea         3                4                 
 Influenza        2                1                 
 Abdominal pain   2                1                 
 Pharyngolaryngeal pain  2                2                 
 Nausea           2                2                 
 Rash             2                2                 
 Rhinorrhea       2                0                 
 Nasal congestion  2                1                 
 Pruritus         1                1                 
 Toothache        1                1                 
         In the pooled pivotal trials, 2% (17/1042) of subjects in the terbinafine group and 2% (6/507) in the griseofulvin group experienced discontinuation of study drug due to adverse events. The most common categories of adverse events causing discontinuation in those exposed to terbinafine included gastrointestinal disorders, skin and subcutaneous disorders, and infections and infestations.
 

 No ophthalmologic safety signal was identified in the pooled pivotal trials. Ophthalmologic assessments included dilated fundoscopy to assess for refractile bodies in the retina, visual acuity assessment, and color vision testing. Of the 940 subjects in the terbinafine group and 471 subjects in the griseofulvin group who completed dilated fundoscopy at posttreatment visits, none of the subjects were found to have refractile bodies of the retina at baseline or end of treatment. For visual acuity, 1% (11/837) of subjects treated with terbinafine and 2% (7/426) of subjects treated with griseofulvin showed a doubling of visual angle after 6 weeks of treatment, while 2% (15/837) treated with terbinafine and 3% (12/426) treated with griseofulvin showed a halving of the visual angle     after 6 weeks of treatment. Of subjects who completed yellow-blue color vision assessment for acquired defects, 5% (13/262) of subjects treated with terbinafine and 6% (8/129) of subjects treated with griseofulvin had color confusion on more than 1 symbol at week 6 than at baseline, while 13% (33/262) of subjects treated with terbinafine and 13% (17/129) of subjects treated with griseofulvin identified more symbols correctly at week 6 than at baseline.



   Lamisil (terbinafine hydrochloride) Tablets  



 Adverse events reported in three US/Canadian placebo-controlled trials included diarrhea (6%), rashes (6%), dyspepsia (4%), nausea (3%), liver abnormalities (3%), pruritus (3%), taste disturbances (3%), abdominal pain (2%), and urticaria (1%).



 Changes in the ocular lens and retina have been reported following the use of Lamisil Tablets     in clinical trials in adult subjects with onychomycosis. The clinical significance of these changes is unknown.



   6.2     Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been identified during postapproval use of oral terbinafine. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  Pancytopenia, agranulocytosis, severe neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]



   Immune system disorders:  Serious hypersensitivity reactions e.g., angioedema and allergic reactions (including anaphylaxis), precipitation and exacerbation of cutaneous and systemic lupus erythematosus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ], serum sickness-like reaction



   Psychiatric disorders:  Anxiety and depressive symptoms independent of taste disturbance have been reported with oral terbinafine use. In some cases, depressive symptoms have been reported to subside with discontinuance of therapy and to recur with reinstitution of therapy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].



   Nervous system disorders:  Cases of taste disturbance, including taste loss, have been reported with the use of oral terbinafine. It can be severe enough to result in decreased food intake, weight loss, anxiety, and depressive symptoms. Cases of smell disturbance, including smell loss, have been reported with the use of oral terbinafine [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2, 5.3)  ]. Cases of paresthesia and hypoesthesia have been reported with the use of oral terbinafine.



   Eye disorders:  Visual field defects, reduced visual acuity



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  Hearing impairment, vertigo, tinnitus



   Vascular disorders:  Vasculitis



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  Pancreatitis, vomiting



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  Cases of liver failure some leading to liver transplant or death [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ], idiosyncratic and symptomatic hepatic injury. Cases of hepatitis, cholestasis, and increased hepatic enzymes [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ] have been seen with the use of oral terbinafine.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Serious skin reactions [e.g., Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, bullous dermatitis, and drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS) syndrome] [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ], acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, psoriasiform eruptions or exacerbation of psoriasis, photosensitivity reactions, hair loss



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  Rhabdomyolysis, arthralgia, myalgia



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  Malaise, fatigue, influenza-like illness, pyrexia



   Investigations:  Altered prothrombin time (prolongation and reduction) in patients concomitantly treated with warfarin and increased blood creatine phosphokinase have been reported
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Liver failure, sometimes leading to death or liver transplant, has occurred with the use of oral terbinafine. Obtain pretreatment serum transaminases. Discontinue Lamisil Oral Granules if liver injury develops. (  5.1  ,  5.8  ) 
 *  Taste disturbance, including taste loss, has been reported with oral terbinafine use. Taste disturbance can be severe, may be prolonged, or may be permanent. Discontinue Lamisil Oral Granules if taste disturbance occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Smell disturbance, including loss of smell, has been reported with the use of oral terbinafine. Smell disturbance may be prolonged or may be permanent. Discontinue Lamisil Oral Granules if smell disturbance occurs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Depressive symptoms have been reported with oral terbinafine use. Prescribers should be alert to the development of depressive symptoms. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Severe neutropenia has been reported. If the neutrophil count is &lt; 1000 cells/mm  3  , Lamisil Oral Granules should be discontinued. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, bullous dermatitis, and drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS) syndrome have been reported with oral terbinafine use. If signs or symptoms of drug reaction occur, discontinue Lamisil Oral Granules. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Hepatotoxicity



  Cases of liver failure, some leading to liver transplant or death, have occurred with the use of oral terbinafine during postmarketing experience in individuals with and without preexisting liver disease. In the majority of liver cases reported in association with oral terbinafine use, the patients had serious underlying systemic conditions. The severity of hepatic events and/or their outcome may be worse in patients with active or chronic liver disease. Treatment with Lamisil Oral Granules should be discontinued if biochemical or clinical evidence of liver injury develops.



 Lamisil Oral Granules are not recommended for patients with chronic or active liver disease. Before prescribing Lamisil Oral Granules, liver function tests should be performed since hepatotoxicity may occur in patients with and without pre-existing liver disease. Periodic monitoring of liver function tests is recommended. Lamisil Oral Granules should be immediately discontinued in case of elevation of liver function tests. Patients prescribed Lamisil Oral Granules and/or their guardians should be warned to report immediately to their physician any symptoms of persistent nausea, anorexia, fatigue, vomiting, right upper abdominal pain or jaundice, dark urine, or pale stools. Patients with these symptoms should discontinue taking Lamisil Oral Granules, and the patient's liver function should be immediately evaluated.



    5.2     Taste Disturbance Including Loss of Taste



  Taste disturbance, including taste loss, has been reported with the use of oral terbinafine. It can be severe enough to result in decreased food intake, weight loss, anxiety, and depressive symptoms. Taste disturbance may resolve within several weeks after discontinuation of treatment, but may be prolonged (greater than 1 year), or may be permanent. If symptoms of a taste disturbance occur, Lamisil Oral Granules should be discontinued.



    5.3     Smell Disturbance Including Loss of Smell



  Smell disturbance, including loss of smell, has been reported with the use of oral terbinafine. Smell disturbance may resolve after discontinuation of treatment, but may be prolonged (greater than one year), or may be permanent. If symptoms of a smell disturbance occur, Lamisil Oral Granules should be discontinued.



    5.4     Depressive Symptoms



  Depressive symptoms have occurred during postmarketing use of oral terbinafine. Prescribers should be alert to the development of depressive symptoms, and patients should be instructed to report depressive symptoms to their physician.



    5.5     Hematologic Effects



  Transient decreases in absolute lymphocyte counts (ALCs) have been observed in controlled clinical trials. In placebo-controlled trials, 8/465 subjects receiving Lamisil Tablets (1.7%) and 3/137 subjects receiving placebo (2.2%) had decreases in ALC to below 1000/mm  3  on 2 or more occasions. In patients with known or suspected immunodeficiency, physicians should consider monitoring complete blood counts if treatment continues for more than 6 weeks. Cases of severe neutropenia have been reported. These were reversible upon discontinuation of oral terbinafine, with or without supportive therapy. If clinical signs and symptoms suggestive of secondary infection occur, a complete blood count should be obtained. If the neutrophil count is &lt;=1000 cells/mm  3  , Lamisil Oral Granules should be discontinued and supportive management started.



    5.6     Serious Skin/Hypersensitivity Reactions



  There have been postmarketing reports of serious skin/hypersensitivity reactions [e.g., Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, bullous dermatitis, and drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS) syndrome] with oral terbinafine. Manifestations of DRESS syndrome may include cutaneous reaction (such as rash or exfoliative dermatitis), eosinophilia, and one or more organ complications such as hepatitis, pneumonitis, nephritis, myocarditis, and pericarditis. If progressive skin rash or signs/symptoms of the above drug reactions occur, treatment with Lamisil Oral Granules should be discontinued.



    5.7     Lupus Erythematosus



  During postmarketing experience, precipitation and exacerbation of cutaneous and systemic lupus erythematosus have been reported in patients taking oral terbinafine. Therapy should be discontinued in patients with clinical signs and symptoms suggestive of lupus erythematosus.



    5.8     Laboratory Monitoring



  Measurement of serum transaminases (ALT and AST) is advised for all patients before taking Lamisil Oral Granules.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
