<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lamictal1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described in more detail in the  Warnings and Precautions  section of the label:



 *    Serious skin rashes [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Multiorgan hypersensitivity reactions and organ failure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Blood dyscrasias [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *    Suicidal behavior and ideation [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *    Aseptic meningitis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
 *    Withdrawal seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  
 *    Status epilepticus [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)]  
 *    Sudden unexplained death in epilepsy [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)]  
   *    Most common adverse reactions with use as adjunctive therapy (treatment difference between LAMICTAL XR and placebo &gt;=4%) were dizziness, tremor/intention tremor, vomiting, and diplopia. (6.1) 
 *    Most common adverse reactions with use as monotherapy were similar to those seen with previous trials conducted with immediate-release lamotrigine and LAMICTAL XR. (6.1) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience with LAMICTAL XR for Treatment of Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic and Partial-Onset Seizures

    Most Common Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials  



   Adjunctive Therapy in Patients with Epilepsy:  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In these 2 trials, adverse reactions led to withdrawal of 4 (2%) patients in the group receiving placebo and 10 (5%) patients in the group receiving LAMICTAL XR. Dizziness was the most common reason for withdrawal in the group receiving LAMICTAL XR (5 patients [3%]). The next most common adverse reactions leading to withdrawal in 2 patients each (1%) were rash, headache, nausea, and nystagmus.



 Table 4 displays the incidence of adverse reactions in these two 19-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials of patients with PGTC and partial onset seizures.



   Table 4. Adverse Reactions in Pooled, Placebo-Controlled, Adjunctive Trials in Patients with Epilepsy  a    




  Body System/Adverse Reaction                       Percent of Patients Receiving Adjunctive LAMICTAL XR(n = 190)    Percent of Patients Receiving Adjunctive Placebo(n = 195)    
  Ear and labyrinth disorders                                                                                
  Vertigo                                            3                           &lt;1                          
  Eye disorders                                                                                              
  Diplopia                                           5                           &lt;1                          
  Vision blurred                                     3                           2                           
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                 
  Nausea                                             7                           4                           
  Vomiting                                           6                           3                           
  Diarrhea                                           5                           3                           
  Constipation                                       2                           &lt;1                          
  Dry mouth                                          2                           1                           
  General disorders and administration site conditions                                                            
  Asthenia and fatigue                               6                           4                           
  Infections and infestations                                                                                
  Sinusitis                                          2                           1                           
  Metabolic and nutritional disorders                                                                        
  Anorexia                                           3                           2                           
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorder                                                             
  Myalgia                                            2                           0                           
  Nervous system                                                                                             
  Dizziness                                          14                          6                           
  Tremor and intention tremor                        6                           1                           
  Somnolence                                         5                           3                           
  Cerebellar coordination and balance disorder       3                           0                           
  Nystagmus                                          2                           &lt;1                          
  Psychiatric disorders                                                                                      
  Depression                                         3                           &lt;1                          
  Anxiety                                            3                           0                           
  Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                            
  Pharyngolaryngeal pain                             3                           2                           
  Vascular disorder                                                                                          
  Hot flush                                          2                           0                           
           a  Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with LAMICTAL XR and at a greater incidence than placebo.
 

 Note: In these trials the incidence of nonserious rash was 2% for LAMICTAL XR and 3% for placebo. In clinical trials evaluating immediate-release lamotrigine, the rate of serious rash was 0.3% in adults on adjunctive therapy for epilepsy  [see Boxed Warning]  .



 Adverse reactions were also analyzed to assess the incidence of the onset of an event in the titration period, and in the maintenance period, and if adverse reactions occurring in the titration phase persisted in the maintenance phase.



 The incidence for many adverse reactions caused by treatment with LAMICTAL XR was increased relative to placebo (i.e., treatment difference between LAMICTAL XR and placebo &gt;=2%) in either the titration or maintenance phases of the trial. During the titration phase, an increased incidence (shown in descending order of percent treatment difference) was observed for diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, somnolence, vertigo, myalgia, hot flush, and anxiety. During the maintenance phase, an increased incidence was observed for dizziness, tremor, and diplopia. Some adverse reactions developing in the titration phase were notable for persisting (&gt;7 days) into the maintenance phase. These persistent adverse reactions included somnolence and dizziness.



 There were inadequate data to evaluate the effect of dose and/or concentration on the incidence of adverse reactions because, although patients were randomized to different target doses based upon concomitant AEDs, the plasma exposure was expected to be generally similar among all patients receiving different doses. However, in a randomized, parallel trial comparing placebo with 300 and 500 mg/day of immediate-release lamotrigine, the incidence of the most common adverse reactions (  &gt;  5%) such as ataxia, blurred vision, diplopia, and dizziness were dose related. Less common adverse reactions (&lt;5%) were not assessed for dose-response relationships.



   Monotherapy in Patients with Epilepsy:  Adverse reactions observed in this trial were generally similar to those observed and attributed to drug in adjunctive and monotherapy immediate-release lamotrigine and adjunctive LAMICTAL XR placebo-controlled trials. Only 2 adverse events, nasopharyngitis and upper respiratory tract infection, were observed at a rate of  &gt;  3% and not reported at a similar rate in previous trials. Because this trial did not include a placebo control group, causality could not be established  [see Clinical Studies (14.3)]  .



   6.2 Other Adverse Reactions Observed during the Clinical Development of Immediate-Release Lamotrigine

  All reported reactions are included except those already listed in the previous tables or elsewhere in the labeling, those too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug.



   Adjunctive Therapy in Adults with Epilepsy  



 In addition to the adverse reactions reported above from the development of LAMICTAL XR, the following adverse reactions with an uncertain relationship to lamotrigine were reported during the clinical development of immediate-release lamotrigine for treatment of epilepsy in adults. These reactions occurred in &gt;=2% of patients receiving immediate-release lamotrigine and more frequently than in the placebo group.



   Body as a Whole:  Headache, flu syndrome, fever, neck pain.



   Musculoskeletal:  Arthralgia.



   Nervous:  Insomnia, convulsion, irritability, speech disorder, concentration disturbance.



   Respiratory:  Pharyngitis, cough increased.



   Skin and Appendages:  Rash, pruritus.



   Urogenital (female patients only):  Vaginitis, amenorrhea, dysmenorrhea.



   Monotherapy in Adults with Epilepsy  



 In addition to the adverse reactions reported above from the development of LAMICTAL XR, the following adverse reactions with an uncertain relationship to lamotrigine were reported during the clinical development of immediate-release lamotrigine for treatment of epilepsy in adults. These reactions occurred in &gt;2% of patients receiving immediate-release lamotrigine and more frequently than in the placebo group.



   Body as a Whole:  Chest pain.



   Digestive:  Rectal hemorrhage, peptic ulcer.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Weight decrease, peripheral edema.



   Nervous:  Hypesthesia, libido increase, decreased reflexes.



   Respiratory:  Epistaxis, dyspnea.



   Skin and Appendages:  Contact dermatitis, dry skin, sweating.



   Special Senses:  Vision abnormality.



   Urogenital (female patients only):  Dysmenorrhea.



   Other Clinical Trial Experience  



 Immediate-release lamotrigine has been administered to 6,694 individuals for whom complete adverse reaction data was captured during all clinical trials, only some of which were placebo controlled.



 Adverse reactions are further classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions:  frequent  adverse reactions are defined as those occurring in at least 1/100 patients;  infrequent  adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients;  rare  adverse reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1,000 patients.



   Cardiovascular System: Infrequent:  Hypertension, palpitations, postural hypotension, syncope, tachycardia, vasodilation.



   Dermatological: Infrequent:  Acne, alopecia, hirsutism, maculopapular rash, urticaria.



   Rare:  Leukoderma, multiforme erythema, petechial rash, pustular rash.



   Digestive System: Infrequent:  Dysphagia, liver function tests abnormal, mouth ulceration.



   Rare:  Gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hemorrhagic colitis, hepatitis, melena, stomach ulcer.



   Endocrine System: Rare:  Goiter, hypothyroidism.



   Hematologic and Lymphatic System: Infrequent:  Ecchymosis, leukopenia.



   Rare:  Anemia, eosinophilia, fibrin decrease, fibrinogen decrease, iron deficiency anemia, leukocytosis, lymphocytosis, macrocytic anemia, petechia, thrombocytopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders: Infrequent:  Aspartate transaminase increased.



   Rare:  Alcohol intolerance, alkaline phosphatase increase, alanine transaminase increase, bilirubinemia, gamma glutamyl transpeptidase increase, hyperglycemia.



   Musculoskeletal System: Rare:  Muscle atrophy, pathological fracture, tendinous contracture.



   Nervous System: Frequent:  Confusion.



   Infrequent:  Akathisia, apathy, aphasia, depersonalization, dysarthria, dyskinesia, euphoria, hallucinations, hostility, hyperkinesia, hypertonia, libido decreased, memory decrease, mind racing, movement disorder, myoclonus, panic attack, paranoid reaction, personality disorder, psychosis, stupor.



   Rare:  Choreoathetosis, delirium, delusions, dysphoria, dystonia, extrapyramidal syndrome, hemiplegia, hyperalgesia, hyperesthesia, hypokinesia, hypotonia, manic depression reaction, neuralgia, paralysis, peripheral neuritis.



   Respiratory System: Rare:  Hiccup, hyperventilation.



   Special Senses: Frequent:  Amblyopia.



   Infrequent:  Abnormality of accommodation, conjunctivitis, dry eyes, ear pain, photophobia, taste perversion, tinnitus.



   Rare:  Deafness, lacrimation disorder, oscillopsia, parosmia, ptosis, strabismus, taste loss, uveitis, visual field defect.



   Urogenital System: Infrequent:  Abnormal ejaculation, hematuria, impotence, menorrhagia, polyuria, urinary incontinence.



   Rare:  Acute kidney failure, breast neoplasm, creatinine increase, female lactation, kidney failure, kidney pain, nocturia, urinary retention, urinary urgency.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience with Immediate-Release Lamotrigine

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of immediate-release lamotrigine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic  



 Agranulocytosis, hemolytic anemia, lymphadenopathy not associated with hypersensitivity disorder.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Esophagitis.



   Hepatobiliary Tract and Pancreas  



 Pancreatitis.



   Immunologic  



 Lupus-like reaction, vasculitis.



   Lower Respiratory  



 Apnea.



   Musculoskeletal  



 Rhabdomyolysis has been observed in patients experiencing hypersensitivity reactions.



   Nervous System  



 Aggression, exacerbation of Parkinsonian symptoms in patients with pre-existing Parkinson's disease, nightmares, tics.



   Non-site Specific  



 Progressive immunosuppression.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SERIOUS SKIN RASHES

  WARNING: SERIOUS SKIN RASHES

    LAMICTAL  (r)   XRTM can cause serious rashes requiring hospitalization and discontinuation of treatment. The incidence of these rashes, which have included Stevens-Johnson syndrome, is approximately 0.8% (8 per 1,000) in pediatric patients (aged 2 to 16 years) receiving immediate-release lamotrigine as adjunctive therapy for epilepsy and 0.3% (3 per 1,000) in adults on adjunctive therapy for epilepsy. In a prospectively followed cohort of 1,983 pediatric patients (aged 2 to 16 years) with epilepsy taking adjunctive immediate-release lamotrigine, there was 1 rash-related death. LAMICTAL XR is not approved for patients younger than 13 years. In worldwide postmarketing experience, rare cases of toxic epidermal necrolysis and/or rash-related death have been reported in adult and pediatric patients, but their numbers are too few to permit a precise estimate of the rate.  



   The risk of serious rash caused by treatment with LAMICTAL XR is not expected to differ from that with immediate-release lamotrigine. However, the relatively limited treatment experience with LAMICTAL XR makes it difficult to characterize the frequency and risk of serious rashes caused by treatment with LAMICTAL XR.  



   Other than age, there are as yet no factors identified that are known to predict the risk of occurrence or the severity of rash caused by LAMICTAL XR. There are suggestions, yet to be proven, that the risk of rash may also be increased by (1) coadministration of LAMICTAL XR with valproate (includes valproic acid and divalproex sodium), (2) exceeding the recommended initial dose of LAMICTAL XR, or (3) exceeding the recommended dose escalation for LAMICTAL XR. However, cases have occurred in the absence of these factors.  



   Nearly all cases of life-threatening rashes caused by immediate-release lamotrigine have occurred within 2 to 8 weeks of treatment initiation. However, isolated cases have occurred after prolonged treatment (e.g., 6 months). Accordingly, duration of therapy cannot be relied upon as means to predict the potential risk heralded by the first appearance of a rash.  



   Although benign rashes are also caused by LAMICTAL XR, it is not possible to predict reliably which rashes will prove to be serious or life threatening. Accordingly, LAMICTAL XR should ordinarily be discontinued at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug related. Discontinuation of treatment may not prevent a rash from becoming life threatening or permanently disabling or disfiguring   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SERIOUS SKIN RASHES



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Cases of life-threatening serious rashes, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis, and/or rash-related death have been caused by lamotrigine. The rate of serious rash is greater in pediatric patients than in adults. Additional factors that may increase the risk of rash include:coadministration with valproate.exceeding recommended initial dose of LAMICTAL XR.exceeding recommended dose escalation for LAMICTAL XR. (5.1) 
 *  Benign rashes are also caused by lamotrigine; however, it is not possible to predict which rashes will prove to be serious or life threatening. LAMICTAL XR should be discontinued at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug related.(5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Life-threatening serious rash and/or rash-related death: Discontinue at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug related. (Boxed Warning,  5.1  ) 
 *    Fatal or life-threatening hypersensitivity reaction: Multiorgan hypersensitivity reactions, also known as drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms, may be fatal or life threatening. Early signs may include rash, fever, and lymphadenopathy. These reactions may be associated with other organ involvement, such as hepatitis, hepatic failure, blood dyscrasias, or acute multiorgan failure. LAMICTAL XR should be discontinued if alternate etiology for this reaction is not found. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Blood dyscrasias (e.g., neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, pancytopenia): May occur, either with or without an associated hypersensitivity syndrome. Monitor for signs of anemia, unexpected infection, or bleeding. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Suicidal behavior and ideation: Monitor for suicidal thoughts or behaviors. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Aseptic meningitis: Monitor for signs of meningitis. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Medication errors due to product name confusion: Strongly advise patients to visually inspect tablets to verify the received drug is correct. (  5.6  ,  16  ,  17  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Skin Rashes [see Boxed Warning]  



  The risk of serious rash caused by treatment with LAMICTAL XR is not expected to differ from that with immediate-release lamotrigine [see Boxed Warning]  . However, the relatively limited treatment experience with LAMICTAL XR makes it difficult to characterize the frequency and risk of serious rashes caused by treatment with LAMICTAL XR.



  Pediatric Population  



 The incidence of serious rash associated with hospitalization and discontinuation of immediate-release lamotrigine in a prospectively followed cohort of pediatric patients (aged 2 to 16 years) with epilepsy receiving adjunctive therapy with immediate-release lamotrigine was approximately 0.8% (16 of 1,983). When 14 of these cases were reviewed by 3 expert dermatologists, there was considerable disagreement as to their proper classification. To illustrate, one dermatologist considered none of the cases to be Stevens-Johnson syndrome; another assigned 7 of the 14 to this diagnosis. There was 1 rash-related death in this 1,983-patient cohort. Additionally, there have been rare cases of toxic epidermal necrolysis with and without permanent sequelae and/or death in US and foreign postmarketing experience.



 There is evidence that the inclusion of valproate in a multidrug regimen increases the risk of serious, potentially life-threatening rash in pediatric patients. In pediatric patients who used valproate concomitantly, 1.2% (6 of 482) experienced a serious rash compared with 0.6% (6 of 952) patients not taking valproate.



 LAMICTAL XR is not approved in patients younger than 13 years.



  Adult Population  



 Serious rash associated with hospitalization and discontinuation of immediate-release lamotrigine occurred in 0.3% (11 of 3,348) of adult patients who received immediate-release lamotrigine in premarketing clinical trials of epilepsy. In worldwide postmarketing experience, rare cases of rash-related death have been reported, but their numbers are too few to permit a precise estimate of the rate.



 Among the rashes leading to hospitalization were Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, angioedema, and those associated with multiorgan hypersensitivity [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



 There is evidence that the inclusion of valproate in a multidrug regimen increases the risk of serious, potentially life-threatening rash in adults. Specifically, of 584 patients administered immediate-release lamotrigine with valproate in epilepsy clinical trials, 6 (1%) were hospitalized in association with rash; in contrast, 4 (0.16%) of 2,398 clinical trial patients and volunteers administered immediate-release lamotrigine in the absence of valproate were hospitalized.



  Patients with History of Allergy or Rash to Other Antiepileptic Drugs  



 The risk of nonserious rash may be increased when the recommended initial dose and/or the rate of dose escalation for LAMICTAL XR is exceeded and in patients with a history of allergy or rash to other AEDs.



    5.2 Multiorgan Hypersensitivity Reactions and Organ Failure



  Multiorgan hypersensitivity reactions, also known as drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), have occurred with lamotrigine. Some have been fatal or life threatening. DRESS typically, although not exclusively, presents with fever, rash, and/or lymphadenopathy in association with other organ system involvement, such as hepatitis, nephritis, hematologic abnormalities, myocarditis, or myositis, sometimes resembling an acute viral infection. Eosinophilia is often present. This disorder is variable in its expression and other organ systems not noted here may be involved.



 Fatalities associated with acute multiorgan failure and various degrees of hepatic failure have been reported in 2 of 3,796 adult patients and 4 of 2,435 pediatric patients who received lamotrigine in epilepsy clinical trials. Rare fatalities from multiorgan failure have also been reported in postmarketing use.



 Isolated liver failure without rash or involvement of other organs has also been reported with lamotrigine.



 It is important to note that early manifestations of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may be present even though a rash is not evident. If such signs or symptoms are present, the patient should be evaluated immediately. LAMICTAL XR should be discontinued if an alternative etiology for the signs or symptoms cannot be established.



 Prior to initiation of treatment with LAMICTAL XR, the patient should be instructed that a rash or other signs or symptoms of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may herald a serious medical event and that the patient should report any such occurrence to a healthcare provider immediately.



    5.3 Blood Dyscrasias



  There have been reports of blood dyscrasias with immediate-release lamotrigine that may or may not be associated with multiorgan hypersensitivity (also known as DRESS) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  . These have included neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, pancytopenia, and, rarely, aplastic anemia and pure red cell aplasia.



    5.4 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  AEDs, including LAMICTAL XR, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (monotherapy and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to 1 of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI: 1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared with patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared with 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately 1 case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were 4 suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number of events is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as 1 week after starting treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanism of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5 to 100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.



 Table 3 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



  Table 3. Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis  




  Indication    Placebo Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients    Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients    Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients    Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients    
  Epilepsy     1.0                3.4                3.5                              2.4                       
  Psychiatric    5.7                8.5                1.5                              2.9                       
  Other        1.0                1.8                1.9                              0.9                       
  Total        2.4                4.3                1.8                              1.9                       
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing LAMICTAL XR or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, the emergence of suicidal thoughts or suicidal behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis



  Therapy with lamotrigine increases the risk of developing aseptic meningitis. Because of the potential for serious outcomes of untreated meningitis due to other causes, patients should also be evaluated for other causes of meningitis and treated as appropriate.



 Postmarketing cases of aseptic meningitis have been reported in pediatric and adult patients taking lamotrigine for various indications. Symptoms upon presentation have included headache, fever, nausea, vomiting, and nuchal rigidity. Rash, photophobia, myalgia, chills, altered consciousness, and somnolence were also noted in some cases. Symptoms have been reported to occur within 1 day to one and a half months following the initiation of treatment. In most cases, symptoms were reported to resolve after discontinuation of lamotrigine. Re-exposure resulted in a rapid return of symptoms (from within 30 minutes to 1 day following re-initiation of treatment) that were frequently more severe. Some of the patients treated with lamotrigine who developed aseptic meningitis had underlying diagnoses of systemic lupus erythematosus or other autoimmune diseases.



 Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) analyzed at the time of clinical presentation in reported cases was characterized by a mild to moderate pleocytosis, normal glucose levels, and mild to moderate increase in protein. CSF white blood cell count differentials showed a predominance of neutrophils in a majority of the cases, although a predominance of lymphocytes was reported in approximately one third of the cases. Some patients also had new onset of signs and symptoms of involvement of other organs (predominantly hepatic and renal involvement), which may suggest that in these cases the aseptic meningitis observed was part of a hypersensitivity reaction [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



    5.6 Potential Medication Errors



  Medication errors involving LAMICTAL have occurred. In particular, the names LAMICTAL or lamotrigine can be confused with the names of other commonly used medications. Medication errors may also occur between the different formulations of LAMICTAL. To reduce the potential of medication errors, write and say LAMICTAL XR clearly. Depictions of the LAMICTAL XR extended-release tablets can be found in the Medication Guide. Each LAMICTAL XR tablet has a distinct color and white center, and is printed with "LAMICTAL XR" and the tablet strength. These distinctive features serve to identify the different presentations of the drug and thus may help reduce the risk of medication errors. LAMICTAL XR is supplied in round, unit-of-use bottles with orange caps containing 30 tablets. The label on the bottle includes a depiction of the tablets that further communicates to patients and pharmacists that the medication is LAMICTAL XR and the specific tablet strength included in the bottle. The unit-of-use bottle with a distinctive orange cap and distinctive bottle label features serves to identify the different presentations of the drug and thus may help to reduce the risk of medication errors. To avoid the medication error of using the wrong drug or formulation, patients should be strongly advised to visually inspect their tablets to verify that they are LAMICTAL XR each time they fill their prescription.



    5.7 Concomitant Use with Oral Contraceptives



  Some estrogen-containing oral contraceptives have been shown to decrease serum concentrations of lamotrigine [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  . Dosage adjustments will be necessary in most patients who start or stop estrogen-containing oral contraceptives while taking LAMICTAL XR [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  . During the week of inactive hormone preparation (pill-free week) of oral contraceptive therapy, plasma lamotrigine levels are expected to rise, as much as doubling at the end of the week. Adverse reactions consistent with elevated levels of lamotrigine, such as dizziness, ataxia, and diplopia, could occur.



    5.8 Withdrawal Seizures



  As with other AEDs, LAMICTAL XR should not be abruptly discontinued. In patients with epilepsy there is a possibility of increasing seizure frequency. Unless safety concerns require a more rapid withdrawal, the dose of LAMICTAL XR should be tapered over a period of at least 2 weeks (approximately 50% reduction per week) [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  .



    5.9 Status Epilepticus



  Valid estimates of the incidence of treatment-emergent status epilepticus among patients treated with immediate-release lamotrigine are difficult to obtain because reporters participating in clinical trials did not all employ identical rules for identifying cases. At a minimum, 7 of 2,343 adult patients had episodes that could unequivocally be described as status epilepticus. In addition, a number of reports of variably defined episodes of seizure exacerbation (e.g., seizure clusters, seizure flurries) were made.



    5.10 Sudden Unexplained Death in Epilepsy (SUDEP)



  During the premarketing development of immediate-release lamotrigine, 20 sudden and unexplained deaths were recorded among a cohort of 4,700 patients with epilepsy (5,747 patient-years of exposure).



 Some of these could represent seizure-related deaths in which the seizure was not observed, e.g., at night. This represents an incidence of 0.0035 deaths per patient-year. Although this rate exceeds that expected in a healthy population matched for age and sex, it is within the range of estimates for the incidence of sudden unexplained death in epilepsy (SUDEP) in patients not receiving lamotrigine (ranging from 0.0005 for the general population of patients with epilepsy, to 0.004 for a recently studied clinical trial population similar to that in the clinical development program for immediate-release lamotrigine, to 0.005 for patients with refractory epilepsy). Consequently, whether these figures are reassuring or suggest concern depends on the comparability of the populations reported upon with the cohort receiving immediate-release lamotrigine and the accuracy of the estimates provided. Probably most reassuring is the similarity of estimated SUDEP rates in patients receiving immediate-release lamotrigine and those receiving other AEDs, chemically unrelated to each other, that underwent clinical testing in similar populations. Importantly, that drug is chemically unrelated to lamotrigine. This evidence suggests, although it certainly does not prove, that the high SUDEP rates reflect population rates, not a drug effect.



    5.11 Addition of LAMICTAL XR to a Multidrug Regimen that Includes Valproate



  Because valproate reduces the clearance of lamotrigine, the dosage of lamotrigine in the presence of valproate is less than half of that required in its absence [see Dosage and Administration (2.1, 2.2), Drug Interactions (7)]  .



    5.12 Binding in the Eye and Other Melanin-Containing Tissues



  Because lamotrigine binds to melanin, it could accumulate in melanin-rich tissues over time. This raises the possibility that lamotrigine may cause toxicity in these tissues after extended use. Although ophthalmological testing was performed in 1 controlled clinical trial, the testing was inadequate to exclude subtle effects or injury occurring after long-term exposure. Moreover, the capacity of available tests to detect potentially adverse consequences, if any, of lamotrigine's binding to melanin is unknown.



 Accordingly, although there are no specific recommendations for periodic ophthalmological monitoring, prescribers should be aware of the possibility of long-term ophthalmologic effects.



    5.13 Laboratory Tests



   False-Positive Drug Test Results  



 Lamotrigine has been reported to interfere with the assay used in some rapid urine drug screens, which can result in false-positive readings, particularly for phencyclidine (PCP). A more specific analytical method should be used to confirm a positive result.



  Plasma Concentrations of Lamotrigine  



 The value of monitoring plasma concentrations of lamotrigine in patients treated with LAMICTAL XR has not been established. Because of the possible pharmacokinetic interactions between lamotrigine and other drugs, including AEDs (see Table 6), monitoring of the plasma levels of lamotrigine and concomitant drugs may be indicated, particularly during dosage adjustments. In general, clinical judgment should be exercised regarding monitoring of plasma levels of lamotrigine and other drugs and whether or not dosage adjustments are necessary.



  Effect on Leukocytes  



 Treatment with LAMICTAL XR caused an increased incidence of subnormal (below the reference range) values in some hematology analytes (e.g., total white blood cells, monocytes). The treatment effect (LAMICTAL XR % - Placebo %) incidence of subnormal counts was 3% for total white blood cells and 4% for monocytes.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
