<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lamictal0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described in more detail in the  Warnings and Precautions  section of the label:



 *    Serious skin rashes [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Multiorgan hypersensitivity reactions and organ failure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Blood dyscrasias [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *    Suicidal behavior and id eation [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *    Aseptic meningitis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
 *    Withdrawal seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  
 *    Status epilepticus [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)]  
 *    Sudden unexplained death in epilepsy [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)]  
   *      Epilepsy: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=10%) in adults were dizziness, headache, diplopia, ataxia, nausea, blurred vision, somnolence, rhinitis, pharyngitis, and rash. Additional adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=10%) reported in children included vomiting, infection, fever, accidental injury, diarrhea, abdominal pain, and tremor. (  6.1  ) 
 *      Bipolar disorder: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;5%) in adults were nausea, insomnia, somnolence, back pain, fatigue, rash, rhinitis, abdominal pain, and xerostomia. (  6.1  ) 
 *      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
      EXCERPT:   
   6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Epilepsy  



   Most Common Adverse Reactions in All Clinical Trials: Adjunctive Therapy in Adults with Epilepsy:  The most commonly observed (&gt;=5% for LAMICTAL and more common on drug than placebo) adverse reactions seen in association with LAMICTAL during adjunctive therapy in adults and not seen at an equivalent frequency among placebo-treated patients were: dizziness, ataxia, somnolence, headache, diplopia, blurred vision, nausea, vomiting, and rash. Dizziness, diplopia, ataxia, blurred vision, nausea, and vomiting were dose related. Dizziness, diplopia, ataxia, and blurred vision occurred more commonly in patients receiving carbamazepine with LAMICTAL than in patients receiving other AEDs with LAMICTAL. Clinical data suggest a higher incidence of rash, including serious rash, in patients receiving concomitant valproate than in patients not receiving valproate  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .



 Approximately 11% of the 3,378 adult patients who received LAMICTAL as adjunctive therapy in premarketing clinical trials discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were rash (3.0%), dizziness (2.8%), and headache (2.5%).



 In a dose-response trial in adults, the rate of discontinuation of LAMICTAL for dizziness, ataxia, diplopia, blurred vision, nausea, and vomiting was dose related.



   Monotherapy in Adults with Epilepsy:  The most commonly observed (&gt;=5% for LAMICTAL and more common on drug than placebo) adverse reactions seen in association with the use of LAMICTAL during the monotherapy phase of the controlled trial in adults not seen at an equivalent rate in the control group were vomiting, coordination abnormality, dyspepsia, nausea, dizziness, rhinitis, anxiety, insomnia, infection, pain, weight decrease, chest pain, and dysmenorrhea. The most commonly observed (&gt;=5% for LAMICTAL and more common on drug than placebo) adverse reactions associated with the use of LAMICTAL during the conversion to monotherapy (add-on) period, not seen at an equivalent frequency among low-dose valproate-treated patients, were dizziness, headache, nausea, asthenia, coordination abnormality, vomiting, rash, somnolence, diplopia, ataxia, accidental injury, tremor, blurred vision, insomnia, nystagmus, diarrhea, lymphadenopathy, pruritus, and sinusitis.



 Approximately 10% of the 420 adult patients who received LAMICTAL as monotherapy in premarketing clinical trials discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were rash (4.5%), headache (3.1%), and asthenia (2.4%).



   Adjunctive Therapy in Pediatric Patients with Epilepsy:  The most commonly observed (&gt;=5% for LAMICTAL and more common on drug than placebo) adverse reactions seen in association with the use of LAMICTAL as adjunctive treatment in pediatric patients aged 2 to 16 years and not seen at an equivalent rate in the control group were infection, vomiting, rash, fever, somnolence, accidental injury, dizziness, diarrhea, abdominal pain, nausea, ataxia, tremor, asthenia, bronchitis, flu syndrome, and diplopia.



 In 339 patients aged 2 to 16 years with partial-onset seizures or generalized seizures of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, 4.2% of patients on LAMICTAL and 2.9% of patients on placebo discontinued due to adverse reactions. The most commonly reported adverse reaction that led to discontinuation of LAMICTAL was rash.



 Approximately 11.5% of the 1,081 pediatric patients aged 2 to 16 years who received LAMICTAL as adjunctive therapy in premarketing clinical trials discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were rash (4.4%), reaction aggravated (1.7%), and ataxia (0.6%).



   Controlled Adjunctive Clinical Trials in Adults with Epilepsy:  Table 8 lists adverse reactions that occurred in adult patients with epilepsy treated with LAMICTAL in placebo-controlled trials. In these trials, either LAMICTAL or placebo was added to the patient's current AED therapy.



   Table 8. Adverse Reactions in Pooled, Placebo-Controlled Adjunctive Trials in Adult Patients with Epilepsy  a,b    




  Body System/Adverse Reaction     Percent of Patients Receiving Adjunctive LAMICTAL  (n = 711)    Percent of Patients Receiving Adjunctive Placebo  (n = 419)    
  Body as a whole                                                                                           
                                  Headache                        
                                                                    29                                    19                                 
                                  Flu syndrome                    
                                                                    7                                     6                                  
                                  Fever                           
                                                                    6                                     4                                  
                                  Abdominal pain                  
                                                                    5                                     4                                  
                                  Neck pain                       
                                                                    2                                     1                                  
                                  Reaction aggravated (seizure exacerbation) 
                                                                    2                                     1                                  
  Digestive                                                                                                 
                                  Nausea                          
                                                                    19                                    10                                 
                                  Vomiting                        
                                                                    9                                     4                                  
                                  Diarrhea                        
                                                                    6                                     4                                  
                                  Dyspepsia                       
                                                                    5                                     2                                  
                                  Constipation                    
                                                                    4                                     3                                  
                                  Anorexia                        
                                                                    2                                     1                                  
  Musculoskeletal                                                                                           
                                  Arthralgia                      
                                                                    2                                     0                                  
  Nervous                                                                                                   
                                  Dizziness                       
                                                                    38                                    13                                 
                                  Ataxia                          
                                                                    22                                    6                                  
                                  Somnolence                      
                                                                    14                                    7                                  
                                  Incoordination                  
                                                                    6                                     2                                  
                                  Insomnia                        
                                                                    6                                     2                                  
                                  Tremor                          
                                                                    4                                     1                                  
                                  Depression                      
                                                                    4                                     3                                  
                                  Anxiety                         
                                                                    4                                     3                                  
                                  Convulsion                      
                                                                    3                                     1                                  
                                  Irritability                    
                                                                    3                                     2                                  
                                  Speech disorder                 
                                                                    3                                     0                                  
                                  Concentration disturbance       
                                                                    2                                     1                                  
  Respiratory                                                                                               
                                  Rhinitis                        
                                                                    14                                    9                                  
                                  Pharyngitis                     
                                                                    10                                    9                                  
                                  Cough increased                 
                                                                    8                                     6                                  
  Skin and appendages                                                                                       
                                  Rash                            
                                                                    10                                    5                                  
                                  Pruritus                        
                                                                    3                                     2                                  
  Special senses                                                                                            
                                  Diplopia                        
                                                                    28                                    7                                  
                                  Blurred vision                  
                                                                    16                                    5                                  
                                  Vision abnormality              
                                                                    3                                     1                                  
  Urogenital                                                                                                
                                  Female patients only            
                                                                    (n = 365)                             (n = 207)                          
                                  Dysmenorrhea                    
                                                                    7                                     6                                  
                                  Vaginitis                       
                                                                    4                                     1                                  
                                  Amenorrhea                      
                                                                    2                                     1                                  
        *       a  Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with LAMICTAL and at a greater incidence than placebo. 
 *       b  Patients in these adjunctive trials were receiving 1 to 3 of the concomitant antiepileptic drugs carbamazepine, phenytoin, phenobarbital, or primidone in addition to LAMICTAL or placebo. Patients may have reported multiple adverse reactions during the trial or at discontinuation; thus, patients may be included in more than 1 category. 
    In a randomized, parallel trial comparing placebo with 300 and 500 mg/day of LAMICTAL, some of the more common drug-related adverse reactions were dose related (see Table 9).
 

   Table 9. Dose-Related Adverse Reactions from a Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Adjunctive Trial in Adults with Epilepsy  




  Adverse Reaction             Percent of Patients Experiencing Adverse Reactions    
  Placebo  (n = 73)            LAMICTAL  300 mg  (n = 71)    LAMICTAL  500 mg  (n = 72)    
  Ataxia                       10                  10                           28a,b                        
  Blurred vision               10                  11                           25a,b                        
  Diplopia                     8                   24a                          49a,b                        
  Dizziness                    27                  31                           54a,b                        
  Nausea                       11                  18                           25a                          
  Vomiting                     4                   11                           18a                          
         *       a  Significantly greater than placebo group ( P &lt;0.05). 
 *       b  Significantly greater than group receiving LAMICTAL 300 mg ( P &lt;0.05). 
    The overall adverse reaction profile for LAMICTAL was similar between females and males and was independent of age. Because the largest non-Caucasian racial subgroup was only 6% of patients exposed to LAMICTAL in placebo-controlled trials, there are insufficient data to support a statement regarding the distribution of adverse reaction reports by race. Generally, females receiving either LAMICTAL as adjunctive therapy or placebo were more likely to report adverse reactions than males. The only adverse reaction for which the reports on LAMICTAL were greater than 10% more frequent in females than males (without a corresponding difference by gender on placebo) was dizziness (difference = 16.5%). There was little difference between females and males in the rates of discontinuation of LAMICTAL for individual adverse reactions.
 

   Controlled Monotherapy Trial in Adults with Partial-Onset Seizures:  Table 10 lists adverse reactions that occurred in patients with epilepsy treated with monotherapy with LAMICTAL in a double-blind trial following discontinuation of either concomitant carbamazepine or phenytoin not seen at an equivalent frequency in the control group.



   Table 10. Adverse Reactions in a Controlled Monotherapy Trial in Adult Patients with Partial-Onset Seizures  a,b    




  Body System/  Adverse Reaction     Percent of Patients Receiving LAMICTALc as Monotherapy  (n = 43)    Percent of Patients Receiving Low-Dose Valproated Monotherapy  (n = 44)    
  Body as a whole                                                                                           
                                    Pain                              
                                                                        5                                        0                             
                                    Infection                         
                                                                        5                                        2                             
                                    Chest pain                        
                                                                        5                                        2                             
  Digestive                                                                                                 
                                    Vomiting                          
                                                                        9                                        0                             
                                    Dyspepsia                         
                                                                        7                                        2                             
                                    Nausea                            
                                                                        7                                        2                             
  Metabolic and nutritional                                                                                 
                                    Weight decrease                   
                                                                        5                                        2                             
  Nervous                                                                                                   
                                    Coordination abnormality          
                                                                        7                                        0                             
                                    Dizziness                         
                                                                        7                                        0                             
                                    Anxiety                           
                                                                        5                                        0                             
                                    Insomnia                          
                                                                        5                                        2                             
  Respiratory                                                                                               
                                    Rhinitis                          
                                                                        7                                        2                             
  Urogenital (female patients only)    (n = 21)                                 (n = 28)                      
                                    Dysmenorrhea                      
                                                                        5                                        0                             
        *       a  Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of patients treated with LAMICTAL and at a greater incidence than valproate-treated patients. 
 *       b  Patients in this trial were converted to LAMICTAL or valproate monotherapy from adjunctive therapy with carbamazepine or phenytoin. Patients may have reported multiple adverse reactions during the trial; thus, patients may be included in more than 1 category. 
 *       c  Up to 500 mg/day. 
 *       d  1,000 mg/day. 
    Adverse reactions that occurred with a frequency of less than 5% and greater than 2% of patients receiving LAMICTAL and numerically more frequent than placebo were:
 

   Body as a Whole:  Asthenia, fever.



   Digestive:  Anorexia, dry mouth, rectal hemorrhage, peptic ulcer.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Peripheral edema.



   Nervous System:  Amnesia, ataxia, depression, hypesthesia, libido increase, decreased reflexes, increased reflexes, nystagmus, irritability, suicidal ideation.



   Respiratory:  Epistaxis, bronchitis, dyspnea.



   Skin and Appendages:  Contact dermatitis, dry skin, sweating.



   Special Senses:  Vision abnormality.



   Incidence in Controlled Adjunctive Trials in Pediatric Patients with Epilepsy:  Table 11 lists adverse reactions that occurred in 339 pediatric patients with partial-onset seizures or generalized seizures of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome who received LAMICTAL up to 15 mg/kg/day or a maximum of 750 mg/day.



   Table 11. Adverse Reactions in Pooled, Placebo-Controlled Adjunctive Trials in Pediatric Patients with Epilepsy  a    




  Body System/  Adverse Reaction    Percent of Patients Receiving LAMICTAL  (n = 168)    Percent of Patients Receiving Placebo  (n = 171)    
  Body as a whole                                                                                            
                           Infection                
                                                      20                                         17                                    
                           Fever                    
                                                      15                                         14                                    
                           Accidental injury        
                                                      14                                         12                                    
                           Abdominal pain           
                                                      10                                         5                                     
                           Asthenia                 
                                                      8                                          4                                     
                           Flu syndrome             
                                                      7                                          6                                     
                           Pain                     
                                                      5                                          4                                     
                           Facial edema             
                                                      2                                          1                                     
                           Photosensitivity         
                                                      2                                          0                                     
  Cardiovascular                                                                                             
                           Hemorrhage               
                                                      2                                          1                                     
  Digestive                                                                                                  
                           Vomiting                 
                                                      20                                         16                                    
                           Diarrhea                 
                                                      11                                         9                                     
                           Nausea                   
                                                      10                                         2                                     
                           Constipation             
                                                      4                                          2                                     
                           Dyspepsia                
                                                      2                                          1                                     
  Hemic and lymphatic                                                                                        
                           Lymphadenopathy          
                                                      2                                          1                                     
  Metabolic and nutritional                                                                                     
                           Edema                    
                                                      2                                          0                                     
  Nervous system                                                                                             
                           Somnolence               
                                                      17                                         15                                    
                           Dizziness                
                                                      14                                         4                                     
                           Ataxia                   
                                                      11                                         3                                     
                           Tremor                   
                                                      10                                         1                                     
                           Emotional lability       
                                                      4                                          2                                     
                           Gait abnormality         
                                                      4                                          2                                     
                           Thinking abnormality     
                                                      3                                          2                                     
                           Convulsions              
                                                      2                                          1                                     
                           Nervousness              
                                                      2                                          1                                     
                           Vertigo                  
                                                      2                                          1                                     
  Respiratory                                                                                                
                           Pharyngitis              
                                                      14                                         11                                    
                           Bronchitis               
                                                      7                                          5                                     
                           Increased cough          
                                                      7                                          6                                     
                           Sinusitis                
                                                      2                                          1                                     
                           Bronchospasm             
                                                      2                                          1                                     
  Skin                                                                                                       
                           Rash                     
                                                      14                                         12                                    
                           Eczema                   
                                                      2                                          1                                     
                           Pruritus                 
                                                      2                                          1                                     
  Special senses                                                                                             
                           Diplopia                 
                                                      5                                          1                                     
                           Blurred vision           
                                                      4                                          1                                     
                           Visual abnormality       
                                                      2                                          0                                     
  Urogenital                                                                                                 
  Male and female patients                                                                                     
                           Urinary tract infection  
                                                      3                                          0                                     
        *       a  Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with LAMICTAL and at a greater incidence than placebo. 
      Bipolar Disorder in Adults  
 

 The most common adverse reactions seen in association with the use of LAMICTAL as monotherapy (100 to 400 mg/day) in adult patients (aged 18 to 82 years) with bipolar disorder in the 2 double-blind placebo-controlled trials of 18 months' duration are included in Table 12. Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of patients and were numerically more frequent during the dose-escalation phase of LAMICTAL in these trials (when patients may have been receiving concomitant medications) compared with the monotherapy phase were: headache (25%), rash (11%), dizziness (10%), diarrhea (8%), dream abnormality (6%), and pruritus (6%).



 During the monotherapy phase of the double-blind placebo-controlled trials of 18 months' duration, 13% of 227 patients who received LAMICTAL (100 to 400 mg/day), 16% of 190 patients who received placebo, and 23% of 166 patients who received lithium discontinued therapy because of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions that most commonly led to discontinuation of LAMICTAL were rash (3%) and mania/hypomania/mixed mood adverse reactions (2%). Approximately 16% of 2,401 patients who received LAMICTAL (50 to 500 mg/day) for bipolar disorder in premarketing trials discontinued therapy because of an adverse reaction, most commonly due to rash (5%) and mania/hypomania/mixed mood adverse reactions (2%).



 The overall adverse reaction profile for LAMICTAL was similar between females and males, between elderly and nonelderly patients, and among racial groups.



   Table 12. Adverse Reactions in 2 Placebo-Controlled Trials in Adult Patients with Bipolar I Disorder  a,b    




  Body System/  Adverse Reaction    Percent of Patients Receiving LAMICTAL  (n = 227)    Percent of Patients Receiving Placebo  (n = 190)    
  General                                                                                                   
                            Back pain                 
                                                        8                                         6                                    
                            Fatigue                   
                                                        8                                         5                                    
                            Abdominal pain            
                                                        6                                         3                                    
  Digestive                                                                                                 
                            Nausea                    
                                                        14                                        11                                   
                            Constipation              
                                                        5                                         2                                    
                            Vomiting                  
                                                        5                                         2                                    
  Nervous System                                                                                            
                            Insomnia                  
                                                        10                                        6                                    
                            Somnolence                
                                                        9                                         7                                    
                            Xerostomia (dry mouth)    
                                                        6                                         4                                    
  Respiratory                                                                                               
                            Rhinitis                  
                                                        7                                         4                                    
                            Exacerbation of cough     
                                                        5                                         3                                    
                            Pharyngitis               
                                                        5                                         4                                    
  Skin                                                                                                      
                            Rash (nonserious)  c      
                                                        7                                         5                                    
        *       a  Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of patients treated with LAMICTAL and at a greater incidence than placebo. 
 *       b  Patients in these trials were converted to LAMICTAL (100 to 400 mg/day) or placebo monotherapy from add-on therapy with other psychotropic medications. Patients may have reported multiple adverse reactions during the trial; thus, patients may be included in more than 1 category. 
 *       c  In the overall bipolar and other mood disorders clinical trials, the rate of serious rash was 0.08% (1 of 1,233) of adult patients who received LAMICTAL as initial monotherapy and 0.13% (2 of 1,538) of adult patients who received LAMICTAL as adjunctive therapy [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)] . 
    Other reactions that occurred in 5% or more patients but equally or more frequently in the placebo group included: dizziness, mania, headache, infection, influenza, pain, accidental injury, diarrhea, and dyspepsia.
 

 Adverse reactions that occurred with a frequency of less than 5% and greater than 1% of patients receiving LAMICTAL and numerically more frequent than placebo were:



   General:  Fever, neck pain.



   Cardiovascular:  Migraine.



   Digestive:  Flatulence.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Weight gain, edema.



   Musculoskeletal:  Arthralgia, myalgia.



   Nervous System:  Amnesia, depression, agitation, emotional lability, dyspraxia, abnormal thoughts, dream abnormality, hypoesthesia.



   Respiratory:  Sinusitis.



   Urogenital:  Urinary frequency.



   Adverse Reactions following Abrupt Discontinuation:  In the 2 controlled clinical trials, there was no increase in the incidence, severity, or type of adverse reactions in patients with bipolar disorder after abruptly terminating therapy with LAMICTAL. In the clinical development program in adults with bipolar disorder, 2 patients experienced seizures shortly after abrupt withdrawal of LAMICTAL  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  .



   Mania/Hypomania/Mixed Episodes:  During the double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trials in bipolar I disorder in which adults were converted to monotherapy with LAMICTAL (100 to 400 mg/day) from other psychotropic medications and followed for up to 18 months, the rates of manic or hypomanic or mixed mood episodes reported as adverse reactions were 5% for patients treated with LAMICTAL (n = 227), 4% for patients treated with lithium (n = 166), and 7% for patients treated with placebo (n = 190). In all bipolar controlled trials combined, adverse reactions of mania (including hypomania and mixed mood episodes) were reported in 5% of patients treated with LAMICTAL (n = 956), 3% of patients treated with lithium (n = 280), and 4% of patients treated with placebo (n = 803).



   6.2 Other Adverse Reactions Observed in All Clinical Trials

  LAMICTAL has been administered to 6,694 individuals for whom complete adverse reaction data was captured during all clinical trials, only some of which were placebo controlled. During these trials, all adverse reactions were recorded by the clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. To provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals having adverse reactions, similar types of adverse reactions were grouped into a smaller number of standardized categories using modified COSTART dictionary terminology. The frequencies presented represent the proportion of the 6,694 individuals exposed to LAMICTAL who experienced an event of the type cited on at least 1 occasion while receiving LAMICTAL. All reported adverse reactions are included except those already listed in the previous tables or elsewhere in the labeling, those too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug.



 Adverse reactions are further classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions:  frequent  adverse reactions are defined as those occurring in at least 1/100 patients;  infrequent  adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients;  rare  adverse reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1,000 patients.



   Body as a Whole  



   Infrequent:  Allergic reaction, chills, malaise.



   Cardiovascular System  



   Infrequent:  Flushing, hot flashes, hypertension, palpitations, postural hypotension, syncope, tachycardia, vasodilation.



   Dermatological  



   Infrequent:  Acne, alopecia, hirsutism, maculopapular rash, skin discoloration, urticaria.



   Rare:  Angioedema, erythema, exfoliative dermatitis, fungal dermatitis, herpes zoster, leukoderma, multiforme erythema, petechial rash, pustular rash, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, vesiculobullous rash.



   Digestive System  



   Infrequent:  Dysphagia, eructation, gastritis, gingivitis, increased appetite, increased salivation, liver function tests abnormal, mouth ulceration.



   Rare:  Gastrointestinal hemorrhage, glossitis, gum hemorrhage, gum hyperplasia, hematemesis, hemorrhagic colitis, hepatitis, melena, stomach ulcer, stomatitis, tongue edema.



   Endocrine System  



   Rare:  Goiter, hypothyroidism.



   Hematologic and Lymphatic System  



   Infrequent:  Ecchymosis, leukopenia.



   Rare:  Anemia, eosinophilia, fibrin decrease, fibrinogen decrease, iron deficiency anemia, leukocytosis, lymphocytosis, macrocytic anemia, petechia, thrombocytopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  



   Infrequent:  Aspartate transaminase increased.



   Rare:  Alcohol intolerance, alkaline phosphatase increase, alanine transaminase increase, bilirubinemia, general edema, gamma glutamyl transpeptidase increase, hyperglycemia.



   Musculoskeletal System  



   Infrequent:  Arthritis, leg cramps, myasthenia, twitching.



   Rare:  Bursitis, muscle atrophy, pathological fracture, tendinous contracture.



   Nervous System  



   Frequent:  Confusion, paresthesia.



   Infrequent:  Akathisia, apathy, aphasia, central nervous system depression, depersonalization, dysarthria, dyskinesia, euphoria, hallucinations, hostility, hyperkinesia, hypertonia, libido decreased, memory decrease, mind racing, movement disorder, myoclonus, panic attack, paranoid reaction, personality disorder, psychosis, sleep disorder, stupor, suicidal ideation.



   Rare:  Choreoathetosis, delirium, delusions, dysphoria, dystonia, extrapyramidal syndrome, faintness, grand mal convulsions, hemiplegia, hyperalgesia, hyperesthesia, hypokinesia, hypotonia, manic depression reaction, muscle spasm, neuralgia, neurosis, paralysis, peripheral neuritis.



   Respiratory System  



   Infrequent:  Yawn.



   Rare:  Hiccup, hyperventilation.



   Special Senses  



   Frequent:  Amblyopia.



   Infrequent:  Abnormality of accommodation, conjunctivitis, dry eyes, ear pain, photophobia, taste perversion, tinnitus.



   Rare:  Deafness, lacrimation disorder, oscillopsia, parosmia, ptosis, strabismus, taste loss, uveitis, visual field defect.



   Urogenital System  



   Infrequent:  Abnormal ejaculation, hematuria, impotence, menorrhagia, polyuria, urinary incontinence.



   Rare:  Acute kidney failure, anorgasmia, breast abscess, breast neoplasm, creatinine increase, cystitis, dysuria, epididymitis, female lactation, kidney failure, kidney pain, nocturia, urinary retention, urinary urgency.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of LAMICTAL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic  



 Agranulocytosis, hemolytic anemia, lymphadenopathy not associated with hypersensitivity disorder.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Esophagitis.



   Hepatobiliary Tract and Pancreas  



 Pancreatitis.



   Immunologic  



 Lupus-like reaction, vasculitis.



   Lower Respiratory  



 Apnea.



   Musculoskeletal  



 Rhabdomyolysis has been observed in patients experiencing hypersensitivity reactions.



   Nervous System  



 Aggression, exacerbation of Parkinsonian symptoms in patients with pre-existing Parkinson's disease, nightmares, tics.



   Non-site Specific  



 Progressive immunosuppression.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SERIOUS SKIN RASHES

  WARNING: SERIOUS SKIN RASHES

    LAMICTAL  (r)   can cause serious rashes requiring hospitalization and discontinuation of treatment. The incidence of these rashes, which have included Stevens-Johnson syndrome, is approximately 0.3% to 0.8% in pediatric patients (aged 2 to 17 years) and 0.08% to 0.3% in adults receiving LAMICTAL. One rash-related death was reported in a prospectively followed cohort of 1,983 pediatric patients (aged 2 to 16 years) with epilepsy taking LAMICTAL as adjunctive therapy. In worldwide postmarketing experience, rare cases of toxic epidermal necrolysis and/or rash-related death have been reported in adult and pediatric patients, but their numbers are too few to permit a precise estimate of the rate.  



   Other than age, there are as yet no factors identified that are known to predict the risk of occurrence or the severity of rash caused by LAMICTAL. There are suggestions, yet to be proven, that the risk of rash may also be increased by (1) coadministration of LAMICTAL with valproate (includes valproic acid and divalproex sodium), (2) exceeding the recommended initial dose of LAMICTAL, or (3) exceeding the recommended dose escalation for LAMICTAL. However, cases have occurred in the absence of these factors.  



   Nearly all cases of life-threatening rashes caused by LAMICTAL have occurred within 2 to 8 weeks of treatment initiation. However, isolated cases have occurred after prolonged treatment (e.g., 6 months). Accordingly, duration of therapy cannot be relied upon as means to predict the potential risk heralded by the first appearance of a rash.  



   Although benign rashes are also caused by LAMICTAL, it is not possible to predict reliably which rashes will prove to be serious or life threatening. Accordingly, LAMICTAL should ordinarily be discontinued at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug related. Discontinuation of treatment may not prevent a rash from becoming life threatening or permanently disabling or disfiguring   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SERIOUS SKIN RASHES



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Cases of life-threatening serious rashes, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis, and/or rash-related death have been caused by lamotrigine. The rate of serious rash is greater in pediatric patients than in adults. Additional factors that may increase the risk of rash include:ocoadministration with valproate.oexceeding recommended initial dose of LAMICTAL.oexceeding recommended dose escalation for LAMICTAL. (5.1) 
 *  Benign rashes are also caused by lamotrigine; however, it is not possible to predict which rashes will prove to be serious or life threatening. LAMICTAL should be discontinued at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug related. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Life-threatening serious rash and/or rash-related death: Discontinue at the first sign of rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug related. (Boxed Warning,  5.1  ) 
 *    Fatal or life-threatening hypersensitivity reaction: Multiorgan hypersensitivity reactions, also known as drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms, may be fatal or life threatening. Early signs may include rash, fever, and lymphadenopathy. These reactions may be associated with other organ involvement, such as hepatitis, hepatic failure, blood dyscrasias, or acute multiorgan failure. LAMICTAL should be discontinued if alternate etiology for this reaction is not found. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Blood dyscrasias (e.g., neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, pancytopenia): May occur, either with or without an associated hypersensitivity syndrome. Monitor for signs of anemia, unexpected infection, or bleeding. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Suicidal behavior and ideation: Monitor for suicidal thoughts or behaviors. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Aseptic meningitis: Monitor for signs of meningitis. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Medication errors due to product name confusion: Strongly advise patients to visually inspect tablets to verify the received drug is correct. (  5.6  ,  16  ,  17  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Skin Rashes [see Boxed Warning]  



   Pediatric Population  



 The incidence of serious rash associated with hospitalization and discontinuation of LAMICTAL in a prospectively followed cohort of pediatric patients (aged 2 to 17 years) is approximately 0.3% to 0.8%. One rash-related death was reported in a prospectively followed cohort of 1,983 pediatric patients (aged 2 to 16 years) with epilepsy taking LAMICTAL as adjunctive therapy. Additionally, there have been rare cases of toxic epidermal necrolysis with and without permanent sequelae and/or death in US and foreign postmarketing experience.



 There is evidence that the inclusion of valproate in a multidrug regimen increases the risk of serious, potentially life-threatening rash in pediatric patients. In pediatric patients who used valproate concomitantly for epilepsy, 1.2% (6 of 482) experienced a serious rash compared with 0.6% (6 of 952) patients not taking valproate.



  Adult Population  



 Serious rash associated with hospitalization and discontinuation of LAMICTAL occurred in 0.3% (11 of 3,348) of adult patients who received LAMICTAL in premarketing clinical trials of epilepsy. In the bipolar and other mood disorders clinical trials, the rate of serious rash was 0.08% (1 of 1,233) of adult patients who received LAMICTAL as initial monotherapy and 0.13% (2 of 1,538) of adult patients who received LAMICTAL as adjunctive therapy. No fatalities occurred among these individuals. However, in worldwide postmarketing experience, rare cases of rash-related death have been reported, but their numbers are too few to permit a precise estimate of the rate.



 Among the rashes leading to hospitalization were Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, angioedema, and those associated with multiorgan hypersensitivity [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



 There is evidence that the inclusion of valproate in a multidrug regimen increases the risk of serious, potentially life-threatening rash in adults. Specifically, of 584 patients administered LAMICTAL with valproate in epilepsy clinical trials, 6 (1%) were hospitalized in association with rash; in contrast, 4 (0.16%) of 2,398 clinical trial patients and volunteers administered LAMICTAL in the absence of valproate were hospitalized.



  Patients with History of Allergy or Rash to Other Antiepileptic Drugs  



 The risk of nonserious rash may be increased when the recommended initial dose and/or the rate of dose escalation for LAMICTAL is exceeded and in patients with a history of allergy or rash to other AEDs.



    5.2 Multiorgan Hypersensitivity Reactions and Organ Failure



  Multiorgan hypersensitivity reactions, also known as drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), have occurred with LAMICTAL. Some have been fatal or life threatening. DRESS typically, although not exclusively, presents with fever, rash, and/or lymphadenopathy in association with other organ system involvement, such as hepatitis, nephritis, hematologic abnormalities, myocarditis, or myositis, sometimes resembling an acute viral infection. Eosinophilia is often present. This disorder is variable in its expression, and other organ systems not noted here may be involved.



 Fatalities associated with acute multiorgan failure and various degrees of hepatic failure have been reported in 2 of 3,796 adult patients and 4 of 2,435 pediatric patients who received LAMICTAL in epilepsy clinical trials. Rare fatalities from multiorgan failure have also been reported in postmarketing use.



 Isolated liver failure without rash or involvement of other organs has also been reported with LAMICTAL.



 It is important to note that early manifestations of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may be present even though a rash is not evident. If such signs or symptoms are present, the patient should be evaluated immediately. LAMICTAL should be discontinued if an alternative etiology for the signs or symptoms cannot be established.



 Prior to initiation of treatment with LAMICTAL, the patient should be instructed that a rash or other signs or symptoms of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may herald a serious medical event and that the patient should report any such occurrence to a healthcare provider immediately.



    5.3 Blood Dyscrasias



  There have been reports of blood dyscrasias that may or may not be associated with multiorgan hypersensitivity (also known as DRESS) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  . These have included neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, pancytopenia, and, rarely, aplastic anemia and pure red cell aplasia.



    5.4 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  AEDs, including LAMICTAL, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (monotherapy and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to 1 of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI: 1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared with patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared with 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately 1 case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were 4 suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number of events is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as 1 week after starting treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanism of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5 to 100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.



 Table 7 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



  Table 7. Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis  




  Indication    Placebo Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients    Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients    Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients    Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients    
  Epilepsy     1.0                3.4                3.5                              2.4                       
  Psychiatric    5.7                8.5                1.5                              2.9                       
  Other        1.0                1.8                1.9                              0.9                       
  Total        2.4                4.3                1.8                              1.9                       
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing LAMICTAL or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, the emergence of suicidal thoughts or suicidal behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis



  Therapy with LAMICTAL increases the risk of developing aseptic meningitis. Because of the potential for serious outcomes of untreated meningitis due to other causes, patients should also be evaluated for other causes of meningitis and treated as appropriate.



 Postmarketing cases of aseptic meningitis have been reported in pediatric and adult patients taking LAMICTAL for various indications. Symptoms upon presentation have included headache, fever, nausea, vomiting, and nuchal rigidity. Rash, photophobia, myalgia, chills, altered consciousness, and somnolence were also noted in some cases. Symptoms have been reported to occur within 1 day to one and a half months following the initiation of treatment. In most cases, symptoms were reported to resolve after discontinuation of LAMICTAL. Re-exposure resulted in a rapid return of symptoms (from within 30 minutes to 1 day following re-initiation of treatment) that were frequently more severe. Some of the patients treated with LAMICTAL who developed aseptic meningitis had underlying diagnoses of systemic lupus erythematosus or other autoimmune diseases.



 Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) analyzed at the time of clinical presentation in reported cases was characterized by a mild to moderate pleocytosis, normal glucose levels, and mild to moderate increase in protein. CSF white blood cell count differentials showed a predominance of neutrophils in a majority of the cases, although a predominance of lymphocytes was reported in approximately one third of the cases. Some patients also had new onset of signs and symptoms of involvement of other organs (predominantly hepatic and renal involvement), which may suggest that in these cases the aseptic meningitis observed was part of a hypersensitivity reaction [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



    5.6 Potential Medication Errors



  Medication errors involving LAMICTAL have occurred. In particular, the names LAMICTAL or lamotrigine can be confused with the names of other commonly used medications. Medication errors may also occur between the different formulations of LAMICTAL. To reduce the potential of medication errors, write and say LAMICTAL clearly. Depictions of the LAMICTAL tablets, chewable dispersible tablets, and orally disintegrating tablets can be found in the Medication Guide that accompanies the product to highlight the distinctive markings, colors, and shapes that serve to identify the different presentations of the drug and thus may help reduce the risk of medication errors. To avoid the medication error of using the wrong drug or formulation, patients should be strongly advised to visually inspect their tablets to verify that they are LAMICTAL, as well as the correct formulation of LAMICTAL, each time they fill their prescription.



    5.7 Concomitant Use with Oral Contraceptives



  Some estrogen-containing oral contraceptives have been shown to decrease serum concentrations of lamotrigine [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  . Dosage adjustments will be necessary in most patients who start or stop estrogen-containing oral contraceptives while taking LAMICTAL [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  . During the week of inactive hormone preparation (pill-free week) of oral contraceptive therapy, plasma lamotrigine levels are expected to rise, as much as doubling at the end of the week. Adverse reactions consistent with elevated levels of lamotrigine, such as dizziness, ataxia, and diplopia, could occur.



    5.8 Withdrawal Seizures



  As with other AEDs, LAMICTAL should not be abruptly discontinued. In patients with epilepsy there is a possibility of increasing seizure frequency. In clinical trials in adults with bipolar disorder, 2 patients experienced seizures shortly after abrupt withdrawal of LAMICTAL. Unless safety concerns require a more rapid withdrawal, the dose of LAMICTAL should be tapered over a period of at least 2 weeks (approximately 50% reduction per week) [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  .



    5.9 Status Epilepticus



  Valid estimates of the incidence of treatment-emergent status epilepticus among patients treated with LAMICTAL are difficult to obtain because reporters participating in clinical trials did not all employ identical rules for identifying cases. At a minimum, 7 of 2,343 adult patients had episodes that could unequivocally be described as status epilepticus. In addition, a number of reports of variably defined episodes of seizure exacerbation (e.g., seizure clusters, seizure flurries) were made.



    5.10 Sudden Unexplained Death in Epilepsy (SUDEP)



  During the premarketing development of LAMICTAL, 20 sudden and unexplained deaths were recorded among a cohort of 4,700 patients with epilepsy (5,747 patient-years of exposure).



 Some of these could represent seizure-related deaths in which the seizure was not observed, e.g., at night. This represents an incidence of 0.0035 deaths per patient-year. Although this rate exceeds that expected in a healthy population matched for age and sex, it is within the range of estimates for the incidence of sudden unexplained death in epilepsy (SUDEP) in patients not receiving LAMICTAL (ranging from 0.0005 for the general population of patients with epilepsy, to 0.004 for a recently studied clinical trial population similar to that in the clinical development program for LAMICTAL, to 0.005 for patients with refractory epilepsy). Consequently, whether these figures are reassuring or suggest concern depends on the comparability of the populations reported upon with the cohort receiving LAMICTAL and the accuracy of the estimates provided. Probably most reassuring is the similarity of estimated SUDEP rates in patients receiving LAMICTAL and those receiving other AEDs, chemically unrelated to each other, that underwent clinical testing in similar populations. Importantly, that drug is chemically unrelated to LAMICTAL. This evidence suggests, although it certainly does not prove, that the high SUDEP rates reflect population rates, not a drug effect.



    5.11 Addition of LAMICTAL to a Multidrug Regimen that Includes Valproate



  Because valproate reduces the clearance of lamotrigine, the dosage of LAMICTAL in the presence of valproate is less than half of that required in its absence [see Dosage and Administration (2.2, 2.3, 2.4), Drug Interactions (7)]  .



    5.12 Binding in the Eye and Other Melanin-Containing Tissues



  Because lamotrigine binds to melanin, it could accumulate in melanin-rich tissues over time. This raises the possibility that lamotrigine may cause toxicity in these tissues after extended use. Although ophthalmological testing was performed in 1 controlled clinical trial, the testing was inadequate to exclude subtle effects or injury occurring after long-term exposure. Moreover, the capacity of available tests to detect potentially adverse consequences, if any, of lamotrigine's binding to melanin is unknown [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  .



 Accordingly, although there are no specific recommendations for periodic ophthalmological monitoring, prescribers should be aware of the possibility of long-term ophthalmologic effects.



    5.13 Laboratory Tests



   False-Positive Drug Test Results  



 Lamotrigine has been reported to interfere with the assay used in some rapid urine drug screens, which can result in false-positive readings, particularly for phencyclidine (PCP). A more specific analytical method should be used to confirm a positive result.



  Plasma Concentrations of Lamotrigine  



 The value of monitoring plasma concentrations of lamotrigine in patients treated with LAMICTAL has not been established. Because of the possible pharmacokinetic interactions between lamotrigine and other drugs, including AEDs (see Table 13), monitoring of the plasma levels of lamotrigine and concomitant drugs may be indicated, particularly during dosage adjustments. In general, clinical judgment should be exercised regarding monitoring of plasma levels of lamotrigine and other drugs and whether or not dosage adjustments are necessary.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
