<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lansoprazole" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Lansoprazole/amoxicillin/clarithromycin  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3%) reported in clinical trials when all three components of this therapy were given concomitantly for 14 days are listed in Table 5.




  Table 5: Adverse Reactions Most Frequently Reported in Clinical Trials (&gt;=3%)    
  Adverse Reaction                                        Triple Therapy                                  
  n=138(%)                                                
  Diarrhea                                                7.0                                             
  Headache                                                6.0                                             
  Taste Perversion                                        5.0                                             
        The additional adverse reactions which were reported as possibly or probably related to treatment (less than 3%) in clinical trials when all three components of this therapy were given concomitantly are listed below and divided by body system:
 

   Body as a Whole  - abdominal pain  Digestive System  - dark stools, dry mouth/thirst, glossitis, rectal itching, nausea, oral moniliasis, stomatitis, tongue discoloration, tongue disorder, vomiting  Musculoskeletal System  - myalgia  Nervous System  - confusion, dizziness  Respiratory System  - respiratory disorders  Skin and Appendages  - skin reactions  Urogenital System  - vaginitis, vaginal moniliasis



 There were no statistically significant differences in the frequency of reported adverse events between the 10- and 14-day triple therapy regimens.



   Lansoprazole  



 The following adverse reactions from the labeling for lansoprazole are provided for information:



 Worldwide, over 10,000 patients have been treated with lansoprazole in Phase 2 or Phase 3 clinical trials involving various dosages and durations of treatment. In general, lansoprazole treatment has been well-tolerated in both short-term and long-term trials.



   Incidence in Clinical Trials

  The following adverse events were reported by the treating physician to have a possible or probable relationship to drug in 1% or more of lansoprazole-treated patients and occurred at a greater rate in lansoprazole-treated patients than placebo-treated patients:




  Table 6: Incidence of Possibly or Probably Treatment-Related Adverse Reactions in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Lansoprazole Studies    
  Body System/Adverse Event                           Lansoprazole(N= 2768)%        Placebo(N= 1023)%       
  Body as a Whole   Abdominal Pain                    2.1                           1.2                     
  Digestive System   Constipation   Diarrhea   Nausea    1.03.81.3                     0.42.31.2               
         Headache was also seen at greater than 1% incidence but was more common on placebo. The incidence of diarrhea was similar between patients who received placebo and patients who received 30 mg of lansoprazole, but higher in the patients who received 60 mg of lansoprazole (2.9%, 4.2%, and 7.4%, respectively).
 

 The most commonly reported possibly or probably treatment-related adverse event during maintenance therapy was diarrhea.



 Additional adverse experiences occurring in less than 1% of patients or subjects who received lansoprazole in domestic trials are shown below:



   Body as a Whole  - abdomen enlarged, allergic reaction, asthenia, back pain, candidiasis, carcinoma, chest pain (not otherwise specified), chills, edema, fever, flu syndrome, halitosis, infection (not otherwise specified), malaise, neck pain, neck rigidity, pain, pelvic pain



   Cardiovascular System  - angina, arrhythmia, bradycardia, cerebrovascular accident/cerebral infarction, hypertension/hypotension, migraine, myocardial infarction, palpitations, shock (circulatory failure), syncope, tachycardia, vasodilation



   Digestive System  - abnormal stools, anorexia, bezoar, cardiospasm, cholelithiasis, colitis, dry mouth, dyspepsia, dysphagia, enteritis, eructation, esophageal stenosis, esophageal ulcer, esophagitis, fecal discoloration, flatulence, gastric nodules/fundic gland polyps, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal anomaly, gastrointestinal disorder, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, glossitis, gum hemorrhage, hematemesis, increased appetite, increased salivation, melena, mouth ulceration, nausea and vomiting, nausea and vomiting and diarrhea, gastrointestinal moniliasis, rectal disorder, rectal hemorrhage, stomatitis, tenesmus, thirst, tongue disorder, ulcerative colitis, ulcerative stomatitis



   Endocrine System  - diabetes mellitus, goiter, hypothyroidism



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  - anemia, hemolysis, lymphadenopathy



   Metabolism and Nutritional Disorders  - avitaminosis, gout, dehydration, hyperglycemia/hypoglycemia, peripheral edema, weight gain/loss



   Musculoskeletal System  - arthralgia, arthritis, bone disorder, joint disorder, leg cramps, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia, myasthenia, ptosis, synovitis



   Nervous System  - abnormal dreams, agitation, amnesia, anxiety, apathy, confusion, convulsion, dementia, depersonalization, depression, diplopia, dizziness, emotional lability, hallucinations, hemiplegia, hostility aggravated, hyperkinesia, hypertonia, hypesthesia, insomnia, libido decreased/increased, nervousness, neurosis, paresthesia, sleep disorder, somnolence, thinking abnormality, tremor, vertigo



   Respiratory System  - asthma, bronchitis, cough increased, dyspnea, epistaxis, hemoptysis, hiccup, laryngeal neoplasia, lung fibrosis, pharyngitis, pleural disorder, pneumonia, respiratory disorder, upper respiratory inflammation/infection, rhinitis, sinusitis, stridor



   Skin and Appendages  - acne, alopecia, contact dermatitis, dry skin, fixed eruption, hair disorder, maculopapular rash, nail disorder, pruritus, rash, skin carcinoma, skin disorder, sweating, urticaria



   Special Senses  - abnormal vision, amblyopia, blepharitis, blurred vision, cataract, conjunctivitis, deafness, dry eyes, ear/eye disorder, eye pain, glaucoma, otitis media, parosmia, photophobia, retinal degeneration/disorder, taste loss, taste perversion, tinnitus, visual field defect



   Urogenital System  - abnormal menses, breast enlargement, breast pain, breast tenderness, dysmenorrhea, dysuria, gynecomastia, impotence, kidney calculus, kidney pain, leukorrhea, menorrhagia, menstrual disorder, penis disorder, polyuria, testis disorder, urethral pain, urinary frequency, urinary retention, urinary tract infection, urinary urgency, urination impaired, vaginitis



   Postmarketing

  Additional adverse experiences have been reported since lansoprazole has been marketed. The majority of these cases are foreign-sourced and a relationship to lansoprazole has not been established. Because these events were reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These events are listed below by COSTART body system:



   Body as a Whole  - anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions  Digestive System  - hepatotoxicity, pancreatitis, vomiting  Hemic and Lymphatic System  - agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, neutropenia, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenia, and thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura  Infections and infestations  -  Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea  Metabolism and Nutritional Disorders  - hypomagnesemia  Musculoskeletal System  - bone fracture, myositis  Skin and Appendages  - severe dermatologic reactions including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, (some fatal)  Special Senses  - speech disorder  Urogenital System  - interstitial nephritis, urinary retention



   Amoxicillin

  The following adverse reactions from the labeling for amoxicillin are provided for information:



 As with other penicillins, it may be expected that untoward reactions will be essentially limited to sensitivity phenomena. They are more likely to occur in individuals who have previously demonstrated hypersensitivity to penicillins and in those with a history of allergy, asthma, hay fever, or urticaria. The following adverse reactions have been reported as associated with the use of penicillins:



   Infections and Infestations  -  Mucocutaneous candidiasis  



   Gastrointestinal  - Nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, black hairy tongue, and hemorrhagic/pseudomembranous colitis.



 Onset of pseudomembranous colitis symptoms may occur during or after antibiotic treatment (see    WARNINGS    ).



   Hypersensitivity Reactions  - Anaphylaxis (see    WARNINGS    ), serum sickness-like reactions, erythematous maculopapular rashes, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis, toxic epidermal necrolysis, acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, hypersensitivity vasculitis and urticaria have been reported.



   Liver  - A moderate rise in AST (SGOT) and/or ALT (SGPT) has been noted, but the significance of this finding is unknown. Hepatic dysfunction including cholestatic jaundice, hepatic cholestasis and acute cytolytic hepatitis have been reported.



   Renal  - Crystalluria has also been reported (see    OVERDOSAGE    ).



   Hemic and Lymphatic Systems  - Anemia, including hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, thrombocytopenic purpura, eosinophilia, leukopenia and agranulocytosis have been reported during therapy with penicillins. These reactions are usually reversible on discontinuation of therapy and are believed to be hypersensitivity phenomena.



   Central Nervous System  - Reversible hyperactivity, agitation, anxiety, insomnia, confusion, behavioral changes, and/or dizziness have been reported rarely.



   Miscellaneous  - Tooth discoloration (brown, yellow, or gray staining) has been rarely reported. Most reports occurred in pediatric patients. Discoloration was reduced or eliminated with brushing or dental cleaning in most cases.



   Clarithromycin  



 The following adverse reactions from the labeling for clarithromycin are provided for information:



 The majority of adverse reactions observed in clinical trials were of a mild and transient nature. Fewer than 3% of adult patients without mycobacterial infections discontinued therapy because of drug-related side effects.



 The most frequently reported events in adults were diarrhea (3%), nausea (3%), abnormal taste (3%), dyspepsia (2%), abdominal pain/discomfort (2%), and headache (2%). Most of these events were described as mild or moderate in severity. Of the reported adverse events, only 1% was described as severe.



 The following post-marketing adverse reactions from the labeling for clarithromycin are provided for information:



 Allergic reactions ranging from urticaria and mild skin eruptions to cases of anaphylaxis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, drug rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), Henoch-Schonlein Purpura and toxic epidermal necrolysis have occurred. Other spontaneously reported adverse reactions include glossitis, stomatitis, oral moniliasis, anorexia, vomiting, pancreatitis, tongue discoloration, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, neutropenia, dizziness, myalgia and hemorrhage. There have been reports of tooth discoloration in patients treated with clarithromycin. Tooth discoloration is usually reversible with professional dental cleaning. There have been isolated reports of hearing loss, which is usually reversible, occurring chiefly in elderly women. Reports of alterations of the sense of smell including smell loss, usually in conjunction with taste perversion or taste loss have also been reported.



 Transient CNS events including anxiety, behavioral changes, confusional states, convulsions, depersonalization, disorientation, hallucinations, insomnia, depression, manic behavior, nightmares, psychosis, tinnitus, tremor, and vertigo have been reported during postmarketing surveillance. Events usually resolve with discontinuation of the drug.



 Adverse reactions related to hepatic dysfunction have been reported in postmarketing experience with clarithromycin (see      WARNINGS, Hepatotoxicity      ).



 There have been rare reports of hypoglycemia, some of which have occurred in patients taking oral hypoglycemic agents or insulin.



 As with other macrolides, clarithromycin has been associated with QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmias, including ventricular tachycardia and torsades de pointes.



 There have been reports of interstitial nephritis coincident with clarithromycin use.



 There have been post-marketing reports of colchicine toxicity with concomitant use of clarithromycin and colchicine, especially in the elderly, some of which occurred in patients with renal insufficiency. Deaths have been reported in some such patients (see    WARNINGS    and    PRECAUTIONS    ).



 There have been cases of rhabdomyolysis reported with clarithromycin use. In some cases, clarithromycin was administered concomitantly with other drugs known to be associated with rhabdomyolysis (such as statins, fibrates, colchicine or allopurinol).



   Laboratory Values

    Lansoprazole  



 The following changes in laboratory parameters in patients who received lansoprazole were reported as adverse reactions:



 Abnormal liver function tests, increased SGOT (AST), increased SGPT (ALT), increased creatinine, increased alkaline phosphatase, increased globulins, increased GGTP, increased/decreased/abnormal WBC, abnormal AG ratio, abnormal RBC, bilirubinemia, blood potassium increased, blood urea increased, crystal urine present, eosinophilia, hemoglobin decreased, hyperlipemia, increased/decreased electrolytes, increased/decreased cholesterol, increased glucocorticoids, increased LDH, increased/decreased/abnormal platelets, increased gastrin levels and positive fecal occult blood. Urine abnormalities such as albuminuria, glycosuria, and hematuria were also reported.



 In the placebo-controlled studies, when SGOT (AST) and SGPT (ALT) were evaluated, 0.4% (4/978) and 0.4% (11/2677) patients, who received placebo and lansoprazole, respectively, had enzyme elevations greater than three times the upper limit of normal range at the final treatment visit. None of these patients who received lansoprazole reported jaundice at any time during the study.



   Clarithromycin  



 Changes in laboratory values due to clarithromycin with possible clinical significance were as follows:



   Hepatic  - elevated SGPT (ALT) &lt;1%, SGOT (AST) &lt;1%, GGT &lt;1%, alkaline phosphatase &lt;1%, LDH &lt;1%, total bilirubin &lt;1%



   Hematologic  - decreased WBC &lt;1%, elevated prothrombin time 1%



   Renal  - elevated BUN 4%, elevated serum creatinine &lt;1%



 GGT, alkaline phosphatase, and prothrombin time data are from adult studies only.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
