<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lantus" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere:



 *  Hypoglycemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity and allergic reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hypokalemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ].  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions commonly associated with LANTUS include hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, injection site reactions, lipodystrophy, pruritus, rash, edema and weight gain. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi- aventis at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trial of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data in Table 1 reflect the exposure of 2327 patients with type 1 diabetes to LANTUS or NPH. The type 1 diabetes population had the following characteristics: Mean age was 38.5 years. Fifty four percent were male, 96.9% were Caucasian, 1.8 % were Black or African American and 2.7 % were Hispanic. The mean BMI was 25.1 kg/m  2  .



 The data in Table 2 reflect the exposure of 1563 patients with type 2 diabetes to LANTUS or NPH. The type 2 diabetes population had the following characteristics: Mean age was 59.3 years. Fifty eight percent were male, 86.7% were Caucasian, 7.8 % were Black or African American and 9 % were Hispanic. The mean BMI was 29.2 kg/m  2  .



 The frequencies of adverse events during LANTUS clinical trials in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus are listed in the tables below.



 Table 1: Adverse events in pooled clinical trials up to 28 weeks duration in adults with type 1 diabetes (adverse events with frequency &gt;=5%) 
                                                 LANTUS, %(n=1257)                 NPH, %(n=1070)           
  
 Upper respiratory tract infection                      22.4                            23.1                
 Infection                                              9.4                             10.3                
 Accidental injury                                      5.7                             6.4                 
 Headache                                               5.5                             4.7                 
        Table 2: Adverse events in pooled clinical trials up to 1 year duration in adults with type 2 diabetes (adverse events with frequency &gt;= 5%) 
                                                  LANTUS, %(n=849)                 NPH, %(n=714)            
  
 Upper respiratory tract infection                      11.4                            13.3                
 Infection                                              10.4                            11.6                
 Retinal vascular disorder                              5.8                             7.4                 
        Table 3: Adverse events in a 5-year trial of adults with type 2 diabetes (adverse events with frequency &gt;= 10%) 
                                                  LANTUS, %(n=514)                 NPH, %(n=503)            
  
 Upper respiratory tract infection                      29.0                            33.6                
 Edema peripheral                                       20.0                            22.7                
 Hypertension                                           19.6                            18.9                
 Influenza                                              18.7                            19.5                
 Sinusitis                                              18.5                            17.9                
 Cataract                                               18.1                            15.9                
 Bronchitis                                             15.2                            14.1                
 Arthralgia                                             14.2                            16.1                
 Pain in extremity                                      13.0                            13.1                
 Back pain                                              12.8                            12.3                
 Cough                                                  12.1                            7.4                 
 Urinary tract infection                                10.7                            10.1                
 Diarrhea                                               10.7                            10.3                
 Depression                                             10.5                            9.7                 
 Headache                                               10.3                            9.3                 
        Table 4: Adverse events in a 28-week clinical trial of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes (adverse events with frequency &gt;= 5% ) 
                                                  LANTUS, %(n=174)                 NPH, %(n=175)            
  
 Infection                                              13.8                            17.7                
 Upper respiratory tract infection                      13.8                            16.0                
 Pharyngitis                                            7.5                             8.6                 
 Rhinitis                                               5.2                             5.1                 
             Severe Hypoglycemia  
 

 Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin, including LANTUS  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  . Tables 5, and 6 and 7 summarize the incidence of severe hypoglycemia in the LANTUS individual clinical trials. Severe symptomatic hypoglycemia was defined as an event with symptoms consistent with hypoglycemia requiring the assistance of another person and associated with either a blood glucose below 50 mg/dL (&lt;=56 mg/dL in the 5-year trial and &lt;=36 mg/dL in the ORIGIN trial) or prompt recovery after oral carbohydrate, intravenous glucose or glucagon administration.



 Percentages of LANTUS-treated adult patients experiencing severe symptomatic hypoglycemia in the LANTUS clinical trials  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  were comparable to percentages of NPH-treated patients for all treatment regimens (see  Tables 5  and  6  ). In the pediatric phase 3 clinical trial, children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes had a higher incidence of severe symptomatic hypoglycemia in the two treatment groups compared to the adult trials with type 1 diabetes.



 Table 5: Severe Symptomatic Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 1 Diabetes 
               Study AType 1 DiabetesAdults28 weeksIn combination with regular insulin  Study BType 1 DiabetesAdults28 weeksIn combination with regular insulin  Study CType 1 DiabetesAdults16 weeksIn combination with insulin lispro  Study DType 1 DiabetesPediatrics26 weeksIn combination with regular insulin   
               LANTUSN=292   NPHN=293    LANTUSN=264   NPHN=270    LANTUSN=310   NPHN=309    LANTUSN=174   NPHN=175     
  
 Percent of patients     10.6         15.0          8.7         10.4          6.5          5.2         23.0         28.6       
              Table 6: Severe Symptomatic Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes 
               Study EType 2 DiabetesAdults52 weeksIn combination with oral agents  Study FType 2 DiabetesAdults28 weeksIn combination with regular insulin  Study GType 2 DiabetesAdults5 yearsIn combination with regular insulin   
                LANTUSN=289       NPHN=281       LANTUSN=259        NPHN=259        LANTUSN=513       NPHN=504      
  
 Percent of patients       1.7             1.1              0.4              2.3               7.8             11.9        
             Table 7 displays the proportion of patients experiencing severe symptomatic hypoglycemia in the Lantus and Standard Care groups in the ORIGIN Trial  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .
 

 Table 7: Severe Symptomatic Hypoglycemia in the ORIGIN trial 
                                      ORIGIN TrialMedian duration of follow-up: 6.2 years   
                                               LANTUSN=6231                   Standard CareN=6273           
  
 Percent of patients                               5.6                                1.8                   
             Peripheral Edema  
 

 Some patients taking LANTUS have experienced sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy.



     Lipodystrophy  



 Administration of insulin subcutaneously, including LANTUS, has resulted in lipoatrophy (depression in the skin) or lipohypertrophy (enlargement or thickening of tissue) in some patients  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ].  



     Insulin initiation and intensification of glucose control  



 Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with a transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. However, long-term glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.



     Weight gain  



 Weight gain has occurred with some insulin therapies including LANTUS and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin and the decrease in glucosuria.



     Allergic Reactions  



     Local Allergy  



 As with any insulin therapy, patients taking LANTUS may experience injection site reactions, including redness, pain, itching, urticaria, edema, and inflammation. In clinical studies in adult patients, there was a higher incidence of treatment-emergent injection site pain in LANTUS-treated patients (2.7%) compared to NPH insulin-treated patients (0.7%). The reports of pain at the injection site did not result in discontinuation of therapy.



     Systemic Allergy  



 Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, generalized skin reactions, angioedema, bronchospasm, hypotension, and shock may occur with any insulin, including LANTUS and may be life threatening.



   6.2 Immunogenicity

  As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. All insulin products can elicit the formation of insulin antibodies. The presence of such insulin antibodies may increase or decrease the efficacy of insulin and may require adjustment of the insulin dose. In phase 3 clinical trials of LANTUS, increases in titers of antibodies to insulin were observed in NPH insulin and LANTUS treatment groups with similar incidences.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of LANTUS. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Medication errors have been reported in which other insulins, particularly rapid-acting insulins, have been accidentally administered instead of LANTUS  [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . To avoid medication errors between LANTUS and other insulins, patients should be instructed to always verify the insulin label before each injection.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Never share a LANTUS SoloStar prefilled pen between patients, even if the needle is changed (  5.1  ) 
 *   Hyper- or hypoglycemia with changes in insulin regimen: Carry out under close medical supervision (  5.2  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia: May be life-threatening. Increase frequency of glucose monitoring with changes to: insulin dosage, co-administered glucose lowering medications, meal pattern, physical activity; and in patients with renal or hepatic impairment and hypoglycemia unawareness (  5.3  ,  6.1  ) 
 *   Medication Errors: Accidental mix-ups between insulin products can occur. Instruct patients to check insulin labels before injection. (  5.4  ,  6.3  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions : Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur. Discontinue LANTUS. Monitor and treat if indicated (  5.5  ,  6.1  ) 
 *   Hypokalemia: May be life-threatening. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk of hypokalemia and treat if indicated. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Fluid retention and heart failure with concomitant use of thiazolidinediones (TZDs) : Observe for signs and symptoms of heart failure; consider dosage reduction or discontinuation of TZD if heart failure occurs (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Never Share a LANTUS SoloStar Prefilled Pen, Syringe, or Needle between Patients



   LANTUS SoloStar prefilled pens must never be shared between patients, even if the needle is changed. Patients using LANTUS vials must never reuse or share needles or syringes with another person. Sharing poses a risk for transmission of blood-borne pathogens.  



    5.2 Hyperglycemia or Hypoglycemia with Changes in Insulin Regimen



   Changes in insulin strength, manufacturer, type, or method of administration may affect glycemic control and predispose to hypoglycemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  or hyperglycemia. These changes should be made cautiously and only under close medical supervision, and the frequency of blood glucose monitoring should be increased. For patients with type 2 diabetes, dosage adjustments of concomitant oral and anti-diabetic products may be needed.  



    5.3 Hypoglycemia



   Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction associated with insulin, including LANTUS. Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening or cause death. Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving or operating other machinery).  



  Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual. Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic nerve disease, in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers) [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  , or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia.  



     Risk Factors for Hypoglycemia    



  The risk of hypoglycemia after an injection is related to the duration of action of the insulin and, in general, is highest when the glucose lowering effect of the insulin is maximal. As with all insulin preparations, the glucose lowering effect time course of LANTUS may vary in different individuals or at different times in the same individual and depends on many conditions, including the area of injection as well as the injection site blood supply and temperature [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ].  Other factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content or timing of meals), changes in level of physical activity, or changes to co-administered medication [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia [See  Use in Specific Populations (8.6  ,  8.7)  ].    



     Risk Mitigation Strategies for Hypoglycemia    



  Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia. In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended.  



  The long-acting effect of LANTUS may delay recovery from hypoglycemia.  



    5.4 Medication Errors



   Accidental mix-ups among insulin products, particularly between long-acting insulins and rapid-acting insulins, have been reported. To avoid medication errors between LANTUS and other insulins, instruct patients to always check the insulin label before each injection [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .  



    5.5 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions



   Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur with insulin products, including LANTUS. If hypersensitivity reactions occur, discontinue LANTUS; treat per standard of care and monitor until symptoms and signs resolve [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . LANTUS is contraindicated in patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to insulin glargine or one of the excipients [ see  Contraindications (4)  ].    



    5.6 Hypokalemia



   All insulin products, including LANTUS, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia. Untreated hypokalemia may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia if indicated (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications, patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations).  



    5.7 Fluid Retention and Heart Failure with Concomitant Use of PPAR-gamma Agonists



  Thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists, can cause dose-related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate heart failure. Patients treated with insulin, including LANTUS, and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of heart failure. If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care, and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
