<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="latuda" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice the rate for placebo) included somnolence, akathisia, nausea, parkinsonism and agitation  (      6.2    ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sunovion Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 877-737-7226 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1. Overall Adverse Reaction Profile

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Use in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (    5.1    )]  
 *  Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Tardive Dyskinesia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Hyperprolactinemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7    )]  
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Body Temperature Regulation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
 *  Suicide [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
 *  Dysphagia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.13  )]  
 *  Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.14  )]  
    The information below is derived from a clinical study database for LATUDA consisting of over 2096 patients with schizophrenia exposed to one or more doses with a total experience of 624 patient-years. Of these patients, 1004 participated in short-term placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies with doses of 20 mg, 40 mg, 80 mg or 120 mg once daily. A total of 533 LATUDA-treated patients had at least 24 weeks and 238 LATUDA-treated patients had at least 52 weeks of exposure.
 

 Adverse events during exposure to study treatment were obtained by general inquiry and voluntarily reported adverse experiences, as well as results from physical examinations, vital signs, ECGs, weights and laboratory investigations. Adverse experiences were recorded by clinical investigators using their own terminology. In order to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events, events were grouped in standardized categories using MedDRA terminology.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. Treatment-emergent adverse events were defined as adverse experiences, which started or worsened on or after the date of the first dose through seven days after study medication discontinuation. There was no attempt to use investigator causality assessments; i.e., all events meeting the defined criteria, regardless of investigator causality are included. It is important to emphasize that, although the reactions occurred during treatment with LATUDA, they were not necessarily caused by it. The label should be read in its entirety to gain an understanding of the safety profile of LATUDA.



 The figures in the tables and tabulations cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatment, uses and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescriber with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the adverse reaction incidence in the population studied.



   6.2. Clinical Studies Experience

  The following findings are based on the short-term placebo-controlled premarketing studies for schizophrenia in which LATUDA was administered at daily doses ranging from 20 to 120 mg (n = 1004).



   

    Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions:  The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate of placebo) in patients treated with LATUDA were somnolence, akathisia, nausea, parkinsonism and agitation.



   

    Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment:  A total of 9.4% (94/1004) LATUDA-treated patients and 5.9% (27/455) of placebo-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions. There were no adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in subjects treated with LATUDA that were at least 2% and at least twice the placebo rate.



   

    Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More in LATUDA-Treated Patients:  Adverse reactions associated with the use of LATUDA (incidence of 2% or greater, rounded to the nearest percent and LATUDA incidence greater than placebo) that occurred during acute therapy (up to 6-weeks in patients with schizophrenia) are shown in Table 6.



 Table 6: Adverse Reaction in 2% or More of LATUDA-Treated Patients and That Occurred at Greater Incidence than in the Placebo-Treated Patients in Short-term Schizophrenia Studies 
   Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
   * Somnolence includes adverse event terms: hypersomnia, hypersomnolence, sedation, and somnolence    
   ** Parkinsonism includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, and tremor    
   *** Dystonia includes adverse event terms: dystonia, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, tongue spasm, torticollis, and trismus    
  
                                               Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction     
    Body System or Organ Class                 Placebo                        All LATUDA                   
       Dictionary-derived Term                 (N = 455)                      (N = 1004)                   
    Gastrointestinal Disorders               
       Nausea                                6                              12                             
       Vomiting                              6                              8                              
       Dyspepsia                             6                              8                              
       Salivary hypersecretion               &lt;1                             2                              
    General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions     
       Fatigue                               3                              4                              
    Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
       Back Pain                             3                              4                              
    Nervous System Disorders                 
       Somnolence*                           10                             22                             
       Akathisia                             3                              15                             
       Parkinsonism**                        5                              11                             
       Dystonia***                           1                              5                              
       Dizziness                             3                              5                              
    Psychiatric Disorders                    
       Insomnia                              7                              8                              
       Agitation                             3                              6                              
       Anxiety                               3                              6                              
       Restlessness                          2                              3                              
           6.3. Dose-Related Adverse Reactions
   Based on the pooled data from the placebo-controlled, short-term, fixed-dose studies, among the adverse reactions that occurred with a greater than 5% incidence in the patients treated with LATUDA, the apparent dose-related adverse reactions were akathisia and somnolence (Table 7).



 Table 7: Dose-Related Adverse Events 
                    Percentage of Subjects Reporting Reaction     
   Adverse Event Term      Placebo    (N = 455)    (%)      LATUDA    20 mg/day    (N = 71)    (%)      LATUDA    40 mg/day    (N = 360)    (%)      LATUDA    80 mg/day    (N = 282)    (%)      LATUDA    120 mg/day    (N = 291)    (%)     
  
   Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer     * Somnolence includes adverse event terms: hypersomnia, hypersomnolence, sedation, and somnolence    
  
       Akathisia   3                6                11               15               22               
       Somnolence*   10               15               19               23               26               
              6.4. Extrapyramidal Symptoms
   In the short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies, for LATUDA-treated patients, the incidence of reported EPS-related events, excluding akathisia and restlessness, was 14.7% versus 5.1% for placebo-treated patients; and the incidence of akathisia for LATUDA-treated patients was 15.0% versus 3.3% for placebo-treated patients. Akathisia appeared to be dose-related and the greatest frequency of parkinsonism and dystonia occurred with the highest dose of LATUDA, 120 mg/day (Table 8).



 Table 8: Percentage of EPS Compared to Placebo 
   Adverse Event Term      Placebo    (N = 455)    (%)      LATUDA    20 mg/day    (N = 71)    (%)      LATUDA    40 mg/day    (N = 360)    (%)      LATUDA    80 mg/day    (N = 282)    (%)      LATUDA    120 mg/day    (N = 291)    (%)     
   All EPS events    9                10               24               26               39                
   All EPS events, excluding Akathisia/Restlessness    5                6                13               11               22                
  
   Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
   * Dystonia includes adverse event terms: dystonia, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, tongue spasm, torticollis, and trismus    
   ** Parkinsonism includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, and tremor    
  
       Akathisia   3                6                11               15               22               
       Dystonia*   1                0                4                5                7                
       Parkinsonism**   5                6                10               7                17               
       Restlessness   2                1                4                1                3                
            In the short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies, data was objectively collected on the Simpson Angus Rating Scale for extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS), the Barnes Akathisia Scale (for akathisia) and the Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (for dyskinesias). The mean change from baseline for LATUDA-treated patients was comparable to placebo-treated patients, with the exception of the Barnes Akathisia Scale global score (LATUDA, 0.2; placebo, 0.0). The percentage of patients who shifted from normal to abnormal was greater in LATUDA-treated patients versus placebo for the BAS (LATUDA, 16.0%; placebo, 7.6%) and the SAS (LATUDA, 5.3%; placebo, 2.5%).
 

   

    Dystonia  



   Class Effect:  Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



 In the short-term, placebo-controlled clinical trials, dystonia occurred in 4.7% of LATUDA-treated subjects (0.0% LATUDA 20 mg, 4.2% LATUDA 40 mg, 4.6% LATUDA 80 mg and 6.5% LATUDA 120 mg) compared to 0.7% of subjects receiving placebo. Seven subjects (0.7%, 7/1004) discontinued clinical trials due to dystonic events - 4 were receiving LATUDA 80 mg/day and 3 were receiving LATUDA 120 mg/day.



   6.5. Laboratory Test Abnormalities and ECG Changes in Clinical Studies

  

    Laboratory Test Abnormalities  



 In a between-group comparison of the pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled studies, there were no clinically important changes in total cholesterol measurements; triglycerides or glucose from Baseline to Endpoint [  see Warnings and Precautions  (    5.5      )  ]. There were also no clinically important differences between LATUDA and placebo in mean change from baseline to endpoint in routine hematology, urinalysis, or serum chemistry. LATUDA was associated with a dose-related increase in prolactin concentration [  see Warnings and Precautions  (    5.6      )  ]



   Creatinine  : In short-term, placebo-controlled trials, the mean change from Baseline in creatinine was 0.06 mg/dL for LATUDA-treated patients compared to 0.03 mg/dL for placebo-treated patients. A creatinine shift from normal to high occurred in 3.1% (30/977) of LATUDA-treated patients and 1.4% (6/439) on placebo. The threshold for high creatinine value varied from &gt;= 1.1 to &gt;= 1.3 mg/dL based on the centralized laboratory definition for each study [  see Dosage in Special Population (      2.3      ); Use in Specific Populations (      8      )].  



   Transaminases:  The mean changes in AST and ALT for LATUDA- and placebo-treated patients were similar. The proportion of patients with transaminases (AST and ALT) elevations &gt;= 3 times ULN was similar for all LATUDA-treated patients (0.8% and 0.8%, respectively) to placebo-treated patients (0.9% and 1.1%, respectively).



   

    ECG Changes  



 Electrocardiogram (ECG) measurements were taken at various time points during the LATUDA clinical trial program. No post-baseline QT prolongations exceeding 500 msec were reported in patients treated with LATUDA. Within a subset of patients defined as having an increased cardiac risk, no potentially important changes in ECG parameters were observed. No cases of torsade de pointes or other severe cardiac arrhythmias were observed in the pre-marketing clinical program.



 The effects of LATUDA on the QT/QTc interval were evaluated in a dedicated QT study involving 87 clinically stable patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder, who were treated with LATUDA doses of 120 mg daily, 600 mg daily, or ziprasidone 160 mg daily. Holter monitor-derived electrocardiographic assessments were obtained over an eight hour period at baseline and steady state. No patients treated with LATUDA experienced QTc increases &gt; 60 msec from baseline, nor did any patient experience a QTc of &gt; 500 msec.



   6.6. Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of LATUDA

  Following is a list of MedDRA terms that reflect adverse reactions reported by patients treated with LATUDA at multiple doses of &gt;= 20 mg once daily during any phase of a study within the database of 2096 patients. The reactions listed are those that could be of clinical importance, as well as reactions that are plausibly drug-related on pharmacologic or other grounds. Reactions listed in Table 6 are not included. Although the reactions reported occurred during treatment with LATUDA, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Reactions are further categorized by MedDRA system organ class and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: those occurring in at least 1/100 patients (frequent) (only those not already listed in the tabulated results from placebo-controlled studies appear in this listing); those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients (infrequent); and those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients (rare).



     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:        Infrequent:      anemia;      Rare:      leukopenia, neutropenia  



     Cardiac Disorders:        Frequent:      tachycardia;      Infrequent:      AV block 1st degree, angina pectoris, bradycardia  



     Ear and Labyrinth Disorders    :    Infrequent:      vertigo  



     Eye disorders:        Frequent:      blurred vision  



     Gastrointestinal Disorders:        Frequent:      abdominal pain, diarrhea;      Infrequent:      gastritis, dysphagia  



     General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions    :    Rare      : Sudden death  



     Investigations:        Frequent:      CPK increased  



     Metabolic and Nutritional System Disorders:        Frequent:      decreased appetite  



     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:        Rare:      rhabdomyolysis  



     Nervous System Disorders:        Infrequent    :  tardive dyskinesia, cerebrovascular accident, dysarthria, syncope  ;    Rare:      neuroleptic malignant syndrome, seizure  



     Psychiatric Disorders:        Infrequent:      abnormal dreams, panic attack, sleep disorder;      Rare:      suicidal behavior  



     Renal and Urinary Disorders    :    Infrequent:      dysuria;      Rare:      renal failure  



     Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:        Infrequent:      amenorrhea, dysmenorrhea;      Rare:      breast enlargement, breast pain, galactorrhea, erectile dysfunction  



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:        Frequent:      rash, pruritus  ;    Rare:      angioedema  



     Vascular Disorders:        Infrequent:      hypertension, orthostatic hypotension  
</Section>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S2">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviors [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-related Psychosis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.23)]  
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Tardive Dyskinesia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Metabolic Changes (Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus, Dyslipidemia, and Weight Gain) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Hyperprolactinemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
 *  Body Temperature Dysregulation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
 *  Suicide [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.13  )]  
 *  Activation of Mania/Hypomania [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.14  )]  
 *  Dysphagia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.15  )]  
 *  Neurological Adverse Reactions in Patients with Parkinson's Disease or Dementia with Lewy Bodies [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.16  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate for placebo) were (  6.1  ):
 

 *  Schizophrenia: somnolence, akathisia, extrapyramidal symptoms, and nausea 
 *  Bipolar depression: akathisia, extrapyramidal symptoms, and somnolence 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sunovion Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-877-737-7226 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The information below is derived from an integrated clinical study database for LATUDA consisting of 3799 patients exposed to one or more doses of LATUDA for the treatment of schizophrenia and bipolar depression in placebo-controlled studies. This experience corresponds with a total experience of 1250.9 patient-years. A total of 1106 LATUDA-treated patients had at least 24 weeks and 371 LATUDA-treated patients had at least 52 weeks of exposure.



 Adverse events during exposure to study treatment were obtained by general inquiry and voluntarily reported adverse experiences, as well as results from physical examinations, vital signs, ECGs, weights and laboratory investigations. Adverse experiences were recorded by clinical investigators using their own terminology. In order to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events, events were grouped in standardized categories using MedDRA terminology.



     Schizophrenia  



 The following findings are based on the short-term, placebo-controlled premarketing studies for schizophrenia in which LATUDA was administered at daily doses ranging from 20 to 160 mg (n=1508).



     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions:  The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate of placebo) in patients treated with LATUDA were somnolence, akathisia, extrapyramidal symptoms, and nausea.



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment:  A total of 9.5% (143/1508) LATUDA-treated patients and 9.3% (66/708) of placebo-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions. There were no adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in subjects treated with LATUDA that were at least 2% and at least twice the placebo rate.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More in LATUDA-Treated Patients:  Adverse reactions associated with the use of LATUDA (incidence of 2% or greater, rounded to the nearest percent and LATUDA incidence greater than placebo) that occurred during acute therapy (up to 6 weeks in patients with schizophrenia) are shown in  Table 15  .



 Table 15: Adverse Reactions in 2% or More of LATUDA-Treated Patients and That Occurred at Greater Incidence than in the Placebo-Treated Patients in Short-term Schizophrenia Studies 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  * Somnolence includes adverse event terms: hypersomnia, hypersomnolence, sedation, and somnolence    
  ** Extrapyramidal symptoms includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, dystonia, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, tongue spasm, torticollis, tremor, and trismus    
  
                            Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction     
                            LATUDA      
   Body System or    Organ Class      Placebo    (N=708)    (%)      20    mg/day    (N=71)    (%)      40    mg/day    (N=487)    (%)      80    mg/day    (N=538)    (%)      120    mg/day    (N=291)    (%)      160    mg/day    (N=121)    (%)      All    LATUDA    (N=1508)    (%)     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                            
      Nausea              5            11          10          9           13          7           10             
      Vomiting            6            7           6           9           9           7           8              
      Dyspepsia           5            11          6           5           8           6           6              
      Salivary     Hypersecretion  &lt;1           1           1           2           4           2           2              
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                                            
      Back Pain           2            0           4           3           4           0           3              
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                            
      Somnolence*         7            15          16          15          26          8           17             
      Akathisia           3            6           11          12          22          7           13             
      Extrapyramidal     Disorder**  6            6           11          12          22          13          14             
      Dizziness           2            6           4           4           5           6           4              
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                            
      Insomnia            8            8           10          11          9           7           10             
      Agitation           4            10          7           3           6           5           5              
      Anxiety             4            3           6           4           7           3           5              
      Restlessness        1            1           3           1           3           2           2              
                  Dose-Related Adverse Reactions in the Schizophrenia Studies  
 

 Akathisia and extrapyramidal symptoms were dose-related. The frequency of akathisia increased with dose up to 120 mg/day (5.6% for LATUDA 20 mg, 10.7% for LATUDA 40 mg, 12.3% for LATUDA 80 mg, and 22.0% for LATUDA 120 mg). Akathisia was reported by 7.4% (9/121) of patients receiving 160 mg/day. Akathisia occurred in 3.0% of subjects receiving placebo. The frequency of extrapyramidal symptoms increased with dose up to 120 mg/day (5.6% for LATUDA 20 mg, 11.5% for LATUDA 40 mg, 11.9% for LATUDA 80 mg, and 22.0% for LATUDA 120 mg).



     Bipolar Depression (Monotherapy)  



 The following findings are based on the short-term, placebo-controlled premarketing study for bipolar depression in which LATUDA was administered at daily doses ranging from 20 to 120 mg (n=331).



     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions:  The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5%, in either dose group, and at least twice the rate of placebo) in patients treated with LATUDA were akathisia, extrapyramidal symptoms, somnolence, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and anxiety.



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment:  A total of 6.0% (20/331) LATUDA-treated patients and 5.4% (9/168) of placebo-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions. There were no adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in subjects treated with LATUDA that were at least 2% and at least twice the placebo rate.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More in LATUDA-Treated Patients:  Adverse reactions associated with the use of LATUDA (incidence of 2% or greater, rounded to the nearest percent and LATUDA incidence greater than placebo) that occurred during acute therapy (up to 6 weeks in patients with bipolar depression) are shown in  Table 16  .



 Table 16: Adverse Reactions in 2% or More of LATUDA-Treated Patients and That Occurred at Greater Incidence than in the Placebo-Treated Patients in a Short-term Monotherapy Bipolar Depression Study 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  *Extrapyramidal symptoms includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, dystonia, extrapyramidal disorder, glabellar reflex abnormal, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, tongue spasm, torticollis, tremor, and trismus    
  ** Somnolence includes adverse event terms: hypersomnia, hypersomnolence, sedation, and somnolence    
  
                                                 Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction     
   Body System or Organ Class       Dictionary-derived Term    Placebo    (N=168)    (%)      LATUDA    20-60 mg/day    (N=164)    (%)      LATUDA    80-120 mg/day    (N=167)    (%)      All LATUDA(N=331)    (%)     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                   
      Nausea                                   8              10             17          14             
      Dry Mouth                                4              6              4           5              
      Vomiting                                 2              2              6           4              
      Diarrhea                                 2              5              3           4              
   Infections and Infestations                  
      Nasopharyngitis                          1              4              4           4              
      Influenza                                1              &lt;1             2           2              
      Urinary Tract Infection                  &lt;1             2              1           2              
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue    Disorders     
      Back Pain                                &lt;1             3              &lt;1          2              
   Nervous System Disorders                     
      Extrapyramidal Symptoms*                 2              5              9           7              
      Akathisia                                2              8              11          9              
      Somnolence**                             7              7              14          11             
   Psychiatric Disorders                        
      Anxiety                                  1              4              5           4              
                 Dose-Related Adverse Reactions in the Monotherapy Study:  
 

 In the short-term, placebo-controlled study (involving lower and higher LATUDA dose ranges) [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )] the adverse reactions that occurred with a greater than 5% incidence in the patients treated with LATUDA in any dose group and greater than placebo in both groups were nausea (10.4%, 17.4%), somnolence (7.3%, 13.8%), akathisia (7.9%, 10.8%), and extrapyramidal symptoms (4.9%, 9.0%) for LATUDA 20 to 60 mg/day and LATUDA 80 to 120 mg/day, respectively.



     Bipolar Depression  



     Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 The following findings are based on two short-term, placebo-controlled premarketing studies for bipolar depression in which LATUDA was administered at daily doses ranging from 20 to 120 mg as adjunctive therapy with lithium or valproate (n=360).



     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions:  The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate of placebo) in subjects treated with LATUDA were akathisia and somnolence.



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment:  A total of 5.8% (21/360) LATUDA-treated patients and 4.8% (16/334) of placebo-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions. There were no adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in subjects treated with LATUDA that were at least 2% and at least twice the placebo rate.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More in LATUDA-Treated Patients:  Adverse reactions associated with the use of LATUDA (incidence of 2% or greater, rounded to the nearest percent and LATUDA incidence greater than placebo) that occurred during acute therapy (up to 6 weeks in patients with bipolar depression) are shown in  Table 17  .



 Table 17: Adverse Reactions in 2% or More of LATUDA-Treated Patients and That Occurred at Greater Incidence than in the Placebo-Treated Patients in the Short-term Adjunctive Therapy Bipolar Depression Studies 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  *Extrapyramidal symptoms includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, dystonia, extrapyramidal disorder, glabellar reflex abnormal, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, tongue spasm, torticollis, tremor, and trismus    
  ** Somnolence includes adverse event terms: hypersomnia, hypersomnolence, sedation, and somnolence    
  
                                              Percentage of Patients Reporting Reaction     
   Body System or Organ Class       Dictionary-derived Term    Placebo    (N=334)    (%)      LATUDA        20 to 120 mg/day    (N=360)    (%)     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                
      Nausea                                10          14                             
      Vomiting                              1           4                              
   General Disorders                         
      Fatigue                               1           3                              
   Infections and Infestations               
      Nasopharyngitis                       2           4                              
   Investigations                            
      Weight Increased                      &lt;1          3                              
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders        
      Increased Appetite                    1           3                              
   Nervous System Disorders                  
      Extrapyramidal Symptoms*              9           14                             
      Somnolence**                          5           11                             
      Akathisia                             5           11                             
   Psychiatric Disorders                     
      Restlessness                          &lt;1          4                              
               Extrapyramidal Symptoms  
 

     Schizophrenia  



 In the short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies, for LATUDA-treated patients, the incidence of reported events related to extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS), excluding akathisia and restlessness, was 13.5% versus 5.8% for placebo-treated patients. The incidence of akathisia for LATUDA-treated patients was 12.9% versus 3.0% for placebo-treated patients. Incidence of EPS by dose is provided in  Table 18  .



 Table 18: Incidence of EPS Compared to Placebo in Schizophrenia Studies 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  * Dystonia includes adverse event terms: dystonia, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, tongue spasm, torticollis, and trismus    
  ** Parkinsonism includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, and tremor    
  
                                                         LATUDA                                   
   Adverse Event Term        Placebo    (N=708)    (%)      20 mg/day    (N=71)    (%)      40 mg/day    (N=487)    (%)      80 mg/day    (N=538)    (%)      120 mg/day    (N=291)    (%)      160 mg/day    (N=121)    (%)     
   All EPS events            9             10            21            23            39            20             
   All EPS events, excluding Akathisia/Restlessness      6             6             11            12            22            13             
      Akathisia            3             6             11            12            22            7                
      Dystonia*            &lt;1            0             4             5             7             2                
      Parkinsonism**       5             6             9             8             17            11               
      Restlessness         1             1             3             1             3             2                
                 Bipolar Depression  
 

     Monotherapy  



 In the short-term, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, for LATUDA-treated patients, the incidence of reported events related to EPS, excluding akathisia and restlessness was 6.9% versus 2.4% for placebo-treated patients. The incidence of akathisia for LATUDA-treated patients was 9.4% versus 2.4% for placebo-treated patients. Incidence of EPS by dose groups is provided in  Table 19  .



 Table 19: Incidence of EPS Compared to Placebo in the Monotherapy Bipolar Depression Study 
                                                         LATUDA                    
   Adverse Event Term        Placebo    (N=168)    (%)      20 to 60 mg/day    (N=164)    (%)      80 to 120 mg/day    (N=167)    (%)     
   All EPS events            5             12            20                        
   All EPS events, excluding Akathisia/Restlessness      2             5             9                         
  
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  * Dystonia includes adverse event terms: dystonia, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, tongue spasm, torticollis, and trismus    
  ** Parkinsonism includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, extrapyramidal disorder, glabellar reflex abnormal, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, and tremor    
  
      Akathisia            2             8             11                          
      Dystonia*            0             0             2                           
      Parkinsonism**       2             5             8                           
      Restlessness         &lt;1            0             3                           
               Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  
 

 In the short-term, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies, for LATUDA-treated patients, the incidence of EPS, excluding akathisia and restlessness, was 13.9% versus 8.7% for placebo. The incidence of akathisia for LATUDA-treated patients was 10.8% versus 4.8% for placebo-treated patients. Incidence of EPS is provided in  Table 20  .



 Table 20: Incidence of EPS Compared to Placebo in the Adjunctive Therapy Bipolar Depression Studies 
   Adverse Event Term        Placebo    (N=334)    (%)           LATUDA        20 to 120 mg/day(N=360)    (%)     
   All EPS events            13                                  24                                       
   All EPS events, excluding Akathisia/Restlessness      9                                   14                                       
  
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  * Dystonia includes adverse event terms: dystonia, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, tongue spasm, torticollis, and trismus    
  ** Parkinsonism includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, extrapyramidal disorder, glabellar reflex abnormal, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, parkinsonism, psychomotor retardation, and tremor    
  
      Akathisia            5                                   11                                         
      Dystonia*            &lt;1                                  1                                          
      Parkinsonism**       8                                   13                                         
      Restlessness         &lt;1                                  4                                          
         In the short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia and bipolar depression studies, data was objectively collected on the Simpson Angus Rating Scale (SAS) for extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS), the Barnes Akathisia Scale (BAS) for akathisia and the Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (AIMS) for dyskinesias.
 

     Schizophrenia  



 The mean change from baseline for LATUDA-treated patients for the SAS, BAS and AIMS was comparable to placebo-treated patients, with the exception of the Barnes Akathisia Scale global score (LATUDA, 0.1; placebo, 0.0). The percentage of patients who shifted from normal to abnormal was greater in LATUDA-treated patients versus placebo for the BAS (LATUDA, 14.4%; placebo, 7.1%), the SAS (LATUDA, 5.0%; placebo, 2.3%) and the AIMS (LATUDA, 7.4%; placebo, 5.8%).



     Bipolar Depression  



     Monotherapy  



 The mean change from baseline for LATUDA-treated patients for the SAS, BAS and AIMS was comparable to placebo-treated patients. The percentage of patients who shifted from normal to abnormal was greater in LATUDA-treated patients versus placebo for the BAS (LATUDA, 8.4%; placebo, 5.6%), the SAS (LATUDA, 3.7%; placebo, 1.9%) and the AIMS (LATUDA, 3.4%; placebo, 1.2%).



   Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 The mean change from baseline for LATUDA-treated patients for the SAS, BAS and AIMS was comparable to placebo-treated patients. The percentage of patients who shifted from normal to abnormal was greater in LATUDA-treated patients versus placebo for the BAS (LATUDA, 8.7%; placebo, 2.1%), the SAS (LATUDA, 2.8%; placebo, 2.1%) and the AIMS (LATUDA, 2.8%; placebo, 0.6%).



     Dystonia  



     Class Effect:  Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first-generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



     Schizophrenia  



 In the short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia clinical studies, dystonia occurred in 4.2% of LATUDA-treated subjects (0.0% LATUDA 20 mg, 3.5% LATUDA 40 mg, 4.5% LATUDA 80 mg, 6.5% LATUDA 120 mg and 2.5% LATUDA 160 mg) compared to 0.8% of subjects receiving placebo. Seven subjects (0.5%, 7/1508) discontinued clinical trials due to dystonic events - four were receiving LATUDA 80 mg/day and three were receiving LATUDA 120 mg/day.



     Bipolar Depression  



     Monotherapy  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, dystonia occurred in 0.9% of LATUDA-treated subjects (0.0% and 1.8% for LATUDA 20 to 60 mg/day and LATUDA 80 to 120 mg/day, respectively) compared to 0.0% of subjects receiving placebo. No subject discontinued the clinical study due to dystonic events.



     Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies, dystonia occurred in 1.1% of LATUDA-treated subjects (20 to 120 mg) compared to 0.6% of subjects receiving placebo. No subject discontinued the clinical study due to dystonic events.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of LATUDA  



 Following is a list of adverse reactions reported by patients treated with LATUDA at multiple doses of &gt;= 20 mg once daily within the premarketing database of 2905 patients with schizophrenia. The reactions listed are those that could be of clinical importance, as well as reactions that are plausibly drug-related on pharmacologic or other grounds. Reactions listed in  Table 15  or those that appear elsewhere in the LATUDA label are not included. Although the reactions reported occurred during treatment with LATUDA, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Reactions are further categorized by organ class and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: those occurring in at least 1/100 patients (frequent) (only those not already listed in the tabulated results from placebo-controlled studies appear in this listing); those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients (infrequent); and those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients (rare).



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:    Infrequent:    anemia  



   Cardiac Disorders:    Frequent:    tachycardia;    Infrequent:    AV block 1st degree, angina pectoris, bradycardia  



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:    Infrequent:    vertigo  



   Eye Disorders:    Frequent:    blurred vision  



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:    Frequent:    abdominal pain, diarrhea;    Infrequent:    gastritis  



   General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions:    Rare:    sudden death  



   Investigations:    Frequent:    CPK increased  



   Metabolism and Nutritional System Disorders:    Frequent:    decreased appetite  



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:    Rare:    rhabdomyolysis  



   Nervous System Disorders:    Infrequent:    cerebrovascular accident, dysarthria  



   Psychiatric Disorders:    Infrequent:    abnormal dreams, panic attack, sleep disorder  



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:    Infrequent:    dysuria;    Rare:    renal failure  



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:    Infrequent:    amenorrhea, dysmenorrhea;    Rare:    breast enlargement, breast pain, galactorrhea, erectile dysfunction  



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    Frequent:    rash, pruritus;    Rare:    angioedema  



   Vascular Disorders:    Frequent:    hypertension  



     Clinical Laboratory Changes  



   Schizophrenia



   Serum Creatinine  : In short-term, placebo-controlled trials, the mean change from Baseline in serum creatinine was +0.05 mg/dL for LATUDA-treated patients compared to +0.02 mg/dL for placebo-treated patients. A creatinine shift from normal to high occurred in 3.0% (43/1453) of LATUDA-treated patients and 1.6% (11/681) on placebo. The threshold for high creatinine value varied from &gt; 0.79 to &gt; 1.3 mg/dL based on the centralized laboratory definition for each study (  Table 21  ).



 Table 21: Serum Creatinine Shifts from Normal at Baseline to High at Study End-Point in Schizophrenia Studies 
   Laboratory Parameter      Placebo    (N=708)      LATUDA 20mg/day    (N=71)      LATUDA 40mg/day    (N=487)      LATUDA 80mg/day    (N=538)      LATUDA 120 mg/day    (N=291)      LATUDA 160mg/day    (N=121)     
   Serum Creatinine Elevated    2%           1%             2%             2%             5%             7%              
               Bipolar Depression
 

     Monotherapy  



     Serum Creatinine  : In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, the mean change from Baseline in serum creatinine was +0.01 mg/dL for LATUDA-treated patients compared to -0.02 mg/dL for placebo-treated patients. A creatinine shift from normal to high occurred in 2.8% (9/322) of LATUDA-treated patients and 0.6% (1/162) on placebo (  Table 22  ).



 Table 22: Serum Creatinine Shifts from Normal at Baseline to High at Study End-Point in a Monotherapy Bipolar Depression Study 
   Laboratory Parameter           Placebo    (N=168)      LATUDA20 to 60 mg/day    (N=164)      LATUDA80 to 120 mg/day    (N=167)     
   Serum Creatinine Elevated    &lt;1%                     2%                        4%                       
              Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  
 

     Serum Creatinine  : In short-term, placebo-controlled premarketing adjunctive studies for bipolar depression, the mean change from Baseline in serum creatinine was +0.04 mg/dL for LATUDA-treated patients compared to -0.01 mg/dL for placebo-treated patients. A creatinine shift from normal to high occurred in 4.3% (15/360) of LATUDA-treated patients and 1.6% (5/334) on placebo (  Table 23  ).



 Table 23: Serum Creatinine Shifts from Normal at Baseline to High at Study End-Point in the Adjunctive Therapy Bipolar Depression Studies 
   Laboratory Parameter           Placebo    (N=334)                 LATUDA    20 to 120 mg/day(N=360)     
   Serum Creatinine Elevated    2%                                 4%                                     
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S3">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



  WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature.  



   Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear.  



   LATUDA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis.

      [see Warnings and Precautions (          5.1

          )]    .





   EXCERPT:     WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. LATUDA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis.       (  5.1  )    
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S4">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS; AND SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS



  WARNINGS: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS; AND SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS



    *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1 )]. 
 *  LATUDA is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1 )]. 
 *  Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies. These studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressant use in patients over age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressant use in patients aged 65 and older [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  In patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy, monitor closely for worsening, and for emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNINGS:    INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS; AND SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. 
 *  LATUDA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis (5.1). 
 *  Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants (5.2) 
 *  Monitor for worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S5">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions: An increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse events (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack) has been seen in elderly patients with dementia-related psychoses treated with atypical antipsychotic drugs. (   5.2   ). 
 *   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring (   5.3   ). 
 *   Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue if clinically appropriate (   5.4   ). 
 *  *   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus: Monitor patients for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Monitor glucose regularly in patients with diabetes or at risk for diabetes. 
 *   Dyslipidemia: Undesirable alterations have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. 
 *   Weight Gain: Gain in body weight has been observed, clinical monitoring of weight is recommended. 
    Metabolic Changes: Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and weight gain (   5.5   ). 
 *   Hyperprolactinemia: Prolactin elevations may occur (   5.6   ). 
 *   Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis have been reported with antipsychotics. Patients with a pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) or a history of leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and LATUDA should be discontinued at the first sign of a decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors (   5.7   ). 
 *   Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope: Dizziness, tachycardia or bradycardia, and syncope may occur, especially early in treatment. Use with caution in patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease, and in antipsychotic-naive patients (   5.8   ). 
 *   Seizures: Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold (   5.9   ). 
 *   Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment: Use caution when operating machinery (   5.10   ). 
 *   Suicide: The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in schizophrenia. Closely supervise high-risk patients (   5.12   ). 
 *  See Full Prescribing Information for additional   WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS    
    
 

   5.1. Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. LATUDA is not approved for the treatment of dementia-related psychosis [ see  Boxed Warning    ].  



    5.2. Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke



  In placebo-controlled trials with risperidone, aripiprazole, and olanzapine in elderly subjects with dementia, there was a higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (cerebrovascular accidents and transient ischemic attacks), including fatalities, compared to placebo-treated subjects. LATUDA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see also  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (     5.1     )].  



    5.3. Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with administration of antipsychotic drugs, including LATUDA.



 Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatinine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. It is important to exclude cases where the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g. pneumonia, systemic infection) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: 1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; 2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and 3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. If reintroduced, the patient should be carefully monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4. Tardive Dyskinesia



  Tardive Dyskinesia is a syndrome consisting of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements that can develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses.



 There is no known treatment for established cases of tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and thereby may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, LATUDA should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that (1) is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs, and (2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient on LATUDA, drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with LATUDA despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.5. Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and body weight gain. While all of the drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



    



   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus  



 Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse events is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of treatment-emergent hyperglycemia-related adverse events in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. Because LATUDA was not marketed at the time these studies were performed, it is not known if LATUDA is associated with this increased risk.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



 Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled studies are presented in Table 2.



 Table 2: Change in Fasting Glucose 
                   Placebo          LATUDA   20 mg/day     LATUDA   40 mg/day     LATUDA   80 mg/day     LATUDA   120 mg/day     
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)     
                   n=438            n=71             n=352            n=270            n=283            
  
   In the uncontrolled, longer-term studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a mean change in glucose of +1.6 mg/dL at week 24 (n = 186), +0.3 mg/dL at week 36 (n = 236) and +1.2 mg/dL at week 52 (n = 244).    
  
  Serum Glucose    -0.7             -0.6             2.5              -0.9             2.5              
   Proportion of Patients with Shifts to &gt;= 126 mg/dL     
  Serum Glucose(&gt;= 126 mg/dL)   8.6%(34/397)     11.7%(7/60)      14.3%( 47/328)   10.0%(24/241)    10.0%(26/260)    
               
 

   Dyslipidemia  



 Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled studies are presented in Table 3.



 Table 3: Change in Fasting Lipids 
                   Placebo          LATUDA   20 mg/day     LATUDA   40 mg/day     LATUDA   80 mg/day     LATUDA   120 mg/day     
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)     
                   n=418            n=71             n=341            n=263            n=268            
  
  Total cholesterol   -8.5             -12.3            -9.4             -9.8             -3.8             
  Triglycerides    -15.7            -29.1            -6.2             -14.2            -3.1             
   Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
  Total Cholesterol(&gt;= 240 mg/dL)   6.6%(23/350)     13.8%(8/58)      7.3%(21/287)     6.9%(15/216)     3.8%(9/238)      
  Triglycerides(&gt;= 200 mg/dL)   12.5%(39/312)    14.3%(7/49)      14.0%(37/264)    8.7%(17/196)     10.5%(22/209)    
            In the uncontrolled, longer-term studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a mean change in total cholesterol and triglycerides of -4.2 (n=186) and -13.6 (n=187) mg/dL at week 24, -1.9 (n = 238) and -3.5 (n = 238) mg/dL at week 36 and -3.6 (n=243) and -6.5 (n=243) mg/dL at week 52, respectively.
 

    



   Weight Gain  



 Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Clinical monitoring of weight is recommended.



 Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled studies are presented in Table 4. The mean weight gain was 0.75 kg for LATUDA-treated patients compared to 0.26 kg for placebo-treated patients. In study 3 [ see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )  ] change in weight from baseline for olanzapine was 4.15 kg. The proportion of patients with a &gt;= 7% increase in body weight (at Endpoint) was 5.6% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 4.0% for placebo-treated patients.



 Table 4: Mean Change in Weight (kg) from Baseline 
                   Placebo   (n=450)      LATUDA20 mg/day   (n=71)      LATUDA40 mg/day   (n= 358)      LATUDA80 mg/day   (n= 279)      LATUDA120 mg/day   (n=291)     
  All Patients    0.26            -0.15               0.67                1.14                0.68             
            In the uncontrolled, longer-term studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a mean change in weight of -0.38 kg at week 24 (n = 531), -0.47 kg at week 36 (n = 303) and -0.71 kg at week 52 (n = 244).
 

    5.6. Hyperprolactinemia



  As with other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2receptors, LATUDA elevates prolactin levels.



 Hyperprolactinemia may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotrophin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported with prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male patients [see Adverse Reactions (     6     )]  .



 In short-term placebo-controlled studies, the median change from baseline to endpoint in prolactin levels for LATUDA-treated patients was 1.1 ng/mL and was - 0.6 ng/mL in the placebo-treated patients. The increase in prolactin was greater in female patients; the median change from baseline to endpoint for females was 1.5 ng/mL and was 1.1 ng/mL in males. The increase in prolactin concentrations was dose-dependent (Table 5).



 Table 5: Median Change in Prolactin (ng/mL) from Baseline 
                   Placebo         LATUDA20 mg/day      LATUDA40 mg/day      LATUDA80 mg/day      LATUDA120 mg/day     
  All Patients    -0.6(n=430)     -1.1(n=70)          0.3(n=351)          1.1(n=259)          3.3(n=284)       
  Females         -1.5(n=102)     -0.7(n=19)          -0.9(n=99)          2.0(n=78)           6.7(n=70)        
  Males           -0.5(n=328)     -1.2(n=51)          0.5(n=252)          0.9(n=181)          3.1(n=214)       
            The proportion of patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5* ULN was 3.6% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 0.7% for placebo-treated patients. The proportion of female patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x ULN was 8.3% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 1% for placebo-treated female patients. The proportion of male patients with prolactin elevations &gt; 5x ULN was 1.9% versus 0.6% for placebo-treated male patients.
 

 In the uncontrolled longer-term studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a median change in prolactin of -1.9 ng/mL at week 24 (n = 188), -5.4 ng/mL at week 36 (n=189) and -3.3 ng/mL at week 52 (n = 243).



 Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin dependent in vitro, a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is considered in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. As is common with compounds which increase prolactin release, an increase in mammary gland neoplasia was observed in a LATUDA carcinogenicity study conducted in rats and mice [see Nonclinical Toxicology (     13     )].  Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans, but the available evidence is too limited to be conclusive.



    5.7. Leukopenia, Neutropenia and Agranulocytosis



  Leukopenia/neutropenia has been reported during treatment with antipsychotic agents. Agranulocytosis (including fatal cases) has been reported with other agents in the class.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) and history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a pre-existing low WBC or a history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and LATUDA should be discontinued at the first sign of decline in WBC, in the absence of other causative factors.



 Patients with neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1000/mm  3  ) should discontinue LATUDA and have their WBC followed until recovery.



    5.8. Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope



  LATUDA may cause orthostatic hypotension, perhaps due to its alpha1-adrenergic receptor antagonism. The incidence of orthostatic hypotension and syncope events from short-term, placebo-controlled studies was (LATUDA incidence, placebo incidence): orthostatic hypotension [0.4% (4/1004), 0.2 % (1/455)] and syncope [&lt; 0.1% (1/1004), 0%]. Assessment of orthostatic hypotension defined by vital sign changes (&gt;= 20 mm Hg decrease in systolic blood pressure and &gt;= 10 bpm increase in pulse from sitting to standing or supine to standing positions). In short-term clinical trials orthostatic hypotension occurred with a frequency of 0.8% with LATUDA 40 mg, 1.4% with LATUDA 80 mg and 1.7% with LATUDA 120 mg compared to 0.9% with placebo.



 LATUDA should be used with caution in patients with known cardiovascular disease (e.g., heart failure, history of myocardial infarction, ischemia, or conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, or conditions that predispose the patient to hypotension (e.g., dehydration, hypovolemia, and treatment with antihypertensive medications). Monitoring of orthostatic vital signs should be considered in patients who are vulnerable to hypotension.



    5.9. Seizures



  As with other antipsychotic drugs, LATUDA should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold, e.g., Alzheimer's dementia. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in patients 65 years or older.



 In short-term placebo-controlled trials, seizures/convulsions occurred in &lt; 0.1% (1/1004) of patients treated with LATUDA compared to 0.2% (1/455) placebo-treated patients.



    5.10. Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  LATUDA, like other antipsychotics, has the potential to impair judgment, thinking or motor skills.



 In short-term, placebo-controlled trials, somnolence was reported in 22.3% (224/1004) of patients treated with LATUDA compared to 9.9% (45/455) of placebo patients, respectively. The frequency of somnolence increases with dose; somnolence was reported in 26.5% (77/291) of patients receiving LATUDA 120 mg/day. In these short-term trials, somnolence included: hypersomnia, hypersomnolence, sedation and somnolence.



 Patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including motor vehicles, until they are reasonably certain that therapy with LATUDA does not affect them adversely.



    5.11. Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing LATUDA for patients who will be experiencing conditions that may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration [see Patient Counseling Information (     17.9     )].  



    5.12. Suicide



  The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in psychotic illness and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy. Prescriptions for LATUDA should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



 In short-term, placebo-controlled studies in patients with schizophrenia, the incidence of treatment-emergent suicidal ideation was 0.6% (6/1004) for LATUDA treated patients compared to 0.4% (2/455) on placebo. No suicide attempts or completed suicides were reported in these studies.



    5.13. Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in elderly patients, in particular those with advanced Alzheimer's dementia. LATUDA is not indicated for the treatment of dementia-related psychosis, and should not be used in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia.



    5.14. Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with LATUDA in patients with certain concomitant systemic illnesses is limited [see Use in Specific Populations (     8.6     ,     8.7     )]  . LATUDA has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were excluded from premarketing clinical studies [see Warnings and Precautions (     5.1     ,  5.8  )].  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S6">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse events (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack) (  5.2  ). 
 *   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring (  5.4  ). 
 *   Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue if clinically appropriate (  5.5  ). 
 *  *  -   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus: Monitor patients for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Monitor glucose regularly in patients with diabetes or at risk for diabetes. 
 *  -   Dyslipidemia: Undesirable alterations have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. 
 *  -   Weight Gain: Gain in body weight has been observed. Monitor weight. 
    Metabolic Changes: Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and weight gain (  5.6  ). 
 *   Hyperprolactinemia: Prolactin elevations may occur (  5.7  ). 
 *   Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis: Perform complete blood counts (CBC) in patients with a pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) or a history of leukopenia or neutropenia. Consider discontinuing LATUDA if a clinically significant decline in WBC occurs in the absence of other causative factors (  5.8  ). 
 *   Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope: Dizziness, tachycardia or bradycardia, and syncope may occur, especially early in treatment. In patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease, and in antipsychotic-naive patients, consider a lower starting dose and slower titration (  5.9  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6- to 1.7-times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. LATUDA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  ]  .



    5.2 Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviors in Adolescents and Young Adults



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment.



 Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk of differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in  Table 2  .



 Table 2 
  Age Range                                          Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated     
                                                    Increases Compared to Placebo                        
 &lt;18                                                14 additional cases                                  
 18-24                                              5 additional cases                                   
                                                    Decreases Compared to Placebo                        
 25-64                                              1 fewer case                                         
 &gt;=65                                               6 fewer cases                                        
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. Prescriptions for LATUDA should be written for the smallest quantity of capsules consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.  



    5.3 Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  In placebo-controlled trials with risperidone, aripiprazole, and olanzapine in elderly subjects with dementia, there was a higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (cerebrovascular accidents and transient ischemic attacks), including fatalities, compared to placebo-treated subjects. LATUDA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see also Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



    5.4 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with administration of antipsychotic drugs, including LATUDA.



 Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. It is important to exclude cases where the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: 1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; 2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and 3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. If reintroduced, the patient should be carefully monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.5 Tardive Dyskinesia



  Tardive dyskinesia is a syndrome consisting of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements that can develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses.



 There is no known treatment for established cases of tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and thereby may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, LATUDA should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that (1) is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs, and (2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient on LATUDA, drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with LATUDA despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.6 Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and body weight gain. While all of the drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



    Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus  



 Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse events is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of treatment-emergent hyperglycemia-related adverse events in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. Because LATUDA was not marketed at the time these studies were performed, it is not known if LATUDA is associated with this increased risk.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



  Schizophrenia  



 Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies are presented in  Table 3  .



 Table 3: Change in Fasting Glucose in Schizophrenia Studies 
                                                  LATUDA                                          
                     Placebo        20 mg/day     40 mg/day       80 mg/day       120 mg/day      160 mg/day     
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)     
                    n=680          n=71          n=478           n=508           n=283           n=113           
  
 Serum Glucose      -0.0           -0.6          +2.6            -0.4            +2.5            + 2.5           
  Proportion of Patients with Shifts to &gt;= 126 mg/dL     
 Serum Glucose(&gt;= 126 mg/dL)  8.3%(52/628)   11.7%(7/60)   12.7%( 57/449)  6.8%(32/472)    10.0%(26/260)   5.6%(6/108)     
             In the uncontrolled, longer-term schizophrenia studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a mean change in glucose of +1.8 mg/dL at week 24 (n=355), +0.8 mg/dL at week 36 (n=299) and +2.3 mg/dL at week 52 (n=307).
 

    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 Data from the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study are presented in  Table 4  .



 Table 4: Change in Fasting Glucose in the Monotherapy Bipolar Depression Study 
                                                            LATUDA                  
                                   Placebo                  20 to 60 mg/day         80 to 120 mg/day        
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)     
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 60 mg/day, LATUDA 80 to 120 mg/day, or placebo    
  
                                   n=148                    n=140                   n=143                   
 Serum Glucose                    +1.8                     -0.8                    +1.8                     
  Proportion of Patients with Shifts to &gt;= 126 mg/dL     
 Serum Glucose(&gt;= 126 mg/dL)      4.3%(6/141)              2.2%(3/138)             6.4%(9/141)              
          In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who received LATUDA as monotherapy in the short-term study and continued in the longer-term study, had a mean change in glucose of +1.2 mg/dL at week 24 (n=129).
 

    Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 Data from the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies are presented in  Table 5  .



 Table 5: Change in Fasting Glucose in the Adjunctive Therapy Bipolar Depression Studies 
                                                                          LATUDA                          
                                           Placebo                        20 to 120 mg/day                
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)        
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 120 mg/day or placebo as adjunctive therapy with lithium or valproate.    
  
                                           n=302                          n=319                           
 Serum Glucose                            -0.9                           +1.2                             
  Proportion of Patients with Shifts to &gt;= 126 mg/dL     
 Serum Glucose(&gt;= 126 mg/dL)              1.0%(3/290)                    1.3%(4/316)                      
         In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who received LATUDA as adjunctive therapy with either lithium or valproate in the short-term study and continued in the longer-term study, had a mean change in glucose of +1.7 mg/dL at week 24 (n=88).
 

    Dyslipidemia  



 Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics.



    Schizophrenia  



 Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies are presented in  Table 6  .



 Table 6: Change in Fasting Lipids in Schizophrenia Studies 
                                                  LATUDA                                          
                     Placebo        20 mg/day     40 mg/day       80 mg/day       120 mg/day      160 mg/day      
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)     
                     n=660          n=71          n=466           n=499           n=268           n=115           
  
 Total Cholesterol  -5.8           -12.3         -5.7            -6.2            -3.8            -6.9             
 Triglycerides      -13.4          -29.1         -5.1            -13.0           -3.1            -10.6            
  Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
 Total Cholesterol (&gt;= 240 mg/dL)  5.3%(30/571)   13.8%(8/58)   6.2%(25/402)    5.3%(23/434)    3.8%(9/238)     4.0%(4/101)      
 Triglycerides(&gt;= 200 mg/dL)  10.1%(53/526)  14.3%(7/49)   10.8%(41/379)   6.3%(25/400)    10.5%(22/209)   7.0%(7/100)      
             In the uncontrolled, longer-term schizophrenia studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a mean change in total cholesterol and triglycerides of -3.8 (n=356) and -15.1 (n=357) mg/dL at week 24, -3.1 (n=303) and -4.8 (n=303) mg/dL at week 36 and -2.5 (n=307) and -6.9 (n=307) mg/dL at week 52, respectively.
 

    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 Data from the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled, monotherapy bipolar depression study are presented in  Table 7  .



 Table 7: Change in Fasting Lipids in the Monotherapy Bipolar Depression Study 
                                                     LATUDA                        
                      Placebo                        20 to 60 mg/day               80 to 120 mg/day     
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)     
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 60 mg/day, LATUDA 80 to 120 mg/day, or placebo    
  
                      n=147                          n=140                         n=144       
 Total cholesterol   -3.2                           +1.2                          -4.6         
 Triglycerides       +6.0                           +5.6                          +0.4         
  Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
 Total cholesterol (&gt;= 240 mg/dL)  4.2%(5/118)                    4.4%(5/113)                   4.4%(5/114)   
 Triglycerides(&gt;= 200 mg/dL)  4.8%(6/126)                    10.1%(12/119)                 9.8%(12/122)   
           In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who received LATUDA as monotherapy in the short-term and continued in the longer-term study had a mean change in total cholesterol and triglycerides of -0.5 (n=130) and -1.0 (n=130) mg/dL at week 24, respectively.
 

  Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 Data from the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled, adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies are presented in  Table 8  .



 Table 8: Change in Fasting Lipids in the Adjunctive Therapy Bipolar Depression Studies 
                                                                LATUDA                                    
                      Placebo                                   20 to 120 mg/day                          
  Mean Change from Baseline (mg/dL)     
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 120 mg/day or placebo as adjunctive therapy with lithium or valproate.    
  
                      n=303                                     n=321                                     
 Total cholesterol   -2.9                                      -3.1                                       
 Triglycerides       -4.6                                      +4.6                                       
  Proportion of Patients with Shifts     
 Total cholesterol(&gt;= 240 mg/dL)  5.7%(15/263)                              5.4%(15/276)                               
 Triglycerides(&gt;= 200 mg/dL)  8.6%(21/243)                              10.8%(28/260)                              
         In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who received LATUDA, as adjunctive therapy with either lithium or valproate in the short-term study and continued in the longer-term study, had a mean change in total cholesterol and triglycerides of -0.9 (n=88) and +5.3 (n=88) mg/dL at week 24, respectively.
 

    Weight Gain  



 Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Clinical monitoring of weight is recommended.



    Schizophrenia  



 Pooled data from short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies are presented in  Table 9  . The mean weight gain was +0.43 kg for LATUDA-treated patients compared to -0.02 kg for placebo-treated patients. Change in weight from baseline for olanzapine was +4.15 kg and for quetiapine extended-release was +2.09 kg in Studies 3 and 5 [see Clinical Studies (  14.1  )]  , respectively. The proportion of patients with a &gt;= 7% increase in body weight (at Endpoint) was 4.8% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 3.3% for placebo-treated patients.



 Table 9: Mean Change in Weight (kg) from Baseline in Schizophrenia Studies 
                                             LATUDA                                            
                Placebo(n=696)     20 mg/day(n=71)     40 mg/day(n=484)     80 mg/day(n=526)     120 mg/day(n=291)     160 mg/day      (n=114)     
 All Patients  -0.02         -0.15          +0.22           +0.54             +0.68           +0.60              
             In the uncontrolled, longer-term schizophrenia studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a mean change in weight of -0.69 kg at week 24 (n=755), -0.59 kg at week 36 (n=443) and -0.73 kg at week 52 (n=377).
 

    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 Data from the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study are presented in  Table 10  . The mean weight gain was +0.29 kg for LATUDA-treated patients compared to -0.04 kg for placebo-treated patients. The proportion of patients with a &gt;= 7% increase in body weight (at Endpoint) was 2.4% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 0.7% for placebo-treated patients.



 Table 10: Mean Change in Weight (kg) from Baseline in the Monotherapy Bipolar Depression Study 
                                                     LATUDA                        
                      Placebo(n=151)                 20 to 60 mg/day(n=143)        80 to 120 mg/day(n=147)     
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 60 mg/day, LATUDA 80 to 120 mg/day, or placebo    
  
 All Patients        -0.04                          +0.56                         +0.02        
           In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who received LATUDA as monotherapy in the short-term and continued in the longer-term study had a mean change in weight of -0.02 kg at week 24 (n=130).
 

    Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 Data from the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies are presented in  Table 11  . The mean weight gain was +0.11 kg for LATUDA-treated patients compared to +0.16 kg for placebo-treated patients. The proportion of patients with a &gt;= 7% increase in body weight (at Endpoint) was 3.1% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 0.3% for placebo-treated patients.



 Table 11: Mean Change in Weight (kg) from Baseline in the Adjunctive Therapy Bipolar Depression Studies 
                                                                LATUDA                                    
                      Placebo(n=307)                            20 to 120 mg/day(n=327)                   
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 120 mg/day or placebo as adjunctive therapy with lithium or valproate.    
  
 All Patients        +0.16                                     +0.11                                      
         In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who were treated with LATUDA, as adjunctive therapy with either lithium or valproate in the short-term and continued in the longer-term study, had a mean change in weight of +1.28 kg at week 24 (n=86).
 

    5.7 Hyperprolactinemia



  As with other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2receptors, LATUDA elevates prolactin levels.



 Hyperprolactinemia may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotrophin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported with prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia, when associated with hypogonadism, may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male patients [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  .



 Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin-dependent in vitro  , a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is considered in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. As is common with compounds which increase prolactin release, an increase in mammary gland neoplasia was observed in a LATUDA carcinogenicity study conducted in rats and mice [see Nonclinical Toxicology (  13  )].  Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans, but the available evidence is too limited to be conclusive.



  Schizophrenia  



 In short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies, the median change from baseline to endpoint in prolactin levels for LATUDA-treated patients was +0.4 ng/mL and was -1.9 ng/mL in the placebo-treated patients. The median change from baseline to endpoint for males was +0.5 ng/mL and for females was -0.2 ng/mL. Median changes for prolactin by dose are shown in  Table 12  .



 Table 12: Median Change in Prolactin (ng/mL) from Baseline in Schizophrenia Studies 
                                               LATUDA                                            
  
                 Placebo        20 mg/day      40 mg/day          80 mg/day       120 mg/day     160 mg/day     
 All Patients   -1.9(n=672)    -1.1(n=70)     -1.4(n=476)        -0.2(n=495)     +3.3(n=284)    +3.3(n=115)     
 Females        -5.1(n=200)    -0.7(n=19)     -4.0(n=149)        -0.2(n=150)     +6.7(n=70)     +7.1(n=36)      
 Males          -1.3(n=472)    -1.2(n=51)     -0.7(n=327)        -0.2(n=345)     +3.1(n=214)    +2.4(n=79)      
             The proportion of patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5* upper limit of normal (ULN) was 2.8% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 1.0% for placebo-treated patients. The proportion of female patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x ULN was 5.7% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 2.0% for placebo-treated female patients. The proportion of male patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x ULN was 1.6% versus 0.6% for placebo-treated male patients.
 

 In the uncontrolled longer-term schizophrenia studies (primarily open-label extension studies), LATUDA was associated with a median change in prolactin of -0.9 ng/mL at week 24 (n=357), -5.3ng/mL at week 36 (n=190) and -2.2 ng/mL at week 52 (n=307).



    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 The median change from baseline to endpoint in prolactin levels, in the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, was +1.7 ng/mL and +3.5 ng/mL with LATUDA 20 to 60 mg/day and 80 to 120 mg/day, respectively compared to +0.3 ng/mL with placebo-treated patients. The median change from baseline to endpoint for males was +1.5 ng/mL and for females was +3.1 ng/mL. Median changes for prolactin by dose range are shown in  Table 13  .



 Table 13: Median Change in Prolactin (ng/mL) from Baseline in the Monotherapy Bipolar Depression Study 
                                                     LATUDA                        
                      Placebo                        20 to 60 mg/day               80 to 120 mg/day     
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 60 mg/day, LATUDA 80 to 120 mg/day, or placebo    
  
 All Patients        +0.3(n=147)                    +1.7(n=140)                   +3.5(n=144)   
 Females             0.0(n=82)                      +1.8(n=78)                    +5.3(n=88)   
 Males               +0.4(n=65)                     +1.2(n=62)                    +1.9(n=56)   
           The proportion of patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x upper limit of normal (ULN) was 0.4% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 0.0% for placebo-treated patients. The proportion of female patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x ULN was 0.6% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 0% for placebo-treated female patients. The proportion of male patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x ULN was 0% versus 0% for placebo-treated male patients.
 

 In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who were treated with LATUDA as monotherapy in the short-term and continued in the longer-term study, had a median change in prolactin of -1.15 ng/mL at week 24 (n=130).



  Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 The median change from baseline to endpoint in prolactin levels, in the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies was +2.8 ng/mL with LATUDA 20 to 120 mg/day compared to 0.0 ng/mL with placebo-treated patients. The median change from baseline to endpoint for males was +2.4 ng/mL and for females was +3.2 ng/mL. Median changes for prolactin across the dose range are shown in  Table 14  .



 Table 14: Median Change in Prolactin (ng/mL) from Baseline in the Adjunctive Therapy Bipolar Depression Studies 
                                                                LATUDA                                    
                      Placebo                                   20 to 120 mg/day                          
  
  Patients were randomized to flexibly dosed LATUDA 20 to 120 mg/day or placebo as adjunctive therapy with lithium or valproate.    
  
 All Patients        0.0(n=301)                                +2.8(n=321)                                
 Females             +0.4(n=156)                               +3.2(n=162)                                
 Males               -0.1(n=145)                               +2.4(n=159)                                
         The proportion of patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x upper limit of normal (ULN) was 0.0% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 0.0% for placebo-treated patients. The proportion of female patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x ULN was 0% for LATUDA-treated patients versus 0% for placebo-treated female patients. The proportion of male patients with prolactin elevations &gt;= 5x ULN was 0% versus 0% for placebo-treated male patients.
 

 In the uncontrolled, open-label, longer-term bipolar depression study, patients who were treated with LATUDA, as adjunctive therapy with either lithium or valproate, in the short-term and continued in the longer-term study, had a median change in prolactin of -2.9 ng/mL at week 24 (n=88).



    5.8 Leukopenia, Neutropenia and Agranulocytosis



  Leukopenia/neutropenia has been reported during treatment with antipsychotic agents. Agranulocytosis (including fatal cases) has been reported with other agents in the class.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) and history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a pre-existing low WBC or a history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and LATUDA should be discontinued at the first sign of decline in WBC, in the absence of other causative factors.



 Patients with neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1000/mm  3  ) should discontinue LATUDA and have their WBC followed until recovery.



    5.9 Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope



  LATUDA may cause orthostatic hypotension and syncope, perhaps due to its alpha1-adrenergic receptor antagonism. Associated adverse reactions can include dizziness, lightheadedness, tachycardia, and bradycardia. Generally, these risks are greatest at the beginning of treatment and during dose escalation. Patients at increased risk of these adverse reactions or at increased risk of developing complications from hypotension include those with dehydration, hypovolemia, treatment with antihypertensive medication, history of cardiovascular disease (e.g., heart failure, myocardial infarction, ischemia, or conduction abnormalities), history of cerebrovascular disease, as well as patients who are antipsychotic-naive. In such patients, consider using a lower starting dose and slower titration, and monitor orthostatic vital signs.



 Orthostatic hypotension, as assessed by vital sign measurement, was defined by the following vital sign changes: &gt;= 20 mm Hg decrease in systolic blood pressure and &gt;= 10 bpm increase in pulse from sitting to standing or supine to standing position.



    Schizophrenia  



 The incidence of orthostatic hypotension and syncope reported as adverse events from short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies was (LATUDA incidence, placebo incidence): orthostatic hypotension [0.3% (5/1508), 0.1% (1/708)] and syncope [0.1% (2/1508), 0% (0/708)].



 In short-term schizophrenia clinical studies, orthostatic hypotension, as assessed by vital signs, occurred with a frequency of 0.8% with LATUDA 40 mg, 2.1% with LATUDA 80 mg, 1.7% with LATUDA 120 mg and 0.8% with LATUDA 160 mg compared to 0.7% with placebo.



    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, there were no reported adverse events of orthostatic hypotension and syncope.



 Orthostatic hypotension, as assessed by vital signs, occurred with a frequency of 0.6% with LATUDA 20 to 60 mg and 0.6% with LATUDA 80 to 120 mg compared to 0% with placebo.



  Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression therapy studies, there were no reported adverse events of orthostatic hypotension and syncope. Orthostatic hypotension, as assessed by vital signs, occurred with a frequency of 1.1% with LATUDA 20 to 120 mg compared to 0.9% with placebo.



    5.10 Seizures



  As with other antipsychotic drugs, LATUDA should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold, e.g., Alzheimer's dementia. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in patients 65 years or older.



  Schizophrenia  



 In short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies, seizures/convulsions occurred in 0.1% (2/1508) of patients treated with LATUDA compared to 0.1% (1/708) placebo-treated patients.



    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, no patient experienced seizures/convulsions.



    Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies, no patient experienced seizures/convulsions.



    5.11 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  LATUDA, like other antipsychotics, has the potential to impair judgment, thinking or motor skills. Caution patients about operating hazardous machinery, including motor vehicles, until they are reasonably certain that therapy with LATUDA does not affect them adversely.



 In clinical studies with LATUDA, somnolence included: hypersomnia, hypersomnolence, sedation and somnolence.



    Schizophrenia  



 In short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies, somnolence was reported by 17.0% (256/1508) of patients treated with LATUDA (15.5% LATUDA 20 mg, 15.6% LATUDA 40 mg, 15.2% LATUDA 80 mg, 26.5% LATUDA 120 mg and 8.3% LATUDA 160 mg/day) compared to 7.1% (50/708) of placebo patients.



    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 In the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, somnolence was reported by 7.3% (12/164) and 13.8% (23/167) with LATUDA 20 to 60 mg and 80 to120 mg, respectively compared to 6.5% (11/168) of placebo patients.



    Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 In the short-term, flexible-dosed, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies, somnolence was reported by 11.4% (41/360) of patients treated with LATUDA 20-120 mg compared to 5.1% (17/334) of placebo patients.



    5.12 Body Temperature Dysregulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing LATUDA for patients who will be experiencing conditions that may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.9  )].  



    5.13 Suicide



  The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in psychotic illness and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy. Prescriptions for LATUDA should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



    Schizophrenia  



 In short-term, placebo-controlled schizophrenia studies, the incidence of treatment-emergent suicidal ideation was 0.4% (6/1508) for LATUDA-treated patients compared to 0.8% (6/708) on placebo. No suicide attempts or completed suicides were reported in these studies.



    Bipolar Depression  



    Monotherapy  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled monotherapy bipolar depression study, the incidence of treatment-emergent suicidal ideation was 0.0% (0/331) with LATUDA-treated patients compared to 0.0% (0/168) with placebo-treated patients. No suicide attempts or completed suicides were reported in this study.



    Adjunctive Therapy with Lithium or Valproate  



 In the short-term, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled adjunctive therapy bipolar depression studies, the incidence of treatment-emergent suicidal ideation was 1.1% (4/360) for LATUDA-treated patients compared to 0.3% (1/334) on placebo. No suicide attempts or completed suicides were reported in these studies.



    5.14 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



  Antidepressant treatment can increase the risk of developing a manic or hypomanic episode, particularly in patients with bipolar disorder. Monitor patients for the emergence of such episodes.



 In the bipolar depression monotherapy and adjunctive therapy (with lithium or valproate) studies, less than 1% of subjects in the LATUDA and placebo groups developed manic or hypomanic episodes.



    5.15 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in elderly patients, in particular those with advanced Alzheimer's dementia. LATUDA and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia.



    5.16 Neurological Adverse Reactions in Patients with Parkinson's Disease or Dementia with Lewy Bodies



  Patients with Parkinson's Disease or Dementia with Lewy Bodies are reported to have an increased sensitivity to antipsychotic medication. Manifestations of this increased sensitivity include confusion, obtundation, postural instability with frequent falls, extrapyramidal symptoms, and clinical features consistent with the neuroleptic malignant syndrome.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
