<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="laviv" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;=1% of subjects in clinical trials, were injection-site reactions, including redness, bruising, swelling, pain, hemorrhage, edema, nodules, papules, irritation, dermatitis, and pruritus.



 Adverse reactions occurring in less than 1% of trial subjects were acne, facial or eyelid edema, hypersensitivity or decreased skin sensation at the injection site, post-procedural discomfort (headache, toothache, and jaw pain), herpes labialis, hyperpigmentation at the injection site, injection-site ischemia, basal cell cancer, and leukocytoclastic vasculitis.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;= 1% of patients who received LAVIV, were injection-site redness, bruising, swelling, pain, hemorrhage, edema, nodules, papules, irritation, dermatitis, and pruritus. (  6  )



 Adverse reactions occurring in fewer than 1% of trial subjects were acne, facial or eyelid edema, hypersensitivity or decreased skin sensation at the injection site, post-procedural discomfort (headache, toothache, and jaw pain), herpes labialis, hyperpigmentation at the injection site, injection-site ischemia, basal cell cancer, and leukocytoclastic vasculitis. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Fibrocell at 484-713-6000 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions observed in the clinical trials of a product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another product and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The overall clinical trial safety database for LAVIV includes 508 subjects who received at least one treatment of LAVIV and 354 subjects who received a vehicle-control in seven clinical trials for treatment of facial wrinkles (a skin biopsy study is described separately). This total safety population included patients aged 20 to 79 years, of whom 92% were female and 92% were White. The average duration of observation in the safety population was approximately 12 months.



 An integrated summary of the adverse reactions from the seven clinical trials is presented in  Table 1  . More than 80% of all adverse reactions were local and required no treatment. Eighty-six percent of all injection-site adverse reactions resolved within one week.



 The adverse reactions to the vehicle (  Table 1  ) should not be viewed as adverse reactions to a placebo but rather as reactions to a non-cellular component of LAVIV, or to the injection procedure, or to both.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 1% of the Study Population Who Received LAVIV or Vehicle 
  * Number and percent of subjects with injection-site reactions    
  
                                         LAVIV (508 Subjects)    n (%)*      Vehicle (354 Subjects)    n (%)*     
   Any Injection-Site Reaction           343 (67)                        144 (40)                          
 Erythema                              81 (16)                         33 (9)                              
 Bruising                              54 (11)                         48 (14)                             
 Swelling                              69 (14)                         15 (4)                              
 Pain                                  31 (6)                          6 (2)                               
 Hemorrhage                            13 (3)                          16 (5)                              
 Edema                                 22 (4)                          0                                   
 Nodules                               20 (4)                          3 (&lt;1)                              
 Papules                               8 (2)                           3 (&lt;1)                              
 Irritation                            6 (1)                           1 (&lt;1)                              
 Dermatitis                            5 (1)                           2 (&lt;1)                              
 Pruritus                              5 (1)                           3 (&lt;1)                              
         Adverse reactions occurring in fewer than 1% of trial subjects were acne, facial or eyelid edema, hypersensitivity or decreased skin sensation at the injection site, post-procedural discomfort (headache, toothache, and jaw pain), herpes labialis, hyperpigmentation at the injection site, injection-site ischemia, basal cell cancer, and leukocytoclastic vasculitis. In the skin biopsy study (described below), one subject was hospitalized for leukocytoclastic vasculitis, with lesions on his legs and trunk appearing nine days after product administration in his upper arm. These lesions resolved within 35 days after onset.
 

     Skin Biopsy Study  



 A skin biopsy study was conducted to observe tissue responses and adverse reactions to LAVIV at the histological level. Twenty-nine subjects who had participated in a prior clinical trial of LAVIV, and who had sufficient quantities of autologous fibroblasts remaining, received up to three treatments of LAVIV in their upper arms at five-week intervals. Seven subjects received three treatments; 21 received two treatments; and one received only one treatment. Saline injections and non-treated areas in the contralateral arm were used as controls. The dose of LAVIV used in the skin biopsy study was the same as in the clinical trials (0.1 milliliter per linear centimeter of skin). The subjects and the two independent histopathology evaluators were blinded to treatment at each skin area.



 Biopsies were taken from LAVIV- and saline-treated sites at 3 and 6 months after the last injection. Biopsies from untreated sites were taken only at 3 months. Histological evaluation was performed for all 29 subjects. At 3 months, histological examination showed inflammatory cell infiltration in 50% of LAVIV-treated sites as compared with 7% of placebo-treated or untreated sites. At 6 months, inflammatory cell infiltration was seen in 27% of the LAVIV-treated sites compared with 12% of placebo-treated sites. In all 29 subjects, there was no histological evidence of abnormal fibroblasts, significant scar formation, or abnormal organization of the extracellular matrix. There were no observed differences in epidermal/dermal thickness or cellularity between LAVIV-injected and placebo-injected skin samples.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity reactions can occur with LAVIV. (  5.1  ) 
 *  LAVIV can cause bleeding and bruising at the treatment site. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Vasculitis has occurred following treatment with LAVIV. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Herpes labialis has occurred following treatment with LAVIV. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Basal cell cancer has occurred following treatment with LAVIV. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Keloid and hypertrophic scarring may occur following post-auricular skin biopsies or LAVIV injections. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Patients with genetic disorders affecting dermal fibroblasts or formation of normal collagen matrices may have an abnormal response to LAVIV. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Immunosuppressed patients, or those who undergo chemotherapy for malignancies or receive immunomodulatory therapies for autoimmune diseases, may have an increased susceptibility to infection and difficulty healing from LAVIV treatments. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Employ universal precautions when handling LAVIV. Patients undergoing procedures associated with LAVIV are not routinely tested for adventitious viruses. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Sterility tests are not completed when LAVIV is shipped to the clinic. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions have occurred in patients treated with LAVIV.



    5.2 Bleeding and Bruising



  Injection-site bleeding and bruising can occur in patients treated with LAVIV. Patients taking aspirin, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS) or anticoagulants, as well as patients with coagulopathies, have a greater risk of severe bleeding or bruising. [See Drug Interactions (  7  )]  



    5.3 Vasculitis



  Leukocytoclastic vasculitis has occurred following treatment with LAVIV. [See Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  



    5.4 Herpes labialis



  Herpes labialis has occurred following treatment with LAVIV.



    5.5 Malignancy



  Chemotherapeutic drugs may interfere with the function of LAVIV. Patients with malignancies requiring ongoing therapy should not use LAVIV. Furthermore, patients undergoing chemotherapy are often immunosuppressed, and therefore may be at increased risk of infection following the use of LAVIV. [See Immunosuppression (  5.8  )]  



 A case of basal cell carcinoma was reported near the injection site seven months following LAVIV treatment in clinical trials. While the etiology of the case is uncertain, LAVIV is not recommended for patients with a known history of skin cancer.



    5.6 Keloid Formation



  The use of LAVIV requires three post-auricular skin biopsies and multiple injections in the nasolabial folds. These procedures traumatize the skin and may lead to keloid or hypertrophic scar formation in susceptible individuals. While excessive scarring or keloid formation was not observed in either the post-auricular biopsy or the injected areas during the clinical trials, the study population included only four African-American subjects, and Fitzpatrick skin types were not recorded. LAVIV is not recommended for patients with a known history of keloids or hypertrophic scarring.



    5.7 Genetic disorders



  Disorders affecting dermal fibroblasts, formation of normal collagen matrices, or other skin components may cause an abnormal response to LAVIV. Thus, LAVIV is not recommended for patients with such genetic disorders as Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, achondroplasia, osteogenesis imperfecta, epidermolysis bullosa, Marfan syndrome, and ataxia-telangiectasia.



    5.8 Immunosuppression and Autoimmune Disorders



  Patients with active autoimmune disease or patients on immunosuppressant therapies may be more susceptible to infection and have difficulty healing following the use of LAVIV. LAVIV is an autologous cell product, and the safety and efficacy of LAVIV in patients with autoimmune disease are unknown.



    5.9 Control of Infectious Disease



  Patients undergoing the treatment procedures associated with LAVIV are not routinely tested for adventitious viruses. Therefore, healthcare providers should employ universal precautions when handling LAVIV or biopsy material.



    5.10 Sterility Testing



  LAVIV is shipped following a passing sterility test result for cryopreserved bulk material (Drug Substance) and a negative Gram stain test result on the final LAVIV drug product. Full sterility test results are not available for the LAVIV drug product prior to treatment for up to 14 days. If microbial contamination is detected after the product has been shipped, Fibrocell will notify the health care providers and recommend appropriate actions.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
