<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lazanda" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Most common (frequency &gt;=5%): vomiting, nausea, dizziness, pyrexia, and constipation. [  6.1  ] 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Archimedes Pharma at 1-866-435-6775 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse event rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of Lazanda has been evaluated in a total of 523 opioid-tolerant patients with breakthrough cancer pain. The average duration of therapy in patients in the long-term study was 73 days, with 153 patients being treated for over 3 months. Patients continuing into the open-label extension period of the safety study have been treated for up to 26 months.



 The most commonly observed adverse events seen with Lazanda are typical of opioid side effects, such as nausea, constipation, somnolence, and headache. Expect opioid side effects and manage them accordingly.



 The clinical trials of Lazanda were designed to evaluate safety and efficacy in treating breakthrough cancer pain; all patients were also taking concomitant opioids, such as sustained-release morphine, sustained-release oxycodone, or transdermal fentanyl, for their persistent cancer pain. The adverse reaction data presented in Table 1 reflect the actual percentage of patients experiencing each adverse effect among patients who received Lazanda for breakthrough cancer pain along with a concomitant opioid for persistent cancer pain. There has been no attempt to correct for concomitant use of other opioids, duration of Lazanda therapy, or cancer-related symptoms. Adverse events are included regardless of causality or severity. Table 1 lists adverse reactions with an overall frequency of 5% or greater within the total population that occurred during titration by maximum dose received. The ability to assign Lazanda a dose-response relationship to these adverse events is limited by the titration schemes used in these studies.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions That Occurred During Titration at a Frequency of &gt;=5% 
 System Organ ClassMeDRA preferred term, n (%)  100 mcg(N=483)   200 mcg(N=380)   400 mcg(N=301)   800 mcg(N=161)   Total(N=516)      
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
   Nausea                   19 (4)           6 (2)            6 (2)            5 (3)            35 (7)            
   Vomiting                 14 (3)           10 (3)           9 (3)            1 (1)            33 (6)            
   Nervous system disorders     
   Dizziness                14 (3)           11 (3)           6 (2)            4 (2)            31 (6)            
            Table 2 lists, by dose, adverse reactions with an overall frequency of &gt;=5% within the total population that occurred after a final titrated dose had been determined.
 

 Table 2: Adverse Reactions That Occurred During Maintenance Treatment at a Frequency of &gt;=5% 
 System Organ ClassMeDRA preferred term, n (%)  100 mcg(N=61)    200 mcg(N=68)    400 mcg(N=109)   800 mcg(N=108)   Total(N=346)      
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
   Vomiting                 8 (13)           5 (7)            9 (8)            12 (11)          34 (10)           
   Nausea                   4 (7)            6 (9)            4 (4)            9 (8)            23 (7)            
   Constipation             6 (10)           1 (1)            8 (7)            5 (5)            20 (6)            
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
   Pyrexia                  3 (5)            5 (7)            8 (7)            6 (6)            22 (6)            
            The adverse reactions listed below represent those that occurred in &gt;=1% of patients from clinical trials while receiving Lazanda. Events are classified by system organ class.
 

   Adverse Events (&gt;=1%)    Eye disorders:  dry eye, swelling, ptosis, strabismus  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  anemia, neutropenia  Cardiac Disorders:  cardiorespiratory arrest  Gastrointestinal Disorders:  vomiting, nausea, constipation, diarrhea, abdominal pain, gastritis, ascites, dry mouth, dyspepsia, mouth ulcer, proctalgia  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  pyrexia, fatigue, edema peripheral, asthenia, edema  Hepatobiliary Disorders:  jaundice  Immune System Disorders:  hypersensitivity  Infections and Infestations:  urinary tract infection, pneumonia, nasopharyngitis, infection, rhinitis, upper respiratory tract infection, bronchitis  Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  fall  Investigations:  weight decreased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  dehydration, decreased appetite, hyperglycemia, anorexia  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  back pain, pain in extremity, arthralgia  Nervous System Disorders:  dizziness, somnolence, headache, dysgeusia  Psychiatric Disorders:  anxiety, insomnia, depression, confusional state, disorientation, agitation  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  dyspnea, epistaxis, cough, pharyngolaryngeal pain, nasal discomfort, rhinorrhea, nasal congestion, postnasal drip, pulmonary embolism  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  pruritus, hyperhidrosis, decubitus ulcer, mouth ulceration  Vascular Disorders:  hypertension, deep vein thrombosis
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL

    WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL  

    RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION  



   Fatal respiratory depression has occurred in patients treated with immediate-release transmucosal fentanyl, including following use in opioid non-tolerant patients and improper dosing.  The substitution of Lazanda for any other fentanyl product may result in fatal overdose.  



   Due to the risk of respiratory depression, Lazanda is contraindicated in the management of acute or postoperative pain including headache/migraine and in opioid non-tolerant patients. [see     Contraindications (4)    ]  



   Lazanda must be kept out of reach of children. [see     Patient Counseling Information (17.1)     and     How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16.1)    ]  



 The concomitant use of Lazanda with CYP3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentrations, and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression [see     Drug Interactions (7)    ]. 



   MEDICATION ERRORS  



   Substantial differences exist in the pharmacokinetic profile of Lazanda compared to other fentanyl products that result in clinically important differences in the extent of absorption of fentanyl that could result in fatal overdose.  



 *  When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other fentanyl products to Lazanda. (2.1) 
 *  When dispensing, do not substitute a Lazanda prescription for other fentanyl products. 
      ABUSE POTENTIAL  
 

   Lazanda contains fentanyl, an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance, with an abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics.  Lazanda can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit.  This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing Lazanda in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse or diversion.    



   Because of the risk for misuse, abuse, addiction, and overdose, Lazanda is available only through a restricted program   required by the Food and Drug Administration, called a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS). Under the Transmucosal Immediate Release Fentanyl (TIRF) REMS Access program, outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program. [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.10)    ] Further information is available at www.TIRFREMSaccess.com or by calling 1-866-822-1483.



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .  



 *  Due to the risk of fatal respiratory depression, Lazanda is contraindicated in opioid non-tolerant patients (1) and in management of acute or postoperative pain, including headache/migraines. (4) 
 *  Keep out of reach of children. (5.3) 
 *  Use with CYP3A4 inhibitors may cause fatal respiratory depression. (7) 
 *  When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other oral transmucosal fentanyl product to Lazanda. (2.1, 5.2) 
 *  When dispensing, do not substitute with any other fentanyl products. (5.2) 
 *  Contains fentanyl, a Schedule II controlled substance with abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics. (9.1) 
 *  Lazanda is available only through a restricted program called the TIRF REMS Access program. Outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors are required to enroll in the program. (5.10) 
    
 







    BOXED WARNING: 

  Medication Guide



   Lazanda  (r)   (La-ZAN-da) CII   



   (fentanyl)nasal spray100 mcg, 400 mcg  



     IMPORTANT:  



   Do not use Lazanda unless you are regularly using another opioid pain medicine around-the-clock for your cancer pain and your body is used to these medicines (this means that you are opioid tolerant). You can ask your healthcare provider if you are opioid tolerant.  



   Keep Lazanda in a safe place away from children.  



   Get emergency medical help right away if:   



 *  a child takes Lazanda. Lazanda can cause an overdose and death in any child who takes it 
 *  an adult who has not been prescribed Lazanda takes it 
 *  an adult who is not already taking opioids around-the-clock takes Lazanda 
      These are medical emergencies that can cause death.  
 

     Read this Medication Guide completely   before you start taking Lazanda and each time you get a new prescription.  There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or your treatment. Be sure to share this important information with members of your household and other caregivers.



   What is the most important information I should know about Lazanda?  



   Lazanda can cause life-threatening breathing problems that can lead to death:  



 *  Do not take Lazanda if you are not opioid tolerant. 
 *  If you stop taking your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine for your cancer, you must stop taking Lazanda. You may no longer be opioid tolerant. Talk to your healthcare provider about how to treat your pain. 
 *  Take Lazanda exactly as prescribed by your healthcare provider.You must not take more than 1 dose of Lazanda for each episode of breakthrough cancer pain. You must wait two hours before treating a new episode of breakthrough cancer pain with Lazanda. See the Medication Guide section "How should I use Lazanda?" and the "Instructions for Use" section at the end of this Medication Guide for detailed information about how to use Lazanda the right way. 
 *  Do not switch from Lazanda to other medicines that contain fentanyl without talking with your healthcare provider. The amount of fentanyl in a dose of Lazanda is not the same as the amount of fentanyl in other medicines that contain fentanyl. Your healthcare provider will prescribe a starting dose of Lazanda that may be different than other fentanyl-containing medicine you may have been taking. 
 *  Do not take Lazanda for short-term pain that you would expect to go away in a few days, such as: pain after surgeryheadache or migrainedental pain 
 *  Never give Lazanda to anyone else, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them or even cause death. 
    Lazanda is a federally controlled substance (CII) because it is a strong opioid (narcotic) pain medicine that can be misused by people who abuse prescription medicines or street drugs.
 

 *  Prevent theft, misuse or abuse. Keep Lazanda in a safe place to protect it from being stolen. Lazanda can be a target for people who abuse opioid (narcotic) medicines or street drugs. 
 *  Selling or giving away this medicine is against the law. 
    Lazanda is available only through a program called the TIRF REMS ACCESS program.  To receive Lazanda, you must:
 

 *  talk to your healthcare provider 
 *  understand the benefits and risks of Lazanda 
 *  agree to all of the instructions 
 *  sign the Patient-Prescriber Agreement form 
      What is Lazanda  (r)  ?  
 

 *  Lazanda is a prescription medicine that contains the medicine fentanyl. 
 *  Lazanda is used to manage breakthrough pain in adults with cancer (18 years of age and older) who are already routinely taking other opioid pain medicines around-the-clock for cancer pain. 
 *  Lazanda is started only after you have been taking other opioid pain medicines and your body has become used to them (you are opioid tolerant). Do not use Lazanda if you are not opioid tolerant. 
 *  You must stay under your healthcare provider's care while taking Lazanda. 
 *  Lazanda is a nasal spray. You use Lazanda by placing the nozzle attached to the bottle in your nostril and spraying. See the Medication Guide section "How should I use Lazanda?" 
 *  Lazanda is only: available through the TIRF REMS ACCESS programgiven to people who are opioid tolerant 
    It is not known if Lazanda is safe and effective in children under 18 years of age.
 

   Who should not take Lazanda?  



   Do not take Lazanda:  



 *  if you are not opioid tolerant. Opioid tolerant means that you are already taking other opioid (narcotic) pain medicines around-the-clock for your cancer pain and your body is used to these medicines 
 *  for short-term pain that you would expect to go away in a few days, such as:pain after surgeryheadache or migrainedental pain 
 *  if you are allergic to fentanyl or any of the ingredients in Lazanda. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of other ingredients in Lazanda. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking Lazanda?  
 

   Before taking Lazanda, tell your healthcare provider if you:   



 *  have trouble breathing or lung problems such as asthma, wheezing, or shortness of breath 
 *  have or had a head injury or brain problem 
 *  have liver or kidney problems 
 *  have seizures 
 *  have a slow heart rate or other heart problems 
 *  have low blood pressure 
 *  have mental health problems including major depression, schizophrenia, or hallucinations (seeing or hearing things that are not there) 
 *  have a past or present drinking problem (alcoholism), or a family history of drinking problems 
 *  have a past or present drug abuse problem or addiction problem, or a family history of a drug abuse problem or addiction problem 
 *  have any other medical conditions 
 *  are pregnant or planning to become pregnant. Lazanda may cause serious harm to your unborn baby 
 *  are breastfeeding or plan to breastfeed. Lazanda can pass into your breast milk. It can cause serious harm to your baby. Do not use Lazanda while breastfeeding 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take,   including prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Some medicines may cause serious or life-threatening medical problems when taken with Lazanda. Sometimes, the doses of certain medicines and Lazanda need to be changed if used together.
 

 *  Do not take any medicine while using Lazanda until you have talked to your healthcare provider. Your healthcare provider will tell you if it is safe to take other medicines while you are using Lazanda. 
 *  Be very careful about taking other medicines that may make you sleepy, such as other pain medicines, anti-depressants, sleeping pills, anti-anxiety medicines, anti-histamines, or tranquilizers. 
    Know the medicines you take. Keep a list of them to show your healthcare provider and pharmacist when you get a new medicine.
 

   How should I use Lazanda?  



   Before you can begin to use Lazanda:  



 *  Your healthcare provider will explain the TIRF REMS ACCESS program to you. 
 *  You will sign the TIRF REMS ACCESS program Patient-Prescriber Agreement form. 
 *  Lazanda is only available at pharmacies that are part of the TIRF REMS ACCESS program. Your healthcare provider will let you know the pharmacy closest to your home where you can have your Lazanda prescription filled. 
      Using Lazanda:  
 

 *  Use Lazanda exactly as your healthcare provider tells you to. Do not use Lazanda more often than prescribed. 
 *  See the "Instructions for Use" section at the end of this Medication Guide for detailed information about the right way to use and throw away (dispose of) Lazanda. 
 *  Lazanda comes in 2 strengths. When you are first prescribed Lazanda, your healthcare provider will start you with the lower strength medicine, and will change the dose until you and your healthcare provider find the right dose for you. Do not change your dose of Lazanda unless your healthcare provider tells you to. 
 *  The beginning dose of Lazanda is always 1 spray in one of your nostrils. 
 *  Always use 1 dose of Lazanda for an episode of breakthrough cancer pain exactly as your healthcare provider tells you to. As your dose is adjusted, your healthcare provider will tell you whether your dose of Lazanda is 1 or 2 sprays: 1 spray is given by spraying 1 time into one of your nostrils2 sprays are given by spraying 1 time into each nostril for a total of 2 sprays.You must never use more than 2 sprays (1 spray in each nostril) for an episode of breakthrough pain. 
 *  If an episode of breakthrough cancer pain continues for more than 30 minutes after you take a dose of Lazanda, follow your healthcare provider's instructions about taking a short-acting opioid pain medicine to manage your pain. 
 *  Wait at least 2 hours before treating a new episode of breakthrough cancer pain with Lazanda. 
 *  It is important for you to keep taking your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine while using Lazanda. 
 *  Talk to your healthcare provider if your dose of Lazanda does not relieve your breakthrough cancer pain. Your healthcare provider will decide if your dose of Lazanda needs to be changed. 
 *  Talk to your healthcare provider if you have more than 4 episodes of breakthrough cancer pain per day. The dose of your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine may need to be adjusted. 
 *  The Lazanda nasal spray pump provides a total of 8 full sprays. When there is a red number "8" in the counting window, you have used all the medicine in the bottle. You may still see medicine in the bottle, but there is not enough for a full dose. Do not try to take more than 8 sprays from a bottle of Lazanda. 
 *  If you use too much Lazanda or overdose, you or your caregiver should call for emergency medical help or have someone take you to the nearest hospital emergency room right away. 
      What should I avoid while using Lazanda?  
 

 *  Do not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how Lazanda affects you. Lazanda can make you sleepy. Ask your healthcare provider when it is okay to do these activities. 
 *  Do not drink alcohol while using Lazanda. It can increase your chance of getting dangerous side effects. 
 *  Avoid drinking grapefruit juice during treatment with Lazanda. 
      What are the possible side effects of Lazanda?  
 

 *  1.Breathing problems that can become life-threatening. See "What is the most important information I should know about Lazanda?" Call your healthcare provider or get emergency medical help right away if you: have trouble breathinghave drowsiness with slowed breathinghave shallow breathing (little chest movement with breathing)feel faint, very dizzy, confused, or have other unusual symptoms 
   *    These symptoms can be a sign that you have taken too much Lazanda or the dose is too high for you. These symptoms may lead to serious problems or death if not treated right away. If you have any of these symptoms, do not take any more Lazanda until you have talked to your healthcare provider. 
   *  2.Decreased blood pressure. This can make you feel dizzy or lightheaded if you get up too fast from sitting or lying down. 
 *  3.Physical dependence. Do not stop taking Lazanda or any other opioid without talking to your healthcare provider. You could become sick with uncomfortable withdrawal symptoms because your body has become used to these medicines. Physical dependency is not the same as drug addiction. 
 *  4.A chance of abuse or addiction. The chance is higher if you are or have ever been addicted to or abused other medicines, street drugs, or alcohol, or if you have a history of mental problems. 
    The most common side effects of Lazanda are:
 

 *  vomiting 
 *  nausea 
 *  constipation 
 *  dizziness 
 *  fever 
    Constipation (not often enough or hard bowel movements) is a very common side effect of pain medicines (opioids) including Lazanda and is unlikely to go away without treatment. Talk to your healthcare provider about dietary changes and the use of laxatives (medicines to treat constipation) and stool softeners to prevent or treat constipation while taking Lazanda.
 

 Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away.



 These are not all the possible side effects of Lazanda. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.



 Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.  



   How should I store Lazanda?  



 *  Always keep Lazanda in a safe place away from children and from anyone for whom it has not been prescribed. Protect Lazanda from theft. 
 *  Store Lazanda at up to 77 degrees F (25 degrees C). Do not freeze Lazanda. 
 *  Lazanda comes in a clear glass bottle with an attached nasal spray pump and a protective cap. 
 *  Store Lazanda in the child-resistant container that comes with it at all times except when you are using it. Store the Lazanda child-resistant container and pouch in the cardboard box when not in use. 
 *  Keep Lazanda away from light. 
 *  See the "Instructions for Use" section at the end of this Medication Guide for information about the right way to dispose of Lazanda when no longer needed. 
      General information about Lazanda  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide.   Use Lazanda only for the purpose for which it was prescribed. Do not give Lazanda to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have  . Lazanda can harm other people and even cause death. Sharing Lazanda is against the law.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about Lazanda. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You can ask your pharmacist or healthcare provider for information about Lazanda that is written for healthcare professionals. 



 For more information about the TIRF REMS ACCESS program, go to www.tirfremsaccess.com or call 1-866-822-1483.



   What are the ingredients in Lazanda?  



 Active ingredient: fentanyl citrateInactive ingredients: mannitol, pectin, phenylethyl alcohol, propylparaben, sucrose, water



   Instructions for Use   



 Before you take Lazanda it is important that you read, understand, and follow the full Medication Guide, including these Instructions for Use. Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you have any questions about the right way to prepare, use, or dispose of Lazanda. Wash your hands with soap and water before and after you use Lazanda.




 What will I find in the Lazanda pack?  Each Lazanda pack contains a cardboard box that includes (See Figure A):a Medication Guide (not shown)a disposal pouch (See Figure B)a child-resistant container, which holds 1 bottle of Lazanda.Take the pouch and the Lazanda bottle in its child-resistant container out of the cardboard box when you are ready to use it. Keep the cardboard box and child-resistant container for storing your Lazanda. You will need to keep the pouch to safely dispose of any medicine left in the bottle. Do not remove the plastic strip from the pouch until you are ready to seal it.Store the Lazanda bottle in the child-resistant container whenever it is not in use.See the section "How should I store Lazanda?" for more information about storing Lazanda.                                             
      
                                                                                                          
 Preparing Lazanda for use  Before you use a new bottle of Lazanda for the first time, you will need to prime (prepare) the bottle. To prime the bottle: 1.Remove the cap from the child-resistant container. To do this, squeeze the raised tabs on the cap and twist the cap to remove (See Figure C). Take the bottle of Lazanda out of the child-resistant container. 2.Remove the protective cap from the nozzle (tip) (See Figure D). 3.Place the tip of the Lazanda bottle into the opening of the pouch. Hold the Lazanda bottle upright so that the spray goes into the pouch (See Figure E).                                    
 4.Look at the counting window. A new unused bottle of Lazanda will show 2 thin red lines in the counting window in the white plastic top on the bottle (See Figure F).                                    
  Firmly press on the grips and then release. You will hear a "click" and you will see 1 wide red bar in the counting window (See Figure G). Keep pressing and releasing the grips 3 more times (for a total of 4 times). Each time, the red bar will become smaller until you see a green bar in the counting window (See Figures H, I, J).                                    
 5.When you see the green bar, this means that Lazanda is ready for use (See Figure K). 6.Remove the tip of the bottle from the pouch. Do not seal the pouch. Do not throw the pouch away. 7.If you are not going to take your medicine right away  Replace the protective cap Put the bottle in its child-resistant container. Put the child-resistant container and pouch in the cardboard box. Store the box securely out of the reach of children and pets 8.Wash your hands with soap and water.                                   
      
 Using Lazanda                                                                                            
 1.Check to be sure that the Lazanda bottle is ready for use. If the bottle is ready for use, you will see either a green bar (See Figure L) or a number (See Figure M) in the counting window. 2.If you have a runny nose, blow your nose now. 3.Remove the protective cap from the nozzle (tip). 4.Sit up with your head upright and hold the Lazanda bottle with your thumb on the bottom of the bottle and your first and middle fingers on the finger grips (See Figure N). Insert the tip a short distance (about 1/2 inch) into your nose, and point the tip toward the bridge of your nose. This will tilt the bottle slightly (See Figure O).                                             
 5.Close off the other nostril with 1 finger (See Figure P). 6.Firmly press down on the finger grips until you hear a "click". 7.Breathe in gently through your nose and out through your mouth 1 time after spraying. Do not sniff after spraying the medicine into your nose.   You may not feel the spray go into your nose. This is normal.After you hear the click, you will see that the number in the counting window has increased by 1. This tells you that a spray has been given. 8.If your healthcare provider has prescribed a second spray, repeat steps 4 through 7, but use the other nostril. 9.After each spray, the number in the counting window will increase by 1. When you see a red number "8" in the counting window, the bottle is finished and you will no longer be able to get a full dose from it. You may still see medicine in the bottle, but there is not enough for a full dose. Do not try to take another dose of Lazanda from this bottle.   
 10.Stay sitting down for at least 1 minute after using Lazanda. 11.Avoid blowing your nose for at least 30 minutes after each spray. 12.Replace the protective cap on the tip of the bottle (See Figure Q). Return the bottle to the child-resistant container after each use, and store securely out of the reach of children.                                             
      
 Disposing of Lazanda Dispose of the Lazanda bottle when no longer needed: If you have used 8 sprays from a bottle, orIf it has been 5 days since you last used the bottle, or If it has been 14 days since you primed (prepared) your bottle Before you throw away the Lazanda bottle, you must empty all the remaining medicine into the pouch. This is to protect others, especially children, from harm. Disposal of any unused Lazanda If you can see a number, other than 8 in the counting window, you have NOT used all 8 sprays in the bottle. There are still doses of Lazanda in the bottle.   
 You must empty the remaining doses of Lazanda from the bottlePut tip in pouch and press and release the grips (See Figure R) until the red number "8" appears in the counting window (See Figure S). When you see the number "8" in the counting window (See Figure S), there is still medicine in the bottle that you must spray in the pouch.Put the tip into the pouch.(See Figure R)Press and release the grips a total of 4 times (See Figure R)You will feel some increased resistance when you press downYou will not hear a click when you press downThe counter will stay on the red number "8" (See Figure S)                                   
 Disposal of Bottle and Pouch1.Put the protective cap back on the spray bottle. Put the empty bottle back into the child-resistant container. 2.Seal the pouch by removing the plastic strip from the flap and folding the flap over (See Figures T and U). Put the sealed pouch into the child-resistant container with the empty bottle. 3.Place the cap back onto the child-resistant container and twist to close. 4.Throw the child-resistant container with the empty bottle and sealed pouch inside it into the trash.  5.Wash your hands with soap and water.                                   
        If you need help with disposal of unused Lazanda bottles, call Archimedes Pharma at 1-866-435-6775 or call your local Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) office.
 

 If you lose the pouch, use a pouch from another Lazanda pack to prime and dispose of unused medicine from this bottle as well as from the next bottle. If you do not have an empty pouch available, you can order one by calling 1-866-435-6775. You will receive the replacement pouch in the mail.



 If you need to continue using Lazanda, open a new bottle and see the   Instructions for Use   section of this Medication Guide about "  Preparing Lazanda for Use  ."



 This Medication Guide has been approved by the US Food and Drug Administration.



 Archimedes Pharma US Inc.  One Crossroads Drive  Bedminster NJ 07921Revised: 12/2011



 Lazanda  (r)   is a registered trademark of Archimedes Development Ltd.(c)2011 Archimedes Development Ltd.All rights reserved.



 MGUS300



  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure  Figure 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Clinically significant respiratory and CNS depression can occur. Monitor patients accordingly. [  5.1  ] 
 *  Do not convert patients to Lazanda from other fentanyl products on a mcg per mcg basis, or substitute a Lazanda prescription for another fentanyl product, such substitution may result in fatal overdose. [  5.2  ] 
 *  Lazanda bottles contain medicine that can be fatal to a child. Ensure proper storage and disposal. [  5.3  ,  16.2  ,  16.3  ] 
 *  Use with other CNS depressants and potent CYP450 3A4 inhibitors may increase depressant effects including hypoventilation, hypotension, and profound sedation. Consider dosage adjustments if warranted. [  5.2  ,  5.4  ] 
 *  Titrate Lazanda cautiously in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or preexisting medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression and in patients susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention. [  5.2  ,  5.6  ,  5.7  ] 
    
 

   5.1 Respiratory Depression



  Serious or fatal respiratory depression can occur even at recommended doses in patients using Lazanda. Respiratory depression is more likely to occur in patients with underlying respiratory disorders and elderly or debilitated patients, in opioid non-tolerant patients, or when opioids are given in conjunction with other drugs that depress respiration.



 Respiratory depression from opioids is manifested by a reduced urge to breathe and a decreased rate of respiration, often associated with a "sighing" pattern of breathing (deep breaths separated by abnormally long pauses). Carbon dioxide retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids. This makes overdoses involving drugs with sedative properties and opioids especially dangerous.



    5.2 Lazanda and other Fentanyl Products



  Lazanda is NOT equivalent to other fentanyl products used to treat breakthrough pain on a mcg per mcg basis. There are differences in the pharmacokinetics of Lazanda relative to other fentanyl products which could potentially result in clinically important differences in the amount of fentanyl absorbed and could result in a fatal overdose.



 When prescribing Lazanda to a patient, DO NOT convert from other fentanyl products. Directions for safely converting patients to Lazanda from other fentanyl products are not currently available. (Note: This includes oral, transdermal, or parenteral formulations of fentanyl). Therefore, for opioid-tolerant patients starting treatment for breakthrough pain, the initial dose of Lazanda is 100 mcg. Individually titrate each patient's dose to provide adequate analgesia while minimizing side effects. [See   Dosage and Administration (2.1)    ]



 When dispensing Lazanda to a patient, DO NOT substitute it for any other fentanyl product prescription.



    5.3 Information for Patients and Their Caregivers



   Patients and their caregivers must be instructed that Lazanda contains medicine in an amount that could be fatal to a child.  



 Patients and their caregivers must be instructed to keep both used and unused bottles in their child-resistant container and out of the reach of children at all times. Partially used bottles represent a special risk to children. As soon as they are no longer required, all used, unopened or partially used bottles must be completely emptied of accessible fentanyl solution by spraying the remaining contents into the carbon-lined pouch. The sealed pouch and the empty bottle should be put into the child-resistant container before discarding in the trash. Hands must be washed with soap and water immediately after handling the pouch. [see   Storage and Handling (16.2)    ,   Disposal of Lazanda (16.3)    , and   Patient/Caregiver Instructions (17.1)    ].



 Physicians and dispensing pharmacists must question patients and caregivers specifically about the presence of children in the home on a full-time or visiting basis and counsel accordingly regarding the dangers to children of inadvertent exposure to Lazanda.



 Lazanda could be fatal to individuals for whom it is not prescribed and for those who are not opioid tolerant.



    5.4 Additive CNS Depressant Effects



  The concomitant use of Lazanda with other CNS depressants, including other opioids, sedatives or hypnotics, general anesthetics, phenothiazines, tranquilizers, skeletal muscle relaxants, sedating antihistamines, and alcoholic beverages may produce increased depressant effects (e.g., hypoventilation, hypotension, and profound sedation). Concomitant use with potent inhibitors of cytochrome P450 3A4 isoform (e.g., erythromycin, ketoconazole, and certain protease inhibitors) may increase fentanyl levels, resulting in increased depressant effects [see   Metabolic Drug Interactions (7.1)    ].



 Patients on concomitant CNS depressants must be monitored for a change in opioid effects and may require adjustment of the dose of Lazanda.



    5.5 Effects on Ability to Drive and Use Machines



  Opioid analgesics impair the mental and/or physical ability required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks (e.g., driving a car or operating machinery). Warn patients taking Lazanda of these dangers and counsel them accordingly.



    5.6 Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Because potent opioids can cause respiratory depression, cautiously adjust the dose of Lazanda in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or preexisting medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression. In such patients, even normal therapeutic doses of Lazanda may further decrease respiratory drive to the point of respiratory failure.



    5.7 Head Injuries and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Administer Lazanda with extreme caution in patients who may be particularly susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention, such as those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or impaired consciousness. Opioids may obscure the clinical course of a patient with a head injury; only use opioids if clinically warranted.



    5.8 Cardiac Disease



  Intravenous fentanyl may produce bradycardia. Use Lazanda with caution in patients with bradyarrhythmias.



    5.9 MAO Inhibitors



  Lazanda is not recommended for use in patients who have received MAO inhibitors within 14 days, because severe and unpredictable potentiation by MAO inhibitors has been reported with opioid analgesics. [see   Non-metabolic Drug Interactions (7.2)    ].



    5.10 Transmucosal Immediate Release Fentanyl (TIRF) Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) Access Program



   Because of the risk of misuse, abuse, addiction, and overdose [see   Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)    ], Lazanda is available only through a restricted program under a REMS called the TIRF REMS Access program. Under the TIRF REMS Access program, outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program. For inpatient administration (e.g. hospitals, hospices, and long-term care facilities that prescribe for inpatient use) of Lazanda, patient and prescriber enrollment is not required.  



 Required components of the TIRF REMS Access program are:



 *  Healthcare professionals who prescribe Lazanda must review the prescriber educational materials for the TIRF REMS Access program, enroll in the program, and comply with the REMS requirements. 
 *  To receive Lazanda, outpatients must understand the risks and benefits and sign a Patient-Prescriber Agreement. 
 *  Pharmacies that dispense Lazanda must enroll in the program and agree to comply with the REMS requirements. 
 *  Wholesalers and distributers that distribute Lazanda must enroll in the program and distribute only to authorized pharmacies. 
    Further information, including a list of qualified pharmacies/distributors, is available at www.tirfremsaccess.com or by calling 1-866-822-1483.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
