<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="leflunomide" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions associated with the use of leflunomide in RA include diarrhea, elevated liver enzymes (ALT and AST), alopecia and rash. In the controlled studies at one year, the following adverse events were reported, regardless of causality. (See  Table 9  .)



 Table 9. Percentage Of Patients With Adverse Events &gt;=3% In Any Leflunomide Treated Group 
                          All RA Studies  Placebo-Controlled Trials  Active-Controlled Trials   
                          MN 301 and US 301    MN 302      
 LEF(N=1339)              LEF(N=315)   PBO(N=210)   SSZ(N=133)   MTX(N=182)   LEF(N=501)   MTX(N=498)    
  
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                                    
 Allergic Reaction            2%           5%           2%           0%           6%           1%           2%        
 Asthenia                     3%           6%           4%           5%           6%           3%           3%        
 Flu Syndrome                 2%           4%           2%           0%           7%           0%           0%        
 Infection, upper respiratory      4%           0%           0%           0%           0%           0%           0%        
 Injury Accident              5%           7%           5%           3%           11%          6%           7%        
 Pain                         2%           4%           2%           2%           5%           1%           &lt;1%       
 Abdominal Pain               6%           5%           4%           4%           8%           6%           4%        
 Back Pain                    5%           6%           3%           4%           9%           8%           7%        
   CARDIOVASCULAR                                                                                                     
 Hypertension                 10%          9%           4%           4%           3%           10%          4%        
 - New onset of hypertension                   1%           &lt;1%          0%           2%           2%           &lt;1%       
 Chest Pain                   2%           4%           2%           2%           4%           1%           2%        
   GASTROINTESTINAL                                                                                                   
 Anorexia                     3%           3%           2%           5%           2%           3%           3%        
 Diarrhea                     17%          27%          12%          10%          20%          22%          10%       
 Dyspepsia                    5%           10%          10%          9%           13%          6%           7%        
 Gastroenteritis              3%           1%           1%           0%           6%           3%           3%        
 Abnormal Liver Enzymes       5%           10%          2%           4%           10%          6%           17%       
 Nausea                       9%           13%          11%          19%          18%          13%          18%       
 GI/Abdominal Pain            5%           6%           4%           7%           8%           8%           8%        
 Mouth Ulcer                  3%           5%           4%           3%           10%          3%           6%        
 Vomiting                     3%           5%           4%           4%           3%           3%           3%        
   METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL                                                                                                
 Hypokalemia                  1%           3%           1%           1%           1%           1%           &lt;1%       
 Weight Loss                  4%           2%           1%           2%           0%           2%           2%        
   MUSCULO-SKELETAL SYSTEM                                                                                                
 Arthralgia                   1%           4%           3%           0%           9%           &lt;1%          1%        
 Leg Cramps                   1%           4%           2%           2%           6%           0%           0%        
 Joint Disorder               4%           2%           2%           2%           2%           8%           6%        
 Synovitis                    2%           &lt;1%          1%           0%           2%           4%           2%        
 Tenosynovitis                3%           2%           0%           1%           2%           5%           1%        
   NERVOUS SYSTEM                                                                                                     
 Dizziness                    4%           5%           3%           6%           5%           7%           6%        
 Headache                     7%           13%          11%          12%          21%          10%          8%        
 Paresthesia                  2%           3%           1%           1%           2%           4%           3%        
   RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                                                                                                 
 Bronchitis                   7%           5%           2%           4%           7%           8%           7%        
 Increased Cough              3%           4%           5%           3%           6%           5%           7%        
 Respiratory Infection        15%          21%          21%          20%          32%          27%          25%       
 Pharyngitis                  3%           2%           1%           2%           1%           3%           3%        
 Pneumonia                    2%           3%           0%           0%           1%           2%           2%        
 Rhinitis                     2%           5%           2%           4%           3%           2%           2%        
 Sinusitis                    2%           5%           5%           0%           10%          1%           1%        
   SKIN AND APPENDAGES                                                                                                
 Alopecia                     10%          9%           1%           6%           6%           17%          10%       
 Eczema                       2%           1%           1%           1%           1%           3%           2%        
 Pruritus                     4%           5%           2%           3%           2%           6%           2%        
 Rash                         10%          12%          7%           11%          9%           11%          10%       
 Dry Skin                     2%           3%           2%           2%           0%           3%           1%        
   UROGENITAL SYSTEM                                                                                                  
 Urinary Tract Infection      5%           5%           7%           4%           2%           5%           6%        
              Adverse events during a second year of treatment with leflunomide in clinical trials were consistent with those observed during the first year of treatment and occurred at a similar or lower incidence.
 

 In addition, the following adverse events have been reported in 1% to &lt;3% of the RA patients in the leflunomide treatment group in controlled clinical trials.



   Body as a Whole:  abscess, cyst, fever, hernia, malaise, pain, neck pain, pelvic pain;



   Cardiovascular:  angina pectoris, migraine, palpitation, tachycardia, varicose vein, vasculitis, vasodilatation;



   Gastrointestinal:  cholelithiasis, colitis, constipation, esophagitis, flatulence, gastritis, gingivitis, melena, oral moniliasis, pharyngitis, salivary gland enlarged, stomatitis (or aphthous stomatitis), tooth disorder;



   Endocrine:  diabetes mellitus, hyperthyroidism;



   Hemic and Lymphatic System:  anemia (including iron deficiency anemia), ecchymosis;



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  creatine phosphokinase increased, hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia, peripheral edema;



   Musculo-Skeletal System:  arthrosis, bone necrosis, bone pain, bursitis, muscle cramps, myalgia, tendon rupture;



   Nervous System:  anxiety, depression, dry mouth, insomnia, neuralgia, neuritis, sleep disorder, sweating increased, vertigo;



   Respiratory System:  asthma, dyspnea, epistaxis, lung disorder;



   Skin and Appendages:  acne, contact dermatitis, fungal dermatitis, hair discoloration, hematoma, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, maculopapular rash, nail disorder, skin discoloration, skin disorder, skin nodule, subcutaneous nodule, ulcer skin;



   Special Senses:  blurred vision, cataract, conjunctivitis, eye disorder, taste perversion;



   Urogenital System:  albuminuria, cystitis, dysuria, hematuria, menstrual disorder, prostate disorder, urinary frequency, vaginal moniliasis.



 Other less common adverse events seen in clinical trials include: 1 case of anaphylactic reaction occurred in Phase 2 following rechallenge of drug after withdrawal due to rash (rare); urticaria; eosinophilia; transient thrombocytopenia (rare); and leukopenia &lt;2000 WBC/mm  3  (rare).



 Adverse events during a second year of treatment with leflunomide in clinical trials were consistent with those observed during the first year of treatment and occurred at a similar or lower incidence.



 In post-marketing experience, the following have been reported rarely:



   Body as a whole:  opportunistic infections, severe infections including sepsis that may be fatal;



   Gastrointestinal:  pancreatitis;



   Hematologic:  agranulocytosis, leukopenia, neutropenia, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenia;



   Hypersensitivity:  angioedema;



   Hepatic:  hepatitis, jaundice/cholestasis, severe liver injury such as hepatic failure and acute hepatic necrosis that may be fatal;



   Respiratory:  interstitial lung disease, including interstitial pneumonitis and pulmonary fibrosis, which may be fatal;



   Nervous system:  peripheral neuropathy;



   Skin and Appendages:  erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, vasculitis including cutaneous necrotizing vasculitis.



   Adverse Reactions (Pediatric Patients)

  The safety of leflunomide was studied in 74 patients with polyarticular course juvenile rheumatoid arthritis ranging in age from 3-17 years (47 patients from the active-controlled study and 27 from an open-label safety and pharmacokinetic study). The most common adverse events included abdominal pain, diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, oral ulcers, upper respiratory tract infections, alopecia, rash, headache, and dizziness. Less common adverse events included anemia, hypertension, and weight loss. Fourteen pediatric patients experienced ALT and/or AST elevations, nine between 1.2 and 3-fold the upper limit of normal, five between 3 and 8-fold the upper limit of normal.



   Post-Marketing Adverse Event Reports

  In addition to adverse events reported from clinical trials, the following events have been reported from worldwide post-marketing experience with leflunomide:



 Cutaneous lupus erythematosus, pustular psoriasis or worsening psoriasis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: CONTRAINDICATIONS AND WARNINGS

  CONTRAINDICATIONS AND WARNINGS

  Pregnancy

    Pregnancy must be excluded before the start of treatment with leflunomide. Leflunomide is contraindicated in pregnant women, or women of childbearing potential who are not using reliable contraception. (see   CONTRAINDICATIONS   and   WARNINGS  .) Pregnancy must be avoided during leflunomide  treatment or prior to the completion of the drug elimination procedure after leflunomide treatment.   



   Hepatotoxicity

    Severe liver injury, including fatal liver failure, has been reported in some patients treated with leflunomide. Patients with pre-existing acute or chronic liver disease, or those with serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;2*ULN before initiating treatment, should not be treated with leflunomide. Use caution when leflunomide is given with other potentially hepatotoxic drugs.  



   Monitoring of ALT levels is recommended at least monthly for six months after starting leflunomide, and thereafter every 6-8 weeks. If ALT elevation &gt; 3 fold ULN occurs, interrupt leflunomide therapy while investigating the probable cause of the ALT elevation by close observation and additional tests. If likely leflunomide-induced, start cholestyramine washout and monitor liver tests weekly until normalized. If leflunomide-induced liver injury is unlikely because some other probable cause has been found, resumption of leflunomide therapy may be considered.  (SEE   WARNINGS - HEPATOTOXICITY  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
