<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lenvima" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the label:



 *  Hypertension [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  Cardiac Dysfunction [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Arterial Thromboembolic Events [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Hepatotoxicity [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) ] 
 *  Proteinuria [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ) ] 
 *  Renal Failure and Impairment [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  ) ] 
 *  Gastrointestinal Perforation and Fistula Formation [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  ) ] 
 *  QT Interval Prolongation [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  ) ] 
 *  Hypocalcemia [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  ) ] 
 *  Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Hemorrhagic Events [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  ) ] 
 *  Impairment of Thyroid Stimulating Hormone Suppression [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 30%) for LENVIMA are hypertension, fatigue, diarrhea, arthralgia/myalgia, decreased appetite, weight decreased, nausea, stomatitis, headache, vomiting, proteinuria, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome, abdominal pain, and dysphonia (  6  ).      
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eisai Inc. at 1-877-873-4724 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.        



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Safety data obtained in 1108 patients with advanced solid tumors who received LENVIMA as a single agent across multiple clinical studies was used to further characterize risks of serious adverse drug reactions [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ,  5.10  ,  5.11  )  ].   The median age was 60 years (range 21-89 years). The dose range was 0.2 mg to 32 mg. The median duration of exposure in the entire population was 5.5 months.



 The safety data described below are derived from Study 1 which randomized (2:1) patients with radioactive iodine-refractory differentiated thyroid cancer (RAI-refractory DTC) to LENVIMA (n=261) or placebo (n=131) [  see Clinical Studies (  14  )  ].  The median treatment duration was 16.1 months for LENVIMA and 3.9 months for placebo. Among 261 patients who received LENVIMA in Study 1, median age was 64 years, 52% were women, 80% were White, 18% were Asian, and 2% were Black; 4% identified themselves as having Hispanic or Latino ethnicity.



 In Study 1, the most common adverse reactions observed in LENVIMA-treated patients (greater than or equal to 30%) were, in order of decreasing frequency, hypertension, fatigue, diarrhea, arthralgia/myalgia, decreased appetite, weight decreased, nausea, stomatitis, headache, vomiting, proteinuria, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia (PPE) syndrome, abdominal pain, and dysphonia.  The most common serious adverse reactions (at least 2%) were pneumonia (4%), hypertension (3%), and dehydration (3%).



 Adverse reactions led to dose reductions in 68% of patients receiving LENVIMA and 5% of patients receiving placebo; 18% of patients discontinued LENVIMA and 5% discontinued placebo for adverse reactions. The most common adverse reactions (at least 10%) resulting in dose reductions of LENVIMA were hypertension (13%), proteinuria (11%), decreased appetite (10%), and diarrhea (10%); the most common adverse reactions (at least 1%) resulting in discontinuation of LENVIMA were hypertension (1%) and asthenia (1%).



 Table 2 presents the percentage of patients in Study 1 experiencing adverse reactions at a higher rate in LENVIMA-treated patients than patients receiving placebo in the double-blind phase of the DTC study. 



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions Occurring in Patients with a Between-Group Difference of  Greater than or Equal to 5% All Grades or Greater than or Equal to  2% Grades 3 and 4 
   Adverse Reaction                                                                                                                                                                                        LENVIMA 24 mg    N=261                                               Placebo    N=131                                                    
   All Grades    (%)                                                                                                                                                                                       Grades 3-4    (%)                                                    All Grades    (%)                                                    Grades 3-4    (%)                                                   
  
   Vascular Disorders                                                                                                                                                                                     
    Hypertension  a                                                                                                                                                                                       73                                                                   44                                                                   16                                                                   4                                                                    
    Hypotension                                                                                                                                                                                          9                                                                    2                                                                    2                                                                    0                                                                     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                                                                                                             
    Diarrhea                                                                                                                                                                                             67                                                                   9                                                                    17                                                                   0                                                                     
    Nausea                                                                                                                                                                                               47                                                                   2                                                                    25                                                                   1                                                                     
    Stomatitis  b                                                                                                                                                                                        41                                                                   5                                                                    8                                                                    0                                                                     
    Vomiting                                                                                                                                                                                             36                                                                   2                                                                    15                                                                   0                                                                     
    Abdominal pain  c                                                                                                                                                                                    31                                                                   2                                                                    11                                                                   1                                                                     
    Constipation                                                                                                                                                                                         29                                                                   0.4                                                                  15                                                                   1                                                                     
    Oral pain  d                                                                                                                                                                                         25                                                                   1                                                                    2                                                                    0                                                                     
    Dry mouth                                                                                                                                                                                            17                                                                   0.4                                                                  8                                                                    0                                                                     
    Dyspepsia                                                                                                                                                                                            13                                                                   0.4                                                                  4                                                                    0                                                                     
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                                                                                                   
    Fatigue  e                                                                                                                                                                                           67                                                                   11                                                                   35                                                                   4                                                                     
    Edema peripheral                                                                                                                                                                                     21                                                                   0.4                                                                  8                                                                    0                                                                     
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                                                                                                        
    Arthralgia/ Myalgia  f                                                                                                                                                                               62                                                                   5                                                                    28                                                                   3                                                                     
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                                                                                                                     
    Weight decreased                                                                                                                                                                                     51                                                                   13                                                                   15                                                                   1                                                                     
    Decreased appetite                                                                                                                                                                                   54                                                                   7                                                                    18                                                                   1                                                                     
    Dehydration                                                                                                                                                                                          9                                                                    2                                                                    2                                                                    1                                                                     
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                                                                                                               
    Headache                                                                                                                                                                                             38                                                                   3                                                                    11                                                                   1                                                                     
    Dysgeusia                                                                                                                                                                                            18                                                                   0                                                                    3                                                                    0                                                                     
    Dizziness                                                                                                                                                                                            15                                                                   0.4                                                                  9                                                                    0                                                                     
   Renal and Urinary Disorders                                                                                                                                                                            
    Proteinuria                                                                                                                                                                                          34                                                                   11                                                                   3                                                                    0                                                                     
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                                                                                                                 
    Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia                                                                                                                                                                    32                                                                   3                                                                    1                                                                    0                                                                     
    Rash  g                                                                                                                                                                                              21                                                                   0.4                                                                  3                                                                    0                                                                     
    Alopecia                                                                                                                                                                                             12                                                                   0                                                                    5                                                                    0                                                                     
    Hyperkeratosis                                                                                                                                                                                       7                                                                    0                                                                    2                                                                    0                                                                     
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                                                                                                                        
    Dysphonia                                                                                                                                                                                            31                                                                   1                                                                    5                                                                    0                                                                     
    Cough                                                                                                                                                                                                24                                                                   0                                                                    18                                                                   0                                                                     
    Epistaxis                                                                                                                                                                                            12                                                                   0                                                                    1                                                                    0                                                                     
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                                                                                                                  
    Insomnia                                                                                                                                                                                             12                                                                   0                                                                    3                                                                    0                                                                     
   Infections and Infestations                                                                                                                                                                            
    Dental and oral infections  h                                                                                                                                                                        10                                                                   1                                                                    1                                                                    0                                                                     
    Urinary tract infection                                                                                                                                                                              11                                                                   1                                                                    5                                                                    0                                                                     
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                                                                                                                                      
    Electrocardiogram QT prolonged                                                                                                                                                                       9                                                                    2                                                                    2                                                                    0                                                                     
  a Includes hypertension, hypertensive crisis, increased blood pressure diastolic, and increased blood pressureb Includes aphthous stomatitis, stomatitis, glossitis, mouth ulceration, and mucosal inflammationc Includes abdominal discomfort, abdominal pain, abdominal pain lower, abdominal pain upper, abdominal tenderness, epigastric discomfort, and gastrointestinal paind Includes oral pain, glossodynia, and oropharyngeal paine Includes asthenia, fatigue, and malaisef Includes musculoskeletal pain, back pain, pain in extremity, arthralgia, and myalgiag Includes rash macular, rash maculo-papular, rash generalized, and rashh Includes gingivitis, oral infection, parotitis, pericoronitis, periodontitis, sialoadenitis, tooth abscess, and tooth infection    
           A clinically important adverse reaction occurring more frequently in LENVIMA-treated patients than patients receiving placebo, but with an incidence of less than 5% was pulmonary embolism (3%, including fatal reports vs 2%, respectively).
 

 Table 3 Laboratory Abnormalities with a difference of at least &gt;= 2% in Grade 3 - 4 events and at a Higher Incidence in LENVIMA-Treated Patientsa 
   Laboratory Abnormality      LENVIMA 24 mg    N=258  b        Placebo    N=131  b       
   Grades 3-4    (%)      Grades 3-4    (%)     
  
   Chemistry       
    Creatinine increased  3                0                 
    Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) increased  4                0                 
    Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) increased  5                0                 
    Hypocalcemia  9                2                 
    Hypokalemia   6                1                 
    Lipase increased  4                1                 
   Hematology      
    Platelet count decreased  2                0                 
   a  With at least 1 grade increase from baseline  b  Subject with at least 1 post baseline laboratory value   
         In addition the following laboratory abnormalities (all Grades) occurred in greater than 5% of LENVIMA-treated patients and at a rate that was two-fold or higher than in patients who received placebo: hypoalbuminemia, increased alkaline phosphatase, hypomagnesemia, hypoglycemia, hyperbilirubinemia, hypercalcemia, hypercholesterolemia, increased serum amylase, and hyperkalemia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypertension: Control blood pressure prior to treatment with LENVIMA. Withhold LENVIMA for Grade 3 hypertension despite optimal hypertensive therapy. Discontinue for life-threatening hypertension (  5.1  ) 
 *  Cardiac Failure: Monitor for clinical symptoms or signs of cardiac decompensation. Withhold LENVIMA for Grade 3 cardiac dysfunction.  Discontinue for Grade 4 cardiac dysfunction (  5.2  ). 
 *  Arterial Thromboembolic Events: Discontinue LENVIMA following an arterial thromboembolic event (  5.3  ). 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Monitor liver function tests before initiation of LENVIMA and periodically throughout treatment. Withhold LENVIMA for Grade 3 or greater liver impairment. Discontinue for hepatic failure (  5.4  ). 
 *  Proteinuria: Monitor for proteinuria before initiation of, and periodically throughout, treatment with LENVIMA. Withhold LENVIMA for &gt;=2 grams of proteinuria for 24 hours. Discontinue for nephrotic syndrome (  5.5  ). 
 *  Renal Failure and Impairment: Withhold LENVIMA for Grade 3 or 4 renal failure/impairment (  5.6  ). 
 *  Gastrointestinal Perforation and Fistula Formation: Discontinue LENVIMA in patients who develop gastrointestinal perforation or life-threatening fistula (  5.7  ). 
 *  QT Interval Prolongation: Monitor and correct electrolyte abnormalities in all patients. Withhold LENVIMA for the development of Grade 3 or greater QT interval prolongation (  5.8  ). 
 *  Hypocalcemia: Monitor blood calcium levels at least monthly and replace calcium as necessary (  5.9  ). 
 *  Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS): Withhold LENVIMA for RPLS until fully resolved (  5.10  ). 
 *  Hemorrhagic Events: Withhold LENVIMA for Grade 3 hemorrhage.  Discontinue for Grade 4 hemorrhage (  5.11  ). 
 *  Impairment of Thyroid Stimulating Hormone Suppression: Monitor TSH levels monthly and adjust thyroid replacement medication as needed in patients with DTC (  5.12  ). 
 *  Embryofetal Toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise of potential risk to a fetus and use of effective contraception (  5.13  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypertension



  In Study 1 hypertension was reported in 73% of LENVIMA-treated patients and 16% of patients in the placebo group [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. The median time to onset of new or worsening hypertension was 16 days for LENVIMA-treated patients. The incidence of Grade 3 hypertension was 44% as compared to 4% for placebo, and the incidence of Grade 4 hypertension was less than 1% in LENVIMA-treated patients and none in the placebo group.



 Control blood pressure prior to treatment with LENVIMA. Monitor blood pressure after 1 week, then every 2 weeks for the first 2 months, and then at least monthly thereafter during treatment with LENVIMA. Withhold LENVIMA for Grade 3 hypertension despite optimal antihypertensive therapy; resume at a reduced dose when hypertension is controlled at less than or equal to Grade 2. Discontinue LENVIMA for life-threatening hypertension  [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.2 Cardiac Dysfunction



  In Study 1, cardiac dysfunction, defined as decreased left or right ventricular function, cardiac failure, or pulmonary edema, was reported in 7% of LENVIMA-treated patients (2% Grade 3 or greater) and 2% (no Grade 3 or greater) of patients in the placebo group. The majority of these cases in LENVIMA-treated patients (14 of 17 cases) were based on findings of decreased ejection fraction as assessed by echocardiography. Six of 261 (2%) LENVIMA-treated patients in Study 1 had greater than 20% reduction in ejection fraction as measured by echocardiography compared to no patients who received placebo. 



 Monitor patients for clinical symptoms or signs of cardiac decompensation. Withhold LENVIMA for development of Grade 3 cardiac dysfunction until improved to Grade 0 or 1 or baseline. Either resume at a reduced dose or discontinue LENVIMA depending on the severity and persistence of cardiac dysfunction. Discontinue LENVIMA for Grade 4 cardiac dysfunction [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.3 Arterial Thromboembolic Events



  In Study 1, arterial thromboembolic events were reported in 5% of LENVIMA-treated patients and 2% of patients in the placebo group. The incidence of arterial thromboembolic events of Grade 3 or greater was 3% in LENVIMA-treated patients and 1% in the placebo group. 



 Discontinue LENVIMA following an arterial thrombotic event. The safety of resuming LENVIMA after an arterial thromboembolic event has not been established and LENVIMA has not been studied in patients who have had an arterial thromboembolic event within the previous 6 months [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.4 Hepatotoxicity



  In Study 1, 4% of LENVIMA-treated patients experienced an increase in alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and 5% experienced an increase in aspartate aminotransferase (AST) that was Grade 3 or greater. No patients in the placebo group experienced Grade 3 or greater increases in ALT or AST. Across clinical studies in which 1108 patients received LENVIMA, hepatic failure (including fatal events) was reported in 3 patients and acute hepatitis was reported in 1 patient. 



 Monitor liver function before initiation of LENVIMA, then every 2 weeks for the first 2 months, and at least monthly thereafter during treatment. Withhold LENVIMA for the development of Grade 3 or greater liver impairment until resolved to Grade 0 to 1 or baseline. Either resume at a reduced dose or discontinue LENVIMA depending on the severity and persistence of hepatotoxicity. Discontinue LENVIMA for hepatic failure [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.5 Proteinuria



  In Study 1, proteinuria was reported in 34% of LENVIMA-treated patients and 3% of patients in the placebo group [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. The incidence of Grade 3 proteinuria in LENVIMA-treated patients was 11% compared to none in the placebo group.



 Monitor for proteinuria before initiation of, and periodically throughout treatment. If urine dipstick proteinuria greater than or equal to 2+ is detected, obtain a 24 hour urine protein. Withhold LENVIMA for &gt;=2 grams of proteinuria/24 hours and resume at a reduced dose when proteinuria is &lt;2 gm/24 hours. Discontinue LENVIMA for nephrotic syndrome [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ]. 



    5.6 Renal Failure and Impairment



  In Study 1, events of renal impairment were reported in 14% of LENVIMA-treated patients compared to 2% of patients in the placebo group. The incidence of Grade 3 or greater renal failure or impairment was 3% in LENVIMA-treated patients and 1% in the placebo group. The primary risk factor for severe renal impairment in LENVIMA-treated patients was dehydration/hypovolemia due to diarrhea and vomiting.  



 Withhold LENVIMA for development of Grade 3 or 4 renal failure/impairment until resolved to Grade 0 to 1 or baseline. Either resume at a reduced dose or discontinue LENVIMA depending on the severity and persistence of renal impairment [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.7 Gastrointestinal Perforation and Fistula Formation



  In Study 1, events of gastrointestinal perforation or fistula were reported in 2% of LENVIMA-treated patients and 0.8% of patients in the placebo group.



 Discontinue LENVIMA in patients who develop gastrointestinal perforation or life-threatening fistula [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.8 QT Interval Prolongation



  In Study 1, QT/QTc interval prolongation was reported in 9% of LENVIMA-treated patients and 2% of patients in the placebo group. The incidence of QT interval prolongation of Grade 3 or greater was 2% in LENVIMA-treated patients compared to no reports in the placebo group. Monitor electrocardiograms in patients with congenital long QT syndrome, congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, or those who are taking drugs known to prolong the QT interval, including Class Ia and III antiarrhythmics.



 Monitor and correct electrolyte abnormalities in all patients. Withhold LENVIMA for the development of Grade 3 or greater QT interval prolongation. Resume LENVIMA at a reduced dose when QT prolongation resolves to Grade 0 or 1 or baseline [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ), Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )  ].



    5.9 Hypocalcemia



  In study 1, 9% of LENVIMA-treated patients experienced Grade 3 or greater hypocalcemia compared to 2% in the placebo group. In most cases hypocalcemia responded to replacement and dose interruption/dose reduction [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. 



 Monitor blood calcium levels at least monthly and replace calcium as necessary during LENVIMA treatment. Interrupt and adjust LENVIMA dosing as necessary depending on severity, presence of ECG changes, and persistence of hypocalcemia [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.10 Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome



  Across clinical studies in which 1108 patients received LENVIMA, there were 3 reported events of reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS). Confirm the diagnosis of RPLS with MRI. Withhold for RPLS until fully resolved. Upon resolution, resume at a reduced dose or discontinue LENVIMA depending on the severity and persistence of neurologic symptoms [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.11 Hemorrhagic Events



  In Study 1, hemorrhagic events occurred in 35% of LENVIMA-treated patients and in 18% of the placebo group. However, the incidence of Grade 3-5 hemorrhage was similar between arms at 2% and 3%, respectively. The most frequently reported hemorrhagic event was epistaxis (11% Grade 1 and 1% Grade 2). Discontinuation due to hemorrhagic events occurred in 1% of LENVIMA-treated patients.



 Across clinical studies in which 1108 patients received LENVIMA, Grade 3 or greater hemorrhage was reported in 2% of patients. In Study 1, there was 1 case of fatal intracranial hemorrhage among 16 patients who received lenvatinib and had CNS metastases at baseline.



 Withhold LENVIMA for the development of Grade 3 hemorrhage until resolved to Grade 0 to 1. Either resume at a reduced dose or discontinue LENVIMA depending on the severity and persistence of hemorrhage. Discontinue LENVIMA in patients who experience Grade 4 hemorrhage [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.12 Impairment of Thyroid Stimulating Hormone Suppression



  LENVIMA impairs exogenous thyroid suppression. In Study 1, 88% of all patients had a baseline thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) level less than or equal to 0.5 mU/L. In those patients with a normal TSH at baseline, elevation of TSH level above 0.5 mU/L was observed post baseline in 57% of LENVIMA-treated patients as compared with 14% of patients receiving placebo.



 Monitor TSH levels monthly and adjust thyroid replacement medication as needed in patients with DTC.



    5.13 Embryofetal Toxicity



  Based on its mechanism of action and data from animal reproduction studies, LENVIMA can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. In animal reproduction studies, oral administration of lenvatinib during organogenesis at doses below the recommended human dose resulted in embryotoxicity, fetotoxicity, and teratogenicity in rats and rabbits. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with LENVIMA and for at least 2 weeks following completion of therapy [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ,  8.3  )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
