<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lescol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Rhabdomyolysis with myoglobinuria and acute renal failure and myopathy (including myositis) [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ]. 
 *  Liver Enzyme Abnormalities [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.2) ]. 
      EXCERPT:   Most frequent adverse reactions (rate &gt;=2% and &gt; placebo) are: headache, dyspepsia, myalgia, abdominal pain and nausea (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1     Clinical Studies Experience in Adult Patients 

  Because clinical studies on LESCOL/LESCOL XL are conducted in varying study populations and study designs, the frequency of adverse reactions observed in the clinical studies of LESCOL/LESCOL XL cannot be directly compared with that in the clinical studies of other statins and may not reflect the frequency of adverse reactions observed in clinical practice.



 In the LESCOL placebo-controlled clinical trials database of 2326 patients treated with LESCOL  1  (age range 18-75 years, 44% women, 94% Caucasians, 4% Blacks, 2% other ethnicities) with a median treatment duration of 24 weeks, 3.4% of patients on LESCOL and 2.3% patients on placebo discontinued due to adverse reactions regardless of causality. The most common adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation and occurred at an incidence greater than placebo were: transaminase increased (0.8%), upper abdominal pain (0.3%), dyspepsia (0.3%), fatigue (0.2%) and diarrhea (0.2%).



 In the LESCOL XL database of controlled clinical trials of 912 patients treated with LESCOL XL (age range 21-87 years, 52% women, 91% Caucasians, 4% Blacks, 5% other ethnicities) with a median treatment duration of 24 weeks, 3.9% of patients on LESCOL XL  discontinued due to adverse reactions regardless of causality. The most common adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation were abdominal pain (0.7%), diarrhea (0.5%), nausea (0.4%), dyspepsia (0.4%) and chest pain (0.3%).



 Clinically relevant adverse experiences occurring in the LESCOL and LESCOL XL controlled studies with a frequency  &gt;  2%, regardless of causality, included the following:



 Table 1  Clinical adverse events reported in &gt;2% in patients treated with LESCOL/LESCOL XL and at an incidence greater than placebo in placebo-controlled trials regardless of causality (% of patients) Pooled Dosages 
                  LESCOL  1  N=2326(%)  Placebo  1  N=960(%)  LESCOL XL  2  N=912(%)   
 Musculoskeletal  Myalgia          5.0              4.5              3.8               
                  Arthritis        2.1              2.0              1.3               
                  Arthropathy      NA               NA               3.2               
 Respiratory      Sinusitis        2.6              1.9              3.5               
                  Bronchitis       1.8              1.0              2.6               
 Gastrointestinal  Dyspepsia        7.9              3.2              3.5               
                  Diarrhea         4.9              4.2              3.3               
                  Abdominal pain   4.9              3.8              3.7               
                  Nausea           3.2              2.0              2.5               
                  Flatulence       2.6              2.5              1.4               
                  Tooth disorder   2.1              1.7              1.4               
 Psychiatric      Insomnia         2.7              1.4              0.8               
 Genitourinary    Urinary tract infection  1.6              1.1              2.7               
 Miscellaneous    Headache         8.9              7.8              4.7               
                  Influenza-like symptoms  5.1              5.7              7.1               
                  Accidental Trauma  5.1              4.8              4.2               
                  Fatigue          2.7              2.3              1.6               
                  Allergy          2.3              2.2              1.0               
   1  Controlled trials with LESCOL Capsules (20 and 40 mg daily and 40 mg twice daily) compared to placebo  2  Controlled trials with LESCOL XL 80 mg Tablets as compared to LESCOL Capsules   
             LESCOL    Intervention Prevention Study  
 

 In the LESCOL Intervention Prevention Study (LIPS), the effect of LESCOL 40 mg, administered twice daily on the risk of recurrent cardiac events was assessed in 1677 patients with CHD who had undergone a percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) procedure. This was a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study, patients were treated with dietary/lifestyle counseling and either LESCOL 40 mg (n=844) or placebo (n=833) given twice daily for a median of 3.9 years [  see Clinical Studies (14.3)  ].



 Table 2  Clinical adverse events reported in &gt;= 2% in patients treated with LESCOL/LESCOL XL and at an incidence greater than placebo in the LIPS Trial regardless of causality (% of patients) 
                  LESCOL40 mg b.i.d.N=822(%)  PlaceboN=818(%)                    
 Cardiac disorders  Atrial fibrillation  2.4              2.0                                
 Gastrointestinal disorders  Abdominal pain upper  6.3              4.5                                
                  Constipation     3.3              2.1                                
                  Dyspepsia        4.5              4.0                                
                  Gastric disorder  2.7              2.1                                
                  Nausea           2.7              2.3                                
 General disorders  Fatigue          4.7              3.8                                
                  Edema peripheral  4.4              2.9                                
 Infections and infestations  Bronchitis       2.3              2.0                                
                  Nasopharyngitis  2.8              2.1                                
 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  Arthralgia       2.1              1.8                                
                  Myalgia          2.2              1.6                                
                  Pain in extremity  4.1              2.7                                
 Nervous system disorders  Dizziness        3.9              3.5                                
                  Syncope          2.4              2.2                                
 Respiratory disorders  Dyspnea exertional  2.8              2.4                                
                                                                                       
 Vascular disorders  Hypertension     5.8              4.2                                
                  Intermittent claudication  2.3              2.1                                
             6.2     Clinical Studies Experience in Pediatric Patients
   In patients aged &lt;18 years, efficacy and safety have not been studied for treatment periods longer than two years. 



 In two open-label, uncontrolled studies, 66 boys and 48 girls with heterozygous familial hypercholesterolemia ( 9-16 years of age, 80% Caucasian, 19% Other [ mixed ethnicity], 1% Asians) were treated with fluvastatin sodium administered as LESCOL capsules 20 mg -40 mg twice daily, or LESCOL XL 80 mg extended-release tablet [  see Clinical Studies (14.2) and Use In Specific Populations (8.4)  ].



   6.3     Postmarketing Experience

  Because adverse reactions from spontaneous reports are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The following effects have been reported with drugs in this class. Not all the effects listed below have necessarily been associated with fluvastatin sodium therapy.



   Musculos    keletal:   muscle cramps, myalgia, myopathy, rhabdomyolysis, arthralgias, muscle spasms, muscle weakness, myositis.



 There have been rare reports of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy associated with statin use [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].



   Neurological:   dysfunction of certain cranial nerves (including alteration of taste, impairment of extra-ocular movement, facial paresis), tremor, dizziness, vertigo, paresthesia, hypoesthesia, dysesthesia, peripheral neuropathy, peripheral nerve palsy.



 There have been rare postmarketing reports of cognitive impairment (e.g., memory loss, forgetfulness, amnesia, memory impairment, confusion) associated with statin use. These cognitive issues have been reported for all statins. The reports are generally nonserious, and reversible upon statin discontinuation, with variable times to symptom onset (1 day to years) and symptom resolution (median of 3 weeks).



   Psychiatric:  anxiety, insomnia, depression, psychic disturbances



   Hypersensitivity Reactions:   An apparent hypersensitivity syndrome has been reported rarely which has included one or more of the following features: anaphylaxis, angioedema, lupus erythematosus-like syndrome, polymyalgia rheumatica, vasculitis, purpura, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, positive ANA, ESR (erythrocyte sedimentation rate) increase, eosinophilia, arthritis, arthralgia, urticaria, asthenia, photosensitivity reaction, fever, chills, flushing, malaise, dyspnea, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome.



   Gastrointestinal:  pancreatitis, hepatitis, including chronic active hepatitis, cholestatic jaundice, fatty change in liver, cirrhosis, fulminant hepatic necrosis, hepatoma, anorexia, vomiting, fatal and non-fatal hepatic failure.



   Skin:   rash, dermatitis, including bullous dermatitis, eczema, alopecia, pruritus, a variety of skin changes (e.g. nodules, discoloration, dryness of skin/mucous membranes, changes to hair/nails).



   Reproductive:   gynecomastia, loss of libido, erectile dysfunction.



   Eye:   progression of cataracts (lens opacities), ophthalmoplegia.



   Laboratory abnormalities:   elevated transaminases, alkaline phosphatase, gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase and bilirubin; thyroid function abnormalities.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *   Skeletal muscle effects (e.g. myopathy and rhabdomyolysis): Risks increase with advanced age ( &gt; 65), uncontrolled hypothyroidism, renal impairment, and combination use with cyclosporine,or gemfibrozil. Advise patients to promptly report to their physician unexplained and/or persistent muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness and discontinue LESCOL/LESCOL XL if myopathy is diagnosed or suspected. (  5.1  ,  8.5  ,  8.7  ) 
 *  Patients should be advised to report promptly any symptoms of myopathy. LESCOL/LESCOL XL therapy should be discontinued if myopathy is diagnosed or suspected (  5.1  ) 
 *   Liver enzyme abnormalities:  Persistent elevations in hepatic transaminases can occur. Check liver enzyme tests before initiating therapy and as clinically indicated thereafter (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Skeletal Muscle



   R   habdomyolysis with acute renal failure secondary to   myoglobinuria   have been reported with   LESCOL   /LESCOL XL   and other drugs in this class.  



 LESCOL/LESCOL XL should be prescribed with caution in patients with predisposing factors for myopathy. These factors include advanced age (&gt;65 years), renal impairment, and inadequately treated hypothyroidism.



 The risk of myopathy and/or rhabdomyolysis with statins is increased with concurrent therapy with cyclosporine, erythromycin, fibrates or niacin. Myopathy was not observed in a clinical trial in 74 patients involving patients who were treated with LESCOL/LESCOL XL together with niacin. Isolated cases of myopathy have been reported during post-marketing experience with concomitant administration of LESCOL/LESCOL XL and colchicine. No information is available on the pharmacokinetic interaction between LESCOL/LESCOL XL and colchicine.



 Uncomplicated myalgia has also been reported in LESCOL-treated patients [ see Adverse Reactions (6)  ]. In clinical trials, uncomplicated myalgia has been observed infrequently in patients treated with LESCOL at rates indistinguishable from placebo. Myopathy, defined as muscle aching or muscle weakness in conjunction with increases in CPK values to greater than 10 times the upper limit of normal, was &lt;0.1% in fluvastatin clinical trials. Myopathy should be considered in any patient with diffuse myalgias, muscle tenderness or weakness, and/or marked elevation of CPK.



 There have been rare reports of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy (IMNM), an autoimmune myopathy, associated with statin use. IMNM is characterized by: proximal muscle weakness and elevated serum creatine kinase, which persist despite discontinuation of statin treatment; muscle biopsy showing necrotizing myopathy without significant inflammation; improvement with immunosuppressive agents.



 All patients should be advised to promptly report to their physician unexplained muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness, particularly if accompanied by malaise or fever or if muscle signs and symptoms persist after discontinuing LESCOL/LESCOL XL.



 LESCOL/LESCOL XL therapy should be discontinued if markedly elevated CPK levels occur or myopathy is diagnosed or suspected. LESCOL/LESCOL XL therapy should also be temporarily withheld in any patient experiencing an acute or serious condition predisposing to the development of renal failure secondary to rhabdomyolysis, e.g., sepsis; hypotension; major surgery; trauma; severe metabolic, endocrine, or electrolyte disorders; or uncontrolled epilepsy. 



    5.2     Liver Enzymes



  Increases in serum transaminases (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]/serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase, or alanine aminotransferase [ALT]/serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) have been reported with HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors, including LESCOL/LESCOL XL. In most cases, the elevations were transient and resolved or improved on continued therapy or after a brief interruption in therapy.



 Approximately 1.1% of patients treated with LESCOL capsules in worldwide trials developed dose-related, persistent elevations of serum transaminase levels to more than 3 times the upper limit of normal. Fourteen of these patients (0.6%) were discontinued from therapy. In all clinical trials, a total of 33/2969 patients (1.1%) had persistent transaminase elevations with an average LESCOL exposure of approximately 71.2 weeks; 19 of these patients (0.6%) were discontinued. The majority of patients with these abnormal biochemical findings were asymptomatic.



 In a pooled analysis of all placebo-controlled studies in which LESCOL capsules were used, persistent transaminase elevations (&gt;3 times the upper limit of normal [ULN] on two consecutive weekly measurements) occurred in 0.2%, 1.5%, and 2.7% of patients treated with daily doses of 20, 40, and 80 mg (titrated to 40 mg twice daily) LESCOL capsules, respectively. Ninety-one percent of the cases of persistent liver function test abnormalities (20 of 22 patients) occurred within 12 weeks of therapy and in all patients with persistent liver function test abnormalities there was an abnormal liver function test present at baseline or by Week 8.



 In the pooled analysis of the 24-week controlled trials, persistent transaminase elevation occurred in 1.9%, 1.8% and 4.9% of patients treated with LESCOL XL 80 mg, LESCOL 40 mg and LESCOL 40 mg twice daily, respectively. In 13 of 16 patients treated with LESCOL XL the abnormality occurred within 12 weeks of initiation of treatment with LESCOL XL 80 mg.



 It is recommended that liver enzyme tests be performed prior to the initiation of LESCOL/LESCOL XL, and if signs or symptoms of liver injury occur.



 There have been rare postmarketing reports of fatal and non-fatal hepatic failure in patients taking statins, including fluvastatin. If serious liver injury with clinical symptoms and/or hyperbilirubinemia or jaundice occurs during treatment with LESCOL/LESCOL XL, promptly interrupt therapy. If an alternate etiology is not found do not restart LESCOL/LESCOL XL.



 In very rare cases, possibly drug-related hepatitis was observed that resolved upon discontinuation of treatment.  1  Active liver disease or unexplained serum transaminase elevations are contraindications to the use of LESCOL and LESCOL XL [ see Contraindications (4) and Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]. Caution should be exercised when LESCOL is administered to patients with a history of liver disease or heavy alcohol ingestion [ see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]. Such patients should be closely monitored.



    5.3     Endocrine Effects



  Increases in HbA1c and fasting serum glucose levels have been reported with HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors, including LESCOL/LESCOL XL.



 Statins interfere with cholesterol synthesis and lower circulating cholesterol levels and, as such, might theoretically blunt adrenal or gonadal steroid hormone production.



 LESCOL/LESCOL XL exhibited no effect upon non-stimulated cortisol levels and demonstrated no effect upon thyroid metabolism as assessed by measurement of thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH). Small declines in total serum testosterone have been noted in treated groups, but no commensurate elevation in LH occurred, suggesting that the observation was not due to a direct effect upon testosterone production. No effect upon FSH in males was noted. Due to the limited number of premenopausal females studied to date, no conclusions regarding the effect of LESCOL/LESCOL XL upon female sex hormones may be made.



 Two clinical studies in patients receiving fluvastatin at doses up to 80 mg daily for periods of 24 to 28 weeks demonstrated no effect of treatment upon the adrenal response to ACTH stimulation. A clinical study evaluated the effect of LESCOL at doses up to 80 mg daily for 28 weeks upon the gonadal response to HCG stimulation. Although the mean total testosterone response was significantly reduced (p&lt;0.05) relative to baseline in the 80 mg group, it was not significant in comparison to the changes noted in groups receiving either 40 mg of LESCOL or placebo.



 Patients treated with LESCOL/LESCOL XL who develop clinical evidence of endocrine dysfunction should be evaluated appropriately. Caution should be exercised if a statin or other agent used to lower cholesterol levels is administered to patients receiving other drugs (e.g. ketoconazole, spironolactone, cimetidine) that may decrease the levels of endogenous steroid hormones.



    5.4     CNS Toxicity



  CNS effects, as evidenced by decreased activity, ataxia, loss of righting reflex, and ptosis were seen in the following animal studies: the 18-month mouse carcinogenicity study at 50 mg/kg/day, the 6-month dog study at 36 mg/kg/day, the 6-month hamster study at 40 mg/kg/day, and in acute, high-dose studies in rats and hamsters (50 mg/kg), rabbits (300 mg/kg) and mice (1500 mg/kg). CNS toxicity in the acute high-dose studies was characterized (in mice) by conspicuous vacuolation in the ventral white columns of the spinal cord at a dose of 5000 mg/kg and (in rats) by edema with separation of myelinated fibers of the ventral spinal tracts and sciatic nerve at a dose of 1500 mg/kg. CNS toxicity, characterized by periaxonal vacuolation, was observed in the medulla of dogs that died after treatment for 5 weeks with 48 mg/kg/day; this finding was not observed in the remaining dogs when the dose level was lowered to 36 mg/kg/day. CNS vascular lesions, characterized by perivascular hemorrhages, edema, and mononuclear cell infiltration of perivascular spaces, have been observed in dogs treated with other members of this drug class. No CNS lesions have been observed after chronic treatment for up to 2 years with fluvastatin in the mouse (at doses up to 350 mg/kg/day), rat (up to 24 mg/kg/day), or dog (up to 16 mg/kg/day).



 Prominent bilateral posterior Y suture lines in the ocular lens were seen in dogs after treatment with 1, 8, and 16 mg/kg/day for 2 years.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
