<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="letairis" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinically significant adverse reactions that appear in other sections of the labeling include:



 *  Embryo-fetal Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  
 *  Fluid Retention [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Pulmonary Edema with PVOD [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Decreased Sperm Count [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hematologic Changes [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;3% compared to placebo) are peripheral edema, nasal congestion, sinusitis, and flushing (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc. at (1-800-445-3235, Option 3) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Safety data for Letairis were obtained from two 12-week, placebo-controlled studies in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) (ARIES-1 and ARIES-2) and four nonplacebo-controlled studies in 483 patients with PAH who were treated with doses of 1, 2.5, 5, or 10 mg once daily. The exposure to Letairis in these studies ranged from 1 day to 4 years (N = 418 for at least 6 months and N = 343 for at least 1 year).



 In ARIES-1 and ARIES-2, a total of 261 patients received Letairis at doses of 2.5, 5, or 10 mg once daily and 132 patients received placebo. The adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;3% more patients receiving Letairis than receiving placebo are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions with Placebo-Adjusted Rates &gt;3% 
                                Placebo(N = 132)           Letairis(N = 261)       
 Adverse Reaction                     n (%)                      n (%)              Placebo-adjusted (%)      
  
 Peripheral edema                    14 (11)                    45 (17)                       6               
 Nasal congestion                     2 (2)                     15 (6)                        4               
 Sinusitis                            0 (0)                      8 (3)                        3               
 Flushing                             1 (1)                     10 (4)                        3               
          Most adverse drug reactions were mild to moderate and only nasal congestion was dose-dependent.
 

 Few notable differences in the incidence of adverse reactions were observed for patients by age or sex. Peripheral edema was similar in younger patients (&lt;65 years) receiving Letairis (14%; 29/205) or placebo (13%; 13/104), and was greater in elderly patients (&gt;=65 years) receiving Letairis (29%; 16/56) compared to placebo (4%; 1/28). The results of such subgroup analyses must be interpreted cautiously.



 The incidence of treatment discontinuations due to adverse events other than those related to PAH during the clinical trials in patients with PAH was similar for Letairis (2%; 5/261 patients) and placebo (2%; 3/132 patients). The incidence of patients with serious adverse events other than those related to PAH during the clinical trials in patients with PAH was similar for placebo (7%; 9/132 patients) and for Letairis (5%; 13/261 patients).



 During 12-week controlled clinical trials, the incidence of aminotransferase elevations &gt;3 * upper limit of normal (ULN) were 0% on Letairis and 2.3% on placebo. In practice, cases of hepatic injury should be carefully evaluated for cause.



       Use in Patients with Prior Endothelin Receptor Antagonist (ERA) Related Serum Liver Enzyme Abnormalities    



 In an uncontrolled, open  -  label study, 36 patients who had previously discontinued endothelin receptor antagonists (ERAs: bosentan, an investigational drug, or both) due to aminotransferase elevations &gt;3 * ULN were treated with Letairis. Prior elevations were predominantly moderate, with 64% of the ALT elevations &lt;5 * ULN, but 9 patients had elevations &gt;8 * ULN. Eight patients had been re-challenged with bosentan and/or the investigational ERA and all eight had a recurrence of aminotransferase abnormalities that required discontinuation of ERA therapy. All patients had to have normal aminotransferase levels on entry to this study. Twenty-five of the 36 patients were also receiving prostanoid and/or phosphodiesterase type 5 (PDE5) inhibitor therapy. Two patients discontinued early (including one of the patients with a prior 8 * ULN elevation). Of the remaining 34 patients, one patient experienced a mild aminotransferase elevation at 12 weeks on Letairis 5 mg that resolved with decreasing the dosage to 2.5 mg, and that did not recur with later escalations to 10 mg. With a median follow-up of 13 months and with 50% of patients increasing the dose of Letairis to 10 mg, no patients were discontinued for aminotransferase elevations. While the uncontrolled study design does not provide information about what would have occurred with re  -  administration of previously used ERAs or show that Letairis led to fewer aminotransferase elevations than would have been seen with those drugs, the study indicates that Letairis may be tried in patients who have experienced asymptomatic aminotransferase elevations on other ERAs after aminotransferase levels have returned to normal.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions were identified during postapproval use of Letairis. Because these reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to estimate reliably the frequency or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: anemia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  , asthenia, dizziness, fatigue, fluid retention  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  , heart failure (associated with fluid retention), hypersensitivity (eg, angioedema, rash), nausea, and vomiting.



 Elevations of liver aminotransferases (ALT, AST) have been reported with Letairis use; in most cases alternative causes of the liver injury could be identified (heart failure, hepatic congestion, hepatitis, alcohol use, hepatotoxic medications). Other endothelin receptor antagonists have been associated with elevations of aminotransferases, hepatotoxicity, and cases of liver failure  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY

  WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY

      Do not administer Letairis to a pregnant female because it may cause fetal harm. Letairis is very likely to produce serious birth defects if used by pregnant females, as this effect has been seen consistently when it is administered to animals 

         

  

      [see 

          

   

       Contraindications (4.1)  , 

          

   

       Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  , and 

          

   

       Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]. 

         

  

          



     Exclude pregnancy before the initiation of treatment with Letairis. Females of reproductive potential must use acceptable methods of contraception during treatment with Letairis and for one month after treatment. Obtain monthly pregnancy tests during treatment and 1 month after discontinuation of treatment 

         

  

      [see 

          

   

       Dosage and Administration (2.2)   and 

          

   

       Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ]

         

  

      .

        

 

       



     Because of the risk of embryo-fetal toxicity, females can only receive Letairis through a restricted program called the Letairis REMS program 

         

  

      [see 

          

   

       Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]

         

  

      .

        

 

       



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Do not administer Letairis to a pregnant female because it may cause fetal harm ( 4.1, 5.1, 8.1). 
 *  Females of reproductive potential: Exclude pregnancy before the start of treatment, monthly during treatment, and 1 month after stopping treatment. Prevent pregnancy during treatment and for one month after stopping treatment by using acceptable methods of contraception ( 2.2, 8.6). 
 *  For all female patients, Letairis is available only through a restricted program called the Letairis Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) ( 5.2). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Fluid retention may require intervention (  5.3  ). 
 *  If patients develop acute pulmonary edema during initiation of therapy with Letairis, consider underlying pulmonary veno-occlusive disease and discontinue treatment if necessary (  5.4  ). 
 *  Decreases in sperm count have been observed in patients taking endothelin receptor antagonists (  5.5  ). 
 *  Decreases in hemoglobin have been observed within the first few weeks; measure hemoglobin at initiation, at 1 month, and periodically thereafter (  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



   Letairis may cause fetal harm when administered during pregnancy and is contraindicated for use in females who are pregnant. In females of reproductive potential, exclude pregnancy prior to initiation of therapy, ensure use of acceptable contraceptive methods, and obtain monthly pregnancy tests [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  , and  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  ,  8.6)  ]  .  



  Letairis is only available for females through a restricted program under a REMS [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .  



    5.2 Letairis REMS Program



   For all females, Letairis is available only through a restricted program called the Letairis REMS, because of the risk of embryo-fetal toxicity [  see   Contraindications (4.1)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  , and  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  ,  8.6)  ].    



  Notable requirements of the Letairis REMS program include the following:Notable requirements of the Letairis REMS program include the following:  



 *  Prescribers must be certified with the program by enrolling and completing training. 
 *  *  Females of reproductive potential must comply with the pregnancy testing and contraception requirements [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ].  
   All females, regardless of reproductive potential, must enroll in the Letairis REMS program prior to initiating Letairis. Male patients are not enrolled in the REMS. 
 *  Pharmacies that dispense Letairis must be certified with the program and must dispense to female patients who are authorized to receive Letairis. 
     Further information is available at www.letairisrems.com or 1-866-664-5327.Further information is available at www.letairisrems.com or 1-866-664-5327.  
 

    5.3 Fluid Retention



  Peripheral edema is a known class effect of endothelin receptor antagonists, and is also a clinical consequence of PAH and worsening PAH. In the placebo-controlled studies, there was an increased incidence of peripheral edema in patients treated with doses of 5 or 10 mg Letairis compared to placebo [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Most edema was mild to moderate in severity, and it occurred with greater frequency and severity in elderly patients.



 In addition, there have been postmarketing reports of fluid retention in patients with pulmonary hypertension, occurring within weeks after starting Letairis. Patients required intervention with a diuretic, fluid management, or, in some cases, hospitalization for decompensating heart failure.



 If clinically significant fluid retention develops, with or without associated weight gain, further evaluation should be undertaken to determine the cause, such as Letairis or underlying heart failure, and the possible need for specific treatment or discontinuation of Letairis therapy.



    5.4 Pulmonary Edema with Pulmonary Veno-occlusive Disease (PVOD)



  If patients develop acute pulmonary edema during initiation of therapy with vasodilating agents such as Letairis, the possibility of PVOD should be considered, and if confirmed Letairis should be discontinued.



    5.5 Decreased Sperm Counts



  Decreased sperm counts have been observed in human and animal studies with another endothelin receptor antagonist and in animal fertility studies with ambrisentan. Letairis may have an adverse effect on spermatogenesis. Counsel patients about potential effects on fertility [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  and  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  .



    5.6 Hematological Changes



  Decreases in hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit have followed administration of other endothelin receptor antagonists and were observed in clinical studies with Letairis. These decreases were observed within the first few weeks of treatment with Letairis, and stabilized thereafter. The mean decrease in hemoglobin from baseline to end of treatment for those patients receiving Letairis in the 12-week placebo-controlled studies was 0.8 g/dL.



 Marked decreases in hemoglobin (&gt;15% decrease from baseline resulting in a value below the lower limit of normal) were observed in 7% of all patients receiving Letairis (and 10% of patients receiving 10 mg) compared to 4% of patients receiving placebo. The cause of the decrease in hemoglobin is unknown, but it does not appear to result from hemorrhage or hemolysis.



 In the long-term open-label extension of the two pivotal clinical studies, mean decreases from baseline (ranging from 0.9 to 1.2 g/dL) in hemoglobin concentrations persisted for up to 4 years of treatment.



 There have been postmarketing reports of decreases in hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit that have resulted in anemia requiring transfusion.



 Measure hemoglobin prior to initiation of Letairis, at one month, and periodically thereafter. Initiation of Letairis therapy is not recommended for patients with clinically significant anemia. If a clinically significant decrease in hemoglobin is observed and other causes have been excluded, consider discontinuing Letairis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
