<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="levaquin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common reactions (&gt;=3%) were nausea, headache, diarrhea, insomnia, constipation and dizziness (  6.2  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-526-7736 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Serious and Otherwise Important Adverse Reactions

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse drug reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of labeling:



 *  Tendon Effects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Exacerbation of Myasthenia Gravis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Other Serious and Sometimes Fatal Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Hepatotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Central Nervous System Effects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *   Clostridium difficile -Associated Diarrhea [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Peripheral Neuropathy that may be irreversible [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Prolongation of the QT Interval [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Musculoskeletal Disorders in Pediatric Patients [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Blood Glucose Disturbances [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Photosensitivity/Phototoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Development of Drug Resistant Bacteria [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
    Hypotension has been associated with rapid or bolus intravenous infusion of LEVAQUIN  (r)  . LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be infused slowly over 60 to 90 minutes, depending on dosage  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  ]  .
 

 Crystalluria and cylindruria have been reported with quinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  . Therefore, adequate hydration of patients receiving LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be maintained to prevent the formation of a highly concentrated urine  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  ]  .



   6.2 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to LEVAQUIN  (r)  in 7537 patients in 29 pooled Phase 3 clinical trials. The population studied had a mean age of 50 years (approximately 74% of the population was &lt; 65 years of age), 50% were male, 71% were Caucasian, 19% were Black. Patients were treated with LEVAQUIN  (r)  for a wide variety of infectious diseases  [see  Indications and Usage (1)  ]  . Patients received LEVAQUIN  (r)  doses of 750 mg once daily, 250 mg once daily, or 500 mg once or twice daily. Treatment duration was usually 3-14 days, and the mean number of days on therapy was 10 days.



 The overall incidence, type and distribution of adverse reactions was similar in patients receiving LEVAQUIN  (r)  doses of 750 mg once daily, 250 mg once daily, and 500 mg once or twice daily. Discontinuation of LEVAQUIN  (r)  due to adverse drug reactions occurred in 4.3% of patients overall, 3.8% of patients treated with the 250 mg and 500 mg doses and 5.4% of patients treated with the 750 mg dose. The most common adverse drug reactions leading to discontinuation with the 250 and 500 mg doses were gastrointestinal (1.4%), primarily nausea (0.6%); vomiting (0.4%); dizziness (0.3%); and headache (0.2%). The most common adverse drug reactions leading to discontinuation with the 750 mg dose were gastrointestinal (1.2%), primarily nausea (0.6%), vomiting (0.5%); dizziness (0.3%); and headache (0.3%).



 Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=1% of LEVAQUIN  (r)  -treated patients and less common adverse reactions, occurring in 0.1 to &lt;1% of LEVAQUIN  (r)  -treated patients, are shown in Table 4 and Table 5, respectively. The most common adverse drug reactions (&gt;=3%) are nausea, headache, diarrhea, insomnia, constipation, and dizziness.



 Table 4: Common (&gt;=1%) Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with LEVAQUIN(r) 
 System/Organ Class                   Adverse Reaction                                      %(N = 7537)     
  
   Infections and Infestations        moniliasis                                                 1          
   Psychiatric Disorders              insomnia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]           4          
   Nervous System Disorders           headachedizziness  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]          63          
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    dyspnea  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]           1          
   Gastrointestinal Disorders         nausea                                                     7          
 diarrhea                             5                                                    
 constipation                         3                                                    
 abdominal pain                       2                                                    
 vomiting                             2                                                    
 dyspepsia                            2                                                    
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    rash  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  pruritus        21          
   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders    vaginitis                                                  1          
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    edema                                                      1          
 injection site reaction              1                                                    
 chest pain                           1                                                    
        Table 5: Less Common (0.1 to 1%) Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with LEVAQUIN(r) (N = 7537) 
 System/Organ Class                        Adverse Reaction                                               
  
   Infections and Infestations             genital moniliasis                                             
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    anemiathrombocytopeniagranulocytopenia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]     
   Immune System Disorders                 allergic reaction  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3,    5.4)  ]     
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders      hyperglycemiahypoglycemia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  hyperkalemia   
   Psychiatric Disorders                   anxietyagitationconfusiondepressionhallucinationnightmare  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  sleep disorderanorexiaabnormal dreaming   
   Nervous System Disorders                tremorconvulsions  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  paresthesia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  vertigohypertoniahyperkinesiasabnormal gaitsomnolencesyncope   
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    epistaxis                                                      
   Cardiac Disorders                       cardiac arrestpalpitationventricular tachycardiaventricular arrhythmia   
   Vascular Disorders                      phlebitis                                                      
   Gastrointestinal Disorders              gastritisstomatitispancreatitisesophagitisgastroenteritisglossitispseudomembranous/  C. difficile  colitis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]     
   Hepatobiliary Disorders                 abnormal hepatic functionincreased hepatic enzymesincreased alkaline phosphatase   
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    urticaria  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]             
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    arthralgiatendinitis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  myalgiaskeletal pain   
   Renal and Urinary Disorders             abnormal renal functionacute renal failure  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]     
        In clinical trials using multiple-dose therapy, ophthalmologic abnormalities, including cataracts and multiple punctate lenticular opacities, have been noted in patients undergoing treatment with quinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  . The relationship of the drugs to these events is not presently established.
 

   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  Table 6 lists adverse reactions that have been identified during post-approval use of LEVAQUIN  (r)  . Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, reliably estimating their frequency or establishing a causal relationship to drug exposure is not always possible.



 Table 6: Postmarketing Reports Of Adverse Drug Reactions 
 System/Organ Class                        Adverse Reaction                                               
  
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    pancytopeniaaplastic anemialeukopeniahemolytic anemia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  eosinophilia   
   Immune System Disorders                 hypersensitivity reactions, sometimes fatal including:  anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions  anaphylactic shock  angioneurotic edema  serum sickness  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3  ,  5.4)  ]     
   Psychiatric Disorders                   psychosisparanoiaisolated reports of suicide attempt and suicidal ideation  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]     
   Nervous System Disorders                exacerbation of myasthenia gravis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  anosmiaageusiaparosmiadysgeusiaperipheral neuropathy (may be irreversible)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  isolated reports of encephalopathyabnormal electroencephalogram (EEG)dysphoniapseudotumor cerebri  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]     
   Eye Disorders                           uveitisvision disturbance, including diplopiavisual acuity reducedvision blurredscotoma   
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders             hypoacusistinnitus                                             
   Cardiac Disorders                       isolated reports of torsade de pointeselectrocardiogram QT prolonged  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  tachycardia   
   Vascular Disorders                      vasodilatation                                                 
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    isolated reports of allergic pneumonitis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]     
   Hepatobiliary Disorders                 hepatic failure (including fatal cases)hepatitisjaundice  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4  ),  (5.5)  ]     
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    bullous eruptions to include:  Stevens-Johnson Syndrome  toxic epidermal necrolysis  erythema multiforme  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  photosensitivity/phototoxicity reaction  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  leukocytoclastic vasculitis   
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    tendon rupture  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  muscle injury, including rupturerhabdomyolysis   
   Renal and Urinary Disorders             interstitial nephritis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]     
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    multi-organ failurepyrexia                                     
   Investigations                          prothrombin time prolongedinternational normalized ratio prolongedmuscle enzymes increased   
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:

    WARNING:  

    Fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages. This risk is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].    



   Fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. Avoid LEVAQUIN  (r)   in patients with a known history of myasthenia gravis     [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]      .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages. This risk is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .  



   Fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. Avoid LEVAQUIN  (r)   in patients with a known history of myasthenia gravis   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]    .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture is increased. This risk is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroids, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants. Discontinue if pain or inflammation in a tendon occurs (  5.1   ,   8.5  ) 
 *  May exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. Avoid use in patients with a known history of myasthenia gravis (  5.2  ) 
 *  Anaphylactic reactions and allergic skin reactions, serious, occasionally fatal, may occur after first dose (  4   ,   5.3  ) 
 *  Hematologic (including agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia), and renal toxicities may occur after multiple doses (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Severe, and sometimes fatal, hepatoxicity has been reported. Discontinue immediately if signs and symptoms of hepatitis occur (  5.5  ) 
 *  Central nervous system effects, including convulsions, anxiety, confusion, depression, and insomnia may occur after the first dose. Use with caution in patients with known or suspected disorders that may predispose them to seizures or lower the seizure threshold. Increased intracranial pressure (pseudotumor cerebri) has been reported (  5.6  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated colitis: evaluate if diarrhea occurs (  5.7  ) 
 *  Peripheral neuropathy: discontinue immediately if symptoms occur in order to prevent irreversibility (  5.8  ) 
 *  Prolongation of the QT interval and isolated cases of torsade de pointes have been reported. Avoid use in patients with known prolongation, those with hypokalemia, and with other drugs that prolong the QT interval (  5.9  ,  8.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Tendinopathy and Tendon Rupture



  Fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages. This adverse reaction most frequently involves the Achilles tendon, and rupture of the Achilles tendon may require surgical repair. Tendinitis and tendon rupture in the rotator cuff (the shoulder), the hand, the biceps, the thumb, and other tendon sites have also been reported. The risk of developing fluoroquinolone-associated tendinitis and tendon rupture is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in those taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants. Factors, in addition to age and corticosteroid use, that may independently increase the risk of tendon rupture include strenuous physical activity, renal failure, and previous tendon disorders such as rheumatoid arthritis. Tendinitis and tendon rupture have been reported in patients taking fluoroquinolones who do not have the above risk factors. Tendon rupture can occur during or after completion of therapy; cases occurring up to several months after completion of therapy have been reported. LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be discontinued if the patient experiences pain, swelling, inflammation or rupture of a tendon. Patients should be advised to rest at the first sign of tendinitis or tendon rupture, and to contact their healthcare provider regarding changing to a non-quinolone antimicrobial drug. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)    ;   Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .



    5.2 Exacerbation of Myasthenia Gravis



  Fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , have neuromuscular blocking activity and may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis. Postmarketing serious adverse events, including deaths and requirement for ventilatory support, have been associated with fluoroquinolone use in persons with myasthenia gravis. Avoid LEVAQUIN  (r)  in patients with a known history of myasthenia gravis [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)    ;   Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ].  



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious and occasionally fatal hypersensitivity and/or anaphylactic reactions have been reported in patients receiving therapy with fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  . These reactions often occur following the first dose. Some reactions have been accompanied by cardiovascular collapse, hypotension/shock, seizure, loss of consciousness, tingling, angioedema (including tongue, laryngeal, throat, or facial edema/swelling), airway obstruction (including bronchospasm, shortness of breath, and acute respiratory distress), dyspnea, urticaria, itching, and other serious skin reactions. LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be discontinued immediately at the first appearance of a skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity. Serious acute hypersensitivity reactions may require treatment with epinephrine and other resuscitative measures, including oxygen, intravenous fluids, antihistamines, corticosteroids, pressor amines, and airway management, as clinically indicated [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ;  Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .



    5.4 Other Serious and Sometimes Fatal Reactions



  Other serious and sometimes fatal events, some due to hypersensitivity, and some due to uncertain etiology, have been reported rarely in patients receiving therapy with fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  . These events may be severe and generally occur following the administration of multiple doses. Clinical manifestations may include one or more of the following:



 *  fever, rash, or severe dermatologic reactions (e.g., toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome); 
 *  vasculitis; arthralgia; myalgia; serum sickness; 
 *  allergic pneumonitis; 
 *  interstitial nephritis; acute renal insufficiency or failure; 
 *  hepatitis; jaundice; acute hepatic necrosis or failure; 
 *  anemia, including hemolytic and aplastic; thrombocytopenia, including thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura; leukopenia; agranulocytosis; pancytopenia; and/or other hematologic abnormalities. 
    The drug should be discontinued immediately at the first appearance of skin rash, jaundice, or any other sign of hypersensitivity and supportive measures instituted [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ;  Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .
 

    5.5 Hepatotoxicity



  Post-marketing reports of severe hepatotoxicity (including acute hepatitis and fatal events) have been received for patients treated with LEVAQUIN  (r).  No evidence of serious drug-associated hepatotoxicity was detected in clinical trials of over 7,000 patients. Severe hepatotoxicity generally occurred within 14 days of initiation of therapy and most cases occurred within 6 days. Most cases of severe hepatotoxicity were not associated with hypersensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  . The majority of fatal hepatotoxicity reports occurred in patients 65 years of age or older and most were not associated with hypersensitivity. LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be discontinued immediately if the patient develops signs and symptoms of hepatitis [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ;  Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ].  



    5.6 Central Nervous System Effects



  Convulsions, toxic psychoses, increased intracranial pressure (including pseudotumor cerebri) have been reported in patients receiving fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  . Fluoroquinolones may also cause central nervous system stimulation which may lead to tremors, restlessness, anxiety, lightheadedness, confusion, hallucinations, paranoia, depression, nightmares, insomnia, and, rarely, suicidal thoughts or acts. These reactions may occur following the first dose. If these reactions occur in patients receiving LEVAQUIN  (r)  , the drug should be discontinued and appropriate measures instituted. As with other fluoroquinolones, LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be used with caution in patients with a known or suspected central nervous system (CNS) disorder that may predispose them to seizures or lower the seizure threshold (e.g., severe cerebral arteriosclerosis, epilepsy) or in the presence of other risk factors that may predispose them to seizures or lower the seizure threshold (e.g., certain drug therapy, renal dysfunction). [see  Adverse Reactions (6)    ;   Drug Interactions (7.4    ,   7.5)    ;   Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .



    5.7 Clostridium difficile-Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated [see     Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ,   Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .



    5.8 Peripheral Neuropathy



   Cases of sensory or sensorimotor axonal polyneuropathy affecting small and/or large axons resulting in paresthesias, hypoesthesias, dysesthesias and weakness have been reported in patients receiving fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  . Symptoms may occur soon after initiation of LEVAQUIN  (r)  and may be irreversible. LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be discontinued immediately if the patient experiences symptoms of neuropathy including pain, burning, tingling, numbness, and/or weakness or other alterations of sensation including light touch, pain, temperature, position sense, and vibratory sensation [see  Adverse Reactions (6)    ,   Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .  



    5.9 Prolongation of the QT Interval



  Some fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  , have been associated with prolongation of the QT interval on the electrocardiogram and infrequent cases of arrhythmia. Rare cases of torsade de pointes have been spontaneously reported during postmarketing surveillance in patients receiving fluoroquinolones, including LEVAQUIN  (r)  . LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be avoided in patients with known prolongation of the QT interval, patients with uncorrected hypokalemia, and patients receiving Class IA (quinidine, procainamide), or Class III (amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic agents. Elderly patients may be more susceptible to drug-associated effects on the QT interval [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)    ,   Use in Specific Populations (8.5)    , and   Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .



    5.10 Musculoskeletal Disorders in Pediatric Patients and Arthropathic Effects in Animals



  LEVAQUIN  (r)  is indicated in pediatric patients (6 months of age and older) only for the prevention of inhalational anthrax (post-exposure) and for plague [see  Indications and Usage (1.13    ,   1.14)    ]. An increased incidence of musculoskeletal disorders (arthralgia, arthritis, tendinopathy, and gait abnormality) compared to controls has been observed in pediatric patients receiving LEVAQUIN  (r)   [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



 In immature rats and dogs, the oral and intravenous administration of levofloxacin resulted in increased osteochondrosis. Histopathological examination of the weight-bearing joints of immature dogs dosed with levofloxacin revealed persistent lesions of the cartilage. Other fluoroquinolones also produce similar erosions in the weight-bearing joints and other signs of arthropathy in immature animals of various species [see  Animal Toxicology and/or Pharmacology (13.2)  ]  .



    5.11 Blood Glucose Disturbances



  As with other fluoroquinolones, disturbances of blood glucose, including symptomatic hyper- and hypoglycemia, have been reported with LEVAQUIN  (r)  , usually in diabetic patients receiving concomitant treatment with an oral hypoglycemic agent (e.g., glyburide) or with insulin. In these patients, careful monitoring of blood glucose is recommended. If a hypoglycemic reaction occurs in a patient being treated with LEVAQUIN  (r)  , LEVAQUIN  (r)  should be discontinued and appropriate therapy should be initiated immediately [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ;   Drug Interactions (7.3)    ;   Patient Counseling Information (17.4)  ]  .



    5.12 Photosensitivity/Phototoxicity



  Moderate to severe photosensitivity/phototoxicity reactions, the latter of which may manifest as exaggerated sunburn reactions (e.g., burning, erythema, exudation, vesicles, blistering, edema) involving areas exposed to light (typically the face, "V" area of the neck, extensor surfaces of the forearms, dorsa of the hands), can be associated with the use of fluoroquinolones after sun or UV light exposure. Therefore, excessive exposure to these sources of light should be avoided. Drug therapy should be discontinued if photosensitivity/phototoxicity occurs [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)    ;   Patient Counseling Information (17.3)  ]  .



    5.13 Development of Drug Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing LEVAQUIN  (r)  in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
