<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="levemir" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse events commonly associated with human insulin therapy include the following:



   Body as Whole  : allergic reactions (see PRECAUTIONS,  Allergy  ).



   Skin and Appendages  : lipodystrophy, pruritus, rash. Mild injection site reactions occurred more frequently with LEVEMIR than with NPH human insulin and usually resolved in a few days to a few weeks (see PRECAUTIONS,  Allergy  ).



   Other:  



   Hypoglycemia:  (see  WARNINGS  and  PRECAUTIONS  ).



 In trials of up to 6 months duration in patients with type 1 and type 2 diabetes, the incidence of severe hypoglycemia with LEVEMIR was comparable to the incidence with NPH, and, as expected, greater overall in patients with type 1 diabetes (Table 4).



   Weight gain:  



 In trials of up to 6 months duration in patients with type 1 and type 2 diabetes, LEVEMIR was associated with somewhat less weight gain than NPH (Table 4). Whether these observed differences represent true differences in the effects of LEVEMIR and NPH insulin is not known, since these trials were not blinded and the protocols (e.g., diet and exercise instructions and monitoring) were not specifically directed at exploring hypotheses related to weight effects of the treatments compared. The clinical significance of the observed differences has not been established.



 Table 4: Safety Information on Clinical Studies  
                                     Weight    (kg)      Hypoglycemia (events/subject/month)     
                  Treatment        # of subjects  Baseline        End of treatment  Major           Minor            
   Type 1          
 Study A          LEVEMIR          N=276         75.0            75.1            0.045           2.184            
 NPH              N=133            75.7          76.4            0.035           3.063            
 Study C          LEVEMIR          N=492         76.5            76.3            0.029           2.397            
 NPH              N=257            76.1          76.5            0.027           2.564            
 Study D Pediatric  LEVEMIR          N=232         N/A             N/A             0.076           2.677            
 NPH              N=115            N/A           N/A             0.083           3.203            
   Type 2          
 Study E          LEVEMIR          N=237         82.7            83.7            0.001           0.306            
 NPH              N=239            82.4          85.2            0.006           0.595            
 Study F          LEVEMIR          N=195         81.8            82.3            0.003           0.193            
 NPH              N=200            79.6          80.9            0.006           0.235            
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
