<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="levitra" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  LEVITRA was administered to over 4430 men (mean age 56, range 18-89 years; 81% White, 6% Black, 2% Asian, 2% Hispanic and 9% Other) during controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials worldwide. Over 2200 patients were treated for 6 months or longer, and 880 patients were treated for at least 1 year.



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials, the discontinuation rate due to adverse events was 3.4% for LEVITRA compared to 1.1% for placebo.



 When LEVITRA was taken as recommended in placebo-controlled clinical trials, the following adverse events were reported (see    Table 5    ).



 Table 5: Adverse Events Reported By &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with LEVITRA and More Frequent on Drug than Placebo in Fixed and FlexibleFlexible dose studies started all patients at LEVITRA 10 mg and allowed decrease in dose to 5 mg or increase in dose to 20 mg based on side effects and efficacy. Dose Randomized, Controlled Trials of 5 mg, 10 mg, or 20 mg Vardenafil 
 Adverse Event    Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
                  PlaceboN = 1199  LEVITRAN = 2203   
  
 Headache         4%               15%               
 Flushing         1%               11%               
 Rhinitis         3%               9%                
 Dyspepsia        1%               4%                
 Accidental Injury  2%               3%                
 Sinusitis        1%               3%                
 Flu Syndrome     2%               3%                
 Dizziness        1%               2%                
 Increased Creatine Kinase  1%               2%                
 Nausea           1%               2%                
         Back pain was reported in 2.0% of patients treated with LEVITRA and 1.7% of patients on placebo.
 

 Placebo-controlled trials suggested a dose effect in the incidence of some adverse events (headache, flushing, dyspepsia, nausea, rhinitis) over the 5 mg, 10 mg, and 20 mg doses of LEVITRA. The following section identifies additional, less frequent events (&lt;2%) reported during the clinical development of LEVITRA. Excluded from this list are those events that are infrequent and minor, those events that may be commonly observed in the absence of drug therapy, and those events that are not reasonably associated with the drug.



    BODY AS A WHOLE: anaphylactic reaction (including laryngeal edema),   asthenia, face edema, pain



    AUDITORY: sudden decrease or loss of hearing, tinnitus



    CARDIOVASCULAR: angina pectoris, chest pain, hypertension,   hypotension, myocardial ischemia, myocardial infarction, palpitation,   postural hypotension, syncope, tachycardia



    DIGESTIVE: abdominal pain, abnormal liver function tests, diarrhea, dry   mouth, dysphagia, esophagitis, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux, GGTP   increased, vomiting



    MUSCULOSKELETAL: arthralgia, back pain, myalgia, neck pain



    NERVOUS: hypertonia, hypesthesia, insomnia, paresthesia, somnolence,   vertigo



    RESPIRATORY: dyspnea, epistaxis, pharyngitis



    SKIN AND APPENDAGES: photosensitivity reaction, pruritus, rash,   sweating



    OPHTHALMOLOGIC: abnormal vision, blurred vision, chromatopsia,   changes in color vision, conjunctivitis (increased redness of the eye), dim   vision, eye pain, glaucoma, photophobia, watery eyes



    UROGENITAL: abnormal ejaculation, priapism (including prolonged or   painful erections)
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
