<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="levulan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In Phase 3 studies, no non-cutaneous adverse events were found to be consistently associated with LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution application followed by blue light exposure.



   Photodynamic Therapy Response:  The constellation of transient local symptoms of stinging and/or burning, itching, erythema and edema as a result of LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution plus BLU-U treatment was observed in all clinical studies of LEVULAN KERASTICK for Topical Solution Photodynamic Therapy for actinic keratoses treatment. Stinging and/or burning subsided between 1 minute and 24 hours after the BLU-U Blue Light Photodynamic Therapy Illuminator was turned off, and appeared qualitatively similar to that perceived by patients with erythropoietic protoporphyria upon exposure to sunlight. There was no clear drug dose or light dose dependent change in the incidence or severity of stinging and/or burning.



 In two Phase 3 trials, the sensation of stinging and/or burning appeared to reach a plateau at 6 minutes into the treatment. Severe stinging and/or burning at one or more lesions being treated was reported by at least 50% of the patients at some time during treatment. The majority of patients reported that all lesions treated exhibited at least slight stinging and/or burning. Less than 3% of patients discontinued light treatment due to stinging and/or burning.



 In the Phase 3 trials, the most common changes in lesion appearance after LEVULAN KERASTICK for Topical Solution Photodynamic Therapy were erythema and edema. In 99% of active treatment patients, some or all lesions were erythematous shortly after treatment, while in 79% of vehicle treatment patients, some or all lesions were erythematous. In 35% of active treatment patients, some or all lesions were edematous, while no vehicle-treated patients had edematous lesions. Both erythema and edema resolved to baseline or improved by 4 weeks after therapy. LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution application to photodamaged perilesional skin resulted in photosensitization of photodamaged skin and in a photodynamic response (  see  Warnings and Precautions    )).



   Other Localized Cutaneous Adverse Experiences:    Table 2  depicts the incidence and severity of cutaneous adverse events in Phase 3 studies, stratified by anatomic site treated.



 TABLE 2 Post-PDT Cutaneous Adverse Events - ALA-018/ALA-019 
                           FACE       SCALP       
                           LEVULAN (n=139)  Vehicle (n=41)  LEVULAN (n=42)  Vehicle (n=21)   
 Degree of Severity        Mild/Moderate  Severe     Mild/Moderate  Severe     Mild/Moderate  Severe     Mild/Moderate  Severe      
  
 Scaling/Crusting          71%        1%         12%        0%         64%        2%         19%        0%          
 Pain                      1%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%          
 Tenderness                1%         0%         0%         0%         2%         0%         0%         0%          
 Itching                   25%        1%         7%         0%         14%        7%         19%        0%          
 Edema                     1%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%          
 Ulceration                4%         0%         0%         0%         2%         0%         0%         0%          
 Bleeding/Hemorrhage       4%         0%         0%         0%         2%         0%         0%         0%          
 Hypo/hyper-pigmentation   22%        20%        36%        33%         
 Vesiculation              4%         0%         0%         0%         5%         0%         0%         0%          
 Pustules                  4%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%          
 Oozing                    1%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%          
 Dysesthesia               2%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%          
 Scabbing                  2%         1%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%          
 Erosion                   14%        1%         0%         0%         2%         0%         0%         0%          
 Excoriation               1%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%         0%          
 Wheal/Flare               7%         1%         0%         0%         2%         0%         0%         0%          
 Skin disorder NOS         5%         0%         0%         0%         12%        0%         5%         0%          
        Adverse Experiences Reported by Body System:  In the Phase 3 studies, 7 patients experienced a serious adverse event. All were deemed remotely or not related to treatment. No clinically significant patterns of clinical laboratory changes were observed for standard serum chemical or hematologic parameters in any of the controlled clinical trials.
 

   EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions occurring during clinical trials with an incidence &gt;= 2% were erythema, edema, stinging/burning, scaling/crusting, hypo/hyperpigmentation, itching/pruritus, erosion, wheal/flare, vesiculation, ulceration, bleeding/hemorrhage, pain, pustules, tenderness, scabbing and dysesthesia (  6  ).



   To Report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact DUSA Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (877) 533-3872 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  Avoid exposure of the photosensitive actinic keratoses to sunlight or bright indoor light prior to blue light treatment. Protect treated lesions from sunlight exposure. Sunscreens will not protect the patient against photosensitivity reactions (  5.1  ). 
 *  The LEVULAN KERASTICK for Topical Solution should be used by a qualified health professional to apply drug only to actinic keratoses and not perilesional skin (  5.2  ). 
 *  Do not apply to the eyes or to mucous membranes. Excessive irritation may be experienced if this product is applied under occlusion (  5.2  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Photosensitivity



  During the time period between the application of LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution and exposure to activating light from the BLU-U Blue Light Photodynamic Therapy Illuminator, the treatment site will become photosensitive. After LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution application, patients should avoid exposure of the photosensitive treatment sites to sunlight or bright indoor light (e.g., examination lamps, operating room lamps, tanning beds, or lights at close proximity) during the period prior to blue light treatment. Exposure may result in a stinging and/or burning sensation and may cause erythema and/or edema of the lesions. Before exposure to sunlight, patients should, therefore, protect treated lesions from the sun by wearing a wide-brimmed hat or similar head covering of light-opaque material. Sunscreens will not protect against photosensitivity reactions caused by visible light. It has not been determined if perspiration can spread the LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution outside the treatment site to eye or surrounding skin.



 Application of LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution to perilesional areas of photodamaged skin of the face or scalp may result in photosensitization. Upon exposure to activating light from the BLU-U Blue Light Photodynamic Therapy Illuminator, such photosensitized skin may produce a stinging and/or burning sensation and may become erythematous and/or edematous in a manner similar to that of actinic keratoses treated with LEVULAN KERASTICK Photodynamic Therapy. Because of the potential for skin to become photosensitized, the LEVULAN KERASTICK should be used by a qualified health professional to apply drug only to actinic keratoses and not perilesional skin.



 If for any reason the patient cannot return for blue light treatment during the prescribed period after application of LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution (14 to 18 hours), the patient should call the doctor. The patient should also continue to avoid exposure of the photosensitized lesions to sunlight or prolonged or intense light for at least 40 hours. If stinging and/or burning is noted, exposure to light should be reduced.



    5.2 Irritation



  The LEVULAN KERASTICK Topical Solution contains alcohol and is intended for topical use only. Do not apply to the eyes or to mucous membranes.  Excessive irritation may be experienced if this product is applied under occlusion.



    5.3 Coagulation Defects



  The LEVULAN KERASTICK for Topical Solution has not been tested on patients with inherited or acquired coagulation defects
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
