<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lexapro" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the incidence of placebo patients) are: insomnia, ejaculation disorder (primarily ejaculatory delay), nausea, sweating increased, fatigue and somnolence, decreased libido, and anorgasmia (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Forest Laboratories LLC. at 1-800-678-1605, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Clinical Trial Data Sources  



     Pediatrics (6 -17 years)  



 Adverse events were collected in 576 pediatric patients (286 Lexapro, 290 placebo) with major depressive disorder in double-blind placebo-controlled studies. Safety and effectiveness of Lexapro in pediatric patients less than 12 years of age has not been established.



     Adults  



 Adverse events information for Lexapro was collected from 715 patients with major depressive disorder who were exposed to escitalopram and from 592 patients who were exposed to placebo in double-blind, placebo-controlled trials. An additional 284 patients with major depressive disorder were newly exposed to escitalopram in open-label trials. The adverse event information for Lexapro in patients with GAD was collected from 429 patients exposed to escitalopram and from 427 patients exposed to placebo in double-blind, placebo-controlled trials.



 Adverse events during exposure were obtained primarily by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of events into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and tabulations that follow, standard World Health Organization (WHO) terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



     Adverse Events Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment  



     Major Depressive Disorder  



     Pediatrics (6 -17 years)  



 Adverse events were associated with discontinuation of 3.5% of 286 patients receiving Lexapro and 1% of 290 patients receiving placebo. The most common adverse event (incidence at least 1% for Lexapro and greater than placebo) associated with discontinuation was insomnia (1% Lexapro, 0% placebo).



     Adults  



 Among the 715 depressed patients who received Lexapro in placebo-controlled trials, 6% discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, as compared to 2% of 592 patients receiving placebo. In two fixed-dose studies, the rate of discontinuation for adverse events in patients receiving 10 mg/day Lexapro was not significantly different from the rate of discontinuation for adverse events in patients receiving placebo. The rate of discontinuation for adverse events in patients assigned to a fixed dose of 20 mg/day Lexapro was 10%, which was significantly different from the rate of discontinuation for adverse events in patients receiving 10 mg/day Lexapro (4%) and placebo (3%). Adverse events that were associated with the discontinuation of at least 1% of patients treated with Lexapro, and for which the rate was at least twice that of placebo, were nausea (2%) and ejaculation disorder (2% of male patients).



     Generalized Anxiety Disorder  



     Adults  



 Among the 429 GAD patients who received Lexapro 10-20 mg/day in placebo-controlled trials, 8% discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, as compared to 4% of 427 patients receiving placebo. Adverse events that were associated with the discontinuation of at least 1% of patients treated with Lexapro, and for which the rate was at least twice the placebo rate, were nausea (2%), insomnia (1%), and fatigue (1%).



     Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials  



     Major Depressive Disorder  



     Pediatrics (6 -17 years)  



 The overall profile of adverse reactions in pediatric patients was generally similar to that seen in adult studies, as shown in  Table 2  . However, the following adverse reactions (excluding those which appear in  Table 2  and those for which the coded terms were uninformative or misleading) were reported at an incidence of at least 2% for Lexapro and greater than placebo: back pain, urinary tract infection, vomiting, and nasal congestion.



     Adults  



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions in Lexapro patients (incidence of approximately 5% or greater and approximately twice the incidence in placebo patients) were insomnia, ejaculation disorder (primarily ejaculatory delay), nausea, sweating increased, fatigue, and somnolence.



   Table 2  enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse events that occurred among 715 depressed patients who received Lexapro at doses ranging from 10 to 20 mg/day in placebo-controlled trials. Events included are those occurring in 2% or more of patients treated with Lexapro and for which the incidence in patients treated with Lexapro was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 TABLE 2 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions observed with a frequency of &gt;= 2% and greater than placebo for Major Depressive Disorder 
  1Primarily ejaculatory delay.                 
  2Denominator used was for males only (N=225 Lexapro; N=188 placebo).    
  3Denominator used was for females only (N=490 Lexapro; N=404 placebo).    
  
   Adverse Reaction                              Lexapro                       Placebo                     
                                                 (N=715)%                      (N=592)%                    
   Autonomic Nervous System Disorders                                                                      
 Dry Mouth                                     6%                            5%                            
 Sweating Increased                            5%                            2%                            
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders                                                                
 Dizziness                                     5%                            3%                            
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                              
 Nausea                                        15%                           7%                            
 Diarrhea                                      8%                            5%                            
 Constipation                                  3%                            1%                            
 Indigestion                                   3%                            1%                            
 Abdominal Pain                                2%                            1%                            
   General                                                                                                 
 Influenza-like Symptoms                       5%                            4%                            
 Fatigue                                       5%                            2%                            
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                   
 Insomnia                                      9%                            4%                            
 Somnolence                                    6%                            2%                            
 Appetite Decreased                            3%                            1%                            
 Libido Decreased                              3%                            1%                            
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                            
 Rhinitis                                      5%                            4%                            
 Sinusitis                                     3%                            2%                            
   Urogenital                                                                                              
 Ejaculation Disorder  1,2                     9%                            &lt;1%                           
 Impotence  2                                  3%                            &lt;1%                           
 Anorgasmia  3                                 2%                            &lt;1%                           
             Generalized Anxiety Disorder  
 

     Adults  



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions in Lexapro patients (incidence of approximately 5% or greater and approximately twice the incidence in placebo patients) were nausea, ejaculation disorder (primarily ejaculatory delay), insomnia, fatigue, decreased libido, and anorgasmia.



     Table 3    enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent of treatment-emergent adverse events that occurred among 429 GAD patients who received Lexapro 10 to 20 mg/day in placebo-controlled trials. Events included are those occurring in 2% or more of patients treated with Lexapro and for which the incidence in patients treated with Lexapro was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 TABLE 3 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions observed with a frequency of &gt;= 2% and greater than placebo for Generalized Anxiety Disorder 
  1Primarily ejaculatory delay.                    
  2Denominator used was for males only (N=182 Lexapro; N=195 placebo).    
  3Denominator used was for females only (N=247 Lexapro; N=232 placebo).    
  
   Adverse Reactions                                Lexapro                     Placebo                    
                                                    (N=429)%                    (N=427)%                   
   Autonomic Nervous System Disorders                                                                      
    Dry Mouth                                     9%                          5%                           
    Sweating Increased                            4%                          1%                           
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders                                                             
    Headache                                      24%                         17%                          
    Paresthesia                                   2%                          1%                           
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                              
    Nausea                                        18%                         8%                           
    Diarrhea                                      8%                          6%                           
    Constipation                                  5%                          4%                           
    Indigestion                                   3%                          2%                           
    Vomiting                                      3%                          1%                           
    Abdominal Pain                                2%                          1%                           
    Flatulence                                    2%                          1%                           
    Toothache                                     2%                          0%                           
   General                                                                                                 
    Fatigue                                       8%                          2%                           
    Influenza-like Symptoms                       5%                          4%                           
   Musculoskeletal System Disorder                                                                         
    Neck/Shoulder Pain                            3%                          1%                           
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                   
    Somnolence                                    13%                         7%                           
    Insomnia                                      12%                         6%                           
    Libido Decreased                              7%                          2%                           
    Dreaming Abnormal                             3%                          2%                           
    Appetite Decreased                            3%                          1%                           
    Lethargy                                      3%                          1%                           
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                            
    Yawning                                       2%                          1%                           
   Urogenital                                                                                              
    Ejaculation Disorder  1,2                     14%                         2%                           
    Anorgasmia  3                                 6%                          &lt;1%                          
    Menstrual Disorder                            2%                          1%                           
             Dose Dependency of Adverse Reactions  
 

 The potential dose dependency of common adverse reactions (defined as an incidence rate of &gt;=5% in either the 10 mg or 20 mg Lexapro groups) was examined on the basis of the combined incidence of adverse reactions in two fixed-dose trials. The overall incidence rates of adverse events in 10 mg Lexapro-treated patients (66%) was similar to that of the placebo-treated patients (61%), while the incidence rate in 20 mg/day Lexapro-treated patients was greater (86%).  Table 4  shows common adverse reactions that occurred in the 20 mg/day Lexapro group with an incidence that was approximately twice that of the 10 mg/day Lexapro group and approximately twice that of the placebo group.



 TABLE 4 Incidence of Common Adverse Reactions in Patients with Major Depressive Disorder 
   Adverse Reaction                  Placebo               10 mg/day                  20 mg/day             
                                     (N=311)               Lexapro                    Lexapro               
                                                           (N=310)                    (N=125)               
   Insomnia                        4%                    7%                         14%                     
   Diarrhea                        5%                    6%                         14%                     
   Dry Mouth                       3%                    4%                         9%                      
   Somnolence                      1%                    4%                         9%                      
   Dizziness                       2%                    4%                         7%                      
   Sweating Increased              &lt;1%                   3%                         8%                      
   Constipation                    1%                    3%                         6%                      
   Fatigue                         2%                    2%                         6%                      
   Indigestion                     1%                    2%                         6%                      
              Male and Female Sexual Dysfunction with SSRIs  
 

 Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that SSRIs can cause such untoward sexual experiences.



 Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, however, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling are likely to underestimate their actual incidence.



 TABLE 5 Incidence of Sexual Side Effects in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials 
   Adverse Event                        Lexapro                           Placebo                          
                                      In Males Only                      
                                      (N=407)                           (N=383)                            
 Ejaculation Disorder(primarily ejaculatory delay)  12%                               1%                                 
 Libido Decreased                     6%                                2%                                 
    Impotence                         2%                                &lt;1%                                
                                      In Females Only                    
                                      (N=737)                           (N=636)                            
 Libido Decreased                     3%                                1%                                 
 Anorgasmia                           3%                                &lt;1%                                
         There are no adequately designed studies examining sexual dysfunction with escitalopram treatment.
 

 Priapism has been reported with all SSRIs.



 While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



     Vital Sign Changes  



 Lexapro and placebo groups were compared with respect to (1) mean change from baseline in vital signs (pulse, systolic blood pressure, and diastolic blood pressure) and (2) the incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially clinically significant changes from baseline in these variables. These analyses did not reveal any clinically important changes in vital signs associated with Lexapro treatment. In addition, a comparison of supine and standing vital sign measures in subjects receiving Lexapro indicated that Lexapro treatment is not associated with orthostatic changes.



     Weight Changes  



 Patients treated with Lexapro in controlled trials did not differ from placebo-treated patients with regard to clinically important change in body weight.



     Laboratory Changes  



 Lexapro and placebo groups were compared with respect to (1) mean change from baseline in various serum chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis variables, and (2) the incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially clinically significant changes from baseline in these variables. These analyses revealed no clinically important changes in laboratory test parameters associated with Lexapro treatment.



     ECG Changes  



 Electrocardiograms from Lexapro (N=625) and placebo (N=527) groups were compared with respect to outliers defined as subjects with QTc changes over 60 msec from baseline or absolute values over 500 msec post-dose, and subjects with heart rate increases to over 100 bpm or decreases to less than 50 bpm with a 25% change from baseline (tachycardic or bradycardic outliers, respectively). None of the patients in the Lexapro group had a QTcF interval &gt;500 msec or a prolongation &gt;60 msec compared to 0.2% of patients in the placebo group. The incidence of tachycardic outliers was 0.2% in the Lexapro and the placebo group. The incidence of bradycardic outliers was 0.5% in the Lexapro group and 0.2% in the placebo group.



 QTcF interval was evaluated in a randomized, placebo and active (moxifloxacin 400 mg) controlled cross-over, escalating multiple-dose study in 113 healthy subjects. The maximum mean  (95% upper confidence bound)  difference from placebo arm were 4.5 (6.4) and 10.7 (12.7) msec for 10 mg and supratherapeutic 30 mg escitalopram given once daily, respectively. Based on the established exposure-response relationship, the predicted QTcF change from placebo arm (95% confidence interval) under the Cmaxfor the dose of 20 mg is 6.6 (7.9) msec. Escitalopram 30 mg given once daily resulted in mean Cmaxof 1.7-fold higher than the mean Cmaxfor the maximum recommended therapeutic dose at steady state (20 mg). The exposure under supratherapeutic 30 mg dose is similar to the steady state concentrations expected in CYP2C19 poor metabolizers following a therapeutic dose of 20 mg.



     Other Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Lexapro  



 Following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse events, as defined in the introduction to the    ADVERSE REACTIONS    section, reported by the 1428 patients treated with Lexapro for periods of up to one year in double-blind or open-label clinical trials during its premarketing evaluation. The listing does not include those events already listed in    Tables 2  &amp;  3    , those events for which a drug cause was remote and at a rate less than 1% or lower than placebo, those events which were so general as to be uninformative, and those events reported only once which did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life threatening. Events are categorized by body system. Events of major clinical importance are described in the Warnings and Precautions section (  5  ).



 Cardiovascular - hypertension, palpitation.



 Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders - light-headed feeling, migraine.



 Gastrointestinal Disorders - abdominal cramp, heartburn, gastroenteritis.



 General - allergy, chest pain, fever, hot flushes, pain in limb.



 Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders - increased weight.



 Musculoskeletal System Disorders - arthralgia, myalgia jaw stiffness.



 Psychiatric Disorders - appetite increased, concentration impaired, irritability.



 Reproductive Disorders/Female - menstrual cramps, menstrual disorder.



 Respiratory System Disorders - bronchitis, coughing, nasal congestion, sinus congestion, sinus headache.



 Skin and Appendages Disorders - rash.



 Special Senses - vision blurred, tinnitus.



 Urinary System Disorders - urinary frequency, urinary tract infection.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

    Adverse Reactions Reported Subsequent to the Marketing of Escitalopram  



 The following additional adverse reactions have been identified from spontaneous reports of escitalopram received worldwide. These adverse reactions have been chosen for inclusion because of a combination of seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to escitalopram and have not been listed elsewhere in labeling. However, because these adverse reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events include:



 Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders: anemia, agranulocytis, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, idiopathic thrombocytopenia purpura, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia.



 Cardiac Disorders: atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, cardiac failure, myocardial infarction, tachycardia, torsade de pointes, ventricular arrhythmia, ventricular tachycardia.



 Ear and labyrinth disorders: vertigo



 Endocrine Disorders: diabetes mellitus, hyperprolactinemia, SIADH.



 Eye Disorders: angle closure glaucoma, diplopia, mydriasis, visual disturbance.



 Gastrointestinal Disorder: dysphagia, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastroesophageal reflux, pancreatitis, rectal hemorrhage.



 General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions: abnormal gait, asthenia, edema, fall, feeling abnormal, malaise.



 Hepatobiliary Disorders: fulminant hepatitis, hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatitis.



 Immune System Disorders: allergic reaction, anaphylaxis.



 Investigations: bilirubin increased, decreased weight, electrocardiogram QT prolongation, hepatic enzymes increased, hypercholesterolemia, INR increased, prothrombin decreased.



 Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders: hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia.



 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders: muscle cramp, muscle stiffness, muscle weakness, rhabdomyolysis.



 Nervous System Disorders: akathisia, amnesia, ataxia, choreoathetosis, cerebrovascular accident, dysarthria, dyskinesia, dystonia, extrapyramidal disorders, grand mal seizures (or convulsions), hypoaesthesia, myoclonus, nystagmus, Parkinsonism, restless legs, seizures, syncope, tardive dyskinesia, tremor.



 Pregnancy, Puerperium and Perinatal Conditions: spontaneous abortion.



 Psychiatric Disorders: acute psychosis, aggression, agitation, anger, anxiety, apathy, completed suicide, confusion, depersonalization, depression aggravated, delirium, delusion, disorientation, feeling unreal, hallucinations (visual and auditory), mood swings, nervousness, nightmare, panic reaction, paranoia, restlessness, self-harm or thoughts of self-harm, suicide attempt, suicidal ideation, suicidal tendency.



 Renal and Urinary Disorders: acute renal failure, dysuria, urinary retention.



 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders: menorrhagia, priapism.



 Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders: dyspnea, epistaxis, pulmonary embolism, pulmonary hypertension of the newborn.



 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders: alopecia, angioedema, dermatitis, ecchymosis, erythema multiforme, photosensitivity reaction, Stevens Johnson Syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, urticaria.



 Vascular Disorders: deep vein thrombosis, flushing, hypertensive crisis, hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, phlebitis, thrombosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS



  WARNINGS: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS



    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of Lexapro or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber.  Lexapro is not approved for use in pediatric patients less than 12 years of age.     [See Warnings and Precautions: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk (  5.1  ), Patient Counseling Information: Information for Patients (  17.1  ), and Use in Specific Populations: Pediatric Use (  8.4  )].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders.  Lexapro is not approved for use in pediatric patients less than 12 years of age (  5.1  ).  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Clinical Worsening/Suicide Risk: Monitor for clinical worsening, suicidality and unusual change in behavior, especially, during the initial few months of therapy or at times of dose changes (  5.1  ). 
 *  Serotonin Syndrome: Serotonin syndrome has been reported with SSRIs and SNRIs, including Lexapro, both when taken alone, but especially when co-administered with other serotonergic agents (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone and St. John's Wort). If such symptoms occur, discontinue Lexapro and initiate supportive treatment. If concomitant use of Lexapro with other serotonergic drugs is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases (  5.2  ). 
 *  Discontinuation of Treatment with Lexapro: A gradual reduction in dose rather than abrupt cessation is recommended whenever possible (  5.3  ). 
 *  Seizures: Prescribe with care in patients with a history of seizure (  5.4  ). 
 *  Activation of Mania/Hypomania: Use cautiously in patients with a history of mania (  5.5  ). 
 *  Hyponatremia: Can occur in association with SIADH (  5.6  ). 
 *  Abnormal Bleeding: Use caution in concomitant use with NSAIDs, aspirin, warfarin or other drugs that affect coagulation (  5.7  ). 
 *  Interference with Cognitive and Motor Performance: Use caution when operating machinery (  5.8  ). 
 *  Angle Closure Glaucoma: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness: Use caution in patients with diseases or conditions that produce altered metabolism or hemodynamic responses (  5.10  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in   Table 1  .  



 TABLE 1 
  Age Range                           Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated     
                                     Increases Compared to Placebo                                       
 &lt;18                                 14 additional cases                                                 
 18-24                               5 additional cases                                                  
                                     Decreases Compared to Placebo                                       
 25-64                               1 fewer case                                                        
 &gt;=65                                6 fewer cases                                                       
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



 All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



 If the decision has been made to discontinue treatment, medication should be tapered, as rapidly as is feasible, but with recognition that abrupt discontinuation can be associated with certain symptoms [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )  ].



 Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers [ see also Patient Counseling Information (  17.1  )  ]. Prescriptions for Lexapro should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



    Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder  



 A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described above represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It should be noted that Lexapro is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs, including Lexapro, alone but particularly with concomitant use of other serotonergic drugs (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort) and with drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (in particular, MAOIs, both those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue).



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination) seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome.



 The concomitant use of Lexapro with MAOIs intended to treat psychiatric disorders is contraindicated. Lexapro should also not be started in a patient who is being treated with MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue. All reports with methylene blue that provided information on the route of administration involved intravenous administration in the dose range of 1 mg/kg to 8 mg/kg. No reports involved the administration of methylene blue by other routes (such as oral tablets or local tissue injection) or at lower doses. There may be circumstances when it is necessary to initiate treatment with an MAOI such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue in a patient taking Lexapro. Lexapro should be discontinued before initiating treatment with the MAOI [ see Contraindications (  4.1  ) and Dosage and Administration (  2.5  and  2.6  )  ].



 If concomitant use of Lexapro with other serotonergic drugs including, triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, buspirone, tryptophan and St. John's Wort is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases.



 Treatment with Lexapro and any concomitant serotonergic agents, should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Discontinuation of Treatment with Lexapro



  During marketing of Lexapro and other SSRIs and SNRIs (serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors), there have been spontaneous reports of adverse events occurring upon discontinuation of these drugs, particularly when abrupt, including the following: dysphoric mood, irritability, agitation, dizziness, sensory disturbances (e.g., paresthesias such as electric shock sensations), anxiety, confusion, headache, lethargy, emotional lability, insomnia, and hypomania. While these events are generally self-limiting, there have been reports of serious discontinuation symptoms.



 Patients should be monitored for these symptoms when discontinuing treatment with Lexapro. A gradual reduction in the dose rather than abrupt cessation is recommended whenever possible. If intolerable symptoms occur following a decrease in the dose or upon discontinuation of treatment, then resuming the previously prescribed dose may be considered. Subsequently, the physician may continue decreasing the dose but at a more gradual rate [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )  ].



    5.4 Seizures



  Although anticonvulsant effects of racemic citalopram have been observed in animal studies, Lexapro has not been systematically evaluated in patients with a seizure disorder. These patients were excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarketing testing. In clinical trials of Lexapro, cases of convulsion have been reported in association with Lexapro treatment. Like other drugs effective in the treatment of major depressive disorder, Lexapro should be introduced with care in patients with a history of seizure disorder.



    5.5 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



  In placebo-controlled trials of Lexapro in major depressive disorder, activation of mania/hypomania was reported in one (0.1%) of 715 patients treated with Lexapro and in none of the 592 patients treated with placebo. One additional case of hypomania has been reported in association with Lexapro treatment. Activation of mania/hypomania has also been reported in a small proportion of patients with major affective disorders treated with racemic citalopram and other marketed drugs effective in the treatment of major depressive disorder. As with all drugs effective in the treatment of major depressive disorder, Lexapro should be used cautiously in patients with a history of mania.



    5.6 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia may occur as a result of treatment with SSRIs and SNRIs, including Lexapro. In many cases, this hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH), and was reversible when Lexapro was discontinued. Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with SSRIs and SNRIs. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume depleted may be at greater risk [ see Geriatric Use (  8.5    )]. Discontinuation of Lexapro should be considered in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia and appropriate medical intervention should be instituted.



 Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which may lead to falls. Signs and symptoms associated with more severe and/or acute cases have included hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.7 Abnormal Bleeding



  SSRIs and SNRIs, including Lexapro, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, warfarin, and other anticoagulants may add to the risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding events related to SSRIs and SNRIs use have ranged from ecchymoses, hematomas, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages.



 Patients should be cautioned about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of Lexapro and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation.



    5.8 Interference with Cognitive and Motor Performance



  In a study in normal volunteers, Lexapro 10 mg/day did not produce impairment of intellectual function or psychomotor performance. Because any psychoactive drug may impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills, however, patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that Lexapro therapy does not affect their ability to engage in such activities.



       5.9 Angle Closure Glaucoma



     Angle Closure Glaucoma: The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including Lexapro may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.



    5.10 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with Lexapro in patients with certain concomitant systemic illnesses is limited. Caution is advisable in using Lexapro in patients with diseases or conditions that produce altered metabolism or hemodynamic responses.



 Lexapro has not been systematically evaluated in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were generally excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarketing testing.



 In subjects with hepatic impairment, clearance of racemic citalopram was decreased and plasma concentrations were increased. The recommended dose of Lexapro in hepatically impaired patients is 10 mg/day [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )  ].



 Because escitalopram is extensively metabolized, excretion of unchanged drug in urine is a minor route of elimination. Until adequate numbers of patients with severe renal impairment have been evaluated during chronic treatment with Lexapro, however, it should be used with caution in such patients [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
