<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lialda" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reactions seen in Lialda clinical trials or with other products that contain or are metabolized to mesalamine are:



 *  Renal impairment, including renal failure [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ]  
 *  Mesalamine-induced acute intolerance syndrome [See Warnings and Precautions (5.2) ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions [See Warnings and Precautions (5.3) ]  
 *  Hepatic impairment, including hepatic failure [See Warnings and Precautions (5.4) ]  
   *  The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 2%) are ulcerative colitis, headache, flatulence, liver function test abnormality, and abdominal pain. ( 6.1 ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Shire US Inc. at 1-800-828-2088 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 LIALDA has been evaluated in 1368 ulcerative colitis patients in controlled and open-label trials.



   Induction of Remission  



 In two 8-week placebo-controlled clinical trials involving 535 ulcerative colitis patients, 356 received 2.4 g/day or 4.8 g/day LIALDA tablets and 179 received placebo. The most frequent adverse reaction leading to discontinuation from LIALDA therapy was exacerbation of ulcerative colitis (0.8%). Pancreatitis occurred in less than 1% of patients during clinical trials and resulted in discontinuation of therapy with LIALDA in patients experiencing this event.



 Adverse reactions occurring in LIALDA or placebo groups at a frequency of at least 1% in two 8-week, double blind, placebo-controlled trials are listed in Table 1. The most common adverse reactions with LIALDA 2.4 g/day and 4.8 g/day were headache (5.6% and 3.4%, respectively) and flatulence (4% and 2.8%, respectively).



   Table 1: Adverse Reactions in Two Eight-Week Placebo-Controlled Trials Experienced by at Least 1% of the LIALDA Group and at a Rate Greater than Placebo  a    




   AdverseReaction      LIALDA2.4 g/day(n = 177)      LIALDA4.8 g/day(n = 179)      Placebo(n = 179)     
   Headache       10 (5.6%)        6 (3.4%)         1 (0.6%)          
   Flatulence     7 (4%)            5 (2.8%)         5 (2.8%)         
   Liver Function Test Abnormal    1 (0.6%)         4 (2.2%)         2 (1.1%)        
   Alopecia         0                2 (1.1%)         0               
   Pruritus         1 (0.6%)         2 (1.1%)         2 (1.1%)        
   a: Adverse reactions for which the placebo rate equalled or exceeded the rate for at least one of the LIALDA treatment groups were abdominal pain, dizziness, dyspepsia, and nausea.   
          The following adverse reactions, presented by body system, were reported infrequently (less than 1%) by LIALDA-treated ulcerative colitis patients in the two controlled trials.
 

   Cardiac Disorder:  tachycardia



   Vascular Disorders:  hypertension, hypotension



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  acne, prurigo, rash, urticaria



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  abdominal distention, colitis, diarrhea, pancreatitis, rectal polyp, vomiting



   Investigations:  decreased platelet count



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  arthralgia, back pain



   Nervous System Disorders:  somnolence, tremor



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  pharyngolaryngeal pain



   General Disorders and Administrative Site Disorders:  asthenia, face edema, fatigue, pyrexia



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  ear pain



   Maintenance of Remission of Ulcerative Colitis  



 The dose evaluated in three studies of LIALDA given for the maintenance of remission in patients with ulcerative colitis was 1.2 g twice daily or 2.4 g/once daily. One of these studies was a 6-month double-blind comparator study while two were 12- to 14-month open-label studies.



 The most common adverse reactions with LIALDA in the maintenance arms of long-term trials were colitis ulcerative (5.8%), headache (2.9%), liver function test abnormal (2.3%), and abdominal pain (2.2%). Of the 1082 subjects in the all maintenance studies pooled, 1.9% had severe adverse reactions. The most common severe adverse reactions were gastrointestinal disorders; these were mainly symptoms associated with ulcerative colitis.



   Table 2: Adverse Reactions in Three Maintenance Trials Experienced by at Least 1% of the LIALDA Group (maintenance phases of trials)   




                      All LIALDA(n=1082)     
  Adverse Reaction  n                 %                
  Colitis ulcerative    63               (5.8%)          
  Headache          31               (2.9%)          
  Liver function test abnormal       25              (2.3%)          
  Abdominal pain    24               (2.2%)          
  Diarrhea          18               (1.7%)          
  Abdominal distension    14               (1.3%)          
  Abdominal pain upper    13               (1.2%)          
  Dyspepsia         13               (1.2%)          
  Back pain         13               (1.2%)          
  Rash              13               (1.2%)          
  Arthralgia        12               (1.1%)          
  Fatigue           11               (1.0%)          
  Hypertension      10               (1.0%)          
         The following adverse reactions, presented by body system, were reported infrequently (less than 1%) by LIALDA-treated ulcerative colitis patients in the three long-term maintenance trials (maintenance phases of these trials):
 

   Cardiac Disorder:  tachycardia



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  acne, alopecia, pruritis, urticaria



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  colitis, flatulence, nausea, pancreatitis, rectal polyp, vomiting



   Nervous System Disorders:  dizziness



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  pharyngolaryngeal pain



   General Disorders and Administrative Site Disorders:  asthenia, pyrexia



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  ear pain



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to the adverse reactions reported above in clinical trials involving LIALDA, the adverse reactions listed below have been identified during post-approval use of LIALDA and other mesalamine-containing products. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole:  lupus-like syndrome, drug fever



   Cardiac Disorders:  pericarditis, pericardial effusion, myocarditis



   Gastrointestinal:  pancreatitis, cholecystitis, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal bleeding, perforated peptic ulcer



   Hepatic:  jaundice, cholestatic jaundice, hepatitis, liver necrosis, liver failure, Kawasaki-like syndrome including changes in liver enzymes



   Hematologic:  agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia



   Immune System Disorders:  anaphylactic reaction, Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS), drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS)



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:   myalgia



   Neurological/Psychiatric:  peripheral neuropathy, Guillain-Barre syndrome, transverse myelitis



   Renal Disorders:  interstitial nephritis



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  hypersensitivity pneumonitis (including interstitial pneumonitis, allergic alveolitis, eosinophilic pneumonitis)



   Skin:  psoriasis, pyoderma gangrenosum, erythema nodosum



   Urogenital:  reversible oligospermia
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Renal impairment may occur. Assess renal function at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. ( 5.1 ) 
 *  Mesalamine-induced acute intolerance syndrome has been reported. Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment. ( 5.2 ) 
 *  Use caution when treating patients who are hypersensitive to sulfasalazine. ( 5.3 ) 
 *  Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported. ( 5.3 ) 
 *  Hepatic failure has been reported in patients with pre-existing liver disease. Use caution when treating patients with liver disease. ( 5.4 ) 
 *  Upper GI tract obstruction may delay onset of action. ( 5.5 ) 
 *  Use of mesalamine may lead to spuriously elevated test results when measuring urinary normetanephrine by liquid chromatography with electrochemical detection. (5.6) 
    
 

   5.1 Renal Impairment



  Renal impairment, including minimal change nephropathy, acute and chronic interstitial nephritis, and, rarely, renal failure, has been reported in patients given products such as LIALDA that contain mesalamine or are converted to mesalamine.



 It is recommended that patients have an evaluation of renal function prior to initiation of LIALDA therapy and periodically while on therapy. Exercise caution when using LIALDA in patients with known renal dysfunction or a history of renal disease.



 In animal studies, the kidney was the principal organ for toxicity. [See    Drug Interactions (7.1)     and    Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2)     ]  



    5.2 Mesalamine-Induced Acute Intolerance Syndrome



  Mesalamine has been associated with an acute intolerance syndrome that may be difficult to distinguish from an exacerbation of ulcerative colitis. Although the exact frequency of occurrence has not been determined, it has occurred in 3% of patients in controlled clinical trials of mesalamine or sulfasalazine. Symptoms include cramping, acute abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea, and sometimes fever, headache, and rash. Observe patients closely for worsening of these symptoms while on treatment. If acute intolerance syndrome is suspected, promptly discontinue treatment with LIALDA.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Some patients who have experienced a hypersensitivity reaction to sulfasalazine may have a similar reaction to LIALDA tablets or to other compounds that contain or are converted to mesalamine.



 Mesalamine-induced cardiac hypersensitivity reactions (myocarditis and pericarditis) have been reported with LIALDA and other mesalamine medications. Caution should be taken in prescribing this medicine to patients with conditions predisposing them to the development of myocarditis or pericarditis.



    5.4 Hepatic Impairment



  There have been reports of hepatic failure in patients with pre-existing liver disease who have been administered mesalamine. Caution should be exercised when administering LIALDA to patients with liver disease.



    5.5 Upper GI Tract Obstruction



  Pyloric stenosis or other organic or functional obstruction in the upper gastrointestinal tract may cause prolonged gastric retention of LIALDA which would delay mesalamine release in the colon.



    5.6 Interference with Laboratory Tests



   Use of mesalamine may lead to spuriously elevated test results when measuring urinary normetanephrine by liquid chromatography with electrochemical detection because of the similarity in the chromatograms of normetanephrine and mesalamine's main metabolite, N-acetylaminosalicylic acid (N-Ac-5-ASA). An alternative, selective assay for normetanephrine should be considered.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
