<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lipiodol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions caused by Lipiodol include hypersensitivity reactions, pulmonary embolism, pulmonary dysfunction, exacerbation of liver disease, procedural complications, abdominal pain, fever, nausea, vomiting, and thyroid dysfunction.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GUERBET LLC at 1-877-729-6679 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions (Table 1) have been identified during post approval use of Lipiodol. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following adverse reactions are described in more detail in other sections of the prescribing information:Pulmonary and cerebral embolism [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ]Hypersensitivity reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ]Exacerbation of chronic liver disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )  ]



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions in the Postmarketing Experience 
  System Organ Class                                  Adverse Reaction                                    
  Endocrine disorders                                 hypothyroidism, hyperthyroidism, thyroiditis        
  Eye disorders                                       retinal vein thrombosis                             
  Gastrointestinal disorders                          nausea, vomiting, diarrhea                          
  General disorders and administration site conditions    fever, pain, granuloma                              
  Hepatobiliary disorders                             hepatic vein thrombosis                             
  Immune system disorders                             hypersensitivity, anaphylactic reaction, anaphylactoid reaction    
  Nervous system disorders                            cerebral embolism                                   
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     pulmonary embolism, dyspnea, cough, acute respiratory distress syndrome    
  Urinary system disorders                            renal insufficiency                                 
          Hysterosalpingography  
 

 Abdominal pain, foreign body reactions, exacerbation of pelvic inflammatory disease.



   Lymphography  



 Cardiovascular collapse, lymphangitis, thrombophlebitis, edema or exacerbation of preexisting lymphedema, dyspnea and cough, fever, iodism (headache, soreness of mouth and pharynx, coryza and skin rash), allergic dermatitis, lipogranuloma, delayed healing at the site of incision.



     Selective Hepatic Intra-arterial Injection    



   Fever, abdominal pain, nausea, and vomiting are the most common reactions; other reactions include hepatic ischemia, liver enzymes abnormalities, transitory decrease in liver function, liver decompensation and renal insufficiency. Procedural risks include vascular complications and infections.  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

     WARNING: FOR INTRALYMPHATIC, INTRAUTERINE AND SELECTIVE HEPATIC INTRA-ARTERIAL USE ONLY  



   Pulmonary and cerebral embolism can result from inadvertent intravascular injection or intravasation of Lipiodol. Inject Lipiodol slowly with radiologic monitoring; do not exceed recommended dose (  5.1  ).

  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: FOR INTRALYMPHATIC, INTRAUTERINE AND SELECTIVE HEPATIC INTRA-ARTERIAL USE ONLY  See Full Prescribing Information for complete Boxed Warning  

Pulmonary and cerebral embolism can result from inadvertent intravascular injection or intravasation of Lipiodol. Inject Lipiodol slowly with radiologic monitoring; do not exceed recommended dose (  5.1  ).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  Pulmonary and cerebral embolism: avoid use in patients with severely impaired lung function, cardiorespiratory failure or right-sided cardiac overload (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions: avoid use in patients with a history of sensitivity to other iodinated contrast agents, bronchial asthma or allergic disorders because of an increased risk of a hypersensitivity reaction to Lipiodol (  5.2  ) 
 *  Exacerbation of chronic liver disease (  5.3  ) 
 *  Thyroid dysfunction (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Pulmonary and Cerebral Embolism



  Pulmonary embolism may occur immediately or after a few hours to days from inadvertent systemic vascular injection or intravasation of Lipiodol and cause decreased pulmonary diffusing capacity and pulmonary blood flow, pulmonary infarction, acute respiratory distress syndrome and fatalities. Embolization of Lipiodol to brain and other major organs may occur. Avoid use of Lipiodol in patients with severely impaired lung function, cardiorespiratory failure, or right-sided cardiac overload. Perform radiological monitoring during the Lipiodol injection. Do not exceed the recommended maximum dose and rate of injection of Lipiodol. During lymphography to minimize the risk of pulmonary embolism obtain radiographic confirmation of intralymphatic (rather than venous) injection, and terminate the procedure when Lipiodol becomes visible in the thoracic duct or lymphatic obstruction is observed.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Anaphylactoid and anaphylactic reactions with cardiovascular, respiratory or cutaneous manifestations, ranging from mild to severe, including death, have uncommonly occurred following Lipiodol administration. Avoid use in patients with a history of sensitivity to other iodinated contrast agents, bronchial asthma or allergic disorders because of an increased risk of a hypersensitivity reaction to Lipiodol. Administer Lipiodol only in situations where trained personnel and therapies are promptly available for the treatment of hypersensitivity reactions, including personnel trained in resuscitation; ensure continuous medical monitoring and maintain an intravenous access line. Most hypersensitivity reactions to Lipiodol occur within half an hour after administration. Delayed reactions can occur up to several days after administration. Observe patients for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity reactions during and for at least 30 minutes following Lipiodol administration.



    5.3 Exacerbation of Chronic Liver Disease



  Lipiodol hepatic intra-arterial administration can exacerbate the following conditions: portal hypertension and cause variceal bleeds due to obstruction of the intrahepatic portal channels by opening a pre sinusoidal anastomosis; hepatic ischemia and cause liver enzyme elevations, fever and abdominal pain; hepatic failure and cause ascites and encephalopathy. Hepatic vein thrombosis, irreversible liver insufficiency and fatalities have been reported. Procedural risks include vascular complications and infections.



    5.4 Thyroid Dysfunction



  Iodinated contrast media can affect thyroid function because of the free iodine content and can cause hyperthyroidism or hypothyroidism in predisposed patients. Patients at risk are those with latent hyperthyroidism and those with Hashimoto thyroiditis, or history of thyroid irradiation. As Lipiodol may remain in the body for several months, thyroid diagnostic results can be affected for up to two years after lymphography.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
