<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lo1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions with the use of COCs are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Serious cardiovascular events and stroke [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *    Vascular events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *    Liver disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
    Adverse reactions commonly reported by COC users are:
 

 *    Irregular uterine bleeding 
 *    Nausea 
 *    Breast tenderness 
 *    Headache 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) in clinical trials were nausea/vomiting, headache, bleeding irregularities, dysmenorrhea, weight change, breast tenderness, acne, abdominal pain, anxiety and depression (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    Warner Chilcott at 1-800-521-8813    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data presented in Section 6.1 are from a clinical trial conducted with a 28-day regimen consisting of norethindrone acetate 1 mg/ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 24 days followed with ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 2 days and ferrous fumarate tablets for 2 days. Lo Minastrin Fe is bioequivalent to this 28-day regimen.



 A multicenter phase 3 clinical trial evaluated the safety and efficacy of the 28-day regimen for pregnancy prevention. The study was a one year, open-label, single-arm, uncontrolled study. A total of 1,660 women aged 18 to 45 were enrolled and took at least one dose of the 28-day regimen and 1,582 had at least one post-treatment evaluation  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ].  



   Common Adverse Reactions (Greater Than or Equal to 2% of all Treated Subjects)  : The most common adverse reactions reported by at least 2% of the 1,660 women using the 28-day regimen were the following in order of decreasing incidence: nausea/vomiting (7%), headache (7%), bleeding irregularities (including metrorrhagia, irregular menstruation, menorrhagia, vaginal hemorrhage and dysfunctional uterine bleeding) (5%), dysmenorrhea (4%), weight fluctuation (4%), breast tenderness (4%), acne (3%), abdominal pain (3%), anxiety (2%), and depression (2%).



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Study Discontinuation  : 10.7% of the women discontinued from the clinical trial due to an adverse reaction. Adverse reactions occurring in greater than or equal to 1% of subjects leading to discontinuation of treatment were in decreasing order: menstrual irregularities (including metrorrhagia, irregular menstruation, menorrhagia and vaginal hemorrhage) (4%), headache/migraine (1%), mood disorder (including mood swings, depression, anxiety) (1%), and weight fluctuation (1%).



   Serious Adverse Reactions  :     deep vein thrombosis, ovarian vein thrombosis, cholecystitis.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of a 28-day regimen consisting of norethindrone acetate 1 mg/ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 24 days followed with ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 2 days and ferrous fumarate tablets for 2 days. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or evaluate a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions are grouped into System Organ Classes.



 Vascular disorders: thrombosis/embolism (coronary artery, pulmonary, cerebral, deep vein)



 Immune system disorders: hypersensitivity reaction



 Skin and subcutaneous tissues: urticaria, rash, pruritis



 Gastrointestinal disorders: nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain/discomfort, diarrhea



 Nervous system disorders: headache, dizziness, migraine headache



 Psychiatric disorders: mood swings, depression, anxiety



 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders: pulmonary embolism, dyspnea



 Reproductive system and breast disorders: breast enlargement, breast tenderness, dysmenorrhea, hypomenorrhea, menorrhagia, menstrual disorder, irregular menstruation, metrorrhagia
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS

  WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS

    Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive (    COC    ) use. This risk increases with age, particularly in women over 35 years of age, and with the number of cigarettes smoked. For this reason, COCs should not be used by women who are over 35 years of age and smoke   [see   Contraindications (4)  ].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Women over 35 years old who smoke should not use Lo Minastrin Fe (4) 
 *  Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive (COC) use (4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Vascular risks: Stop Lo Minastrin Fe if a thrombotic event occurs. Stop at least 4 weeks before through 2 weeks after major surgery. Start no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery in women who are not breastfeeding (  5.1  ) 
 *    Liver disease: Discontinue if jaundice occurs (  5.2  ) 
 *    High blood pressure: If used in women with well-controlled hypertension, monitor blood pressure and stop Lo Minastrin Fe if blood pressure rises significantly (  5.3  ) 
 *    Carbohydrate and lipid metabolic effects: Monitor prediabetic and diabetic women taking Lo Minastrin Fe. Consider an alternative contraceptive method for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemia (  5.5  ) 
 *    Headache: Evaluate significant change in headaches and discontinue if indicated (  5.6  ) 
 *    Uterine bleeding: Evaluate irregular bleeding or amenorrhea (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thromboembolic Disorders and Other Vascular Problems



  Stop Lo Minastrin Fe if an arterial or deep venous thrombotic event (VTE) occurs. Stop Lo Minastrin Fe if there is unexplained loss of vision, proptosis, diplopia, papilledema, or retinal vascular lesions. Evaluate for retinal vein thrombosis immediately.



 If feasible, stop Lo Minastrin Fe at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery or other surgeries known to have an elevated risk of VTE.



 Start Lo Minastrin Fe no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. The risk of postpartum VTE decreases after the third postpartum week, whereas the risk of ovulation increases after the third postpartum week.



 The use of COCs increases the risk of VTE. However, pregnancy increases the risk of VTE as much or more than the use of COCs. The risk of VTE in women using COCs is 3 to 9 per 10,000 woman-years. The risk of VTE is highest during the first year of use of a COC. The risk of thromboembolic disease due to oral contraceptives gradually disappears after COC use is discontinued.



 Use of COCs also increases the risk of arterial thromboses such as strokes and myocardial infarctions, especially in women with other risk factors for these events. COCs have been shown to increase both the relative and attributable risks of cerebrovascular events (thrombotic and hemorrhagic strokes), although, in general, the risk is greatest in older (greater than 35 years of age), hypertensive women who also smoke. COCs also increase the risk for stroke in women with underlying risk factors.



 Use COCs with caution in women with cardiovascular disease risk factors.



    5.2 Liver Disease



   Impaired Liver Function  



 Do not use Lo Minastrin Fe in women with acute viral hepatitis or severe (decompressed) cirrhosis of the liver [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . Acute or chronic disturbances of liver function may necessitate the discontinuation of COC use until markers of liver function return to normal and COC causation has been excluded. Discontinue Lo Minastrin Fe if jaundice develops.



  Liver Tumors  



 Lo Minastrin Fe is contraindicated in women with benign and malignant liver tumors [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . Hepatic adenomas are associated with COC use. An estimate of the attributable risk is 3.3 cases per 100,000 COC users. Rupture of hepatic adenomas may cause death through intra-abdominal hemorrhage.



 Studies have shown an increased risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in long-term (greater than 8 years) COC users. However, the attributable risk of liver cancers in COC users is less than one case per million users.



    5.3 High Blood Pressure



  Lo Minastrin Fe is contraindicated in women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . For women with well-controlled hypertension, monitor blood pressure and stop Lo Minastrin Fe if blood pressure rises significantly.



 An increase in blood pressure has been reported in women taking COCs, and this increase is more likely in older women with extended duration of use. The incidence of hypertension increases with increasing concentrations of progestin.



    5.4 Gallbladder Disease



  Studies suggest a small increased relative risk of developing gallbladder disease among COC users. Use of COCs may also worsen existing gallbladder disease.



 A past history of COC-related cholestasis predicts an increased risk with subsequent COC use. Women with a history of pregnancy-related cholestasis may be at an increased risk for COC-related cholestasis.



    5.5 Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects



  Carefully monitor prediabetic and diabetic women who are taking Lo Minastrin Fe. COCs may decrease glucose tolerance in a dose-related fashion.



 Consider alternative contraception for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemias. A small proportion of women will have adverse lipid changes while on COCs.



 Women with hypertriglyceridemia, or a family history thereof, may be at an increased risk of pancreatitis when using COCs.



    5.6 Headache



  If a woman taking Lo Minastrin Fe develops new headaches that are recurrent, persistent, or severe, evaluate the cause and discontinue Lo Minastrin Fe if indicated.



 Consider discontinuation of Lo Minastrin Fe in the case of an increased frequency or severity of migraine during COC use (which may be prodromal of a cerebrovascular event) [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.7 Bleeding Irregularities and Amenorrhea



   Unscheduled bleeding and Spotting  



 Unscheduled (breakthrough or intracyclic) bleeding and spotting sometimes occur in patients on COCs, especially during the first three months of use. If bleeding persists or occurs after previously regular cycles, check for causes such as pregnancy or malignancy. If pathology and pregnancy are excluded, bleeding irregularities may resolve over time or with a change to a different COC.



 Based on patient diaries from a clinical trial evaluating the safety and efficacy of a 28-day regimen consisting of norethindrone acetate 1 mg/ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 24 days followed with ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 2 days and ferrous fumarate tablets for 2 days, 36-53% of women experienced unscheduled bleeding per cycle. Among these women, the mean number of days of unscheduled bleeding and/or spotting during a 28-day cycle ranged from 1.8 to 3.2 days. A total of 58 subjects out of 1,582 discontinued the study due to bleeding or spotting.



  Amenorrhea and Oligomenorrhea  



 Women who are not pregnant and use Lo Minastrin Fe may experience amenorrhea. In the clinical trial with a 28-day regimen consisting of norethindrone acetate 1 mg/ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 24 days followed with ethinyl estradiol 10 mcg tablets for 2 days and ferrous fumarate tablets for 2 days, 31-49% of the women experienced amenorrhea in at least one cycle between Cycles 2 to 13.



 Some women may experience post-pill amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea, especially when such a condition was preexistent. If scheduled (withdrawal) bleeding does not occur, consider the possibility of pregnancy. If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed dosing schedule (missed one or more active tablets or started taking them on a day later than she should have), consider the possibility of pregnancy at the time of the first missed period and take appropriate diagnostic measures. If the patient has adhered to the prescribed regimen and misses two consecutive periods, rule out pregnancy.



    5.8 COC Use before or during Early Pregnancy



  Extensive epidemiologic studies have revealed no increased risk of birth defects in women who have used oral contraceptives prior to pregnancy. Studies also do not suggest a teratogenic effect, particularly in so far as cardiac anomalies and limb reduction defects are concerned, when oral contraceptives are taken inadvertently during early pregnancy. Discontinue Lo Minastrin Fe if pregnancy is confirmed.



 Administration of oral contraceptives to induce withdrawal bleeding should not be used as a test for pregnancy [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].  



    5.9 Depression



  Carefully observe women with a history of depression and discontinue Lo Minastrin Fe if depression recurs to a serious degree.



    5.10 Carcinoma of the Breast and Cervix



  Lo Minastrin Fe is contraindicated in women who currently have or have had breast cancer because breast cancer is a hormonally-sensitive tumor [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



 There is substantial evidence that COCs do not increase the incidence of breast cancer. Although some past studies have suggested that COCs might increase the incidence of breast cancer, more recent studies have not confirmed such findings.



 Some studies suggest that COCs are associated with an increase in the risk of cervical cancer or intraepithelial neoplasia. However, there is controversy about the extent to which these findings may be due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors.



    5.11 Effect on Binding Globulins



  The estrogen component of COCs may raise the serum concentrations of thyroxine-binding globulin, sex hormone-binding globulin, and cortisol-binding globulin. The dose of replacement thyroid hormones or cortisol therapy may need to be increased.



    5.12 Monitoring



  A woman who is taking COCs should have a yearly visit with her healthcare provider for a blood pressure check and for other indicated healthcare.



    5.13 Hereditary Angioedema



  In women with hereditary angioedema, exogenous estrogens may induce or exacerbate symptoms of angioedema.



    5.14 Chloasma



  Chloasma may occasionally occur, especially in women with a history of chloasma gravidarum. Women with a tendency to chloasma should avoid exposure to the sun or ultraviolet radiation while taking Lo Minastrin Fe.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
