<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lopid" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In the double-blind controlled phase of the primary prevention component of the Helsinki Heart Study, 2046 patients received LOPID for up to five years. In that study, the following adverse reactions were statistically more frequent in subjects in the LOPID group:




                                                                 LOPID(N = 2046)      PLACEBO(N = 2035)     
                                                               Frequency inpercent of subjects   
  
 Gastrointestinal reactions                                            34.2                  23.8           
   Dyspepsia                                                           19.6                  11.9           
   Abdominal pain                                                       9.8                   5.6           
   Acute appendicitis                                                   1.2                   0.6           
     (histologically confirmed in most cases    where data were available)                                               
 Atrial fibrillation                                                    0.7                   0.1           
 Adverse events reported by more than 1% of subjects, but without a significant difference between groups:   
 Diarrhea                                                               7.2                   6.5           
 Fatigue                                                                3.8                   3.5           
 Nausea/Vomiting                                                        2.5                   2.1           
 Eczema                                                                 1.9                   1.2           
 Rash                                                                   1.7                   1.3           
 Vertigo                                                                1.5                   1.3           
 Constipation                                                           1.4                   1.3           
 Headache                                                               1.2                   1.1           
           Gallbladder surgery  was performed in 0.9% of LOPID and 0.5% of placebo subjects in the primary prevention component, a 64% excess, which is not statistically different from the excess of gallbladder surgery observed in the clofibrate group compared to the placebo group of the WHO study. Gallbladder surgery was also performed more frequently in the LOPID group compared to the placebo group (1.9% versus 0.3%, p=0.07) in the secondary prevention component. A statistically significant increase in appendectomy in the gemfibrozil group was seen also in the secondary prevention component (6 on gemfibrozil versus 0 on placebo, p=0.014).
 

 Nervous system and special senses adverse reactions were more common in the LOPID group. These included hypesthesia, paresthesias, and taste perversion. Other adverse reactions that were more common among LOPID treatment group subjects but where a causal relationship was not established include cataracts, peripheral vascular disease, and intracerebral hemorrhage.



 From other studies it seems probable that LOPID is causally related to the occurrence of MUSCULOSKELETAL SYMPTOMS (see    WARNINGS    ), and to  ABNORMAL LIVER FUNCTION TESTS  and  HEMATOLOGIC CHANGES  (see    PRECAUTIONS    ).



 Reports of viral and bacterial infections (common cold, cough, urinary tract infections) were more common in gemfibrozil treated patients in other controlled clinical trials of 805 patients. Additional adverse reactions that have been reported for gemfibrozil are listed below by system. These are categorized according to whether a causal relationship to treatment with LOPID is probable or not established:




                                    CAUSAL RELATIONSHIPPROBABLE        CAUSAL RELATIONSHIPNOT ESTABLISHED   
  
 General:Cardiac:                                                      weight lossextrasystoles             
 Gastrointestinal:                  cholestatic jaundice               pancreatitishepatomacolitis          
 Central Nervous                                                                                            
   System:                          dizzinesssomnolenceparesthesiaperipheral neuritisdecreased libidodepressionheadache  confusionconvulsionssyncope          
 Eye:                               blurred vision                     retinal edema                        
 Genitourinary:                     impotence                          decreased male fertilityrenal dysfunction   
 Musculoskeletal:                   myopathymyastheniamyalgiapainful extremitiesarthralgiasynovitisrhabdomyolysis (see      WARNINGS    and      Drug Interactions    under       PRECAUTIONS    )                                       
 Clinical                                                                                                   
   Laboratory:                      increased creatine  phosphokinaseincreased bilirubinincreased liver  transaminases  (AST, ALT)increased alkaline  phosphatase  positive antinuclear  antibody       
 Hematopoietic:                     anemialeukopeniabone marrow hypoplasiaeosinophilia  thrombocytopenia                     
 Immunologic:                       angioedemalaryngeal edemaurticaria  anaphylaxisLupus-like syndromevasculitis   
 Integumentary:                     exfoliative dermatitisrashdermatitispruritus  alopeciaphotosensitivity             
           Additional adverse reactions that have been reported include cholecystitis and cholelithiasis (  see    WARNINGS  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
