<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lotemax1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions associated with ophthalmic steroids include elevated intraocular pressure, which may be associated with infrequent optic nerve damage, visual acuity and field defects, posterior subcapsular cataract formation, delayed wound healing and secondary ocular infection from pathogens including herpes simplex, and perforation of the globe where there is thinning of the cornea or sclera.



 The most common adverse drug reactions reported were anterior chamber inflammation (5%), eye pain (2%), and foreign body sensation (2%).



   EXCERPT:    The most common adverse drug reactions were anterior chamber inflammation (5%), eye pain (2%), and foreign body sensation (2%). (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bausch &amp; Lomb at 1-800-323-0000 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Intraocular pressure (IOP) increase - Prolonged use of corticosteroids may result in glaucoma with damage to the optic nerve, defects in visual acuity and fields of vision. If this product is used for 10 days or longer, IOP should be monitored. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Cataracts- Use of corticosteroids may result in posterior subcapsular cataract formation. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Delayed healing-The use of steroids after cataract surgery may delay healing and increase the incidence of bleb formation. In those diseases causing thinning of the cornea or sclera, perforations have been known to occur with the use of topical steroids. The initial prescription and renewal of the medication order should be made by a physician only after examination of the patient with the aid of magnification such as slit lamp biomicroscopy and, where appropriate, fluorescein staining. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Bacterial infections-Prolonged use of corticosteroids may suppress the host response and thus increase the hazard of secondary ocular infection. In acute purulent conditions, steroids may mask infection or enhance existing infection. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Viral infections-Employment of a corticosteroid medication in the treatment of patients with a history of herpes simplex requires great caution. Use of ocular steroids may prolong the course and may exacerbate the severity of many viral infections of the eye (including herpes simplex). (  5.5  ) 
 *    Fungal infections-Fungal infections of the cornea are particularly prone to develop coincidentally with long-term local steroid application. Fungus invasion must be considered in any persistent corneal ulceration where a steroid has been used or is in use. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Intraocular Pressure (IOP) Increase



  Prolonged use of corticosteroids may result in glaucoma with damage to the optic nerve, defects in visual acuity and fields of vision. Steroids should be used with caution in the presence of glaucoma. If this product is used for 10 days or longer, intraocular pressure should be monitored.



    5.2 Cataracts



  Use of corticosteroids may result in posterior subcapsular cataract formation .  



    5.3 Delayed Healing



  The use of steroids after cataract surgery may delay healing and increase the incidence of bleb formation. In those diseases causing thinning of the cornea or sclera, perforations have been known to occur with the use of topical steroids. The initial prescription and renewal of the medication order should be made by a physician only after examination of the patient with the aid of magnification such as slit lamp biomicroscopy and, where appropriate, fluorescein staining.



    5.4 Bacterial Infections



  Prolonged use of corticosteroids may suppress the host response and thus increase the hazard of secondary ocular infections. In acute purulent conditions of the eye, steroids may mask infection or enhance existing infection.



    5.5 Viral Infections



  Employment of a corticosteroid medication in the treatment of patients with a history of herpes simplex requires great caution. Use of ocular steroids may prolong the course and may exacerbate the severity of many viral infections of the eye (including herpes simplex).



    5.6 Fungal Infections



  Fungal infections of the cornea are particularly prone to develop coincidentally with long-term local steroid application. Fungus invasion must be considered in any persistent corneal ulceration where a steroid has been used or is in use. Fungal cultures should be taken when appropriate.



    5.7 Contact Lens Wear



  Patients should not wear contact lenses during their course of therapy with LOTEMAX.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
