<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lotronex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described in more detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Complications of constipation [see  Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Ischemic colitis [see  Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;2% and &gt;placebo) in clinical studies were constipation, abdominal discomfort and pain, nausea, and gastrointestinal discomfort and pain. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sebela at 1-844-732-3521 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Patients With Irritable Bowel Syndrome:    Table 1  summarizes adverse reactions from 22 repeat-dose studies in patients with IBS who were treated with 1 mg of LOTRONEX twice daily for 8 to 24 weeks. The adverse reactions in Table 1 were reported in 1% or more of patients who received LOTRONEX and occurred more frequently on LOTRONEX than on placebo. A statistically significant difference was observed for constipation in patients treated with LOTRONEX compared to placebo (p&lt;0.0001).



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Patients With Irritable Bowel Syndrome and More Frequently on LOTRONEX 1 mg Twice Daily Than Placebo 
                                                       LOTRONEX                    
 Body System                Placebo                    1 mg twice daily            
 Adverse Reaction           (n = 2,363)                (n = 8,328)                 
 Gastrointestinal                                                                  
 Constipation               6%                         29%                         
 Abdominal discomfort and pain  4%                         7%                          
 Nausea                     5%                         6%                          
 Gastrointestinal discomfort and pain  3%                         5%                          
 Abdominal distention       1%                         2%                          
 Regurgitation and reflux   2%                         2%                          
 Hemorrhoids                1%                         2%                          
      
 

     Gastrointestinal:  Constipation is a frequent and dose-related side effect of treatment with LOTRONEX  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  . In clinical studies constipation was reported in approximately 29% of patients with IBS treated with LOTRONEX 1 mg twice daily (n = 9,316). This effect was statistically significant compared to placebo (p&lt;0.0001). Eleven percent (11%) of patients treated with LOTRONEX 1 mg twice daily withdrew from the studies due to constipation. Although the number of patients with IBS treated with LOTRONEX 0.5 mg twice daily is relatively small (n = 243), only 11% of those patients reported constipation and 4% withdrew from clinical studies due to constipation. Among the patients treated with LOTRONEX 1 mg twice daily who reported constipation, 75% reported a single episode and most reports of constipation (70%) occurred during the first month of treatment, with the median time to first report of constipation onset of 8 days. Occurrences of constipation in clinical trials were generally mild to moderate in intensity, transient in nature, and resolved either spontaneously with continued treatment or with an interruption of treatment. However, serious complications of constipation have been reported in clinical studies and in postmarketing experience  [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  . In Studies 1 and 2, 9% of patients treated with LOTRONEX reported constipation and 4 consecutive days with no bowel movement  [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  . Following interruption of treatment, 78% of the affected patients resumed bowel movements within a 2-day period and were able to re-initiate treatment with LOTRONEX.



     Hepatic  : A similar incidence in elevation of ALT (&gt;2-fold) was seen in patients receiving LOTRONEX or placebo (1.0% vs. 1.2%). A single case of hepatitis (elevated ALT, AST, alkaline phosphatase, and bilirubin) without jaundice in a patient receiving LOTRONEX was reported in a 12-week study. A causal association with LOTRONEX has not been established.



     Long-Term Safety  : Patient experience in controlled clinical trials is insufficient to estimate the incidence of ischemic colitis in patients taking LOTRONEX for longer than 6 months.



     Women With Severe Diarrhea-Predominant Irritable Bowel Syndrome:    Table 2  summarizes the gastrointestinal adverse reactions from 1 repeat-dose study in female patients with severe diarrhea-predominant IBS who were treated for 12 weeks. The adverse reactions in Table 2 were reported in 3% or more of patients who received LOTRONEX and occurred more frequently with LOTRONEX than with placebo. Other events reported in 3% or more of patients who received LOTRONEX and occurring more frequently with LOTRONEX than with placebo included upper respiratory tract infection, viral gastroenteritis, muscle spasms, headaches, and fatigue.



 Table 2. Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=3% of Women With Severe Diarrhea-Predominant Irritable Bowel Syndrome and More Frequently on LOTRONEX Than Placebo. 
                                                       LOTRONEX                   LOTRONEX                   LOTRONEX                    
 Adverse Reaction           Placebo                    0.5 mg once daily          1 mg once daily            1 mg twice daily            
                            (n = 176)                  (n = 175)                  (n = 172)                  (n = 176)                   
 Constipation               5%                         9%                         16%                        19%                         
 Abdominal pain             3%                         5%                         6%                         7%                          
 Diarrhea                   2%                         3%                         2%                         2%                          
 Hemorrhoidalhemorrhage     2%                         3%                         2%                         2%                          
 Flatulance                 2%                         2%                         1%                         3%                          
 Hemorrhoids                2%                         1%                         1%                         3%                          
 Abdominal painupper        1%                         3%                         1%                         1%                          
      Adverse reactions reported in another study of 701 women with severe diarrhea-predominant IBS were similar to those shown in  Table 2  . Gastrointestinal adverse reactions reported in 3% or more of patients who received LOTRONEX and occurring more frequently with LOTRONEX than with placebo included constipation (14% and 10% of patients taking LOTRONEX 1 mg twice daily or 0.5 mg as needed, respectively, compared with 2% taking placebo), abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, and flatulence. Other events reported in 3% or more of patients who received LOTRONEX and occurring more frequently with LOTRONEX than with placebo included nasopharyngitis, sinusitis, upper respiratory tract infection, urinary tract infection, viral gastroenteritis, and cough.
 

     Constipation:  Constipation was the most frequent adverse reaction among women with severe diarrhea-predominant IBS represented in  Table 2  . There was a dose response in the groups treated with LOTRONEX in the number of patients withdrawn due to constipation (2% on placebo, 5% on 0.5 mg once daily, 8% on 1 mg once daily, and 11% on 1 mg twice daily). Among these patients with severe diarrhea-predominant IBS treated with LOTRONEX who reported constipation most (75%) reported one episode which occurred within the first 15 days of treatment and persisted for 4 to 5 days.



     Other Events Observed During Clinical Evaluation of LOTRONEX:  During its assessment in clinical trials, multiple and single doses of LOTRONEX were administered, resulting in 11,874 subject exposures in 86 completed clinical studies. The conditions, dosages, and duration of exposure to LOTRONEX varied between trials, and the studies included healthy male and female volunteers as well as male and female patients with IBS and other indications.



 In the listing that follows, reported adverse reactions were classified using a standardized coding dictionary. Only those events that an investigator believed were possibly related to LOTRONEX, occurred in at least 2 patients, and occurred at a greater frequency during treatment with LOTRONEX than during placebo administration are presented. Serious adverse reactions occurring in at least 1 patient for whom an investigator believed there was reasonable possibility that the event was related to treatment with LOTRONEX and occurring at a greater frequency in patients treated with LOTRONEX than placebo-treated patients are also presented.



 In the following listing, events are categorized by body system. Within each body system, events are presented in descending order of frequency. The following definitions are used:  infrequent  adverse reactions are those occurring on one or more occasion in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients;  rare  adverse reactions are those occurring on one or more occasion in fewer than 1/1,000 patients.



 Although the events reported occurred during treatment with LOTRONEX, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 *   Blood and Lymphatic: Rare: Quantitative red cell or hemoglobin defects, and hemorrhage. 
 *   Cardiovascular: Infrequent: Tachyarrhythmias. Rare: Arrhythmias, increased blood pressure, and extrasystoles. 
 *   Drug Interaction, Overdose, and Trauma: Rare: Contusions and hematomas. 
 *   Ear, Nose, and Throat: Rare: Ear, nose, and throat infections; viral ear, nose, and throat infections; and laryngitis. 
 *   Endocrine and Metabolic: Rare: Disorders of calcium and phosphate metabolism, hyperglycemia, hypothalamus/pituitary hypofunction, hypoglycemia, and fluid disturbances. 
 *   Eye: Rare: Light sensitivity of eyes. 
 *   Gastrointestinal: Infrequent: Hyposalivation, dyspeptic symptoms, gastrointestinal spasms, ischemic colitis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )] , and gastrointestinal lesions. Rare: Abnormal tenderness, colitis, gastrointestinal signs and symptoms, proctitis, diverticulitis, positive fecal occult blood, hyperacidity, decreased gastrointestinal motility and ileus, gastrointestinal obstructions, oral symptoms, gastrointestinal intussusception, gastritis, gastroduodenitis, gastroenteritis, and ulcerative colitis. 
 *   Hepatobiliary Tract and Pancreas: Rare: Abnormal bilirubin levels and cholecystitis. 
 *   Lower Respiratory: Infrequent: Breathing disorders. 
 *   Musculoskeletal: Rare: Muscle pain; muscle stiffness, tightness and rigidity; and bone and skeletal pain. 
 *   Neurological: Infrequent: Hypnagogic effects. Rare: Memory effects, tremors, dreams, cognitive function disorders, disturbances of sense of taste, disorders of equilibrium, confusion, sedation, and hypoesthesia. 
 *   Non-Site Specific: Infrequent: Malaise and fatigue, cramps, pain, temperature regulation disturbances. Rare: Burning sensations, hot and cold sensations, cold sensations, and fungal infections. 
 *   Psychiatry: Infrequent: Anxiety. Rare: Depressive moods. 
 *   Reproduction: Rare: Sexual function disorders, female reproductive tract bleeding and hemorrhage, reproductive infections, and fungal reproductive infections. 
 *   Skin: Infrequent: Sweating and urticaria. Rare: Hair loss and alopecia; acne and folliculitis; disorders of sweat and sebum; allergic skin reaction; eczema; skin infections; dermatitis and dermatosis; and nail disorders. 
 *   Urology: Infrequent: Urinary frequency. Rare: Bladder inflammation; polyuria and diuresis; and urinary tract hemorrhage. 
      6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   In addition to events reported in clinical trials, the following events have been identified during use of LOTRONEX in clinical practice. Because they were reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to LOTRONEX.



 *   Gastrointestinal: Impaction, perforation, ulceration, small bowel mesenteric ischemia. 
 *   Neurological: Headache. 
 *   Skin: Rash. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SERIOUS GASTROINTESTINAL ADVERSE REACTIONS

  WARNING: SERIOUS GASTROINTESTINAL ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Infrequent but serious gastrointestinal adverse reactions have been reported with the use of LOTRONEX. These events, including ischemic colitis and serious complications of constipation, have resulted in hospitalization, and rarely, blood transfusion, surgery, and death.  



 *  LOTRONEX is indicated only for women with severe diarrhea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) who have not responded adequately to conventional therapy [see Indications and Usage ( 1)] . 
 *  LOTRONEX should be discontinued immediately in patients who develop constipation or symptoms of ischemic colitis. Patients should immediately report constipation or symptoms of ischemic colitis to their prescriber. LOTRONEX should not be resumed in patients who develop ischemic colitis. Patients who have constipation should immediately contact their prescriber if the constipation does not resolve after LOTRONEX is discontinued. Patients with resolved constipation should resume LOTRONEX only on the advice of their treating prescriber [see Dosage and Administration ( 2.1), Warnings and Precautions ( 5.1), ( 5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: SERIOUS GASTROINTESTINAL ADVERSE REACTIONS
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



   Infrequent but serious gastrointestinal adverse reactions have been reported with the use of LOTRONEX. These events, including ischemic colitis and serious complications of constipation, have resulted in hospitalization and, rarely, blood transfusion, surgery, and death.  



 *  LOTRONEX is indicated only for women with severe diarrhea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) who have not responded adequately to conventional therapy. ( 1) 
 *  Discontinue LOTRONEX immediately in patients who develop constipation or symptoms of ischemic colitis. Do not resume LOTRONEX in patients who develop ischemic colitis. ( 2.1, 5.1, 5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious Complications of Constipation: May occur in some patients without warning. Includes obstruction, ileus, impaction, toxic megacolon, and secondary bowel ischemia and in rare cases perforation and death have been reported. Risk is increased in patients who are elderly, debilitated, or taking medications that decrease bowel motility. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Discontinue LOTRONEX immediately if constipation occurs. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Ischemic colitis: May occur in some patients without warning. Promptly evaluate patients with signs of ischemic colitis (e.g., rectal bleeding, bloody diarrhea, new or worsening abdominal pain). (  5.2  ) 
 *  Discontinue LOTRONEX immediately if signs of ischemic colitis occur, such as rectal bleeding, bloody diarrhea, or new or worsening abdominal pain. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Complications of Constipation



   Some patients have experienced serious complications of constipation without warning.  



 Serious complications of constipation, including obstruction, ileus, impaction, toxic megacolon, and secondary bowel ischemia, have been reported with use of LOTRONEX during clinical trials. Complications of constipation have been reported with use of 1 mg twice daily and with lower doses. A dose response relationship has not been established for serious complications of constipation. The incidence of serious complications of constipation was approximately 0.1% (1 per 1,000 patients) in women receiving either LOTRONEX or placebo.  In addition, rare cases of perforation and death have been reported from postmarketing clinical practice. In some cases, complications of constipation required intestinal surgery, including colectomy. Patients who are elderly, debilitated, or taking additional medications that decrease gastrointestinal motility may be at greater risk for complications of constipation.



 LOTRONEX should be discontinued immediately in patients who develop constipation [see  Boxed Warning  ].  



    5.2 Ischemic Colitis



   Some patients have experienced ischemic colitis without warning.  



 Ischemic colitis has been reported in patients receiving LOTRONEX in clinical trials as well as during marketed use of the drug. In IBS clinical trials, the cumulative incidence of ischemic colitis in women receiving LOTRONEX was 0.2% (2 per 1,000 patients, 95% confidence interval 1 to 3) through 3 months and was 0.3% (3 per 1,000 patients, 95% confidence interval 1 to 4) through 6 months.  Ischemic colitis has been reported with use of 1 mg twice daily and with lower doses. A dose-response relationship has not been established. Ischemic colitis was reported in one patient receiving placebo. The patient experience in controlled clinical trials is insufficient to estimate the incidence of ischemic colitis in patients taking LOTRONEX for longer than 6 months.



 LOTRONEX should be discontinued immediately in patients with signs of ischemic colitis such as rectal bleeding, bloody diarrhea, or new or worsening abdominal pain. Because ischemic colitis can be life-threatening, patients with signs or symptoms of ischemic colitis should be evaluated promptly and have appropriate diagnostic testing performed. Treatment with LOTRONEX should not be resumed in patients who develop ischemic colitis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
