<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lovaza" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;3% and greater than placebo) were eructation, dyspepsia, and taste perversion. (6)



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reactions reported in at least 3% and at a greater rate than placebo for patients treated with LOVAZA based on pooled data across 23 clinical studies are listed in Table 1.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring at Incidence &gt;=3% and Greater than Placebo in Clinical Studies of LOVAZA 
  BODY SYSTEM  Adverse Reaction*                  LOVAZA  (N = 655)    Placebo  (N = 370)    
  n                                               %              n              %            
    Eructation                                    29             4              5            1                
    Dyspepsia                                     22             3              6            2                
    Taste perversion                              27             4              1            &lt;1               
             *    Studies included subjects with HTG and severe HTG.
 

 Additional adverse reactions from clinical studies are listed below:



   Digestive System:  Constipation, gastrointestinal disorder and vomiting.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  Increased ALT and increased AST.



   Skin:  Pruritus and rash.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the events described below have been identified during post-approval use of LOVAZA. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or to always establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following events have been reported: anaphylactic reaction, hemorrhagic diathesis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  In patients with hepatic impairment, monitor ALT and AST levels periodically during therapy. (5.1) 
 *  LOVAZA may increase levels of LDL. Monitor LDL levels periodically during therapy. (5.1) 
 *  Use with caution in patients with known hypersensitivity to fish and/or shellfish. (5.2) 
 *  There is a possible association between LOVAZA and more frequent recurrences of symptomatic atrial fibrillation or flutter in patients with paroxysmal or persistent atrial fibrillation, particularly within the first months of initiating therapy. (5.3) 
    
 

   5.1 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  In patients with hepatic impairment, alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) levels should be monitored periodically during therapy with LOVAZA. In some patients, increases in ALT levels without a concurrent increase in AST levels were observed.



 In some patients, LOVAZA increases LDL-C levels. LDL-C levels should be monitored periodically during therapy with LOVAZA.



 Laboratory studies should be performed periodically to measure the patient's TG levels during therapy with LOVAZA.



    5.2 Fish Allergy



  LOVAZA contains ethyl esters of omega-3 fatty acids (EPA and DHA) obtained from the oil of several fish sources. It is not known whether patients with allergies to fish and/or shellfish, are at increased risk of an allergic reaction to LOVAZA. LOVAZA should be used with caution in patients with known hypersensitivity to fish and/or shellfish.



     5.3 Recurrent   Atrial   Fibrillation (AF) or Flutter  



   In a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of 663 patients with symptomatic paroxysmal AF (n=542) or persistent AF (n=121), recurrent AF or flutter was observed in patients randomized to LOVAZA who received 8 grams/day for 7 days and 4 grams/day thereafter for 23 weeks at a higher rate relative to placebo. Patients in this trial had median baseline triglycerides of 127 mg/   dL   , had no substantial structural heart disease, were taking no anti-arrhythmic therapy (rate control permitted), and were in normal sinus rhythm at baseline.  



  At 24 weeks, in the paroxysmal AF stratum, there were 129 (47%) first recurrent symptomatic AF or flutter events on placebo and 141 (53%) on LOVAZA [primary endpoint, HR 1.19; 95% CI 0.93, 1.35]. In the persistent AF stratum, there were 19 (35%) events on placebo and 34 (52%) events on LOVAZA [HR 1.63; 95% CI 0.91, 2.18]. For both strata combined, the HR was 1.25; 95% CI 1.00, 1.40. Although the clinical significance of these results is uncertain, there is a possible association between LOVAZA and more frequent recurrences of symptomatic   atrial   fibrillation or flutter in patients with paroxysmal or persistent   atrial   fibrillation, particularly within the first 2 to 3 months of initiating therapy.  



  LOVAZA is not indicated for the treatment of AF or flutter.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
