<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lumigan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reaction (range 25% - 45%) is conjunctival hyperemia. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Allergan at 1-800-433-8871 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical studies with bimatoprost ophthalmic solutions (0.01% or 0.03%) the most common adverse event was conjunctival hyperemia (range 25% - 45%). Approximately 0.5% to 3% of patients discontinued therapy due to conjunctival hyperemia with 0.01% or 0.03% bimatoprost ophthalmic solutions. Other common events (&gt;10%) included growth of eyelashes, and ocular pruritus.



 Additional ocular adverse events (reported in 1 to 10% of patients) with bimatoprost ophthalmic solutions included ocular dryness, visual disturbance, ocular burning, foreign body sensation, eye pain, pigmentation of the periocular skin, blepharitis, cataract, superficial punctate keratitis, eyelid erythema, ocular irritation, eyelash darkening, eye discharge, tearing, photophobia, allergic conjunctivitis, asthenopia, increases in iris pigmentation, conjunctival edema, conjunctival hemorrhage, and abnormal hair growth. Intraocular inflammation, reported as iritis was reported in less than 1% of patients.



 Systemic adverse events reported in approximately 10% of patients with bimatoprost ophthalmic solutions were infections (primarily colds and upper respiratory tract infections). Other systemic adverse events (reported in 1 to 5% of patients) included headaches, abnormal liver function tests, and asthenia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  *     Pigmentation of the iris, periorbital tissue (eyelid) and eyelashes can occur. Iris pigmentation is likely to be permanent (  5.1  ). 
   Pigmentation. 
 *  *     Gradual change to eyelashes including increased length, thickness and number of lashes. Usually reversible. (  5.2  ) 
   Eyelash Changes. 
    
 

   5.1 Pigmentation



  Bimatoprost ophthalmic solution has been reported to cause changes to pigmented tissues. The most frequently reported changes have been increased pigmentation of the iris, periorbital tissue (eyelid) and eyelashes. Pigmentation is expected to increase as long as bimatoprost is administered. The pigmentation change is due to increased melanin content in the melanocytes rather than to an increase in the number of melanocytes. After discontinuation of bimatoprost, pigmentation of the iris is likely to be permanent, while pigmentation of the periorbital tissue and eyelash changes have been reported to be reversible in some patients. Patients who receive treatment should be informed of the possibility of increased pigmentation. The long term effects of increased pigmentation are not known.



 Iris color change may not be noticeable for several months to years. Typically, the brown pigmentation around the pupil spreads concentrically towards the periphery of the iris and the entire iris or parts of the iris become more brownish. Neither nevi nor freckles of the iris appear to be affected by treatment. While treatment with LUMIGAN    (r)  0.01% and 0.03% (bimatoprost ophthalmic solution) can be continued in patients who develop noticeably increased iris pigmentation, these patients should be examined regularly. (see PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION,  17.1  ).



    5.2 Eyelash Changes



   LUMIGAN    (r)  0.01% and 0.03% may gradually change eyelashes and vellus hair in the treated eye. These changes include increased length, thickness, and number of lashes. Eyelash changes are usually reversible upon discontinuation of treatment.



    5.3 Intraocular Inflammation



   LUMIGAN    (r)  0.01% and 0.03% should be used with caution in patients with active intraocular inflammation (e.g., uveitis) because the inflammation may be exacerbated.



    5.4 Macular Edema



  Macular edema, including cystoid macular edema, has been reported during treatment with bimatoprost ophthalmic solution. LUMIGAN    (r)  0.01% and 0.03% should be used with caution in aphakic patients, in pseudophakic patients with a torn posterior lens capsule, or in patients with known risk factors for macular edema.



    5.5 Angle-closure, Inflammatory, or Neovascular Glaucoma



   LUMIGAN    (r)  0.01% and 0.03% has not been evaluated for the treatment of angle-closure, inflammatory or neovascular glaucoma.



    5.6 Bacterial Keratitis



  There have been reports of bacterial keratitis associated with the use of multiple-dose containers of topical ophthalmic products. These containers had been inadvertently contaminated by patients who, in most cases, had a concurrent corneal disease or a disruption of the ocular epithelial surface (see PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION,  17.3  ).



    5.7 Use with Contact Lenses



  Contact lenses should be removed prior to instillation of LUMIGAN    (r)  0.01% and 0.03% and may be reinserted 15 minutes following its administration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
