<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lupaneta" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:     Leuprolide acetate for depot suspension  : Most common related adverse reactions (&gt;10%) were hot flashes/sweats, headache/migraine, depression/emotional lability, nausea/vomiting, nervousness/anxiety, insomnia, pain, acne, asthenia, vaginitis, weight gain, constipation/diarrhea  (6.1)  



   Progestins  : breakthrough bleeding, spotting  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AbbVie Inc. at 1-800-633-9110 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of co-administering leuprolide acetate for depot suspension and norethindrone acetate was evaluated in two clinical studies in which a total of 242 women were treated for up to one year. Women were treated with monthly IM injections of leuprolide acetate 3.75 mg (13 injections) alone or monthly IM injections of leuprolide acetate 3.75 mg (13 injections) and 5 mg norethindrone acetate daily. The population age range was 17-43 years old. The majority of patients were Caucasian (87%).



 One study was a controlled clinical trial in which 106 women were randomized to one year of treatment with leuprolide acetate for depot suspension alone or with leuprolide acetate for depot suspension and norethindrone acetate. The other study was an open-label single arm clinical study in 136 women of one year of treatment with leuprolide acetate for depot suspension and norethindrone acetate, with follow-up for up to 12 months after completing treatment.



   Adverse Reactions (&gt;1%) Leading to Study Discontinuation  :



 In the controlled study, 18% of patients treated monthly with leuprolide acetate and 18% of patients treated monthly with leuprolide acetate plus norethindrone acetate discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions, most commonly hot flashes (6%) and insomnia (4%) in the leuprolide acetate alone group and hot flashes and emotional lability (4% each) in the leuprolide acetate and norethindrone group.



 In the open label study, 13% of patients treated monthly with leuprolide acetate plus norethindrone acetate discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions, most commonly depression (4%) and acne (2%).



   Common Adverse Reactions:  



 Table 1 lists the adverse reactions observed in at least 5% of patients in any treatment group, during the first 6 months of treatment in the add-back clinical studies, in which patients were treated with monthly leuprolide acetate for depot suspension 3.75 mg with or without norethindrone acetate co-treatment. The most frequently-occurring adverse reactions observed in these studies were hot flashes and headaches.




 * LA-Only = leuprolide acetate 3.75 mg LA/N = leuprolide acetate 3.75 mg plus norethindrone acetate 5 mg   
  
   Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in the First Six Months of Treatment in &gt;= 5% of Patients with Endometriosis     
                    Controlled Study      Open Label Study     
   LA-Only*         LA/N             LA/N            
   N=51             N=55             N=136           
   Adverse Reactions      N                %                N                %                N                %               
   Any Adverse Reaction    50               98               53               96               126              93                
   Body as a Whole     
                  Asthenia                          18                                18                                11                
                  Headache/Migraine  65               51               46                
                  Injection Site Reaction  2                9                3                 
                  Pain             24               29               21                
   Cardiovascular System     
                  Hot flashes/Sweats                   98                                87                                57                
   Digestive System     
                  Altered Bowel Function (constipation, diarrhea)                   14                                15                                10                
                  Changes in Appetite  4                0                6                 
                  GI Disturbance (dyspepsia, flatulence)  4                7                4                 
                  Nausea/Vomiting  25               29               13                
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders     
                  Edema                             0                                 9                                 7                 
                  Weight Gain      12               13               4                 
   Nervous System     
                  Depression/Emotional Lability                   31                                27                                34                
                  Dizziness/Vertigo  16               11               7                 
                  Insomnia/Sleep Disorder  31               13               15                
                  Decreased Libido  10               4                7                 
                  Memory Disorder  6                2                4                 
                  Nervousness/Anxiety  8                4                11                
                  Neuromuscular Disorder (leg cramps, paresthesia)  2                9                3                 
   Skin and Appendages     
                  Androgen-Like Effects (acne, alopecia)                   4                                 5                                 18                
                  Skin/Mucous Membrane Reaction  4                9                11                
   Urogenital System     
                  Breast Changes/Pain/Tenderness                   6                                 13                                8                 
                  Menstrual Disorders  2                0                5                 
                  Vaginitis        20               15               8                 
      In the controlled clinical trial, 50 of 51 (98%) patients in the leuprolide acetate alone group and 48 of 55 (87%) patients in the leuprolide acetate and norethindrone group reported experiencing hot flashes on one or more occasions during treatment. Table 2 presents hot flash data in the sixth month of treatment.
 


 * LA-Only = leuprolide acetate 3.75 mg LA/N = leuprolide acetate 3.75 mg plus norethindrone acetate 5 mg  1  Statistically significantly less than the LA-Only group (p&lt;0.01)  2  Number of patients assessed.   
  
   Table 2. Hot Flashes in the Month Prior to the Assessment Visit (Controlled Study)     
   Assessment Visit      Treatment Group      Number of Patients Reporting Hot Flashes      Number of Days with Hot Flashes      Maximum Number Hot Flashes in 24 Hours     
                  N                (%)              N  2             Mean             N  2             Mean              
 Week 24          LA-Only*         32/37            86               37               19               36               5.8               
                  LA/N             22/38            58  1            38               7  1             38               1.9  1            
        Serious Adverse Reactions  :
 

 Urinary tract infection, renal calculus, depression



   Changes in Laboratory Values during Treatment  :



   Liver Enzymes  



 In the two clinical trials of women with endometriosis, 4 of 191 patients receiving leuprolide acetate and norethindrone acetate for up to 12 months developed an elevated (at least twice the upper limit of normal) SGPT and 2 of 136 developed an elevated GGT. Five of the 6 increases were observed beyond 6 months of treatment. None was associated with an elevated bilirubin concentration.



   Lipids  



 Percent changes from baseline for serum lipids and percentages of patients with serum lipid values outside of the normal range in the two studies of leuprolide acetate and norethindrone acetate are summarized in the tables below. The major impact of adding norethindrone acetate to treatment with leuprolide acetate for depot suspension was a decrease in serum HDL cholesterol and an increase in the LDL/HDL ratio.




 * mg/dL ratio     
  
   Table 3. Serum Lipids: Mean Percent Changes from Baseline Values at Treatment Week 24     
                    leuprolide acetate 3.75 mg      leuprolide acetate for depot suspension 3.75 mg plusnorethindrone acetate 5 mg daily     
   Controlled Study(n=39)      Controlled Study(n=41)      Open Label Study(n=117)     
   BaselineValue*      Wk 24% Change      BaselineValue*      Wk 24% Change      BaselineValue*      Wk 24% Change     
 Total Cholesterol  170.5            9.2%             179.3            0.2%             181.2            2.8%              
 HDL Cholesterol  52.4             7.4%             51.8             -18.8%           51.0             -14.6%            
 LDL Cholesterol  96.6             10.9%            101.5            14.1%            109.1            13.1%             
 LDL/HDL Ratio    2.0              5.0%             2.1              43.4%            2.3              39.4%             
 Triglycerides    107.8            17.5%            130.2            9.5%             105.4            13.8%             
      Changes from baseline tended to be greater at Week 52. After treatment, mean serum lipid levels from patients with follow up data (105 of 158 patients) returned to pretreatment values.
 


 * Includes all patients regardless of baseline value.   
  
   Table 4. Percent of Patients with Serum Lipid Values Outside of the Normal Range     
                    leuprolide acetate for depot suspension 3.75 mgplus norethindrone acetate 5 mg daily     
   Controlled Study(n=41)      Open Label Study(n=117)     
 Baseline         Wk 24*           Baseline         Wk 24*            
 Total Cholesterol (&gt;240 mg/dL)  15%              20%              6%               7%                
 HDL Cholesterol (&lt;40 mg/dL)  15%              44%              15%              41%               
 LDL Cholesterol (&gt;160 mg/dL)  5%               7%               9%               11%               
 LDL/HDL Ratio (&gt;4.0)  2%               15%              7%               21%               
 Triglycerides (&gt;200 mg/dL)  12%              10%              5%               9%                
        6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of leuprolide acetate for depot suspension or norethindrone acetate. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Leuprolide Acetate for Depot Suspension  



 During postmarketing surveillance with other dosage forms and in the same or different populations, the following adverse reactions were reported:



 *  Allergic reactions (anaphylactic, rash, urticaria, and photosensitivity reactions) 
 *  Mood swings, including depression 
 *  Suicidal ideation and attempt 
 *  Symptoms consistent with an anaphylactoid or asthmatic process 
 *  Localized reactions including induration and abscess at the site of injection 
 *  Symptoms consistent with fibromyalgia (e.g., joint and muscle pain, headaches, sleep disorders, gastrointestinal distress, and shortness of breath), individually and collectively 
      Other adverse reactions reported are:  
 

   Hepato-biliary disorder  - Serious liver injury



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications  - Spinal fracture



   Investigations  - Decreased white blood count



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorder  - Tenosynovitis-like symptoms



   Nervous System disorder  - Convulsion, peripheral neuropathy, paralysis



   Vascular disorder  - Hypotension, Hypertension



 Serious venous and arterial thrombotic and thromboembolic events, including deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, myocardial infarction, stroke, and transient ischemic attack



   Pituitary apoplexy  



 During post-marketing surveillance, cases of pituitary apoplexy (a clinical syndrome secondary to infarction of the pituitary gland) have been reported after the administration of leuprolide acetate and other GnRH agonists. In a majority of these cases, a pituitary adenoma was diagnosed, with a majority of pituitary apoplexy cases occurring within 2 weeks of the first dose, and some within the first hour.  In these cases, pituitary apoplexy has presented as sudden headache, vomiting, visual changes, ophthalmoplegia, altered mental status, and sometimes cardiovascular collapse. Immediate medical attention has been required.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
