<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lupron0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions with GnRH agonists including LUPRON DEPOT-PED 7.5 mg, 11.25 mg, or 15 mg for 1-month administration and LUPRON DEPOT-PED 11.25 mg or 30 mg for 3-month administration are injection site reactions/pain including abscess, general pain, headache, emotional lability and hot flushes/sweating.



 During the early phase of therapy, gonadotropins and sex steroids rise above baseline because of the initial stimulatory effect of the drug (hormonal flare effect). Therefore, an increase in clinical signs and symptoms of puberty may be observed  [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  .



    EXCERPT:    *  Adverse events related to suppression of endogenous sex steroid secretion may occur with LUPRON DEPOT-PED 7.5 mg, 11.25 mg, or 15 mg for 1-month administration.  (6.1,    6.3)   
 *  In clinical studies for LUPRON DEPOT-PED 11.25 mg or 30 mg for 3-month administration, the most frequent (&gt;=2 patients) adverse reactions were: injection site pain, weight increased, headache, mood altered, and injection site swelling.  (6.2)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AbbVie Inc. at 1-800-633-9110 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 LUPRON DEPOT-PED 7.5 mg, 11.25 mg, or 15 mg for 1-month administration - Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In two studies of children with central precocious puberty, in 2% or more of the patients receiving the drug, the following adverse reactions were reported to have a possible or probable relationship to drug as ascribed by the treating physician. Reactions which are not considered drug-related are excluded.




 * Most events were mild or moderate in severity.   
  
   Table 2. Percentage of Patients with Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=2% of Pediatric Patients Receiving LUPRON DEPOT-PED 1-month     
                    Number of Patients(N = 421)     
                    N                (%)             
 Body as a Whole   
   Injection Site Reactions Including Abscess*  37               (9)               
   General Pain   12               (3)               
   Headache       11               (3)               
 Cardiovascular System   
   Vasodilation   9                (2)               
 Integumentary System (Skin and Appendages)   
   Acne/Seborrhea  13               (3)               
   Rash Including Erythema Multiforme  12               (3)               
 Nervous System    
   Emotional Lability  19               (5)               
 Urogenital System   
   Vaginitis/Vaginal Bleeding/Vaginal Discharge  13               (3)               
      Less Common Adverse Reactions
 

 The following treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported in less than 2% of the patients and are listed below by body system.



   Body as a Whole  - aggravation of preexisting tumor and decreased vision, allergic reaction, body odor, fever, flu syndrome, hypertrophy, infection;  Cardiovascular System  - bradycardia, hypertension, peripheral vascular disorder, syncope;  Digestive System  - constipation, dyspepsia, dysphagia, gingivitis, increased appetite, nausea/vomiting;  Endocrine System  - accelerated sexual maturity, feminization, goiter;  Hemic and Lymphatic System  - purpura;  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  - growth retarded, peripheral edema, weight gain;  Musculoskeletal System  - arthralgia, joint disorder, myalgia, myopathy;  Nervous System  - depression, hyperkinesia, nervousness, somnolence;  Respiratory System  - asthma, epistaxis, pharyngitis, rhinitis, sinusitis;  Integumentary System (Skin and Appendages)  - alopecia, hair disorder, hirsutism, leukoderma, nail disorder, skin hypertrophy;  Urogenital System  - cervix disorder/neoplasm, dysmenorrhea, gynecomastia/breast disorders, menstrual disorder, urinary incontinence.



   Laboratory  : The following laboratory events were reported as adverse reactions: antinuclear antibody present and increased sedimentation rate.



   6.2 LUPRON DEPOT-PED 11.25 mg or 30 mg for 3-month administration - Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.




   Table 3. Percentage of Patients with Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=2 Pediatric PatientsReceiving LUPRON DEPOT-PED 11.25 mg or 30 mg for 3-month administration.     
                    11.25 mg every 3 MonthsN=42      30 mg every 3 MonthsN=42      OverallN = 84     
                    N                %                N                %                N                %               
 Injection site pain  8                (19)             9                (21)             17               (20)              
 Weight increased  3                (7)              3                (7)              6                (7)               
 Headache         1                (2)              3                (7)              4                (5)               
 Mood altered     2                (5)              2                (5)              4                (5)               
 Injection site swelling  1                (2)              1                (2)              2                (2)               
      Less Common Adverse Reactions
 

 The following treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported in one patient and are listed below by system organ class:



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  - abdominal pain, nausea;  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  - asthenia, gait disturbance, injection site abscess sterile, injection site hematoma, injection site induration, injection site warmth, irritability;  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  - decreased appetite, obesity;  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  - musculoskeletal pain, pain in extremity;  Nervous System Disorders  - crying, dizziness;  Psychiatric Disorders  - tearfulness;  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  - cough;  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  - hyperhidrosis;  Vascular Disorders  - pallor.



   6.3 Postmarketing

  The following adverse events have been observed with this or other formulations of leuprolide acetate injection. As leuprolide has multiple indications, and therefore patient populations, some of these adverse events may not be applicable to every patient.



 Allergic reactions (anaphylactic, rash, urticaria, and photosensitivity reactions) have also been reported.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : nausea, abdominal pain, vomiting;



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  : chest pain, injection site reactions including induration and abscess have been reported;



   Investigations  : decreased WBC, weight increased;



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  : diabetes mellitus;



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  : tenosynovitis-like symptoms;



   Nervous System Disorders  : neuropathy peripheral, convulsion, spinal fracture/paralysis;



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  : hot flush, flushing, hyperhidrosis;



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  prostate pain;



   Vascular Disorders  : hypertension, hypotension.



   Pituitary apoplexy:  During post-marketing surveillance, rare cases of pituitary apoplexy (a clinical syndrome secondary to infarction of the pituitary gland) have been reported after the administration of gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonists. In a majority of these cases, a pituitary adenoma was diagnosed, with a majority of pituitary apoplexy cases occurring within 2 weeks of the first dose, and some within the first hour. In these cases, pituitary apoplexy has presented as sudden headache, vomiting, visual changes, ophthalmoplegia, altered mental status, and sometimes cardiovascular collapse. Immediate medical attention has been required.



 See other LUPRON DEPOT and LUPRON Injection package inserts for other events reported in different patient populations.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  An increase in clinical signs and symptoms of puberty may be observed during the first 2-4 weeks of therapy since gonadotropins and sex steroids rise above baseline because of the initial stimulatory effect of the drug before being suppressed.  (5.1)   
 *  Convulsions have been observed in patients with or without a history of seizures, epilepsy, cerebrovascular disorders, central nervous system anomalies or tumors, and in patients on concomitant medications that have been associated with convulsions.  (5.2)   
    
 

   5.1 Initial Rise of Gonadotropins and Sex Steroid Levels



  During the early phase of therapy, gonadotropins and sex steroids rise above baseline because of the initial stimulatory effect of the drug. Therefore, an increase in clinical signs and symptoms of puberty may be observed [see Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)  ]  .



    5.2 Convulsions



  Postmarketing reports of convulsions have been observed in patients on leuprolide acetate therapy. These included patients with a history of seizures, epilepsy, cerebrovascular disorders, central nervous system anomalies or tumors, and patients on concomitant medications that have been associated with convulsions such as bupropion and SSRIs. Convulsions have also been reported in patients in the absence of any of the conditions mentioned above.



    5.3 Monitoring and Laboratory Tests



  Response to LUPRON DEPOT-PED 7.5 mg, 11.25 mg, or 15 mg for 1-month administration should be monitored with a GnRHa stimulation test, basal LH or serum concentration of sex steroid levels beginning 1-2 months following initiation of therapy, with changing doses, or potentially during therapy in order to confirm maintenance of efficacy. Measurement of bone age for advancement should be done every 6-12 months.



 Response to LUPRON DEPOT-PED 11.25 mg or 30 mg for 3-month administration should be monitored with a GnRHa stimulation test, basal LH or serum concentration of sex steroid levels at months 2-3, month 6 and further as judged clinically appropriate, to ensure adequate suppression. Additionally, height (for calculation of growth rate) and bone age should be assessed every 6-12 months.



 Once a therapeutic dose has been established, gonadotropin and sex steroid levels will decline to prepubertal levels. Gonadotropins and/or sex steroids may increase or rise above prepubertal levels if the dose is inadequate. Noncompliance with drug regimen or inadequate dosing may result in inadequate control of the pubertal process with gonadotropins and/or sex steroids increasing above prepubertal levels [see Clinical Studies  (14)  and Adverse Reactions  (6)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
