<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lupron1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



    EXCERPT:    *  LUPRON DEPOT 7.5 mg for 1-month administration: The most common adverse reactions (&gt;10%) were general pain, hot flashes/sweats, GI disorders, edema, respiratory disorder, urinary disorder.  (6.1)   
 *  LUPRON DEPOT 22.5 mg for 3-month administration: The most common adverse reactions (&gt;10%) were general pain, injection site reaction, hot flashes/sweats, GI disorders, joint disorders, testicular atrophy, urinary disorders.  (6.2)   
 *  LUPRON DEPOT 30 mg for 4-month administration: The most common adverse reactions (&gt;10%) were asthenia, flu syndrome, general pain, headache, injection site reaction, hot flashes/sweats, GI disorders, edema, skin reaction, urinary disorders.  (6.3)   
 *  LUPRON DEPOT 45 mg for 6-month administration: The most common adverse reactions (&gt;10%) were hot flush, injection site pain, upper respiratory infection, and fatigue.  (6.4)   
    In postmarketing experience, mood swings, depression, rare reports of suicidal ideation and attempt, rare reports of pituitary apoplexy, and rare reports of serious drug-induced liver injury have been reported.  (6.5)  
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AbbVie Inc.at 1-800-633-9110 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 LUPRON DEPOT 7.5 mg for 1-Month Administration

  In the majority of patients testosterone levels increased above baseline during the first week, declining thereafter to baseline levels or below by the end of the second week of treatment.



 Potential exacerbations of signs and symptoms during the first few weeks of treatment is a concern in patients with vertebral metastases and/or urinary obstruction or hematuria which, if aggravated, may lead to neurological problems such as temporary weakness and/or paresthesia of the lower limbs or worsening of urinary symptoms  [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  .



 In a clinical trial of LUPRON DEPOT 7.5 mg for 1-month administration, the following adverse reactions were reported in 5% or more of the patients during the initial 24-week treatment period.




   Table 2. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients     
   LUPRON DEPOT 7.5 mg for 1-Month Administration (N=56)     
                    N                (%)             
   Body As A Whole                                       
 General pain     13               (23.2)            
 Infection        3                (5.4)             
   Cardiovascular System                                       
 Hot flashes/sweats*  32               (57.1)            
   Digestive System                                       
 GI disorders     8                (14.3)            
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                       
 Edema            8                (14.3)            
   Nervous System                                       
 Libido decreased*  3                (5.4)             
   Respiratory System                                       
 Respiratory disorder  6                (10.7)            
   Urogenital System                                       
 Urinary disorder  7                (12.5)            
 Impotence*       3                (5.4)             
 Testicular atrophy*  3                (5.4)             
 * Due to the expected physiologic effect of decreased testosterone levels.   
      In this same study, the following adverse reactions were reported in less than 5% of the patients on LUPRON DEPOT 7.5 mg for 1-month administration.
 

   Body As A Whole  - Asthenia, Cellulitis, Fever, Headache, Injection site reaction, Neoplasm



   Cardiovascular System  - Angina, Congestive heart failure



   Digestive System  - Anorexia, Dysphagia, Eructation, Peptic ulcer



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  - Ecchymosis



   Musculoskeletal System  - Myalgia



   Nervous System  - Agitation, Insomnia/sleep disorders, Neuromuscular disorders



   Respiratory System  - Emphysema, Hemoptysis, Lung edema, Sputum increased



   Skin and Appendages  - Hair disorder, Skin reaction



   Urogenital System  - Balanitis, Breast enlargement, Urinary tract infection



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



 Abnormalities of certain parameters were observed, but their relationship to drug treatment are difficult to assess in this population. The following were recorded in &gt;=5% of patients at final visit: Decreased albumin, decreased hemoglobin/hematocrit, decreased prostatic acid phosphatase, decreased total protein, decreased urine specific gravity, hyperglycemia, hyperuricemia, increased BUN, increased creatinine, increased liver function tests (AST, LDH), increased phosphorus, increased platelets, increased prostatic acid phosphatase, increased total cholesterol, increased urine specific gravity, leukopenia.



   6.2 LUPRON DEPOT 22.5 mg for 3-Month Administration

  In two clinical trials of LUPRON DEPOT 22.5 mg for 3-month administration, the following adverse reactions were reported to have a possible or probable relationship to drug as ascribed by the treating physician in 5% or more of the patients receiving the drug.  Often, causality is difficult to assess in patients with metastatic prostate cancer.  Reactions considered not drug-related are excluded.




   Table 3. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients     
   LUPRON DEPOT 22.5 mg for 3-Month Administration     
   Body System/Reaction      N=94             (%)             
   Body As A Whole                                       
 Asthenia         7                (7.4)             
 General Pain     25               (26.6)            
 Headache         6                (6.4)             
 Injection Site Reaction  13               (13.8)            
   Cardiovascular System                                       
 Hot flashes/Sweats  55               (58.5)            
   Digestive System                                       
 GI Disorders     15               (16.0)            
   Musculoskeletal System                                       
 Joint Disorders  11               (11.7)            
   Central/Peripheral Nervous System                                       
 Dizziness/Vertigo  6                (6.4)             
 Insomnia/Sleep Disorders  8                (8.5)             
 Neuromuscular Disorders  9                (9.6)             
   Respiratory System                                       
 Respiratory Disorders  6                (6.4)             
   Skin and Appendages                                       
 Skin Reaction    8                (8.5)             
   Urogenital System                                       
 Testicular Atrophy  19               (20.2)            
 Urinary Disorders  14               (14.9)            
      In these same studies, the following adverse reactions were reported in less than 5% of the patients on LUPRON DEPOT 22.5 mg for 3-month administration.
 

   Body As A Whole  - Enlarged abdomen, Fever



   Cardiovascular System  - Arrhythmia, Bradycardia, Heart failure, Hypertension, Hypotension, Varicose vein



   Digestive System  - Anorexia, Duodenal ulcer, Increased appetite, Thirst/dry mouth



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  - Anemia, Lymphedema



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  - Dehydration, Edema



   Central/Peripheral Nervous System  - Anxiety, Delusions, Depression, Hypesthesia, Libido decreased*, Nervousness, Paresthesia



   Respiratory System  - Epistaxis, Pharyngitis, Pleural effusion, Pneumonia



   Special Senses  - Abnormal vision, Amblyopia, Dry eyes, Tinnitus



   Urogenital System  - Gynecomastia, Impotence*, Penis disorders, Testis disorders.



 * Physiologic effect of decreased testosterone.



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



 Abnormalities of certain parameters were observed, but are difficult to assess in this population. The following were recorded in &gt;=5% of patients: Increased BUN, Hyperglycemia, Hyperlipidemia (total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, triglycerides), Hyperphosphatemia, Abnormal liver function tests, Increased PT, Increased PTT. Additional laboratory abnormalities reported were: Decreased platelets, Decreased potassium and Increased WBC.



   6.3 LUPRON DEPOT 30 mg for 4-Month Administration

  The 4-month formulation of LUPRON DEPOT 30 mg was utilized in clinical trials that studied the drug in 49 nonorchiectomized prostate cancer patients for 32 weeks or longer and in 24 orchiectomized prostate cancer patients for 20 weeks.



 In the above described clinical trials, the following adverse reactions were reported in &gt;= 5% of the patients during the treatment period.




   Table 4. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 5% of Patients     
   LUPRON DEPOT 30 mg for 4-Month Administration     
   Body System/Events      Nonorchiectomized      Orchiectomized     
                    Study 013        Study 012       
                    N=49             (%)              N=24             (%)             
   Body As A Whole                                                                         
 Asthenia         6                (12.2)           1                (4.2)             
 Flu Syndrome     6                (12.2)           0                (0.0)             
 General Pain     16               (32.7)           1                (4.2)             
 Headache         5                (10.2)           1                (4.2)             
 Injection Site Reaction  4                (8.2)            9                (37.5)            
   Cardiovascular System                                                                         
 Hot flashes/Sweats  23               (46.9)           2                (8.3)             
   Digestive System                                                                         
 GI Disorders     5                (10.2)           3                (12.5)            
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                         
 Dehydration      4                (8.2)            0                (0.0)             
 Edema            4                (8.2)            5                (20.8)            
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                         
 Joint Disorder   8                (16.3)           1                (4.2)             
 Myalgia          4                (8.2)            0                (0.0)             
   Nervous System                                                                         
 Dizziness/Vertigo  3                (6.1)            2                (8.3)             
 Neuromuscular Disorders  3                (6.1)            1                (4.2)             
 Paresthesia      4                (8.2)            1                (4.2)             
   Respiratory System                                                                         
 Respiratory Disorder  4                (8.2)            1                (4.2)             
   Skin and Appendages                                                                         
 Skin Reaction    6                (12.2)           0                (0.0)             
   Urogenital System                                                                         
 Urinary Disorders  5                (10.2)           4                (16.7)            
      In these same studies, the following adverse reactions were reported in less than 5% of the patients on LUPRON DEPOT 30 mg for 4-month administration.
 

   Body As A Whole  - Abscess, Accidental injury, Allergic reaction, Cyst, Fever, Generalized edema, Hernia, Neck pain, Neoplasm



   Cardiovascular System  - Atrial fibrillation, Deep thrombophlebitis, Hypertension



   Digestive System  - Anorexia, Eructation, Gastrointestinal hemorrhage, Gingivitis, Gum hemorrhage, Hepatomegaly, Increased appetite, Intestinal obstruction, Periodontal abscess



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  - Lymphadenopathy



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  - Healing abnormal, Hypoxia, Weight loss



   Musculoskeletal System  - Leg cramps, Pathological fracture, Ptosis



   Nervous System  - Abnormal thinking, Amnesia, Confusion, Convulsion, Dementia, Depression, Insomnia/sleep disorders, Libido decreased*, Neuropathy, Paralysis



   Respiratory System  - Asthma, Bronchitis, Hiccup, Lung disorder, Sinusitis, Voice alteration



   Skin and Appendages  - Herpes zoster, Melanosis



   Urogenital System  - Bladder carcinoma, Epididymitis, Impotence*, Prostate disorder, Testicular atrophy*, Urinary incontinence, Urinary tract infection.



 * Physiologic effect of decreased testosterone.



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



 Abnormalities of certain parameters were observed, but their relationship to drug treatment is difficult to assess in this population. The following were recorded in &gt;= 5% of patients: Decreased bicarbonate, Decreased hemoglobin/hematocrit/RBC, Hyperlipidemia (total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, triglycerides), Decreased HDL-cholesterol, Eosinophilia, Increased glucose, Increased liver function tests (ALT, AST, GGTP, LDH), Increased phosphorus. Additional laboratory abnormalities were reported: Increased BUN and PT, Leukopenia, Thrombocytopenia, Uricaciduria.



   6.4 LUPRON DEPOT 45 mg for 6-Month Administration

  One open label, multicenter study was conducted with LUPRON DEPOT 45 mg for 6-month administration in 151 prostate cancer patients. Patients were treated for 48 weeks, with 139/151 receiving two injections 24 weeks apart.



 In the above described clinical trial, the following adverse events were reported in &gt;= 5% of the patients during the treatment period. The Table 5 includes all adverse events reported in &gt;= 5% of patients as well as the incidences of these adverse events that were considered, by the treating physician, to have a definite or possible relationship to LUPRON.




   Table 5. Adverse Events in &gt;= 5% of Patients     
   LUPRON DEPOT  45 mg for 6-Month Administration       
                    Treatment Emergent      Treatment Related     
   Adverse Event      N = 151          (%)              N = 151          (%)             
 Hot Flush/Flushing  89               58.9             88               58.3              
 Injection Site Pain/Discomfort  29               19.2             16               10.6              
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection/Influenza-like Illness  1    32               21.2             0                0                 
 Fatigue/Lethargy  20               13.2             18               11.9              
 Constipation     15               9.9              5                3.3               
 Arthralgia       14               9.3              2                1.3               
 Insomnia/Sleep Disorder  13               8.6              5                3.3               
 Headache/Sinus Headache  12               7.9              3                2.0               
 Musculoskeletal Pain/ Myalgia  12               7.9              3                2.0               
 Second Primary Neoplasm  2    11               7.3              0                0                 
 Cough            10               6.6              2                1.3               
 Hematuria/Hemorrhagic Cystitis  10               6.6              0                0                 
 Hypertension/BP Increased  10               6.6              3                2.0               
 Rash             9                6.0              3                2.0               
 Dysuria          9                6.0              1                0.7               
 Urinary Tract Infection/Cystitis  9                6.0              0                0                 
 Anemia/Hemoglobin Decreased  10               6.6              2                1.3               
 Back Pain        8                5.3              0                0                 
 COPD             8                5.3              0                0                 
 Dizziness        8                5.3              3                2.0               
 Dyspnea/Dyspnea on Exertion  8                5.3              2                1.3               
 Nocturia         8                5.3              2                1.3               
 Peripheral/Pitting Edema  8                5.3              2                1.3               
 Coronary Artery Disease/Angina  8                5.3              1                0.7               
        1  Includes influenza, nasal congestion, nasopharyngitis, rhinorrhea, upper respiratory tract infection, and viral upper respiratory tract infection
 

   2  Includes basal cell carcinoma, bladder transitional cell carcinoma, lung neoplasm, malignant melanoma, non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, and squamous cell carcinoma



 The following adverse events led to discontinuation; fatigue, hot flush, second primary neoplasm, asthenia, coronary artery disease, constipation, hyperkalemia, and sleep disorder. Serious adverse events in &gt;= 2% of patients, regardless of causality, included chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, coronary artery disease/angina, cerebrovascular accident/transient ischemic attack, pneumonia, and second primary neoplasms.



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



 At baseline, 13.9% of patients had a CTCAE v4.0 grade 1 or 2 decreased hemoglobin. During the study, 42.4% of subjects had grade 1 decreased hemoglobin (10 - &lt;12-5 g/dL), 2.0% had grade 2 ( 8 - &lt;10 g/dL) and 1.3% of subjects had grade 3 or 4 (&lt;8 g/dL). Likewise, 28.5% of patients had a grade 1 or 2 increased cholesterol at baseline while 55.0% had grade 1 increased cholesterol (&gt;199- 300 mg/dL), 3.3% had a grade 2 increase (&gt;300-400 mg/dL), and 0.7% of subjects had grade 3 (&gt;400 mg/dL) during the study.



   6.5 Postmarketing

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of LUPRON DEPOT. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 During postmarketing surveillance, which includes other dosage forms and other patient populations, the following adverse reactions were reported.



 Like other drugs in this class, mood swings, including depression, have been reported. There have been very rare reports of suicidal ideation and attempt. Many, but not all, of these patients had a history of depression or other psychiatric illness. Patients should be counseled on the possibility of development or worsening of depression during treatment with LUPRON.



 Symptoms consistent with an anaphylactoid or asthmatic process have been rarely (incidence rate of about 0.002%) reported. Rash, urticaria, and photosensitivity reactions have also been reported.



   Changes in Bone Density  - Decreased bone density has been reported in the medical literature in men who have had orchiectomy or who have been treated with a GnRH agonist analog. In a clinical trial, 25 men with prostate cancer, 12 of whom had been treated previously with leuprolide acetate for at least six months, underwent bone density studies as a result of pain. The leuprolide-treated group had lower bone density scores than the nontreated control group. It can be anticipated that long periods of medical castration in men will have effects on bone density.



   Pituitary apoplexy  - During post-marketing surveillance, rare cases of pituitary apoplexy (a clinical syndrome secondary to infarction of the pituitary gland) have been reported after the administration of gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonists. In a majority of these cases, a pituitary adenoma was diagnosed, with a majority of pituitary apoplexy cases occurring within 2 weeks of the first dose, and some within the first hour. In these cases, pituitary apoplexy has presented as sudden headache, vomiting, visual changes, ophthalmoplegia, altered mental status, and sometimes cardiovascular collapse. Immediate medical attention has been required.



 Localized reactions including induration and abscess have been reported at the site of injection.



 Symptoms consistent with fibromyalgia (e.g., joint and muscle pain, headaches, sleep disorders, gastrointestinal distress, and shortness of breath) have been reported individually and collectively.



   Cardiovascular System  - Hypotension, Myocardial infarction, Pulmonary embolism



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorder  - Interstitial lung disease



   Hepato-biliary disorder  - Serious drug-induced liver injury



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  - Decreased WBC



   Central/Peripheral Nervous System  - Convulsion, Peripheral neuropathy, Spinal fracture/paralysis



   Endocrine System  - Diabetes



   Musculoskeletal System  - Tenosynovitis-like symptoms



   Urogenital System  - Prostate pain



 See other LUPRON DEPOT and LUPRON Injection package inserts for other reactions reported in women and pediatric populations.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  *  Isolated cases of transient worsening of symptoms, or additional signs and symptoms of prostate cancer during the first few weeks of treatment.  (5.1)   
 *  A small number of patients may experience a temporary increase in bone pain which can be managed symptomatically.  (5.1)   
 *  Isolated cases of ureteral obstruction and spinal cord compression have been reported with GnRH agonists, which may contribute to paralysis with or without fatal complications.  (5.1)   
   Increased serum testosterone (~ 50% above baseline) during first week of treatment; monitor serum testosterone and PSA.  (5.1  ,  5.6)   
 *  Hyperglycemia and Diabetes: Hyperglycemia and an increased risk of developing diabetes have been reported in men receiving GnRH analogs. Monitor blood glucose level and manage according to current clinical practice.  (5.2)   
 *  Cardiovascular Diseases: Increased risk of myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death and stroke has been reported in association with use of GnRH analogs in men. Monitor for cardiovascular disease and manage according to current clinical practice.  (5.3)   
 *  Effect on QT/QTc Interval: Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval. Consider risks and benefits.  (5.4)   
 *  Convulsions have been observed in patients with or without a history of predisposing factors. Manage convulsions according to the current clinical practice.  (5.5)   
    
 

   5.1 Tumor Flare



  Initially, LUPRON DEPOT, like other GnRH agonists, causes increases in serum levels of testosterone to approximately 50% above baseline during the first weeks of treatment. Isolated cases of ureteral obstruction and spinal cord compression have been observed, which may contribute to paralysis with or without fatal complications. Transient worsening of symptoms may develop. A small number of patients may experience a temporary increase in bone pain, which can be managed symptomatically.



 Patients with metastatic vertebral lesions and/or with urinary tract obstruction should be closely observed during the first few weeks of therapy.



    5.2 Hyperglycemia and Diabetes



  Hyperglycemia and an increased risk of developing diabetes have been reported in men receiving GnRH agonists. Hyperglycemia may represent development of diabetes mellitus or worsening of glycemic control in patients with diabetes. Monitor blood glucose and/or glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) periodically in patients receiving a GnRH agonist and manage with current practice for treatment of hyperglycemia or diabetes.



    5.3 Cardiovascular Diseases



  Increased risk of developing myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death and stroke has been reported in association with use of GnRH agonists in men. The risk appears low based on the reported odds ratios, and should be evaluated carefully along with cardiovascular risk factors when determining a treatment for patients with prostate cancer. Patients receiving a GnRH agonist should be monitored for symptoms and signs suggestive of development of cardiovascular disease and be managed according to current clinical practice.



    5.4 Effect on QT/QTc Interval



   Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT/QTc interval. Providers should consider whether the benefits of androgen deprivation therapy outweigh the potential risks in patients with congenital long QT syndrome, congestive heart failure, frequent electrolyte abnormalities, and in patients taking drugs known to prolong the QT interval. Electrolyte abnormalities should be corrected. Consider periodic monitoring of electrocardiograms and electrolytes.  



    5.5 Convulsions



   Postmarketing reports of convulsions have been observed in patients on leuprolide acetate therapy. These included patients with a history of seizures, epilepsy, cerebrovascular disorders, central nervous system anomalies or tumors, and in patients on concomitant medications that have been associated with convulsions such as bupropion and SSRIs. Convulsions have also been reported in patients in the absence of any of the conditions mentioned above. Patients receiving a GnRH agonist who experience convulsion should be managed according to current clinical practice.  



    5.6 Laboratory Tests



  Monitor serum levels of testosterone following injection of LUPRON DEPOT 7.5 mg for 1-month administration, 22.5 mg for 3-month administration, 30 mg for 4-month administration, or 45 mg for 6-month administration. In the majority of patients, testosterone levels increased above baseline, and then declined thereafter to castrate levels (&lt; 50 ng/dL) within four weeks. [see Clinical Studies  (14)  and Adverse Reactions  (6)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
