<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="luvox" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

      Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   EXCERPT:   Most common reactions in controlled trials with OCD patients and patients from another studied population (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice that for placebo) were  abnormal ejaculation, anorexia, anorgasmia, asthenia, diarrhea, nausea, somnolence, sweating  and  tremor (  6.2  )  . The following additional reactions occurred:  anxiety, decreased libido, myalgia, pharyngitis,  and  vomiting  in the OCD population; and  dyspepsia, dizziness, insomnia,  and  yawning  in another studied population.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Jazz Pharmaceuticals, Inc., at 1-800-520-5568 phone; 1-510-595-8183 fax; jazzsafety@jazzpharma.com; or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/Medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Data Sources

       LUVOX CR Capsules were studied in one 12-week controlled trial in patients with OCD (N = 124; mean exposure 66.6 days) and in two 12-week controlled trials for another condition (N = 279; mean exposure 59.2 days). Patients in these trials were initiated on 100 mg/day and were titrated in 50 mg increments over the first 6 weeks to within a range of 100 mg to 300 mg/day. The reactions listed in  Table 2  show reactions from the two populations separately.  Table 3  shows reactions from the three controlled studies combined.



   6.2 Adverse Reactions Observed in Controlled Trials

           Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment:    Of the 124 patients with OCD and 279 patients in other studies treated with LUVOX CR Capsules in controlled clinical trials, 19% and 26% discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction. The most common reactions (&gt;=1%) associated with discontinuation and considered to be drug related (i.e., those reactions associated with dropout at a rate at least twice that of placebo) were  anorexia  (including, but not limited to, loss of appetite and decreased appetite)  (1%), anxiety (3%), asthenia (3%), diarrhea (2%), dizziness (4%), headache (2%), insomnia (5%), nausea (7%), nervousness (1%), somnolence (5%),  and  thinking abnormal (1%)  .



          Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions:    LUVOX CR Capsules have been studied in one controlled trial in patients with OCD (N = 124) and two controlled trials for another condition (N = 279). In general, adverse reaction rates were similar in the two data sets as well as in a study of pediatric patients with OCD treated with immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets. The most commonly observed treatment-emergent adverse reactions associated with the use of LUVOX CR Capsules and likely to be drug-related (incidence of 5% or greater and at least twice that for placebo) and derived from  Table 2  were:  abnormal ejaculation, anorexia, anorgasmia, asthenia, diarrhea, nausea, somnolence, sweating,  and  tremor  . In the one controlled trial in patients with OCD, the following additional reactions occurred at an incidence of 5% or greater and at least twice that for placebo:  anxiety, decreased libido, myalgia, pharyngitis,  and  vomiting  . The following additional reactions occurred in another studied population:  dyspepsia, dizziness, insomnia,  and  yawning  . In a study evaluating immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets in pediatric patients with OCD, the following additional reactions were identified using the above rule:  agitation, depression, dysmenorrhea, flatulence, hyperkinesia,  and  rash  .



          Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of &gt;=2%:      Table 2  enumerates adverse reactions that occurred in adults at a frequency of 2% or more, and were more frequent than in the placebo group, among patients treated with LUVOX CR Capsules in two short-term, placebo-controlled trials (12 weeks) in another population and one short-term placebo-controlled OCD trial (12 weeks) and in which patients were dosed once-a-day in a range of 100 to 300 mg/day. This table shows the percentage of patients in each group who had at least one occurrence of a reaction at some time during their treatment. Reported adverse reactions were classified using a COSTART-based Dictionary terminology.



      The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing health care provider with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the side-effect incidence rate in the population studied.  TABLE 2 TREATMENT-EMERGENT ADVERSE REACTION INCIDENCE RATES BY BODY SYSTEM IN ADULT OCD PATIENTS AND ANOTHER STUDIED POPULATION  1    




                                          PERCENTAGE OF PATIENTS REPORTING REACTION     
                                          OBSESSIVE COMPULSIVE DISORDER      OTHER STUDIED POPULATION     
   BODY SYSTEM/    ADVERSE REACTION       LUVOX CR    N = 124      PLACEBO    N = 124      LUVOX CR    N = 279      PLACEBO    N = 276     
  
                                         BODY AS A WHOLE                      
                                                                                
                                          Headache                            
                                                                                                      32                    
                                                                 31               
                                            35    
                                      30                    
                                                
                                          Asthenia                            
                                                                                                      26                    
                                                                 8                
                                            24    
                                      10                    
                                                
                                          Pain  2                             
                                                                                                      10                    
                                                                 8                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Abdominal Pain                      
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            5     
                                      4                     
                                                
                                          Accidental Injury                   
                                                                                                      5                     
                                                                 3                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Chest Pain                          
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            3     
                                      1                     
                                                
                                          Viral Infection                     
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         CARDIOVASCULAR                       
                                                                                
                                          Palpitation                         
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            3     
                                      1                     
                                                
                                          Vasodilatation                      
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            2     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                          Hypertension                        
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         DIGESTIVE SYSTEM                     
                                                                                
                                          Nausea                              
                                                                                                      34                    
                                                                 13               
                                            39    
                                      11                    
                                                
                                          Diarrhea                            
                                                                                                      18                    
                                                                 8                
                                            14    
                                      5                     
                                                
                                          Anorexia  3                         
                                                                                                      13                    
                                                                 5                
                                            14    
                                      1                     
                                                
                                          Dyspepsia                           
                                                                                                      8                     
                                                                 5                
                                            10    
                                      4                     
                                                
                                          Constipation                        
                                                                                                      4                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            6     
                                      5                     
                                                
                                          Vomiting                            
                                                                                                      6                     
                                                                 2                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Tooth Disorder                      
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Liver Function Test Abnormal        
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            2     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                          Gingivitis                          
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 0                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         HEMIC  AND  LYMPHATIC                
                                                                                
                                          Ecchymosis                          
                                                                                                      4                     
                                                                 2                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         Metabolic  and  Nutritional Disorders  
                                                                                
                                          Weight Loss                         
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         MUSCULOSKELETAL                      
                                                                                
                                          Myalgia                             
                                                                                                      5                     
                                                                 2                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         NERVOUS SYSTEM                       
                                                                                
                                          Insomnia                            
                                                                                                      35                    
                                                                 20               
                                            32    
                                      13                    
                                                
                                          Somnolence                          
                                                                                                      27                    
                                                                 11               
                                            26    
                                      9                     
                                                
                                          Dizziness                           
                                                                                                      12                    
                                                                 10               
                                            15    
                                      7                     
                                                
                                          Dry Mouth                           
                                                                                                      10                    
                                                                 9                
                                            11    
                                      8                     
                                                
                                          Nervousness                         
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            10    
                                      9                     
                                                
                                          Libido Decreased                    
                                                                                                      6                     
                                                                 2                
                                            6     
                                      4                     
                                                
                                             Male                             
                                                                                                      10                    
                                                                 5                
                                            8     
                                      6                     
                                                
                                             Female                           
                                                                                                      4                     
                                                                 1                
                                            4     
                                      3                     
                                                
                                          Anxiety                             
                                                                                                      6                     
                                                                 2                
                                            8     
                                      5                     
                                                
                                          Tremor                              
                                                                                                      6                     
                                                                 0                
                                            8     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                          Abnormal Thinking                   
                                                                                                      3                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            3     
                                      2                     
                                                
                                          Abnormal Dreams                     
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            3     
                                      2                     
                                                
                                          Agitation                           
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            3     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                          Hypertonia                          
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            2     
                                      1                     
                                                
                                          Apathy                              
                                                                                                      3                     
                                                                 0                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Paresthesia                         
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            3     
                                      2                     
                                                
                                          Neurosis                            
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Twitching                           
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 0                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                   
                                                                                
                                          Pharyngitis                         
                                                                                                      6                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Yawn                                
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 0                
                                            5     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                          Laryngitis                          
                                                                                                      3                     
                                                                 0                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Bronchitis                          
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            2     
                                      1                     
                                                
                                          Epistaxis                           
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 0                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         SKIN                                 
                                                                                
                                          Sweating                            
                                                                                                      7                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            6     
                                      2                     
                                                
                                          Acne                                
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 0                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         SPECIAL SENSES                       
                                                                                
                                          Taste Perversion                    
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            2     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                          Amblyopia                           
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                         UROGENITAL                           
                                                                                
                                          Abnormal Ejaculation                
                                                                                                      10                    
                                                                 0                
                                            11    
                                      2                     
                                                
                                          Anorgasmia                          
                                                                                                      5                     
                                                                 0                
                                            5     
                                      1                     
                                                
                                             Male                             
                                                                                                      4                     
                                                                 0                
                                            4     
                                      2                     
                                                
                                             Female                           
                                                                                                      5                     
                                                                 0                
                                            5     
                                      0                     
                                                
                                          Menorrhagia                         
                                                                                                      3                     
                                                                 0                
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
                                          Sexual Function Abnormal            
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            3     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                              Male                            
                                                                                                      4                     
                                                                 3                
                                            2     
                                      1                     
                                                
                                              Female                          
                                                                                                      0                     
                                                                 0                
                                            3     
                                      0                     
                                                
                                          Urinary Tract Infection             
                                                                                                      -                     
                                                                 -                
                                            2     
                                      &lt;1                    
                                                
                                          Polyuria                            
                                                                                                      2                     
                                                                 &lt;1               
                                            -     
                                      -                     
                                                
              1  Events for which fluvoxamine maleate incidence was equal to or less than placebo include the following for OCD patients: abdominal pain, flu syndrome, infection, palpitation, flatulence, increased appetite, weight gain, abnormal dreams, amnesia, hypertonia, nervousness, paresthesia, increased cough, dyspnea, rhinitis, and ear pain. In the other studied population the following events were seen: abdominal pain, accidental injury, back pain, flu syndrome, infection, pain, flatulence, pharyngitis, rhinitis, rash, and dysmenorrhea.
 

   2  Term includes body aches/pains, dental pain, pain from surgery, unspecified pain, and general pain secondary to injuries (sprains, fractures).



   3  Includes, but is not limited to, loss of appetite and decreased appetite.



   6.3 Other Adverse Reactions in OCD Pediatric Population

       In pediatric patients (N=57) treated with immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets, the overall profile of adverse reactions was generally similar to that seen in adult studies, as shown in  Table 2  . However, the following adverse reactions, not appearing in  Table 2  , were reported in two or more of the pediatric patients and were more frequent with immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets than with placebo: cough increase, dysmenorrhea, ecchymosis, emotional lability, epistaxis, hyperkinesia, manic reaction, rash, sinusitis, and weight decrease.



   6.4 Male and Female Sexual Dysfunction with SSRIs

       Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder and with aging, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) can cause such untoward sexual experiences.



      Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, however, in part because patients and health care providers may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling are likely to underestimate their actual incidence.



        Table 3  displays the incidence of sexual side effects reported by at least 2% of patients taking LUVOX CR Capsules in placebo-controlled trials.



 TABLE 3 PERCENTAGE OF PATIENTS REPORTING SEXUAL ADVERSE REACTIONS IN PLACEBO-CONTROLLED TRIALS 
                                     LUVOX CR  N = 403                    Placebo  N = 400                   
  Abnormal Ejaculation               11                                   2                                  
  Anorgasmia                                                                                                 
       Male                          4                                    1                                  
       Female                        5                                    0                                  
  Impotence                          2                                    2                                  
  Libido Decreased                                                                                           
       Male                          8                                    5                                  
       Female                        4                                    2                                  
  Sexual Function Abnormal                                                                                   
       Male                          3                                    1                                  
       Female                        2                                    0                                  
              Fluvoxamine treatment has been associated with several cases of priapism. In those cases with a known outcome, patients recovered without sequelae and upon discontinuation of fluvoxamine.
 

      While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, health care providers should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



   6.5 Weight and Vital Sign Changes

       No statistically significant differences in weight gain or loss were found between patients treated with LUVOX CR Capsules or placebo. Comparisons of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets or LUVOX CR Capsules versus placebo groups in separate short-term trials on (1) median change from baseline on various vital signs variables and on (2) incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially important changes from baseline on various measures of vital signs variables revealed no important differences between fluvoxamine maleate and placebo.



   6.6 Laboratory Changes

       Comparisons of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets or LUVOX CR Capsules versus placebo groups in separate short-term trials on (1) median change from baseline on various serum chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis variables and on (2) incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially important changes from baseline on various serum chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis variables revealed no important differences between fluvoxamine maleate and placebo.



   6.7 ECG Changes

       Comparisons of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets or LUVOX CR Capsules and placebo groups in separate pools of short-term OCD and depression trials on (1) mean change from baseline on various ECG variables and on (2) incidence of patients meeting criteria for potentially important changes from baseline on various ECG variables revealed no important differences between fluvoxamine maleate and placebo.



   6.8 Other Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Fluvoxamine

       During premarketing clinical trials conducted in North America and Europe, multiple doses of LUVOX CR Capsules or immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets were administered for a combined total of 3219 patient exposures in patients suffering OCD or other studied disorders. These exposures include 482 patient exposures with LUVOX CR Capsules and 2737 patient exposures with immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets. Untoward reactions associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using descriptive terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse reactions without first grouping similar types of untoward reactions into a limited (i.e., reduced) number of standard reaction categories.



      In the tabulations that follow, a COSTART-based Dictionary terminology has been used to classify reported adverse reactions. If the COSTART term for a reaction was so general as to be uninformative, it was replaced with a more informative term when possible. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the total patient exposures to multiple doses of fluvoxamine maleate who experienced a reaction of the type cited on at least one occasion while receiving fluvoxamine maleate. Reactions are further classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions: frequent adverse reactions are defined as those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse reactions are those occurring between 1/100 and 1/1000 patients; and rare adverse reactions are those occurring in less than 1/1000 patients. It is important to emphasize that, although the events reported did occur during treatment with fluvoxamine maleate, a causal relationship to fluvoxamine maleate has not been established.



      For LUVOX CR, all reported events are included in the list below, with the following exclusions: 1) those events already listed in  Table 2  or previous sections of this prescribing information; 2) those events for which there is no basis to suspect a causal relationship; and 3) events that were reported in only one patient and judged not to be potentially serious.



     Body as a Whole:  Infrequent:  chills, malaise, photosensitivity reaction, suicide attempt.



     Cardiovascular System:  Infrequent:  syncope.



     Digestive System:  Infrequent:  eructation, increased salivation.



     Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  Frequent:  weight gain.



     Nervous System:  Infrequent:  confusion, incoordination, sleep disorder, suicidal tendency.



     Skin and Appendages:  Infrequent:  eczema, urticaria.



     Special Senses:  Infrequent:  dry eyes, photophobia, taste loss.



     Urogenital System:  Infrequent:  vaginal hemorrhage  1  .



   1  Based on the number of females.



      For immediate-release fluvoxamine tablets, all reported events are included in the list below, with the following exclusions: 1) those events already listed in  Table 2  , in previous sections of this prescribing information, or in the LUVOX CR list of  Other Reactions Observed During Premarketing Evaluation  ; 2) those events for which there is no basis to suspect a causal relationship; and 3) events that were reported in only one patient and judged not to be potentially serious.



     Body as a Whole:  Infrequent:  allergic reaction, neck pain, neck rigidity, overdose;  Rare:  sudden death.



     Cardiovascular System:  Frequent:  hypotension;  Infrequent:  angina pectoris, bradycardia, cardiomyopathy, cardiovascular disease, cold extremities, conduction delay, myocardial infarction, pallor, pulse irregular, ST segment changes;  Rare:  AV block, cerebrovascular accident, embolus, pericarditis, phlebitis, pulmonary infarction, supraventricular extrasystoles.



     Digestive System:  Frequent:  elevated liver transaminases;  Infrequent:  colitis, esophagitis, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastrointestinal ulcer, glossitis, hemorrhoids, melena, rectal hemorrhage, stomatitis;  Rare:  biliary pain, cholecystitis, cholelithiasis, fecal incontinence, hematemesis, intestinal obstruction, jaundice.



     Endocrine System:  Infrequent:  hypothyroidism;  Rare:  goiter.



     Hemic and Lymphatic Systems:  Infrequent:  leukocytosis, lymphadenopathy, thrombocytopenia;  Rare:  leukopenia, purpura.



     Metabolic and Nutritional Systems:  Frequent:  edema;  Infrequent:  dehydration, hypercholesterolemia;  Rare:  diabetes mellitus, hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, lactate dehydrogenase increased.



     Musculoskeletal System:  Infrequent:  arthralgia, arthritis, bursitis, generalized muscle spasm, myasthenia;  Rare:  myopathy.



     Nervous System:  Frequent:  amnesia, apathy, hyperkinesia, hypokinesia, manic reaction, myoclonus, psychotic reaction;  Infrequent:  agoraphobia, akathisia, ataxia, CNS depression, convulsion, delirium, delusion, depersonalization, dyskinesia, dystonia, emotional lability, euphoria, extrapyramidal syndrome, gait unsteady, hallucinations, hemiplegia, hostility, hypersomnia, hypochondriasis, hypotonia, hysteria, increased libido, paralysis, paranoid reaction, phobia, psychosis, stupor, twitching, vertigo;  Rare:  akinesia, coma, fibrillations, mutism, obsessions, reflexes decreased, slurred speech, tardive dyskinesia, torticollis, trismus, withdrawal syndrome.



     Respiratory System:  Frequent:  cough increased, sinusitis;  Infrequent:  asthma, bronchitis, hoarseness, hyperventilation;  Rare:  apnea, congestion of upper airway, hemoptysis, hiccups, laryngismus, obstructive pulmonary disease, pneumonia.



     Skin:  Infrequent:  alopecia, dry skin, exfoliative dermatitis, furunculosis, seborrhea, skin discoloration.



     Special Senses:  Infrequent:  accommodation abnormal, conjunctivitis, diplopia, eye pain, mydriasis, otitis media, parosmia, visual field defect;  Rare:  corneal ulcer.



     Urogenital System:  Infrequent:  anuria, cystitis, delayed menstruation  1  , dysuria, female lactation  1  , hematuria, menopause  1  , metrorrhagia  1  , nocturia, premenstrual syndrome  1  , urination impaired, vaginitis  1  ;  Rare:  kidney calculus, hematospermia  2  , oliguria.



   1  Based on the number of females.  2  Based on the number of males.



   6.9 Postmarketing Reports

       The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets or LUVOX CR Capsules. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. (Reactions that are discussed in other sections of this prescribing information are not repeated here.) These reactions include: activation syndrome, aggression, agranulocytosis, anaphylactic reaction, anger, blood glucose increased, bruxism, cardio-respiratory arrest, crying, dysarthria, dysphagia, electrocardiogram QT prolonged, fall, fatigue, feeling drunk, feeling jittery, gait disturbance, gastroesophageal reflux disease, glossodynia, hepatitis, homicidal ideation, impulsive behavior, ileus, inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion, interstitial lung disease, irritability, loss of consciousness, lethargy, muscular weakness, Parkinsonism, pancreatitis, pyrexia, renal impairment, rhabdomyolysis, self injurious behavior, shock, somnolence neonatal, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, tachycardia, urinary retention, ventricular arrythmia, ventricular tachycardia (including torsades de pointes known to cause cardiac arrest, sometimes fatal), vision blurred, white blood cell count decreased.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

  Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of LUVOX CR (fluvoxamine maleate) Extended-Release Capsules or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber.   (See     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS-Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk   [  5.1  ]    and     USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS-Pediatric Use   [  8.4  ]  .)



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SUICIDALITY and ANTIDEPRESSANTS



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder and other psychiatric disorders   (  5.1  )  .



 









    BOXED WARNING: 17.11 FDA-Approved Medication Guide

    17.11 FDA-Approved Medication Guide  

    Medication Guide    LUVOX CR  (r)   (LOO Vox CR)    (Fluvoxamine Maleate) Extended-Release Capsules  



 Read the Medication Guide that comes with LUVOX CR Capsules before you start taking it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or treatment. Talk to your healthcare provider if there is something you do not understand or want to learn more about.



   What is the most important information I should know about LUVOX CR Capsules?  



 LUVOX CR is the same kind of medicine as those used to treat depression. These medicines may cause serious side effects, including:



   1. Suicidal thoughts or actions:   



 *  LUVOX CR Capsules and other antidepressant medicines may increase suicidal thoughts or actions in some children, teenagers, or young adults within the first few months of treatment or when the dose is changed. 
 *  Depression or other serious mental illnesses are the most important causes of suicidal thoughts or actions. 
 *  Watch for these changes and call your healthcare provider right away if you notice: New or sudden changes in mood, behavior, actions, thoughts, or feelings, especially if severe. Pay particular attention to such changes when LUVOX CR is started or when the dose is changed. 
    Keep all follow-up visits with your healthcare provider and call between visits if you are worried about symptoms. 
 

   Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 in an emergency, especially if they are new, worse, or worry you:   



 *  attempts to commit suicide 
 *  acting on dangerous impulses 
 *  acting aggressive or violent 
 *  thoughts about suicide or dying 
 *  new or worse depression 
 *  new or worse anxiety or panic attacks 
 *  feeling agitated, restless, angry or irritable 
 *  trouble sleeping 
 *  an increase in activity or talking more than what is normal for you 
 *  other unusual changes in behavior or mood 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 in an emergency. LUVOX CR Capsules may be associated with these serious side effects:   
 

   2. Serotonin Syndrome. This condition can be life-threatening and may include:   



 *  agitation, hallucinations, coma or other changes in mental status 
 *  coordination problems or muscle twitching (overactive reflexes) 
 *  racing heartbeat, high or low blood pressure 
 *  sweating or fever 
 *  nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea 
 *  muscle rigidity 
      3.  Visual Problems  
 

 *  eye pain 
 *  changes in vision 
 *  swelling or redness in or around the eye. Only some people are at risk for these problems. You may want to undergo an eye examination to see if you are at risk and receive preventative treatment if you are. 
      4. Severe allergic reactions:   
 

 *  trouble breathing 
 *  swelling of the face, tongue, eyes, or mouth 
 *  rash, itchy welts (hives) or blisters, alone or with fever or joint pain 
      5. Abnormal bleeding:   LUVOX CR Capsules and other antidepressant medicines may increase your risk of bleeding or bruising, especially if you take the blood thinner warfarin (Coumadin  (r)  , Jantoven  (r)  ), a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAIDs, like ibuprofen or naproxen), or aspirin. 
 

   6. Seizures or convulsions   



   7. Manic episodes:   



 *  greatly increased energy 
 *  severe trouble sleeping 
 *  racing thoughts 
 *  reckless behavior 
 *  unusually grand ideas 
 *  excessive happiness or irritability 
 *  talking more or faster than usual 
      8. Changes in appetite or weight.   Children and adolescents should have height and weight monitored during treatment. 
 

   9. Low salt (sodium) levels in the blood.   Elderly people may be at greater risk for this. Symptoms may include: 



 *  headache 
 *  weakness or feeling unsteady 
 *  confusion, problems concentrating or thinking, or memory problems 
      Do not stop taking LUVOX CR Capsules without first talking to your healthcare provider.   Stopping LUVOX CR Capsules may cause serious symptoms, including: 
 

 *  anxiety, irritability, high or low mood, feeling restless or changes in sleep habits 
 *  headache, sweating, nausea, dizziness 
 *  electric shock-like sensations, shaking, confusion 
      What is LUVOX CR Capsules?   
 

 LUVOX CR Capsules is a prescription medicine used to treat obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD). It is the same kind of drug that is used to treat depression. It is important to talk with your healthcare provider about the risks of treating OCD and also the risks of not treating it. You should discuss all treatment choices with your healthcare provider. 



 Talk to your healthcare provider if you do not think that your condition is getting better with LUVOX CR treatment. 



   Who should not take LUVOX CR Capsules?  



 Do not take LUVOX CR Capsules if you: 



 *  are allergic to fluvoxamine maleate or any of the ingredients in LUVOX CR Capsules. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in LUVOX CR Capsules. 
 *  take a Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitor (MAOI). Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure if you take an MAOI, including the antibiotic linezolid. Do not take an MAOI within 2 weeks of stopping LUVOX CR Capsules unless directed to do so by your physician. Do not start LUVOX CR Capsules if you stopped taking an MAOI in the last 2 weeks unless directed to do so by your physician. People who take LUVOX CR Capsules close in time to an MAOI may have serious or even life-threatening side effects. Get medical help right away if you have any of these symptoms: 
 *    high fever uncontrolled muscle spasms stiff muscles rapid changes in heart rate or blood pressure confusion loss of consciousness (pass out) 
 *  take Mellaril(r) (thioridazine). Mellaril(r) should not be taken with LUVOX CR Capsules because this can cause serious heart rhythm problems or sudden death. 
 *  take Zanaflex(r) (tizanidine) because LUVOX CR can increase the amount of Zanaflex in your body, which could increase its actions and side effects. This could include causing drowsiness and a drop in blood pressure and affecting how well you do things that require alertness. 
 *  take the antipsychotic medicine Orap(r) (pimozide) because this can cause serious heart problems. 
 *  Take Lotronex(r) (alosetron) because LUVOX CR can increase the amount of Lotronex in your body, which could increase its actions and side effects. 
 *  take Rozerem(r) (ramelteon) because LUVOX CR can increase the amount of Rozerem in your body, which could increase its actions and side effects. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking LUVOX CR Capsules? Ask if you are not sure.  
 

 Before starting LUVOX CR Capsules, tell your healthcare provider if you: 



 *  are taking certain drugs such as: Clozaril(r) (clozapine): used to treat schizophrenia Mexitil(r) (mexiletine): used to treat problems with heart rhythm Triptans: used to treat migraine headache Medicines used to treat mood, anxiety, psychotic or thought disorders, including tricyclics, lithium, SSRIs, SNRIs, or antipsychotics Tramadol: used to reduce pain Benzodiazepines: used to reduce anxiety, stress, emotional upset, or seizures; helps you sleep; helps with alcohol withdrawal; reduces restlessness; and relaxes muscles Methadone: used to relieve pain or to help with addiction Theophylline used to treat swollen air passages in your lungs, to relax the muscles in your chest to ease shortness of breath, often to treat asthma Warfarin and other drugs that affect how your blood clots Diuretics to treat high blood pressure, congestive heart failure, or swelling Over-the-counter supplements such as tryptophan or St. John's Wort 
 *  have liver problems 
 *  have kidney problems 
 *  have heart problems 
 *  have or had seizures or convulsions 
 *  have bipolar disorder or mania 
 *  have low sodium levels in your blood 
 *  have a history of a stroke 
 *  have high blood pressure 
 *  have or had bleeding problems 
 *  are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. It is not known if LUVOX CR Capsules will harm your unborn baby. Talk to your healthcare provider about the benefits and risks of treating obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD) during pregnancy 
 *  are breast-feeding or plan to breast-feed. Some LUVOX CR may pass into your breast milk. Talk to your healthcare provider about the best way to feed your baby while taking LUVOX CR Capsules. 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines that you take,   including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. LUVOX CR Capsules and some medicines may interact with each other, may not work as well, or may cause serious side effects. 
 

 Your healthcare provider or pharmacist can tell you if it is safe to take LUVOX CR Capsules with your other medicines. Do not start or stop any medicine while taking LUVOX CR Capsules without talking to your healthcare provider first. 



   

  If you take LUVOX CR Capsules, you should not take any other medicines that contain fluvoxamine maleate including: Fluvoxamine Maleate Immediate-Release Tablets.



     How should I take LUVOX CR Capsules?   



 *  Take LUVOX CR Capsules at night exactly as prescribed. Your healthcare provider may need to change the dose of LUVOX CR Capsules until it is the right dose for you. 
 *  LUVOX CR Capsules may be taken with or without food. 
 *  If you miss a dose of LUVOX CR Capsules, take the missed dose as soon as you remember. If it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and take your next dose at the regular time. Do not take two doses of LUVOX CR Capsules at the same time. 
 *  If you take too much LUVOX CR, call your healthcare provider or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What should I avoid while taking LUVOX CR Capsules?   
 

 LUVOX CR Capsules can cause sleepiness or may affect your ability to make decisions, think clearly, or react quickly. You should not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how LUVOX CR Capsules affect you. Do not drink alcohol while using LUVOX CR Capsules. 



   What are the possible side effects of LUVOX CR Capsules?   



 LUVOX CR may cause serious side effects, including all of those described in the section entitled "What is the most important information I should know about LUVOX CR?" 



 Common possible side effects in people who take fluvoxamine include: 



 *  Nausea 
 *  Sleepiness 
 *  Weakness 
 *  Dizziness 
 *  Feeling anxious 
 *  Trouble sleeping 
 *  Sexual problems 
 *  Sweating 
 *  Shaking 
 *  Not feeling hungry 
 *  Dry mouth 
 *  Diarrhea 
 *  Muscle pain 
 *  Sore throat 
 *  Throwing up 
 *  Upset stomach 
 *  Yawning 
    Other side effects in children and adolescents taking fluvoxamine include: 
 

 *   abnormal increase in muscle movement or agitation depression heavy menstrual periods flatulence (gas) rash 
    Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away. These are not all the possible side effects of LUVOX CR Capsules. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist. 
 

   CALL YOUR DOCTOR FOR MEDICAL ADVICE ABOUT SIDE EFFECTS. YOU MAY REPORT SIDE EFFECTS TO FDA AT 1-800-FDA-1088.   



   How should I store LUVOX CR Capsules?   



 *  Store LUVOX CR Capsules at 59 degrees F to 86 degrees F (15 degrees C to 30 degrees C). 
 *  Keep LUVOX CR Capsules away from high temperatures (above 86 degrees F or 30 degrees C) and high humidity (dampness). 
 *  Keep the LUVOX CR Capsules bottle closed tightly. 
      Keep LUVOX CR Capsules and all medicines out of the reach of children.  
 

   General information about LUVOX CR Capsules  Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use LUVOX CR Capsules for a condition for which it was not prescribed. Do not give LUVOX CR Capsules to other people, even if they have the same condition. It may harm them. 



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about LUVOX CR Capsules. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You may ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for information about LUVOX CR Capsules that is written for healthcare professionals. 



 For more information about LUVOX CR Capsules, call (1-800-520-5568) or go to   jazzsafety@jazzpharma.com  .



   What are the ingredients in LUVOX CR Capsules?  



 Active ingredient: fluvoxamine maleate Inactive ingredients: 



 *  Extended-Release Capsules: ammonio methacrylate copolymer type B, dibutyl sebacate, colorants (FD&amp;C Blue No. 2, Opacode Grey, red iron oxide, titanium dioxide), gelatin (porcine- or bovine-derived), sugar spheres, and talc. LUVOX CR Capsules are gluten-free. 
    Distributed by Jazz Pharmaceuticals, Inc. Palo Alto CA 94304 
 

 Revised July 2014



 This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. 



 LUVOX CR  (r)   is a registered trademark of Abbott Products, Inc. 



 LCR-MG Rev 0714
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Clinical Worsening/Suicide Risk: Monitor for clinical worsening of suicidal thoughts/behaviors especially during the initial months of therapy and at times of dose changes (  5.1  ) . 
 *     Bipolar Disorder: Screen for bipolar disorder (  5.1  ) . 
 *     Serotonin Syndrome: Serotonin syndrome has been reported with SSRIs and SNRIs, including LUVOX CR Capsules, both when taken alone, but especially when co-administered with other serotonergic agents (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort). If such symptoms occur, discontinue LUVOX CR Capsules and initiate supportive treatment. If concomitant use of LUVOX CR Capsules with other serotonergic drugs is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonim syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases (  5.2  ) . 
 *     Angle Closure Glaucome: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants (   5.3   ). 
 *     Other Potentially Important Drug Interactions:  Benzodiazepines: Use with caution. Coadministration with diazepam is generally not advisable (  5.9  ) . Clozapine: Clozapine levels may be increased and produce orthostatic hypotension or seizures (  5.9  ) . Methadone: Coadministration may produce opioid intoxication. Discontinuation of fluvoxamine may produce opioid withdrawal (  5.9  ) . Mexiletine: Monitor serum mexiletine levels (  5.9  ) . Theophylline: Clearance decreased; reduce theophylline dose by one-third (  5.9  ) . Warfarin: Plasma concentrations increased and prothrombin times prolonged; monitor prothrombin time and adjust warfarin dose accordingly (  5.9  ) . 
 *     Discontinuation: Symptoms associated with discontinuation have been reported (  5.10  ) . In the absence of an emergency, abrupt discontinuation not recommended (  2.7  ,  5.2  ) . 
 *     Abnormal Bleeding: May increase bleeding risk, especially when used with NSAIDs, aspirin, warfarin, or other drugs that affect coagulation (  5.11  ) . 
 *     Activation of Mania/Hypomania has occurred (  5.12  ) . 
 *     Seizures: Avoid administering fluvoxamine in patients with unstable epilepsy; monitor patients with controlled epilepsy; discontinue treatment if seizures occur or frequency increases (  5.13  ) . 
 *     Hyponatremia: May occur with SSRIs and SNRIs, including LUVOX CR Capsules. The elderly may be at increased risk. Consider discontinuing in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia (  5.14  ) . 
 *     Concomitant Illness: Use caution in patients with diseases or conditions that affect hemodynamic responses or metabolism. Patients with impaired liver function may require a lower starting dose and slower titration (    5.15    ) . 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



       Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. The pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults age 65 and older.



      The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in  Table 1  .



 TABLE 1 DRUG-PLACEBO DIFFERENCES IN NUMBER OF CASES OF SUICIDALITY PER 1000 PATIENTS TREATED 
  Age Range                                         Drug-Related Increases                                
       &lt;18                                               14 additional cases                              
       18-24                                             5 additional cases                               
  Age Range                                         Drug-Related Decreases                                
       25-64                                             1 fewer case                                     
       &gt;= 65                                             6 fewer cases                                    
         
 

      No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about the drug effect on suicide.



      It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



       All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



      The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



      Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



      If the decision has been made to discontinue treatment, medication should be tapered, as rapidly as is feasible, but with recognition that abrupt discontinuation can be associated with certain symptoms (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION-Discontinuation of Treatment with LUVOX CR Capsules  [  2.7  ]  , for a description of the risks of discontinuation of LUVOX CR Capsules  ).



       Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers  . Prescriptions for LUVOX CR Capsules should be written for the smallest quantity of capsules consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



       Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder:  A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described above represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It should be noted that LUVOX CR Capsules are not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



       The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs, including LUVOX CR Capsules, alone but particularly with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort), and with drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (in particular, MAOIs, both those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue).



      Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome.



      The concomitant use of LUVOX CR Capsules with MAOIs intended to treat psychiatric disorders is contraindicated. LUVOX CR should also not be started in a patient who is being treated with MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue. All reports with methylene blue that provided information on the route of administration involved intravenous administration in the dose range of 1 mg/kg to 8 mg/kg. No reports involved the administration of methylene blue by other routes (such as oral tablets or local tissue injection) or at lower doses. There may be circumstances when it is necessary to initiate treatment with an MAOI such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue in a patient taking LUVOX CR. LUVOX CR should be discontinued before initiating treatment with the MAOI (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  [  4.1  ]  and  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  [  2.5  ,  2.6  ]  ).



      If concomitant use of LUVOX CR Capsules with other serotonergic drugs, including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort, is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases.



      Treatment with LUVOX CR Capsules and any concomitant serotonergic agents should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur, and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



     5.3 Angle Closure Glaucoma  



   Angle-Closure Glaucoma: The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including Luvox CR may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.  



    5.4 Potential Thioridazine Interaction



       The effect of fluvoxamine (25 mg immediate-release tablets given twice daily for one week) on thioridazine steady-state concentrations was evaluated in 10 male inpatients with schizophrenia. Concentrations of thioridazine and its two active metabolites, mesoridazine and sulforidazine, increased 3-fold following coadministration of fluvoxamine.



      Thioridazine administration produces a dose-related prolongation of the QTc interval, which is associated with serious ventricular arrhythmias, such as torsades de pointes-type arrhythmias, and sudden death. It is likely that this experience underestimates the degree of risk that might occur with higher doses of thioridazine. Moreover, the effect of fluvoxamine may be even more pronounced when it is administered at higher doses.



      Therefore, LUVOX CR Capsules should not be coadministered with thioridazine (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  [  4  ]  ).



    5.5 Potential Tizanidine Interaction



       Fluvoxamine is a potent inhibitor of CYP1A2, and tizanidine is a CYP1A2 substrate. The effect of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets (100 mg daily for four days) on the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of a single dose of tizanidine has been studied in 10 healthy male subjects. Tizanidine Cmaxwas increased approximately 12-fold (range 5-fold to 32-fold), elimination half-life was increased by almost 3-fold, and AUC increased 33-fold (range 14-fold to 103-fold). The mean maximal effect on blood pressure was a 35 mm Hg decrease in systolic blood pressure, a 20 mm Hg decrease in diastolic blood pressure, and a 4 beat/min decrease in heart rate. Drowsiness was significantly increased, and performance on the psychomotor task was significantly impaired. LUVOX CR Capsules and tizanidine should not be used together (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  [  4  ]  ).



    5.6 Potential Pimozide Interaction



       Pimozide is metabolized by the CYP3A4 isozyme and it has been demonstrated that ketoconazole, a potent inhibitor of CYP3A4, blocks the metabolism of this drug, resulting in increased plasma concentrations of parent drug. An increased plasma concentration of pimozide causes QT prolongation and has been associated with torsades de pointes-type ventricular tachycardia, sometimes fatal. As noted below, a substantial pharmacokinetic interaction has been observed for fluvoxamine in combination with alprazolam, a drug that is known to be metabolized by the CYP3A4 isozyme. Although it has not been definitively demonstrated that fluvoxamine is a potent CYP3A4 inhibitor, it is likely to be, given the substantial interaction of fluvoxamine with alprazolam. Consequently, it is recommended that fluvoxamine not be used in combination with pimozide (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  [  4  ]  ).



    5.7 Potential Alosetron Interaction



       In a pharmacokinetic study, 40 healthy female subjects received fluvoxamine in escalating doses from 50 to 200 mg/day for 16 days with coadministration of alosetron 1 mg on the last day. Fluvoxamine increased mean alosetron plasma concentrations (AUC) approximately 6-fold and prolonged the half-life by approximately 3-fold. Consequently, it is recommended that LUVOX CR Capsules not be used in combination with alosetron (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  [  4  ]  and Lotronex  (r)  (alosetron) package insert).



    5.8 Potential Ramelteon Interaction



       When immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets 100 mg twice daily were administered for 3 days prior to single-dose coadministration of ramelteon 16 mg and immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets, the AUC for ramelteon increased approximately 190-fold and the Cmaxincreased approximately 70-fold compared to ramelteon administered alone. Ramelteon should not be used in combination with LUVOX CR Capsules (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  [  4  ]  ).



    5.9 Other Potentially Important Drug Interactions



         Benzodiazepines:    Benzodiazepines metabolized by hepatic oxidation (e.g., alprazolam, midazolam, triazolam, etc.) should be used with caution because the clearance of these drugs is likely to be reduced by fluvoxamine. The clearance of benzodiazepines metabolized by glucuronidation (e.g., lorazepam, oxazepam, temazepam) is unlikely to be affected by fluvoxamine.



            Alprazolam -  When immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets (100 mg given once daily) and alprazolam (1 mg given 4 times per day) were coadministered to steady state, plasma concentrations and other pharmacokinetic parameters (AUC, Cmax, T1/2) of alprazolam were approximately twice those observed when alprazolam was administered alone; oral clearance was reduced by about 50%. The elevated plasma alprazolam concentrations resulted in decreased psychomotor performance and memory. This interaction, which has not been investigated using higher doses of fluvoxamine, may be more pronounced if a 300 mg daily dose is coadministered, particularly since fluvoxamine exhibits non-linear pharmacokinetics over the dosage range 100-300 mg. If alprazolam is coadministered with LUVOX CR Capsules, the initial alprazolam dosage should be at least halved and titration to the lowest effective dose is recommended. No dosage adjustment is required for LUVOX CR Capsules.



            Diazepam -  The coadministration of LUVOX CR Capsules and diazepam is generally not advisable. Because fluvoxamine reduces the clearance of both diazepam and its active metabolite, N-desmethyldiazepam, there is a strong likelihood of substantial accumulation of both species during chronic coadministration.



      Evidence supporting the conclusion that it is inadvisable to coadminister fluvoxamine and diazepam is derived from a study in which healthy volunteers taking 150 mg/day of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets were administered a single oral dose of 10 mg of diazepam. In these subjects (N=8), the clearance of diazepam was reduced by 65% and that of N-desmethyldiazepam to a level that was too low to measure over the course of the 2-week-long study.



      It is likely that this experience significantly underestimates the degree of accumulation that might occur with repeated diazepam administration. Moreover, as noted with alprazolam, the effect of fluvoxamine may even be more pronounced when it is administered at higher doses.



      Accordingly, diazepam and fluvoxamine should not ordinarily be coadministered.



        Clozapine:    Elevated serum levels of clozapine have been reported in patients taking immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets and clozapine. Since clozapine-related seizures and orthostatic hypotension appear to be dose related, the risk of these adverse reactions may be higher when fluvoxamine and clozapine are coadministered. Patients should be closely monitored when LUVOX CR Capsules and clozapine are used concurrently.



        Methadone:    Significantly increased methadone (plasma level:dose) ratios have been reported when immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets were administered to patients receiving maintenance methadone treatment, with symptoms of opioid intoxication in one patient. Opioid withdrawal symptoms were reported following fluvoxamine maleate discontinuation in another patient.



        Mexiletine:    The effect of steady-state fluvoxamine (50 mg given twice daily for 7 days) on the single dose pharmacokinetics of mexiletine (200 mg) was evaluated in 6 healthy Japanese males. The clearance of mexiletine was reduced by 38% following coadministration with fluvoxamine compared to mexiletine alone. If fluvoxamine and mexiletine are coadministered, serum mexiletine levels should be monitored.



        Theophylline:    The effect of steady-state immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets (50 mg tablets given twice daily) on the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of theophylline (375 mg as 442 mg aminophylline) was evaluated in 12 healthy non-smoking, male volunteers. The clearance of theophylline was decreased approximately 3-fold. Therefore, if theophylline is coadministered with fluvoxamine maleate, its dose should be reduced to one-third of the usual daily maintenance dose and plasma concentrations of theophylline should be monitored. No dosage adjustment is required for LUVOX CR Capsules.



        Warfarin and Other Drugs That Interfere With Hemostasis (NSAIDs, Aspirin, etc.):    Serotonin release by platelets plays an important role in hemostasis. Epidemiological studies of the case-control and cohort design have demonstrated an association between use of psychotropic drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of upper gastrointestinal bleeding. These studies have also shown that concurrent use of an NSAID or aspirin may potentiate this risk of bleeding. Thus, patients should be cautioned about the use of such drugs concurrently with fluvoxamine (see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS-Abnormal Bleeding  [  5.10  ]  ).



            Warfarin -  When immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets (50 mg given three times daily) were administered concomitantly with warfarin for two weeks, warfarin plasma concentrations increased by 98% and prothrombin times were prolonged. Thus patients receiving oral anticoagulants and LUVOX CR Capsules should have their prothrombin time monitored and their anticoagulant dose adjusted accordingly. No dosage adjustment is required for LUVOX CR Capsules.



    5.10 Discontinuation of Treatment



       During marketing of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets and other SSRIs and SNRIs (serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors), there have been spontaneous reports of adverse reactions occurring upon discontinuation of these drugs, particularly when abrupt, including the following: dysphoric mood, irritability, agitation, dizziness, sensory disturbances (e.g., paresthesias, such as electric shock sensations), anxiety, confusion, headache, lethargy, emotional lability, insomnia, and hypomania. While these reactions are generally self-limiting, there have been reports of serious discontinuation symptoms.



      Patients should be monitored for these symptoms when discontinuing treatment with LUVOX CR Capsules. A gradual reduction in the dose rather than abrupt cessation is recommended whenever possible. If intolerable symptoms occur following a decrease in the dose or upon discontinuation of treatment, then resuming the previously prescribed dose may be considered. Subsequently, the health care provider may continue decreasing the dose but at a more gradual rate (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  [  2.7  ]  ).



    5.11 Abnormal Bleeding



       SSRIs and SNRIs, including LUVOX CR Capsules, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, warfarin, and other anticoagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding events related to SSRIs and SNRIs use have ranged from ecchymoses, hematomas, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages.



      Patients should be cautioned about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of LUVOX CR Capsules and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation (see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  [  5.8  ]  ).



    5.12 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



       During premarketing studies of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets involving primarily depressed patients, hypomania or mania occurred in approximately 1% of patients treated with fluvoxamine. In a 10-week pediatric OCD study, 2 out of 57 patients (4%) treated with fluvoxamine experienced manic reactions, compared to none of 63 placebo patients. Activation of mania/hypomania has also been reported in a small proportion of patients with major affective disorder who were treated with other marketed antidepressants. As with all antidepressants, LUVOX CR Capsules should be used cautiously in patients with a history of mania.



    5.13 Seizures



       During premarketing studies with immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets, seizures were reported in 0.2% of fluvoxamine-treated patients. Caution is recommended when the drug is administered to patients with a history of convulsive disorders. Fluvoxamine should be avoided in patients with unstable epilepsy, and patients with controlled epilepsy should be carefully monitored. Treatment with fluvoxamine should be discontinued if seizures occur or if seizure frequency increases.



    5.14 Hyponatremia



       Hyponatremia may occur as a result of treatment with SSRIs and SNRIs, including LUVOX CR Capsules. In many cases, this hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with SSRIs and SNRIs (see  USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS, Geriatric Use  [  8.5  ]  ). Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume depleted may be at greater risk. Discontinuation of LUVOX CR Capsules should be considered in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia and appropriate medical intervention should be instituted.



      Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which may lead to falls. Signs and symptoms associated with more severe and/or acute cases have included hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.15 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



       Closely monitored clinical experience with LUVOX CR Capsules in patients with concomitant systemic illness is limited. Caution is advised in administering LUVOX CR Capsules to patients with diseases or conditions that could affect hemodynamic responses or metabolism.



      LUVOX CR Capsules or immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets have not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were systematically excluded from many clinical studies during premarketing testing of these products. Evaluation of the electrocardiograms for patients with depression or OCD who participated in premarketing studies revealed no differences between fluvoxamine and placebo in the emergence of clinically important ECG changes.



       Patients with Hepatic Impairment -  In patients with liver dysfunction, following administration of immediate-release fluvoxamine maleate tablets, fluvoxamine clearance was decreased by approximately 30%. Patients with liver dysfunction should begin with a low dose of LUVOX CR Capsules and increase it slowly with careful monitoring.



    5.16 Laboratory Tests



       There are no specific laboratory tests recommended.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
