<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="lyrica1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5% and twice placebo) are dizziness, somnolence, dry mouth, edema, blurred vision, weight gain and thinking abnormal (primarily difficulty with concentration/attention). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer at (800) 438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In all controlled and uncontrolled trials across various patient populations during the premarketing development of LYRICA, more than 10,000 patients have received LYRICA. Approximately 5000 patients were treated for 6 months or more, over 3100 patients were treated for 1 year or longer, and over 1400 patients were treated for at least 2 years.



     Adverse Reactions Most Commonly Leading to Discontinuation in All Premarketing Controlled Clinical Studies  



 In premarketing controlled trials of all populations combined, 14% of patients treated with LYRICA and 7% of patients treated with placebo discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions. In the LYRICA treatment group, the adverse reactions most frequently leading to discontinuation were dizziness (4%) and somnolence (4%). In the placebo group, 1% of patients withdrew due to dizziness and &lt;1% withdrew due to somnolence. Other adverse reactions that led to discontinuation from controlled trials more frequently in the LYRICA group compared to the placebo group were ataxia, confusion, asthenia, thinking abnormal, blurred vision, incoordination, and peripheral edema (1% each).



     Most Common Adverse Reactions in All Premarketing Controlled Clinical Studies  



 In premarketing controlled trials of all patient populations combined, dizziness, somnolence, dry mouth, edema, blurred vision, weight gain, and "thinking abnormal" (primarily difficulty with concentration/attention) were more commonly reported by subjects treated with LYRICA than by subjects treated with placebo (&gt;=5% and twice the rate of that seen in placebo).



     Controlled Studies with Neuropathic Pain Associated with Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy  



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  



 In clinical trials in patients with neuropathic pain associated with diabetic peripheral neuropathy, 9% of patients treated with LYRICA and 4% of patients treated with placebo discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions. In the LYRICA treatment group, the most common reasons for discontinuation due to adverse reactions were dizziness (3%) and somnolence (2%). In comparison, &lt;1% of placebo patients withdrew due to dizziness and somnolence. Other reasons for discontinuation from the trials, occurring with greater frequency in the LYRICA group than in the placebo group, were asthenia, confusion, and peripheral edema. Each of these events led to withdrawal in approximately 1% of patients.



     Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 Table 3 lists all adverse reactions, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;=1% of patients with neuropathic pain associated with diabetic neuropathy in the combined LYRICA group for which the incidence was greater in this combined LYRICA group than in the placebo group. A majority of pregabalin-treated patients in clinical studies had adverse reactions with a maximum intensity of "mild" or "moderate".



 Table 3. Treatment-emergent adverse reaction incidence in controlled trials in neuropathic pain associated with diabetic peripheral neuropathy (events in at least 1% of all LYRICA-treated patients and at least numerically more in all LYRICA than in the placebo group) 
 Body systemPreferred term      75 mg/day     150 mg/day    300 mg/day    600 mg/day     All PGB       Placebo      
                                 [N=77]%       [N=212]%      [N=321]%      [N=369]%      [N=979]%      [N=459]%     
  
   Body as a whole                                                                                                  
 Asthenia                           4             2             4             7             5             2         
 Accidental injury                  5             2             2             6             4             3         
 Back pain                          0             2             1             2             2             0         
 Chest pain                         4             1             1             2             2             1         
 Face edema                         0             1             1             2             1             0         
   Digestive system                                                                                                 
 Dry mouth                          3             2             5             7             5             1         
 Constipation                       0             2             4             6             4             2         
 Flatulence                         3             0             2             3             2             1         
   Metabolic andnutritional disorders     
 Peripheral edema                   4             6             9             12            9             2         
 Weight gain                        0             4             4             6             4             0         
 Edema                              0             2             4             2             2             0         
 Hypoglycemia                       1             3             2             1             2             1         
   Nervous system                                                                                                   
 Dizziness                          8             9             23            29            21            5         
 Somnolence                         4             6             13            16            12            3         
 Neuropathy                         9             2             2             5             4             3         
 Ataxia                             6             1             2             4             3             1         
 Vertigo                            1             2             2             4             3             1         
 Confusion                          0             1             2             3             2             1         
 Euphoria                           0             0             3             2             2             0         
 Incoordination                     1             0             2             2             2             0         
 Thinking abnormal                  1             0             1             3             2             0         
 Tremor                             1             1             1             2             1             0         
 Abnormal gait                      1             0             1             3             1             0         
 Amnesia                            3             1             0             2             1             0         
 Nervousness                        0             1             1             1             1             0         
   Respiratory system                                                                                               
 Dyspnea                            3             0             2             2             2             1         
   Special senses                                                                                                   
 Blurry vision                      3             1             3             6             4             2         
 Abnormal vision                    1             0             1             1             1             0         
                 Controlled Studies in Postherpetic Neuralgia  
 

     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  



 In clinical trials in patients with postherpetic neuralgia, 14% of patients treated with LYRICA and 7% of patients treated with placebo discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions. In the LYRICA treatment group, the most common reasons for discontinuation due to adverse reactions were dizziness (4%) and somnolence (3%). In comparison, less than 1% of placebo patients withdrew due to dizziness and somnolence. Other reasons for discontinuation from the trials, occurring in greater frequency in the LYRICA group than in the placebo group, were confusion (2%), as well as peripheral edema, asthenia, ataxia, and abnormal gait (1% each).



     Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 Table 4 lists all adverse reactions, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;= 1% of patients with neuropathic pain associated with postherpetic neuralgia in the combined LYRICA group for which the incidence was greater in this combined LYRICA group than in the placebo group. In addition, an event is included, even if the incidence in the all LYRICA group is not greater than in the placebo group, if the incidence of the event in the 600 mg/day group is more than twice that in the placebo group. A majority of pregabalin-treated patients in clinical studies had adverse reactions with a maximum intensity of "mild" or "moderate". Overall, 12.4% of all pregabalin-treated patients and 9.0% of all placebo-treated patients had at least one severe event while 8% of pregabalin-treated patients and 4.3% of placebo-treated patients had at least one severe treatment-related adverse event.



 Table 4. Treatment-emergent adverse reaction incidence in controlled trials in neuropathic pain associated with postherpetic neuralgia (events in at least 1% of all LYRICA-treated patients and at least numerically more in all LYRICA than in the placebo group) 
 Body systemPreferred term       75 mg/d       150 mg/d      300 mg/d      600 mg/d      All PGB       Placebo      
                                 [N=84]%       [N=302]%      [N=312]%      [N=154]%      [N=852]%      [N=398]%     
  
   Body as a whole                                                                                                  
 Infection                          14            8             6             3             7             4         
 Headache                           5             9             5             8             7             5         
 Pain                               5             4             5             5             5             4         
 Accidental injury                  4             3             3             5             3             2         
 Flu syndrome                       1             2             2             1             2             1         
 Face edema                         0             2             1             3             2             1         
   Digestive system                                                                                                 
 Dry mouth                          7             7             6             15            8             3         
 Constipation                       4             5             5             5             5             2         
 Flatulence                         2             1             2             3             2             1         
 Vomiting                           1             1             3             3             2             1         
   Metabolic andnutritional disorders     
 Peripheral edema                   0             8             16            16            12            4         
 Weight gain                        1             2             5             7             4             0         
 Edema                              0             1             2             6             2             1         
   Musculoskeletal system       
 Myasthenia                         1             1             1             1             1             0         
   Nervous system                                                                                                   
 Dizziness                          11            18            31            37            26            9         
 Somnolence                         8             12            18            25            16            5         
 Ataxia                             1             2             5             9             5             1         
 Abnormal gait                      0             2             4             8             4             1         
 Confusion                          1             2             3             7             3             0         
 Thinking abnormal                  0             2             1             6             2             2         
 Incoordination                     2             2             1             3             2             0         
 Amnesia                            0             1             1             4             2             0         
 Speech disorder                    0             0             1             3             1             0         
   Respiratory system                                                                                               
 Bronchitis                         0             1             1             3             1             1         
   Special senses                                                                                                   
 Blurry vision                      1             5             5             9             5             3         
 Diplopia                           0             2             2             4             2             0         
 Abnormal vision                    0             1             2             5             2             0         
 Eye Disorder                       0             1             1             2             1             0         
   Urogenital System            
 Urinary Incontinence               0             1             1             2             1             0         
                 Controlled Add-On Studies in Adjunctive Therapy for Adult Patients with Partial Onset Seizures  
 

     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  



 Approximately 15% of patients receiving LYRICA and 6% of patients receiving placebo in add-on epilepsy trials discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions. In the LYRICA treatment group, the adverse reactions most frequently leading to discontinuation were dizziness (6%), ataxia (4%), and somnolence (3%). In comparison, &lt;1% of patients in the placebo group withdrew due to each of these events. Other adverse reactions that led to discontinuation of at least 1% of patients in the LYRICA group and at least twice as frequently compared to the placebo group were asthenia, diplopia, blurred vision, thinking abnormal, nausea, tremor, vertigo, headache, and confusion (which each led to withdrawal in 2% or less of patients).



     Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 Table 5 lists all dose-related adverse reactions occurring in at least 2% of all LYRICA-treated patients. Dose-relatedness was defined as the incidence of the adverse event in the 600 mg/day group was at least 2% greater than the rate in both the placebo and 150 mg/day groups. In these studies, 758 patients received LYRICA and 294 patients received placebo for up to 12 weeks. Because patients were also treated with 1 to 3 other AEDs, it is not possible to determine whether the following adverse reactions can be ascribed to LYRICA alone, or the combination of LYRICA and other AEDs. A majority of pregabalin-treated patients in clinical studies had adverse reactions with a maximum intensity of "mild" or "moderate".



 Table 5. Dose-related treatment-emergent adverse reaction incidence in controlled trials in adjunctive therapy for adult patients with partial onset seizures (events in at least 2% of all LYRICA-treated patients and the adverse reaction in the 600 mg/day group was &gt;=2% the rate in both the placebo and 150 mg/day groups) 
 Body SystemPreferred Term  150 mg/d[N = 185]%  300 mg/d[N = 90]%  600 mg/d[N = 395]%  All PGB[N = 670]%  Placebo[N = 294]%   
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                                
 Accidental Injury                 7               11               10                9                5          
 Pain                              3                2                5                4                3          
   Digestive System                                                                                               
 Increased Appetite                2                3                6                5                1          
 Dry Mouth                         1                2                6                4                1          
 Constipation                      1                1                7                4                2          
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                      
 Weight Gain                       5                7               16               12                1          
 Peripheral Edema                  3                3                6                5                2          
   Nervous System                                                                                                 
 Dizziness                        18               31               38               32               11          
 Somnolence                       11               18               28               22               11          
 Ataxia                            6               10               20               15                4          
 Tremor                            3                7               11                8                4          
 Thinking Abnormal                 4                8                9                8                2          
 Amnesia                           3                2                6                5                2          
 Speech Disorder                   1                2                7                5                1          
 Incoordination                    1                3                6                4                1          
 Abnormal Gait                     1                3                5                4                0          
 Twitching                         0                4                5                4                1          
 Confusion                         1                2                5                4                2          
 Myoclonus                         1                0                4                2                0          
   Special Senses                                                                                                 
 Blurred Vision                    5                8               12               10                4          
 Diplopia                          5                7               12                9                4          
 Abnormal Vision                   3                1                5                4                1          
                Controlled Studies with Fibromyalgia  
 

     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  



 In clinical trials of patients with fibromyalgia, 19% of patients treated with pregabalin (150-600 mg/day) and 10% of patients treated with placebo discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions. In the pregabalin treatment group, the most common reasons for discontinuation due to adverse reactions were dizziness (6%) and somnolence (3%). In comparison, &lt;1% of placebo-treated patients withdrew due to dizziness and somnolence. Other reasons for discontinuation from the trials, occurring with greater frequency in the pregabalin treatment group than in the placebo treatment group, were fatigue, headache, balance disorder, and weight increased. Each of these adverse reactions led to withdrawal in approximately 1% of patients.



     Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 Table 6 lists all adverse reactions, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;=2% of patients with fibromyalgia in the 'all pregabalin' treatment group for which the incidence was greater than in the placebo treatment group. A majority of pregabalin-treated patients in clinical studies experienced adverse reactions with a maximum intensity of "mild" or "moderate".



 Table 6. Treatment-emergent adverse reaction incidence in controlled trials in fibromyalgia (events) in at least 2% of all LYRICA-treated patients and occurring more frequently in the all pregabalin-group than in the placebo treatment group) 
 System Organ ClassPreferred term    150mg/d       300mg/d       450mg/d       600mg/d       All PGB       Placebo      
                                 [N=132]%      [N=502]%      [N=505]%      [N=378]%     [N=1517]%      [N=505]%     
  
   Ear and LabyrinthDisorders     
 Vertigo                            2             2             2             1             2             0         
   Eye Disorders                                                                                                    
 Vision blurred                     8             7             7             12            8             1         
   GastrointestinalDisorders     
 Dry mouth                          7             6             9             9             8             2         
 Constipation                       4             4             7             10            7             2         
 Vomiting                           2             3             3             2             3             2         
 Flatulence                         1             1             2             2             2             1         
 Abdominal distension               2             2             2             2             2             1         
   General Disorders andAdministrative SiteConditions     
 Fatigue                            5             7             6             8             7             4         
 Edema peripheral                   5             5             6             9             6             2         
 Chest pain                         2             1             1             2             2             1         
 Feeling abnormal                   1             3             2             2             2             0         
 Edema                              1             2             1             2             2             1         
 Feeling drunk                      1             2             1             2             2             0         
   Infections andInfestations     
 Sinusitis                          4             5             7             5             5             4         
   Investigations               
 Weight increased                   8             10            10            14            11            2         
   Metabolism andNutrition Disorders     
 Increased appetite                 4             3             5             7             5             1         
 Fluid retention                    2             3             3             2             2             1         
   Musculoskeletal andConnective TissueDisorders     
 Arthralgia                         4             3             3             6             4             2         
 Muscle spasms                      2             4             4             4             4             2         
 Back pain                          2             3             4             3             3             3         
   Nervous SystemDisorders      
 Dizziness                          23            31            43            45            38            9         
 Somnolence                         13            18            22            22            20            4         
 Headache                           11            12            14            10            12            12        
 Disturbance in attention           4             4             6             6             5             1         
 Balance disorder                   2             3             6             9             5             0         
 Memory impairment                  1             3             4             4             3             0         
 Coordination abnormal              2             1             2             2             2             1         
 Hypoesthesia                       2             2             3             2             2             1         
 Lethargy                           2             2             1             2             2             0         
 Tremor                             0             1             3             2             2             0         
   Psychiatric Disorders        
 Euphoric Mood                      2             5             6             7             6             1         
 Confusional state                  0             2             3             4             3             0         
 Anxiety                            2             2             2             2             2             1         
 Disorientation                     1             0             2             1             2             0         
 Depression                         2             2             2             2             2             2         
   Respiratory, Thoracicand Mediastinal Disorders     
 Pharyngolaryngeal pain             2             1             3             3             2             2         
                 Controlled Studies in Neuropathic Pain Associated with Spinal Cord Injury  
 

     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  



 In clinical trials of patients with neuropathic pain associated with spinal cord injury, 13% of patients treated with pregabalin and 10% of patients treated with placebo discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions. In the pregabalin treatment group, the most common reasons for discontinuation due to adverse reactions were somnolence (3%) and edema (2%). In comparison, none of the placebo-treated patients withdrew due to somnolence and edema. Other reasons for discontinuation from the trials, occurring with greater frequency in the pregabalin treatment group than in the placebo treatment group, were fatigue and balance disorder. Each of these adverse reactions led to withdrawal in less than 2% of patients.



     Most Common Adverse Reactions  



 Table 7 lists all adverse reactions, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;=2% of patients with neuropathic pain associated with spinal cord injury in the controlled trials. A majority of pregabalin-treated patients in clinical studies experienced adverse reactions with a maximum intensity of "mild" or "moderate".



 Table 7. Treatment-emergent adverse reaction incidence in controlled trials in neuropathic pain associated with spinal cord injury (events in at least 2% of all LYRICA-treated patients and occurring more frequently in the all pregabalin-group than in the placebo treatment group) 
 System Organ ClassPreferred term                           PGB(N=182)               Placebo (N=174)        
 %                                                               %               
  
   Ear and labryrinth disorders                       
 Vertigo                                                        2.7                        1.1              
   Eye disorders                                      
 Vision blurred                                                 6.6                        1.1              
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
 Dry mouth                                                     11.0                        2.9              
 Constipation                                                   8.2                        5.7              
 Nausea                                                         4.9                        4.0              
 Vomiting                                                       2.7                        1.1              
   General disorders andadministration site conditions     
 Fatigue                                                       11.0                        4.0              
 Edema peripheral                                              10.4                        5.2              
 Edema                                                          8.2                        1.1              
 Pain                                                           3.3                        1.1              
   Infections and infestations                        
 Nasopharyngitis                                                8.2                        4.6              
   Investigations                                     
 Weight increased                                               3.3                        1.1              
 Blood creatine phosphokinase increased                         2.7                         0               
   Musculoskeletal andconnective tissue disorders     
 Muscular weakness                                              4.9                        1.7              
 Pain in extremity                                              3.3                        2.3              
 Neck pain                                                      2.7                        1.1              
 Back pain                                                      2.2                        1.7              
 Joint swelling                                                 2.2                         0               
   Nervous system disorders                           
 Somnolence                                                    35.7                       11.5              
 Dizziness                                                     20.9                        6.9              
 Disturbance in attention                                       3.8                         0               
 Memory impairment                                              3.3                        1.1              
 Paresthesia                                                    2.2                        0.6              
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
 Insomnia                                                       3.8                        2.9              
 Euphoric mood                                                  2.2                        0.6              
   Renal and urinary disorders                        
 Urinary incontinence                                           2.7                        1.1              
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders             
 Decubitus ulcer                                                2.7                        1.1              
   Vascular disorders                                 
 Hypertension                                                   2.2                        1.1              
 Hypotension                                                    2.2                         0               
             Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Studies of LYRICA  
 

 Following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported by patients treated with LYRICA during all clinical trials. The listing does not include those events already listed in the previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, those events for which a drug cause was remote, those events which were so general as to be uninformative, and those events reported only once which did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life-threatening.



 Events are categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions:  frequent  adverse reactions are those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients;  infrequent  adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients;  rare  reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients. Events of major clinical importance are described in the  Warnings and Precautions  section (5).



 Body as a Whole -  Frequent:  Abdominal pain, Allergic reaction, Fever,  Infrequent:  Abscess, Cellulitis, Chills, Malaise, Neck rigidity, Overdose, Pelvic pain, Photosensitivity reaction,  Rare:  Anaphylactoid reaction, Ascites, Granuloma, Hangover effect, Intentional Injury, Retroperitoneal Fibrosis, Shock



 Cardiovascular System -  Infrequent:  Deep thrombophlebitis, Heart failure, Hypotension, Postural hypotension, Retinal vascular disorder, Syncope;  Rare:  ST Depressed, Ventricular Fibrillation



 Digestive System -  Frequent:  Gastroenteritis, Increased appetite;  Infrequent:  Cholecystitis, Cholelithiasis, Colitis, Dysphagia, Esophagitis, Gastritis, Gastrointestinal hemorrhage, Melena, Mouth ulceration, Pancreatitis, Rectal hemorrhage, Tongue edema;  Rare:  Aphthous stomatitis, Esophageal Ulcer, Periodontal abscess



 Hemic and Lymphatic System -  Frequent:  Ecchymosis;  Infrequent:  Anemia, Eosinophilia, Hypochromic anemia, Leukocytosis, Leukopenia, Lymphadenopathy, Thrombocytopenia;  Rare:  Myelofibrosis, Polycythemia, Prothrombin decreased, Purpura, Thrombocythemia



 Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders -  Rare:  Glucose Tolerance Decreased, Urate Crystalluria



 Musculoskeletal System -  Frequent:  Arthralgia, Leg cramps, Myalgia, Myasthenia;  Infrequent:  Arthrosis;  Rare:  Chondrodystrophy, Generalized Spasm



 Nervous System -  Frequent:  Anxiety, Depersonalization, Hypertonia, Hypoesthesia, Libido decreased, Nystagmus, Paresthesia, Sedation, Stupor, Twitching;  Infrequent:  Abnormal dreams, Agitation, Apathy, Aphasia, Circumoral paresthesia, Dysarthria, Hallucinations, Hostility, Hyperalgesia, Hyperesthesia, Hyperkinesia, Hypokinesia, Hypotonia, Libido increased, Myoclonus, Neuralgia,  Rare:  Addiction, Cerebellar syndrome, Cogwheel rigidity, Coma, Delirium, Delusions, Dysautonomia, Dyskinesia, Dystonia, Encephalopathy, Extrapyramidal syndrome, Guillain-Barre syndrome, Hypalgesia, Intracranial hypertension, Manic reaction, Paranoid reaction, Peripheral neuritis, Personality disorder, Psychotic depression, Schizophrenic reaction, Sleep disorder, Torticollis, Trismus



 Respiratory System -  Rare:  Apnea, Atelectasis, Bronchiolitis, Hiccup, Laryngismus, Lung edema, Lung fibrosis, Yawn



 Skin and Appendages -  Frequent:  Pruritus,  Infrequent:  Alopecia, Dry skin, Eczema, Hirsutism, Skin ulcer, Urticaria, Vesiculobullous rash;  Rare:  Angioedema, Exfoliative dermatitis, Lichenoid dermatitis, Melanosis, Nail Disorder, Petechial rash, Purpuric rash, Pustular rash, Skin atrophy, Skin necrosis, Skin nodule, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, Subcutaneous nodule



 Special senses -  Frequent:  Conjunctivitis, Diplopia, Otitis media, Tinnitus;  Infrequent:  Abnormality of accommodation, Blepharitis, Dry eyes, Eye hemorrhage, Hyperacusis, Photophobia, Retinal edema, Taste loss, Taste perversion;  Rare:  Anisocoria, Blindness, Corneal ulcer, Exophthalmos, Extraocular palsy, Iritis, Keratitis, Keratoconjunctivitis, Miosis, Mydriasis, Night blindness, Ophthalmoplegia, Optic atrophy, Papilledema, Parosmia, Ptosis, Uveitis



 Urogenital System -  Frequent:  Anorgasmia, Impotence, Urinary frequency, Urinary incontinence;  Infrequent:  Abnormal ejaculation, Albuminuria, Amenorrhea, Dysmenorrhea, Dysuria, Hematuria, Kidney calculus, Leukorrhea, Menorrhagia, Metrorrhagia, Nephritis, Oliguria, Urinary retention, Urine abnormality;  Rare:  Acute kidney failure, Balanitis, Bladder Neoplasm, Cervicitis, Dyspareunia, Epididymitis, Female lactation, Glomerulitis, Ovarian disorder, Pyelonephritis



     Comparison of Gender and Race  



 The overall adverse event profile of pregabalin was similar between women and men. There are insufficient data to support a statement regarding the distribution of adverse experience reports by race.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of LYRICA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Nervous System Disorders - Headache



 Gastrointestinal Disorders - Nausea, Diarrhea



 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders - Gynecomastia, Breast Enlargement



 In addition, there are post-marketing reports of events related to reduced lower gastrointestinal tract function (e.g., intestinal obstruction, paralytic ileus, constipation) when LYRICA was co-administered with medications that have the potential to produce constipation, such as opioid analgesics. There are also post-marketing reports of respiratory failure and coma in patients taking pregabalin and other CNS depressant medications.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Angioedema (e.g. swelling of the throat, head and neck) can occur, and may be associated with life-threatening respiratory compromise requiring emergency treatment. Discontinue LYRICA immediately in these cases. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions (e.g. hives, dyspnea, and wheezing) can occur. Discontinue LYRICA immediately in these patients. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Increased seizure frequency may occur in patients with seizure disorders if LYRICA is rapidly discontinued. Withdraw LYRICA gradually over a minimum of 1 week. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Antiepileptic drugs, including LYRICA, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior. (  5.4  ) 
 *  LYRICA may cause peripheral edema. Exercise caution when co-administering LYRICA and thiazolidinedione antidiabetic agents. (  5.5  ) 
 *  LYRICA may cause dizziness and somnolence and impair patients' ability to drive or operate machinery.(  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Angioedema



  There have been postmarketing reports of angioedema in patients during initial and chronic treatment with LYRICA. Specific symptoms included swelling of the face, mouth (tongue, lips, and gums), and neck (throat and larynx). There were reports of life-threatening angioedema with respiratory compromise requiring emergency treatment. Discontinue LYRICA immediately in patients with these symptoms.



 Exercise caution when prescribing LYRICA to patients who have had a previous episode of angioedema. In addition, patients who are taking other drugs associated with angioedema (e.g., angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors [ACE-inhibitors]) may be at increased risk of developing angioedema.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity



  There have been postmarketing reports of hypersensitivity in patients shortly after initiation of treatment with LYRICA. Adverse reactions included skin redness, blisters, hives, rash, dyspnea, and wheezing. Discontinue LYRICA immediately in patients with these symptoms.



    5.3 Withdrawal of Antiepileptic Drugs (AEDs)



  As with all AEDs, withdraw LYRICA gradually to minimize the potential of increased seizure frequency in patients with seizure disorders. If LYRICA is discontinued, taper the drug gradually over a minimum of 1 week.



    5.4 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including LYRICA, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Monitor patients treated with any AED for any indication for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.



 Table 2 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 2. Risk by indication for antiepileptic drugs in the pooled analysis 
 Indication            Placebo Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients  Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients  Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients  Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events Per 1000 Patients   
  
 Epilepsy                      1.0                   3.4                   3.5                   2.4            
 Psychiatric                   5.7                   8.5                   1.5                   2.9            
 Other                         1.0                   1.8                   1.9                   0.9            
 Total                         2.4                   4.3                   1.8                   1.9            
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing LYRICA or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Inform patients, their caregivers, and families that LYRICA and other AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and advise them of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Report behaviors of concern immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.5 Peripheral Edema



  LYRICA treatment may cause peripheral edema. In short-term trials of patients without clinically significant heart or peripheral vascular disease, there was no apparent association between peripheral edema and cardiovascular complications such as hypertension or congestive heart failure. Peripheral edema was not associated with laboratory changes suggestive of deterioration in renal or hepatic function.



 In controlled clinical trials the incidence of peripheral edema was 6% in the LYRICA group compared with 2% in the placebo group. In controlled clinical trials, 0.5% of LYRICA patients and 0.2% placebo patients withdrew due to peripheral edema.



 Higher frequencies of weight gain and peripheral edema were observed in patients taking both LYRICA and a thiazolidinedione antidiabetic agent compared to patients taking either drug alone. The majority of patients using thiazolidinedione antidiabetic agents in the overall safety database were participants in studies of pain associated with diabetic peripheral neuropathy. In this population, peripheral edema was reported in 3% (2/60) of patients who were using thiazolidinedione antidiabetic agents only, 8% (69/859) of patients who were treated with LYRICA only, and 19% (23/120) of patients who were on both LYRICA and thiazolidinedione antidiabetic agents. Similarly, weight gain was reported in 0% (0/60) of patients on thiazolidinediones only; 4% (35/859) of patients on LYRICA only; and 7.5% (9/120) of patients on both drugs.



 As the thiazolidinedione class of antidiabetic drugs can cause weight gain and/or fluid retention, possibly exacerbating or leading to heart failure, exercise caution when co-administering LYRICA and these agents.



 Because there are limited data on congestive heart failure patients with New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV cardiac status, exercise caution when using LYRICA in these patients.



    5.6 Dizziness and Somnolence



  LYRICA may cause dizziness and somnolence. Inform patients that LYRICA-related dizziness and somnolence may impair their ability to perform tasks such as driving or operating machinery [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.5)  ]  .



 In the LYRICA controlled trials, dizziness was experienced by 30% of LYRICA-treated patients compared to 8% of placebo-treated patients; somnolence was experienced by 23% of LYRICA-treated patients compared to 8% of placebo-treated patients. Dizziness and somnolence generally began shortly after the initiation of LYRICA therapy and occurred more frequently at higher doses. Dizziness and somnolence were the adverse reactions most frequently leading to withdrawal (4% each) from controlled studies. In LYRICA-treated patients reporting these adverse reactions in short-term, controlled studies, dizziness persisted until the last dose in 30% and somnolence persisted until the last dose in 42% of patients [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .



    5.7 Weight Gain



  LYRICA treatment may cause weight gain. In LYRICA controlled clinical trials of up to 14 weeks, a gain of 7% or more over baseline weight was observed in 9% of LYRICA-treated patients and 2% of placebo-treated patients. Few patients treated with LYRICA (0.3%) withdrew from controlled trials due to weight gain. LYRICA associated weight gain was related to dose and duration of exposure, but did not appear to be associated with baseline BMI, gender, or age. Weight gain was not limited to patients with edema [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



 Although weight gain was not associated with clinically important changes in blood pressure in short-term controlled studies, the long-term cardiovascular effects of LYRICA-associated weight gain are unknown.



 Among diabetic patients, LYRICA-treated patients gained an average of 1.6 kg (range: -16 to 16 kg), compared to an average 0.3 kg (range: -10 to 9 kg) weight gain in placebo patients. In a cohort of 333 diabetic patients who received LYRICA for at least 2 years, the average weight gain was 5.2 kg.



 While the effects of LYRICA-associated weight gain on glycemic control have not been systematically assessed, in controlled and longer-term open label clinical trials with diabetic patients, LYRICA treatment did not appear to be associated with loss of glycemic control (as measured by HbA1C).



    5.8 Abrupt or Rapid Discontinuation



  Following abrupt or rapid discontinuation of LYRICA, some patients reported symptoms including insomnia, nausea, headache, anxiety, hyperhidrosis, and diarrhea. Taper LYRICA gradually over a minimum of 1 week rather than discontinuing the drug abruptly.



    5.9 Tumorigenic Potential



  In standard preclinical in vivo  lifetime carcinogenicity studies of LYRICA, an unexpectedly high incidence of hemangiosarcoma was identified in two different strains of mice [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . The clinical significance of this finding is unknown. Clinical experience during LYRICA's premarketing development provides no direct means to assess its potential for inducing tumors in humans.



 In clinical studies across various patient populations, comprising 6396 patient-years of exposure in patients &gt;12 years of age, new or worsening-preexisting tumors were reported in 57 patients. Without knowledge of the background incidence and recurrence in similar populations not treated with LYRICA, it is impossible to know whether the incidence seen in these cohorts is or is not affected by treatment.



    5.10 Ophthalmological Effects



  In controlled studies, a higher proportion of patients treated with LYRICA reported blurred vision (7%) than did patients treated with placebo (2%), which resolved in a majority of cases with continued dosing. Less than 1% of patients discontinued LYRICA treatment due to vision-related events (primarily blurred vision).



 Prospectively planned ophthalmologic testing, including visual acuity testing, formal visual field testing and dilated funduscopic examination, was performed in over 3600 patients. In these patients, visual acuity was reduced in 7% of patients treated with LYRICA, and 5% of placebo-treated patients. Visual field changes were detected in 13% of LYRICA-treated, and 12% of placebo-treated patients. Funduscopic changes were observed in 2% of LYRICA-treated and 2% of placebo-treated patients.



 Although the clinical significance of the ophthalmologic findings is unknown, inform patients to notify their physician if changes in vision occur. If visual disturbance persists, consider further assessment. Consider more frequent assessment for patients who are already routinely monitored for ocular conditions [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.8)  ]  .



    5.11 Creatine Kinase Elevations



  LYRICA treatment was associated with creatine kinase elevations. Mean changes in creatine kinase from baseline to the maximum value were 60 U/L for LYRICA-treated patients and 28 U/L for the placebo patients. In all controlled trials across multiple patient populations, 1.5% of patients on LYRICA and 0.7% of placebo patients had a value of creatine kinase at least three times the upper limit of normal. Three LYRICA treated subjects had events reported as rhabdomyolysis in premarketing clinical trials. The relationship between these myopathy events and LYRICA is not completely understood because the cases had documented factors that may have caused or contributed to these events. Instruct patients to promptly report unexplained muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness, particularly if these muscle symptoms are accompanied by malaise or fever. Discontinue treatment with LYRICA if myopathy is diagnosed or suspected or if markedly elevated creatine kinase levels occur.



    5.12 Decreased Platelet Count



  LYRICA treatment was associated with a decrease in platelet count. LYRICA-treated subjects experienced a mean maximal decrease in platelet count of 20 * 10  3  /uL, compared to 11 * 10  3  /uL in placebo patients. In the overall database of controlled trials, 2% of placebo patients and 3% of LYRICA patients experienced a potentially clinically significant decrease in platelets, defined as 20% below baseline value and &lt;150 * 10  3  /uL. A single LYRICA treated subject developed severe thrombocytopenia with a platelet count less than 20 * 10  3  / uL. In randomized controlled trials, LYRICA was not associated with an increase in bleeding-related adverse reactions.



    5.13 PR Interval Prolongation



  LYRICA treatment was associated with PR interval prolongation. In analyses of clinical trial ECG data, the mean PR interval increase was 3-6 msec at LYRICA doses &gt;=300 mg/day. This mean change difference was not associated with an increased risk of PR increase &gt;=25% from baseline, an increased percentage of subjects with on-treatment PR &gt;200 msec, or an increased risk of adverse reactions of second or third degree AV block.



 Subgroup analyses did not identify an increased risk of PR prolongation in patients with baseline PR prolongation or in patients taking other PR prolonging medications. However, these analyses cannot be considered definitive because of the limited number of patients in these categories.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
