<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="maci" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most frequently occurring adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) reported for MACI were arthralgia, tendonitis, back pain, joint swelling, and joint effusion.



 Serious adverse reactions reported for MACI were arthralgia, cartilage injury, meniscus injury, treatment failure, and osteoarthritis.



   EXCERPT:   The most frequently occurring adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) reported for MACI were arthralgia, tendonitis, back pain, joint swelling, and joint effusion. (  6  )



 Serious adverse reactions reported for MACI were arthralgia, cartilage injury, meniscus injury, treatment failure, and osteoarthritis. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Vericel at 1-800-453-6948 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  for voluntary reporting of adverse reactions.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another product and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a 2-year prospective, multicenter, randomized, open-label, parallel-group clinical trial    1    , 144 patients, ages 18 to 54 years, were randomized to receive a 1-time treatment with MACI or microfracture (1:1, 72 patients in each treatment group). Demographic characteristics of patients in the trial were similar in both treatment groups. The majority of patients were male (62.5% MACI, 66.7% microfracture), and the mean ages were 34.8 (MACI) and 32.9 (microfracture) years. Overall, 70 patients in the MACI group and 67 patients in the microfracture group completed 2 years of follow-up.



 In addition, all 144 subjects from the 2-year clinical trial had the option to enroll in a 3-year follow-up study (extension study). Safety and efficacy assessments were performed at yearly scheduled visits. The demographic characteristics of patients (N = 128) enrolled in the extension study were similar in both treatment groups and consistent with the overall population of the 2-year clinical trial.



 The proportion of patients with at least 1 subsequent surgical procedure (any surgical procedure performed on the treated knee joint, including arthroscopy, arthrotomy, or manipulation under anesthesia) in the 2 years following study treatment was comparable between treatment groups (8.3% in the MACI group and 9.7% in the microfracture group).



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients in either treatment group in the 2-year clinical trial are provided in  Table 1  .



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions in &gt;=5% of Patients in Any Treatment Group in the 2-Year Clinical Trial 
   System Organ Class                             MACIn = 72n (%)             Microfracturen = 72n (%)      
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                     
  Arthralgia                                         37 (51.4)                       46 (63.9)              
  Back pain                                           8 (11.1)                        7 (9.7)               
  Joint swelling                                      7 (9.7)                         4 (5.6)               
  Joint effusion                                      5 (6.9)                         4 (5.6)               
   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications                                                                     
  Cartilage injury                                    3 (4.2)                         9 (12.5)              
  Ligament sprain                                     3 (4.2)                         5 (6.9)               
  Procedural pain                                     3 (4.2)                         4 (5.6)               
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                     
  Treatment failure                                   1 (1.4)                         4 (5.6)               
         In the 3-year extension study, adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of patients were (MACI vs microfracture): arthralgia (46.2% vs 50.8%), tendonitis (6.2% vs 1.6%), back pain (4.6% vs 6.3%), osteoarthritis (4.6% vs 7.9%), joint effusion (3.1% vs 7.9%), cartilage injury (6.2% vs 15.9%), procedural pain (3.1% vs 7.9%), ligament sprain (1.5% vs 7.9%), and treatment failure (4.6% vs 7.9%).
 

 Serious adverse reactions reported in patients in either treatment group for integrated data across the 2-year clinical trial and the 3-year extension study are provided in  Table 2  .



 Table 2. Serious Adverse Reactions in Patients in Any Treatment Group Across the 2-Year Clinical Trial and the 3-Year Extension Study 
   System Organ Class                             MACIn = 72n (%)             Microfracturen = 72n (%)      
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                     
  Arthralgia                                          1 (1.4)                         7 (9.7)               
  Joint Lock                                             0                            3 (4.2)               
  Meniscus Injury                                     3 (4.2)                            0                  
  Osteoarthritis                                      3 (4.2)                            0                  
   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications                                                                     
  Cartilage injury                                    3 (4.2)                         8 (11.1)              
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                     
  Treatment failure                                   3 (4.2)                         7 (9.7)               
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   Graft complication (e.g., abnormalities to the repair graft that become symptomatic; this could include graft overgrowth [tissue hypertrophy], under-fill or damage to the repair tissue that has elicited a painful response, or mechanical symptoms), graft delamination (i.e., a dislodging of the repair graft from the underlying subchondral bone that has become symptomatic; this can be measured as marginal, partial, or a complete delaminated graft), and tendonitis have been reported during use of MACI outside the United States. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to MACI exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Safety of MACI in patients with malignancy in the area of cartilage biopsy or implant is unknown. Expansion of malignant or dysplastic cells present in biopsy tissue during manufacture and subsequent implantation may be possible. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Because patients undergoing procedures associated with MACI are not routinely tested for transmissible infectious diseases, cartilage biopsy and MACI implant may carry risk of transmitting infectious diseases. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Local inflammation or active infection in the bone, joint, and surrounding soft tissue, meniscal pathology, cruciate ligament instability, and misalignment should be assessed and treated prior to or concurrent with MACI implantation. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Final sterility test results are not available at the time of shipping. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Malignancy



  The safety of MACI used in patients with malignancy in the area of cartilage biopsy or implant is unknown. The potential exists for expansion of malignant or dysplastic cells present in biopsy tissue during manufacture and subsequent implantation. In addition, implantation of normal autologous chondrocytes could theoretically stimulate growth of malignant cells in the area of the implant, although there have been no such incidents reported in humans or animals.



    5.2 Transmissible Infectious Diseases



  MACI is intended solely for autologous use. Patients undergoing the surgical procedures associated with MACI are not routinely tested for transmissible infectious diseases. Therefore, the cartilage biopsy and the MACI implant may carry the risk of transmitting infectious diseases to personnel handling these tissues. Accordingly, health care providers should employ universal precautions in handling the biopsy samples and the MACI product.



 Product manufacture includes reagents derived from animal materials. All animal-derived reagents are tested for viruses, retroviruses, bacteria, fungi, yeast, and mycoplasma before use. Bovine materials are sourced to minimize the risk of transmitting a prion protein that causes bovine spongiform encephalopathy and may cause a rare fatal condition in humans called variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease.



 These measures do not totally eliminate the risk of transmitting these or other transmissible infectious diseases and disease agents. Report the occurrence of a transmitted infection to Vericel Corporation at 1-888-453-6948.



    5.3 Presurgical Assessment of Comorbidities



  To create a favorable environment for healing, assess and treat the following conditions prior to or concurrent with implantation with MACI:



 *   Local inflammation or active infection in the bone, joint, and surrounding soft tissue : patients should be deferred until complete recovery. 
 *   Meniscal pathology : presence of an unstable or torn meniscus requires partial resection, repair, or replacement prior to or concurrent with MACI implantation. MACI is not recommended in patients with a total meniscectomy. 
 *   Cruciate ligament instability : the joint should not possess excessive laxity, which may create excessive shear and rotational forces across the joint. Both anterior and posterior cruciate ligaments should be stable or undergo reconstruction prior to or concurrent with MACI implantation. 
 *   Misalignment : the tibio-femoral joint should be properly aligned, and patella tracking should be normalized. Varus or valgus misalignment of the tibio-femoral joint and abnormal patella tracking may abnormally load joint surfaces and jeopardize the implant. Misalignment and patella tracking should be addressed with a corrective osteotomy or similar corrective procedure prior to or concurrent with MACI implantation. 
       5.4 Product Sterility
 

  MACI is shipped after passing preliminary test results from in-process microbial tests. A final sterility test is initiated prior to shipping, but the result will not be available prior to implantation. If microbial contamination is detected after the product has been shipped, Vericel will notify the health care provider(s) and recommend appropriate actions.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
