<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="makena" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  For the most serious adverse reactions to the use of progestins, see  Warnings and Precautions (  5  ).  



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions reported in &gt;=2% of subjects and at a higher rate in the Makena group than in the control group are injection site reactions (pain [35%], swelling [17%], pruritus [6%], nodule [5%]), urticaria (12%), pruritus (8%), nausea (6%), and diarrhea (2%). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Lumara Health at 1-877-411-2510 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a vehicle (placebo)-controlled clinical trial of 463 pregnant women at risk for spontaneous preterm delivery based on obstetrical history, 310 received 250 mg of Makena and 153 received a vehicle formulation containing no drug by a weekly intramuscular injection beginning at 16 to 20 weeks of gestation and continuing until 37 weeks of gestation or delivery, whichever occurred first.  1    [See Clinical Studies (  14.1  ).]  



 Certain pregnancy-related fetal and maternal complications or events were numerically increased in the Makena-treated subjects as compared to control subjects, including miscarriage and stillbirth, admission for preterm labor, preeclampsia or gestational hypertension, gestational diabetes, and oligohydramnios (Tables 1 and 2).



 Table 1 Selected Fetal Complications 
   1  N = Total number of subjects enrolled prior to 20 weeks 0 days  2  N = Total number of subjects at risk &gt;= 20 weeks   
  
  Pregnancy Complication                      Makena                         Control                         
                                              n/N                            n/N                             
  Miscarriage (&lt; 20 weeks)1                   5/209                          0/107                           
  Stillbirth (&gt;= 20 weeks)2                   6/305                          2/153                           
        Table 2 Selected Maternal Complications 
   1  Other than delivery admission.              
  
  Pregnancy Complication                          MakenaN=310%                  ControlN=153%                
  Admission for preterm labor1                    16.0                          13.8                         
  Preeclampsia or gestational hypertension        8.8                           4.6                          
  Gestational diabetes                            5.6                           4.6                          
  Oligohydramnios                                 3.6                           1.3                          
           Common Adverse Reactions:  
 

 The most common adverse reaction was injection site pain, which was reported after at least one injection by 34.8% of the Makena group and 32.7% of the control group. Table 3 lists adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=2% of subjects and at a higher rate in the Makena group than in the control group.



 Table 3 Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 2% of Makena-Treated Subjects and at a Higher Rate than Control Subjects 
     Preferred Term                                MakenaN=310%                 ControlN=153%               
  Injection site pain                              34.8                         32.7                        
  Injection site swelling                          17.1                         7.8                         
  Urticaria                                        12.3                         11.1                        
  Pruritus                                         7.7                          5.9                         
  Injection site pruritus                          5.8                          3.3                         
  Nausea                                           5.8                          4.6                         
  Injection site nodule                            4.5                          2.0                         
  Diarrhea                                         2.3                          0.7                         
         In the clinical trial, 2.2% of subjects receiving Makena were reported as discontinuing therapy due to adverse reactions compared to 2.6% of control subjects. The most common adverse reactions that led to discontinuation in both groups were urticaria and injection site pain/swelling (1% each).
 

 Pulmonary embolus in one subject and injection site cellulitis in another subject were reported as serious adverse reactions in Makena-treated subjects.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Makena. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *   Body as a whole : Local injection site reactions (including erythema, urticaria, rash, irritation, hypersensitivity, warmth); fatigue; fever; hot flashes/flushes 
 *   Digestive disorders : Vomiting 
 *   Infections : Urinary tract infection 
 *   Nervous system disorders : Headache, dizziness 
 *   Pregnancy, puerperium and perinatal conditions: Cervical incompetence, premature rupture of membranes 
 *   Reproductive system and breast disorders: Cervical dilation, shortened cervix 
 *   Respiratory disorders : Dyspnea, chest discomfort 
 *   Skin : Rash 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Thromboembolic disorders: Discontinue if thrombosis or thromboembolism occurs (  5.1  ) 
 *  Allergic reactions: Consider discontinuing if allergic reactions occur (  5.2  ) 
 *  Decreased glucose tolerance: Monitor prediabetic and diabetic women receiving Makena (  5.3  ) 
 *  Fluid retention: Monitor women with conditions that may be affected by fluid retention, such as preeclampsia, epilepsy, cardiac or renal dysfunction (  5.4  ) 
 *  Depression: Monitor women with a history of clinical depression; discontinue Makena if depression recurs (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thromboembolic Disorders



  Discontinue Makena if an arterial or deep venous thrombotic or thromboembolic event occurs.



    5.2 Allergic Reactions



  Allergic reactions, including urticaria, pruritus and angioedema, have been reported with use of Makena or with other products containing castor oil. Consider discontinuing the drug if such reactions occur.



    5.3 Decrease in Glucose Tolerance



  A decrease in glucose tolerance has been observed in some patients on progestin treatment. The mechanism of this decrease is not known. Carefully monitor prediabetic and diabetic women while they are receiving Makena.



    5.4 Fluid Retention



  Because progestational drugs may cause some degree of fluid retention, carefully monitor women with conditions that might be influenced by this effect (e.g., preeclampsia, epilepsy, migraine, asthma, cardiac or renal dysfunction).



    5.5 Depression



  Monitor women who have a history of clinical depression and discontinue Makena if clinical depression recurs.



    5.6 Jaundice



  Carefully monitor women who develop jaundice while receiving Makena and consider whether the benefit of use warrants continuation.



    5.7 Hypertension



  Carefully monitor women who develop hypertension while receiving Makena and consider whether the benefit of use warrants continuation.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
