<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="marqibo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are also discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  For intravenous use only [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Extravasation tissue injury [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Peripheral Neuropathy [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Myelosuppression [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Tumor lysis syndrome [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Constipation and bowel obstruction [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Fatigue [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *  Hepatic toxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 30%) in clinical studies include constipation, nausea, pyrexia, fatigue, peripheral neuropathy, febrile neutropenia, diarrhea, anemia, decreased appetite, and insomnia (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Talon Therapeutics at 1-888 292 9617 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Safety Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Integrated Summary of Safety in Relapsed and/or Refractory Ph- Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia  



 Marqibo, at a dose of 2.25 mg/m  2  weekly, was studied in a total of 83 patients in two trials: study 1 and study 2. Adverse reactions were observed in 100% of patients. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;30%) were constipation (57%), nausea (52%), pyrexia (43%), fatigue (41%), peripheral neuropathy (39%), febrile neutropenia (38%), diarrhea (37%), anemia (34%), decreased appetite (33%), and insomnia (32%).



 Adverse reactions of Grade 3 or greater were reported in 96% of patients. Adverse reactions of Grade 3 or greater and occurring in &gt;= 5% of patients are summarized in  Table 2  .



 Table 2. Most Commonly Reported (&gt; 5%) Grade National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v3.0. 3 or Greater Adverse Reactions among 83 Patients Receiving the Clinical Dosing Regimen 
 Adverse Reactions Grade &gt;= 3                                                      Study 1 and 2(N=83)n (%)   
  
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders                                                 47 (56.6)         
   Febrile Neutropenia                                                                  26 (31.3)         
   Neutropenia                                                                          15 (18.1)         
   Anemia                                                                               14 (16.9)         
   Thrombocytopenia                                                                     14 (16.9)         
   Infections                                                                           33 (39.8)         
   Pneumonia                                                                             7 (8.4)          
   Septic Shock                                                                          5 (6.0)          
   Staphylococcal Bacteremia                                                             5 (6.0)          
   Neuropathy                                                                           27 (32.5)         
   Peripheral Sensory and Motor Neuropathy                                              14 (16.7)         
   Constipation                                                                          4 (4.8)          
   Ileus, Colonic Pseudo-Obstruction                                                     5 (6.0)          
   Asthenia                                                                              4 (4.8)          
   Muscular Weakness                                                                     1 (1.2)          
   Respiratory Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                       17 (20.5)         
   Respiratory Distress                                                                  5 (6.0)          
   Respiratory Failure                                                                   4 (4.8)          
   General Disorders and Administration Site Condition                                  31 (37.3)         
   Pyrexia                                                                              12 (14.5)         
   Fatigue                                                                              10 (12.0)         
   Pain                                                                                  7 (8.4)          
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                           21 (25.3)         
   Abdominal Pain                                                                        7 (8.4)          
   Investigations                                                                       20 (24.1)         
   Aspartate Aminotransferase Increased                                                  6 (7.2)          
   Vascular Disorders                                                                    8 (9.6)          
   Hypotension                                                                           5 (6.0)          
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                 9 (10.8)         
   Mental Status Changes                                                                 3 (3.6)          
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                     9 (10.8)         
   Cardiac Arrest                                                                        5 (6.0)          
   Renal and Urinary Disorders                                                           6 (7.2)          
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                       7 (8.4)          
        A total of 75.9% of patients experienced serious adverse events (SAEs) during the studies. The most commonly reported SAEs included febrile neutropenia (20.5%), pyrexia (13.3%), hypotension (7.2%), respiratory distress (6.0%), and cardiac arrest (6.0%).
 

 Dose reduction, delay, or omission occurred in 53% of patients during the treatment.



 Twenty-eight percent of patients experienced adverse reactions leading to treatment discontinuation. The most common adverse reactions that caused treatment discontinuation were peripheral neuropathy (10%), leukemia-related (7%), and tumor lysis syndrome (2%).



 Adverse reactions related to neuropathy and leading to treatment discontinuation were decreased vibratory sense, facial palsy, hyporeflexia, constipation, asthenia, fatigue, and musculoskeletal pain, each reported in at least 1 patient.



 Deaths occurred in 23% of patients in study 1. The non-leukemia related causes of deaths were brain infarct (1), intracerebral hemorrhage (2), liver failure (1), multi system organ failure (2), pneumonia and septic shock (3), respiratory failure (4), pulmonary hemorrhage (1), and sudden cardiac death (1).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

    WARNING  

    *  For Intravenous Use Only - Fatal if Given by Other Routes [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Death has occurred with intrathecal administration. 
 *  Marqibo (vinCRIStine sulfate LIPOSOME injection) has different dosage recommendations than vinCRIStine sulfate injection. Verify drug name and dose prior to preparation and administration to avoid overdosage. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING  
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .  



 *  For Intravenous Use Only - Fatal if Given by Other Routes (5.1) 
 *  Death has occurred with intrathecal use 
 *  Marqibo (vinCRIStine sulfate LIPOSOME injection) has different dosage recommendations than vinCRIStine sulfate injection. Verify drug name and dose prior to preparation and administration to avoid overdosage. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Intrathecal administration is fatal (  5.1  ) 
 *  Extravasation causes tissue injury (  5.2  ) 
 *  Neurologic toxicity: Monitor patients for peripheral motor and sensory, central and autonomic neuropathy, and reduce, interrupt, or discontinue dosing. Patients with preexisting severe neuropathy should be treated with Marqibo only after careful risk-benefit assessment (  2.2  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  Myelosuppression: Monitor blood counts prior to each dose of Marqibo. Neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, or anemia may occur; consider Marqibo dose reduction or interruption and supportive care measures (  5.4  ) 
 *  Tumor lysis syndrome: Anticipate, monitor for, and manage (  5.5  ) 
 *  Constipation, bowel obstruction, and/or paralytic ileus: Institute a prophylactic bowel regimen to prevent potential constipation, bowel obstruction, and/or paralytic ileus (  5.6  ) 
 *  Fatigue: Severe fatigue can occur (  5.7  ) 
 *  Hepatic toxicity: Monitor liver function and modify or interrupt dosing (  5.8  ) 
 *  Embryofetal toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise women of potential risk to the fetus (  5.9  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 For Intravenous Use Only



  Fatal if Given by Other Routes. Death has occurred with intrathecal use.



    5.2 Extravasation Tissue Injury



  Only administer through a secure and free-flowing venous access line. If extravasation is suspected, discontinue infusion immediately and consider local treatment measures.



    5.3 Neurologic Toxicity



  Sensory and motor neuropathies are common and are cumulative. Monitor patients for symptoms of neuropathy, such as hypoesthesia, hyperesthesia, paresthesia, hyporeflexia, areflexia, neuralgia, jaw pain, decreased vibratory sense, cranial neuropathy, ileus, burning sensation, arthralgia, myalgia, muscle spasm, or weakness, both before and during treatment. Orthostatic hypotension may occur. The risk of neurologic toxicity is greater if Marqibo is administered to patients with preexisting neuromuscular disorders or when other drugs with risk of neurologic toxicity are being given. In the studies of relapsed and/or refractory adult ALL patients, Grade &gt;= 3 neuropathy events occurred in 32.5% of patients. Worsening neuropathy requires dose delay, reduction, or discontinuation of Marqibo [ see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)    ].



    5.4 Myelosuppression



  Monitor complete blood counts prior to each dose of Marqibo. If Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, or anemia develops, consider Marqibo dose modification or reduction as well as supportive care measures.



    5.5 Tumor Lysis Syndrome



  Tumor lysis syndrome (TLS) may occur in patients with ALL receiving Marqibo. Anticipate, monitor for, and manage.



    5.6 Constipation and Bowel Obstruction



  Ileus, bowel obstruction, and colonic pseudo-obstruction have occurred. Marqibo can cause constipation [ see  Adverse Reactions (6)    ]. Institute a prophylactic bowel regimen to mitigate potential constipation, bowel obstruction, and/or paralytic ileus, considering adequate dietary fiber intake, hydration, and routine use of stool softeners, such as docusate. Additional treatments, such as senna, bisacodyl, milk of magnesia, magnesium citrate, and lactulose may be considered.



    5.7 Fatigue



  Marqibo can cause severe fatigue. Marqibo dose delay, reduction, or discontinuation may be necessary.



    5.8 Hepatic Toxicity



  Fatal liver toxicity and elevated levels of aspartate aminotransferase have occurred. Elevated levels of aspartate aminotransferase of Grade &gt;=3 occurred in 6-11% of patients in clinical trials. Monitor hepatic function tests. Reduce or interrupt Marqibo for hepatic toxicity.



    5.9 Embryofetal Toxicity



  Marqibo can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Vincristine sulfate liposome injection was teratogenic or caused embryo-fetal death in animals. Women of childbearing potential should avoid becoming pregnant while being treated with Marqibo. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of Marqibo in pregnant women and there were no reports of pregnancy in any of the clinical studies in the Marqibo clinical development program. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
