<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="matulane" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Leukopenia, anemia and thrombopenia occur frequently. Nausea and vomiting are the most commonly reported side effects.



 Other adverse reactions are:



   Hematologic  



 Pancytopenia; eosinophilia; hemolytic anemia; bleeding tendencies such as petechiae, purpura, epistaxis and hemoptysis.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Hepatic dysfunction, jaundice, stomatitis, hematemesis, melena, diarrhea, dysphagia, anorexia, abdominal pain, constipation, dry mouth.



   Neurologic  



 Coma, convulsions, neuropathy, ataxia, paresthesia, nystagmus, diminished reflexes, falling, foot drop, headache, dizziness, unsteadiness.



   Cardiovascular  



 Hypotension, tachycardia, syncope.



   Ophthalmic  



 Retinal hemorrhage, papilledema, photophobia, diplopia, inability to focus.



   Respiratory  



 Pneumonitis, pleural effusion, cough.



   Dermatologic  



 Herpes, dermatitis, pruritus, alopecia, hyperpigmentation, rash, urticaria, flushing.



   Allergic  



 Generalized allergic reactions.



   Genitourinary  



 Hematuria, urinary frequency, nocturia.



   Musculoskeletal  



 Pain, including myalgia and arthralgia; tremors.



   Psychiatric  



 Hallucinations, depression, apprehension, nervousness, confusion, nightmares.



   Endocrine  



 Gynecomastia in prepubertal and early pubertal boys.



   Miscellaneous  



 Intercurrent infections, hearing loss, pyrexia, diaphoresis, lethargy, weakness, fatigue, edema, chills, insomnia, slurred speech, hoarseness, drowsiness.



 Second nonlymphoid malignancies (including lung cancer, acute myelocytic leukemia and malignant myelosclerosis) and azoospermia have been reported in patients with Hodgkin's disease treated with procarbazine in combination with other chemotherapy and/or radiation. The risks of secondary lung cancer from treatment appear to be multiplied by tobacco use.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    WARNING  



 It is recommended that MATULANE be given only by or under the supervision of a physician experienced in the use of potent antineoplastic drugs. Adequate clinical and laboratory facilities should be available to patients for proper monitoring of treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
