<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mavik" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The safety experience in U.S. placebo-controlled trials included 1069 hypertensive patients, of whom 832 received MAVIK. Nearly 200 hypertensive patients received MAVIK for over one year in open-label trials. In controlled trials, withdrawals for adverse events were 2.1% on placebo and 1.4% on MAVIK. Adverse events considered at least possibly related to treatment occurring in 1% of MAVIK-treated patients and more common on MAVIK than placebo, pooled for all doses, are shown below, together with the frequency of discontinuation of treatment because of these events.



 ADVERSE EVENTS IN PLACEBO-CONTROLLED HYPERTENSION TRIALS 
                                      Occurring at 1% or greater                                           
                                      MAVIK    (N=832)    % Incidence    (% Discontinuance)      PLACEBO    (N=237)    % Incidence    (% Discontinuance)     
 Cough                              1.9 (0.1)                          0.4 (0.4)                           
 Dizziness                          1.3 (0.2)                          0.4 (0.4)                           
 Diarrhea                           1.0 (0.0)                          0.4 (0.0)                           
      Headache and fatigue were all seen in more than 1% of MAVIK-treated patients but were more frequently seen on placebo. Adverse events were not usually persistent or difficult to manage.
 

   Left Ventricular Dysfunction Post Myocardial Infarction

  Adverse reactions related to MAVIK occurring at a rate greater than that observed in placebo-treated patients with left ventricular dysfunction, are shown below. The incidences represent the experiences from the TRACE study. The follow-up time was between 24 and 50 months for this study.



 Percentage of Patients with Adverse Events Greater Than Placebo 
   Placebo-Controlled (TRACE)    Mortality Study     
   Adverse Event                      Trandolapril    N=876              Placebo    N=873                  
 Cough                              35                                 22                                  
 Dizziness                          23                                 17                                  
 Hypotension                        11                                 6.8                                 
 Elevated serum uric acid           15                                 13                                  
 Elevated BUN                       9.0                                7.6                                 
 PICA or CABG                       7.3                                6.1                                 
 Dyspepsia                          6.4                                6.0                                 
 Syncope                            5.9                                3.3                                 
 Hyperkalemia                       5.3                                2.8                                 
 Bradycardia                        4.7                                4.4                                 
 Hypocalcemia                       4.7                                3.9                                 
 Myalgia                            4.7                                3.1                                 
 Elevated creatinine                4.7                                2.4                                 
 Gastritis                          4.2                                3.6                                 
 Cardiogenic shock                  3.8                                &lt; 2                                 
 Intermittent claudication          3.8                                &lt; 2                                 
 Stroke                             3.3                                3.2                                 
 Asthenia                           3.3                                2.6                                 
      Clinical adverse experiences possibly or probably related or of uncertain relationship to therapy occurring in 0.3% to 1.0% (except as noted) of the patients treated with MAVIK (with or without concomitant calcium ion antagonist or diuretic) in controlled or uncontrolled trials (N=1134) and less frequent, clinically significant events seen in clinical trials or post-marketing experience include (listed by body system):
 

   General Body Function

  Chest pain.



   Cardiovascular

  AV first degree block, bradycardia, edema, flushing, and palpitations.



   Central Nervous System

  Drowsiness, insomnia, paresthesia, vertigo.



   Dermatologic

  Pruritus, rash, pemphigus.



   Eye, Ear, Nose, Throat

  Epistaxis, throat inflammation, upper respiratory tract infection.



   Emotional, Mental, Sexual States

  Anxiety, impotence, decreased libido.



   Gastrointestinal

  Abdominal distention, abdominal pain/cramps, constipation, dyspepsia, diarrhea, vomiting, nausea.



   Hemopoietic

  Decreased leukocytes, decreased neutrophils.



   Metabolism and Endocrine

  Increased liver enzymes including SGPT (ALT).



   Musculoskeletal System

  Extremity pain, muscle cramps, gout.



   Pulmonary

  Dyspnea.



   Postmarketing

  The following adverse reactions were identified during post approval use of MAVIK. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     General Body Function  

  Malaise, fever.



     Cardiovascular  

  Myocardial infarction, myocardial ischemia, angina pectoris, cardiac failure, ventricular tachycardia, tachycardia, transient ischemic attack, arrhythmia.



     Central Nervous System  

  Cerebral hemorrhage.



     Dermatologic  

  Alopecia, sweating, Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis.



     Emotional, Mental, Sexual States  

  Hallucination, depression.



     Gastrointestinal  

  Dry mouth, pancreatitis, jaundice and hepatitis.



     Hemopoietic  

  Agranulocytosis, pancytopenia.



     Metabolism and Endocrine  

  Increased SGOT (AST).



     Pulmonary  

  Bronchitis.



     Renal and Urinary  

  Renal failure.



   Clinical Laboratory Test Findings

    Hematology  

  Thrombocytopenia.



     Serum Electrolytes  

  Hyponatremia.



     Creatinine and Blood Urea Nitrogen  

  Increases in creatinine levels occurred in 1.1% of patients receiving MAVIK alone and 7.3% of patients treated with MAVIK, a calcium ion antagonist and a diuretic. Increases in blood urea nitrogen levels occurred in 0.6% of patients receiving MAVIK alone and 1.4% of patients receiving MAVIK, a calcium ion antagonist, and a diuretic. None of these increases required discontinuation of treatment. Increases in these laboratory values are more likely to occur in patients with renal insufficiency or those pretreated with a diuretic and, based on experience with other ACE inhibitors, would be expected to be especially likely in patients with renal artery stenosis. (see    PRECAUTIONS    and    WARNINGS    .)



     Liver Function Tests  

  Occasional elevation of transaminases at the rate of 3X upper normals occurred in 0.8% of patients and persistent increase in bilirubin occurred in 0.2% of patients. Discontinuation for elevated liver enzymes occurred in 0.2% of patients.



   Other

  Another potentially important adverse experience, eosinophilic pneumonitis, has been attributed to other ACE inhibitors.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

  WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue MAVIK as soon as possible. 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (See WARNINGS: Fetal Toxicity). 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
