<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="medical" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   In children 6 months through 35 months of age, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reactions were pain (57%) (Assessed in children 24 months through 35 months of age)(Assessed in children 6 months through 23 months of age) or tenderness (54%), erythema (37%), and swelling (22%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were irritability (54%), abnormal crying (41%), malaise (38%), drowsiness (38%), appetite loss (32%), myalgia (27%), vomiting (15%), and fever (14%). In children 3 years through 8 years of age, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reactions were pain (67%), erythema (34%), and swelling (25%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were myalgia (39%), malaise (32%), and headache (23%). In adults 18 years and older, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reaction was pain (47%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were myalgia (24%), headache (16%), and malaise (11%). In adults 65 years of age and older, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reaction was pain (33%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were myalgia (18%), headache (13%), and malaise (11%).
 

    EXCERPT:    *  In children 6 months through 35 months of age, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reactions were pain (57%) or tenderness (54%), erythema (37%), and swelling (22%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were irritability (54%), abnormal crying (41%), malaise (38%), drowsiness (38%), appetite loss (32%), myalgia (27%), vomiting (15%), and fever (14%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In children 3 years through 8 years of age, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reactions were pain (67%), erythema (34%), and swelling (25%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were myalgia (39%), malaise (32%), and headache (23%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In adults 18 years and older, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reaction was pain (47%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were myalgia (24%), headache (16%), and malaise (11%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In adults 65 years of age and older, the most common (&gt;=10%) injection-site reaction was pain (33%); the most common solicited systemic adverse reactions were myalgia (18%), headache (13%), and malaise (11%). (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sanofi Pasteur Inc., at 1-800-822-2463 (1-800-VACCINE) or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or  www.vaers.hhs.gov.
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse event rates observed in the clinical trial(s) of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trial(s) of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Children 6 Months Through 8 Years of Age  



 Study 1 (NCT01240746, see http://clinicaltrials.gov) was a single-blind, randomized, active-controlled multi-center safety and immunogenicity study conducted in the US. In this study, children 6 months through 35 months of age received one or two 0.25 mL doses of either Fluzone Quadrivalent or one of two formulations of a comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (TIV-1 or TIV-2), and children 3 years through 8 years of age received one or two 0.5 mL doses of either Fluzone Quadrivalent, TIV-1, or TIV-2. Each of the trivalent formulations contained an influenza type B virus that corresponded to one of the two type B viruses in Fluzone Quadrivalent (a type B virus of the Victoria lineage or a type B virus of the Yamagata lineage). For participants who received two doses, the doses were administered approximately 4 weeks apart. The safety analysis set included 1841 children 6 months through 35 months of age and 2506 children 3 years through 8 years of age. Among participants 6 months through 8 years of age in the three vaccine groups combined, 49.3% were female (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 49.2%; TIV-1, 49.8%; TIV-2, 49.4%), 58.4% Caucasian (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 58.4%; TIV-1, 58.9%; TIV-2, 57.8%), 20.2% Black (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 20.5%; TIV-1, 19.9%; TIV-2, 19.1%), 14.1% Hispanic (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 14.3%; TIV-1, 13.2%; TIV-2, 14.7%), and 7.3% were of other racial/ethnic groups (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 6.8%; TIV-1, 8.0%; TIV-2, 8.5%). Table 2 and Table 3 summarize solicited injection-site and systemic adverse reactions reported within 7 days post-vaccination via diary cards. Participants were monitored for unsolicited adverse events for 28 days after each dose and serious adverse events (SAEs) during the 6 months following the last dose.



 Table 2: Study 1NCT01240746: Percentage of Solicited Injection-site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 7 Days After Vaccination in Children 6 Months Through 35 Months of Age (Safety Analysis Set)The safety analysis set includes all persons who received at least one dose of study vaccine 
                         Fluzone Quadrivalent(N=1223)  TIV-1(B Victoria)(N=310)  TIV-2(B Yamagata)(N=308)   
 Any(%)                  Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any(%)    Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any(%)    Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   
  
   Injection-site adverse reactions               
   Pain                    57.0      10.2        1.0       52.3      11.5        0.8       50.3       5.4        2.7      
   Tenderness              54.1      11.3        1.9       48.4       8.2        1.9       49.7      10.3        0.0      
   Erythema                37.3       1.5        0.2       32.9       1.0        0.0       33.3       1.0        0.0      
   Swelling                21.6       0.8        0.2       19.7       1.0        0.0       17.3       0.0        0.0      
   Systemic adverse reactions               
   Fever (&gt;=100.4 degrees F)      14.3       5.5        2.1       16.0       6.6        1.7       13.0       4.1        2.0      
   Malaise                 38.1      14.5        4.6       35.2      14.8        4.7       32.4      12.8        6.8      
   Myalgia                 26.7       6.6        1.9       26.6       9.4        1.6       25.0       6.8        2.7      
   Headache                8.9        2.5        0.6       9.4        3.9        0.0       12.2       4.7        0.0      
   Irritability            54.0      26.4        3.2       52.8      20.1        3.1       53.5      22.9        2.8      
   Crying abnormal         41.2      12.3        3.3       36.5       8.2        1.9       29.9      10.4        2.1      
   Drowsiness              37.7       8.4        1.3       32.1       3.8        0.6       31.9       5.6        0.7      
   Appetite loss           32.3       9.1        1.8       33.3       5.7        1.9       25.0       8.3        0.7      
   Vomiting                14.8       6.2        1.0       11.3       4.4        0.6       13.9       6.3        0.0      
               Table 3: Study 1NCT01240746: Percentage of Solicited Injection-site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 7 Days After Vaccination in Children 3 Years Through 8 Years of Age (Safety Analysis Set)The safety analysis set includes all persons who received at least one dose of study vaccine 
                         Fluzone Quadrivalent(N=1669)  TIV-1(B Victoria)(N=424)  TIV-2(B Yamagata)(N=413)   
 Any(%)                  Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any(%)    Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any(%)    Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   
  
   Injection-site adverse reactions               
   Pain                    66.6      15.8        2.1       64.6       9.5        2.0       63.8      11.6        2.8      
   Erythema                34.1       2.9        1.8       36.8       3.4        1.2       35.2       2.5        1.8      
   Swelling                24.8       2.8        1.4       25.4       1.5        1.2       25.9       2.5        1.8      
   Systemic adverse reactions               
   Fever(&gt;=100.4 degrees F)      7.0        2.1        2.1       7.1        2.2        1.2       7.6        2.8        0.8      
   Headache                23.1       6.8        2.2       21.2       5.1        2.7       24.4       7.5        2.0      
   Malaise                 31.9      11.2        5.5       32.8      11.4        5.6       33.4      10.8        5.0      
   Myalgia                 38.6      12.2        3.3       34.1       9.0        2.7       38.4      11.1        2.8      
                Among children 6 months through 8 years of age, unsolicited non-serious adverse events were reported in 1360 (47.0%) recipients in the Fluzone Quadrivalent group, 352 (48.0%) recipients in the TIV-1 group, and 346 (48.0%) recipients in the TIV-2 group. The most commonly reported unsolicited non-serious adverse events were cough, vomiting, and pyrexia. During the 28 days following vaccination, a total of 16 (0.6%) recipients in the Fluzone Quadrivalent group, 4 (0.5%) recipients in the TIV-1 group, and 4 (0.6%) recipients in the TIV-2 group, experienced at least one SAE; no deaths occurred. Throughout the study period, a total of 41 (1.4%) recipients in the Fluzone Quadrivalent group, 7 (1.0%) recipients in the TIV-1 group, and 14 (1.9%) recipients in the TIV-2 group, experienced at least one SAE. Three SAEs were considered to be possibly related to vaccination: croup in a Fluzone Quadrivalent recipient and 2 episodes of febrile seizure, 1 each in a TIV-1 recipient and a TIV-2 recipient. One death occurred in the TIV-1 group (a drowning 43 days post-vaccination).
 

     Adults  



 In study 2 (NCT00988143, see http://clinicaltrials.gov), a multi-centered randomized, open-label trial conducted in the US, adults 18 years of age and older received one dose of either Fluzone Quadrivalent or one of two formulations of comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (TIV-1 or TIV-2). Each of the trivalent formulations contained an influenza type B virus that corresponded to one of the two type B viruses in Fluzone Quadrivalent (a type B virus of the Victoria lineage or a type B virus of the Yamagata lineage). The safety analysis set included 570 recipients, half aged 18-60 years and half aged 61 years or older. Among participants in the three vaccine groups combined, 67.2% were female (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 68.4%; TIV-1, 67.9%; TIV-2, 65.3%), 88.4% Caucasian (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 91.1%; TIV-1, 86.8%; TIV-2, 87.4%), 9.6% Black (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 6.8%; TIV-1, 12.1%; TIV-2, 10.0%), 0.4% Hispanic (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 0.0%; TIV-1, 0.5%; TIV-2, 0.5%), and 1.7% were of other racial/ethnic groups (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 2.1%; TIV-1, 0.5%; TIV-2, 2.2%). Table 4 summarizes solicited injection-site and systemic adverse reactions reported within 3 days post-vaccination via diary cards. Participants were monitored for unsolicited adverse events and SAEs during the 21 days following vaccination.



 Table 4: Study 2NCT00988143: Percentage of Solicited Injection-site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 3 Days After Vaccination in Adults 18 Years of Age and Older (Safety Analysis Set)The safety analysis set includes all persons who received study vaccine 
                         Fluzone Quadrivalent(N=190)  TIV-1(B Victoria)(N=190)  TIV-2(B Yamagata)(N=190)   
 Any (%)                 Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any (%)   Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any (%)   Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   
  
   Injection-site adverse reactions               
   Pain                    47.4       6.8        0.5       52.1       7.9        0.5       43.2       6.3        0.0      
   Erythema                1.1        0.0        0.0       1.6        0.5        0.0       1.6        0.5        0.0      
   Swelling                0.5        0.0        0.0       3.2        0.5        0.0       1.1        0.0        0.0      
   Induration              0.5        0.0        0.0       1.6        0.5        0.0       0.5        0.0        0.0      
   Ecchymosis              0.5        0.0        0.0       0.5        0.0        0.0       0.5        0.0        0.0      
   Systemic adverse reactions               
   Myalgia                 23.7       5.8        0.0       25.3       5.8        0.0       16.8       5.8        0.0      
   Headache                15.8       3.2        0.5       18.4       6.3        0.5       18.0       4.2        0.0      
   Malaise                 10.5       1.6        1.1       14.7       3.2        1.1       12.1       4.7        0.5      
   Shivering               2.6        0.5        0.0       5.3        1.1        0.0       3.2        0.5        0.0      
   Fever(&gt;=100.4 degrees F)      0.0        0.0        0.0       0.5        0.5        0.0       0.5        0.5        0.0      
                Unsolicited non-serious adverse events were reported in 33 (17.4%) recipients in the Fluzone Quadrivalent group, 45 (23.7%) recipients in the TIV-1 group, and 45 (23.7%) recipients in the TIV-2 group. The most commonly reported unsolicited non-serious adverse events were headache, cough, and oropharyngeal pain. In the follow-up period, there were two SAEs, 1 (0.5%) in the Fluzone Quadrivalent group and 1 (0.5%) in the TIV-2 group. No deaths were reported during the trial period.
 

     Geriatric Adults  



 In Study 3 (NCT01218646, see http://clinicaltrials.gov), a multi-center, randomized, double-blind trial conducted in the US, adults 65 years of age and older received one dose of either Fluzone Quadrivalent, or one of two formulations of comparator trivalent influenza vaccine (TIV-1 or TIV-2). Each of the trivalent formulations contained an influenza type B virus that corresponded to one of the two type B viruses in Fluzone Quadrivalent (a type B virus of the Victoria lineage or a type B virus of the Yamagata lineage). The safety analysis set included 675 recipients. Among participants in the three vaccine groups combined, 55.7% were female (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 57.3%; TIV-1, 56.0%; TIV-2, 53.8%), 89.5% Caucasian (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 87.6%; TIV-1, 89.8%; TIV-2, 91.1%), 2.2% Black (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 4.0%; TIV-1, 1.8%; TIV-2, 0.9%), 7.4% Hispanic (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 8.4%; TIV-1, 7.6%; TIV-2, 6.2%) and 0.9% were of other racial/ethnic groups (Fluzone Quadrivalent, 0.0%; TIV-1, 0.9%; TIV-2, 1.8%).



 Table 5 summarizes solicited injection-site and systemic adverse reactions reported within 7 days post-vaccination via diary cards. Participants were monitored for unsolicited adverse events and SAEs during the 21 days following vaccination.



 Table 5: Study 3NCT01218646: Percentage of Solicited Injection-site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 7 Days After Vaccination in Adults 65 Years of Age and Older (Safety Analysis Set)The safety analysis set includes all persons who received study vaccine 
                         Fluzone Quadrivalent(N=225)  TIV-1(B Victoria)(N=225)  TIV-2(B Yamagata)(N=225)   
 Any (%)                 Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any (%)   Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   Any (%)   Grade 2(%)  Grade 3(%)   
  
   Injection-site adverse reactions               
   Pain                    32.6       1.3        0.9       28.6       2.7        0.0       23.1       0.9        0.0      
   Erythema                2.7        0.9        0.0       1.3        0.0        0.0       1.3        0.4        0.0      
   Swelling                1.8        0.4        0.0       1.3        0.0        0.0       0.0        0.0        0.0      
   Systemic adverse reactions               
   Myalgia                 18.3       4.0        0.4       18.3       4.0        0.0       14.2       2.7        0.4      
   Headache                13.4       1.3        0.4       11.6       1.3        0.0       11.6       1.8        0.4      
   Malaise                 10.7       4.5        0.4       6.3        0.4        0.0       11.6       2.7        0.9      
   Fever(&gt;=100.4 degrees F)      1.3        0.0        0.4       0.0        0.0        0.0       0.9        0.4        0.4      
                Unsolicited non-serious adverse events were reported in 28 (12.4%) recipients in the Fluzone Quadrivalent group, 22 (9.8%) recipients in the TIV-1 group, and 22 (9.8%) recipients in the TIV-2 group. The most commonly reported adverse events were oropharyngeal pain, rhinorrhea, injection-site induration, and headache. Three SAEs were reported during the follow-up period, 2 (0.9%) in the TIV-1 group and 1 (0.4%) in the TIV-2 group. No deaths were reported during the trial period.
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  Currently, there are no post-marketing data available for Fluzone Quadrivalent vaccine.



 The following events have been spontaneously reported during the post-approval use of the trivalent formulation of Fluzone. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure. Adverse events were included based on one or more of the following factors: severity, frequency of reporting, or strength of evidence for a causal relationship to Fluzone.



 *   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders : Thrombocytopenia, lymphadenopathy 
 *   Immune System Disorders : Anaphylaxis, other allergic/hypersensitivity reactions (including urticaria, angioedema) 
 *   Eye Disorders : Ocular hyperemia 
 *   Nervous System Disorders : Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS), convulsions, febrile convulsions, myelitis (including encephalomyelitis and transverse myelitis), facial palsy (Bell's palsy), optic neuritis/neuropathy, brachial neuritis, syncope (shortly after vaccination), dizziness, paresthesia 
 *   Vascular Disorders : Vasculitis, vasodilatation/flushing 
 *   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorder s: Dyspnea, pharyngitis, rhinitis, cough, wheezing, throat tightness 
 *   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders : Stevens-Johnson syndrome 
 *   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions : Pruritus, asthenia/fatigue, pain in extremities, chest pain 
 *   Gastrointestinal Disorders : Vomiting 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  If Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS) has occurred within 6 weeks following previous influenza vaccination, the decision to give Fluzone Quadrivalent should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  The 1976 swine influenza vaccine was associated with an elevated risk of Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS). Evidence for a causal relation of GBS with other influenza vaccines is inconclusive; if an excess risk exists, it is probably slightly more than 1 additional case per 1 million persons vaccinated. (See  ref. 1  ) If GBS has occurred within 6 weeks following previous influenza vaccination, the decision to give Fluzone Quadrivalent should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and risks.



    5.2 Preventing and Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of Fluzone Quadrivalent.



    5.3 Altered Immunocompetence



  If Fluzone Quadrivalent is administered to immunocompromised persons, including those receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained.



    5.4 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with Fluzone Quadrivalent may not protect all recipients.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
