<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="menomune" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Common (&gt;10%) adverse events in children 2 to 10 years of age were injection site pain, drowsiness, irritability, and diarrhea. (  6  ) 
 *  Common (&gt;10%) adverse events in persons 11 to 55 years of age were pain, redness, and induration at the injection site, headache, fatigue, malaise, arthralgia, and diarrhea. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sanofi Pasteur Inc. at 1-800-822-2463 (1-800-VACCINE) or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or http://vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1. Data from Clinical Studies

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In three clinical trials primarily designed to assess the safety and immunogenicity of another vaccine, Menactra  (r)  [Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine], participants were randomized to receive Menactra or Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine, which was used as a control vaccine. In these three trials, 1519 children 2-10 years of age, 972 persons 11-18 years of age, and 1170 adults 18-55 years of age, respectively, received a dose of Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine. Overall, of the children 2-10 years of age who received Menactra or Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine, 68% were enrolled at US sites and 32% were enrolled at a Chilean site. The median ages of US and Chilean children were 6 and 5 years, respectively; overall, 50.5% were males and 92.0% were Caucasian. Among participants 11-55 years of age who received Menactra or Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine, all were enrolled at US sites; 54.8% were female; 87.7% were Caucasian.



 Solicited local and systemic reactions were monitored daily for 7 days post-vaccination using a diary card. Information on serious adverse events was collected at interim clinic visits and by telephone interview conducted 6 months post-vaccination. At least 94% of participants from the three studies completed the 6-month follow-up.



     Serious Adverse Events  



 Across the three studies, serious adverse events within 6-months following Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine were reported in 0.7% of 1519 children 2-10 years of age, 0.6% of 972 persons 11-18 years of age, and 1.7% of 1170 persons 18-55 years of age.



      Solicited Adverse Events   (Events in Table 1 and Table 2 were collected in the clinical trials under "Solicited local and systemic reactions.") 
 

 The most commonly reported solicited adverse events in US children 2-10 years of age were injection site pain, irritability, and diarrhea. (Table 1)



 The most commonly reported solicited adverse events in adolescents, ages 11-18 years, and adults, ages 18-55 years, were injection site pain, headache, and fatigue. (Table 2)



 Table 1: Percentage of US Participants 2-10 Years of Age Reporting Solicited Adverse Events Within 7 Days Following Administration of Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 Vaccine 
                                                     N=1019-1027        
 Event                                               Any               Moderate            Severe             
                                                     %                 %                   %                  
  
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                             
   Injection site reaction                                                                                    
 Pain                                                26.1              2.5                 0.0                
 Redness                                             7.9               0.5                 0.0                
 Induration                                          4.2               0.6                 0.0                
 Swelling                                            2.8               0.3                 0.0                
   Systemic events                                                                                            
 Fever                                               5.2               1.7                 0.2                
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                 
 Anorexia                                            8.7               1.3                 0.8                
 Vomiting                                            2.7               0.7                 0.6                
 Diarrhea                                            11.8              2.5                 0.3                
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                   
 Drowsiness                                          11.2              2.5                 0.5                
 Irritability                                        12.2              2.6                 0.6                
 Seizures                                            0.0               N/A                 N/A                
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                             
 Arthralgia                                          5.3               0.7                 0.0                
   Skin and subcutaneous disorders                                                                            
 Rash                                                3.0               N/A                 N/A                
         Table 2: Percentage of Participants 11-55 Years of Age Reporting Solicited Adverse Events Within 7 Days Following Administration of Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 Vaccine 
                                     Study 1N=970  Study 2N=1159   
                                     Participants 11-18 years of age  Participants 18-55 years of age   
 Event                                   Any        Moderate       Severe       Any        Moderate       Severe    
  
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                
   Injection site reaction                                                                                          
 Pain                                   28.7          2.6          0.0         48.1          3.3          0.1       
 Redness                                5.7           0.4          0.0         16.0          1.9          0.1       
 Induration                             5.2           0.5          0.0         11.0          1.0          0.0       
 Swelling                               3.6           0.3          0.0         7.6           0.7          0.0       
   Systemic events                                                                                                  
 Fatigue                                25.1          6.2          0.2         32.3          6.6          0.4       
 Malaise                                16.8          3.4          0.4         22.3          4.7          0.9       
 Chills                                 3.5           0.4          0.1         5.6           1.0          0.0       
 Fever                                  3.0           0.3          0.1         0.5           0.1          0.0       
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                       
 Diarrhea                               10.2          1.3          0.0         14.0          2.9          0.3       
 Anorexia                               7.7           1.1          0.2         9.9           1.6          0.4       
 Vomiting                               1.4           0.5          0.3         1.5           0.2          0.4       
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                         
 Headache                               29.3          6.5          0.4         41.8          8.9          0.9       
 Seizure                                0.0           N/A          N/A         0.0           N/A          N/A       
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                                   
 Arthralgia                             10.2          2.1          0.1         16.0          2.6          0.1       
   Skin and subcutaneous disorders                                                                                   
 Rash                                   1.4           N/A          N/A         0.8           N/A          N/A       
               6.2. Data from Post-Marketing Experience
   The following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during post-approval use of Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine since 1993 through November 2008. Because these events were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or to establish a causal relationship to Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine exposure.



 The following adverse events were included based on severity, frequency of reporting or the strength of causal association to Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine.



 *  *     Hypersensitivity, such as rash, urticaria, pruritus, dyspnea, angioedema 
   Immune System Disorders 
 *  *     Headache, vasovagal syncope, dizziness, paresthesia, Guillain-Barre syndrome 
   Nervous System Disorders 
 *  *     Nausea, vomiting, diarrhea 
   Gastrointestinal Disorders 
 *  *     Myalgia, arthralgia 
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders 
 *  *     Fever, injection site reaction, malaise, asthenia, chills, fatigue 
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  The stoppers to the vials of lyophilized vaccine and diluent contain dry natural latex rubber that may cause allergic reactions. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1. Latex



  The stoppers to the vials of lyophilized vaccine and diluent contain dry natural latex rubber that may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive persons.



    5.2. Management of Acute Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine.



    5.3. Moderate or Severe Acute Illness



  To avoid diagnostic confusion between manifestations of an acute illness and possible vaccine adverse effects, vaccination with Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine should be postponed in persons with moderate or severe acute illness. (4)



    5.4. Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine may not protect all recipients.



    5.5. Altered Immunocompetence



  Persons who are immunosuppressed, including persons receiving immunosuppressive therapy, may have a diminished immune response to Menomune - A/C/Y/W-135 vaccine [see   Drug Interactions (7)    ] .  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
