<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="menveo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    Common solicited adverse reactions ( &gt; 10%) among children initiating vaccination at 2 months of age and receiving the four-dose series were tenderness (24% to 41%) and erythema at injection site (11% to 15%), irritability (42% to 57%), sleepiness (29% to 50%), persistent crying (21% to 41%), change in eating habits (17% to 23%), vomiting (5% to 11%), and diarrhea (8% to 16%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    Common solicited adverse reactions ( &gt;= 10%) among children initiating vaccination at 7 months through 23 months of age and receiving the two-dose series were tenderness (10% to 16%) and erythema at injection site (12% to 15%), irritability (27% to 40%), sleepiness (17% to 29%), persistent crying (12-21%), change in eating habits (12% to 20%), and diarrhea (10% to 16%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    Common solicited adverse reactions ( &gt; 10%) among children 2 years through 10 years of age who received MENVEO were injection site pain (31%), erythema (23%), irritability (18%), induration (16%), sleepiness (14%), malaise (12%), and headache (11%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    Common solicited adverse reactions ( &gt; 10%) among adolescents and adults who received MENVEO were pain at the injection site (41%), headache (30%), myalgia (18%), malaise (16%), and nausea (10%). (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249    or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or  www.vaers.hhs.gov.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Children 2 Months through 23 Months of Age  



 The safety of MENVEO in infants vaccinated at 2, 4, 6, and 12 months of age was evaluated in three randomized multicenter clinical studies  1-3  conducted in the U.S., Australia, Canada, Taiwan, and several countries of Latin America in which 8,735 infants received at least one dose of MENVEO and routine infant vaccines (diphtheria toxoid; acellular pertussis; tetanus toxoid; inactivated polio types 1, 2, and 3; hepatitis B;  Haemophilus influenzae  type b (Hib) antigens; pentavalent rotavirus; and 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate). With Dose 4 of MENVEO, toddlers received concomitantly the following vaccines: 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate; measles, mumps, rubella, and varicella; and inactivated hepatitis A. A total of 2,864 infants in these studies received the routine infant/toddler vaccines only. The infants who received MENVEO were Caucasian (33%), Hispanic (44%), African American (8%), Asian (8%), and other racial/ethnic groups (7%); 51% were male, with a mean age of 65.1 days (Standard Deviation [SD]: 7.5 days) at the time of first vaccination.



 Safety data for administration of two doses of MENVEO in children between 6 through 23 months of age are available from three randomized studies  1,4,5  conducted in the U.S., Latin America, and Canada, of which one U.S. study specifically addressed the safety of MENVEO administered concomitantly with measles, mumps, rubella, and varicella vaccine (MMRV). The 1,985 older infants and toddlers who received two doses of MENVEO were Caucasian (49%), Hispanic (32%), African American (11%), and other racial/ethnic groups (8%), 51% male, with a mean age of 10.1 months (SD: 2.0 months).



   Children 2 Years through 10 Years of Age  



 The safety of MENVEO in children 2 years through 10 years of age was evaluated in four clinical trials  6-9  conducted in North America (66%), Latin America (28%), and Europe (6%) in which 3,181 subjects received MENVEO and 2,116 subjects received comparator vaccines (either Meningococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, Groups A, C, Y, and W-135 Combined - MENOMUNE  (r)  , Sanofi Pasteur [n = 861], or Meningococcal (Groups A, C, Y, and W-135) Polysaccharide Diphtheria Toxoid Conjugate Vaccine - MENACTRA  (r)  , Sanofi Pasteur [n = 1,255]). The subjects 2 years through 10 years of age who received MENVEO were Caucasian (69%), Hispanic (13%), African American (7%), and other racial/ethnic groups (6%), 51% male, with a mean age of 5.2 years. The safety of a second dose of MENVEO administered 2 months following a first dose was studied in 351 children 2 years through 5 years of age.



   Adolescents and Adults  



 The safety of MENVEO in individuals 11 through 55 years of age was evaluated in five randomized controlled clinical trials  10-14  in which 6,185 participants received MENVEO alone (5,286 participants), MENVEO concomitant with other vaccine(s) (899 participants), or a U.S.-licensed comparator vaccine (1,966 participants). In the concomitant trials  11,14  MENVEO was given with vaccines containing: tetanus toxoid, diphtheria toxoid and pertussis (Tdap), or Tdap with human papillomavirus (HPV). The comparator vaccine was either MENOMUNE (209 participants) or MENACTRA (1,757 participants). The trials were conducted in North America (46%), Latin America (41%), and Europe (13%). In two of the studies, subjects received concomitant vaccination with Tdap or with Tdap plus HPV. Overall, subjects were Caucasian (50%), followed by Hispanic (40%), African American (7%), and other racial/ethnic groups (3%). Among recipients of MENVEO, 61%, 17%, and 22% were in the 11 through 18-year, 19 through 34-year and 35 through 55-year age groups, respectively, with a mean age of 23.5 years (SD: 12.9 years). Among MENACTRA recipients, 31%, 32%, and 37% were in the 11 through 18-year, 19 through 34-year and 35 through 55-year age groups, respectively, with a mean age of 29.2 years (SD: 13.4 years). Among MENOMUNE recipients, 100% were in the 11 through 18-year age group, and the mean age was 14.2 years (SD: 1.8 years).



 In most trials, solicited local and systemic adverse reactions were monitored daily for 7 days following each (one or more) vaccination and recorded on a diary card. Participants were monitored for unsolicited adverse events which included adverse events requiring a physician visit or Emergency Department visit (i.e., medically-attended) or which led to a subject's withdrawal from the study. Among children, adolescents, and adults aged 2 years to 55 years, medically significant adverse events and serious adverse events (SAE) were monitored for 6 months after vaccination. Across the studies of infants and toddlers aged 2 months through 23 months, either all medically-attended or all medically-significant adverse events were collected in the period between the infant dose(s) and the toddler doses and during the 6-month period after the toddler dose.



     Solicited Adverse Reactions    



 The reported frequencies of solicited local and systemic adverse reactions from U.S. infants in the largest multinational safety study of MENVEO  2  are presented in Table 1. Among the U.S. participants in the group receiving MENVEO with routine vaccines, 51% were female; 64% were Caucasian, 12% were African American, 15% were Hispanic, 2% were Asian, and 7% were of other racial/ethnic groups.



 In infants initiating vaccination at 2 months of age and receiving the four-dose series, common solicited adverse reactions (  &gt;  10%) were tenderness (24% to 41%) and erythema at injection site (11% to 15%), irritability (42% to 57%), sleepiness (29% to 50%), persistent crying (21% to 41%), change in eating habits (17% to 23%), vomiting (5% to 11%), and diarrhea (8% to 16%). The rates of solicited adverse reactions reported for subjects aged 2 months and above receiving MENVEO with routine vaccines at 2, 4, 6 and 12 months of age were comparable to rates among subjects who only received routine vaccines.



   Table 1: Rates of Solicited Adverse Reactions Reported in U.S. Infants, 2 Months of Age and Older, during the 7 Days following Each Vaccination with MENVEO Administered with Routine Infant/Toddler Vaccines, or Routine Infant/Toddler Vaccines Alone, at 2, 4, 6, and 12 Months of Age  a    




                 Dose 1       Dose 2      Dose 3       Dose 4      
                 MENVEO withRoutine  b    
                %             
                                             Routine Vaccines  b    
              %           
                                        MENVEO    
              withRoutine  b    
             %          
                                       Routine Vaccines  b    
              %           
                                        MENVEO    
              withRoutine  b    
             %          
                                       Routine Vaccines  b    
              %           
                                        MENVEO    
              withRoutine  b    
             %          
                                       Routine Vaccines  b    
              %           
                            
  Local Adverse Reactionsc    n = 1,250-1,252    n = 428     n = 1,205-1,207    n = 399     n = 1,056-1,058    n = 351-352    n = 1,054-1,055    n = 334-337    
  Tenderness, any    41           45          31           36          24           32          29           39          
  Tenderness, severed    3            5           2            2           1            3           1            1           
  Erythema, any    11           14          12           21          14           23          15           25          
  Erythema,  &gt;50 mm    &lt;1           &lt;1          0            0           0            0           0            0           
  Induration, any    8            16          9            17          8            19          8            21          
  Induration,  &gt;50 mm    0            &lt;1          0            0           0            0           0            0           
  Systemic Adverse Reactions    n = 1,246-1,251    n = 427-428    n = 1,119-1,202    n = 396-398    n = 1,050-1,057    n = 349-350    n = 1,054-1,056    n = 333-337    
  Irritability, any    57           59          48           46          42           38          43           42          
  Irritability, severee    2            2           1            3           1            1           2            1           
  Sleepiness, any    50           50          37           36          30           30          29           27          
  Sleepiness, severef    2            1           1            1           &lt;1           &lt;1          1            0           
  Persistent crying, any    41           38          28           24          22           17          21           18          
  Persistent crying,  &gt;=3 hours    2            2           2            2           1            1           1            1           
  Change in eating habits, any    23           24          18           17          17           13          19           16          
  Change in eating habits, severeg    1            1           1            1           1            &lt;1          1            0           
  Vomiting, any    11           9           7            6           6            4           5            4           
  Vomiting, severeh    &lt;1           0           &lt;1           0           &lt;1           0           &lt;1           0           
  Diarrhea, any    16           11          11           8           8            6           13           9           
  Diarrhea, severei    &lt;1           &lt;1          &lt;1           &lt;1          1            &lt;1          1            1           
  Rashj          3            3           3            4           3            3           4            3           
  Fever &gt;=38. degrees Ck    3            2           4            6           7            6           9            7           
  Fever 38.0-38.9 degrees C    3            2           4            5           7            6           6            5           
  Fever 39.0-39.9 degrees C    0            0           1            1           &lt;1           0           2            2           
  Fever &gt;=40.0 degrees C    0            &lt;1          0            &lt;1          0            0           &lt;1           0           
              *     Clinicaltrials.gov Identifier NCT00806195.  2   
 *     n = Number of subjects who completed the diary card for a given symptom at the specified vaccination. 
 *       a  As-Treated Safety Subpopulation = U.S. children who received at least one dose of study vaccine and whose diary cards were completed per protocol and returned to the site. 
 *       b  Routine infant/toddler vaccines include DTaP-IPV-Hib and PCV7 at Doses 1, 2, 3, and PCV7, MMRV and Hepatitis A vaccines at Dose 4. HBV and rotavirus vaccines were allowed according to ACIP recommendations. 
 *       c  Local reactogenicity of MENVEO and PCV7 was assessed. 
 *       d  Tenderness, severe = Cried when injected limb moved. 
 *       e  Irritability, severe = Unable to console. 
 *       f  Sleepiness, severe = Sleeps most of the time, hard to arouse. 
 *       g  Change in eating habits, severe = Missed &gt;2 feeds. 
 *       h  Vomiting, severe = Little/no intake for more prolonged time. 
 *       i  Diarrhea, severe = &gt;=6 liquid stools, no solid consistency. 
 *       j  Rash was assessed only as present or not present, without a grading for severity. 
 *       k  Axillary temperature. 
    The safety of a second dose of MENVEO administered at 12 months of age concomitantly with MMRV was investigated in a randomized, controlled, multicenter study  5  conducted in the U.S. The rates of solicited adverse reactions reported were comparable between the concomitantly administered group (MENVEO with MMRV) and the group which received MMRV alone, or MENVEO alone. The frequency and severity of solicited local and systemic reactions occurring within 7 days following vaccination at 12 months of age are shown in Table 2. In subjects who received both MENVEO and MMRV at 12 months of age local reactions at both injection sites were evaluated separately. Body temperature measurements were collected for 28 days following the 12-months-of-age visit, when MMRV was administered to the vaccinees. Common solicited adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) among children initiating vaccination at 7 months through 23 months of age and receiving the two-dose series were tenderness (10% to 16%) and erythema at injection site (12% to 15%), irritability (27% to 40%), sleepiness (17% to 29%), persistent crying (12% to 21%), change in eating habits (12% to 20%), and diarrhea (10% to 16%). An examination of the fever profile during this period showed that MENVEO administered with MMRV did not increase the frequency or intensity of fever above that observed for the MMRV-only group.
 

   Table 2: Rates of Solicited Adverse Reactions Reported in U.S. Toddlers during the 7 Days following Vaccination with MENVEO Administered at 7-9 Months and 12 Months of Age, MENVEO Administered Alone at 7-9 Months and with MMRV at 12 Months of Age, and MMRV Administered Alone at 12 Months of Age  a    




                             MENVEO           MENVEO + MMRV    MMRV             
  MENVEO  7-9 Months  %      MENVEO  12 Months  %    MENVEO  7-9 Months  %    MENVEO with MMRV  12 Months%    MMRV  12 Months  %    
  Local Adverse Reactions- MENVEO Site    n = 460-462      n = 381-384      n = 430-434      n = 386-387                        
  Tenderness, any            11               10               11               16              N/A                
  Tenderness, severeb        &lt;1               &lt;1               &lt;1               0               N/A                
  Erythema, any              15               13               13               12              N/A                
  Erythema, &gt;50 mm           &lt;1               &lt;1               0                1               N/A                
  Induration, any            8                8                7                8               N/A                
  Induration, &gt;50 mm         &lt;1               &lt;1               0                1               N/A                
  Local Adverse Reactions- MMRV Site                                                       n = 382-383     n = 518-520        
  Tenderness, any            N/A              N/A              N/A              16              19                 
  Tenderness, severeb        N/A              N/A              N/A              0               &lt;1                 
  Erythema, any              N/A              N/A              N/A              15              14                 
  Erythema, &gt;50 mm           N/A              N/A              N/A              1               &lt;1                 
  Induration, any            N/A              N/A              N/A              13              8                  
  Induration, &gt;50 mm         N/A              N/A              N/A              &lt;1              0                  
  Systemic Adverse Reactions    n = 461-463      n = 385-386      n = 430-434      n = 387-389     n = 522-524        
  Irritability, any          40               27               37               37              44                 
  Irritability, severec      2                2                2                1               3                  
  Sleepiness, any            26               17               29               26              32                 
  Sleepiness, severed        2                1                1                1               2                  
  Persistent crying, any     21               12               20               19              20                 
  Persistent crying,  &gt;=3 hours    2                1                1                1               2                  
  Change in eating habits, any    17               12               17               20              20                 
  Change in eating habits, severee    &lt;1               1                1                2               1                  
  Vomiting, any              9                6                9                6               6                  
  Vomiting, severef          &lt;1               &lt;1               &lt;1               &lt;1              &lt;1                 
  Diarrhea, any              16               10               15               15              20                 
  Diarrhea, severeg          2                1                &lt;1               1               2                  
  Rashh                      3                5                6                6               8                  
  Fever &gt;=38.0 degrees Ci    5                5                6                9               7                  
  Fever 38.0-38.9 degrees C    3                3                5                7               7                  
  Fever 39.0-39.9 degrees C    2                2                1                1               1                  
  Fever &gt;=40.0 degrees C     &lt;1               1                &lt;1               &lt;1              0                  
           *     Clinicaltrials.gov Identifier NCT00626327  5  . 
 *     n = Number of subjects who completed the diary card for a given symptom at the specified vaccination. 
 *       a  As-Treated Safety Subpopulation = U.S. children who received at least one dose of study vaccine and whose diary cards were completed per protocol and returned to the site. 
 *       b  Tenderness, severe = Cried when injected limb moved. 
 *       c  Irritability, severe = Unable to console. 
 *       d  Sleepiness, severe = Sleeps most of the time, hard to arouse. 
 *       e  Change in eating habits, severe = Missed &gt;2 feeds. 
 *       f  Vomiting, severe = Little/no intake for more prolonged time. 
 *       g  Diarrhea, severe = &gt;=6 liquid stools, no solid consistency. 
 *       h  Rash was assessed only as present or not present, without a grading for severity. 
 *       i  Axillary temperature. 
    In clinical trials of children 2 years through 10 years of age,  6-9  the most frequently occurring adverse reactions (  &gt;  10%) among all subjects who received MENVEO were injection site pain (31%), erythema (23%), irritability (18%), induration (16%), sleepiness (14%), malaise (12%), and headache (11%). Among subjects 11 years through 55 years of age, the most frequently occurring adverse reactions (  &gt;  10%) among all subjects who received MENVEO were pain at the injection site (41%), headache (30%), myalgia (18%), malaise (16%), and nausea (10%).
 

 The rates of solicited adverse reactions reported for subjects 2 years through 5 years and 6 years through 10 years of age who received a single dose of MENVEO or MENACTRA in a randomized controlled, multicenter study  9  conducted in the U.S. and Canada are shown in Table 3. Following a second dose of MENVEO administered to children 2 years through 5 years of age, the most common solicited adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) were pain at injection site (28%), erythema (22%), irritability (16%), induration (13%), and sleepiness (12%). The solicited adverse events from a separate randomized, controlled, multicenter study conducted in the U.S. in adolescents and adults  12  are provided in Tables 4 and 5, respectively. In neither study were concomitant vaccines administered with the study vaccines.



   Table 3: Rates of Solicited Adverse Reactions within 7 Days following a Single Vaccination in Children 2 Years through 5 Years and 6 Years through 10 Years of Age  




  Participants 2 through 5 Years of Age    
  Local Adverse Reaction        MENVEO  n = 693  %    MENACTRA  n = 684  %    
  Any                           Moderate      Severe        Any            Moderate     Severe        
  Injection site paina          33            6             1              35           8             0.4           
  Erythemab                     27            5             1              25           3             0.3           
  Indurationb                   18            2             0.4            18           2             0.3           
  Systemic Adverse Reactione                                                                                        
  Irritabilitya                 21            6             1              22           7             1             
  Sleepinessa                   16            3             1              18           5             1             
  Change in eatinga             9             2             1              10           2             0.3           
  Diarrheaa                     7             1             0.1            8            1             0             
  Headachea                     5             1             0              6            1             0.3           
  Rashc                         4             -             -              5            -             -             
  Arthralgiaa                   3             1             0.1            4            1             0             
  Vomitinga                     3             1             0.1            3            1             0             
  Feverd                        2             0.4           0              2            0.3           0             
  Participants 6 through 10 Years of Age    
  Local Adverse Reaction        MENVEO  n = 582  %    MENACTRA  n = 571  %    
  Any                           Moderate      Severe        Any            Moderate     Severe        
  Injection site paina          39            8             1              45           10            2             
  Erythemab                     28            5             1              22           2             0.2           
  Indurationb                   17            2             0.3            13           2             0             
  Systemic Adverse Reactione                                                                                        
  Headachea                     18            3             1              13           2             1             
  Malaisea                      14            3             1              11           3             1             
  Myalgiaa                      10            2             1              10           2             1             
  Nauseaa                       8             2             1              6            2             0.4           
  Arthralgiaa                   6             1             0              4            1             0.4           
  Chillsa                       5             1             0              5            1             0.4           
  Rashc                         5             -             -              3            -             -             
  Feverd                        2             1             0              2            0             0.4           
            *     Clinicaltrials.gov Identifier NCT00616421.  9   
 *       a  Moderate: Some limitation in normal daily activity, Severe: Unable to perform normal daily activity. 
 *       b  Moderate: &gt;=50-100 mm, Severe: &gt;=100 mm. 
 *       c  Rash was assessed only as present or not present, without a grading for severity. 
 *       d  Fever grading: Any: &gt;=38 degrees C, Moderate: 39-39.9 degrees C, Severe: &gt;=40 degrees C. Parents reported the use of antipyretic medication to treat or prevent symptoms in 11% and 13% of subjects 2 through 5 years of age, 9% and 10% of subjects 6 through 10 years of age for MENVEO and MENACTRA, respectively. 
 *       e  Different systemic reactions were solicited in different age groups. 
      Table 4: Rates of Solicited Adverse Reactions within 7 Days following Vaccination in Individuals 11 Years through 18 Years of Age  
 


  Local Adverse  Reaction    MENVEO  n = 1,631  %    MENACTRA  n = 539  %    
  Any                        Moderate       Severe         Any            Moderate       Severe         
                                                                                                                       
  Injection site paina       44             9              1              53             11             1              
  Erythemab                  15             2              0.4            16             1              0              
  Indurationb                12             2              0.2            11             1              0              
  Systemic Adverse  Reaction                                                                                              
  Headachea                  29             8              2              28             7              1              
  Myalgiaa                   19             4              1              18             5              0.4            
  Nauseaa                    12             3              1              9              2              1              
  Malaisea                   11             3              1              12             5              1              
  Chillsa                    8              2              1              7              1              0.2            
  Arthralgiaa                8              2              0.4            6              1              0              
  Rashc                      3              -              -              3              -              -              
  Feverd                     1              0.4            0              1              0              0              
            *     Clinicaltrials.gov Identifier NCT00450437.  12   
 *       a  Moderate: Some limitation in normal daily activity, Severe: Unable to perform normal daily activity. 
 *       b  Moderate: &gt;=50-100 mm, Severe: &gt;=100 mm. 
 *       c  Rash was assessed only as present or not present, without a grading for severity. 
 *       d  Fever grading: Any: &gt;=38 degrees C, Moderate: 39-39.9 degrees C, Severe: &gt;=40 degrees C. 
      Table 5: Rates of Solicited Adverse Reactions within 7 Days following Vaccination in Individuals 19 Years through 55 Years of Age  
 


  Local AdverseReaction    MENVEOn = 1,018  %    MENACTRAn = 336  %    
  Any                    Moderate       Severe         Any            Moderate       Severe         
                                                                                                                   
  Injection site paina    38             7              0.3            41             6              0              
  Erythemab              16             2              1              12             1              0              
  Indurationb            13             1              0.4            9              0.3            0              
  SystemicAdverseReaction                                                                                              
  Headachea              25             7              2              25             7              1              
  Myalgiaa               14             4              0.5            15             3              1              
  Malaisea               10             3              1              10             2              1              
  Nauseaa                7              2              0.4            5              1              0.3            
  Arthralgiaa            6              2              0.4            6              1              1              
  Chillsa                4              1              0.1            4              1              0              
  Rashc                  2              -              -              1              -              -              
  Feverd                 1              0.3            0              1              0.3            0              
            *     Clinicaltrials.gov Identifier NCT00450437.  12   
 *       a  Moderate: Some limitation in normal daily activity, Severe: Unable to perform normal daily activity. 
 *       b  Moderate: &gt;=50-100 mm, Severe: &gt;=100 mm. 
 *       c  Rash was assessed only as present or not present, without a grading for severity. 
 *       d  Fever grading: Any: &gt;=38 degrees C, Moderate: 39-39.9 degrees C, Severe: &gt;=40 degrees C. 
        Solicited Adverse Reactions following Concomitant Vaccine Administration    
 

 The safety of 4-dose series of MENVEO administered concomitantly with U.S.-licensed routine infant and toddler vaccines was evaluated in one pivotal trial  2  . The safety of a 2-dose series of MENVEO initiated at 7-9 months of age, with the second dose administered concomitantly with U.S.-licensed MMR and V vaccine at 12 months of age, was evaluated in one pivotal trial.  5  Rates of solicited adverse reactions which occurred 7 days following vaccination are shown in Tables 1 and 2, respectively. There was no significant increase in the rates of solicited systemic or local reactions observed in recipients of routine childhood vaccines when concomitantly vaccinated with MENVEO.  [  See  Concomitant Administration with Other Vaccines (7.1).]  



 The safety of MENVEO administered concomitantly with Tdap and HPV was evaluated in a single center study  14  conducted in Costa Rica. Solicited local and systemic adverse reactions were reported as noted above. In this study, subjects 11 through 18 years of age received MENVEO concomitantly with Tdap and HPV (n = 540), or MENVEO followed one month later by Tdap and then one month later by HPV (n = 541), or Tdap followed one month later by MENVEO and then one month later by HPV (n = 539). Some solicited systemic adverse reactions were more frequently reported in the group that received MENVEO, Tdap, and HPV concomitantly, (headache 40%, malaise 25%, myalgia 27%, and arthralgia 17%) compared with the group that first received MENVEO alone (headache 36%, malaise 20%, myalgia 19%, and arthralgia 11%). Among subjects administered MENVEO alone (one month prior to Tdap), 36% reported headache, 20% malaise, and 16% myalgia. Among subjects administered MENVEO one month after Tdap, 27% reported headache, 18% malaise, and 16% myalgia.



     Serious Adverse Events in All Safety Studies    



 Serious adverse events in subjects receiving a four-dose series of MENVEO at 2, 4, 6, and 12 months were evaluated in three randomized multicenter clinical studies.  1-3  In the two controlled studies,  2,3  the proportions of infants randomized to receive the four-dose series of MENVEO concomitantly with routine vaccinations and infants who received routine vaccinations alone that reported serious adverse events during different study periods were, respectively: a) 2.7% and 2.2%, during the infant series; b) 2.5% and 2.5%, between the infant series and the toddler dose; c) 0.3% and 0.3%, in the one month following the toddler dose; and d) 1.6% and 2.2%, during the 6-month follow-up period after the last dose. In the third study,  1  which was controlled up to the toddler dose, the proportions of infants randomized to dosing regimens that included receiving four doses of MENVEO concomitantly with routine vaccinations at 2, 4, 6, and 12 months and infants who received routine vaccinations alone that reported serious adverse events during different study periods were, respectively: a) 3.5% and 3.6%, during the infant series; and b) 2.8% and 3.3%, between the infant series and the toddler dose; and c) 0.5% and 0.7%, in the one month following the toddler dose. In the same study, 1.9% of infants randomized to receive the four-dose series of MENVEO concomitantly with routine vaccinations reported serious adverse events during the 6-month follow-up period after the toddler dose. The most common serious adverse events reported in these three studies were wheezing, pneumonia, gastroenteritis, and convulsions, and most occurred at highest frequency after the infant series.



 In a study of older infants  5  randomized to receive the two-dose series of MENVEO concomitantly with MMRV at 12 months of age, the rates of serious adverse events during the study, including the 6-month follow-up period after the last dose, were 3.6% and 3.8%, for the groups receiving MENVEO with MMRV and MENVEO only, respectively. Infants receiving MMRV alone, who had a shorter period of study participation as they were enrolled at 12 months of age, had a lower rate of serious adverse events (1.5%). Among 1,597 study subjects included in the safety population, the most commonly reported serious adverse events in all study arms combined were dehydration (0.4%) and gastroenteritis (0.3%). Across the submitted studies of individuals 2 through 23 months of age, within 28 days of vaccination, two deaths were reported in the groups receiving MENVEO (one case of sudden death and one case of sepsis), while no deaths were reported in the control group. None of the deaths was assessed as related to vaccination. Among subjects with symptom onset within 42 days of vaccination (Days 12, 25, 29), 3/12,049 [0.02%, 95% CI: (0.01%, 0.07%)] recipients of MENVEO and 0/2,877 [0%, 95% CI: (0%, 0.13%)] control recipients were diagnosed with Kawasaki Disease. One case of acute disseminated encephalomyelitis with symptom onset 29 days post-Dose 4 was observed in a participant given MENVEO coadministered with routine U.S. childhood vaccines at 12 months of age (including MMR and varicella vaccines).



 The information regarding serious adverse events in subjects 2 years through 10 years of age was derived from 3 randomized, controlled clinical trials.  7-9  Safety follow-up ranged from 6 months through 12 months and included 2,883 subjects administered MENVEO. Serious adverse events reported during the safety follow-up periods occurred in 21/2,883 (0.7%) of subjects receiving MENVEO, in 7/1,255 (0.6%) of MENACTRA subjects, and 2/861 (0.2%) of MENOMUNE subjects. In the subjects receiving either one or two doses of MENVEO, there were 6 subjects with pneumonia, 3 subjects with appendicitis, and 2 subjects with dehydration; all other events were reported to occur in one subject. Among 1,255 subjects administered a single dose of MENACTRA and 861 subjects administered MENOMUNE, there were no events reported to occur in more than one subject. The serious adverse events occurring within the first 30 days after receipt of each vaccine were as follows: MENVEO (6/2,883 [0.2%]) - appendicitis, pneumonia, staphylococcal infection, dehydration, febrile convulsion, and tonic convulsion; MENACTRA (1/1255 [0.1%]) - inguinal hernia; MENOMUNE (2/861 [0.2%]) - abdominal pain, lobar pneumonia. In a supportive study,  6  298 subjects received one or two doses of MENVEO and 22 (7%) had serious adverse events over a 13-month follow-up period including 13 subjects with varicella and 2 subjects with laryngitis. All other events were reported to occur in one subject. During the 30 days post vaccination in this study, one limb injury and one case of varicella were reported.



 The information regarding serious adverse events in subjects 11 years through 55 years of age was derived from 5 randomized, controlled clinical trials.  10-14  Serious adverse events reported within 6 months of vaccination occurred in 40/6,185 (0.6%) of subjects receiving MENVEO, 13/1,757 (0.7%) of MENACTRA subjects, and 5/209 (2.4%) of MENOMUNE subjects. During the 6 months following immunization, serious adverse events reported by more than one subject were as follows: MENVEO - appendicitis (3 subjects), road traffic accident (3 subjects), and suicide attempt (5 subjects); MENACTRA - intervertebral disc protrusion (2 subjects); MENOMUNE - none. Serious adverse events that occurred within 30 days of vaccination were reported by 7 of 6,185 (0.1%) subjects in the group receiving MENVEO, 4 of 1,757 (0.2%) subjects in the MENACTRA group, and by none of 209 subjects in the MENOMUNE group. The events that occurred during the first 30 days post immunization with MENVEO were: vitello-intestinal duct remnant, Cushing's syndrome, viral hepatitis, pelvic inflammatory disease, intentional multiple drug overdose, simple partial seizure, and suicidal depression. The events that occurred during the first 30 days post immunization with MENACTRA were: herpes zoster, fall, intervertebral disc protrusion, and angioedema.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to reports in clinical trials, worldwide voluntary reports of adverse events received for MENVEO in persons 11 through 55 years of age since market introduction of this vaccine are listed below. This list includes serious events or events which have plausible causal connection to MENVEO. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine.



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders  



 Hearing impaired, ear pain, vertigo, vestibular disorder.



   Eye Disorders  



 Eyelid ptosis.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  



 Injection site pruritus, pain, erythema, inflammation and swelling, fatigue, malaise, pyrexia.



   Immune System Disorders  



 Hypersensitivity.



   Infections and Infestations  



 Vaccination site cellulitis.



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications  



 Fall, head injury.



   Investigation  



 Alanine aminotransferase increased, body temperature increased.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  



 Arthralgia, bone pain.



   Nervous System Disorders  



 Dizziness, syncope, tonic convulsion, headache, facial paresis, balance disorder.



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  



 Oropharyngeal pain.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Skin exfoliation.



   Postmarketing Observational Safety Study  



 In a postmarketing observational safety study conducted in a United States health maintenance organization, data from electronic health records of 48,899 persons 11 through 21 years of age were used to evaluate pre-specified events of interest following vaccination with MENVEO. Using a self-controlled case series method, Bell's palsy showed a statistically significant increased risk in the period 1 to 84 days post vaccination compared with the control period, with an overall adjusted relative incidence of 2.9 (95% CI: 1.1-7.5). Among the 8 reported cases of Bell's palsy, 6 cases occurred in persons who received MENVEO concomitantly with one or more of the following vaccines: Tdap, HPV, and Influenza vaccine. All reported Bell's palsy cases resolved.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Appropriate medical treatment must be available should an acute allergic reaction, including an anaphylactic reaction, occur following administration of MENVEO. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Syncope, sometimes resulting in falling injury, has been reported following vaccination with MENVEO. Vaccinees should be observed for at least 15 minutes after vaccine administration. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including MENVEO, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Acute Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment must be available should an acute allergic reaction, including an anaphylactic reaction, occur following administration of MENVEO.



    5.2 Syncope



  Syncope, sometimes resulting in falling injury associated with seizure-like movements, has been reported following vaccination with MENVEO. Vaccinees should be observed for at least 15 minutes after vaccine administration to prevent and manage syncopal reactions.



    5.3 Altered Immunocompetence



  Safety and effectiveness of MENVEO have not been evaluated in immunocompromised persons. If MENVEO is administered to immunocompromised persons, including those receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained.



    5.4 Guillain-Barre Syndrome



  Guillain-Barre syndrome (GBS) has been reported in temporal relationship following administration of another U.S.-licensed meningococcal quadrivalent polysaccharide conjugate vaccine. The decision to administer MENVEO to subjects with a known history of Guillain-Barre Syndrome should take into account the potential benefits and risks.



    5.5 Apnea in Premature Infants



  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including MENVEO, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status, and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
