<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mesnex1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling.



 *    Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ] 
 *    Dermatological Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] 
 *    Benzyl Alcohol Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] 
 *    Laboratory Test Interferences [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ] 
 *    Use in Patients with a History of Adverse Reactions to Thiol Compounds [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt; 10%) when MESNEX is given with ifosfamide are nausea, vomiting, constipation, leukopenia, fatigue, fever, anorexia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, granulocytopenia, diarrhea, asthenia, abdominal pain, headache, alopecia, and somnolence. (  6.1  )
 

 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare at 1-866-888-2472, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 MESNEX adverse reaction data are available from four Phase 1 studies in which single intravenous doses of 600-1200 mg MESNEX Injection without concurrent chemotherapy were administered to a total of 53 healthy volunteers and single oral doses of 600-2400 mg of MESNEX Tablets were administered to a total of 82 healthy volunteers. The most frequently reported side effects (observed in two or more healthy volunteers) for healthy volunteers receiving single doses of MESNEX Injection alone were headache, injection site reactions, flushing, dizziness, nausea, vomiting, somnolence, diarrhea, anorexia, fever, pharyngitis, hyperesthesia, influenza-like symptoms, and coughing. In two Phase 1 multiple-dose studies where healthy volunteers received MESNEX Tablets alone or intravenous MESNEX followed by repeated doses of MESNEX Tablets, flatulence and rhinitis were reported. In addition, constipation was reported by healthy volunteers who had received repeated doses of intravenous MESNEX.



 Additional adverse reactions in healthy volunteers receiving MESNEX alone included injection site reactions, abdominal pain/colic, epigastric pain/burning, mucosal irritation, lightheadedness, back pain, arthralgia, myalgia, conjunctivitis, nasal congestion, rigors, paresthesia, photophobia, fatigue, lymphadenopathy, extremity pain, malaise, chest pain, dysuria, pleuritic pain, dry mouth, dyspnea, and hyperhidrosis. In healthy volunteers, MESNEX was commonly associated with a rapid (within 24 hours) decrease in lymphocyte count, which was generally reversible within one week of administration.



 Because MESNEX is used in combination with ifosfamide or ifosfamide-containing chemotherapy regimens, it is difficult to distinguish the adverse reactions which may be due to MESNEX from those caused by the concomitantly administered cytotoxic agents.



 Adverse reactions reasonably associated with MESNEX administered intravenously and orally in four controlled studies in which patients received ifosfamide or ifosfamide-containing regimens are presented in Table 3.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 5% of Patients Receiving MESNEX in combination with Ifosfamide-containing Regimens 
  MESNEX Regimen             Intravenous-Intravenous-IntravenousIntravenous dosing of ifosfamide and MESNEX followed by either intravenous or oral doses of MESNEX according to the applicable dosage schedule. [see Dosage and Administration (2)]    Intravenous-Oral-Ora            
  N exposed                  119 (100.0%)                                   119 (100%)                      
  Incidence of AEs           101 (84.9%)                                    106 (89.1%)                     
  Nausea                     65 (54.6)                                      64 (53.8)                       
  Vomiting                   35 (29.4)                                      45 (37.8)                       
  Constipation               28 (23.5)                                      21 (17.6)                       
  Leukopenia                 25 (21.0)                                      21 (17.6)                       
  Fatigue                    24 (20.2)                                      24 (20.2)                       
  Fever                      24 (20.2)                                      18 (15.1)                       
  Anorexia                   21 (17.6)                                      19 (16.0)                       
  Thrombocytopenia           21 (17.6)                                      16 (13.4)                       
  Anemia                     20 (16.8)                                      21 (17.6)                       
  Granulocytopenia           16 (13.4)                                      15 (12.6)                       
  Asthenia                   15 (12.6)                                      21 (17.6)                       
  Abdominal Pain             14 (11.8)                                      18 (15.1)                       
  Alopecia                   12 (10.1)                                      13 (10.9)                       
  Dyspnea                    11 (9.2)                                       11 (9.2)                        
  Chest Pain                 10 (8.4)                                       11 (9.2)                        
  Hypokalemia                10 (8.4)                                       11 (9.2)                        
  Diarrhea                   9 (7.6)                                        17 (14.3)                       
  Dizziness                  9 (7.6)                                        5 (4.2)                         
  Headache                   9 (7.6)                                        13 (10.9)                       
  Pain                       9 (7.6)                                        10 (8.4)                        
  Sweating Increased         9 (7.6)                                        2 (1.7)                         
  Back Pain                  8 (6.7)                                        6 (5.0)                         
  Hematuria                  8 (6.7)                                        7 (5.9)                         
  Injection Site Reaction    8 (6.7)                                        10 (8.4)                        
  Edema                      8 (6.7)                                        9 (7.6)                         
  Edema Peripheral           8 (6.7)                                        8 (6.7)                         
  Somnolence                 8 (6.7)                                        12 (10.1)                       
  Anxiety                    7 (5.9)                                        4 (3.4)                         
  Confusion                  7 (5.9)                                        6 (5.0)                         
  Face Edema                 6 (5.0)                                        5 (4.2)                         
  Insomnia                   6 (5.0)                                        11 (9.2)                        
  Coughing                   5 (4.2)                                        10 (8.4)                        
  Dyspepsia                  4 (3.4)                                        6 (5.0)                         
  Hypotension                4 (3.4)                                        6 (5.0)                         
  Pallor                     4 (3.4)                                        6 (5.0)                         
  Dehydration                3 (2.5)                                        7 (5.9)                         
  Pneumonia                  2 (1.7)                                        8 (6.7)                         
  Tachycardia                1 (0.8)                                        7 (5.9)                         
  Flushing                   1 (0.8)                                        6 (5.0)                         
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been reported in the postmarketing experience of patients receiving MESNEX in combination with ifosfamide or similar drugs, making it difficult to distinguish the adverse reactions which may be due to MESNEX from those caused by the concomitantly administered cytotoxic agents. Because these reactions are reported from a population of unknown size, precise estimates of frequency cannot be made.



 Cardiovascular: Hypertension



 Gastrointestinal: Dysgeusia



 Hepatobiliary: Hepatitis



 Nervous System: Convulsion



 Respiratory: Hemoptysis
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity reactions: Anaphylactic reactions have been reported. Less severe hypersensitivity reactions may also occur. Monitor patients. If a reaction occurs, discontinue MESNEX and provide supportive care. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Dermatologic toxicity: Skin rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis have occurred. Skin rash, urticaria, and angioedema have also been seen. Monitor patients. If a reaction occurs, discontinue MESNEX and provide supportive care. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Benzyl alcohol toxicity: The preservative benzyl alcohol has been associated with serious adverse reactions and death in neonates and premature infants. Avoid use in neonates, premature, and low-birth weight infants. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Laboratory test alterations: False positive tests for urinary ketones and interference with enzymatic CPK activity tests have been seen. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  MESNEX may cause systemic hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis. These reactions may include fever, cardiovascular symptoms (hypotension, tachycardia), acute renal impairment, hypoxia, respiratory distress, urticaria, angioedema, laboratory signs of disseminated intravascular coagulation, hematological abnormalities, increased liver enzymes, nausea, vomiting, arthralgia, and myalgia. These reactions may occur with the first exposure or after several months of exposure. Monitor for signs or symptoms. Discontinue MESNEX and provide supportive care.



    5.2 Dermatologic Toxicity



  Drug rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms and bullous and ulcerative skin and mucosal reactions, consistent with Stevens-Johnson syndrome or toxic epidermal necrolysis have occurred. MESNEX may cause skin and mucosal reactions characterized by urticaria, rash, erythema, pruritus, burning sensation, angioedema, periorbital edema, flushing and stomatitis. These reactions may occur with the first exposure or after several months of exposure. Discontinue MESNEX and provide supportive care.



    5.3 Benzyl Alcohol Toxicity



  Benzyl alcohol, a preservative in MESNEX, has been associated with serious adverse reactions and death (including gasping syndrome) in neonates, premature, and low-birth weight infants. The minimum amount of benzyl alcohol at which toxicity may occur is not known. Consider the combined daily metabolic load of benzyl alcohol from all sources when prescribing MESNEX (10.4 mg benzyl alcohol per mL). Neonates, premature, and low-birth weight infants, as well as patients receiving high dosages, may be more likely to develop toxicity. Monitor patients for signs or symptoms of toxicity. Avoid use in neonates, premature, and low-birth weight infants. [See  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].



    5.4 Laboratory Test Interferences



   False-Positive Urine Tests for Ketone Bodies  



 A false positive test for urinary ketones may arise in patients treated with MESNEX when using nitroprusside sodium-based urine tests (including dipstick tests). The addition of glacial acetic acid can be used to differentiate between a false positive result (cherry-red color that fades) and a true positive result (red-violet color that intensifies).



  False-Negative Tests for Enzymatic CPK Activity  



 MESNEX may interfere with enzymatic creatinine phosphokinase (CPK) activity tests that use a thiol compound (e.g., N-acetylcysteine) for CPK reactiviation. This may result in a falsely low CPK level.



  False-Positive Tests for Ascorbic Acid  



 MESNEX may cause false-positive reactions in Tillman's reagent-based urine screening tests for ascorbic acid.



    5.5 Use in Patients with a History of Adverse Reactions to Thiol Compounds



  MESNEX is a thiol compound, i.e., a sulfhydryl (SH) group-containing organic compound. Hypersensitivity reactions to MESNEX and to amifostine, another thiol compound, have been reported. It is not clear whether patients who experienced an adverse reaction to a thiol compound are at increased risk for a hypersensitivity reaction to MESNEX.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
