<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="metadate" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The premarketing development program for METADATE CD included exposures in a total of 228 participants in clinical trials (188 pediatric patients with ADHD, 40 healthy adult subjects). These participants received METADATE CD 20, 40, and/or 60 mg/day. The 188 patients (ages 6 to 15) were evaluated in one controlled clinical study, one controlled, crossover clinical study, and one uncontrolled clinical study. Safety data on all patients are included in the discussion that follows. Adverse reactions were assessed by collecting adverse events, results of physical examinations, vital signs, weights, laboratory analyses, and ECGs.



 Adverse events during exposure were obtained primarily by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of events into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and listings that follow, COSTART terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events.



 The stated frequencies of adverse events represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



   Adverse Findings In Clinical Trials With METADATE CD

  Adverse Events Associated With Discontinuation Of Treatment

  In the 3-week placebo-controlled, parallel-group trial, two METADATE CD-treated patients (1%) and no placebo-treated patients discontinued due to an adverse event (rash and pruritus; and headache, abdominal pain, and dizziness, respectively).



   Adverse Events Occurring At An Incidence Of 5% Or More Among METADATE CD-Treated Patients

    *     Table 1 enumerates, for a pool of the three studies in pediatric patients with ADHD, at METADATE CD doses of 20, 40, or 60 mg/day, the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events. One study was a 3-week placebo-controlled, parallel-group trial, one study was a controlled, crossover trial, and the third study was an open titration trial. The table includes only those events that occurred in 5% or more of patients treated with METADATE CD where the incidence in patients treated with METADATE CD was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients. 
    The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidence rate in the population studied.
 

 TABLE 1 Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Events1 in a Pool of 3-4 Week Clinical Trials of METADATE CD 
     Body System               Preferred Term                          METADATE CD      (n=188)        Placebo      (n=190)       
  
   1  : Events, regardless of causality, for which the incidence for patients treated with METADATE CD was at least 5% and greater than the incidence among placebo-treated patients. Incidence has been rounded to the nearest whole number.   
  
  General                   Headache                                                           12%                      
                                                      8%            
                            Abdominal pain (stomach ache)             7%                        4%            
  Digestive System          Anorexia (loss of appetite)               9%                        2%            
  Nervous System                                                     Insomnia                                 
                                                                                      5%                        2%            
            Adverse Events With Other Marketed Methylphenidate HCl Products
   Nervousness and insomnia are the most common adverse reactions reported with other methylphenidate products. Other reactions include hypersensitivity (including skin rash, urticaria, fever, arthralgia, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme with histopathological findings of necrotizing vasculitis, and thrombocytopenic purpura); anorexia; nausea; dizziness; palpitations; headache; dyskinesia; drowsiness; blood pressure and pulse changes, both up and down; tachycardia; angina; cardiac arrhythmia; abdominal pain; weight loss during prolonged therapy. There have been rare reports of Tourette's Syndrome and obsessive-compulsive disorder. Toxic psychosis has been reported. Although a definite causal relationship has not been established, the following have been reported in patients taking this drug: instances of abnormal liver function, ranging from transaminase elevation to hepatic coma; isolated cases of cerebral arteritis and/or occlusion; leucopenia and/or anemia; transient depressed mood; a few instances of scalp hair loss. Very rare reports of neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS) have been reported, and, in most of these, patients were concurrently receiving therapies associated with NMS. In a single report, a ten year old boy who had been taking methylphenidate for approximately 18 months experienced an NMS-like event within 45 minutes of ingesting his first dose of venlafaxine. It is uncertain whether this case represented a drug-drug interaction, a response to either drug alone, or some other cause.



 In children, loss of appetite, abdominal pain, weight loss during prolonged therapy, insomnia and tachycardia may occur more frequently; however, any of the other adverse reactions listed above may also occur.



   Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to the adverse events listed above, the following have been reported in patients receiving METADATE CD worldwide. The list is alphabetized: abnormal behavior, aggression, anxiety, bruxism, cardiac arrest, depression, fixed drug eruption, hyperactivity, irritability, libido changes, migraine, obsessive-compulsive disorder, peripheral coldness, Raynaud's phenomenon, reversible ischaemic neurological deficit, rhabdomyolysis, sudden death, suicidal behavior (including completed suicide), and thrombocytopenia. Data are insufficient to support an estimation of incidence or establish causation.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: MEDICATION GUIDE

  MEDICATION GUIDE

    *   METADATE CD(r) (methylphenidate HCl, USP) Extended-Release Capsules CII 
    Read the Medication Guide that comes with METADATE CD before you or your child starts taking it and each time you get a refill.  There may be new information.  This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your doctor about your or your child's treatment with METADATE CD.
 


  What is the most important information I should know about Metadate CD?The following have been reported with use of methylphenidate HCl, USP and other stimulant medicines.1.Heart-related problems :1.sudden death in patients who have heart problems or heart defects2.stroke and heart attack in adults3.increased blood pressure and heart rateTell your doctor if you or your child have any heart problems, heart defects, high blood pressure, or a family history of these problems.Your doctor should check you or your child carefully for heart problems before starting METADATE CD.Your doctor should check your or your child's blood pressure and heart rate regularly during treatment with METADATE CD. Call your doctor right away if you or your child has any signs of heart problems such as chest pain, shortness of breath, or fainting while taking METADATE CD.2.Mental (Psychiatric) problems :All Patients1.new or worse behavior and thought problems2.new or worse bipolar illness3.new or worse aggressive behavior or hostilityChildren and Teenagers1.new psychotic symptoms (such as hearing voices, believing things that are not true, are suspicious) or new manic symptomsTell your doctor about any mental problems you or your child have, or about a family history of suicide, bipolar illness, or depression.Call your doctor right away if you or your child have any new or worsening mental symptoms or problems while taking METADATE CD, especially seeing or hearing things that are not real, believing things that are not real, or are suspicious.   
  3. Circulation Problems in fingers and toes (Peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon): fingers or toes may feel numb, cool, painful, and/or may change color from pale, to blue, to red1.Tell your doctor if you have or your child has numbness, pain, skin color change, or sensitivity to temperature in your fingers or toes.2.Call your doctor right away if you have or your child has any signs of unexplained wounds appearing on fingers or toes while taking METADATE CD.   
         What Is METADATE CD?  
 

 METADATE CD is a central nervous system stimulant prescription medicine.   It is used for the treatment of Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD).   



 METADATE CD may help increase attention and decrease impulsiveness and hyperactivity in patients with ADHD.



 METADATE CD should be used as a part of a total treatment program for ADHD that may include counseling or other therapies.



   

    METADATE CD is a federally controlled substance (CII) because it can be abused or lead to dependence.  Keep METADATE CD in a safe place to prevent misuse and abuse.  Selling or giving away METADATE CD may harm others, and is against the law.  Tell your doctor if you or your child have (or have a family history of) ever abused or been dependent on alcohol, prescription medicines or street drugs.



     Who should not take METADATE CD?  



   METADATE CD should not be taken if you or your child:  



 *  1.are very anxious, tense, or agitated 
 *  2.have an eye problem called glaucoma 
 *  3.have tics or Tourette's syndrome, or a family history of Tourette's syndrome. Tics are hard to control repeated movements or sounds. 
 *  4.have severe high blood pressure or a heart problem 
 *  5.have hyperthyroidism 
 *  6.are taking or have taken within the past 14 days an antidepression medicine called a monoamine oxidase inhibitor or MAOI. 
 *  7.are allergic to anything in METADATE CD. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients. 
    METADATE CD should not be used in children less than 6 years old because it has not been studied in this age group.
 

   METADATE CD may not be right for you or your child.  Before starting METADATE CD tell your or your child's doctor about all health conditions (or a family history of) including:  



 *  1.heart problems, heart defects, high blood pressure 
 *  2.mental problems including psychosis, mania, bipolar illness, or depression 
 *  3.tics or Tourette's syndrome 
 *  4.seizures or have had an abnormal brain wave test (EEG) 
 *  5.circulation problem in fingers and toes 
    Tell your doctor if you or your child is pregnant, planning to become pregnant, or breastfeeding.
 

   Can METADATE CD be taken with other medicines?  



   Tell your doctor about all of the medicines that you or your child take including prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements.   METADATE CD and some medicines may interact with each other and cause serious side effects.  Sometimes the doses of other medicines will need to be adjusted while taking METADATE CD.



 Your doctor will decide whether METADATE CD can be taken with other medicines.



   Especially tell your doctor if you or your child takes:  



 *  1.anti-depression medicines including MAOIs 
 *  2.seizure medicines 
 *  3.blood thinner medicines 
 *  4.blood pressure medicines 
 *  5.cold or allergy medicines that contain decongestants 
    Know the medicines that you or your child takes.  Keep a list of your medicines with you to show your doctor and pharmacist.
 

   Do not start any new medicine while taking METADATE CD without talking to your doctor first.  



   How should METADATE CD be taken?  



 *  1.Take METADATE CD exactly as prescribed. Your doctor may adjust the dose until it is right for you or your child. 
 *  2.Take METADATE CD once each day in the morning before breakfast. METADATE CD is an extended release capsule. It releases medicine into your body throughout the day. 
 *  3.METADATE CD can be taken with or without food. 
 *  4.Swallow METADATE CD capsules whole with water or other liquids. If you cannot swallow the capsule, open it and sprinkle the medicine over a spoonful of applesauce. Swallow the applesauce and medicine mixture without chewing. Follow with a drink of water or other liquid. Never chew or crush the capsule or the medicine inside the capsule. 
 *  5.METADATE CD should not be taken with alcohol. This may result in a more rapid release of the dose of METADATE CD. 
 *  6.From time to time, your doctor may stop METADATE CD treatment for a while to check ADHD symptoms. 
 *  7.Your doctor may do regular checks of the blood, heart, and blood pressure while taking METADATE CD. Children should have their height and weight checked often while taking METADATE CD. METADATE CD treatment may be stopped if a problem is found during these check-ups. 
 *  8.If you or your child takes too much METADATE CD or overdoses, call your doctor or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What are possible side effects of METADATE CD?  
 

 See   "What is the most important information I should know about METADATE CD?"   for information on reported heart and mental problems.



   Other serious side effects include:  



 *  1.slowing of growth (height and weight) in children 
 *  2.seizures, mainly in patients with a history of seizures 
 *  3.eyesight changes or blurred vision 
 *  4.Painful and prolonged erections (priapism) have occurred with methylphenidate. If you or your child develop priapism, seek medical help right away. Because of the potential for lasting damage, priapism should be evaluated by a doctor immediately. 
      Common side effects include:  
 

 *  1.headache 
 *  2.decreased appetite 
 *  3.stomach ache 
 *  4.nervousness 
 *  5.trouble sleeping 
 *  6.dizziness 
    Talk to your doctor if you or your child has side effects that are bothersome or do not go away.
 

 This is not a complete list of possible side effects.  Ask your doctor or pharmacist for more information



   Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects.  You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.  



   How should I store METADATE CD?  



 *  1.Store METADATE CD in a safe place at room temperature, 59 to 86 degrees F (15 to 30 degrees C). Protect from moisture. 
 *  2.Keep METADATE CD and all medicines out of the reach of children. 
      General information about METADATE CD  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide.  Do not use METADATE CD for a condition for which it was not prescribed.  Do not give METADATE CD to other people, even if they have the same condition.  It may harm them and it is against the law.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about METADATE CD.  If you would like more information, talk with your doctor.  You can ask your doctor or pharmacist for information about METADATE CD that was written for healthcare professionals.  For more information about METADATE CD call  1-866-822-0068.



   What are the ingredients in METADATE CD?  



   Active Ingredient:   methylphenidate HCl   Inactive Ingredients:   sugar spheres, povidone, hydroxypropylmethylcellulose and polyethylene glycol, ethylcellulose aqueous dispersion, dibutyl sebacate, gelatin, and titanium dioxide.



 The individual capsules contain the following coloring agents:10 mg capsules:  FD&amp;C Blue No. 2, FDA/E172 Yellow Iron Oxide20 mg capsules:  FD&amp;C Blue No. 230 mg capsules:  FD&amp;C Blue No. 2, FDA/E172 Red Iron Oxide40 mg capsules:  FDA/E172 Yellow Iron Oxide50 mg capsules:  FD&amp;C Blue No. 2, FDA/E172 Red Iron Oxide



   This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.  



 Marketed by UCB, Inc.Smyrna, GA 30080



 Repackaged by:RxPak Division of McKesson CorpMemphis, TN 38141



 Made in USA



 METADATE CD is a registered trademark of the UCB Group of companies(c)2014, UCB, Inc., Smyrna, GA 30080All rights reserved.



 Rev. 06/2014
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
