<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="metformin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets Clinical Studies  

  In the controlled clinical studies of Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets in patients with type 2 diabetes, a total of 424 patients received Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets therapy (up to 2500 mg/day) and 430 patients received immediate-release metformin. Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=5% of the Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets or immediate-release metformin patients are listed in  Table 6.  These pooled results show that the most frequently reported adverse reactions in the Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets group were infection, diarrhea, and nausea. Similar incidences of these adverse reactions were seen in the immediate-release metformin group.



 Table 6 Number and Percentage of Patients With the Most Common (Incidence &gt;=5%) Treatment-Emergent Signs or Symptoms by Body System and Preferred Term - Pooled Phase II and III Studies 
                    Metformin Hydrochloride    Extended-Release    (n = 424)      Immediate-Release    Metformin    (n = 430)     
   Body System Preferred Term      n                (%)              n                (%)             
   Body as a Whole                                                                         
  Accidental Injury   31               (7.3)            24               (5.6)            
  Headache         20               (4.7)            22               (5.1)            
  Infection        87               (20.5)           90               (20.9)           
   Digestive System                                                                         
  Diarrhea         71               (16.7)           51               (11.9)           
  Dyspepsia        18               (4.2)            22               (5.1)            
  Nausea           36               (8.5)            32               (7.4)            
   Respiratory System                                                                         
  Rhinitis         18               (4.2)            24               (5.6)            
           The most frequent adverse events thought to be related to Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets were diarrhea, nausea, dyspepsia, flatulence, and abdominal pain. The frequency of dyspepsia was 4.2% in the Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets group compared to 5.1%in the immediate-release group, the frequency of flatulence was 3.5% in the Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets group compared to 3.7% in the immediate-release group, and the frequency of abdominal pain was 3.3% in the Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets group compared to 4.4% in the immediate-release group.
 

 In the controlled studies, 4.7% of patients treated with Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets and 4.9% of patients treated with immediate-release metformin were discontinued due to adverse events.



     Immediate-Release Metformin  

  Immediate-Release Metformin Phase III Clinical Studies



 In a U.S. double-blind clinical study of immediate-release metformin in patients with type 2 diabetes, a total of 141 patients received immediate-releasemetformin therapy (up to 2550 mg per day) and 145 patients received placebo. Adverse reactions reported in greater than 5% of the immediate-release metformin patients, and that were more common in immediate-release metformin than placebo-treated patients, are listed in  Table 7.  



 Table 7 Most Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;5.0%) in a Placebo-Controlled Clinical Study of Immediate-Release Metformin Monotherapy* 
                    Immediate-Release    Metformin Monotherapy    (n = 141)      Placebo    (n = 145)     
   Adverse    Reaction                    % of    Patients     
  Diarrhea        53.2             11.7              
  Nausea/Vomiting   25.5             8.3              
  Flatulence       12.1             5.5              
  Asthenia         9.2              5.5              
  Indigestion      7.1              4.1              
  Abdominal Discomfort   6.4              4.8              
  Headache         5.7              4.8              
         * Reactions that were more common in immediate-release metformin than placebo-treated patients
 

 Diarrhea led to discontinuation of study medication in 6% of patients treated with immediate-release metformin. Additionally, the following adverse reactions were reported in &gt;=1.0 - &lt;=5.0% of immediate-release metformin patients and were more commonly reported with immediate-release metformin than placebo: abnormal stools, hypoglycemia, myalgia, lightheaded, dyspnea, nail disorder, rash, sweating increased, taste disorder, chest discomfort, chills, flu syndrome, flushing, palpitation.



     Pediatric Patients  

  No pediatric clinical studies have been conducted with Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets. In clinical trials with immediate-release metformin in pediatric patients with type 2 diabetes, the profile of adverse reactions was similar to that observed in adults.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS:

    LACTIC ACIDOSIS:  

    Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to     metformin accumulation during treatment with Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-    Release Tablets; when it occurs, it is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic     acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic     conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue     hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate levels (&gt;5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an     increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio.When metformin is     implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels &gt;5 ug/mL are     generally found.  



   The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin hydrochlo    ride is very low (approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years). Reported cases have occurred primarily in     diabetic patients with significant renal insufficiency, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant     medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with     congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, in particular     those with unstable or acute congestive heart failure who are at risk of hypoperfusion and hypoxemia, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis     increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of     lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets     and by use of the minimum effective dose of Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-    Release Tablets. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by     careful monitoring of renal function. Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release     Tablets treatment should not be initiated in patients &gt;=80 years of age unless meas    urement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced, as     these patients are more susceptible to developing lactic acidosis. In addition,     Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis.     Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear     lactate, Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets should generally be     avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease. Patients     should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake, either acute or chronic, when     taking Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets. since alcohol     potentiates the effects of metformin hydrochloride on lactate metabolism. In     addition, Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets should be temporarily     discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical     procedure (see also     PRECAUTIONS    ).  



   The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied only by nonspecific     symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence,     and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia,     hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis. The     patient and the patient's physician must be aware of the possible importance of such     symptoms and the patient should be instructed to notify the physician immediately     if they occur (see also     PRECAUTIONS    ). Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release     Tablets should be withdrawn until the situation is clarified. Serum electrolytes,     ketones, blood glucose and, if indicated, blood pH, lactate levels, and even blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of     Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets, gastrointestinal symptoms,     which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to be drug related. Later     occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease.  



   Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less     than 5 mmol/L in patients taking Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-Release     Tablets do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explain    able by other mechanisms, such as poorly controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous     physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling (see also     PRECAUTIONS    ).  



   Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis     lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia).  



   Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking Metformin Hydrochloride Extended-    Release Tablets, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general     supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin hydrochloride is     dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic     conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and     remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt     reversal of symptoms and recovery (see also     CONTRAINDICATIONS     and     PRECAUTIONS    ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
