<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="methadone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Initial Administration

  The initial methadone dose should be carefully titrated to the individual. Induction too rapid for the patient's sensitivity is more likely to produce adverse effects.



   The major hazards of methadone are respiratory depression and, to a lesser degree, systemic hypotension. Respiratory arrest, shock, cardiac arrest, and death have occurred.  



 The most frequently observed adverse reactions include lightheadedness, dizziness, sedation, nausea, vomiting, and sweating. These effects seem to be more prominent in ambulatory patients and in those who are not suffering severe pain. In such individuals, lower doses of methadone are advisable.



 Other adverse reactions that have been reported in patients (including opioid addicts taking methadone for detoxification or maintenance) receiving methadone include the following:



   Body as a Whole:  asthenia (weakness), edema, headache



   Cardiovascular:  Arrhythmias, bigeminal rhythms, bradycardia, extrasystoles, tachycardia, Torsade de Pointes, ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia. ECG abnormalities, prolonged QT interval, T-wave inversion, cardiomyopathy, flushing, heart failure, hypotension, palpitations, phlebitis, syncope.



   Digestive:  Abdominal pain, anorexia, biliary tract spasm, constipation, dry mouth, glossitis



   Hematologic and Lymphatic:  Reversible thrombocytopenia has been described in opioid addicts with chronic hepatitis.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, weight gain



   Nervous:  Agitation, confusion, seizures, disorientation, dysphoria, euphoria, insomnia



   Respiratory:  Pulmonary edema



   Skin and appendages:  



 *     Intramuscular and Subcutaneous: Local tissue reactions (pain, erythema, swelling), particularly with continuous subcutaneous infusion 
 *     Intravenous: Pruritis, urticaria, other skin rashes, and rarely, hemorrhagic urticaria 
      Special senses:  Visual disturbances
 

   Urogenital:  Antidiuretic effect, amenorrhea, urinary retention or hesitancy, reduced libido and/or potency



   Maintenance on a Stabilized Dose

  During prolonged administration of methadone, there is usually a gradual, yet progressive, disappearance of side effects over a period of several weeks. However, constipation and sweating often persist.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    CONDITIONS FOR DISTRIBUTION AND USE OF METHADONE PRODUCTS     FOR THE TREATMENT OF OPIOID ADDICTION  



 Code of Federal Regulations, Title 42, Sec 8



 METHADONE PRODUCTS WHEN USED FOR THE TREATMENT OF OPIOID ADDICTION IN DETOXIFICATION OR MAINTENANCE PROGRAMS, SHALL BE DISPENSED ONLY BY OPIOID TREATMENT PROGRAMS (AND AGENCIES, PRACTITIONERS OR INSTITUTIONS BY FORMAL AGREEMENT WITH THE PROGRAM SPONSOR) CERTIFIED BY THE SUBSTANCE ABUSE AND MENTAL HEALTH SERVICES ADMINISTRATION AND APPROVED BY THE DESIGNATED STATE AUTHORITY. CERTIFIED TREATMENT PROGRAMS SHALL DISPENSE AND USE METHADONE IN ORAL FORM ONLY AND ACCORDING TO THE TREATMENT REQUIREMENTS STIPULATED IN THE FEDERAL OPIOID TREATMENT STANDARDS (42 CFR 8.12).   See below for important regulatory exceptions to the general requirement for certification to provide opioid agonist treatment.  



 FAILURE TO ABIDE BY THE REQUIREMENTS IN THESE REGULATIONS MAY RESULT IN CRIMINAL PROSECUTION, SEIZURE OF THE DRUG SUPPLY, REVOCATION OF THE PROGRAM APPROVAL, AND INJUNCTION PRECLUDING OPERATION OF THE PROGRAM.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
