<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="methylphenidate" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Drug Dependence [see  Box Warning  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity to Methylphenidate [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  
 *  Agitation [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ]  
 *  Glaucoma [see  Contraindications (4.3)  ]  
 *  Tics [see  Contraindications (4.4)  ]  
 *  Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors [see  Contraindications (4.5)  and  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  
 *  Serious Cardiovascular Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Priapism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Long-Term Suppression of Growth [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Visual Disturbance [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Potential for Gastrointestinal Obstruction [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Hematologic Monitoring [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
    The most common adverse reaction in double-blind clinical trials (&gt;5%) in pediatric patients (children and adolescents) was abdominal pain upper. The most common adverse reactions in double-blind clinical trials (&gt;5%) in adult patients were decreased appetite, headache, dry mouth, nausea, insomnia, anxiety, dizziness, weight decreased, irritability, and hyperhidrosis  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  
 

 The most common adverse reactions associated with discontinuation (&gt;=1%) from either pediatric or adult clinical trials were anxiety, irritability, insomnia, and blood pressure increased  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ].  



 The development program for Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets included exposures in a total of 3906 participants in clinical trials. Children, adolescents, and adults with ADHD were evaluated in 6 controlled clinical studies and 11 open-label clinical studies (see  Table 3  ). Safety was assessed by collecting adverse events, vital signs, weights, and ECGs, and by performing physical examinations and laboratory analyses.



 Table 3. Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets Exposure in Double-Blind and Open-Label Clinical Studies 
 Patient Population                        N                     Dose Range                                 
  
 Children                                  2216                  18 to 54 mg once daily                     
 Adolescents                               502                   18 to 72 mg once daily                     
 Adults                                    1188                  18 to 108 mg once daily                    
         Adverse events during exposure were obtained primarily by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using their own terminology. Consequently, to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events, events were grouped in standardized categories using MedDRA terminology.
 

 The stated frequencies of adverse events represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type listed. An event was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



 Throughout this section, adverse reactions are reported. Adverse reactions are adverse events that were considered to be reasonably associated with the use of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets based on the comprehensive assessment of the available adverse event information. A causal association for Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets often cannot be reliably established in individual cases. Further, because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The majority of adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reaction in double-blind clinical trials (&gt;5%) in children and adolescents was abdominal pain upper. The most common adverse reactions in double-blind clinical trials (&gt;5%) in adult patients were decreased appetite, headache, dry mouth, nausea, insomnia, anxiety, dizziness, weight decreased, irritability, and hyperhidrosis. (  6.1  and  6.2  )



 The most common adverse reactions associated with discontinuation (&gt;=1%) from either pediatric or adult clinical trials were anxiety, irritability, insomnia, and blood pressure increased. (  6.3  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Actavis at 1-800-272-5525 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials

  Adverse reactions in either the pediatric or adult double-blind adverse reactions tables may be relevant for both patient populations.



   Children and Adolescents



 Table 4 lists the adverse reactions reported in 1% or more of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets-treated children and adolescent subjects in 4 placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trials.



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=1% of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets-Treated Children and Adolescent Subjects in 4 Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Clinical Trials of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets 
 System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction                          Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets(n=321)%    Placebo(n=318)%      
  
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
   Abdominal pain upper                                                6.2                   3.8            
   Vomiting                                                            2.8                   1.6            
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                     
   Pyrexia                                                             2.2                   0.9            
   Infections and Infestations                                                                              
   Nasopharyngitis                                                     2.8                   2.2            
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
   Dizziness                                                           1.9                    0             
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                                            2.8                   0.3            
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                          
   Cough                                                               1.9                   0.9            
   Oropharyngeal pain                                                  1.2                   0.9            
         The majority of adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity.
 

   Adults



 Table 5 lists the adverse reactions reported in 1% or more of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets-treated adults in 2 placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trials.



 Table 5. Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;=1% of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets-Treated Adult Subjects in 2 Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Clinical Trials Included doses up to 108 mg. 
 System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction                          Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets(n=415)%    Placebo(n=212)%      
  
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                                        
   Tachycardia                                                         4.8                    0             
   Palpitations                                                        3.1                   0.9            
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                                                                              
   Vertigo                                                             1.7                    0             
   Eye Disorders                                                                                            
   Vision blurred                                                      1.7                   0.5            
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
   Dry mouth                                                           14.0                  3.8            
   Nausea                                                              12.8                  3.3            
   Dyspepsia                                                           2.2                   0.9            
   Vomiting                                                            1.7                   0.5            
   Constipation                                                        1.4                   0.9            
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                     
   Irritability                                                        5.8                   1.4            
   Infections and Infestations                                                                              
   Upper respiratory tract infection                                   2.2                   0.9            
   Investigations                                                                                           
   Weight decreased                                                    6.5                   3.3            
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                       
   Decreased appetite                                                  25.3                  6.6            
   Anorexia                                                            1.7                    0             
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                          
   Muscle tightness                                                    1.9                    0             
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
   Headache                                                            22.2                  15.6           
   Dizziness                                                           6.7                   5.2            
   Tremor                                                              2.7                   0.5            
   Paresthesia                                                         1.2                    0             
   Sedation                                                            1.2                    0             
   Tension headache                                                    1.2                   0.5            
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Insomnia                                                            12.3                  6.1            
   Anxiety                                                             8.2                   2.4            
   Initial insomnia                                                    4.3                   2.8            
   Depressed mood                                                      3.9                   1.4            
   Nervousness                                                         3.1                   0.5            
   Restlessness                                                        3.1                    0             
   Agitation                                                           2.2                   0.5            
   Aggression                                                          1.7                   0.5            
   Bruxism                                                             1.7                   0.5            
   Depression                                                          1.7                   0.9            
   Libido decreased                                                    1.7                   0.5            
   Affect lability                                                     1.4                   0.9            
   Confusional state                                                   1.2                   0.5            
   Tension                                                             1.2                   0.5            
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                          
   Oropharyngeal pain                                                  1.7                   1.4            
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                   
   Hyperhidrosis                                                       5.1                   0.9            
         The majority of ADRs were mild to moderate in severity.
 

   6.2 Other Adverse Reactions Observed in Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets Clinical Trials

  This section includes adverse reactions reported by Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets -treated subjects in double-blind trials that do not meet the criteria specified for Table 4 or Table 5 and all adverse reactions reported by Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets-treated subjects who participated in open-label and postmarketing clinical trials.



 Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders: Leukopenia



 Eye Disorders: Accommodation disorder, Dry eye



 Vascular Disorders: Hot flush



 Gastrointestinal Disorders: Abdominal discomfort, Abdominal pain, Diarrhea



 General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions: Asthenia, Fatigue, Feeling jittery, Thirst



 Infections and Infestations: Sinusitis



 Investigations: Alanine aminotransferase increased, Blood pressure increased, Cardiac murmur, Heart rate increased



 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders: Muscle spasms



 Nervous System Disorders: Lethargy, Psychomotor hyperactivity, Somnolence



 Psychiatric Disorders: Anger, Hypervigilance, Mood altered, Mood swings, Panic attack, Sleep disorder, Tearfulness, Tic



 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders: Erectile dysfunction



 Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders: Dyspnea



 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders: Rash, Rash macular



 Vascular Disorders: Hypertension



   6.3 Discontinuation Due to Adverse Reactions

  Adverse reactions in the 4 placebo-controlled studies of children and adolescents leading to discontinuation occurred in 2 Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets patients (0.6%) including depressed mood (1, 0.3%) and headache and insomnia (1, 0.3%), and 6 placebo patients (1.9%) including headache and insomnia (1, 0.3%), irritability (2, 0.6%), headache (1, 0.3%), psychomotor hyperactivity (1, 0.3%), and tic (1, 0.3%).



 In the 2 placebo-controlled studies of adults, 25 Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets patients (6.0%) and 6 placebo patients (2.8%) discontinued due to an adverse reaction. Those events with an incidence of &gt;0.5% in the Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets patients included anxiety (1.7%), irritability (1.4%), blood pressure increased (1.0%), and nervousness (0.7%). In placebo patients, blood pressure increased and depressed mood had an incidence of &gt;0.5% (0.9%).



 In the 11 open-label studies of children, adolescents, and adults, 266 Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets patients (7.0%) discontinued due to an adverse reaction. Those events with an incidence of &gt;0.5% included insomnia (1.2%), irritability (0.8%), anxiety (0.7%), decreased appetite (0.7%), and tic (0.6%).



   6.4 Tics

  In a long-term uncontrolled study (n=432 children), the cumulative incidence of new onset of tics was 9% after 27 months of treatment with Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets.



 In a second uncontrolled study (n=682 children) the cumulative incidence of new-onset tics was 1% (9/682 children). The treatment period was up to 9 months with mean treatment duration of 7.2 months.



   6.5 Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases

  In the laboratory classroom clinical trials in children (Studies 1 and 2), both Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets once daily and methylphenidate three times daily increased resting pulse by an average of 2 to 6 bpm and produced average increases of systolic and diastolic blood pressure of roughly 1 to 4 mm Hg during the day, relative to placebo. In the placebo-controlled adolescent trial (Study 4), mean increases from baseline in resting pulse rate were observed with Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets and placebo at the end of the double-blind phase (5 and 3 beats/minute, respectively). Mean increases from baseline in blood pressure at the end of the double-blind phase for Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets and placebo-treated patients were 0.7 and 0.7 mm Hg (systolic) and 2.6 and 1.4 mm Hg (diastolic), respectively. In one placebo-controlled study in adults (Study 6), dose-dependent mean increases of 3.9 to 9.8 bpm from baseline in standing pulse rate were observed with Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets at the end of the double-blind treatment vs. an increase of 2.7 beats/minute with placebo. Mean changes from baseline in standing blood pressure at the end of double-blind treatment ranged from 0.1 to 2.2 mm Hg (systolic) and -0.7 to 2.2 mm Hg (diastolic) for Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets and was 1.1 mm Hg (systolic) and -1.8 mm Hg (diastolic) for placebo. In a second placebo-controlled study in adults (Study 5), mean changes from baseline in resting pulse rate were observed for Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets and placebo at the end of the double-blind treatment (3.6 and -1.6 beats/minute, respectively). Mean changes from baseline in blood pressure at the end of the double-blind treatment for Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets and placebo-treated patients were -1.2 and -0.5 mm Hg (systolic) and 1.1 and 0.4 mm Hg (diastolic), respectively  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



   6.6 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency:



 Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders: Pancytopenia, Thrombocytopenia, Thrombocytopenic purpura



 Cardiac Disorders: Angina pectoris, Bradycardia, Extrasystoles, Supraventricular tachycardia, Ventricular extrasystoles



 Eye Disorders: Diplopia, Mydriasis, Visual impairment



 General Disorders: Chest pain, Chest discomfort, Drug effect decreased, Hyperpyrexia, Therapeutic response decreased



 Immune System Disorders: Hypersensitivity reactions such as Angioedema, Anaphylactic reactions, Auricular swelling, Bullous conditions, Exfoliative conditions, Urticarias, Pruritus NEC, Rashes, Eruptions, and Exanthemas NEC



 Investigations: Blood alkaline phosphatase increased, Blood bilirubin increased, Hepatic enzyme increased, Platelet count decreased, White blood cell count abnormal



 Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders: Arthralgia, Myalgia, Muscle twitching, Rhabdomyolysis



 Nervous System Disorders: Convulsion, Grand mal convulsion, Dyskinesia



 Psychiatric Disorders: Disorientation, Hallucination, Hallucination auditory, Hallucination visual, Mania, Logorrhea, Libido changes



 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders: Priapism



 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders: Alopecia, Erythema



 Vascular Disorders: Raynaud's phenomenon
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: DRUG DEPENDENCE

    WARNING: DRUG DEPENDENCE  

    Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets should be given cautiously to patients with a history of drug dependence or alcoholism. Chronic abusive use can lead to marked tolerance and psychological dependence with varying degrees of abnormal behavior. Frank psychotic episodes can occur, especially with parenteral abuse. Careful supervision is required during withdrawal from abusive use since severe depression may occur. Withdrawal following chronic therapeutic use may unmask symptoms of the underlying disorder that may require follow-up.  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: DRUG DEPENDENCE



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets should be given cautiously to patients with a history of drug dependence or alcoholism. Chronic abusive use can lead to marked tolerance and psychological dependence, with varying degrees of abnormal behavior.  



 









    BOXED WARNING: 

    MEDICATION GUIDE  



   Methylphenidate (meth-ill-fen-i-date) HCl Extended-Release Tablets CII  



 Read the Medication Guide that comes with Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets before you or your child starts taking it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your doctor about your or your child's treatment with Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets.



     What is the most important information I should know about Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets?  



   The following have been reported with use of methylphenidate HCl and other stimulant medicines:  



   1.   Heart-related problems:    



 *  sudden death in patients who have heart problems or heart defects 
 *  stroke and heart attack in adults 
 *  increased blood pressure and heart rate 
    Tell your doctor if you or your child has any heart problems, heart defects, high blood pressure, or a family history of these problems.
 

 Your doctor should check you or your child carefully for heart problems before starting Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets.



 Your doctor should check your or your child's blood pressure and heart rate regularly during treatment with Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets.



   Call your doctor right away if you or your child has any signs of heart problems such as chest pain, shortness of breath, or fainting while taking Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets.  



   2.   Mental (Psychiatric) problems:    



   All Patients  



 *  new or worse behavior and thought problems 
 *  new or worse bipolar illness 
 *  new or worse aggressive behavior or hostility 
      Children and Teenagers  
 

 *  new psychotic symptoms (such as hearing voices, believing things that are not true, are suspicious) or new manic symptoms 
    Tell your doctor about any mental problems you or your child have, or about a family history of suicide, bipolar illness, or depression.
 

   Call your doctor right away if you or your child has any new or worsening mental symptoms or problems while taking Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets, especially seeing or hearing things that are not real, believing things that are not real, or are suspicious.  



   3. Painful and prolonged erections (priapism)  



 Painful and prolonged erections (priapism) have occurred with methylphenidate. If you or your child develop priapism, seek medical help right away.   Because of the potential for lasting damage, priapism should be evaluated by a doctor immediately.  



   4. Circulation problems in fingers and toes    [Peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon]:



 *  fingers or toes may feel numb, cool, painful 
 *  fingers or toes may change color from pale, to blue, to red 
    Tell your doctor if you have or your child has numbness, pain, skin color change, or sensitivity to temperature in your fingers or toes.
 

   Call your doctor right away if you have or your child has any signs of unexplained wounds appearing on fingers or toes while taking Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets.  



     What are Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets?  



 Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets are a central nervous system stimulant prescription medicine. They are   used for the treatment of attention deficit and hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).   Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets may help increase attention and decrease impulsiveness and hyperactivity in patients with ADHD.



 Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets should be used as a part of a total treatment program for ADHD that may include counseling or other therapies. 



     Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets are a federally controlled substance (CII) because they can be abused or lead to dependence. Keep Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets in a safe place to prevent misuse and abuse. Selling or giving away Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets may harm others, and is against the law.  



 Tell your doctor if you or your child has (or has a family history of) ever abused or been dependent on alcohol, prescription medicines, or street drugs. 



     Who should not take Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets?   



   Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets should not be taken if you or your child:  



 *  is very anxious, tense, or agitated 
 *  has an eye problem called glaucoma 
 *  has tics or Tourette's syndrome, or a family history of Tourette's syndrome. Tics are hard-to-control repeated movements or sounds. 
 *  is taking or has taken within the past 14 days an antidepression medicine called a monoamine oxidase inhibitor or MAOI. 
 *  is allergic to anything in Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients. 
    Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets should not be used in children less than 6 years old because they have not been studied in this age group.   Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets may not be right for you or your child. Before starting Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets, tell your or your child's doctor about all health conditions (or a family history of) including:  
 

 *  heart problems, heart defects, or high blood pressure 
 *  mental problems including psychosis, mania, bipolar illness, or depression 
 *  tics or Tourette's syndrome 
 *  seizures or have had an abnormal brain wave test (EEG) 
 *  circulation problems in fingers and toes 
 *  esophagus, stomach, or small or large intestine problems 
    Tell your doctor if you or your child is pregnant, planning to become pregnant, or breastfeeding.
 

   Can Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets be taken with other medicines?  



   Tell your doctor about all of the medicines that you or your child takes including prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements.   Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets and some medicines may interact with each other and cause serious side effects. Sometimes the doses of other medicines will need to be adjusted while taking Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets.



 Your doctor will decide whether Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets can be taken with other medicines.



   Especially tell your doctor if you or your child takes:  



 *  antidepression medicines including MAOIs 
 *  seizure medicines 
 *  blood thinner medicines 
 *  blood pressure medicines 
 *  cold or allergy medicines that contain decongestants 
    Know the medicines that you or your child takes. Keep a list of your medicines with you to show your doctor and pharmacist.
 

   Do not start any new medicine while taking Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets without talking to your doctor first.  



   How should Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets be taken?  



 *  Take Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets exactly as prescribed. Your doctor may adjust the dose until it is right for you or your child. 
 *  Do not chew, crush, or divide the tablets. Swallow Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets whole with water or other liquids. Tell your doctor if you or your child cannot swallow Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets whole. A different medicine may need to be prescribed. 
 *  Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets can be taken with or without food. 
 *  Take Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets once each day in the morning. Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets are extended-release tablets. They release medication into your or your child's body throughout the day. 
 *  The Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets do not dissolve completely in the body after all the medicine has been released. You or your child may sometimes notice the empty tablet in a bowel movement. This is normal. 
 *  From time to time, your doctor may stop Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets treatment for a while to check ADHD symptoms. 
 *  Your doctor may do regular checks of the blood, heart, and blood pressure while taking Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets. Children should have their height and weight checked often while taking Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets. Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablet treatment may be stopped if a problem is found during these check-ups. 
 *  If you or your child takes too much Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets or overdoses, call your doctor or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What are possible side effects of Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets?  
 

 See   "  What is the most important information I should know about Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets?  "   for information on reported heart and mental problems.



   Other serious side effects include:  



 *  slowing of growth (height and weight) in children 
 *  seizures, mainly in patients with a history of seizures 
 *  eyesight changes or blurred vision 
 *  blockage of the esophagus, stomach, small or large intestine in patients who already have a narrowing in any of these organs 
      Common side effects include:  
 


 decreased appetitedry mouthtrouble sleepingdizzinessstomach acheincreased sweating  headachenauseaanxietyweight lossirritability         
        Stimulants may impair the ability of you or your child to operate potentially hazardous machinery or vehicles. You or your child should exercise caution until you or your child is reasonably certain that Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets do not adversely affect your or your child's ability to engage in such activities.
 

 Talk to your doctor if you or your child has side effects that are bothersome or do not go away.



 This is not a complete list of possible side effects. Ask your doctor or pharmacist for more information.



 Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.



 You may also report side effects to Actavis at 1-800-272-5525.



   How should I store Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets?  



 *  Store Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets in a safe place at room temperature, 59 to 86 degrees  F (15 to 30 degrees  C). Protect from moisture. 
 *  Keep Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets and all medicines out of the reach of children. 
      General information about Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets for a condition for which they were not prescribed. Do not give Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets to other people, even if they have the same condition. It may harm them and it is against the law.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets. If you would like more information, talk with your doctor. You can ask your doctor or pharmacist for information about Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets that was written for healthcare professionals. For more information about Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets call 1-800-272-5525.



   What are the ingredients in Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets?  



   Active Ingredient:   methylphenidate HCl



   Inactive Ingredients:   butylated hydroxytoluene, carnauba wax, cellulose acetate, hypromellose, lactose, phosphoric acid, poloxamer, polyethylene glycol, polyethylene oxides, povidone, propylene glycol, sodium chloride, stearic acid, succinic acid, synthetic iron oxides, titanium dioxide, and triacetin.



   This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.  



 Manufactured by: Janssen-Cilag Manufacturing, LLC Gurabo, Puerto Rico 00778 or Alza Corp. Vacaville, CA 95688



 Distributed by: Actavis Pharma, Inc. Parsippany, NJ 07054 USA



 Revised: May 2015
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious Cardiovascular Events: Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at usual doses in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. Sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults taking stimulant drugs at usual doses for ADHD. Stimulant products generally should not be used in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, coronary artery disease, or other serious heart problems. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Increase in Blood Pressure: Monitor patients for changes in heart rate and blood pressure and use with caution in patients for whom an increase in blood pressure or heart rate would be problematic. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Events: Use of stimulants may cause treatment-emergent psychotic or manic symptoms in patients with no prior history, or exacerbation of symptoms in patients with preexisting psychiatric illness. Clinical evaluation for Bipolar Disorder is recommended prior to stimulant use. Monitor for aggressive behavior. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Seizures: Stimulants may lower the convulsive threshold. Discontinue in the presence of seizures. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Priapism: cases of painful and prolonged penile erections and priapism have been reported with methylphenidate products. Immediate medical attention should be sought if signs or symptoms of painful or prolonged penile erections or priapism are observed. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon: Stimulants used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Visual Disturbance: difficulties with accommodation and blurring of vision have been reported with stimulant treatment. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Long-Term Suppression of Growth: monitor height and weight at appropriate intervals in pediatric patients. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal obstruction with preexisting GI narrowing. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Hematologic monitoring: Periodic CBC, differential, and platelet counts are advised during prolonged therapy. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Cardiovascular Events



  Sudden Death and Preexisting Structural Cardiac Abnormalities or Other Serious Heart Problems



    Children and Adolescents  



 Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulant treatment at usual doses in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. Although some serious heart problems alone carry an increased risk of sudden death, stimulant products generally should not be used in children or adolescents with known serious structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, or other serious cardiac problems that may place them at increased vulnerability to the sympathomimetic effects of a stimulant drug.



    Adults  



 Sudden deaths, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults taking stimulant drugs at usual doses for ADHD. Although the role of stimulants in these adult cases is also unknown, adults have a greater likelihood than children of having serious structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, coronary artery disease, or other serious cardiac problems. Adults with such abnormalities should also generally not be treated with stimulant drugs.



   Hypertension and Other Cardiovascular Conditions



 Stimulant medications cause a modest increase in average blood pressure (about 2 to 4 mm Hg) and average heart rate (about 3 to 6 bpm) [see  Adverse Reactions (6.5)  ]  , and individuals may have larger increases. While the mean changes alone would not be expected to have short-term consequences, all patients should be monitored for larger changes in heart rate and blood pressure. Caution is indicated in treating patients whose underlying medical conditions might be compromised by increases in blood pressure or heart rate, e.g., those with preexisting hypertension, heart failure, recent myocardial infarction, or ventricular arrhythmia.



   Assessing Cardiovascular Status in Patients Being Treated with Stimulant Medications



 Children, adolescents, or adults who are being considered for treatment with stimulant medications should have a careful history (including assessment for a family history of sudden death or ventricular arrhythmia) and physical exam to assess for the presence of cardiac disease, and should receive further cardiac evaluation if findings suggest such disease (e.g., electrocardiogram and echocardiogram). Patients who develop symptoms such as exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or other symptoms suggestive of cardiac disease during stimulant treatment should undergo a prompt cardiac evaluation.



    5.2 Psychiatric Adverse Events



  Preexisting Psychosis



 Administration of stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with a preexisting psychotic disorder.



   Bipolar Illness



 Particular care should be taken in using stimulants to treat ADHD in patients with comorbid bipolar disorder because of concern for possible induction of a mixed/manic episode in such patients. Prior to initiating treatment with a stimulant, patients with comorbid depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression.



   Emergence of New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms



 Treatment-emergent psychotic or manic symptoms, e.g., hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania in patients without a prior history of psychotic illness or mania can be caused by stimulants at usual doses. If such symptoms occur, consideration should be given to a possible causal role of the stimulant, and discontinuation of treatment may be appropriate. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies, such symptoms occurred in about 0.1% (4 patients with events out of 3482 exposed to methylphenidate or amphetamine for several weeks at usual doses) of stimulant-treated patients compared to 0 in placebo-treated patients.



   Aggression



 Aggressive behavior or hostility is often observed in patients with ADHD, and has been reported in clinical trials and the postmarketing experience of some medications indicated for the treatment of ADHD. Although there is no systematic evidence that stimulants cause aggressive behavior or hostility, patients beginning treatment for ADHD should be monitored for the appearance of or worsening of aggressive behavior or hostility.



    5.3 Seizures



  There is some clinical evidence that stimulants may lower the convulsive threshold in patients with prior history of seizures, in patients with prior EEG abnormalities in absence of seizures, and, very rarely, in patients without a history of seizures and no prior EEG evidence of seizures. In the presence of seizures, the drug should be discontinued.



    5.4 Priapism



  Prolonged and painful erections, sometimes requiring surgical intervention, have been reported with methylphenidate products, including Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets, in both pediatric and adult patients [see  Adverse Reactions (6.6)  ]  . Priapism was not reported with drug initiation but developed after some time on the drug, often subsequent to an increase in dose. Priapism has also appeared during a period of drug withdrawal (drug holidays or during discontinuation). Patients who develop abnormally sustained or frequent and painful erections should seek immediate medical attention.



    5.5 Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon



  Stimulants, including Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets, used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Signs and symptoms are usually intermittent and mild; however, very rare sequelae include digital ulceration and/or soft tissue breakdown. Effects of peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon, were observed in post-marketing reports at different times and at therapeutic doses in all age groups throughout the course of treatment. Signs and symptoms generally improve after reduction in dose or discontinuation of drug. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. Further clinical evaluation (e.g., rheumatology referral) may be appropriate for certain patients.



    5.6 Long-Term Suppression of Growth



  Careful follow-up of weight and height in children ages 7 to 10 years who were randomized to either methylphenidate or nonmedication treatment groups over 14 months, as well as in naturalistic subgroups of newly methylphenidate-treated and nonmedication-treated children over 36 months (to the ages of 10 to 13 years), suggests that consistently medicated children (i.e., treatment for 7 days per week throughout the year) have a temporary slowing in growth rate (on average, a total of about 2 cm less growth in height and 2.7 kg less growth in weight over 3 years), without evidence of growth rebound during this period of development. Published data are inadequate to determine whether chronic use of amphetamines may cause similar suppression of growth; however, it is anticipated that they likely have this effect as well. Therefore, growth should be monitored during treatment with stimulants, and patients who are not growing or gaining height or weight as expected may need to have their treatment interrupted.



    5.7 Visual Disturbance



  Difficulties with accommodation and blurring of vision have been reported with stimulant treatment.



    5.8 Potential for Gastrointestinal Obstruction



  Because Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets are nondeformable and do not appreciably change in shape in the GI tract, Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets should not ordinarily be administered to patients with preexisting severe gastrointestinal narrowing (pathologic or iatrogenic, for example: esophageal motility disorders, small bowel inflammatory disease, "short gut" syndrome due to adhesions or decreased transit time, past history of peritonitis, cystic fibrosis, chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction, or Meckel's diverticulum). There have been rare reports of obstructive symptoms in patients with known strictures in association with the ingestion of drugs in nondeformable controlled-release formulations. Due to the controlled-release design of the tablet, Methylphenidate HCl Extended-Release Tablets should be used only in patients who are able to swallow the tablet whole [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  .



    5.9 Hematologic Monitoring



  Periodic CBC, differential, and platelet counts are advised during prolonged therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
