<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="metolazone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Metolazone tablets, USP, are usually well tolerated, and most reported adverse reactions have been mild and transient. Many of metolazone tablets, USP, related adverse reactions represent extensions of its expected pharmacologic activity and can be attributed to either its antihypertensive action or its renal/metabolic actions. The following adverse reactions have been reported. Several are single or comparably rare occurrences. Adverse reactions are listed in decreasing order of severity within body systems.



   Cardiovascular

  Chest pain/discomfort, orthostatic hypotension, excessive volume depletion, hemoconcentration, venous thrombosis, palpitations.



   Central And Peripheral Nervous System

  Syncope, neuropathy, vertigo, paresthesias, psychotic depression, impotence, dizziness/lightheadedness, drowsiness, fatigue, weakness, restlessness (sometimes resulting in insomnia), headache.



   Dermatologic/Hypersensitivity

  Toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, necrotizing angiitis (cutaneous vasculitis), skin necrosis, purpura, petechiae, dermatitis (photosensitivity), urticaria, pruritus, skin rashes.



   Gastrointestinal

  Hepatitis, intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice, pancreatitis, vomiting, nausea, epigastric distress, diarrhea, constipation, anorexia, abdominal bloating, abdominal pain.



   Hematologic

  Aplastic/hypoplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia.



   Metabolic

  Hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hyperuricemia, hypochloremia, hypochloremic alkalosis, hyperglycemia, glycosuria, increase in serum urea nitrogen (BUN) or creatinine, hypophosphatemia, hypomagnesemia, hypercalcemia.



   Musculoskeletal

  Joint pain, acute gouty attacks, muscle cramps or spasm.



   Other

  Transient blurred vision, chills, dry mouth.



 In addition, adverse reactions reported with similar antihypertensive-diuretics, but which have not been reported to date for metolazone tablets, USP, include: bitter taste, sialadenitis, xanthopsia, respiratory distress (including pneumonitis), and anaphylactic reactions. These reactions should be considered as possible occurrences with clinical usage of metolazone tablets, USP.



 Whenever adverse reactions are moderate or severe, metolazone tablets, USP, dosage should be reduced or therapy withdrawn.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
