<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="metoprolol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE EVENTS

    6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.Metoprolol succinate extended release/hydrochlorothiazideThe metoprolol succinate extended release and hydrochlorothiazide combination was evaluated for safety in 891 patients with hypertension in clinical trials. In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, factorial trial (Study 1), 843 patients were treated with various combinations of metoprolol succinate (doses of 25 to 200 mg) and hydrochlorothiazide (doses of 6.25 to 25 mg) [see Clinical Studies (14)]. Adverse events which occurred more than 1% more frequently in patients treated with METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE than placebo were: nasopharyngitis (3.4% vs 1.3%) and fatigue (2.6% vs 0.7%).The adverse reactions of metoprolol succinate extended release are a mixture of dose-dependent phenomena (primarily bradycardia and fatigue) and those of hydrochlorothiazide are a mixture of dose-dependent (primarily hypokalemia) and dose independent phenomena (e.g., pancreatitis), the former much more common than the latter. Therapy with METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE will be associated with both sets of dose independent reactions.



     Laboratory Abnormalities    



   Liver Enzyme Tests  -Increases in liver enzymes or serum bilirubin.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE, metoprolol succinate extended release, and/or hydrochlorothiazide. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate their frequency reliably or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure



   Metoprolol  The following adverse reactions have been reported for immediate release metoprolol tartrate. Most adverse reactions have been mild and transient.  Central Nervous System:  Confusion, short-term memory loss, headache, somnolence, nightmares, insomnia, anxiety/nervousness, hallucinations, paresthesia, dizziness



   Cardiovascular:  Shortness of breath, bradycardia, cold extremities; arterial insufficiency (usually of the Raynaud type), palpitations, peripheral edema, syncope, chest pain



   Respiratory:  Dyspnea



   Gastrointestinal:  Diarrhea, nausea, dry mouth, gastric pain, constipation, flatulence, heartburn, hepatitis, vomiting.



   Hypersensitivity Reactions:  Pruritus, rash



   Miscellaneous:  Musculoskeletal pain, arthralgia, blurred vision, decreased libido, male impotence, tinnitus, reversible alopecia, dry eyes, worsening of psoriasis, Peyronie's disease, sweating, photosensitivity, taste disturbance, depression



     Other Beta-Adrenergic Blockers    In addition, adverse reactions not listed above, that have been reported with other beta-adrenoceptor blockers and should be considered potential adverse reactions to METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE.



   Central Nervous System:  Reversible mental depression progressing to catatonia; an acute reversible syndrome characterized by disorientation for time and place, emotional lability, clouded sensorium, and decreased performance on neuropsychometrics



   Hematologic:  Non-thrombocytopenic purpura, thrombocytopenic purpura



   Hypersensitivity Reactions  : Laryngospasm, and respiratory distress



     Hydrochlorothiazide    Adverse reactions that have been reported with hydrochlorothiazide are listed below:  Body as a Whole  : Weakness



   Cardiovascular:  Orthostatic hypotension



   Digestive:  Pancreatitis, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice), sialadenitis, cramping, gastric irritation, anorexia



   Hematologic:  Aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia



   Hypersensitivity Reactions:  Anaphylactic reactions, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis and cutaneous vasculitis), respiratory distress including pneumonitis and pulmonary edema, photosensitivity, fever, urticaria



   Metabolic:  Glycosuria



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle spasm



   Nervous System/Psychiatric  : Vertigo, paresthesias, restlessness



   Renal:  Interstitial nephritis



   Skin:  Erythema multiforme including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis including toxic epidermal necrolysis



   Special Senses:  Transient blurred vision, xanthopsia
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: BOXED WARNING

  BOXED WARNING

  WARNING: CARDIAC ISCHEMIA AFTER ABRUPT DISCONTINUATION



 Following abrupt discontinuation of therapy with beta adrenergic blockers, exacerbations of angina pectoris and myocardial infarction have occurred.



 When discontinuing chronically administered DUTOPROL, particularly in patients with ischemic heart disease, gradually reduce the dose over a period of 1-2 weeks and monitor the patient. If angina markedly worsens or acute coronary insufficiency develops, promptly resume therapy, at least temporarily, and take other measures appropriate for the management of unstable angina. Warn patients against interruption or discontinuation of therapy without the physician's advice.



 Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, avoid abrupt discontinuation of DUTOPROL therapy even in patients treated only for hypertension [see   Warnings and Precautions]  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    5.1 Cardiac Ischemia after Abrupt Discontinuation    Following abrupt cessation of therapy with beta adrenergic blockers, exacerbations of angina pectoris and myocardial infarction may occur. When discontinuing chronically administered METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE, particularly in patients with ischemic heart disease, gradually reduce the dosage over a period of 1-2 weeks and monitor the patient. If angina markedly worsens or acute coronary ischemia develops, promptly resume therapy and take measures appropriate for the management of unstable angina. Warn patients not to interrupt therapy without their physician's advice. Because coronary artery disease is common and may be unrecognized, avoid abrupt discontinuation of METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE in patients treated only for hypertension.
 

     5.2 Heart Failure  Worsening cardiac failure may occur during up-titration of beta-blockers. If such symptoms occur, increase diuretics and restore clinical stability (compensated heart failure) before advancing the dose of METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE [see Dosage and Administration (2)]. It may be necessary to lower the dose of METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE or temporarily discontinue it [see Boxed Warning.] Such episodes do not preclude subsequent successful titration of METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE.
 

     5.3 Bronchospasm  Beta adrenergic blockers can cause bronchospasm. Patients with bronchospastic disease should, in general, not receive beta adrenergic blockers. Because of its relative beta1 cardio-selectivity, however, metoprolol-containing products including METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE may be used in patients with bronchospastic disease who do not respond to or cannot tolerate other antihypertensive treatment. Because beta1-selectivity is not absolute, in such patients use the lowest possible METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE dose and have bronchodilators (e.g., beta2-agonists) readily available or administer concomitantly.
 

     5.4 Bradycardia  Bradycardia, including sinus pause, heart block, and cardiac arrest have occurred with the use of METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE. Patients with first-degree atrioventricular block, sinus node dysfunction, or conduction disorders (including Wolff-Parkinson-White) may be at increased risk. The concomitant use of beta adrenergic blockers and non-dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers (e.g., verapamil and diltiazem), digoxin or clonidine increases the risk of significant bradycardia. Monitor heart rate and rhythm in patients receiving METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE. If severe bradycardia develops, reduce or stop METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE.
 

     5.5 Risks of Use in Major Surgery  Avoid initiation of high-dose regimen of METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE in patients with cardiovascular risk factors undergoing non-cardiac surgery, since use in such patients has been associated with bradycardia, hypotension, stroke and death.Chronically administered beta adrenergic blockers should not be routinely withdrawn prior to major surgery; however, the impaired ability of the heart to respond to reflex adrenergic stimuli may augment the risks of general anesthesia and surgical procedures [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].
 

     5.6 Masked Signs of Hypoglycemia  Beta adrenergic blockers may mask tachycardia occurring with hypoglycemia, but other manifestations such as dizziness and sweating may not be significantly affected.
 

     5.7 Electrolyte and Metabolic Effects  METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE contains hydrochlorothiazide which can cause hypokalemia and hyponatremia. Hypomagnesemia can result in hypokalemia which may be difficult to treat despite potassium repletion. Monitor serum electrolytes periodically.Hydrochlorothiazide may alter glucose tolerance and raise serum levels of cholesterol and triglycerides.Hydrochlorothiazide reduces clearance of uric acid and may cause or exacerbate hyperuricemia and precipitate gout in susceptible patients.Hydrochlorothiazide decreases urinary calcium excretion and may cause elevations of serum calcium. Monitor calcium levels.
 

     5.8 Renal Impairment  Patients with chronic kidney disease, severe heart failure, or volume depletion may be at increased risk for developing acute renal failure on drugs containing hydrochlorothiazide, including METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE.
 

     5.9 Exacerbated Symptoms of Peripheral Vascular Disease  Beta adrenergic blockers can precipitate or aggravate symptoms of arterial insufficiency in patients with peripheral vascular disease.
 

     5.10 Increased Blood Pressure in Patients with Pheochromocytoma  Administration of beta adrenergic blockers alone in patients with pheochromocytoma has been associated with a paradoxical increase in blood pressure because of the attenuation of beta-mediated vasodilatation in skeletal muscle. If METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE is used in patients with pheochromocytoma, first initiate an alpha-blocker.
 

     5.11 Thyrotoxicosis after Discontinuation in Patients with Hyperthyroidism  Beta adrenergic blockers may mask certain clinical signs of hyperthyroidism, such as tachycardia. Abrupt withdrawal of a beta adrenergic blocker may precipitate a thyroid storm. Therefore, in patients with hyperthyroidism discontinue METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE gradually.
 

     5.12 Reduced Effectiveness of Epinephrine in Treating Anaphylaxis  Beta adrenergic blocker- treated patients treated with epinephrine for a severe anaphylactic reaction may be less responsive to the typical doses of epinephrine. In these patients, consider other medications.
 

     5.13 Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle-Closure Glaucoma  Hydrochlorothiazide, a sulfonamide, can cause acute transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma (idiosyncratic reactions). Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of hydrochlorothiazide initiation. Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss. Given that METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE contains hydrochlorothiazide, if these symptoms occur, discontinue METOPROLOL SUCCINATE AND HYDROCHLOROTHIAZIDE. Consider prompt medical or surgical treatment if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled.
 

     5.14 Exacerbation of Systemic Lupus Erythematosus  Hydrochlorothiazide can exacerbate or activate systemic lupus erythematosus.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
