<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="metozolv" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt; 2%) are headache, nausea, vomiting, fatigue, and somnolence (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Salix Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-508-0024 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or        www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 A total of 86 subjects entered three studies with METOZOLV ODT; 12 subjects entered a pilot bioavailability study (BA); 44 subjects entered a bioequivalence (BE) study, and 30 subjects entered a food-effect study.  The adverse reactions from the BE and food-effect study are summarized in Table 1.  The pilot BA study data are not included because it was performed with a formulation different from the METOZOLV ODT formulation.    



 The adverse experience profile seen with METOZOLV ODT was similar to metoclopramide tablets.  Thirty-three (33) adverse reactions were reported after receiving METOZOLV ODT and 30 adverse reactions were reported after receiving metoclopramide tablets.



 



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions in BE and Food-Effect Study in &gt;= 2% of Subjects




   Adverse Reaction     METOZOLV ODT  N1,3 (%)2     Metoclopramide tablets  N1,4 (%)2    
   Nausea           4 (4.2 %)        4 (5.6 %)       
   Vomiting         2 (2.1 %)        1 (1.4 %)       
   Fatigue          2 (2.1 %)        2 (2.8 %)       
   Headache         5 (5.2 %)        3 (4.2 %)       
   Somnolence       2 (2.1 %)        2 (2.8 %)       
   Dizziness        1 (1.0 %)        3 (4.2 %)       
       1     N = number of subjects that reported adverse reactions    2    Percent (%) occurrence = N divided by number of subjects dosed with respective study drug    3     Number of subjects dosed with METOZOLV ODT:  68 under fasted conditions and 28 under fed conditions.    4     Number of subjects dosed with metoclopramide tablets: 28 under fed conditions and 44 under fasted conditions.    
         The most frequently reported adverse reactions (greater than 2%) associated with METOZOLV ODT were:  nausea, vomiting, fatigue, somnolence and headache.  The most frequently reported adverse reactions (greater than 2%) associated with metoclopramide tablets were:  nausea, headache, fatigue, somnolence, and dizziness.  The combined data from the fasted BE study and the food-effect study did not demonstrate any significant differences in the adverse event profile for METOZOLV ODT compared to metoclopramide tablets.
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions are from the cumulative post-marketing experience with metoclopramide tablets.  Since the reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   CNS    Effects:   Restlessness, drowsiness, fatigue, and lassitude occur in approximately 10% of patients receiving the most commonly prescribed dosage of 10 mg four times a day.  Insomnia, headache, confusion, dizziness, or depression with suicidal ideation occurs less frequently.  The incidence of drowsiness is greater at higher doses.  There are isolated reports of seizures without clear-cut relationship to metoclopramide.  Rarely, hallucinations have been reported.



   Extrapyramidal Syndromes (EPS):   Acute dystonic reactions, the most common type of EPS associated with metoclopramide, occur in approximately 0.2% of patients (1 in 500) treated with 30 to 40 mg of metoclopramide per day. Symptoms include involuntary movements of limbs, facial grimacing, torticollis, oculogyric crisis, rhythmic protrusion of tongue, bulbar type of speech, trismus, opisthotonus (tetanus-like reactions), and rarely, stridor and dyspnea possibly due to laryngospasm; ordinarily these symptoms are readily reversed by diphenhydramine [see     Warnings and Precautions      (      5.1      )  ].



 Drug-induced Parkinsonian-like symptoms may include bradykinesia, tremor, cogwheel rigidity, mask-like facies [see     Warnings and Precautions        (    5.2      )  ].



 Tardive dyskinesia is most frequently characterized by involuntary movements of the tongue, face, mouth, or jaw, and sometimes by involuntary movements of the trunk and/or extremities; movements may be choreoathetotic in appearance.  Motor restlessness (akathisia) may include inability to sit still, pacing, and foot tapping.  These symptoms may disappear spontaneously or respond to a reduction in dosage.



   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome:   Rare occurrences of Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) have been reported  [  see     Warnings and Precautions        (    5.3      )].   



   Endocrine Disturbances:   Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence secondary to hyperprolactinemia. Fluid retention secondary to transient elevation of aldosterone.



   Cardiovascular:   Hypotension, hypertension, supraventricular tachycardia, bradycardia, fluid retention, acute congestive heart failure, possible AV block.



   Gastrointestinal:   Nausea, bowel disturbances, primarily diarrhea.



   Hepatic:   Rarely, cases of hepatotoxicity characterized by such findings as jaundice and altered liver function tests, when metoclopramide was administered with other drugs with known hepatotoxic potential.



   Renal:   Urinary frequency and incontinence.



   Hematologic:   A few cases of neutropenia, leukopenia, or agranulocytosis, generally without clear-cut relationship to metoclopramide.  Methemoglobinemia in adults and especially with overdosage in neonates.  Sulfhemoglobinemia in adults.



   Allergic Reactions:   A few cases of rash, urticaria, or bronchospasm, especially in patients with a history of asthma.  Rarely, angioneurotic edema, including glossal or laryngeal edema.



   Miscellaneous:   Visual disturbances.  Porphyria.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: TARDIVE DYSKINESIA

    WARNING: TARDIVE DYSKINESIA  

    Treatment with metoclopramide can cause tardive dyskinesia, a serious movement disorder that is often irreversible. The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia increases with duration of treatment and total cumulative dose.   



   Metoclopramide therapy should be discontinued in patients who develop signs or symptoms of tardive dyskinesia.  There is no known treatment for tardive dyskinesia.  In some patients, symptoms may lessen or resolve after metoclopramide treatment is stopped.  



   Treatment with metoclopramide for longer than 12 weeks should be avoided in all but rare cases where therapeutic benefit is thought to outweigh the risk of developing tardive dyskinesia.   [See Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: TARDIVE DYSKINESIA  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



   Treatment with metoclopramide can cause tardive dyskinesia, a serious movement disorder that is often irreversible. The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia increases with the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose.   



   Metoclopramide therapy should be discontinued in patients who develop signs or symptoms of tardive dyskinesia. There is no known treatment for tardive dyskinesia. In some patients, symptoms may lessen or resolve after metoclopramide treatment is stopped.  



   Treatment with metoclopramide for longer than 12 weeks should be avoided in all but rare cases where therapeutic benefit is thought to outweigh the risk of developing tardive dyskinesia.           (              5.1              )        
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Tardive Dyskinesia (  5.1  ) 
 *  Acute Dystonic Reactions, Drug-induced Parkinsonism and Other Extrapyramidal Symptoms (  5.2  ) 
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (  5.3  ) 
 *  Depression (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hypertension (  5.5  ) 
 *  Congestive Heart Failure and Ventricular Arrhythmia (  5.6  ) 
 *  Withdrawal from Metoclopramide (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Tardive Dyskinesia



   (see  Boxed Warning  )  



 Treatment with metoclopramide can cause tardive dyskinesia (TD), a potentially irreversible and disfiguring disorder characterized by involuntary movements of the face, tongue, or extremities. The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia increases with the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose. An analysis of utilization patterns showed that about 20% of patients who used metoclopramide took it for longer than 12 weeks.  Treatment with metoclopramide for longer than the recommended 12 weeks should be avoided in all but rare cases where therapeutic benefit is thought to outweigh the risk of developing TD.



  Although the risk of developing TD in the general population may be increased among the elderly, women, and diabetics, it is not possible to predict which patients will develop metoclopramide-induced TD.  Both the risk of developing TD and the likelihood that TD will become irreversible increase with duration of treatment and total cumulative dose.
 

  Metoclopramide should be discontinued in patients who develop signs or symptoms of TD.  There is no known effective treatment for established cases of TD, although in some patients, TD may remit, partially or completely, within several weeks to months after metoclopramide is withdrawn. 
 

  Metoclopramide itself may suppress, or partially suppress, the signs of TD, thereby masking the underlying disease process.  The effect of this symptomatic suppression upon the long-term course of TD is unknown. Therefore, metoclopramide should not be used for the symptomatic control of TD.
 

    5.2 Acute Dystonic Reactions, Drug-induced Parkinsonism, and Other Extrapyramidal Symptoms



  Extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS), manifested primarily as acute dystonic reactions, occur in approximately 1 in 500 patients treated with the usual adult dosages of 30 to 40 mg/day of metoclopramide. These usually are seen during the first 24 to 48 hours of treatment with metoclopramide, occur more frequently in pediatric patients and adult patients less than 30 years of age and are even more frequent at higher doses. These symptoms may include involuntary movements of limbs and facial grimacing, torticollis, oculogyric crisis, rhythmic protrusion of tongue, bulbar type of speech, trismus, or dystonic reactions resembling tetanus. Rarely, dystonic reactions may present as stridor and dyspnea, possibly due to laryngospasm. If these symptoms occur, inject 50 mg diphenhydramine hydrochloride intramuscularly. Benztropine mesylate, 1 to 2 mg intramuscularly, may also be used to reverse these reactions.



 Drug-induced Parkinsonism can occur during metoclopramide therapy, more commonly within the first 6 months after beginning treatment, but also after longer periods.  Parkinsonian symptoms generally subside within 2 to 3 months following discontinuation of metoclopramide.  Patients with a history of Parkinson's disease should be given metoclopramide cautiously, if at all, since such patients can experience exacerbation of Parkinsonian symptoms when taking metoclopramide.



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome



  There have been rare reports of an uncommon but potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) associated with metoclopramide.  Clinical manifestations of NMS include hyperthermia, muscle rigidity, altered consciousness, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis and cardiac arrhythmias). The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated.  In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to identify cases where the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, malignant hyperthermia, drug fever and primary central nervous system (CNS) pathology. The management of NMS should include immediate discontinuation of metoclopramide and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and, treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. Bromocriptine and dantrolene sodium have been used in treatment of NMS, but their effectiveness has not been established [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )].  



    5.4 Depression



  Depression associated with metoclopramide use has occurred in patients with and without a history of depression.  Symptoms ranged from mild to severe and included suicidal ideation and suicide.  For those patients with a prior history of depression, metoclopramide should only be given if the expected benefits outweigh the potential risks.



    5.5 Hypertension



  In one study in hypertensive patients, intravenously administered metoclopramide was shown to release catecholamines; hence, caution should be exercised when metoclopramide is used in patients with hypertension.  There are also clinical reports of hypertensive crises in some patients with undiagnosed pheochromocytoma, thus any rapid rise in blood pressure associated with METOZOLV ODT use should result in immediate cessation of metoclopramide use in those patients [  see     Contraindications   (     4.2     )].  



    5.6 Congestive Heart Failure and Ventricular Arrhythmia



  Since metoclopramide produces a transient increase in plasma aldosterone, patients with cirrhosis or congestive heart failure may be at risk of developing fluid retention and volume overload.  If these side effects occur at any time in any patients during metoclopramide therapy, the drug should be discontinued.



    5.7 Withdrawal from Metoclopramide



  Adverse reactions, especially those involving the nervous system, may occur after stopping the use of METOZOLV ODT. A small number of patients may experience withdrawal symptoms after stopping that could include dizziness, nervousness, and/or headaches.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
