<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="metronidazole2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following reactions have been reported during treatment with metronidazole.



   Central Nervous System

  The most serious adverse reactions reported in patients treated with metronidazole have been convulsive seizures, encephalopathy, aseptic meningitis, optic and peripheral neuropathy, the latter characterized mainly by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity. Since persistent peripheral neuropathy has been reported in some patients receiving prolonged administration of metronidazole, patients should be specifically warned about these reactions and should be told to stop the drug and report immediately to their physicians if any neurologic symptoms occur. In addition, patients have reported headache, syncope, dizziness, vertigo, incoordination, ataxia, confusion, dysarthria, irritability, depression, weakness, and insomnia (see  WARNINGS  ).



 The following reactions have also been reported during treatment with metronidazole.



   Gastrointestinal

  The most common adverse reactions reported have been referable to the gastrointestinal tract, particularly nausea, sometimes accompanied by headache, anorexia and occasionally vomiting, diarrhea; epigastric distress; abdominal cramping; and constipation.



   Mouth

  A sharp, unpleasant metallic taste is not unusual. Furry tongue, glossitis and stomatitis have occurred; these may be associated with a sudden overgrowth of  Candida  which may occur during effective therapy.



   Dermatologic

  Erythematous rash and pruritus.



   Hematopoietic

  Reversible neutropenia (leukopenia); rarely, reversible thrombocytopenia.



   Local Reactions

  Thrombophlebitis after intravenous infusion. This reaction can be minimized or avoided by avoiding prolonged use of indwelling intravenous catheters.



   Cardiovascular

  Flattening of the T-wave may be seen in electrocardiographic tracings.



   Hypersensitivity

  Urticaria, erythematous rash, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, flushing, nasal congestion, dryness of the mouth (or vagina or vulva) and fever.



   Renal

  Dysuria, cystitis, polyuria, incontinence, and a sense of pelvic pressure. Instances of darkened urine have been reported by approximately one patient in 100,000. Although the pigment which is probably responsible for this phenomenon has not been positively identified, it is almost certainly a metabolite of metronidazole and seems to have no clinical significance.



   Other

  Proliferation of  Candida  in the vagina, dyspareunia, decrease of libido, proctitis and fleeting joint pains sometimes resembling "serum sickness". Rare cases of pancreatitis, which abated on withdrawal of the drug, have been reported.



 Patients with Crohn's disease are known to have an increased incidence of gastrointestinal and certain extraintestinal cancers. There have been some reports in the medical literature of breast and colon cancer in Crohn's disease patients who have been treated with metronidazole at high doses for extended periods of time. A cause and effect relationship has not been established. Crohn's disease is not an approved indication for Metronidazole Injection, USP.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
