<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="metrogel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt; 2%) are nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, and headache. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Galderma Laboratories, L.P. at 1-866-735-4137, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.In a controlled clinical trial, 557 patients used metronidazole gel, 1% and 189 patients used the gel vehicle once daily for up to 10 weeks. The following table summarizes selected adverse reactions that occurred at a rate of &gt;=1%:



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions That Occurred at a Rate of &gt;=1% 
   System Organ Class/Preferred Term                   Metronidazole Gel, 1%      Gel Vehicle               
                                                       N= 557                     N= 189                    
  
   Patients with at least one AE       Number (%) of Patients      186 (33.4)                 51 (27.0)                 
   Infections and infestations                         76 (13.6)                  28 (14.8)                 
    Bronchitis                                       6 (1.1)                    3 (1.6)                     
    Influenza                                        8 (1.4)                    1 (0.5)                     
    Nasopharyngitis                                  17 (3.1)                   8 (4.2)                     
    Sinusitis                                        8 (1.4)                    3 (1.6)                     
    Upper respiratory tract infection                14 (2.5)                   4 (2.1)                     
    Urinary tract infection                          6 (1.1)                    1 (0.5)                     
    Vaginal mycosis                                  1 (0.2)                    2 (1.1)                     
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders      19 (3.4)                   5 (2.6)                   
    Back pain                                        3 (0.5)                    2 (1.1)                     
   Neoplasms                                           4 (0.7)                    2 (1.1)                   
    Basal cell carcinoma                             1 (0.2)                    2 (1.1)                     
   Nervous system disorders                            18 (3.2)                   3 (1.6)                   
    Headache                                         12 (2.2)                   1 (0.5)                     
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders      22 (3.9)                   5 (2.6)                   
    Nasal congestion                                 6 (1.1)                    3 (1.6)                     
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders              36 (6.5)                   12 (6.3)                  
    Contact dermatitis                               7 (1.3)                    1 (0.5)                     
    Dry skin                                         6 (1.1)                    3 (1.6)                     
   Vascular disorders                                  8 (1.4)                    1 (0.5)                   
    Hypertension                                     6 (1.1)                    1 (0.5)                     
     Table 2: Local Cutaneous Signs and Symptoms of Irritation That Were Worse Than Baseline 
                                                       Metronidazole Gel, 1%      Gel Vehicle               
  
   Sign/Symptom                                        N= 544                     N= 184                    
   Dryness                                             138 (25.4)                 63 (34.2)                 
    Mild                                             93 (17.1)                  41 (22.3)                   
    Moderate                                         42 (7.7)                   20 (10.9)                   
    Severe                                           3 (0.6)                    2 (1.1)                     
   Scaling                                             134 (24.6)                 60 (32.6)                 
    Mild                                             88 (16.2)                  32 (17.4)                   
    Moderate                                         43 (7.9)                   27 (14.7)                   
    Severe                                           3 (0.6)                    1 (0.5)                     
   Pruritus                                            86 (15.8)                  35 (19.0)                 
    Mild                                             53 (9.7)                   21 (11.4)                   
    Moderate                                         27 (5.0)                   13 (7.1)                    
    Severe                                           6 (1.1)                    1 (0.5)                     
   Stinging/burning                                    56 (10.3)                  28 (15.2)                 
    Mild                                             39 (7.2)                   18 (9.8)                    
    Moderate                                         7 (1.3)                    9 (4.9)                     
    Severe                                           10 (1.8)                   1 (0.5)                     
      The following additional adverse experiences have been reported with the topical use of metronidazole: skin irritation, transient redness, metallic taste, tingling or numbness of extremities, and nausea.
 

   6.2 Post Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reaction has been identified during post approval use of topical metronidazole: peripheral neuropathy.  Because this reaction is reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    *  Peripheral neuropathy, characterized by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity has been reported in patients treated with systemic metronidazole. Although not evident in clinical trials for topical metronidazole, peripheral neuropathy has been reported with the post approval use. The appearance of abnormal neurologic signs should prompt immediate reevaluation of METROGEL therapy. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Metronidazole is a nitroimidazole and should be used with care in patients with evidence of, or history of, blood dyscrasia. (  5.2  ) 
 *  If dermatitis occurs, patients may need to discontinue use.  (  5.3  ) 
 *  Topical metronidazole has been reported to cause tearing of the eyes.  Therefore, contact with the eyes should be avoided. (  5.4  ) 
      EXCERPT:   
 

   5.1 Neurologic Disease



  Peripheral neuropathy, characterized by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity has been reported in patients treated with systemic metronidazole. Although not evident in clinical trials for topical metronidazole, peripheral neuropathy has been reported with the post approval use. The appearance of abnormal neurologic signs should prompt immediate reevaluation of METROGEL therapy. Metronidazole should be administered with caution to patients with central nervous system diseases.



    5.2 Blood Dyscrasias



  Metronidazole is a nitroimidazole; use with care in patients with evidence of, or history of, blood dyscrasia.



    5.3 Contact Dermatitis



  Irritant and allergic contact dermatitis have been reported.  If dermatitis occurs, patients may need to discontinue use.



    5.4 Eye Irritation



  Topical metronidazole has been reported to cause tearing of the eyes.  Avoid contact with the eyes.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
