<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mevacor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Phase III Clinical Studies

  In Phase III controlled clinical studies involving 613 patients treated with MEVACOR, the adverse experience profile was similar to that shown below for the 8,245-patient EXCEL study (see  Expanded Clinical Evaluation of Lovastatin (EXCEL) Study  ).



 Persistent increases of serum transaminases have been noted (see  WARNINGS, Liver Dysfunction  ). About 11% of patients had elevations of CK levels of at least twice the normal value on one or more occasions. The corresponding values for the control agent cholestyramine was 9 percent. This was attributable to the noncardiac fraction of CK. Large increases in CK have sometimes been reported (see  WARNINGS, Myopathy/Rhabdomyolysis  ).



   Expanded Clinical Evaluation of Lovastatin (EXCEL) Study

  MEVACOR was compared to placebo in 8,245 patients with hypercholesterolemia (total-C 240-300 mg/dL [6.2-7.8 mmol/L]) in the randomized, double-blind, parallel, 48-week EXCEL study. Clinical adverse experiences reported as possibly, probably or definitely drug-related in &gt;=1% in any treatment group are shown in the table below. For no event was the incidence on drug and placebo statistically different.




                           Placebo(N = 1663)%  MEVACOR20 mg q.p.m.(N = 1642)%  MEVACOR40 mg q.p.m.(N = 1645)%  MEVACOR20 mg b.i.d.(N = 1646)%  MEVACOR40 mg b.i.d.(N = 1649)%   
  
   Body As a Whole          
       Asthenia            1.4              1.7              1.4              1.5              1.2               
   Gastrointestinal         
       Abdominal pain      1.6              2.0              2.0              2.2              2.5               
       Constipation        1.9              2.0              3.2              3.2              3.5               
       Diarrhea            2.3              2.6              2.4              2.2              2.6               
       Dyspepsia           1.9              1.3              1.3              1.0              1.6               
       Flatulence          4.2              3.7              4.3              3.9              4.5               
       Nausea              2.5              1.9              2.5              2.2              2.2               
   Musculoskeletal          
       Muscle cramps       0.5              0.6              0.8              1.1              1.0               
       Myalgia             1.7              2.6              1.8              2.2              3.0               
   Nervous System/Psychiatric     
       Dizziness           0.7              0.7              1.2              0.5              0.5               
       Headache            2.7              2.6              2.8              2.1              3.2               
   Skin                     
       Rash                0.7              0.8              1.0              1.2              1.3               
   Special Senses           
       Blurred vision      0.8              1.1              0.9              0.9              1.2               
            Other clinical adverse experiences reported as possibly, probably or definitely drug-related in 0.5 to 1.0 percent of patients in any drug-treated group are listed below. In all these cases the incidence on drug and placebo was not statistically different.  Body as a Whole  : chest pain;  Gastrointestinal:  acid regurgitation, dry mouth, vomiting;  Musculoskeletal:  leg pain, shoulder pain, arthralgia;  Nervous System/Psychiatric  : insomnia, paresthesia;  Skin  : alopecia, pruritus;  Special Senses  : eye irritation.
 

 In the EXCEL study (see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Clinical Studies  ), 4.6% of the patients treated up to 48 weeks were discontinued due to clinical or laboratory adverse experiences which were rated by the investigator as possibly, probably or definitely related to therapy with MEVACOR. The value for the placebo group was 2.5%.



   Air Force/Texas Coronary Atherosclerosis Prevention Study (AFCAPS/TexCAPS)

  In AFCAPS/TexCAPS (see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Clinical Studies  ) involving 6,605 participants treated with 20-40 mg/day of MEVACOR (n=3,304) or placebo (n=3,301), the safety and tolerability profile of the group treated with MEVACOR was comparable to that of the group treated with placebo during a median of 5.1 years of follow-up. The adverse experiences reported in AFCAPS/TexCAPS were similar to those reported in EXCEL (see  ADVERSE REACTIONS, Expanded Clinical Evaluation of Lovastatin (EXCEL) Study  ).



   Concomitant Therapy

  In controlled clinical studies in which lovastatin was administered concomitantly with cholestyramine, no adverse reactions peculiar to this concomitant treatment were observed. The adverse reactions that occurred were limited to those reported previously with lovastatin or cholestyramine. Other lipid-lowering agents were not administered concomitantly with lovastatin during controlled clinical studies. Preliminary data suggests that the addition of gemfibrozil to therapy with lovastatin is not associated with greater reduction in LDL-C than that achieved with lovastatin alone. In uncontrolled clinical studies, most of the patients who have developed myopathy were receiving concomitant therapy with cyclosporine, gemfibrozil or niacin (nicotinic acid). The combined use of lovastatin with cyclosporine or gemfibrozil should be avoided. Caution should be used when prescribing other fibrates or lipid-lowering doses (&gt;=1 g/day) of niacin with lovastatin (see  WARNINGS, Myopathy/Rhabdomyolysis  ).



 The following effects have been reported with drugs in this class. Not all the effects listed below have necessarily been associated with lovastatin therapy.



   Skeletal:  muscle cramps, myalgia, myopathy, rhabdomyolysis, arthralgias.



 There have been rare reports of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy associated with statin use (see  WARNINGS, Myopathy/Rhabdomyolysis  ).



   Neurological:  dysfunction of certain cranial nerves (including alteration of taste, impairment of extra-ocular movement, facial paresis), tremor, dizziness, vertigo, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, peripheral nerve palsy, psychic disturbances, anxiety, insomnia, depression.



 There have been rare postmarketing reports of cognitive impairment (e.g., memory loss, forgetfulness, amnesia, memory impairment, confusion) associated with statin use. These cognitive issues have been reported for all statins. The reports are generally nonserious, and reversible upon statin discontinuation, with variable times to symptom onset (1 day to years) and symptom resolution (median of 3 weeks).



   Hypersensitivity Reactions:  An apparent hypersensitivity syndrome has been reported rarely which has included one or more of the following features: anaphylaxis, angioedema, lupus erythematous-like syndrome, polymyalgia rheumatica, dermatomyositis, vasculitis, purpura, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, positive ANA, ESR increase, eosinophilia, arthritis, arthralgia, urticaria, asthenia, photosensitivity, fever, chills, flushing, malaise, dyspnea, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome.



   Gastrointestinal:  pancreatitis, hepatitis, including chronic active hepatitis, cholestatic jaundice, fatty change in liver; and rarely, cirrhosis, fulminant hepatic necrosis, and hepatoma; anorexia, vomiting, fatal and non-fatal hepatic failure.



   Skin:  alopecia, pruritus. A variety of skin changes (e.g., nodules, discoloration, dryness of skin/mucous membranes, changes to hair/nails) have been reported.



   Reproductive:  gynecomastia, loss of libido, erectile dysfunction.



   Eye:  progression of cataracts (lens opacities), ophthalmoplegia.



   Laboratory Abnormalities:  elevated transaminases, alkaline phosphatase, gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase, and bilirubin; thyroid function abnormalities.



   Adolescent Patients (ages 10-17 years)

  In a 48-week controlled study in adolescent boys with heFH (n=132) and a 24-week controlled study in girls who were at least 1 year post-menarche with heFH (n=54), the safety and tolerability profile of the groups treated with MEVACOR (10 to 40 mg daily) was generally similar to that of the groups treated with placebo (see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Clinical Studies in Adolescent Patients  and  PRECAUTIONS, Pediatric Use  ).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
