<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="miglustat" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Peripheral Neuropathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Tremor [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Diarrhea and weight loss [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Reductions in platelet count [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5%) diarrhea, weight loss, stomach pain, gas, nausea and vomiting headache including migraine, tremor, leg cramps, dizziness, weakness, vision problems, thrombocytopenia, muscle cramps, back pain, constipation, dry mouth, heaviness in arms and legs, memory loss, unsteady walking, anorexia, indigestion, paresthesia, stomach bloating, stomach pain not related to food, and menstrual changes (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact CoTherix at 1-855-246-5637 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure of 80 patients with type 1 Gaucher disease in two open-label, uncontrolled, monotherapy trials, one open-label, active-controlled trial, and two extensions, who received miglustat at doses ranging from 50mg to 200 mg three times daily. Patients were aged 18 to 69 years at first treatment. The population was evenly distributed by gender.



 The most common serious adverse reaction reported with miglustat treatment in clinical trials was peripheral neuropathy  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions in patients treated with miglustat (occuring in &gt;=5%) that were considered related to miglustat are shown in Tables 1 and 2.  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2  ,  5.3)  ].  



 The most common adverse reactions requiring intervention were diarrhea and tremor.  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2  ,  5.3)  ].  



 In two open-label, uncontrolled monotherapy trials, adult type 1 Gaucher disease patients were treated with miglustat at a starting dose of 100 mg three times daily (dose range 100 to 200 mg three times daily) for up to 12 months in 28 patients [Study 1], or at a dose of 50 mg three times daily for up to 6 months in 18 patients [Study 2]. Table 1 below lists adverse reactions that occurred during the trials in &gt;=5% of patients.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions in &gt;=5% of Patients in Two Open-Label, Uncontrolled Monotherapy Trials of Miglustat 
                                      Incidence of adverse reactions     
                                     Study 1(starting dose 100 mg three times daily)  Study 2(50 mg three times daily)    
  
   Patients entered in Study (n)                    28                                 18                   
   Body System - Preferred Term           % of patients reporting            % of patients reporting        
   Gastrointestinal System                                                                                  
   Diarrhea                                         89                                 89                   
   Flatulence                                       29                                 44                   
   Abdominal Pain                                   18                                 50                   
   Nausea                                           14                                 22                   
   Vomiting                                          4                                 11                   
   Bloating                                          0                                  6                   
   Anorexia                                          7                                  0                   
   Dyspepsia                                         7                                  0                   
   Epigastric pain not food-related                  0                                  6                   
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                           
   Weight Decrease                                  39                                 67                   
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System                                                                           
   Headache                                         21                                 22                   
   Tremor                                           11                                 11                   
   Dizziness                                         0                                 11                   
   Leg cramps                                        4                                 11                   
   Paresthesia                                       7                                  0                   
   Migraine                                          0                                  6                   
   Vision Disorders                                                                                         
   Visual Disturbance                                0                                 17                   
   Musculoskeletal Disorders                                                                                
   Cramps                                            0                                 11                   
   Platelet, Bleeding, and Clotting Disorders                                                                           
   Thrombocytopenia                                  7                                  6                   
   Reproductive disorders, female                                                                           
   Menstrual disorder                                0                                  6                   
         In an open-label, active-controlled study, 36 adult type 1 Gaucher disease patients were treated with miglustat, imiglucerase, or miglustat plus imiglucerase [Study 3] for up to 12 months. Table 2 lists adverse reactions that occurred during the trial in &gt;=5% of patients.
 

 Table 2: Adverse Reactions in &gt;=5% of Patients in Open-Label Active Controlled Study 
                                      Incidence of adverse reactions     
                                           Miglustat  (r)  alone               Imiglucerase alone           
  
   Patients entered in Study (n)                    12                                 12                   
     Body System - Preferred Term         % of patients reporting            % of patients reporting        
   Gastrointestinal System                                                                                  
   Diarrhea                                         100                                 0                   
   Abdominal Pain                                   67                                  0                   
   Flatulence                                       50                                  0                   
   Constipation                                      8                                  0                   
   Nausea                                            8                                  0                   
   Dry Mouth                                         8                                  0                   
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Pain                                              0                                  8                   
   Generalized weakness                             17                                  0                   
   Abdominal distension                              8                                  0                   
   Back pain                                         8                                  0                   
   Heaviness in limbs                                8                                  0                   
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                           
   Weight Decrease                                  67                                  0                   
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System                                                                           
   Tremor                                           17                                  0                   
   Dizziness                                         8                                  0                   
   Leg cramps                                        8                                  0                   
   Unsteady gait                                     8                                  0                   
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Memory loss                                       8                                  0                   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  Therapy should be directed by physicians knowledgeable in the management of patients with Gaucher disease.



    EXCERPT:    *   Peripheral neuropathy : Perform baseline and follow-up neurological evaluations at 6 month intervals in all patients (  5.1  ). 
 *   Tremor or exacerbation of existing tremors : Reduce dose to ameliorate tremor or discontinue treatment if tremor does not resolve within days of dose reduction (  5.2  ). 
 *   Diarrhea and weight loss : Evaluate for underlying gastrointestinal disease in patients who do not respond to usual interventions (e.g. diet modification) (  5.3  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Peripheral Neuropathy



  In clinical trials, cases of peripheral neuropathy have been reported in 3% of Gaucher's patients treated with miglustat. All patients receiving miglustat treatment should undergo baseline and repeat neurological evaluations at approximately 6-month intervals. Patients who develop symptoms of peripheral neuropathy such as pain, weakness, numbness and tingling should have a careful re-assessment of the risk/benefit of miglustat therapy, and cessation of treatment may be considered.



    5.2 Tremor



  Approximately 30% of patients have reported tremor or exacerbation of existing tremor on treatment. These tremors were described as an exaggerated physiological tremor of the hands. Tremor usually began within the first month of therapy and in many cases resolved between 1 to 3 months during treatment. Reduce dose to ameliorate tremor or discontinue treatment if tremor does not resolve within days of dose reduction.



    5.3 Diarrhea and Weight Loss



  Diarrhea and weight loss were common in clinical studies of patients treated with miglustat, occurring in approximately 85% and up to 65% of treated patients, respectively. Diarrhea appears to be the result of the inhibitory activity of miglustat on intestinal disaccharidases such as sucrase-isomaltase in the gastrointestinal tract leading to reduced absorption of dietary disaccharides in the small intestine, with a resultant osmotic diarrhea. It is unclear if weight loss results from the diarrhea and associated gastrointestinal complaints, a decrease in food intake, or a combination of these or other factors. The incidence of weight loss was most evident in the first 12 months of treatment. Diarrhea decreased over time with continued miglustat treatment, and may respond to individualized diet modification (e.g., reduction of sucrose, lactose and other carbohydrate intake), to taking miglustat between meals, and/or to anti-diarrheal medications, most commonly loperamide. Patients may be instructed to avoid high carbohydrate content foods during treatment with miglustat if they present with diarrhea.



 Patients with persistent gastrointestinal events that continue during treatment with miglustat, and who do not respond to usual interventions (e.g. diet modification), should be evaluated to determine whether significant underlying gastrointestinal disease is present. The safety of treatment with miglustat has not been evaluated in patients with significant gastrointestinal disease, such as inflammatory bowel disease, and continued treatment of these patients with miglustat should occur only after consideration of the risks and benefits of continued treatment.



    5.4 Reductions in Platelet Count



  In clinical trials evaluating the use of miglustat for treatment of indications other than type 1 Gaucher disease, mild reductions in platelet counts without association with bleeding were observed in some patients; approximately 40% of patients in this trial had low platelet counts (defined as below 150 * 10  9  /L) before starting treatment with miglustat. Monitoring of platelet counts is recommended in patients with type 1 Gaucher disease. Mild reductions in platelet counts without association with bleeding were observed in patients with type 1 Gaucher disease who were switched from enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) to miglustat.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
