<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mirapex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)    ] 
 *  Symptomatic Orthostatic Hypotension [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)    ] 
 *  Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.3)    ] 
 *  Hallucinations and Psychotic-like Behavior [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)    ] 
 *  Dyskinesia [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.5)    ] 
 *  Rhabdomyolysis [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.7)    ] 
 *  Retinal Pathology [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)    ] 
 *  Events Reported with Dopaminergic Therapy [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.9)    ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and greater than placebo):
 

 *  Early PD without levodopa: somnolence, nausea, constipation, dizziness, fatigue, hallucinations, dry mouth, muscle spasms, and peripheral edema  (6.1)   
 *  Advanced PD with levodopa: dyskinesia, nausea, constipation, hallucinations, headache, and anorexia  (6.1)   
        To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or            www.fda.gov/medwatch        .
 

 

  6.1   Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug (or of another development program of a different formulation of the same drug) and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During the premarketing development of MIRAPEX ER tablets, patients with early Parkinson's disease were treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets, placebo, or immediate-release pramipexole tablets. In addition, a randomized, double-blind, parallel group trial was conducted in 156 early Parkinson's disease patients (Hoehn &amp; Yahr Stages I-III) to assess overnight switching of immediate-release pramipexole tablets to MIRAPEX ER tablets. In this latter study, concomitant treatment with stable doses of levodopa, monoamine oxidase B inhibitor (MAOB-I) drugs, anticholinergics, or amantadine, individually or in combination, was allowed. In a third trial, advanced Parkinson's disease patients received MIRAPEX ER tablets, placebo, or immediate-release pramipexole tablets as adjunctive therapy to levodopa.



   Early Parkinson's Disease  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and more frequent than placebo) after 33 weeks of treatment with MIRAPEX ER tablets in the trial of early Parkinson's disease patients were somnolence, nausea, constipation, dizziness, fatigue, hallucinations, dry mouth, muscle spasms, and peripheral edema.



 Twenty four of 223 (11%) patients treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets for 33 weeks discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions compared to 4 of 103 (4%) patients who received placebo and approximately 20 of 213 (9%) patients who received immediate-release pramipexole tablets. The adverse reaction most commonly causing discontinuation of treatment with MIRAPEX ER tablets was nausea (2%).



 Table 1 lists adverse reactions that occurred with a frequency of at least 2% with MIRAPEX ER and were more frequent than with placebo during 33 weeks of treatment in a double-blind, placebo-controlled study in early Parkinson's disease. In this study, patients did not receive concomitant levodopa; however, levodopa was permitted as rescue medication.



 Table 1 Adverse-Reactions in a 33-Week Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial with MIRAPEX ER in Early Parkinson's Disease 
   Body System/Adverse Reaction        Placebo                                 MIRAPEX ER            Immediate-Release Pramipexole       
         (n=103)                                 (n=223)               (n=213)            
         %                                       %                     %                  
     Nervous system disorders                                                                                           
     Somnolence                              15                    36                    33                     
     Dizziness                               7                     12                    12                     
     Tremor                                  1                     3                     3                      
     Balance disorder                        1                     2                     0                      
     Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                           
     Nausea                                  9                     22                    24                     
     Constipation                            2                     14                    12                     
     Dry mouth                               1                     5                     4                      
     Vomiting                                0                     4                     4                      
     Upper abdominal pain                    1                     3                     4                      
     Dyspepsia                               2                     3                     3                      
     Abdominal discomfort                    0                     2                     1                      
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                         
     Hallucinations, including visual, auditory and mixed  1                     5                     6                      
     Insomnia                                3                     4                     4                      
     Sleep attacks or sudden onset of sleep  1                     3                     6                      
     Sleep disorder                          1                     2                     3                      
     Depression                              0                     2                     0                      
     General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                                           
     Fatigue                                 4                     6                     6                      
     Peripheral edema                        4                     5                     8                      
     Asthenia                                2                     3                     1                      
     Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                                           
     Muscle spasms                           3                     5                     3                      
     Injury, poisoning and procedural complications                                                                                           
     Fall                                    1                     4                     4                      
   Ear and labyrinth disorders                                                                                         
     Vertigo                                 1                     4                     2                      
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                                         
     Cough                                   1                     3                     3                      
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                                         
     Increased appetite                      1                     3                     2                      
     Vascular disorders                                                                                           
     Orthostatic hypotension                 1                     3                     0                      
      Because this study used a flexible dose titration design, it was not possible to assess the effects of dose on the incidence of adverse reactions.
 

 Adverse reactions can initially occur in either the titration or maintenance phase.  Some adverse reactions developed in MIRAPEX ER-treated patients during the titration phase and persisted (&gt;=7 days) into the maintenance phase (i.e., MIRAPEX ER % - placebo % = treatment difference &gt;=2%); persistent adverse reactions were somnolence, nausea, constipation, fatigue, and dry mouth.



 A double-blind, randomized, parallel group trial evaluated the tolerability of an overnight switch from immediate-release pramipexole tablets to MIRAPEX ER tablets at the same daily dose in 156 early Parkinson's disease patients with or without levodopa. One of 104 patients switched from immediate-release pramipexole tablets to MIRAPEX ER tablets discontinued due to adverse reactions (vertigo and nausea).



   Advanced Parkinson's Disease  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and greater frequency than in placebo) during 18 weeks of treatment with MIRAPEX ER tablets in the trial of advanced Parkinson's disease patients with concomitant levodopa were dyskinesia, nausea, constipation, hallucinations, headache, and anorexia.



 Eight of 164 (5%) patients treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets for 18 weeks discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions compared to 7 of 178 (4%) patients who received placebo and 8 of 175 (5%) patients who received immediate-release pramipexole tablets. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of treatment with MIRAPEX ER tablets were nausea (1%) and hallucination (1%).



 Table 2 lists adverse reactions that occurred with a frequency of at least 2% with MIRAPEX ER and were more frequent than with placebo during 18 weeks of treatment in patients with advanced Parkinson's disease treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets. In this study, MIRAPEX ER tablets, immediate-release pramipexole tablets, or placebo was administered to patients who were also receiving concomitant levodopa.



 Table 2 Adverse-Reactions in an 18-Week Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial with MIRAPEX ER in Advanced Parkinson's Disease 
     Body System/Adverse  Reaction             Placebo               MIRAPEX ER            Immediate-Release Pramipexole       
                                               n=178                 n=164                 n=175              
                                               %                     %                     %                  
     Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
    Dyskinesia                             8                     17                    18                     
    Headache                               3                     7                     4                      
    Dizziness (postural)                   1                     2                     3                      
     Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                               
    Nausea                                 10                    11                    11                     
    Constipation                           5                     7                     6                      
    Salivary hypersecretion                0                     2                     0                      
    Diarrhea                               1                     2                     1                      
     Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
    Hallucinations, including visual, auditory and mixed  2                     9                     7                      
    Insomnia                               2                     4                     4                      
     Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                         
    Anorexia                               2                     5                     1                      
     Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                         
    Back pain                              1                     2                     3                      
      Because this flexible dose study used a titration design, it was not possible to assess the effects of dose on the incidence of adverse reactions.
 

 Adverse reactions can initially occur in either the titration or maintenance phase. Some adverse reactions developed in MIRAPEX ER-treated patients during the titration phase and persisted (&gt;=7 days) into the maintenance phase (i.e., MIRAPEX ER % - placebo % = treatment difference &gt;=2%); persistent adverse reactions were dyskinesia and insomnia.



   Laboratory Tests  During the development of MIRAPEX ER tablets, no systematic abnormalities on routine laboratory testing were noted.



   Other adverse reactions observed during clinical trials of pramipexole in early and advanced Parkinson's disease  Other adverse reactions in clinical studies involving pramipexole include abnormal dreams, akathisia, amnesia, decreased libido, decreased weight, dyspnea, pneumonia, and vision abnormalities.



   6.2   Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of immediate-release pramipexole tablets, primarily in Parkinson's disease patients. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to pramipexole tablets. Similar types of events were grouped into a smaller number of standardized categories using the MedDRA terminology: cardiac failure, inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH), syncope, vomiting, and weight increase.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Falling asleep during activities of daily living: Sudden onset of sleep may occur without warning; advise patients to report symptoms  (5.1)   
 *  Symptomatic orthostatic hypotension: Monitor closely especially during dose escalation  (5.2)   
 *  Impulse control/Compulsive behaviors: Patients may experience compulsive behaviors and other intense urges  (5.3)   
 *  Hallucinations and Psychotic-like Behavior: May occur; risk increases with age  (5.4)   
 *  Dyskinesia: May be caused or exacerbated by MIRAPEX ER  (5.5)   
 *  Events reported with dopaminergic therapy: Include hyperpyrexia and confusion, fibrotic complications, and melanoma  (5.9)   
    
 

   5.1   Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence



  Patients treated with pramipexole have reported falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, which sometimes resulted in accidents. Although many of these patients reported somnolence while on pramipexole tablets, some perceived that they had no warning signs (sleep attack) such as excessive drowsiness, and believed that they were alert immediately prior to the event. Some of these events had been reported as late as one year after the initiation of treatment. In placebo-controlled clinical trials in Parkinson's disease, the sudden onset of sleep or sleep attacks were reported in 8 of 387 (2%) patients treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets compared to 2 of 281 (1%) patients on placebo.



 In early Parkinson's disease, somnolence was reported in 36% of 223 patients treated with MIRAPEX ER, median dose 3.0 mg/day, compared to 15% of 103 patients on placebo. In advanced Parkinson's disease, somnolence was reported in 15% of 164 patients treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets, median dose 3 mg/day, compared to 16% of 178 patients on placebo. It has been reported that falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living usually occurs in a setting of preexisting somnolence, although patients may not give such a history. For this reason, prescribers should reassess patients for drowsiness or sleepiness, especially since some of the events occur well after the start of treatment. Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge drowsiness or sleepiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities.



 Before initiating treatment with MIRAPEX ER tablets, advise patients of the potential to develop drowsiness, and specifically ask about factors that may increase the risk for somnolence such as the use of concomitant sedating medications or alcohol, the presence of sleep disorders, and concomitant medications that increase pramipexole plasma levels (e.g., cimetidine) [  see Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ]. If a patient develops significant daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require active participation (e.g., conversations, eating, etc.), MIRAPEX ER tablets should ordinarily be discontinued. If a decision is made to continue MIRAPEX ER tablets, advise patients not to drive and to avoid other potentially dangerous activities that might result in harm if the patients become somnolent. While dose reduction reduces the degree of somnolence, there is insufficient information to establish that dose reduction will eliminate episodes of falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living.



    5.2   Symptomatic Orthostatic Hypotension



  Dopamine agonists, in clinical studies and clinical experience, appear to impair the systemic regulation of blood pressure, with resulting orthostatic hypotension, especially during dose escalation. Parkinson's disease patients, in addition, appear to have an impaired capacity to respond to an orthostatic challenge. For these reasons, Parkinson's disease patients being treated with dopaminergic agonists, including MIRAPEX ER, ordinarily require careful monitoring for signs and symptoms of orthostatic hypotension, especially during dose escalation, and should be informed of this risk. In placebo-controlled clinical trials in Parkinson's disease, symptomatic orthostatic hypotension was reported in 10 of 387 (3%) patients treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets compared to 3 of 281 (1%) patients on placebo. One patient of 387 on MIRAPEX ER tablets discontinued treatment due to hypotension.



    5.3   Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors



  Case reports and the results of cross-sectional studies suggest that patients can experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money, binge eating, and/or other intense urges, and the inability to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications, including MIRAPEX ER, that increase central dopaminergic tone and that are generally used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease. In some cases, although not all, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose was reduced or the medication was discontinued. Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal, it is important for prescribers to specifically ask patients or their caregivers about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending or other urges while being treated with MIRAPEX ER. Physicians should consider dose reduction or stopping the medication if a patient develops such urges while taking MIRAPEX ER.



 A total of 1056 patients with Parkinson's disease who participated in two MIRAPEX ER placebo-controlled studies of up to 33 weeks duration were specifically asked at each visit about the occurrence of these symptoms. A total of 14 of 387 (4%) treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets, 12 of 388 (3%) treated with immediate-release pramipexole tablets, and 4 of 281 (1%) treated with placebo reported compulsive behaviors, including pathological gambling, hypersexuality, and/or compulsive buying.



    5.4   Hallucinations and Psychotic-like Behavior



   In placebo-controlled clinical trials in Parkinson's disease, hallucinations (visual or auditory or mixed) were reported in 25 of 387 (6%) patients treated with MIRAPEX ER tablets compared to 5 of 281 (2%) patients receiving placebo. Hallucinations led to discontinuation of treatment in 5 of 387 (1%) patients on MIRAPEX ER tablets.  



  Age appears to increase the risk of hallucinations attributable to pramipexole. In placebo-controlled clinical trials in Parkinson's disease, hallucinations were reported in 15 of 162 (9%) patients &gt;=65 years of age taking MIRAPEX ER tablets compared to 10 of 225 (4%) patients &lt;65 years of age taking MIRAPEX ER tablets.  



  Postmarketing reports with dopamine agonists, including MIRAPEX ER, indicate that patients may experience new or worsening mental status and behavioral changes, which may be severe, including psychotic-like behavior during treatment with MIRAPEX ER or after starting or increasing the dose of MIRAPEX ER. Other drugs prescribed to improve the symptoms of Parkinson's disease can have similar effects on thinking and behavior. This abnormal thinking and behavior can consist of one or more of a variety of manifestations including paranoid ideation, delusions, hallucinations, confusion, psychotic-like behavior, disorientation, aggressive behavior, agitation, and delirium.  



  Patients with a major psychotic disorder should ordinarily not be treated with dopamine agonists, including MIRAPEX ER, because of the risk of exacerbating the psychosis. In addition, certain medications used to treat psychosis may exacerbate the symptoms of Parkinson's disease and may decrease the effectiveness of MIRAPEX ER [ see Drug Interactions  (7.1)    ].  



    5.5   Dyskinesia



  MIRAPEX ER tablets may potentiate the dopaminergic side effects of levodopa and may cause or exacerbate preexisting dyskinesia.



    5.6   Renal Impairment



  The elimination of pramipexole is dependent on renal function [  see Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ]. Patients with mild renal impairment (a creatinine clearance above 50 mL/min) require no reduction in daily dose. MIRAPEX ER tablets have not been studied in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;50 mL/min) or on hemodialysis [  see Dosage and Administration  (2.2)  , Use in Specific Populations  (8.6)  , and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].



    5.7   Rhabdomyolysis



  In the clinical development program for immediate-release pramipexole tablets, a single case of rhabdomyolysis occurred in a 49-year-old male with advanced Parkinson's disease. The patient was hospitalized with an elevated CPK (10,631 IU/L). The symptoms resolved with discontinuation of the medication.



 Advise patients to contact a physician if they experience any unexplained muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness, as these may be symptoms of rhabdomyolysis.



    5.8   Retinal Pathology



    Human Data    A two-year open-label, randomized, parallel-group safety study of retinal deterioration and vision compared immediate-release pramipexole tablets and immediate-release ropinirole. Two hundred thirty four Parkinson's disease patients (115 on pramipexole, mean dose 3.0 mg/day and 119 on ropinirole, mean dose 9.5 mg/day) were evaluated using a panel of clinical ophthalmological assessments.  Of 234 patients who were evaluable, 196 had been treated for two years and 29 were judged to have developed clinical abnormalities that were considered meaningful (19 patients in each treatment arm had received treatment for less than two years).  There was no statistical difference in retinal deterioration between the treatment arms; however, the study was only capable of detecting a very large difference between treatments.  In addition, because the study did not include an untreated comparison group (placebo treated), it is unknown whether the findings reported in patients treated with either drug are greater than the background rate in an aging population.
 

   Animal Data    Pathologic changes (degeneration and loss of photoreceptor cells) were observed in the retina of albino rats in a 2-year carcinogenicity study. While retinal degeneration was not diagnosed in pigmented rats treated for 2 years, a thinning in the outer nuclear layer of the retina was slightly greater in rats given drug compared with controls. Evaluation of the retinas of albino mice, monkeys, and minipigs did not reveal similar changes. The potential significance of this effect for humans has not been established, but cannot be disregarded because disruption of a mechanism that is universally present in vertebrates (i.e., disk shedding) may be involved [  see Nonclinical Toxicology  (13.2)      ].
 

    5.9   Events Reported with Dopaminergic Therapy



  Although the events enumerated below may not have been reported with the use of pramipexole in its development program, they are associated with the use of other dopaminergic drugs. The expected incidence of these events, however, is so low that even if pramipexole caused these events at rates similar to those attributable to other dopaminergic therapies, it would be unlikely that even a single case would have occurred in a cohort of the size exposed to pramipexole in studies to date.



    Hyperpyrexia and Confusion    Although not reported with pramipexole in the clinical development program, a symptom complex resembling the neuroleptic malignant syndrome (characterized by elevated temperature, muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, and autonomic instability), with no other obvious etiology, has been reported in association with rapid dose reduction, withdrawal of, or changes in dopaminergic therapy. If possible, avoid sudden discontinuation or rapid dose reduction in patients taking MIRAPEX ER tablets. If the decision is made to discontinue MIRAPEX ER tablets, the dose should be tapered to reduce the risk of hyperpyrexia and confusion [ see Dosage and Administration  (2.2)    ].  
 

   Fibrotic Complications    Cases of retroperitoneal fibrosis, pulmonary infiltrates, pleural effusion, pleural thickening, pericarditis, and cardiac valvulopathy have been reported in patients treated with ergot-derived dopaminergic agents. While these complications may resolve when the drug is discontinued, complete resolution does not always occur.
 

 Although these adverse events are believed to be related to the ergoline structure of these compounds, whether other, non-ergot derived dopamine agonists can cause them is unknown.



 Cases of possible fibrotic complications, including peritoneal fibrosis, pleural fibrosis, and pulmonary fibrosis have been reported in the postmarketing experience with immediate-release pramipexole tablets. While the evidence is not sufficient to establish a causal relationship between pramipexole and these fibrotic complications, a contribution of pramipexole cannot be completely ruled out.



   Melanoma    Epidemiologic studies have shown that patients with Parkinson's disease have a higher risk (2- to approximately 6-fold higher) of developing melanoma than the general population. Whether the observed increased risk was due to Parkinson's disease or other factors, such as drugs used to treat Parkinson's disease, is unclear.
 

 For the reasons stated above, patients and providers are advised to monitor for melanomas frequently and on a regular basis when using MIRAPEX ER tablets for  any    indication. Ideally, periodic skin examinations should be performed by appropriately qualified individuals (e.g., dermatologists).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
