<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mirvaso" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During clinical trials, 1210 subjects were exposed to MIRVASO topical gel. A total of 833 subjects were treated for persistent (nontransient) erythema associated with rosacea, and 330 of those were treated once daily for 29 days in vehicle-controlled trials.



 Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of subjects treated with MIRVASO topical gel once daily for 29 days and for which the rate for MIRVASO topical gel exceeded the rate for vehicle are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1 - Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials by At Least 1% of Subjects Treated for 29 Days 
   Preferred Term            MIRVASO Topical Gel  (N=330)  n (%)    Vehicle Gel (N=331)   n (%)     
   Subjects with at least one adverse reaction, Number (%) of Subjects      109 (33)                   91 (28)                   
  Erythema                  12 (4%)                    3 (1%)                      
  Flushing                  9 (3%)                     0                           
  Skin burning sensation    5 (2%)                     2 (1%)                      
  Dermatitis contact        3 (1%)                     1 (&lt;1%)                     
  Dermatitis                3 (1%)                     1 (&lt;1%)                     
  Skin warm                 3 (1%)                     0                           
  Paraesthesia              2 (1%)                     1 (&lt;1%)                     
  Acne                      2 (1%)                     1 (&lt;1%)                     
  Pain of skin              2 (1%)                     0                           
  Vision blurred            2 (1%)                     0                           
  Nasal congestion          2 (1%)                     0                           
          Open-label, Long-term Study    
 

 An open-label study of MIRVASO topical gel when applied once daily for up to one year was conducted in subjects with persistent (nontransient) facial erythema of rosacea. Subjects were allowed to use other rosacea therapies. A total of 276 subjects applied MIRVASO topical gel for at least one year. The most common adverse events (  &gt;  4% of subjects) for the entire study were flushing (10%), erythema (8%), rosacea (5%), nasopharyngitis (5%), skin burning sensation (4%), increased intraocular pressure (4%), and headache (4%).



     Allergic contact dermatitis    



 Allergic contact dermatitis to MIRVASO topical gel was reported in approximately 1% of subjects across the clinical development program. Two subjects underwent patch testing with individual product ingredients. One subject was found to be sensitive to brimonidine tartrate, and one subject was sensitive to phenoxyethanol (a preservative).



   EXCERPT:   In controlled clinical trials with MIRVASO topical gel the most common adverse reactions (incidence  &gt;  1%) included erythema, flushing, skin burning sensation, and contact dermatitis.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Galderma Laboratories, L.P. at 1-866-735-4137 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



     EXCERPT:    *  Potentiation of Vascular Insufficiency (5.1) 
 *  Severe Cardiovascular Disease (5.2) 
 *  Serious Adverse Reactions Following Ingestion of MIRVASO topical gel (5.3) 
 *  Erythema and Flushing (5.4) 
    
 

    5.1 Potentiation of Vascular Insufficiency  



  MIRVASO topical gel should be used with caution in patients with depression, cerebral or coronary insufficiency, Raynaud's phenomenon, orthostatic hypotension, thrombangiitis obliterans, scleroderma, or Sjogren's syndrome.



     5.2 Severe Cardiovascular Disease  



  Alpha-2 adrenergic agonists can lower blood pressure. MIRVASO topical gel should be used with caution in patients with severe or unstable or uncontrolled cardiovascular disease.



     5.3 Serious Adverse Reactions Following Ingestion of MIRVASO topical gel  



  Two young children of a subject in a clinical trial experienced serious adverse reactions following accidental ingestion of MIRVASO topical gel. Adverse reactions experienced by one or both children included lethargy, respiratory distress with apneic episodes (requiring intubation), sinus bradycardia, confusion, psychomotor hyperactivity, and diaphoresis. Both children were hospitalized overnight and discharged the following day without sequelae.



 Keep MIRVASO topical gel out of reach of children.



     5.4 Erythema and Flushing  



  Some subjects in the clinical trials discontinued use of MIRVASO topical gel because of erythema or flushing.



 The effect of MIRVASO topical gel may begin to diminish hours after application. For some subjects in the clinical trials, erythema was reported to return worse compared to the severity at baseline [   see Adverse Reactions (6)   ]  .



 Intermittent flushing occurred in some subjects treated with MIRVASO topical gel. The onset of flushing relative to application of MIRVASO topical gel varied, ranging from approximately 30 minutes to several hours [   see Adverse Reactions (6)   ]  .



 Erythema and flushing appeared to resolve after discontinuation of MIRVASO topical gel.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
