<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mivacron" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Observed in Clinical Trials

  MIVACRON (a mixture of three stereoisomers) was well tolerated during extensive clinical trials in inpatients and outpatients. Prolonged neuromuscular block, which is an important adverse experience associated with neuromuscular blocking agents as a class, was reported as an adverse experience in three of 2074 patients administered MIVACRON. The most commonly reported adverse experience following the administration of MIVACRON was transient, dose-dependent cutaneous flushing about the face, neck, and/or chest. Flushing was most frequently noted after the initial dose of MIVACRON and was reported in about 25% of adult patients who received 0.15 mg/kg MIVACRON over 5 to 15 seconds. When present, flushing typically began within 1 to 2 minutes after the dose of MIVACRON and lasted for 3 to 5 minutes. Of 105 patients who experienced flushing after 0.15 mg/kg MIVACRON, two patients also experienced mild hypotension that was not treated, and one patient experienced moderate wheezing that was successfully treated.



 Overall, hypotension was infrequently reported as an adverse experience in the clinical trials of MIVACRON. One of 332 (0.3%) healthy adults who received 0.15 mg/kg MIVACRON over 5 to 15 seconds and none of 37 cardiac surgery patients who received 0.15 mg/kg MIVACRON over 60 seconds were treated for a decrease in blood pressure in association with the administration of MIVACRON. One to two percent of healthy adults given greater than or equal to 0.2 mg/kg MIVACRON over 5 to 15 seconds, 2% to 3% of healthy adults given 0.2 mg/kg over 30 seconds, none of 100 healthy adults given 0.25 mg/kg as a divided dose (0.15 mg/kg followed in 30 seconds by 0.1 mg/kg), and 2% to 4% of cardiac surgery patients given greater than or equal to 0.2 mg/kg over 60 seconds were treated for a decrease in blood pressure. None of the 63 children who received the recommended dose of 0.2 mg/kg MIVACRON was treated for a decrease in blood pressure in association with the administration of MIVACRON.



 The following adverse experiences were reported in patients administered MIVACRON (all events judged by investigators during the clinical trials to have a possible causal relationship):



   

    Incidence Greater Than 1%  



   

      Cardiovascular    



 Flushing (16%)



   

    Incidence Less Than 1%  



   

      Cardiovascular    



 Hypotension, tachycardia, bradycardia, cardiac arrhythmia, phlebitis



   

      Respiratory    



 Bronchospasm, wheezing, hypoxemia



   

      Dermatological    



 Rash, urticaria, erythema, injection site reaction



   

      Nonspecific    



 Prolonged drug effect



   

      Neurologic    



 Dizziness



   

      Musculoskeletal    



 Muscle spasms



   Observed in Clinical Practice

  Based on initial clinical practice experience in patients who received MIVACRON, spontaneously reported adverse events are uncommon. Some of these events occurred at recommended doses and required treatment.



   Anaphylaxis/Anaphylactoid Reactions  : From post-marketing surveillance, MIVACRON has been associated with reports of anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions which in some cases have been life-threatening and fatal. Because these reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency (see    WARNINGS    and    PRECAUTIONS    ). In some of these reports, sensitivity to MIVACRON was confirmed using skin test procedures.



 Other adverse reaction data from clinical practice are insufficient to establish a causal relationship or to support an estimate of their incidence. These adverse events include:



   

    Musculoskeletal  



 Diminished drug effect, prolonged drug effect



   

    Cardiovascular  



 Hypotension (rarely severe), flushing



   

    Respiratory  



 Bronchospasm



   

    Integumentary  



 Rash
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
