<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mobic" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular thrombotic events [  see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)    ] 
 *  Gastrointestinal effects - risk of GI ulceration, bleeding, and perforation [  see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)    ] 
 *  Hepatic effects [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.3)    ] 
 *  Hypertension [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)    ] 
 *  Congestive heart failure and edema [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.5)    ] 
 *  Renal effects [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)    ] 
 *  Anaphylactoid reactions [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.7)    ] 
 *  Adverse skin reactions [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)    ] 
   *  Most common (&gt;=5% and greater than placebo) adverse events in adults are diarrhea, upper respiratory tract infections, dyspepsia, and influenza-like symptoms (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adverse events observed in pediatric studies were similar in nature to the adult clinical trial experience (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:       To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    
 

 

  6.1  Clinical Trials Experience

    Adults  

  

      Osteoarthritis and Rheumatoid Arthritis    



 The MOBIC Phase 2/3 clinical trial database includes 10,122 OA patients and 1012 RA patients treated with MOBIC 7.5 mg/day, 3505 OA patients and 1351 RA patients treated with MOBIC 15 mg/day. MOBIC at these doses was administered to 661 patients for at least 6 months and to 312 patients for at least one year. Approximately 10,500 of these patients were treated in ten placebo- and/or active-controlled osteoarthritis trials and 2363 of these patients were treated in ten placebo- and/or active-controlled rheumatoid arthritis trials. Gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events were the most frequently reported adverse events in all treatment groups across MOBIC trials.



 A 12-week multicenter, double-blind, randomized trial was conducted in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee or hip to compare the efficacy and safety of MOBIC with placebo and with an active control. Two 12-week multicenter, double-blind, randomized trials were conducted in patients with rheumatoid arthritis to compare the efficacy and safety of MOBIC with placebo.



 Table 1a depicts adverse events that occurred in &gt;=2% of the MOBIC treatment groups in a 12-week placebo- and active-controlled osteoarthritis trial.



 Table 1b depicts adverse events that occurred in &gt;=2% of the MOBIC treatment groups in two 12-week placebo-controlled rheumatoid arthritis trials.



 Table 1a Adverse Events (%) Occurring in &gt;=2% of MOBIC Patients in a 12-Week Osteoarthritis Placebo- and Active-Controlled Trial 
                                Placebo                    MOBIC7.5 mg daily          MOBIC15 mg daily           Diclofenac100 mg daily       
     No. of Patients            157                        154                        156                        153                     
  
   1  WHO preferred terms edema, edema dependent, edema peripheral, and edema legs combined  2  WHO preferred terms rash, rash erythematous, and rash maculo-papular combined   
  
     Gastrointestinal       17.2                       20.1                       17.3                       28.1                        
 Abdominal pain             2.5                        1.9                        2.6                        1.3                         
 Diarrhea                   3.8                        7.8                        3.2                        9.2                         
 Dyspepsia                  4.5                        4.5                        4.5                        6.5                         
 Flatulence                 4.5                        3.2                        3.2                        3.9                         
 Nausea                     3.2                        3.9                        3.8                        7.2                         
     Body as a Whole                                                                                                                     
 Accident household         1.9                        4.5                        3.2                        2.6                         
 Edema  1                   2.5                        1.9                        4.5                        3.3                         
 Fall                       0.6                        2.6                        0.0                        1.3                         
 Influenza-like symptoms    5.1                        4.5                        5.8                        2.6                         
     Central and PeripheralNervous System       
 Dizziness                  3.2                        2.6                        3.8                        2.0                         
 Headache                   10.2                       7.8                        8.3                        5.9                         
     Respiratory                                                                                                                         
 Pharyngitis                1.3                        0.6                        3.2                        1.3                         
 Upper respiratory tract infection  1.9                        3.2                        1.9                        3.3                         
     Skin                                                                                                                                
 Rash  2                    2.5                        2.6                        0.6                        2.0                         
     Table 1b Adverse Events (%) Occurring in &gt;=2% of MOBIC Patients in two 12-Week Rheumatoid Arthritis Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                                Placebo                    MOBIC7.5 mg daily          MOBIC15 mg daily        
     No. of Patients            469                        481                        477                     
  
   1   MedDRA high level term (preferred terms): dyspeptic signs and symptoms (dyspepsia, dyspepsia aggravated, eructation, gastrointestinal irritation), upper respiratory tract infections-pathogen unspecified (laryngitis NOS, pharyngitis NOS, sinusitis NOS), joint related signs and symptoms (arthralgia, arthralgia aggravated, joint crepitation, joint effusion, joint swelling)  2   MedDRA preferred term: nausea, abdominal pain NOS, influenza-like illness, headaches NOS, and rash NOS   
  
     Gastrointestinal Disorders      14.1                       18.9                       16.8                        
 Abdominal pain NOS  2      0.6                        2.9                        2.3                         
 Dyspeptic signs and symptoms  1    3.8                        5.8                        4.0                         
 Nausea  2                  2.6                        3.3                        3.8                         
     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions       
 Influenza-like illness  2    2.1                        2.9                        2.3                         
     Infection and Infestations    Upper respiratory tract infections-pathogen class unspecified  1    4.1                        7.0                        6.5                         
     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    Joint related signs and symptoms  1    1.9                        1.5                        2.3                         
     Nervous System Disorders       
 Headaches NOS  2           6.4                        6.4                        5.5                         
     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    Rash NOS  2    1.7                        1.0                        2.1                         
      The adverse events that occurred with MOBIC in &gt;=2% of patients treated short-term (4 to 6 weeks) and long-term (6 months) in active-controlled osteoarthritis trials are presented in Table 2.
 

 Table 2 Adverse Events (%) Occurring in &gt;=2% of MOBIC Patients in 4 to 6 Weeks and 6 Month Active-Controlled Osteoarthritis Trials 
                                4 to 6 Weeks Controlled Trials          6 Month Controlled Trials       
                                MOBIC7.5 mg daily          MOBIC15 mg daily           MOBIC7.5 mg daily          MOBIC15 mg daily        
     No. of Patients            8955                       256                        169                        306                     
  
   1  WHO preferred terms edema, edema dependent, edema peripheral, and edema legs combined  2  WHO preferred terms rash, rash erythematous, and rash maculo-papular combined   
  
     Gastrointestinal       11.8                       18.0                       26.6                       24.2                        
 Abdominal pain             2.7                        2.3                        4.7                        2.9                         
 Constipation               0.8                        1.2                        1.8                        2.6                         
 Diarrhea                   1.9                        2.7                        5.9                        2.6                         
 Dyspepsia                  3.8                        7.4                        8.9                        9.5                         
 Flatulence                 0.5                        0.4                        3.0                        2.6                         
 Nausea                     2.4                        4.7                        4.7                        7.2                         
 Vomiting                   0.6                        0.8                        1.8                        2.6                         
     Body as a Whole                                                                                                                     
 Accident household         0.0                        0.0                        0.6                        2.9                         
 Edema  1                   0.6                        2.0                        2.4                        1.6                         
 Pain                       0.9                        2.0                        3.6                        5.2                         
     Central and PeripheralNervous System                                                                                                                   
 Dizziness                  1.1                        1.6                        2.4                        2.6                         
 Headache                   2.4                        2.7                        3.6                        2.6                         
     Hematologic                                                                                                                         
 Anemia                     0.1                        0.0                        4.1                        2.9                         
     Musculoskeletal                                                                                                                     
 Arthralgia                 0.5                        0.0                        5.3                        1.3                         
 Back pain                  0.5                        0.4                        3.0                        0.7                         
     Psychiatric                                                                                                                         
 Insomnia                   0.4                        0.0                        3.6                        1.6                         
     Respiratory                                                                                                                         
 Coughing                   0.2                        0.8                        2.4                        1.0                         
 Upper respiratory tract infection  0.2                        0.0                        8.3                        7.5                         
     Skin                                                                                                                                
 Pruritus                   0.4                        1.2                        2.4                        0.0                         
 Rash  2                    0.3                        1.2                        3.0                        1.3                         
     Urinary                                                                                                                             
 Micturition frequency      0.1                        0.4                        2.4                        1.3                         
 Urinary tract infection    0.3                        0.4                        4.7                        6.9                         
      Higher doses of MOBIC (22.5 mg and greater) have been associated with an increased risk of serious GI events; therefore, the daily dose of MOBIC should not exceed 15 mg.
 

     Pediatrics  

  

      Pauciarticular and Polyarticular Course Juvenile Rheumatoid Arthritis (JRA)    



 Three hundred and eighty-seven patients with pauciarticular and polyarticular course JRA were exposed to MOBIC with doses ranging from 0.125 to 0.375 mg/kg per day in three clinical trials. These studies consisted of two 12-week multicenter, double-blind, randomized trials (one with a 12-week open-label extension and one with a 40-week extension) and one 1-year open-label PK study. The adverse events observed in these pediatric studies with MOBIC were similar in nature to the adult clinical trial experience, although there were differences in frequency. In particular, the following most common adverse events, abdominal pain, vomiting, diarrhea, headache, and pyrexia, were more common in the pediatric than in the adult trials. Rash was reported in seven (&lt;2%) patients receiving MOBIC. No unexpected adverse events were identified during the course of the trials. The adverse events did not demonstrate an age or gender-specific subgroup effect.



 The following is a list of adverse drug reactions occurring in &lt;2% of patients receiving MOBIC in clinical trials involving approximately 16,200 patients.




     Body as a Whole             allergic reaction, face edema, fatigue, fever, hot flushes, malaise, syncope, weight decrease, weight increase   
     Cardiovascular              angina pectoris, cardiac failure, hypertension, hypotension, myocardial infarction, vasculitis   
     Central and Peripheral Nervous System      convulsions, paresthesia, tremor, vertigo                                
     Gastrointestinal            colitis, dry mouth, duodenal ulcer, eructation, esophagitis, gastric ulcer, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hematemesis, hemorrhagic duodenal ulcer, hemorrhagic gastric ulcer, intestinal perforation, melena, pancreatitis, perforated duodenal ulcer, perforated gastric ulcer, stomatitis ulcerative   
     Heart Rate and Rhythm       arrhythmia, palpitation, tachycardia                                     
     Hematologic                 leukopenia, purpura, thrombocytopenia                                    
     Liver and Biliary System      ALT increased, AST increased, bilirubinemia, GGT increased, hepatitis    
     Metabolic and Nutritional      dehydration                                                              
     Psychiatric                 abnormal dreaming, anxiety, appetite increased, confusion, depression, nervousness, somnolence   
     Respiratory                 asthma, bronchospasm, dyspnea                                            
     Skin and Appendages         alopecia, angioedema, bullous eruption, photosensitivity reaction, pruritus, sweating increased, urticaria   
     Special Senses              abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, taste perversion, tinnitus              
     Urinary System              albuminuria, BUN increased, creatinine increased, hematuria, renal failure   
        6.2  Post Marketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of MOBIC. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions about whether to include an adverse event from spontaneous reports in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the event, (2) number of reports, or (3) strength of causal relationship to the drug. Adverse reactions reported in worldwide post marketing experience or the literature include: acute urinary retention; agranulocytosis; alterations in mood (such as mood elevation); anaphylactoid reactions including shock; erythema multiforme; exfoliative dermatitis; interstitial nephritis; jaundice; liver failure; Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS

CARDIOVASCULAR and GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS

  WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS

CARDIOVASCULAR and GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS

  



 Cardiovascular Risk  *  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  MOBIC is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery [see Contraindications (4.2) and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
   Gastrointestinal Risk  *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse reactions including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:       WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR and
 GASTROINTESTINAL RISKS    



       See full prescribing

information for complete boxed warning.      



 Cardiovascular Risk  *  NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. (5.1) 
 *  MOBIC is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery (4.2, 5.1) 
   Gastrointestinal Risk  *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious and potentially fatal cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke. Patients with known CV disease/risk factors may be at greater risk.  (5.1)   
 *  Serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events which can be fatal. The risk is greater in patients with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding, and in patients at higher risk for GI events, especially the elderly.  (5.2)   
 *  Elevated liver enzymes, and rarely, severe hepatic reactions. Discontinue use immediately if abnormal liver enzymes persist or worsen.  (5.3)   
 *  New onset or worsening of hypertension. Blood pressure should be monitored closely during treatment.  (5.4)   
 *  Fluid retention and edema. Should be used with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure.  (5.5)   
 *  Renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury with long-term use. Use with caution in the elderly, those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, and those taking diuretics, ACE-inhibitors, or angiotensin II antagonists. The use of MOBIC in patients with severe renal impairment is not recommended.  (5.6)   
 *  Serious skin adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal and can occur without warning. Discontinue MOBIC at first appearance of rash or skin reactions.  (5.8)   
    
 

   5.1  Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years' duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Patients should be informed about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 Two large, controlled, clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10 to 14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke [  see Contraindications  (4.2)      ].



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID does increase the risk of serious GI events [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)      ].



    5.2  Gastrointestinal (GI) Effects - Risk of GI Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including MOBIC, can cause serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs, occur in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3 to 6 months, and in about 2% to 4% of patients treated for one year. These trends continue with longer duration of use, increasing the likelihood of developing a serious GI event at some time during the course of therapy. However, even short-term therapy is not without risk.



 Prescribe NSAIDs, including MOBIC, with extreme caution in those with a prior history of ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or gastrointestinal bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing a GI bleed compared to patients with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk for GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants, longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most spontaneous reports of fatal GI events are in elderly or debilitated patients and therefore, special care should be taken in treating this population.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest possible duration. Patients and physicians should remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulceration and bleeding during MOBIC therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI adverse event is suspected. This should include discontinuation of MOBIC until a serious GI adverse event is ruled out. For high-risk patients, consider alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs.



    5.3  Hepatic Effects



  Borderline elevations of one or more liver tests may occur in up to 15% of patients taking NSAIDs including MOBIC. These laboratory abnormalities may progress, may remain unchanged, or may be transient with continuing therapy. Notable elevations of ALT or AST (approximately three or more times the upper limit of normal) have been reported in approximately 1% of patients in clinical trials with NSAIDs. In addition, rare cases of severe hepatic reactions, including jaundice and fatal fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis and hepatic failure, some of them with fatal outcomes have been reported [  see Adverse Reactions  (6.1)      ].



 A patient with symptoms and/or signs suggesting liver dysfunction, or in whom an abnormal liver test has occurred, should be evaluated for evidence of the development of a more severe hepatic reaction while on therapy with MOBIC. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.), discontinue MOBIC [  see Use in Specific Populations  (8.6)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].



    5.4  Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including MOBIC, can lead to onset of new hypertension or worsening of pre-existing hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. NSAIDs, including MOBIC, should be used with caution in patients with hypertension. Blood pressure (BP) should be monitored closely during the initiation of NSAID treatment and throughout the course of therapy.



 Patients taking ACE inhibitors, thiazides, or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs.



    5.5  Congestive Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention and edema have been observed in some patients taking NSAIDs. Use MOBIC with caution in patients with fluid retention, hypertension, or heart failure.



    5.6  Renal Effects



  Long-term administration of NSAIDs, including MOBIC, can result in renal papillary necrosis, renal insufficiency, acute renal failure, and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics, ACE-inhibitors, and angiotensin II receptor antagonists, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



 A pharmacokinetic study in patients with mild and moderate renal impairment revealed that no dosage adjustments in these patient populations are required. Patients with severe renal impairment have not been studied. The use of MOBIC in patients with severe renal impairment with CrCl less than 20 mL/min is not recommended. A study performed in patients on hemodialysis revealed that although overall Cmaxwas diminished in this population, the proportion of free drug not bound to plasma was increased. Therefore it is recommended that meloxicam dosage in this population not exceed 7.5 mg per day. Closely monitor the renal function of patients with impaired renal function who are taking MOBIC [  see Dosage and Administration  (2.1)  , Use in Specific Populations  (8.7)  , and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ].



 Use caution when initiating treatment with MOBIC in patients with considerable dehydration. It is advisable to rehydrate patients first and then start therapy with MOBIC. Caution is also recommended in patients with pre-existing kidney disease.



 The extent to which metabolites may accumulate in patients with renal impairment has not been studied with MOBIC. Because some MOBIC metabolites are excreted by the kidney, monitor patients with significant renal impairment closely.



    5.7  Anaphylactoid Reactions



  As with other NSAIDs, anaphylactoid reactions have occurred in patients without known prior exposure to MOBIC. MOBIC should not be given to patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [  see Contraindications  (4.1)  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.12)      ]. Seek emergency help in cases where an anaphylactoid reaction occurs.



    5.8  Adverse Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs, including MOBIC, can cause serious skin adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations and discontinue use of the drug at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity.



    5.9  Pregnancy



  Starting at 30 weeks gestation, avoid the use of MOBIC because it may cause premature closure of the ductus arteriosus [  see Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  and Patient Counseling Information  (17.8)      ].



    5.10  Corticosteroid Treatment



  MOBIC cannot be expected to substitute for corticosteroids or to treat corticosteroid insufficiency. Abrupt discontinuation of corticosteroids may lead to disease exacerbation. Slowly taper patients on prolonged corticosteroid therapy if a decision is made to discontinue corticosteroids.



    5.11  Masking of Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of MOBIC in reducing fever and inflammation may diminish the utility of these diagnostic signs in detecting complications of presumed noninfectious, painful conditions.



    5.12  Hematological Effects



  Anemia may occur in patients receiving NSAIDs, including MOBIC. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs, including MOBIC, should have their hemoglobin or hematocrit checked if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia.



 NSAIDs inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effect on platelet function is quantitatively less, of shorter duration, and reversible. Carefully monitor patients treated with MOBIC who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants.



    5.13  Use in Patients with Pre-existing Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm, which can be fatal. Since cross reactivity, including bronchospasm, between aspirin and other NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, MOBIC should not be administered to patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and should be used with caution in patients with pre-existing asthma.



    5.14  Monitoring



  Because serious GI tract ulcerations and bleeding can occur without warning symptoms, physicians should monitor for signs or symptoms of GI bleeding. Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs should have their CBC and a chemistry profile checked periodically. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver or renal disease develop, systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.) or if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, MOBIC should be discontinued.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
