<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="montelukast" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and greater than placebo listed in descending order of frequency): upper respiratory infection, fever, headache, pharyngitis, cough, abdominal pain, diarrhea, otitis media, influenza, rhinorrhea, sinusitis, otitis (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. In the following description of clinical trials experience, adverse reactions are listed regardless of causality assessment.



 The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and greater than placebo; listed in descending order of frequency) in controlled clinical trials were: upper respiratory infection, fever, headache, pharyngitis, cough, abdominal pain, diarrhea, otitis media, influenza, rhinorrhea, sinusitis, otitis.



     Adults and Adolescents 15 Years of Age and Older with Asthma  



 Montelukast sodium has been evaluated for safety in approximately 2950 adult and adolescent patients 15 years of age and older in clinical trials. In placebo-controlled clinical trials, the following adverse experiences reported with montelukast sodium occurred in greater than or equal to 1% of patients and at an incidence greater than that in patients treated with placebo:



 Table 1: Adverse Experiences Occurring in &gt;=1% of Patients with an Incidence Greater than that in Patients Treated with Placebo 
                                                     Montelukast Sodium10 mg/day(%)(n=1955)     Placebo (%)(n=1180)      
  
   Body As A Whole                                                                                          
   Pain, abdominal                                              2.9                        2.5              
   Asthenia/fatigue                                             1.8                        1.2              
   Fever                                                        1.5                        0.9              
   Trauma                                                       1.0                        0.8              
   Digestive System Disorders                                                                               
   Dyspepsia                                                    2.1                        1.1              
   Pain, dental                                                 1.7                        1.0              
   Gastroenteritis, infectious                                  1.5                        0.5              
   Nervous System/Psychiatric                                                                               
   Headache                                                    18.4                       18.1              
   Dizziness                                                    1.9                        1.4              
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                             
   Influenza                                                    4.2                        3.9              
   Cough                                                        2.7                        2.4              
   Congestion, nasal                                            1.6                        1.3              
   Skin/Skin Appendages Disorder                                                                            
   Rash                                                         1.6                        1.2              
   Laboratory Adverse Experiences                                                                           
   ALT increased                                                2.1                        2.0              
   AST increased                                                1.6                        1.2              
   Pyuria                                                       1.0                        0.9              
         The frequency of less common adverse events was comparable between montelukast sodium and placebo.
 

 The safety profile of montelukast sodium, when administered as a single dose for prevention of EIB in adult and adolescent patients 15 years of age and older, was consistent with the safety profile previously described for montelukast sodium.



 Cumulatively, 569 patients were treated with montelukast sodium for at least 6 months, 480 for one year, and 49 for two years in clinical trials. With prolonged treatment, the adverse experience profile did not significantly change.



     Pediatric Patients 6 to 14 Years of Age with Asthma  



 Montelukast sodium has been evaluated for safety in 476 pediatric patients 6 to 14 years of age. Cumulatively, 289 pediatric patients were treated with montelukast sodium for at least 6 months, and 241 for one year or longer in clinical trials. The safety profile of montelukast sodium in the 8-week, double-blind, pediatric efficacy trial was generally similar to the adult safety profile. In pediatric patients 6 to 14 years of age receiving montelukast sodium, the following events occurred with a frequency &gt;=2% and more frequently than in pediatric patients who received placebo: pharyngitis, influenza, fever, sinusitis, nausea, diarrhea, dyspepsia, otitis, viral infection, and laryngitis. The frequency of less common adverse events was comparable between montelukast sodium and placebo. With prolonged treatment, the adverse experience profile did not significantly change.



 The safety profile of montelukast sodium, when administered as a single dose for prevention of EIB in pediatric patients 6 years of age and older, was consistent with the safety profile previously described for montelukast sodium.



 In studies evaluating growth rate, the safety profile in these pediatric patients was consistent with the safety profile previously described for montelukast sodium. In a 56-week, double-blind study evaluating growth rate in pediatric patients 6 to 8 years of age receiving montelukast sodium, the following events not previously observed with the use of montelukast sodium in this age group occurred with a frequency &gt;=2% and more frequently than in pediatric patients who received placebo: headache, rhinitis (infective), varicella, gastroenteritis, atopic dermatitis, acute bronchitis, tooth infection, skin infection, and myopia.



     Pediatric Patients 2 to 5 Years of Age with Asthma  



 Montelukast sodium has been evaluated for safety in 573 pediatric patients 2 to 5 years of age in single- and multiple-dose studies. Cumulatively, 426 pediatric patients 2 to 5 years of age were treated with montelukast sodium for at least 3 months, 230 for 6 months or longer, and 63 patients for one year or longer in clinical trials. In pediatric patients 2 to 5 years of age receiving montelukast sodium, the following events occurred with a frequency &gt;=2% and more frequently than in pediatric patients who received placebo: fever, cough, abdominal pain, diarrhea, headache, rhinorrhea, sinusitis, otitis, influenza, rash, ear pain, gastroenteritis, eczema, urticaria, varicella, pneumonia, dermatitis, and conjunctivitis.



     Pediatric Patients 6 to 23 Months of Age with Asthma  



 Safety and effectiveness in pediatric patients younger than 12 months of age with asthma have not been established.



 Montelukast sodium has been evaluated for safety in 175 pediatric patients 6 to 23 months of age. The safety profile of montelukast sodium in a 6-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical study was generally similar to the safety profile in adults and pediatric patients 2 to 14 years of age. In pediatric patients 6 to 23 months of age receiving montelukast sodium, the following events occurred with a frequency &gt;=2% and more frequently than in pediatric patients who received placebo: upper respiratory infection, wheezing; otitis media; pharyngitis, tonsillitis, cough; and rhinitis. The frequency of less common adverse events was comparable between montelukast sodium and placebo.



     Adults and Adolescents 15 Years of Age and Older with Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis  



 Montelukast sodium has been evaluated for safety in 2199 adult and adolescent patients 15 years of age and older in clinical trials. Montelukast sodium administered once daily in the morning or in the evening had a safety profile similar to that of placebo. In placebo-controlled clinical trials, the following event was reported with montelukast sodium with a frequency &gt;=1% and at an incidence greater than placebo: upper respiratory infection, 1.9% of patients receiving montelukast sodium vs. 1.5% of patients receiving placebo. In a 4-week, placebo-controlled clinical study, the safety profile was consistent with that observed in 2-week studies. The incidence of somnolence was similar to that of placebo in all studies.



     Pediatric Patients 2 to 14 Years of Age with Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis  



 Montelukast sodium has been evaluated in 280 pediatric patients 2 to 14 years of age in a 2-week, multicenter, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group safety study. Montelukast sodium administered once daily in the evening had a safety profile similar to that of placebo. In this study, the following events occurred with a frequency &gt;=2% and at an incidence greater than placebo: headache, otitis media, pharyngitis, and upper respiratory infection.



     Adults and Adolescents 15 Years of Age and Older with Perennial Allergic Rhinitis  



 Montelukast sodium has been evaluated for safety in 3357 adult and adolescent patients 15 years of age and older with perennial allergic rhinitis of whom 1632 received montelukast sodium in two, 6-week, clinical studies. Montelukast sodium administered once daily had a safety profile consistent with that observed in patients with seasonal allergic rhinitis and similar to that of placebo. In these two studies, the following events were reported with montelukast sodium with a frequency &gt;=1% and at an incidence greater than placebo: sinusitis, upper respiratory infection, sinus headache, cough, epistaxis, and increased ALT. The incidence of somnolence was similar to that of placebo.



     Pediatric Patients 6 Months to 14 Years of Age with Perennial Allergic Rhinitis  



 The safety in patients 2 to 14 years of age with perennial allergic rhinitis is supported by the safety in patients 2 to 14 years of age with seasonal allergic rhinitis. The safety in patients 6 to 23 months of age is supported by data from pharmacokinetic and safety and efficacy studies in asthma in this pediatric population and from adult pharmacokinetic studies.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of montelukast sodium. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Blood and lymphatic system disorders: increased bleeding tendency, thrombocytopenia.



 Immune system disorders: hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, hepatic eosinophilic infiltration.



 Psychiatric disorders: agitation including aggressive behavior or hostility, anxiousness, depression, disorientation, disturbance in attention, dream abnormalities, hallucinations, insomnia, irritability, memory impairment, restlessness, somnambulism, suicidal thinking and behavior (including suicide), and tremor  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  .



 Nervous system disorders: drowsiness, paraesthesia/hypoesthesia, seizures.



 Cardiac disorders: palpitations.



 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders: epistaxis, pulmonary eosinophilia.



 Gastrointestinal disorders: diarrhea, dyspepsia, nausea, pancreatitis, vomiting.



 Hepatobiliary disorders: Cases of cholestatic hepatitis, hepatocellular liver-injury, and mixed-pattern liver injury have been reported in patients treated with montelukast sodium. Most of these occurred in combination with other confounding factors, such as use of other medications, or when montelukast sodium was administered to patients who had underlying potential for liver disease such as alcohol use or other forms of hepatitis.



 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders: angioedema, bruising, erythema multiforme, erythema nodosum, pruritus, Stevens-Johnson syndrome/toxic epidermal necrolysis, urticaria.



 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders: arthralgia, myalgia including muscle cramps.



 Renal and urinary disorders: enuresis in children.



 General disorders and administration site conditions: edema.



 Patients with asthma on therapy with montelukast sodium may present with systemic eosinophilia, sometimes presenting with clinical features of vasculitis consistent with Churg-Strauss syndrome, a condition which is often treated with systemic corticosteroid therapy. These events have been sometimes associated with the reduction of oral corticosteroid therapy. Physicians should be alert to eosinophilia, vasculitic rash, worsening pulmonary symptoms, cardiac complications, and/or neuropathy presenting in their patients  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Do not prescribe montelukast sodium to treat an acute asthma attack (  5.1  ). 
 *  Advise patients to have appropriate rescue medication available (  5.1  ). 
 *  Inhaled corticosteroid may be reduced gradually. Do not abruptly substitute montelukast sodium for inhaled or oral corticosteroids (  5.2  ). 
 *  Patients with known aspirin sensitivity should continue to avoid aspirin or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents while taking montelukast sodium (  5.3  ). 
 *  Neuropsychiatric events have been reported with montelukast sodium. Instruct patients to be alert for neuropsychiatric events. Evaluate the risks and benefits of continuing treatment with montelukast sodium if such events occur (  5.4  and  6.2  ). 
 *  Systemic eosinophilia, sometimes presenting with clinical features of vasculitis consistent with Churg-Strauss syndrome, has been reported. These events have been sometimes associated with the reduction of oral corticosteroid therapy (  5.5  and  6.2  ). 
 *  Inform patients with phenylketonuria that the 4-mg and 5-mg chewable tablets contain phenylalanine (  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Asthma



  Montelukast sodium is not indicated for use in the reversal of bronchospasm in acute asthma attacks, including status asthmaticus. Patients should be advised to have appropriate rescue medication available. Therapy with montelukast sodium can be continued during acute exacerbations of asthma. Patients who have exacerbations of asthma after exercise should have available for rescue a short-acting inhaled beta-agonist.



    5.2 Concomitant Corticosteroid Use



  While the dose of inhaled corticosteroid may be reduced gradually under medical supervision, montelukast sodium should not be abruptly substituted for inhaled or oral corticosteroids.



    5.3 Aspirin Sensitivity



  Patients with known aspirin sensitivity should continue avoidance of aspirin or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents while taking montelukast sodium. Although montelukast sodium is effective in improving airway function in asthmatics with documented aspirin sensitivity, it has not been shown to truncate bronchoconstrictor response to aspirin and other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs in aspirin-sensitive asthmatic patients [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  .



    5.4 Neuropsychiatric Events



  Neuropsychiatric events have been reported in adult, adolescent, and pediatric patients taking montelukast sodium. Post-marketing reports with montelukast sodium use include agitation, aggressive behavior or hostility, anxiousness, depression, disorientation, disturbance in attention, dream abnormalities, hallucinations, insomnia, irritability, memory impairment, restlessness, somnambulism, suicidal thinking and behavior (including suicide), and tremor. The clinical details of some post-marketing reports involving montelukast sodium appear consistent with a drug-induced effect.



 Patients and prescribers should be alert for neuropsychiatric events. Patients should be instructed to notify their prescriber if these changes occur. Prescribers should carefully evaluate the risks and benefits of continuing treatment with montelukast sodium if such events occur [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.5 Eosinophilic Conditions



  Patients with asthma on therapy with montelukast sodium may present with systemic eosinophilia, sometimes presenting with clinical features of vasculitis consistent with Churg-Strauss syndrome, a condition which is often treated with systemic corticosteroid therapy. These events have been sometimes associated with the reduction of oral corticosteroid therapy. Physicians should be alert to eosinophilia, vasculitic rash, worsening pulmonary symptoms, cardiac complications, and/or neuropathy presenting in their patients. A causal association between montelukast sodium and these underlying conditions has not been established [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.6 Phenylketonuria



  Phenylketonuric patients should be informed that the 4-mg and 5-mg chewable tablets contain phenylalanine (a component of aspartame), 0.674 and 0.842 mg per 4-mg and 5-mg chewable tablet, respectively.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
