<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="morphine3" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions associated with morphine sulfate use include: respiratory depression, apnea, and to a lesser degree, circulatory depression, respiratory arrest, shock and cardiac arrest.



 The common adverse reactions seen on initiation of therapy with morphine sulfate are dose-dependent and are typical opioid-related side effects. The most frequent of these include constipation, nausea, and somnolence. Other commonly observed adverse reactions include: lightheadedness, dizziness, sedation, vomiting, and sweating. The frequency of these events depends upon several factors including clinical setting, the patient's level of opioid tolerance, and host factors specific to the individual. Anticipate and manage these events as part of opioid analgesia therapy.



 Other less frequently observed adverse reactions expected from opioid analgesics, including morphine sulfate include:



 : malaise, withdrawal syndrome  Body as a Whole  



 : bradycardia, hypertension, hypotension, palpitations, syncope, tachycardia  Cardiovascular System  



 : anorexia, biliary pain, dyspepsia, dysphagia, gastroenteritis, abnormal liver function tests, rectal disorder, thirst  Digestive System  



 hypogonadism  Endocrine:  



 : anemia, thrombocytopenia  Hemic and Lymphatic System  



 : edema, weight loss  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  



 : skeletal muscle rigidity, decreased bone mineral density  Musculoskeletal  



 : abnormal dreams, abnormal gait, agitation, amnesia, anxiety, ataxia, confusion, convulsions, coma, delirium, depression, dry mouth, euphoria, hallucinations, lethargy, nervousness, abnormal thinking, tremor, vasodilation, vertigo, headache  Nervous System  



 : hiccup, hypoventilation, voice alteration  Respiratory System  



 : dry skin, urticaria, pruritus  Skin and Appendages  



 : amblyopia, eye pain, taste perversion  Special Senses  



 : abnormal ejaculation, dysuria, impotence, decreased libido, oliguria, urinary retention or hesitancy, anti-diuretic effect, amenorrhea  Urogenital System  



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are constipation, nausea, somnolence, lightheadedness, dizziness, sedation, vomiting, sweating. ( )  6  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Roxane Laboratories, Inc. at (614) 276-4000 or Technical Product Information (800) 962-8364 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF MEDICATION ERRORS

  WARNING: RISK OF MEDICATION ERRORS

    Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is available in 10 mg per 5 mL, 20 mg per 5 mL and 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) concentrations.  



   The 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) concentration is indicated for use in opioid-tolerant patients only.  



   Take care when prescribing and administering Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between different concentrations and between mg and mL, which could result in accidental overdose and death. Take care to ensure the proper dose is communicated and dispensed.  



   Keep Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution out of the reach of children. In case of accidental ingestion, seek emergency medical help immediately.  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF MEDICATION ERRORS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is available in 10 mg per 5 mL, 20 mg per 5 mL and 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) concentrations. The 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) concentration is indicated for use in opioid-tolerant patients only.  



   Take care to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between different concentration and between mg and mL, which could result in accidental overdose and death. (5.1)  



   Keep Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution out of the reach of children.  



 









    BOXED WARNING: Medication Guide

  Medication Guide

    MORPHINE SULFATE (mor-pheen) (CII)  



   Oral Solution  



   

  .

                                      IMPORTANT: Keep Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution in a safe place away from children. Accidental use by a child is a medical emergency and can cause death. If a child accidentally takes Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, get emergency help right away  



   Read the Medication Guide that comes with Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution before you start taking it and each time you get a new prescription. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking with your healthcare provider about your medical condition or your treatment.



   What is the most important information I should know about Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  



   Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution can cause serious side effects, including death.  



 *  Take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution exactly as prescribed by your healthcare provider. If you take the wrong dose or strength of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, you could overdose and die. 
 *  It is especially important when you take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution that you know exactly what dose and strength to take, and the right way to measure your medicine. Your healthcare provider or pharmacist should show you the right way to measure your medicine. 
 *  Always use the oral syringe provided with Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) to help make sure you measure the right amount. 
 *  The oral solution comes in several different doses (amount of medicine per mL) and strengths (number of mgs). 
 *  Do not take the strongest dose of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL), unless you are "opioid tolerant." Opioid tolerant means that you have been regularly using Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution or another opioid medicine for your constant (around the clock) pain and your body is used to it. 
 *      
      What is Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  
 

 Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is in a group of drugs called narcotic pain relievers. Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is only for adults who have moderate to severe pain.



 *  Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is a prescription medicine that is used to manage moderate to severe pain that is expected to last a short period of time (acute), and pain that continues around-the-clock and is expected to last for a long period of time (chronic).  
 *  Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is a federally controlled substance (CII) because it is a strong opioid pain medicine that can be abused by people who abuse prescription medicines or street drugs.  
 *  Prevent theft, misuse or abuse. Keep Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution in a safe place to keep it from being stolen. Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution can be a target for people who misuse or abuse prescription medicines or street drugs.  
 *  Never give Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution to anyone else, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them or even cause death.  
 *  Selling or giving away this medicine is against the law.  
 *  It is not known if Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is safe and effective in children under age 18 years of age.  
 *  Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) is only for adults with moderate to severe pain who are already using an opioid narcotic pain medicine and have been using this medicine continuously for several weeks or longer.  
     
 

   Who should not take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  



 *  Do not take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution if you: See the end of this Medication guide for a complete list of ingredients in Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution. are allergic to morphine, morphine salts or any of the ingredients in Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution.are having an asthma attack or have severe asthma, trouble breathing, or lung problems have a bowel blockage called paralytic ileus  
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  
 

 *  Before taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, tell your healthcare provider if you:have trouble breathing or lung problems have had a head injury have liver or kidney problems have had adrenal gland problems, such as Addison's disease have severe scoliosis that affects your breathing have thyroid problems have problems urinating or enlargement of your prostate have had convulsions or seizures have a past or present drinking problem or alcoholism have severe mental problems or hallucinations (seeing or hearing things that are not really there). have constipation or other bowel problems have problems with your pancreas or gallbladder have past or present substance abuse or drug addiction plan to have surgery have any other medical conditions are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. It is not known if Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution will harm your unborn baby. Talk to your healthcare provider if you are pregnant or plan to become pregnant.  
    If you take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution regularly before your baby is born, your newborn baby may have withdrawal symptoms because their body has become used to the medicine. Symptoms of withdrawal in a newborn baby may include:
 

 *    irritability being very active problems sleeping high pitched cry shaking (tremors) vomiting diarrhea or more stools than normal weight loss fever  
    If you take Morphine Sulfate right before your baby is born, your baby could have breathing problems.
 

 *   are breast-feeding or plan to breast-feed. Some Morphine Sulfate passes into your breast milk. A nursing baby could become very sleepy and have problems breathing or feeding well. If you stop breast-feeding, your baby may have withdrawal symptoms. See the list of withdrawal symptoms above. You and your healthcare provider should decide if you will take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution or breast-feed.  
     
 

 , including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Sometimes the doses of medicines that you take with Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution may need to be changed if used together. Be especially careful about taking other medicines that make you sleepy such as:

                                      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take  



 *   sleeping pills other pain medicines anti-nausea medicines tranquilizers muscle relaxants antihistamines anti-anxiety medicines anti-depressants anticholinergic medicines antibiotic or antifungal medicines heart medicines anti-seizure medicines  
 *  Tell your healthcare provider if you take cimetidine (Tagamet).  
 *  Do not take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution if you already take a monoamine oxidase inhibitor medicine (MAOI) or within 14 days after you stop taking an MAOI medicine.  
 *  Do not take any new medicine while using Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution until you have talked with your healthcare provider or pharmacist. They will tell you if it is safe to take other medicines with Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution.  
    Ask your healthcare provider if you are not sure if your medicine is one listed above.
 

   Know the medicines you take. Keep a list of them and show it to your healthcare provider and pharmacist when you get a new medicine.  



   How should I take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  



 *  See "What is the most important information I should know about Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?" 
 *  . Do not change your dose unless your healthcare provider tells you to. Your healthcare provider may change your dose after seeing how the medicine affects you. Call your healthcare provider if your pain is not well controlled with your prescribed dose of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution.  Take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution exactly as prescribed 
 *  . You can take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution with or without food 
 *  . Always use the oral syringe provided with your Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) to help make sure you measure the right amount. See the Instructions for Use at the end of this Medication Guide for information about how to measure your dose the right way. Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure what dose of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution you should take or if you are not sure how to use the oral syringe. Make sure you understand exactly how to measure your dose 
 *  If you have been taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution for more than a few weeks, stopping Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution suddenly can make you sick with withdrawal symptoms (for example, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anxiety, and shivering). If your healthcare provider decides you no longer need Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, ask how to slowly reduce this medicine. Do not stop taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution without talking to your healthcare provider. Do not stop taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution suddenly. 
 *  you can take the dose when you remember it if you have pain, or you can wait for the next dose. If you miss one dose of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution 
    Talk with your healthcare provider regularly about your pain to see if you still need to take Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution.
 

   What should I avoid while taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  



 *  You should not drink alcohol while using Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution. Drinking alcohol with Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution may increase your risk of having dangerous side effects or death.  
 *  especially when you start taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution and when your dose is changed, until you know how Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution affects you. Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution can make you sleepy. Ask your healthcare provider to tell you when it is okay to do these activities. Do not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities, 
      What are the possible side effects of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  
 

 *  See "What is the most important information I should know about Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?" 
 *  Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution can cause serious breathing problems that can become life-threatening, especially if Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is used the wrong way. Call your healthcare provider or get help right away if: your breathing slows down you have shallow breathing (little chest movement with breathing) you feel faint, dizzy, confused, or you have any other unusual symptoms  
    These can be symptoms that you have taken too much Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution (overdose) or the dose is too high for you.
                                       These symptoms may lead to serious problems or death if not treated right away.  



 *  This can make you feel dizzy if you get up too fast from sitting or lying down. Low blood pressure is also more likely to happen if you take other medicines that can also lower your blood pressure. Severe low blood pressure can happen if you lose blood or take certain other medicines. Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution can cause your blood pressure to drop. 
 *  The chance is higher if you are or have been addicted to or abused other medicines, street drugs, or alcohol, or if you have a history of mental problems. There is a risk of abuse or addiction with Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution. 
 *  Do not stop taking Morphine Sulfate or any other opioid without talking to your healthcare provider about how to slowly stop your medicine. You could become sick with uncomfortable withdrawal symptoms because your body has become used to these medicines. Physical dependence is not the same as drug addiction. Tell your healthcare provider if you have any of these symptoms of withdrawal while slowly stopping Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution: Morphine Sulfate can cause physical dependence.feel restless tearing eyes runny nose yawning sweating chills or hair on your arms "stand up" muscle aches, backache dilated pupils of your eyes feel irritable or anxious trouble sleeping nausea, loss of appetite, vomiting, diarrhea, stomach-area (abdominal) cramps increase in your blood pressure faster breathing, or faster heart beats  
     
 

 *  Common side effects of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution include:constipation nausea sleepiness lightheadedness dizziness drowsiness vomiting sweating  
    Constipation (not often enough or hard bowel movements) is a very common side effect of pain medicines (opioids). Talk to your healthcare provider about dietary changes, and the use of laxatives (medicines to treat constipation) and stool softeners to prevent or treat constipation while taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution.
 

 Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away.



 These are not all the possible side effects of Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.



 Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.



   How should I store Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  



 *  Store Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution at 68o to 77o F (20o to 25o C).  
 *  After you stop taking Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, flush the unused oral solution down the toilet.  
 *  Keep Morphine Sulfate out of the reach of children. Accidental overdose by a child is a medical emergency and can lead to death. 
      General information about Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution for a condition for which it was not prescribed.

                                      Do not give your Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have. Selling or giving away Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution may harm others, may cause death, and is against the law.  



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You can ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for information about Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution that is written for healthcare professionals.



 For more information about Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution, go to or call Roxane Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-962-8364.

                                      www.roxane.com  



   What are the ingredients in Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution?  



 morphine sulfate USP

                                      Active ingredient:  



 citric acid, edetate disodium, glycerin, sodium benzoate, sorbitol, and water.

                                      Inactive ingredients:  



 *  The 10 mg/5 mL oral solution also contains: FD&amp;C Green No. 3 (fast green)  
 *  The 20 mg/5 mL oral solution also contains: FD&amp;C Green No. 3 (fast green), methylparaben, and propylparaben  
 *  The 100 mg per 5 mL tinted solution also contains D &amp; C Red No. 33 and sucralose.  
    This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.
 

 Roxane Laboratories, Inc.



 Columbus, Ohio 43216



   10008802/02 Revised February 2015  



 (c)RLI, 2015



   INSTRUCTIONS FOR USE  



   MORPHINE SULFATE ORAL SOLUTION 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL)  



   Oral Syringe  



   Important information about measuring Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution  



    Always use the oral syringe provided with your Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution to make sure you measure the right amount.  



    Measure the dose of medicine from the widest part of the plunger. Do not measure from the narrow tip. See figure 1  



 1. Insert the tip of the oral syringe into the medicine bottle.



 2. Pull back the plunger to the line that matches the dose prescribed by your healthcare provider.



 3. Remove the oral syringe from the medicine bottle.



 4. Take your medicine by slowly pushing the plunger until the oral syringe is empty.



   Figure 1  



  FIGURE 1 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Risk of Medication Errors: Use caution when prescribing, dispensing, and administering to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between different concentrations and between mg and mL, which could result in accidental overdose and death. ( )  5.1   
 *    Respiratory depression: Increased risk in elderly, debilitated patients, those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or upper airway obstruction. ( )  5.2   
 *    Controlled substance: Morphine sulfate is a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to other opioids. ( )  5.3   
 *    CNS effects: Additive CNS depressive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs. ( )  5.4   
 *    Elevation of intracranial pressure: May be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, other intracranial lesions. ( )  5.5   
 *    Hypotensive effect: Increased risk with compromised ability to maintain blood pressure. ( )  5.6   
 *    Prolonged gastric obstruction: In patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, especially paralytic ileus. ( )  5.7   
 *    Sphincter of Oddi spasm and diminished biliary/pancreatic secretions. Increased risk with biliary tract disease. ( )  5.8   
 *    Special Risk Groups: Use with caution and in reduced dosages in patients with severe renal or hepatic impairment, Addison's disease, hypothyroidism, prostatic hypertrophy, or urethral stricture, elderly, CNS depression, toxic psychosis, acute alcoholism and delirium tremens, may aggravate or induce seizures. ( )  5.9   
 *    Impaired mental/physical abilities: Caution must be used with potentially hazardous activities. ( )  5.10   
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Medication Errors



  Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution is available in 10 mg per 5 mL, 20 mg per 5 mL and 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) concentrations. Use caution when prescribing, dispensing, and administering Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between different concentrations and between mg and mL, which could result in accidental overdose and death. Use caution to ensure the dose is communicated clearly and dispensed accurately. Always use the enclosed calibrated oral syringe when administering Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) to ensure the dose is measured and administered accurately.



    5.2 Respiratory Depression



  Respiratory depression is the primary risk of morphine sulfate. Respiratory depression occurs more frequently in elderly or debilitated patients and in those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or upper airway obstruction, in whom even moderate therapeutic doses may significantly decrease pulmonary ventilation.



 Use morphine sulfate with extreme caution in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale and in patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve (e.g., severe kyphoscoliosis), hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression. In such patients, even usual therapeutic doses of morphine sulfate may increase airway resistance and decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea. Consider alternative non-opioid analgesics, and use morphine sulfate only under careful medical supervision at the lowest effective dose in such patients.



 Morphine sulfate 100 mg per 5 mL (20 mg/mL) oral solution is for use in . Administration of this formulation may cause fatal respiratory depression when administered to patients who are not tolerant to the respiratory depressant effects of opioids. opioid-tolerant patients only  



    5.3 Misuse, Abuse and Diversion of Opioids



  Morphine sulfate is an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance. Such drugs are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders. Diversion of Schedule II products is an act subject to criminal penalty.



 Morphine sulfate can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing morphine sulfate in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion.



 Morphine sulfate may be abused by inhaling or injecting the product. These practices pose a significant risk to the abuser that could result in overdose and death. [ ] See    DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE (9)  



 Concerns about abuse, addiction, and diversion should not prevent the proper management of pain. Healthcare professionals should contact their State Professional Licensing Board or State Controlled Substances Authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.4 Interactions with Alcohol and Drugs of Abuse



  Morphine sulfate may be expected to have additive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs that cause central nervous system depression because respiratory depression, hypotension, profound sedation, coma or death may result.



    5.5 Use In Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  In the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a preexisting increase in intracranial pressure, the possible respiratory depressant effects of morphine sulfate and its potential to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2 retention) may be markedly exaggerated. Furthermore, morphine sulfate can produce effects on pupillary response and consciousness, which may obscure neurologic signs of further increases in intracranial pressure in patients with head injuries.



    5.6 Hypotensive Effect



  Morphine sulfate may cause severe hypotension in an individual whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a depleted blood volume or concurrent administration of drugs such as phenothiazines or general anesthetics. Morphine sulfate may produce orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients.



 Administer morphine sulfate with caution to patients in circulatory shock, as vasodilation produced by the drug may further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure.



    5.7 Gastrointestinal Effects



  Do not administer morphine sulfate to patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, especially paralytic ileus because morphine sulfate diminishes propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and may prolong the obstruction.



 The administration of morphine sulfate may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal condition.



    5.8 Use in Pancreatic/Biliary Tract Disease



  Use morphine sulfate with caution in patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, as morphine sulfate may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and diminish biliary and pancreatic secretions.



    5.9 Special Risk Groups



  Use morphine sulfate with caution and in reduced dosages in patients with severe renal or hepatic impairment, Addison's disease, hypothyroidism, prostatic hypertrophy, or urethral stricture, and in elderly or debilitated patients. [ ]  See    USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS (8.5)  



 Exercise caution in the administration of morphine sulfate to patients with CNS depression, toxic psychosis, acute alcoholism and delirium tremens.



 All opioids may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and all opioids may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings.



 Keep Morphine Sulfate Oral Solution out of the reach of children. In case of accidental ingestion, seek emergency medical help immediately.



    5.10 Driving and Operating Machinery



  Caution patients that morphine sulfate could impair the mental and/or physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery.



 Caution patients about the potential combined effects of morphine sulfate with other CNS depressants, including other opioids, phenothiazines, sedative/hypnotics and alcohol. [ ] See    DRUG INTERACTIONS (7)  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
