<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="morphine4" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions associated with Morphine Sulfate Injection USP include, respiratory depression, apnea, and to a lesser degree, circulatory depression, respiratory arrest, shock, and cardiac arrest.  Rarely, anaphylactoid reactions have been reported when morphine or other phenanthrene alkaloids of opium are administered intravenously.



 The most frequently observed adverse reactions include sedation, lightheadedness, dizziness, nausea, vomiting, constipation, and diaphoresis. These effects seem to be more prominent in ambulatory patients and in those who are not experiencing severe pain. Some adverse reactions in ambulatory patients may be alleviated if the patient lies down.



 Other possible adverse reactions include:



     Central Nervous System    - Euphoria, dysphoria, weakness, headache, agitation, tremor, uncoordinated muscle movements, visual disturbances, transient hallucinations and disorientation.



     Gastrointestinal    - Constipation, biliary tract spasm.



     Cardiovascular    - Tachycardia, bradycardia, palpitation, faintness, syncope, and orthostatic hypotension.



     Genitourinary    - Oliguria and urinary retention; an antidiuretic effect has been reported.



     Allergic    - Pruritus, urticaria, and skin rashes. Anaphylactoid reactions have been reported following intravenous administration.



     Other    - Opiate-induced histamine release may be responsible for the flushing of the face, diaphoresis, and pruritus often seen with these drugs. Wheals and urticaria at the site of injection are probably related to histamine release. Local tissue irritation, pain and induration have been reported following repeated subcutaneous injection. Morphine may alter temperature regulation in susceptible individuals and will depress the cough reflex.



   EXCERPT:   The most serious adverse reaction encountered is respiratory depression, apnea, circulatory depression, respiratory arrest, shock, and cardiac arrest. Other common frequently observed adverse reactions include: sedation, lightheadedness, dizziness, nausea, vomiting, and constipation. (6)



  



    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Hospira, Inc. at 1-800-441-4100 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or        www.fda.gov/medwatch    . 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Dosing errors:  Take care when prescribing and administering to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between different concentrations and between mg and mL, which could result in accidental overdose and death. (5.1)   
 *  Cardiovascular instability:  High doses are excitatory, resulting from sympathetic hyperactivity and increase in circulatory catecholamine (5.2) 
 *  Respiratory depression:  Rapid intravenous administration may result in chest wall rigidity (5.3) 
 *  CNS toxicity:  High doses are excitatory, resulting in convulsions (5.4) 
 *  CNS Depressants: May increase the risk of respiratory depression, hypotension, sedation, coma, or death if use in conjunction with other CNS active drugs (5.6) 
 *  Increased intracranial pressure or head injury:  May increase respiratory depressant effects and elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (5.7) 
 *  Hypotensive effect: May cause hypotension in ambulatory patients (5.8) 
 *  Gastrointestinal effects:  May diminish propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and prolong obstruction (5.10) 
 *  Biliary surgery or disorders of biliary tract: May cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and diminish biliary and pancreatic secretions (5.11) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Medication Errors



  Morphine Sulfate Injection is available in five concentrations for direct injection.  Take care when prescribing and administering Morphine Sulfate Injection to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between different concentrations and between mg and mL, which could result in accidental overdose and death.  Take care to ensure the proper dose is communicated and dispensed.  When writing prescriptions, include both the total dose in mg and the total dose in volume.



    5.2 Cardiovascular Instability



  While low doses of intravenously administered morphine have little effect on cardiovascular stability, high doses are excitory, resulting from sympathetic hyperactivity and increase in circulatory catecholamines. Have Naloxone Injection and resuscitative equipment immediately available for use in case of life-threatening or intolerable side effects and whenever morphine therapy is being initiated.



    5.3 Respiratory Depression



  Respiratory depression is the primary risk of Morphine Sulfate Injection USP.  Respiratory depression occurs more frequently in elderly or debilitated patients and in those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or upper airway obstruction, in whom even moderate therapeutic doses may significantly decrease pulmonary ventilation. Morphine administration should be limited to use by those familiar with the management of respiratory depression. Rapid intravenous administration may result in chest wall rigidity.



 Patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale and in patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve (e.g., severe kyphoscoliosis), hypoxia, hypercapnia, or preexisting respiratory depression have an increased risk of increased airway resistance and decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea with use of Morphine Sulfate Injection USP.  Therefore, consider alternative non-opioid analgesics, and use Morphine Sulfate Injection USP only under careful medical supervision at the lowest effective dose in such patients.



    5.4 Central Nervous System (CNS) Toxicity



  Excitation of the central nervous system, resulting in convulsion, may accompany high doses of morphine given intravenously.  Dysphoric reactions may occur after any size dose and toxic psychoses have been reported.



    5.5 Misuse, Abuse and Diversion of Opioids



  Morphine sulfate is an opioid agonist and Schedule II controlled substance.  Such drugs are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders.  Diversion of Scheduled II products is an act subject to criminal penalty.  [  See        Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)      .]



 Morphine sulfate can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit.  This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing Morphine Sulfate Injection USP in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion.



 Concerns about abuse, addiction, and diversion should not prevent the proper management of pain.  Healthcare professionals should contact their State of Professional Licensing Board or State Controlled Substances Authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.6 Central Nervous System (CNS) Depressants



  The depressant effects of morphine are potentiated by the presence of other CNS depressants such as alcohol, sedatives, antihistamines, or psychotropic drugs.  Use of Morphine in conjunction with other CNS active drugs may increase the risk of respiratory depression, hypotension, profound sedation, coma, or death.



    5.7 Increased Intracranial Pressure or Head Injury



  Use Morphine Sulfate Injection with extreme caution in patients with head injury or increased intracranial pressure. In the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a preexisting increase in intracranial pressure, the possible respiratory depressant effects of Morphine Sulfate Injection USP and its potential to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2retention) may be markedly exaggerated.  Pupillary changes (miosis) from morphine may obscure the existence, extent and course of intracranial pathology. Clinicians should maintain a high index of suspicion for adverse drug reactions when evaluating altered mental status or movement abnormalities in patients receiving this modality of treatment.



    5.8 Hypotensive Effect



  Morphine Sulfate Injection may cause severe hypotension in an individual whose ability to maintain their blood pressure has been compromised by depleted blood volume, shock, impaired myocardial function or concurrent administration of sympatholytic drugs, and drugs such as phenothiazines or general anesthetics.  Orthostatic hypotension is a frequent complication in single-dose parenteral morphine analgesia in ambulatory patients.



 The vasodilation produced by Morphine Sulfate Injection USP may further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure in patients in circulatory shock.



    5.9 Driving and Operating Machinery



  Morphine may impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery.  Caution patients accordingly.



    5.10 Gastrointestinal Effects



  Do not administer Morphine Sulfate Injection USP to patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, especially paralytic ileus because Morphine Sulfate Injection USP diminishes propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and may prolong the obstruction.



 The administration of Morphine Sulfate Injection USP may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal condition.



    5.11 Use in Biliary Surgery or Disorders of the Biliary Tract



  Morphine Sulfate Injection USP may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and diminish biliary and pancreatic secretions.



    5.12 Special Risk Groups



  Use Morphine Sulfate Injection USP with caution and in reduced dosages in patients with severe renal or hepatic impairment, Addison's disease, hypothyroidism, prostatic hypertrophy, or urethral stricture, and in elderly or debilitated patients.  [  See           Use in Specific Populations (8.5)          .]



 Exercise caution in the administration of Morphine Sulfate Injection USP to patients with CNS depression, toxic psychosis, acute alcoholism and delirium tremens.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
