<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="morphine1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The major hazards of morphine, as with other narcotic analgesics, are respiratory depression, and to a lesser degree, circulatory depression, respiratory arrest, shock, and cardiac arrest have occurred, particularly with overdosage, rapid intravenous administration, and pre-existing hypovolemic shock. Rarely, anaphylactoid reactions have been reported when morphine or other phenanthrene alkaloids of opium are administered intravenously.



 The most frequently observed adverse reactions include sedation, lightheadedness, dizziness, nausea, vomiting, and sweating. These effects seem to be more prominent in ambulatory patients and in those who are not experiencing severe pain. Some adverse reactions in ambulatory patients may be alleviated if the patient lies down (see also    PRECAUTIONS      "Hypotensive Effect"  ).



 Other possible adverse reactions include:



 Central Nervous System - Euphoria, dysphoria, weakness, headache, agitation, tremor, uncoordinated muscle movements, visual disturbances, transient hallucinations and disorientation.



 Gastrointestinal - Constipation, biliary tract spasm.



 Cardiovascular - Tachycardia, bradycardia, palpitation, faintness, syncope, and orthostatic hypotension.



 Genitourinary - Oliguria and urinary retention; an antidiuretic effect has been reported.



 Allergic - Allergic reactions to opiates occur infrequently; pruritus, urticaria and other skin rashes are most common. Rarely, anaphylactoid reactions have been reported following intravenous administration.



 Other - Opiate-induced histamine release may be responsible for the flushing of the face, sweating, and pruritus often seen with these drugs. Wheals and urticaria at the site of injection are probably related to histamine release. Local tissue irritation, pain and induration have been reported following repeated subcutaneous injection. Morphine, like other opioids, may alter temperature regulation in susceptible individuals and will depress the cough reflex.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
