<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="morphabond" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described, or described in greater detail, in other sections:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Interactions with Benzodiazepine or Other CNS Depressants [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Adrenal Insufficiency [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Severe Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
 *  Withdrawal [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions: constipation, nausea, and sedation. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Daiichi Sankyo, Inc. at 1-877-437-7763 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 MORPHABOND ER may increase the risk of serious adverse reactions such as those observed with other opioid analgesics, including respiratory depression, apnea, respiratory arrest, circulatory depression, hypotension, or shock [  see Overdosage (  10  )].  



   Most Frequently Observed Reactions  



 In clinical trials, the most common adverse reactions with morphine sulfate extended-release were constipation, dizziness, sedation, nausea, vomiting, sweating, dysphoria, and euphoric mood.



 Some of these effects seem to be more prominent in ambulatory patients and in those not experiencing severe pain.



   Less Frequently Observed Reactions  



   Cardiovascular disorders:  tachycardia, bradycardia, palpitations



   Eye disorders:  visual impairment, vision blurred, diplopia, miosis



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  dry mouth, diarrhea, abdominal pain, constipation, dyspepsia



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  chills, feeling abnormal, edema, edema peripheral, weakness



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  biliary colic



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  anorexia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  muscle rigidity, muscle twitching



   Nervous system disorders:  presyncope, syncope, headache, tremor, uncoordinated muscle movements, convulsion, intracranial pressure increased, taste alteration, paresthesia, nystagmus



   Psychiatric disorders:  agitation, mood altered, anxiety, depression, abnormal dreams, hallucination, disorientation, insomnia



   Renal and urinary disorders:  urinary retention, urinary hesitation, antidiuretic effect



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:  reduced libido and/or potency



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  laryngospasm



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  pruritus, urticaria, rash



   Vascular disorders:  flushing, hypotension, hypertension



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of morphine sulfate. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 amenorrhea, asthenia, bronchospasm, confusional state, drug hypersensitivity, fatigue, hyperalgesia, hypertonia, ileus, increased hepatic enzymes, intestinal obstruction, lethargy, malaise, pulmonary edema, thinking disturbances, somnolence, and vertigo.



   Serotonin syndrome:  Cases of serotonin syndrome, a potentially life-threatening condition, have been reported during concomitant use of opioids with serotonergic drugs.



   Adrenal insufficiency:  Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than one month of use.



   Anaphylaxis:  Anaphylaxis has been reported with ingredients contained in MORPHABOND ER.



   Androgen deficiency:  Cases of androgen deficiency have occurred with chronic use of opioids  [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and RISKS FROM CONCOMITANT USE WITH BENZODIAZEPINES OR OTHER CNS DEPRESSANTS

  WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and RISKS FROM CONCOMITANT USE WITH BENZODIAZEPINES OR OTHER CNS DEPRESSANTS

    Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse  



   MORPHABOND ERTM exposes patients and other users to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death.  Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing MORPHABOND ER, and monitor all patients regularly for the development of these behaviors and conditions   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression  



   Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of MORPHABOND ER.  Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of MORPHABOND ER or following a dose increase.  Instruct patients to swallow MORPHABOND ER tablets whole; crushing, chewing, or dissolving MORPHABOND ER tablets can cause rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of morphine   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    



   Accidental Ingestion  



   Accidental ingestion of even one dose of MORPHABOND ER, especially by children, can result in a fatal overdose of morphine   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



   Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome  



   Prolonged use of MORPHABOND ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts.  If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )].    



   Risks From Concomitant Use With Benzodiazepines Or Other CNS Depressants  



   Concomitant use of opioids with benzodiazepines or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants, including alcohol, may result in profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ), Drug Interactions (  7  )].    



 *  Reserve concomitant prescribing of MORPHABOND ER and benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate. 
 *  Limit dosages and durations to the minimum required. 
 *  Follow patients for signs and symptoms of respiratory depression and sedation. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING:  ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and RISKS FROM CONCOMITANT USE WITH BENZODIAZEPINES OR OTHER CNS DEPRESSANTS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  MORPHABOND ER exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for these behaviors and conditions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients to swallow MORPHABOND ER tablets whole to avoid exposure to a potentially fatal dose of morphine. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental ingestion of MORPHABOND ER, especially by children, can result in a fatal overdose of morphine. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of MORPHABOND ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If prolonged opioid use is required in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
 *  Concomitant use of opioids with benzodiazepines or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants, including alcohol, may result in profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death. Reserve concomitant prescribing for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate; limit dosages and durations to the minimum required; and follow patients for signs and symptoms of respiratory depression and sedation. (5.4, 7) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease or in Elderly, Cachectic, or Debilitated Patients : Monitor closely, particularly during initiation and titration. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Adrenal Insufficiency : If diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement of corticosteroids, and wean patient off of the opioid. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Severe Hypotension : Monitor during dose initiation and titration. Avoid use of MORPHABOND ER in patients with circulatory shock. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Risks of Use in Patients with Increased Intracranial Pressure, Brain Tumors, Head Injury, or Impaired Consciousness : Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression. Avoid use of MORPHABOND ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  MORPHABOND ER contains morphine, a Schedule II controlled substance. As an opioid, MORPHABOND ER exposes its users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse. Because extended-release products such as MORPHABOND ER deliver the opioid over an extended period of time, there is a greater risk for overdose and death due to the larger amount of morphine present [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  .



 Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed MORPHABOND ER. Addiction can occur at recommended doses and if the drug is misused or abused.



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing MORPHABOND ER, and monitor all patients receiving MORPHABOND ER for development of these behaviors and conditions. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed opioids such as MORPHABOND ER, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks of proper use of MORPHABOND ER along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, and misuse.



 Abuse or misuse of MORPHABOND ER by crushing, chewing, snorting, or injecting the dissolved product will result in the uncontrolled delivery of morphine and can result in overdose and death [see Overdosage (  10  )].  



 Opioids are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing MORPHABOND ER. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper storage and disposal of unused drug [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  . Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.2 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see Overdosage (  10  )]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.



 While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of MORPHABOND ER, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dosage increase. Monitor patients closely for respiratory depression, especially within the first 24-72 hours of initiating therapy with and following dosage increases of MORPHABOND ER.



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of MORPHABOND ER are essential [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  . Overestimating the MORPHABOND ER dosage when converting patients from another opioid product can result in a fatal overdose with the first dose.



 Accidental ingestion of even one dose of MORPHABOND ER, especially by children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of morphine.



    5.3 Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Prolonged use of MORPHABOND ER during pregnancy can result in withdrawal in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. Observe newborns for signs of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and manage accordingly. Advise pregnant women using opioids for a prolonged period of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ), Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



    5.4 Risks from Concomitant Use with Benzodiazepines or Other CNS Depressants



  Profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death may result from the concomitant use of MORPHABOND ER with benzodiazepines or other CNS system depressants (e.g., non-benzodiazepine sedatives/hypnotics, tranquilizers, muscle relaxants, general anesthetics, anxiolytics, antipsychotics, other opioids, alcohol). Because of these risks, reserve concomitant prescribing of these drugs for use in patients for whom alternative treatment options are inadequate.



 Observational studies have demonstrated that concomitant use of opioid analgesics and benzodiazepines increases the risk of drug-related mortality compared to use of opioid analgesics alone. Because of similar pharmacological properties, it is reasonable to expect similar risk with the concomitant use of other CNS depressant drugs with opioid analgesics [see Drug Interactions (  7  )].  



 If the decision is made to prescribe a benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant concomitantly with an opioid analgesic, prescribe the lowest effective dosages and minimum durations of concomitant use. In patients already receiving an opioid analgesic, prescribe a lower initial dose of the benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant than indicated in the absence of an opioid, and titrate based on clinical response. If an opioid analgesic is initiated in a patient already taking a benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant, prescribe a lower initial dose of the opioid analgesic, and titrate based on clinical response. Follow patients closely for signs and symptoms of respiratory depression and sedation.



 Advise both patients and caregivers about the risks of respiratory depression and sedation when MORPHABOND ER is used with benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants (including alcohol and illicit drugs). Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until the effects of concomitant use of the benzodiazepine or other CNS depressant have been determined. Screen patients for risk of substance use disorders, including opioid abuse and misuse, and warn them of the risk for overdose and death associated with the use of additional CNS depressants including alcohol and illicit drugs [see Drug Interactions (  7  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



    5.5 Life -Threatening Respiratory Depression in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease or in Elderly, Cachectic, or Debilitated Patients



  The use of MORPHABOND ER in patients with acute or severe bronchial asthma in an unmonitored setting or in the absence of resuscitative equipment is contraindicated.



  Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease  : MORPHABOND ER-treated patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and those with a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression are at increased risk of decreased respiratory drive including apnea, even at recommended dosages of MORPHABOND ER [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .



  Elderly, Cachetic, or Debilitated Patients  : Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].  



 Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating MORPHABOND ER and when MORPHABOND ER is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ,  5.4  )]  . Alternatively, consider the use of non-opioid analgesics in these patients.



    5.6 Interaction with Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors



  Monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) may potentiate the effects of morphine, including respiratory depression, coma, and confusion. MORPHABOND ER should not be used in patients taking MAOIs or within 14 days of stopping such treatment.



    5.7 Adrenal Insufficiency



  Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than one month of use. Presentation of adrenal insufficiency may include non-specific symptoms and signs including nausea, vomiting, anorexia, fatigue, weakness, dizziness, and low blood pressure. If adrenal insufficiency is suspected, confirm the diagnosis with diagnostic testing as soon as possible. If adrenal insufficiency is diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement doses of corticosteroids. Wean the patient off of the opioid to allow adrenal function to recover and continue corticosteroid treatment until adrenal function recovers. Other opioids may be tried as some cases reported use of a different opioid without recurrence of adrenal insufficiency. The information available does not identify any particular opioids as being more likely to be associated with adrenal insufficiency.



    5.8 Severe Hypotension



  MORPHABOND ER may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is increased risk in patients whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a reduced blood volume or concurrent administration of certain CNS depressant drugs (e.g., phenothiazines or general anesthetics) [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  . Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dosage of MORPHABOND ER. In patients with circulatory shock, MORPHABOND ER may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. Avoid the use of MORPHABOND ER in patients with circulatory shock.



    5.9 Risks of Use in Patients with Increased Intracranial Pressure, Brain Tumors, Head Injury, or Impaired Consciousness



  In patients who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors), MORPHABOND ER may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2retention can further increase intracranial pressure. Monitor such patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with MORPHABOND ER.



 Opioids may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury. Avoid the use of MORPHABOND ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.10 Risks of Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  MORPHABOND ER is contraindicated in patients with known or suspected gastrointestinal obstruction, including paralytic ileus.



 The morphine in MORPHABOND ER may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Opioids may cause increases in the serum amylase. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, for worsening symptoms.



    5.11 Increased Risk of Seizures in Patients with Seizure Disorders



  The morphine in MORPHABOND ER may increase the frequency of seizures in patients with seizure disorders, and may increase the risk of seizures occurring in other clinical settings associated with seizures. Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during MORPHABOND ER therapy.



    5.12 Withdrawal



  Avoid the use of mixed agonist/antagonist (e.g., pentazocine, nalbuphine, and butorphanol) or partial agonist (e.g., buprenorphine) analgesics in patients who are receiving a full opioid agonist analgesic, including MORPHABOND ER. In these patients, mixed agonists/antagonist and partial agonist analgesics may reduce the analgesic effect and/or may precipitate withdrawal symptoms [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  .



 When discontinuing MORPHABOND ER, gradually taper the dosage [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  . Do not abruptly discontinue MORPHABOND ER [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.3  )]  .



    5.13 Risks of Driving and Operating Machinery



  MORPHABOND ER may impair the mental or physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to the effects of MORPHABOND ER and know how they will react to the medication [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
