<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="moxifloxacin1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common reactions (&gt;= 3%) were nausea, diarrhea, headache, and dizziness. (  6.2  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Fresenius Kabi USA, LLC, Vigilance &amp; Medical Affairs at 1-800-551-7176 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Serious and Otherwise Important Adverse Reactions

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in the Warnings and Precautions section of the label:



   Tendinopathy and Tendon Rupture  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



   QT Prolongation  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]    



   Hypersensitivity Reactions  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  



   Other Serious and Sometimes Fatal Reactions  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  



   Central Nervous System Effects  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]    



    Clostridium Difficile  -Associated Diarrhea  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  



   Peripheral Neuropathy that may be irreversible  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]    



   Blood Glucose Disturbances  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  



   Photosensitivity/Phototoxicity  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  



    Development of Drug Resistant Bacteria  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]   



   6.2 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  



 The data described below reflect exposure to moxifloxacin in 14,981 patients in 71 active controlled Phase II - IV clinical trials in different indications  [see       Indications and Usage (1)]    .  The population studied had a mean age of 50 years (approximately 73% of the population was &lt; 65 years of age), 50% were male, 63% were Caucasian, 12% were Asian and 9% were Black.  Patients received moxifloxacin 400 mg once daily PO, IV, or sequentially (IV followed by PO).  Treatment duration was usually 6 to 10 days, and the mean number of days on therapy was 9 days. 



 Discontinuation of moxifloxacin due to adverse events occurred in 5% of patients overall, 4.1% of patients treated with 400 mg PO, 3.9% with 400 mg IV and 8.2% with sequential therapy 400 mg PO/IV.  The most common adverse events leading to discontinuation with the 400 mg PO doses were nausea (0.8%), diarrhea (0.5%), dizziness (0.5%), and vomiting (0.4%).  The most common adverse event leading to discontinuation with the 400 mg IV dose was rash (0.5%).  The most common adverse events leading to discontinuation with the 400 mg IV/PO sequential dose were diarrhea (0.5%) and pyrexia (0.4%).



 Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;= 1% of moxifloxacin-treated patients and less common adverse reactions, occurring in 0.1 to &lt; 1% of moxifloxacin-treated patients, are shown in Table 2 and Table 3, respectively.  The most common adverse drug reactions (&gt;= 3%) are nausea, diarrhea, headache, and dizziness.



   Table 2: Common (&gt;= 1%) Adverse Reactions Reported in Active-Controlled    Clinical Trials with Moxifloxacin   




   System Organ Class         Adverse Reactions  a            % (N=14,981)              
  
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    Anemia                     1.1                         
   Gastrointestinal Disorders    Nausea                     6.9                         
 Diarrhea                   6                           
 Vomiting                   2.4                         
 Constipation               1.9                         
 Abdominal pain             1.5                         
 Abdominal pain upper       1.1                         
 Dyspepsia                  1                           
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    Pyrexia                    1.1                         
   Investigations           Alanine aminotransferase increased  1.1                         
   Metabolism and Nutritional Disorder    Hypokalemia                1                           
   Nervous System Disorders    HeadacheDizziness          4.23                        
   Psychiatric Disorders    Insomnia                   1.9                         
        a  MedDRA Version 12.0
 

   Table 3: Less Common (0.1 to &lt; 1%) Adverse Reactions Reported in Active-Controlled  



                                             Clinical Trials with Moxifloxacin (N=14,981)  




   System Organ Class         Adverse Reactions  a                                      
  
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    Thrombocythemia                                        
 Eosinophilia                                           
 Neutropenia                                            
 Thrombocytopenia                                       
 Leukopenia                                             
 Leukocytosis                                           
   Cardiac Disorders        Atrial fibrillation                                    
 Palpitations                                           
 Tachycardia                                            
 Cardiac failure congestive                              
 Angina pectoris                                        
 Cardiac failure                                        
 Cardiac arrest                                         
 Bradycardia                                            
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders    Vertigo                                                
 Tinnitus                                               
   Eye Disorders            Vision blurred                                         
   Gastrointestinal Disorders    Dry mouth                                              
 Abdominal discomfort                                   
 Flatulence                                             
 Abdominal distention                                   
 Gastritis                                              
 Gastroesophageal reflux disease                              
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    Fatigue                     
 Chest pain                  
 Asthenia                    
 Edema peripheral            
 Pain                        
 Malaise                     
 Infusion site extravasation   
 Edema                       
 Chills                      
 Chest discomfort            
 Facial pain                 
   Hepatobiliary Disorders    Hepatic function abnormal   
   Infections and Infestations    Vulvovaginal candidiasis    
 Oral candidiasis            
 Vulvovaginal mycotic infection   
 Candidiasis                 
 Vaginal infection           
 Oral fungal infection       
 Fungal infection            
 Gastroenteritis             
   Investigations           Aspartate aminotransferase increased   
 Gamma-glutamyltransferase increased   
 Blood alkaline phosphatase increased   
 Hepatic enzyme increased    
 Electrocardiogram QT prolonged   
 Blood lactate dehydrogenase increased   
 Platelet count increased    
 Blood amylase increased     
 Blood glucose increased     
 Lipase increased            
 Hemoglobin decreased        
 Blood creatinine increased   
 Transaminases increased     
 White blood cell count increased   
 Blood urea increased        
 Liver function test abnormal   
 Hematocrit decreased        
 Prothrombin time prolonged   
 Eosinophil count increased   
 Activated partial thromboplastin time prolonged   
 Blood bilirubin increased   
 Blood triglycerides increased   
 Blood uric acid increased   
 Blood pressure increased    
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders    Hyperglycemia               
 Anorexia                    
 Hypoglycemia                
 Hyperlipidemia              
 Decreased appetite          
 Dehydration                 
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    Back pain                   
 Pain in extremity           
 Arthralgia                  
 Myalgia                     
 Muscle spasms               
 Musculoskeletal chest pain   
 Musculoskeletal pain        
   Nervous System Disorders    Dysgeusia                   
 Somnolence                  
 Tremor                      
 Lethargy                    
 Paresthesia                 
 Tension headache            
 Hypoesthesia                
 Syncope                     
   Psychiatric Disorders    Anxiety                     
 Confusional state           
 Agitation                   
 Depression                  
 Nervousness                 
 Restlessness                
 Hallucination               
 Disorientation              
   Renal and Urinary Disorders    Renal failure               
 Dysuria                     
 Renal failure acute         
   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders    Vulvovaginal pruritus       
   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders    Dyspnea                     
 Asthma                      
 Wheezing                    
 Bronchospasm                
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    Rash                        
 Pruritus                    
 Hyperhidrosis               
 Erythema                    
 Urticaria                   
 Dermatitis allergic         
 Night sweats                
   Vascular Disorders       Hypertension                
 Hypotension                 
 Phlebitis                   
        a  MedDRA Version 12.0
 

   6.3 Laboratory Changes

  Changes in laboratory parameters, without regard to drug relationship, which are not listed above and which occurred in &gt;= 2% of patients and at an incidence greater than in controls included: increases in MCH, neutrophils, WBCs, PT ratio, ionized calcium, chloride, albumin, globulin, bilirubin; decreases in hemoglobin, RBCs, neutrophils, eosinophils, basophils, PT ratio, glucose, pO2, bilirubin, and amylase.  It cannot be determined if any of the above laboratory abnormalities were caused by the drug or the underlying condition being treated. 



   6.4 Postmarketing Experience

  Table 4 lists adverse reactions that have been identified during post-approval use of moxifloxacin.  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. 



                                                                                              Table 4: Postmarketing Reports of Adverse Drug Reactions   




   System/Organ Class         Adverse Reaction          
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    AgranulocytosisPancytopenia    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]       
   Cardiac Disorders        Ventricular tachyarrhythmias (including in very rare cases cardiac arrest and torsades de pointes, and usually in patients with concurrent severe underlying proarrhythmic conditions)   
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders    Hearing impairment, including deafness (reversible in majority of cases)   
   Eye Disorders            Vision loss (especially in the course of CNS reactions, transient in majority of cases)   
   Hepatobiliary Disorders    Hepatitis (predominantly cholestatic)Hepatic failure (including fatal cases)JaundiceAcute hepatic necrosis    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]       
   Immune System Disorders    Anaphylactic reactionAnaphylactic shockAngioedema (including laryngeal edema)    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4  ,  5.5)  ]       
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    Tendon rupture    [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]         
   Nervous System Disorders    Altered coordinationAbnormal gait    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]    Myasthenia gravis (exacerbation of)    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]    Muscle weaknessPeripheral neuropathy (that may be irreversible), polyneuropathy    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]       
   Psychiatric Disorders    Psychotic reaction (very rarely culminating in self-injurious behavior, such as suicidal ideation/thoughts or suicide attempts    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]       
   Renal and Urinary Disorders    Renal dysfunctionInterstitial nephritis    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]       
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    Allergic pneumonitis    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]       
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    Photosensitivity/phototoxicity reaction    [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]    Stevens-Johnson syndromeToxic epidermal necrolysis    [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]       
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: TENDON EFFECTS and MYASTHENIA GRAVIS

  WARNING: TENDON EFFECTS and MYASTHENIA GRAVIS

    Fluoroquinolones, including moxifloxacin, are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages.  This risk is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants.      Discontinue if pain or inflammation in a tendon occurs       [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].       Fluoroquinolones, including moxifloxacin, may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis.  Avoid moxifloxacin in patients with known history of myasthenia gravis   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: TENDON EFFECTS and MYASTHENIA GRAVIS  



     See full prescribing Information for complete boxed warning    



   Fluoroquinolones, including moxifloxacin, are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages.  This risk is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants.      Discontinue if pain or inflammation in a tendon occurs   (  5.1  )  .      



   Fluoroquinolones, including moxifloxacin, may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis.  Avoid moxifloxacin in patients with known history of myasthenia gravis   (  5.2  )  .   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Prolongation of the QT interval and isolated cases of torsades de pointes has been reported.  Avoid use in patients with known prolongation, hypokalemia, and with drugs that prolong the QT interval. (  5.3  ,  7.4  ,  8.5  ).  Use caution in patients with proarrhythmic conditions such as clinically significant bradycardia or acute myocardial ischemia. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic reactions, may occur after first or subsequent doses.  Discontinue drug use at first sign of skin rash, jaundice or any other sign of hypersensitivity. (  5.4  ,  5.5  ) 
 *  Central nervous system (CNS) events including dizziness, confusion, hallucination, depression, and suicidal thoughts or acts may occur after first dose.  Use caution in patients with known or suspected CNS disorders that may predispose to seizures or lower the seizure threshold. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea: Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Peripheral neuropathy: Discontinue if symptoms occur. (  5.8  ) 
 *  High sodium load: each unit dose contains 52.5 mEq (1207 mg) of sodium.  Avoid in patients with sodium restriction. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Tendinopathy and Tendon Rupture



  Fluoroquinolones, including moxifloxacin, are associated with an increased risk of tendinitis and tendon rupture in all ages.  This adverse reaction most frequently involves the Achilles tendon, and rupture of the Achilles tendon may require surgical repair.  Tendinitis and tendon rupture in the rotator cuff (the shoulder), the hand, the biceps, the thumb, and other tendon sites have also been reported.  The risk of developing fluoroquinolone-associated tendinitis and tendon rupture is further increased in older patients usually over 60 years of age, in patients taking corticosteroid drugs, and in patients with kidney, heart or lung transplants.  Factors, in addition to age and corticosteroid use, that may independently increase the risk of tendon rupture include strenuous physical activity, renal failure, and previous tendon disorders such as rheumatoid arthritis.  Tendinitis and tendon rupture have also occurred in patients taking fluoroquinolones who do not have the above risk factors.  Tendon rupture can occur during or after completion of therapy; cases occurring up to several months after completion of therapy have been reported.  Moxifloxacin should be discontinued if the patient experiences pain, swelling, inflammation or rupture of a tendon.  Patients should be advised to rest at the first sign of tendinitis or tendon rupture, and to contact their healthcare provider regarding changing to a non-quinolone antimicrobial drug [see      Adverse Reactions (6.4)      and      Patient Counseling Information (17)     ]  . 



    5.2 Exacerbation of Myasthenia Gravis



  Fluoroquinolones, including moxifloxacin, have neuromuscular blocking activity and may exacerbate muscle weakness in persons with myasthenia gravis.  Postmarketing serious adverse events, including deaths and requirement for ventilatory support, have been associated with fluoroquinolone use in persons with myasthenia gravis.  Avoid moxifloxacin in patients with known history of myasthenia gravis [see   Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . 



    5.3 QT Prolongation



  Moxifloxacin has been shown to prolong the QT interval of the electrocardiogram in some patients.  Following oral dosing with 400 mg of moxifloxacin the mean (+/- SD) change in QTc from the pre-dose value at the time of maximum drug concentration was 6 msec (+/- 26) (n = 787).  Following a course of daily intravenous dosing (400 mg; 1 hour infusion each day) the mean change in QTc from the Day 1 pre-dose value was 10 msec (+/- 22) on Day 1 (n = 667) and 7 msec (+/- 24) on Day 3 (n = 667).  



 The drug should be avoided in patients with known prolongation of the QT interval, patients with uncorrected hypokalemia and patients receiving Class IA (for example, quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (for example, amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic agents, due to the lack of clinical experience with the drug in these patient populations.



 Pharmacokinetic studies between moxifloxacin and other drugs that prolong the QT interval such as cisapride, erythromycin, antipsychotics, and tricyclic antidepressants have not been performed.  An additive effect of moxifloxacin and these drugs cannot be excluded; therefore caution should be exercised when moxifloxacin is given concurrently with these drugs.  In premarketing clinical trials, the rate of cardiovascular adverse events was similar in 798 moxifloxacin and 702 comparator treated patients who received concomitant therapy with drugs known to prolong the QTc interval.



 Moxifloxacin should be used with caution in patients with ongoing proarrhythmic conditions, such as clinically significant bradycardia, acute myocardial ischemia.  The magnitude of QT prolongation may increase with increasing concentrations of the drug or increasing rates of infusion of the intravenous formulation.  Therefore the recommended dose or infusion rate should not be exceeded.  QT prolongation may lead to an increased risk for ventricular arrhythmias including torsades de pointes.  No excess in cardiovascular morbidity or mortality attributable to QTc prolongation occurred with moxifloxacin treatment in over 15,500 patients in controlled clinical studies, including 759 patients who were hypokalemic at the start of treatment, and there was no increase in mortality in over 18,000 moxifloxacin tablet treated patients in a postmarketing observational study in which ECGs were not performed.  Elderly patients using moxifloxacin injection may be more susceptible to drug-associated QT prolongation [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  ].    In addition, moxifloxacin should be used with caution in patients with mild, moderate, or severe liver cirrhosis [see      Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)     and      Patient Counseling Information (17)     ].  



    5.4 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious anaphylactic reactions, some following the first dose, have been reported in patients receiving quinolone therapy, including moxifloxacin.  Some reactions were accompanied by cardiovascular collapse, loss of consciousness, tingling, pharyngeal or facial edema, dyspnea, urticaria, and itching.  Serious anaphylactic reactions require immediate emergency treatment with epinephrine.  Moxifloxacin should be discontinued at the first appearance of a skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity.  Oxygen, intravenous steroids, and airway management, including intubation, may be administered as indicated [see      Adverse Reactions (6)      and     Patient Counseling Information (17)     ]  . 



    5.5 Other Serious and Sometimes Fatal Reactions



  Other serious and sometimes fatal events, some due to hypersensitivity, and some due to uncertain etiology, have been reported rarely in patients receiving therapy with quinolones, including moxifloxacin.  These events may be severe and generally occur following the administration of multiple doses.  Clinical manifestations may include one or more of the following:



  Fever, rash, or severe dermatologic reactions (for example, toxic epidermal   necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome)



  Vasculitis; arthralgia; myalgia; serum sickness



  Allergic pneumonitis



  Interstitial nephritis; acute renal insufficiency or failure



  Hepatitis; jaundice; acute hepatic necrosis or failure



  Anemia, including hemolytic and aplastic; thrombocytopenia, including thrombotic   thrombocytopenic purpura; leukopenia; agranulocytosis; pancytopenia; and/or other hematologic abnormalities



 The drug should be discontinued immediately at the first appearance of a skin rash, jaundice, or any other sign of hypersensitivity and supportive measures instituted [see   Patient Counseling Information (17)  and   Adverse Reactions (6.4)  ]  . 



    5.6 Central Nervous System Effects



  Fluoroquinolones, including moxifloxacin, may cause central nervous system (CNS) events, including: nervousness, agitation, insomnia, anxiety, nightmares or paranoia [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2,    6.4)  ]  .



 Convulsions and increased intracranial pressure (including pseudotumor cerebri) have been reported in patients receiving fluoroquinolones.  Fluoroquinolones may also cause central nervous system (CNS) events including: dizziness, confusion, tremors, hallucinations, depression, and, rarely, suicidal thoughts or acts.  These reactions may occur following the first dose.  If these reactions occur in patients receiving moxifloxacin, the drug should be discontinued and appropriate measures instituted.  As with all fluoroquinolones, moxifloxacin should be used with caution in patients with known or suspected CNS disorders (for example, severe cerebral arteriosclerosis, epilepsy) or in the presence of other risk factors that may predispose to seizures or lower the seizure threshold [see     Drug Interactions (7.3)     ,      Adverse Reactions (6.2,          6.4     )    and      Patient Counseling Information (17)     ]  .



    5.7 Clostridium Difficile-Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including moxifloxacin, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis.  Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .  



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD.  Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy.  CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use.  Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.  



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued.  Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2)  and   Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . 



    5.8 Peripheral Neuropathy



  Cases of sensory or sensorimotor axonal polyneuropathy affecting small and/or large axons resulting in paresthesias, hypoesthesias, dysesthesias and weakness have been reported in patients receiving fluoroquinolones including moxifloxacin.  Symptoms may occur soon after initiation of moxifloxacin and may be irreversible.  Moxifloxacin should be discontinued immediately if the patient experiences symptoms of peripheral neuropathy including pain, burning, tingling, numbness, and/or weakness or other alterations of sensation including light touch, pain, temperature, position sense, and vibratory sensation [see      Adverse Reactions      (     6.2     ,      6.4     ) and     Patient Counseling Information (17)     ]  . 



    5.9 High Sodium Load



  Each unit dose of moxifloxacin injection contains 52.5 mEq (1,207 mg) of sodium. Avoid use of moxifloxacin injection in patients with congestive heart failure, elderly, and those with restricted sodium intake [see   Use in     Specific Populations (8.5)  ,   Description (11)  ].  



    5.10 Arthropathic Effects in Animals



  The oral administration of moxifloxacin caused lameness in immature dogs.  Histopathological examination of the weight-bearing joints of these dogs revealed permanent lesions of the cartilage.  Related quinolone-class drugs also produce erosions of cartilage of weight-bearing joints and other signs of arthropathy in immature animals of various species [see   Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2  )]  .



    5.11 Blood Glucose Disturbances



  As with all fluoroquinolones, disturbances in blood glucose, including both hypoglycemia and hyperglycemia have been reported with moxifloxacin.  In moxifloxacin-treated patients, dysglycemia occurred predominantly in elderly diabetic patients receiving concomitant treatment with an oral hypoglycemic agent (for example, sulfonylurea) or with insulin.  In diabetic patients, careful monitoring of blood glucose is recommended [see     Adverse Reactions (6.2)] .    If a hypoglycemic reaction occurs, moxifloxacin should be discontinued and appropriate therapy should be initiated immediately [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2)  and   Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . 



    5.12 Photosensitivity/Phototoxicity



  Moderate to severe photosensitivity/phototoxicity reactions, the latter of which may manifest as exaggerated sunburn reactions (for example, burning, erythema, exudation, vesicles, blistering, edema) involving areas exposed to light (typically the face, "V" area of the neck, extensor surfaces of the forearms, dorsa of the hands), can be associated with the use of quinolone antibiotics after sun or UV light exposure.  Therefore, excessive exposure to these sources of light should be avoided.  Drug therapy should be discontinued if phototoxicity occurs [see   Adverse Reactions (6.4)  and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]    . 



    5.13 Development of Drug Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing moxifloxacin in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria [see   Patient Counseling Information (17)]    .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
