<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mozobil" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Anaphylactic shock and hypersensitivity reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Potential for tumor cell mobilization in leukemia patients  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]   
 *  Increased circulating leukocytes and decreased platelet counts  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]   
 *  Potential for tumor cell mobilization [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Potential for splenic enlargement  [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]   
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 10%): diarrhea, nausea, fatigue, injection site reactions, headache, arthralgia, dizziness, and vomiting. (  6  )
 

     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genzyme Corporation at 1-877-4MOZOBIL or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or        www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 10%) reported in patients who received Mozobil in conjunction with G-CSF regardless of causality and more frequent with Mozobil than placebo during HSC mobilization and apheresis were diarrhea, nausea, fatigue, injection site reactions, headache, arthralgia, dizziness, and vomiting.



 Safety data for Mozobil in combination with G-CSF were obtained from two randomized placebo-controlled studies (301 patients) and 10 uncontrolled studies (242 patients). Patients were primarily treated with Mozobil at daily doses of 0.24 mg/kg SC. Median exposure to Mozobil in these studies was 2 days (range 1 to 7 days).



 In the two randomized studies in patients with NHL and MM, a total of 301 patients were treated in the Mozobil and G-CSF group and 292 patients were treated in the placebo and G-CSF group. Patients received daily morning doses of G-CSF 10 micrograms/kg for 4 days prior to the first dose of Mozobil 0.24 mg/kg SC or placebo and on each morning prior to apheresis. The adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 5% of the patients who received Mozobil regardless of causality and were more frequent with Mozobil than placebo during HSC mobilization and apheresis are shown in Table 2. 



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 5% of Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma and Multiple Myeloma Patients Receiving Mozobil(r) and More Frequent than Placebo During HSC Mobilization and Apheresis 
                                Percent of Patients (%)   
  Mozobil(r) and G-CSF(n = 301)  Placebo and G-CSF(n = 292)   
 All Grades                    Grade 3       Grade 4       All Grades    Grade 3       Grade 4        
  
     Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                           
     Diarrhea                   37           &lt; 1           0             17            0             0              
     Nausea                    34            1             0             22            0             0              
     Vomiting                  10            &lt; 1           0             6             0             0              
     Flatulence                7             0             0             3             0             0              
     General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                                           
     Injection site reactions          34            0             0             10            0             0              
     Fatigue                   27            0             0             25            0             0              
     Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                                               
     Arthralgia                13            0             0             12            0             0              
     Nervous system disorders                                                                                           
     Headache                  22            &lt; 1           0             21            1             0              
     Dizziness                 11            0             0             6             0             0              
     Psychiatric disorders                                                                                           
    Insomnia                   7             0             0             5             0             0              
      In the randomized studies, 34% of patients with NHL or MM had mild to moderate injection site reactions at the site of subcutaneous administration of Mozobil. These included erythema, hematoma, hemorrhage, induration, inflammation, irritation, pain, paresthesia, pruritus, rash, swelling, and urticaria.
 

 Mild to moderate allergic reactions were observed in less than 1% of patients within approximately 30 min after Mozobil administration, including one or more of the following: urticaria (n = 2), periorbital swelling (n = 2), dyspnea (n = 1) or hypoxia (n = 1). Symptoms generally responded to treatments (e.g., antihistamines, corticosteroids, hydration or supplemental oxygen) or resolved spontaneously.



 Vasovagal reactions, orthostatic hypotension, and/or syncope can occur following subcutaneous injections.         In Mozobil oncology and healthy volunteer clinical studies, less than 1% of subjects experienced vasovagal reactions following subcutaneous administration of Mozobil doses &lt;= 0.24 mg/kg. The majority of these events occurred within 1 hour of Mozobil administration. Because of the potential for these reactions, appropriate precautions should be taken.



 Other adverse reactions in the randomized studies that occurred in &lt; 5% of patients but were reported as related to Mozobil during HSC mobilization and apheresis included abdominal pain, hyperhidrosis, abdominal distention, dry mouth, erythema, stomach discomfort, malaise, hypoesthesia oral, constipation, dyspepsia, and musculoskeletal pain.



 Hyperleukocytosis: In clinical trials, white blood cell counts of 100,000/mcL or greater were observed, on the day prior to or any day of apheresis, in 7% of patients receiving Mozobil and in 1% of patients receiving placebo. No complications or clinical symptoms of leukostasis were observed.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following adverse reactions have been reported from post-marketing experience with Mozobil. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Immune System Disorders:  Anaphylactic reactions, including anaphylactic shock



   Psychiatric disorders  : Abnormal dreams and nightmares
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Anaphylactic shock and Serious Hypersensitivity Reactions have occurred. Monitor patients during and after completion of Mozobil administration. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Tumor Cell Mobilization in Leukemia Patients: Mozobil may mobilize leukemic cells and should not be used in leukemia patients. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hematologic Effects: Increased circulating leukocytes and decreased platelet counts have been observed.  Monitor blood cell counts and platelet counts during Mozobil use. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Potential for Tumor Cell Mobilization:  Tumor cells may be released from marrow during HSC mobilization with Mozobil and G-CSF.  Effect of reinfusion of tumor cells is unknown. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Potential for Splenic Rupture: Evaluate patients who report left upper abdominal and/or scapular or shoulder pain. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Embryo-fetal Toxicity: May cause fetal harm. Advise women not to become pregnant when taking Mozobil.  (  5.6  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylactic shock and Hypersensitivity reactions



  Serious hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic-type reactions, some of which have been life-threatening with clinically significant hypotension and shock have occurred in patients receiving Mozobil [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . Observe patients for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity during and after Mozobil administration for at least 30 minutes and until clinically stable following completion of each administration. Only administer Mozobil when personnel and therapies are immediately available for the treatment of anaphylaxis and other hypersensitivity reactions.



 In clinical studies, mild or moderate allergic reactions occurred within approximately 30 minutes after Mozobil administration in less than 1% of patients [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.2 Tumor Cell Mobilization in Leukemia Patients



  For the purpose of HSC mobilization, Mozobil may cause mobilization of leukemic cells and subsequent contamination of the apheresis product. Therefore, Mozobil is not intended for HSC mobilization and harvest in patients with leukemia.



    5.3 Hematologic Effects



   Leukocytosis  



 Administration of Mozobil in conjunction with G-CSF increases circulating leukocytes as well as HSC populations. Monitor white blood cell counts during Mozobil use. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  



    Thrombocytopenia  



 Thrombocytopenia has been observed in patients receiving Mozobil. Monitor platelet counts in all patients who receive Mozobil and then undergo apheresis.



    5.4 Potential for Tumor Cell Mobilization



  When Mozobil is used in combination with G-CSF for HSC mobilization, tumor cells may be released from the marrow and subsequently collected in the leukapheresis product. The effect of potential reinfusion of tumor cells has not been well-studied.



    5.5 Splenic Enlargement and Potential for Rupture



  Higher absolute and relative spleen weights associated with extramedullary hematopoiesis were observed following prolonged (2 to 4 weeks) daily plerixafor SC administration in rats at doses approximately 4-fold higher than the recommended human dose based on body surface area. The effect of Mozobil on spleen size in patients was not specifically evaluated in clinical studies. Evaluate individuals receiving Mozobil in combination with G-CSF who report left upper abdominal pain and/or scapular or shoulder pain for splenic integrity.



    5.6 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  Mozobil may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Plerixafor is teratogenic in animals. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women using Mozobil. Advise women of childbearing potential to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving treatment with Mozobil .  If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.   [see        Use In Specific Populations (8.1)        ]    
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
