<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="muse" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In-Clinic Titration:

  In the 2 largest double-blind, parallel, placebo-controlled trials, 1511 patients received MUSE at least 1 time in the clinic setting. The most frequently reported drug-related side effects during in-clinic titration included pain in the penis (36%), urethra (13%), or testes (5%). These discomforts were most commonly reported as mild and transient, but about 7% of patients withdrew at this stage because of adverse events. Urethral bleeding/spotting and other minor abrasions to the urethra were reported in approximately 3% of patients. Symptomatic lowering of blood pressure (hypotension) occurred in 3% of patients; in addition, some lowering of blood pressure may occur without symptoms. Dizziness was reported in 4% of patients. Syncope (fainting) was reported by 0.4% of patients. (See    WARNINGS    ).



   Home Treatment:

  996 patients (66% of those who began titration) were studied during the home treatment portion of 2 Phase III placebo-controlled studies. Fewer than 2% of patients discontinued from these studies primarily because of adverse events. The following table summarizes the frequency of adverse events reported by patients using MUSE or placebo.



 Adverse Events Reported by &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with MUSE, and More Common than on Placebo, at Home in Phase III Placebo-Controlled Clinical Studies for up to 3 Months 
                                MUSE       Placebo                                 MUSE           Placebo      
   Event                          n = 486      n = 511    Event                         n = 486        n = 511     
 UROGENITAL SYSTEM                                     BODY AS A WHOLE                                         
      Penile Pain               32%        3%               Flu Symptoms           4%             2%           
      Urethral Burning          12%        4%               Headache               3%             2%           
      Minor Urethral Bleeding/  5%         1%               Pain                   3%             1%           
        Spotting                                            Accidental Injury      3%             2%           
      Testicular Pain           5%         1%               Back Pain              2%             1%           
 NERVOUS SYSTEM                                             Pelvic Pain            2%             &lt;1%          
      Dizziness                 2%         &lt;1%         RESPIRATORY                                             
                                                            Rhinitis               2%             &lt;1%          
                                                            Infection              3%             2%           
            Other drug-related side effects observed during in-clinic titration and home treatment include swelling of leg veins, leg pain, perineal pain, and rapid pulse, each occurring in &lt;2% of patients.
 

     Female Partner Adverse Events:  The most common drug-related adverse event reported by female partners during placebo-controlled clinical studies was vaginal burning/itching, reported by 5.8% of partners of patients on active vs. 0.8% of partners of patients on placebo. It is unknown whether this adverse event experienced by female partners was a result of the medication or a result of resuming sexual intercourse, which occurred much more frequently in partners of patients on active medication.



 To report suspected adverse reactions, contact Meda Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-888-345-6873 or contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088, fax 1-800-FDA-0178 or online at www.fda.gov/medwatch/report.htm.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
