<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="mycamine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The overall safety of Mycamine was assessed in 3227 adult and pediatric patients and 520 volunteers in 46 clinical trials, including the invasive candidiasis, esophageal candidiasis and prophylaxis trials, who received single or multiple doses of Mycamine, ranging from 0.75 mg/kg to 10 mg/kg in pediatric patients and 12.5 mg to 150 mg/day or greater in adult patients.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of Mycamine cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does provide a basis for identifying adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



    EXCERPT:    *    Most common adverse reactions include diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, pyrexia, thrombocytopenia, and headache (  6  ) 
 *    Histamine-mediated symptoms including rash, pruritus, facial swelling, and vasodilatation (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact: Astellas Pharma US, Inc. at 1-800-727-7003 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Infusion Reactions

  Possible histamine-mediated symptoms have been reported with Mycamine, including rash, pruritus, facial swelling, and vasodilatation.



 Injection site reactions, including phlebitis and thrombophlebitis have been reported, at Mycamine doses of 50-150 mg/day. These reactions tended to occur more often in patients receiving Mycamine via peripheral intravenous administration.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience in Adults

           In all clinical trials with Mycamine, 2497/2748 (91%) adult patients experienced at least one treatment-emergent adverse reaction.



       Candidemia and Other Candida Infections      



 In a randomized, double-blind study for treatment of candidemia and other  Candida  infections, treatment-emergent adverse reactions occurred in 183/200 (92%), 187/202 (93%) and 171/193 (89%) patients in the Mycamine 100 mg/day, Mycamine 150 mg/day, and caspofungin (a 70 mg loading dose followed by a 50 mg/day dose) treatment groups, respectively. Selected treatment-emergent adverse reactions, those occurring in 5% or more of the patients and more frequently in a Mycamine treatment group, are shown in  Table 3  .



 Table 3. SelectedDuring IV treatment + 3 days  Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Adult Patients with Candidemia and Other Candida Infections 
 Patient base: all randomized patients who received at least 1 dose of trial drug   
  
  System Organ ClassMedDRA v5.0(Preferred Term)Within a system organ class patients may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.     Mycamine 100 mg  n (%)    Mycamine 150 mg  n (%)    Caspofungin70 mg loading dose on day 1 followed by 50 mg/day thereafter (caspofungin)  n (%)    
  Number of Patients                                    200                   202                   193               
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                            81 (41)               89 (44)               76 (39)           
       Diarrhea                                         15 (8)                26 (13)               14 (7)            
       Nausea                                           19 (10)               15 (7)                20 (10)           
       Vomiting                                         18 (9)                15 (7)                16 (8)            
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                    77 (39)               83 (41)               73 (38)           
       Hypoglycemia                                     12 (6)                14 (7)                9 (5)             
       Hypernatremia                                    8 (4)                 13 (6)                8 (4)             
       Hyperkalemia                                     10 (5)                8 (4)                 5 (3)             
  General Disorders/ Administration Site Conditions     59 (30)               56 (28)               51 (26)           
       Pyrexia                                          14 (7)                22 (11)               15 (8)            
  Investigations                                        36 (18)               49 (24)               37 (19)           
       Blood Alkaline Phosphatase Increased             11 (6)                16 (8)                8 (4)             
  Cardiac Disorders                                     35 (18)               48 (24)               36 (19)           
       Atrial Fibrillation                              5 (3)                 10 (5)                0                 
          In a second, supportive, randomized, double-blind study for treatment of candidemia and other  Candida  infections, treatment-emergent adverse reactions occurred in 245/264 (93%) and 250/265 (94%) patients in the Mycamine (100 mg/day) and AmBisome (3 mg/kg/day) treatment groups, respectively. The following treatment-emergent adverse reactions in the Mycamine treated patients at least 16 years of age were notable: nausea (10% vs. 8%); diarrhea (11% vs. 11%), vomiting (13% vs. 9%), abnormal liver function tests (4% vs. 3%); increased aspartate aminotransferase (3% vs. 2%), and increased blood alkaline phosphatase (3% vs. 2%), in the Mycamine and AmBisome treatment groups, respectively.
 

     Esophageal Candidiasis    



 In a randomized, double-blind study for treatment of esophageal candidiasis, a total of 202/260 (78%) patients who received Mycamine 150 mg/day and 186/258 (72%) patients who received intravenous fluconazole 200 mg/day experienced an adverse reaction. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions resulting in discontinuation were reported in 17 (7%) Mycamine treated patients; and in 12 (5%) fluconazole treated patients. Selected treatment-emergent adverse reactions, those occurring in 5% or more of the patients and more frequently in the Mycamine group, are shown in  Table 4  .



 Table 4. SelectedDuring treatment + 3 days. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Adult Patients with Esophageal Candidiasis 
 Patient base: all randomized patients who received at least 1 dose of trial drug   
  
  System Organ ClassMedDRA v5.0(Preferred Term)Within a system organ class patients may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.    Mycamine  150 mg/day  n (%)    Fluconazole  200 mg/day  n (%)    
  Number of Patients                                    260             258             
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                            84 (32)         93 (36)         
       Diarrhea                                         27 (10)         29 (11)         
       Nausea                                           20 (8)          23 (9)          
       Vomiting                                         17 (7)          17 (7)          
  General Disorders/Administration Site Conditions      52 (20)         45 (17)         
       Pyrexia                                          34 (13)         21 (8)          
  Nervous System Disorders                              42 (16)         40 (16)         
       Headache                                         22 (9)          20 (8)          
  Vascular Disorders                                    54 (21)         21 (8)          
       Phlebitis                                        49 (19)         13 (5)          
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                36 (14)         26 (10)         
       Rash                                             14 (5)          6 (2)           
               Prophylaxis of Candida Infections in Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant Recipients      
 

 A double-blind study was conducted in a total of 882 patients scheduled to undergo an autologous or allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant. The median duration of treatment was 18 days (range 1 to 51 days) in both treatment arms.



 All adult patients who received Mycamine (382) or fluconazole (409) experienced at least one adverse reaction during the study. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions resulting in Mycamine discontinuation were reported in 15 (4%) adult patients; while those resulting in fluconazole discontinuation were reported in 32 (8%). Selected adverse reactions, those reported in 15% or more of adult patients and more frequently on the Mycamine treatment arm, are shown in  Table 5  .



 Table 5. Selected Adverse Reactions in Adult Patients During Prophylaxis of Candida Infection in Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant Recipients 
 Patient base: all randomized adult patients who received at least 1 dose of trial drug   
  
  System Organ ClassMedDRA v12.0(Preferred Term)Within a system organ class patients may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.    Mycamine  50 mg/day  n (%)    Fluconazole  400 mg/day  n (%)    
  Number of Patients                          382            409             
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                  377 (99)       404 (99)        
       Diarrhea                               294 (77)       327 (80)        
       Nausea                                 270 (71)       290 (71)        
       Vomiting                               252 (66)       274 (67)        
       Abdominal Pain                         100 (26)       93 (23)         
  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders        368 (96)       385 (94)        
       Neutropenia                            288 (75)       297 (73)        
       Thrombocytopenia                       286 (75)       280 (69)        
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders      257 (67)       275 (67)        
       Rash                                   95 (25)        91 (22)         
  Nervous System Disorders                    250 (65)       254 (62)        
       Headache                               169 (44)       154 (38)        
  Psychiatric Disorders                       233 (61)       235 (58)        
       Insomnia                               142 (37)       140 (34)        
       Anxiety                                84 (22)        87 (21)         
  Cardiac Disorders                           133 (35)       138 (34)        
       Tachycardia                            99 (26)        91 (22)         
         Other selected adverse reactions reported at less than 5% in adult clinical trials are listed below:
 

 *     Blood and lymphatic system disorders : coagulopathy, pancytopenia, thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura 
 *     Cardiac disorders : cardiac arrest, myocardial infarction, pericardial effusion 
 *     General disorders and administration site conditions : infusion reaction, injection site thrombosis 
 *     Hepatobiliary disorders : hepatocellular damage, hepatomegaly, jaundice, hepatic failure 
 *      Immune disorders : hypersensitivity, anaphylactic reaction 
 *     Nervous system disorders : convulsions, encephalopathy, intracranial hemorrhage 
 *     Psychiatric disorders : delirium 
 *     Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders : urticaria 
      6.3 Clinical Trials Experience in Pediatric Patients
   The overall safety of Mycamine was assessed in 479 patients 3 days through 16 years of age who received at least one dose of Mycamine in 11 separate clinical studies. The mean treatment duration was 24.8 days. A total of 246 patients received at least one dose of Mycamine 2 mg/kg or higher.



 Of the 479 pediatric patients, 264 (55%) were male, 319 (67%) were Caucasians, with the following age distribution: 116 (24%) less than 2 years, 108 (23%) between 2 and 5 years, 140 (29%) between 6 years and 11 years, and 115 (24%) between 12 and 16 years of age.



 In all pediatric studies with Mycamine, 439/479 (92%) patients experienced at least one treatment-emergent adverse reaction.



 Two studies that included pediatric patients were randomized, double-blind, and active-controlled: The invasive candidiasis and candidemia study investigated the efficacy and safety of Mycamine (2 mg/kg/day for patients weighing 40 kg or less and 100 mg/day for patients weighing greater than 40 kg) compared to AmBisome (3 mg/kg/day) in 112 pediatric patients. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions occurred in 51/56 (91%) of patients in the Mycamine group and 52/56 (93%) of patients in the AmBisome group. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions resulting in Mycamine discontinuation were reported in 2 (4%) pediatric patients; while those resulting in AmBisome discontinuation were reported in 9 (16%).



 The prophylaxis study in patients undergoing HSCT investigated the efficacy of Mycamine (1 mg/kg/day for patients weighing 50 kg or less and 50 mg/day for patients weighing greater than 50 kg) as compared to fluconazole (8 mg/kg/day for patients weighing 50 kg or less and 400 mg/day for patients weighing greater than 50 kg). All 91 pediatric patients experienced at least one treatment-emergent adverse reaction. Three (7%) pediatric patients discontinued Mycamine due to adverse reaction; while one (2%) patient discontinued fluconazole.



 The selected treatment-emergent adverse reactions, those occurring in 15% or more of the patients and more frequently in a Mycamine group, for all Mycamine pediatric studies and for the two comparative studies (candidemia and prophylaxis) described above are shown in  Table 6  .



 Table 6. Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in All Pediatric Patients, in Patients with Candidemia and Other Candida Infections (C/IC), and in Hematopoietic Stem-Cell Recipients During Prophylaxis of Candida Infections 
  System Organ ClassMedDRA v12.0(Preferred Term) Within a system organ class, patients may experience more than 1 adverse reaction.    All Micafungin-treated Patientsn = 479n (%)    C/IC           Prophylaxis    
  Mycaminen = 56n (%)                     AmBisome n = 56n (%)       Mycaminen = 43n (%)    Fluconazolen = 48n (%)    
  Gastrointestinal disorders              285 (60)                   22 (40)        18 (32)        43 (100)       45 (94)         
  Vomiting                                146 (31)                   10 (18)        8 (14)         28 (65)        32 (67)         
  Diarrhea                                106 (22)                   4 (7)          5 (9)          22 (51)        31 (65)         
  Nausea                                  91 (19)                    4 (7)          4 (7)          30 (70)        25 (52)         
  Abdominal pain                          76 (16)                    2 (4)          2 (4)          15 (35)        12 (25)         
  Abdominal distension                    29 (6)                     1 (2)          1 (2)          8 (19)         6 (13)          
  General disorders and administration site conditions    256 (53)                   14 (25)        14 (25)        41 (95)        46 (96)         
  Pyrexia                                 103 (22)                   5 (9)          9 (16)         26 (61)        31 (65)         
  Infusion related reaction               24 (5)                     0              3 (5)          7 (16)         4 (8)           
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders    197 (41)                   11 (20)        8 (14)         33 (77)        38 (79)         
  Pruritus                                54 (11)                    0              1 (2)          14 (33)        15 (31)         
  Rash                                    55 (12)                    1 (2)          1 (2)          13 (30)        13 (27)         
  Urticaria                               24 (5)                     0              1 (2)          8 (19)         4 (8)           
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders    194 (41)                   9 (16)         13 (23)        30 (70)        33 (69)         
  Epistaxis                               45 (9)                     0              0              4 (9)          8 (17)          
  Blood and lymphatic system disorders    161 (34)                   17 (30)        13 (23)        40 (93)        44 (92)         
  Thrombocytopenia                        70 (15)                    5 (9)          3 (5)          31 (72)        37 (77)         
  Neutropenia                             61 (13)                    3 (5)          4 (7)          33 (77)        34 (71)         
  Anemia                                  63 (13)                    10 (18)        6 (11)         22 (51)        24 (50)         
  Febrile neutropenia                     23 (5)                     0              0              7 (16)         7 (15)          
  Investigations                          191 (40)                   12 (21)        8 (14)         24 (56)        25 (52)         
  Alanine aminotransferase increased      45 (10)                    0              0              7 (16)         1 (2)           
  Urine output decreased                  18 (4)                     0              0              10 (23)        8 (17)          
  Cardiac disorders                       97 (20)                    7 (13)         3 (5)          10 (23)        17 (35)         
  Tachycardia                             47 (10)                    2 (4)          1 (2)          7 (16)         12 (25)         
  Renal and urinary disorders             78 (16)                    4 (7)          4 (7)          16 (37)        15 (31)         
  Hematuria                               18 (4)                     0              0              10 (23)        7 (15)          
  Psychiatric disorders                   80 (17)                    3 (5)          1 (2)          20 (47)        9 (19)          
  Anxiety                                 35 (7)                     0              0              10 (23)        3 (6)           
  Patient base: all randomized patients who received at least one dose of trial drug.    
             Other clinically significant adverse reactions reported at less than 15% in pediatric clinical trials are listed below:
 

 *     Hepatobiliary disorders : hyperbilirubinemia 
 *     Investigations: liver function tests abnormal 
 *     Renal Disorders: renal failure 
      6.4 Postmarketing Adverse Reactions
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during the post-approval use of micafungin sodium for injection. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency.



 *     Blood and lymphatic system disorders : disseminated intravascular coagulation 
 *     Hepatobiliary disorders: hepatic disorder 
 *     Renal and urinary disorders : renal impairment 
 *     Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders : Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis 
 *     Vascular disorders : shock 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Hypersensitivity Reactions



 *    Anaphylaxis and anaphylactoid reactions (including shock) have been observed. Discontinue Mycamine and administer appropriate treatment (  5.1  ) 
    Hematological Effects
 

 *    Isolated cases of acute intravascular hemolysis, hemolytic anemia and hemoglobinuria have been reported (  5.2  ) 
    Hepatic Effects
 

 *    Abnormalities in liver function tests; isolated cases of hepatic impairment, hepatitis, and hepatic failure have been observed (  5.3  ) 
    Renal Effects
 

 *    Elevations in BUN and creatinine; isolated cases of renal impairment or acute renal failure have been reported (  5.4  ) 
    Monitor closely patients who develop clinical or laboratory evidence of the above reactions and evaluate risk/benefit of continuing Mycamine therapy. (  5  )
 

 



   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Isolated cases of serious hypersensitivity (anaphylaxis and anaphylactoid) reactions (including shock) have been reported in patients receiving Mycamine. If these reactions occur, Mycamine infusion should be discontinued and appropriate treatment administered.



    5.2 Hematological Effects



  Acute intravascular hemolysis and hemoglobinuria was seen in a healthy volunteer during infusion of Mycamine (200 mg) and oral prednisolone (20 mg). This reaction was transient, and the subject did not develop significant anemia. Isolated cases of significant hemolysis and hemolytic anemia have also been reported in patients treated with Mycamine. Patients who develop clinical or laboratory evidence of hemolysis or hemolytic anemia during Mycamine therapy should be monitored closely for evidence of worsening of these conditions and evaluated for the risk/benefit of continuing Mycamine therapy.



    5.3 Hepatic Effects



  Laboratory abnormalities in liver function tests have been seen in healthy volunteers and patients treated with Mycamine. In some patients with serious underlying conditions who were receiving Mycamine along with multiple concomitant medications, clinical hepatic abnormalities have occurred, and isolated cases of significant hepatic impairment, hepatitis, and hepatic failure have been reported. Patients who develop abnormal liver function tests during Mycamine therapy should be monitored for evidence of worsening hepatic function and evaluated for the risk/benefit of continuing Mycamine therapy.



    5.4 Renal Effects



  Elevations in BUN and creatinine, and isolated cases of significant renal impairment or acute renal failure have been reported in patients who received Mycamine. In fluconazole-controlled trials, the incidence of drug-related renal adverse reactions was 0.4% for Mycamine treated patients and 0.5% for fluconazole treated patients. Patients who develop abnormal renal function tests during Mycamine therapy should be monitored for evidence of worsening renal function.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
