<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="myfortic" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6??????????ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label.



 *  Embryofetal Toxicity [ see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ] 
 *  Lymphomas and Other Malignancies [ see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.4) ] 
 *  Serious Infections [ see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.5) ] 
 *  New or Reactivated Viral Infections [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.6) ] 
 *  Blood Dyscrasias Including Pure Red Cell Aplasia [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.7) ] 
 *  Serious GI Tract Complications [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.8) ] 
 *  Rare Hereditary Deficiencies [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.10) ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (???20%): anemia, leukopenia, constipation, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, dyspepsia, urinary tract infection, CMV infection, insomnia, and postoperative pain. (  6.2  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1??????????Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below derive from two randomized, comparative, active-controlled, double-blind, double-dummy trials in prevention of acute rejection in  de novo  and converted stable kidney transplant patients.



 In the  de novo  trial, patients were administered either Myfortic 1.44 grams per day (N=213) or MMF 2 grams per day (N=210) within 48 hours post-transplant for 12 months in combination with cyclosporine, USP MODIFIED and corticosteroids. Forty-one percent of patients also received antibody therapy as induction treatment. In the conversion trial, renal transplant patients who were at least 6 months post-transplant and receiving 2 grams per day MMF in combination with cyclosporine USP MODIFIED, with or without corticosteroids for at least two weeks prior to entry in the trial were randomized to Myfortic 1.44 grams per day (N=159) or MMF 2 grams per day (N=163) for 12 months.



 The average age of patients in both studies was 47 years and 48 years (  de novo  study and conversion study, respectively), ranging from 22 to 75 years. Approximately 66% of patients were male; 82% were white, 12% were black, and 6% other races. About 40% of patients were from the United States and 60% from other countries.



 In the  de novo  trial, the overall incidence of discontinuation due to adverse reactions was 18% (39/213) and 17% (35/210) in the Myfortic and MMF arms, respectively. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in the Myfortic arm were graft loss (2%), diarrhea (2%), vomiting (1%), renal impairment (1%), CMV infection (1%), and leukopenia (1%). The overall incidence of patients reporting dose reduction at least once during the 0 to 12 month study period was 59% and 60% in the Myfortic and MMF arms, respectively. The most frequent reasons for dose reduction in the Myfortic arm were adverse reactions (44%), dose reductions according to protocol guidelines (17%), dosing errors (11%) and missing data (2%).



 The most common adverse reactions (???20%) associated with the administration of Myfortic were anemia, leukopenia, constipation, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, dyspepsia, urinary tract infection, CMV infection, insomnia, and postoperative pain.



 The adverse reactions reported in ???10% of patients in the  de novo  trial are presented in Table 2 below.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions (%) Reported in ???10% of de novo Kidney Transplant Patients in Either Treatment Group 
 **The trial was not designed to support comparative claims for Myfortic for the adverse reactions reported in this table.   
  
                    de novo    Renal Trial     
 System organ classAdverse drug reactions    Myfortic1.44 grams per day(n=213)(%)      mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)2 grams per day(n=210)(%)     
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders     
 ??????????Anemia  22               22                
 ??????????Leukopenia  19               21                
   Gastrointestinal System Disorders     
 ??????????Constipation  38               40                
 ??????????Nausea  29               27                
 ??????????Diarrhea  24               25                
 ??????????Vomiting  23               20                
 ??????????Dyspepsia  23               19                
 ??????????Abdominal pain upper  14               14                
 ??????????Flatulence  10               13                
   General and Administrative Site Disorders     
 ??????????Edema  17               18                
 ??????????Edema lower limb  16               17                
 ??????????Pyrexia  13               19                
   Investigations     
 ??????????Increased blood creatinine  15               10                
   Infections and Infestations     
 ??????????Urinary Tract Infection  29               33                
 ??????????CMV Infection  20               18                
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders     
 ??????????Hypocalcemia  11               15                
 ??????????Hyperuricemia  13               13                
 ??????????Hyperlipidemia  12               10                
 ??????????Hypokalemia  13               9                 
 ??????????Hypophosphatemia  11               9                 
   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders     
 ??????????Back pain  12               6                 
 ??????????Arthralgia  7                11                
   Nervous System Disorder     
 ??????????Insomnia  24               24                
 ??????????Tremor  12               14                
 ??????????Headache  13               11                
   Vascular Disorders     
 ??????????Hypertension  18               18                
         Table 3 summarizes the incidence of opportunistic infections in  de novo  transplant patients.
 

 Table 3: Viral and Fungal Infections (%) Reported Over 0 to 12 Months 
                    de novo    Renal Trial     
                    Myfortic1.44 grams per day(n=213)(%)      mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)2 grams per day(n=210)(%)     
 Any Cytomegalovirus  22               21                
 - Cytomegalovirus Disease  5                4                 
 Herpes Simplex   8                6                 
 Herpes Zoster    5                4                 
 Any Fungal Infection  11               12                
 - Candida NOS    6                6                 
 - Candida albicans  2                4                 
         Lymphoma developed in 2  de novo  patients (1%), (1 diagnosed 9 days after treatment initiation) and in 2 conversion patients (1%) receiving Myfortic with other immunosuppressive agents in the 12-month controlled clinical trials.
 

 Nonmelanoma skin carcinoma occurred in 1%  de novo  and 12% conversion patients. Other types of malignancy occurred in 1% de novo and 1% conversion patients [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].



 The adverse reactions reported in &lt;10% of  de novo  or conversion patients treated with Myfortic in combination with cyclosporine and corticosteroids are listed in Table 4.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions Reported in &lt;10% of Patients Treated with Myfortic in Combination with Cyclosporine* and Corticosteroids 
 * USP MODIFIED    
  
 Blood and Lymphatic Disorders  Lymphocele, thrombocytopenia   
 Cardiac Disorder  Tachycardia       
 Eye Disorder     Vision blurred    
 Gastrointestinal Disorders  Abdominal pain, abdominal distension, gastroesophageal reflux disease, gingival hyperplasia   
 General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  Fatigue, peripheral edema   
 Infections and Infestations  Nasopharyngitis, herpes simplex, upper respiratory infection, oral candidiasis, herpes zoster, sinusitis, influenza, wound infection, implant infection, pneumonia, sepsis   
 Investigations   Hemoglobin decrease, liver function tests abnormal   
 Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  Hypercholesterolemia, hyperkalemia, hypomagnesemia, diabetes mellitus, hyperglycemia   
 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  Arthralgia, pain in limb, peripheral swelling, muscle cramps, myalgia   
 Nervous System Disorders  Dizziness (excluding vertigo)   
 Psychiatric Disorders  Anxiety           
 Renal and Urinary Disorders  Renal tubular necrosis, renal impairment, hematuria, urinary retention   
 Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  Cough, dyspnea, dyspnea exertional   
 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  Acne, pruritus, rash   
 Vascular Disorders  Hypertension aggravated, hypotension   
        The following additional adverse reactions have been associated with the exposure to mycophenolic acid (MPA) when administered as a sodium salt or as mofetil ester:
 

   Gastrointestinal:  Intestinal perforation, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastric ulcers, duodenal ulcers [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ], colitis (including CMV colitis), pancreatitis, esophagitis, and ileus.



   Infections:  Serious life-threatening infections such as meningitis and infectious endocarditis, tuberculosis, and atypical mycobacterial infection [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].



   Respiratory:  Interstitial lung disorders, including fatal pulmonary fibrosis.



   6.2??????????Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Myfortic or other MPA derivatives. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  Congenital malformations including ear, facial, cardiac and nervous system malformations and an increased incidence of first trimester pregnancy loss have been reported following exposure to MMF during pregnancy [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1) ]. 
 *  *  Cases of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), sometimes fatal. 
 *  Polyomavirus associated nephropathy (PVAN), especially due to BK virus infection, associated with serious outcomes, including deteriorating renal function and renal graft loss. 
 *  Viral reactivation in patients infected with HBV or HCV. 
   Infections [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5, 5.6) ] 
 *  Cases of pure red cell aplasia (PRCA) have been reported in patients treated with MPA derivatives in combination with other immunosuppressive agents [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7) ]. 
    The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Myfortic: agranulocytosis, asthenia, osteomyelitis, lymphadenopathy, lymphopenia, wheezing, dry mouth, gastritis, peritonitis, anorexia, alopecia, pulmonary edema, Kaposi???s sarcoma.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: EMBRYOFETAL TOXICITY, MALIGNANCIES, AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS

  WARNING: EMBRYOFETAL TOXICITY, MALIGNANCIES, AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS

    *  Use during pregnancy is associated with increased risks of pregnancy loss and congenital malformations. Females of reproductive potential must be counseled regarding pregnancy prevention and planning [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1), Use in Specific Populations (8.1, 8.6)]. 
 *  Increased risk of development of lymphoma and other malignancies, particularly of the skin, due to immunosuppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]. 
 *  Increased susceptibility to bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5, 5.6)]. 
 *  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe Myfortic. Patients receiving Myfortic should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physician responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: EMBRYOFETAL TOXICITY, MALIGNANCIES, AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Use during pregnancy is associated with increased risks of pregnancy loss and congenital malformations. Females of reproductive potential must be counseled regarding pregnancy prevention and planning. (5.1, 8.1, 8.6) 
 *  Increased risk of development of lymphoma and other malignancies, particularly of the skin, due to immunosuppression. (5.4) 
 *  Increased susceptibility to bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections. (5.5, 5.6) 
 *  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe Myfortic. (5.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5??????????WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  New or Reactivated Viral Infections: Consider reducing immunosuppression. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Blood Dyscrasias including Pure Red Cell Aplasia (PRCA): Monitor for neutropenia or anemia; consider treatment interruption or dose reduction. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Serious GI Tract Complications (gastrointestinal bleeding, perforations and ulcers): Administer with caution to patients with active digestive system disease. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Immunizations: Avoid live vaccines. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Patients with Hereditary Deficiency of Hypoxanthine-guanine Phosphoribosyl-transferase (HGPRT): May cause exacerbation of disease symptoms; avoid use. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1??????????Embryofetal Toxicity



   Use of Myfortic during pregnancy is associated with an increased risk of first trimester pregnancy loss and an increased risk of congenital malformations, especially external ear and other facial abnormalities including cleft lip and palate, and anomalies of the distal limbs, heart, esophagus, kidney, and nervous system [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].  



    5.2??????????Pregnancy Exposure Prevention and Planning



  Females of reproductive potential must be aware of the increased risk of first trimester pregnancy loss and congenital malformations and must be counseled regarding pregnancy prevention and planning. For recommended pregnancy testing and contraception methods [see Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ].



    5.3??????????Management of Immunosuppression



  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe Myfortic. Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physicians responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient [ see Boxed Warning  ].



    5.4??????????Lymphoma and Other Malignancies



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Myfortic, are at increased risk of developing lymphomas and other malignancies, particularly of the skin [ see Adverse Reactions (6)  ]. The risk appears to be related to the intensity and duration of immunosuppression rather than to the use of any specific agent.



 As usual for patients with increased risk for skin cancer, exposure to sunlight and UV light should be limited by wearing protective clothing and using a sunscreen with a high protection factor.



 Post-transplant lymphoproliferative disorder (PTLD) has been reported in immunosuppressed organ transplant recipients. The majority of PTLD events appear related to Epstein Barr Virus (EBV) infection. The risk of PTLD appears greatest in those individuals who are EBV seronegative, a population which includes many young children.



    5.5??????????Serious Infections



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Myfortic, are at increased risk of developing bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, and new or reactivated viral infections including opportunistic infections [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]. These infections may lead to serious, including fatal outcomes. Because of the danger of oversuppression of the immune system which can increase susceptibility to infection, combination immunosuppressant therapy should be used with caution.



    5.6??????????New or Reactivated Viral Infections



  Polyomavirus associated nephropathy (PVAN), JC virus associated progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), cytomegalovirus (CMV) infections, reactivation of hepatitis B (HBV) or hepatitis C (HCV) have been reported in patients treated with immunosuppressants, including the mycophenolic acid (MPA) derivatives Myfortic and MMF. Reduction in immunosuppression should be considered for patients who develop evidence of new or reactivated viral infections. Physicians should also consider the risk that reduced immunosuppression represents to the functioning allograft.



 PVAN, especially due to BK virus infection, is associated with serious outcomes, including deteriorating renal function and renal graft loss. Patient monitoring may help detect patients at risk for PVAN.



 PML, which is sometimes fatal, commonly presents with hemiparesis, apathy, confusion, cognitive deficiencies, and ataxia. Risk factors for PML include treatment with immunosuppressant therapies and impairment of immune function. In immunosuppressed patients, physicians should consider PML in the differential diagnosis in patients reporting neurological symptoms and consultation with a neurologist should be considered as clinically indicated.



 The risk of CMV viremia and CMV disease is highest among transplant recipients seronegative for CMV at time of transplant who receive a graft from a CMV seropositive donor. Therapeutic approaches to limiting CMV disease exist and should be routinely provided. Patient monitoring may help detect patients at risk for CMV disease. [ see Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].



 Viral reactivation has been reported in patients infected with HBV or HCV. Monitoring infected patients for clinical and laboratory signs of active HBV or HCV infection is recommended.



    5.7??????????Blood Dyscrasias Including Pure Red Cell Aplasia



  Cases of pure red cell aplasia (PRCA) have been reported in patients treated with MPA derivatives in combination with other immunosuppressive agents. The mechanism for MPA derivatives induced PRCA is unknown; the relative contribution of other immunosuppressants and their combinations in an immunosuppressive regimen is also unknown. In some cases PRCA was found to be reversible with dose reduction or cessation of therapy with MPA derivatives. In transplant patients, however, reduced immunosuppression may place the graft at risk. Changes to Myfortic therapy should only be undertaken under appropriate supervision in transplant recipients in order to minimize the risk of graft rejection.



 Patients receiving Myfortic should be monitored for blood dyscrasias (e.g., neutropenia or anemia). The development of neutropenia may be related to Myfortic itself, concomitant medications, viral infections, or some combination of these reactions. Complete blood count should be performed weekly during the first month, twice monthly for the second and the third month of treatment, then monthly through the first year. If blood dyscrasias occur [neutropenia develops (ANC &lt;1.3 ?? 10  3  /mcL) or anemia], dosing with Myfortic should be interrupted or the dose reduced, appropriate tests performed, and the patient managed accordingly.



    5.8??????????Serious GI Tract Complications



  Gastrointestinal bleeding (requiring hospitalization), intestinal perforations, gastric ulcers, and duodenal ulcers have been reported in patients treated with Myfortic. Myfortic should be administered with caution in patients with active serious digestive system disease.



    5.9??????????Immunizations



  The use of live attenuated vaccines should be avoided during treatment with Myfortic; examples include (but not limited to) the following: intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, BCG, yellow fever, varicella, and TY21a typhoid vaccines.



    5.10??????????Rare Hereditary Deficiencies



  Myfortic is an inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase inhibitor (IMPDH Inhibitor). Myfortic should be avoided in patients with rare hereditary deficiency of hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyl-transferase (HGPRT) such as Lesch-Nyhan and Kelley-Seegmiller syndromes because it may cause an exacerbation of disease symptoms characterized by the overproduction and accumulation of uric acid leading to symptoms associated with gout such as acute arthritis, tophi, nephrolithiasis or urolithiasis and renal disease including renal failure.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
