<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="naftin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions are application site reactions (2%). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merz Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 877-743-8454 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In two randomized, vehicle-controlled trials, 1143 subjects were treated with NAFTIN Gel versus 571 subjects treated with the vehicle. The trial subjects were 12 to 92 years old, were primarily male (76%), and were 59% Caucasian, 38% Black or African American, and 23% Hispanic or Latino. Subjects received doses once daily, topically, for 2 weeks to cover the affected skin areas plus a 1/2-inch margin of surrounding healthy skin. The most common adverse reactions were application site reactions which occurred at the rate of 2% in NAFTIN Gel arm versus 1% in vehicle arm. Most adverse reactions were mild in severity.



 In an open-label pediatric pharmacokinetics and safety trial 22 pediatric subjects 12-17 years of age with interdigital tinea pedis received NAFTIN Gel. The incidence of adverse reactions in the pediatric population was similar to that observed in adult population.



 Cumulative irritancy testing revealed the potential for NAFTIN Gel to cause irritation. There was no evidence that NAFTIN Gel causes contact sensitization, phototoxicity, or photoallergenicity in healthy skin.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of naftifine hydrochloride: blisters, burning sensation, crusting, dryness, erythema/redness, inflammation, irritation, maceration, pain, pruritus [mild]/itching, rash and swelling.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   If redness or irritation develops with the use of NAFTIN Gel treatment should be discontinued. (  5.1  )



 



   5.1 Local Adverse Reactions



  If irritation or sensitivity develops with the use of NAFTIN Gel, treatment should be discontinued.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
