<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="namzaric" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed below and elsewhere in the labeling.



 *  Cardiovascular Conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Peptic Ulcer Disease and Gastrointestinal Bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Nausea and Vomiting [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Genitourinary Conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Pulmonary Conditions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
   *  The most common adverse reactions occurring at a frequency of at least 5% and greater than placebo with memantine hydrochloride extended-release 28 mg/day were headache, diarrhea, and dizziness (  6.1  ) 
 *  The most common adverse reactions occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in patients receiving donepezil and at twice or more the placebo rate, include diarrhea, anorexia, vomiting, nausea, and ecchymosis (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Forest Laboratories, LLC. at 1-800-678-1605 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Memantine Hydrochloride  



 Memantine hydrochloride extended-release was evaluated in a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in 676 patients with moderate to severe dementia of the Alzheimer's type (341 patients treated with memantine 28 mg/day dose and 335 patients treated with placebo) for a treatment period up to 24 weeks. Of the patients randomized, 236 treated with memantine 28 mg/day and 227 treated with placebo were on a stable dose of donepezil for 3 months prior to screening.



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation with Memantine Hydrochloride  



 In the placebo-controlled clinical trial of memantine hydrochloride extended-release, the proportion of patients in the memantine hydrochloride extended-release 28 mg/day dose group and in the placebo group who discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions was 10% and 6%, respectively. The most common adverse reaction in the memantine hydrochloride extended-release treated group that led to treatment discontinuation was dizziness, at a rate of 1.5%.



     Most Common Adverse Reactions with Memantine Hydrochloride  



 The most common adverse reactions with memantine hydrochloride extended-release in patients with moderate to severe Alzheimer's disease, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in the memantine hydrochloride extended-release group and at a higher frequency than placebo, were headache, diarrhea, and dizziness.



   Table 1  lists adverse reactions that occurred at an incidence of &gt;= 2% in the memantine hydrochloride extended-release treated group and occurred at a rate greater than placebo.



 Table 1: Adverse reactions with memantine hydrochloride extended-release in patients with moderate to severe Alzheimer's disease 
   Adverse Reaction                             Placebo    (n = 335)    %      Memantine hydrochloride    extended-release    28 mg    (n = 341)    %     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                  
 Diarrhea                                     4                          5                                
 Constipation                                 1                          3                                
 Abdominal pain                               1                          2                                
 Vomiting                                     1                          2                                
   Infections and Infestations                 
 Influenza                                    3                          4                                
   Investigations                                                                                         
 Increased weight                             1                          3                                
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
 Back pain                                    1                          3                                
   Nervous System Disorders                    
 Headache                                     5                          6                                
 Dizziness                                    1                          5                                
 Somnolence                                   1                          3                                
   Psychiatric Disorders                       
 Anxiety                                      3                          4                                
 Depression                                   1                          3                                
 Aggression                                   1                          2                                
   Renal and Urinary Disorders                 
 Urinary incontinence                         1                          2                                
   Vascular Disorders                          
 Hypertension                                 2                          4                                
 Hypotension                                  1                          2                                
             Donepezil hydrochloride  
 

     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation with Donepezil Hydrochloride  



 In controlled clinical trials of donepezil hydrochloride, the rate of discontinuation due to adverse reactions for patients treated with donepezil hydrochloride was approximately 12%, compared to 7% for patients treated with placebo. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation, defined as those occurring in at least 2% of donepezil hydrochloride patients and at twice or more the incidence seen with placebo, were anorexia (2%), nausea (2%), diarrhea (2%) and urinary tract infection (2%).



     Most Common Adverse Reactions with Donepezil Hydrochloride  



 The most common adverse reactions reported with donepezil hydrochloride in controlled clinical trials in patients with severe Alzheimer's disease, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% in the donepezil hydrochloride group and at twice or more the placebo rate, were diarrhea, anorexia, vomiting, nausea, and ecchymosis. The most common adverse reactions reported with donepezil hydrochloride in controlled clinical trials in patients with mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease were insomnia, muscle cramp, and fatigue.



   Table 2  lists adverse reactions that occurred at an incidence of &gt;= 2% in the donepezil hydrochloride group and at a rate greater than placebo in controlled trials in patients with severe Alzheimer's disease.



 Table 2: Adverse reactions with donepezil hydrochloride in patients with severe Alzheimer's disease 
   Body System/Adverse Event                                 Placebo(n = 392)    %      Donepezil hydrochloride    10 mg/day    (n = 501)    %     
   Percent of Patients with any Adverse Event                73           81                              
   Body as a Whole                                          
 Accident                                                  12           13                                
 Infection                                                 9            11                                
 Headache                                                  3            4                                 
 Pain                                                      2            3                                 
 Back pain                                                 2            3                                 
 Fever                                                     1            2                                 
 Chest pain                                                &lt; 1          2                                 
   Cardiovascular System                                    
 Hypertension                                              2            3                                 
 Hemorrhage                                                1            2                                 
 Syncope                                                   1            2                                 
   Digestive System                                         
 Diarrhea                                                  4            10                                
 Vomiting                                                  4            8                                 
 Anorexia                                                  4            8                                 
 Nausea                                                    2            6                                 
   Hemic and Lymphatic System                               
 Ecchymosis                                                2            5                                 
   Metabolic and Nutritional Systems                        
 Increased creatine phosphokinase                          1            3                                 
 Dehydration                                               1            2                                 
 Hyperlipemia                                              &lt; 1          2                                 
   Nervous System                                           
 Insomnia                                                  4            5                                 
 Hostility                                                 2            3                                 
 Nervousness                                               2            3                                 
 Hallucinations                                            1            3                                 
 Somnolence                                                1            2                                 
 Dizziness                                                 1            2                                 
 Depression                                                1            2                                 
 Confusion                                                 1            2                                 
 Emotional lability                                        1            2                                 
 Personality disorder                                      1            2                                 
   Skin and Appendages                                      
 Eczema                                                    2            3                                 
   Urogenital System                                        
 Urinary incontinence                                      1            2                                 
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of memantine hydrochloride and donepezil hydrochloride. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Memantine Hydrochloride  



 Acute renal failure, agranulocytosis, cardiac failure congestive, hepatitis, leukopenia (including neutropenia), pancreatitis, pancytopenia, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, suicidal ideation, thrombocytopenia, and thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura.



     Donepezil Hydrochloride  



 Abdominal pain, agitation, cholecystitis, confusion, convulsions, hallucinations, heart block (all types), hemolytic anemia, hepatitis, hyponatremia, neuroleptic malignant syndrome, pancreatitis, and rash.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  NAMZARIC is likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia (  5.1  ) 
 *  NAMZARIC may have vagotonic effects on the sinoatrial and atrioventricular nodes manifesting as bradycardia or heart block (  5.2  ) 
 *  Monitor patients for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers (  5.3  ) 
 *  NAMZARIC can cause diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting (  5.4  ) 
 *  NAMZARIC may cause bladder outflow obstructions (  5.5  ) 
 *  Conditions that raise urine pH may decrease the urinary elimination of memantine, resulting in increased plasma levels of memantine (  5.5  ,  7.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anesthesia



  Donepezil hydrochloride, as a cholinesterase inhibitor, is likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia.



    5.2 Cardiovascular Conditions



  Because of their pharmacological action, cholinesterase inhibitors may have vagotonic effects on the sinoatrial and atrioventricular nodes. This effect may manifest as bradycardia or heart block in patients both with and without known underlying cardiac conduction abnormalities. Syncopal episodes have been reported in association with the use of donepezil hydrochloride.



    5.3 Peptic Ulcer Disease and Gastrointestinal Bleeding



  Through their primary action, cholinesterase inhibitors may be expected to increase gastric acid secretion due to increased cholinergic activity. Clinical studies of donepezil hydrochloride in a dose of 5 mg/day to 10 mg/day have shown no increase, relative to placebo, in the incidence of either peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding. Patients treated with NAMZARIC should be monitored closely for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers, e.g., those with a history of ulcer disease or those receiving concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs).



    5.4 Nausea and Vomiting



  Donepezil hydrochloride, when initiated, as a predictable consequence of its pharmacological properties, has been shown to produce diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting. Although in most cases, these effects have been mild and transient, sometimes lasting one to three weeks, and have resolved during continued use of donepezil hydrochloride, patients should be observed closely at the initiation of treatment.



    5.5 Genitourinary Conditions



  Although not observed in clinical trials of donepezil hydrochloride, cholinomimetics may cause bladder outflow obstruction.



 Conditions that raise urine pH may decrease the urinary elimination of memantine resulting in increased plasma levels of memantine [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



    5.6 Seizures



  Cholinomimetics, including donepezil hydrochloride, are believed to have some potential to cause generalized convulsions. However, seizure activity also may be a manifestation of Alzheimer's disease.



    5.7 Pulmonary Conditions



  Because of their cholinomimetic actions, cholinesterase inhibitors should be prescribed with care to patients with a history of asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
