<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="naprosyn0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions reported in controlled clinical trials in 960 patients treated for rheumatoid arthritis or osteoarthritis are listed below. In general, reactions in patients treated chronically were reported 2 to 10 times more frequently than they were in short-term studies in the 962 patients treated for mild to moderate pain or for dysmenorrhea. The most frequent complaints reported related to the gastrointestinal tract.



 A clinical study found gastrointestinal reactions to be more frequent and more severe in rheumatoid arthritis patients taking daily doses of 1500 mg naproxen compared to those taking 750 mg naproxen (see    CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY    ).



 In controlled clinical trials with about 80 pediatric patients and in well-monitored, open-label studies with about 400 pediatric patients with juvenile arthritis treated with naproxen, the incidence of rash and prolonged bleeding times were increased, the incidence of gastrointestinal and central nervous system reactions were about the same, and the incidence of other reactions were lower in pediatric patients than in adults.



 In patients taking naproxen in clinical trials, the most frequently reported adverse experiences in approximately 1% to 10% of patients are:



    Gastrointestinal (GI) Experiences, including:  heartburn (Incidence of reported reaction between 3% and 9%. Those reactions occurring in less than 3% of the patients are unmarked.) , abdominal pain, nausea, constipation, diarrhea, dyspepsia, stomatitis
 

   Central Nervous System:  headache, dizziness, drowsiness, lightheadedness, vertigo



   Dermatologic:  pruritus (itching), skin eruptions, ecchymoses, sweating, purpura



   Special Senses:  tinnitus, visual disturbances, hearing disturbances



   Cardiovascular:  edema, palpitations



   General:  dyspnea, thirst



 In patients taking NSAIDs, the following adverse experiences have also been reported in approximately 1% to 10% of patients.



   Gastrointestinal (GI) Experiences, including:  flatulence, gross bleeding/perforation, GI ulcers (gastric/duodenal), vomiting



   General:  abnormal renal function, anemia, elevated liver enzymes, increased bleeding time, rashes



 The following are additional adverse experiences reported in &lt;1% of patients taking naproxen during clinical trials and through postmarketing reports. Those adverse reactions observed through postmarketing reports are italicized.



   Body as a Whole:    anaphylactoid reactions, angioneurotic edema, menstrual disorders, pyrexia (chills and fever)  



   Cardiovascular:    congestive heart failure, vasculitis, hypertension, pulmonary edema  



   Gastrointestinal:    inflammation, bleeding (sometimes fatal, particularly in the elderly), ulceration, perforation and obstruction of the upper or lower gastrointestinal tract. Esophagitis, stomatitis, hematemesis,  pancreatitis, vomiting,  colitis,    exacerbation of inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease).  



   Hepatobiliary:  jaundice,  abnormal liver function tests, hepatitis (some cases have been fatal)  



   Hemic and Lymphatic:    eosinophilia, leucopenia,  melena, thrombocytopenia, agranulocytosis,  granulocytopenia, hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia  



   Metabolic and Nutritional:    hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia  



   Nervous System:  inability to concentrate,  depression, dream abnormalities, insomnia, malaise,     myalgia, muscle weakness,     aseptic meningitis, cognitive dysfunction, convulsions  



   Respiratory:    eosinophilic pneumonitis, asthma  



   Dermatologic:    alopecia, urticaria,  skin rashes,  toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme,     erythema nodosum, fixed drug eruption, lichen planus, pustular reaction, systemic lupus erythematoses, bullous reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, photosensitive dermatitis,     photosensitivity reactions, including rare cases resembling porphyria cutanea tarda (pseudoporphyria) or epidermolysis bullosa. If skin fragility, blistering or other symptoms suggestive of pseudoporphyria occur, treatment should be discontinued and the patient monitored.  



   Special Senses:    hearing impairment, corneal opacity, papillitis, retrobulbar optic neuritis, papilledema  



   Urogenital:    glomerular nephritis, hematuria, hyperkalemia, interstitial nephritis, nephrotic syndrome, renal disease, renal failure, renal papillary necrosis, raised serum creatinine  



   Reproduction (female):    infertility  



 In patients taking NSAIDs, the following adverse experiences have also been reported in &lt;1% of patients.



   Body as a Whole:  fever, infection, sepsis, anaphylactic reactions, appetite changes, death



   Cardiovascular:  hypertension, tachycardia, syncope, arrhythmia, hypotension, myocardial infarction



   Gastrointestinal:  dry mouth, esophagitis, gastric/peptic ulcers, gastritis, glossitis, eructation



   Hepatobiliary:  hepatitis, liver failure



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  rectal bleeding, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  weight changes



   Nervous System:  anxiety, asthenia, confusion, nervousness, paresthesia, somnolence, tremors, convulsions, coma, hallucinations



   Respiratory:  asthma, respiratory depression, pneumonia



   Dermatologic:  exfoliative dermatitis



   Special Senses:  blurred vision, conjunctivitis



   Urogenital:  cystitis, dysuria, oliguria/polyuria, proteinuria
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  Cardiovascular Risk

    *  NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk (see WARNINGS). 
 *  Naproxen as NAPROSYN, EC-NAPROSYN, ANAPROX, ANAPROX DS or NAPROSYN Suspension is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery (see WARNINGS). 
      Gastrointestinal Risk
     *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events (see WARNINGS). 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
