<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="naropin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS:

  Reactions to ropivacaine are characteristic of those associated with other amide-type local anesthetics. A major cause of adverse reactions to this group of drugs may be associated with excessive plasma levels, which may be due to overdosage, unintentional intravascular injection or slow metabolic degradation.



 The reported adverse events are derived from clinical studies conducted in the U.S. and other countries. The reference drug was usually bupivacaine. The studies used a variety of premedications, sedatives, and surgical procedures of varying length. A total of 3,988 patients have been exposed to Naropin at concentrations up to 1% in clinical trials. Each patient was counted once for each type of adverse event.



        Incidence    &gt;=  5%  

  For the indications of epidural administration in surgery, cesarean section, postoperative pain management, peripheral nerve block, and local infiltration, the following treatment-emergent adverse events were reported with an incidence of &gt;=5% in all clinical studies (N=3988):  hypotension (37%), nausea (24.8%), vomiting (11.6%), bradycardia (9.3%), fever (9.2%), pain (8%), postoperative complications (7.1%), anemia (6.1%), paresthesia (5.6%), headache (5.1%), pruritus (5.1%), and back pain (5%).



     Incidence 1 to 5%  

  Urinary retention, dizziness, rigors, hypertension, tachycardia, anxiety, oliguria, hypoesthesia, chest pain, hypokalemia, dyspnea, cramps, and urinary tract infection.



        Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials    

  The reported adverse events are derived from controlled clinical studies with Naropin (concentrations ranged from 0.125% to 1% for Naropin and 0.25% to 0.75% for bupivacaine) in the U.S. and other countries involving 3,094 patients. Table 3A and 3B list adverse events (number and percentage) that occurred in at least 1% of Naropin-treated patients in these studies. The majority of patients receiving concentrations higher than 5 mg/mL (0.5%) were treated with Naropin.



 



 



 



  Table 3A  Table 3B      Incidence &lt;1%  

  The following adverse events were reported during the Naropin clinical program in more than one patient (N=3988), occurred at an overall incidence of &lt;1%, and were considered relevant:



   Application Site Reactions  - injection site pain



   Cardiovascular System  - vasovagal reaction, syncope, postural hypotension, non-specific ECG abnormalities



   Female Reproductive  - poor progression of labor, uterine atony



   Gastrointestinal System  - fecal incontinence, tenesmus, neonatal vomiting



   General and Other Disorders  - hypothermia, malaise, asthenia, accident and/or injury



   Hearing and Vestibular  - tinnitus, hearing abnormalities



   Heart Rate and Rhythm  - extrasystoles, non-specific arrhythmias, atrial fibrillation



   Liver and Biliary System  - jaundice



   Metabolic Disorders  - hypomagnesemia



   Musculoskeletal System  - myalgia



   Myo/Endo/Pericardium  - ST segment changes, myocardial infarction



   Nervous System  - tremor, Horner's syndrome, paresis, dyskinesia, neuropathy, vertigo, coma, convulsion, hypokinesia, hypotonia, ptosis, stupor



   Psychiatric Disorders  - agitation, confusion, somnolence, nervousness, amnesia, hallucination, emotional lability, insomnia, nightmares



   Respiratory System  - bronchospasm, coughing



   Skin Disorders  - rash, urticaria



   Urinary System Disorders  - urinary incontinence, micturition disorder



   Vascular  - deep vein thrombosis, phlebitis, pulmonary embolism



   Vision  - vision abnormalities



 For the indication epidural anesthesia for surgery, the 15 most common adverse events were compared between different concentrations of Naropin and bupivacaine. Table 4 is based on data from trials in the U.S. and other countries where Naropin was administered as an epidural anesthetic for surgery.



 



 Using data from the same studies, the number (%) of patients experiencing hypotension is displayed by patient age, drug and concentration in Table 5. In Table 6, the adverse events for Naropin are broken down by gender.



 



 



  Table 4  Table 5  Table 6        Systemic Reactions    

  The most commonly encountered acute adverse experiences that demand immediate countermeasures are related to the central nervous system and the cardiovascular system. These adverse experiences are generally dose-related and due to high plasma levels that may result from overdosage, rapid absorption from the injection site, diminished tolerance or from unintentional intravascular injection of the local anesthetic solution. In addition to systemic dose-related toxicity, unintentional subarachnoid injection of drug during the intended performance of lumbar epidural block or nerve blocks near the vertebral column (especially in the head and neck region) may result in underventilation or apnea ("Total or High Spinal"). Also, hypotension due to loss of sympathetic tone and respiratory paralysis or underventilation due to cephalad extension of the motor level of anesthesia may occur. This may lead to secondary cardiac arrest if untreated. Factors influencing plasma protein binding, such as acidosis, systemic diseases that alter protein production or competition with other drugs for protein binding sites, may diminish individual tolerance.



 Epidural administration of Naropin has, in some cases, as with other local anesthetics, been associated with transient increases in temperature to &gt;38.5 C. This occurred more frequently at doses of Naropin &gt;16 mg/h.



      Neurologic Reactions  

  These are characterized by excitation and/or depression. Restlessness, anxiety, dizziness, tinnitus, blurred vision or tremors may occur, possibly proceeding to convulsions. However, excitement may be transient or absent, with depression being the first manifestation of an adverse reaction. This may quickly be followed by drowsiness merging into unconsciousness and respiratory arrest. Other central nervous system effects may be nausea, vomiting, chills, and constriction of the pupils.



 The incidence of convulsions associated with the use of local anesthetics varies with the route of administration and the total dose administered. In a survey of studies of epidural anesthesia, overt toxicity progressing to convulsions occurred in approximately 0.1% of local anesthetic administrations.



 The incidence of adverse neurological reactions associated with the use of local anesthetics may be related to the total dose and concentration of local anesthetic administered and are also dependent upon the particular drug used, the route of administration, and the physical status of the patient. Many of these observations may be related to local anesthetic techniques, with or without a contribution from the drug. During lumbar epidural block, occasional unintentional penetration of the subarachnoid space by the catheter or needle may occur. Subsequent adverse effects may depend partially on the amount of drug administered intrathecally as well as the physiological and physical effects of a dural puncture. These observations may include spinal block of varying magnitude (including high or total spinal block), hypotension secondary to spinal block, urinary retention, loss of bladder and bowel control (fecal and urinary incontinence), and loss of perineal sensation and sexual function. Signs and symptoms of subarachnoid block typically start within 2 to 3 minutes of injection. Doses of 15 and 22.5 mg of Naropin resulted in sensory levels as high as T5 and T4, respectively. Analgesia started in the sacral dermatomes in 2 to 3 minutes and extended to the T10 level in 10 to 13 minutes and lasted for approximately 2 hours. Other neurological effects following unintentional subarachnoid administration during epidural anesthesia may include persistent anesthesia, paresthesia, weakness, paralysis of the lower extremities, and loss of sphincter control; all of which may have slow, incomplete or no recovery. Headache, septic meningitis, meningismus, slowing of labor, increased incidence of forceps delivery, or cranial nerve palsies due to traction on nerves from loss of cerebrospinal fluid have been reported (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  discussion of Lumbar Epidural Block). A high spinal is characterized by paralysis of the arms, loss of consciousness, respiratory paralysis and bradycardia.



      Cardiovascular System Reactions  

  HIgh doses or unintentional intravascular injection may lead to high plasma levels and related depression of the myocardium, decreased cardiac output, heart block, hypotension, bradycardia, ventricular arrhythmias, including ventricular tachycardia and ventricular fibrillation, and possibly cardiac arrest (see  WARNINGS, PRECAUTIONS,  and  OVERDOSAGE  ).



      Allergic Reactions  

  Allergic type reactions are rare and may occur as a result of sensitivity to the local anesthetic (see  WARNINGS  ). These reactions are characterized by signs such as urticaria, pruritus, erythema, angioneurotic edema (including laryngeal edema), tachycardia, sneezing, nausea, vomiting, dizziness, syncope, excessive sweating, elevated temperature, and possibly, anaphylactoid symptomatology (including severe hypotension). Cross-sensitivity among members of the amide-type local anesthetic group has been reported. The usefulness of screening for sensitivity has not been definitively established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
