<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="natroba" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse events (&gt;1% ) were application site erythema and ocular erythema. (  6.1  )



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ParaPRO, LLC at 1-855-628-7622 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 NATROBA Topical Suspension was studied in two randomized, active-controlled trials (N=552) in subjects with head lice; the results are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1: Selected Adverse Events Occurring in at least 1% of Subjects 
 Signs                                            Spinosad(N=552)               Permethrin 1%(N=457)        
  
 Application site erythema                            17 (3%)                         31 (7%)               
 Ocular erythema                                      12 (2%)                         15 (3%)               
 Application site irritation                           5 (1%)                          7 (2%)               
      Other less common reactions (less than 1% but more than 0.1%) were application site dryness, application site exfoliation, alopecia, and dry skin.Systemic safety was not assessed in pediatric subjects under 6 months of age as laboratory parameters were not monitored in these controlled studies.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Benzyl alcohol toxicity: Not recommended in infants below the age of 6 months; potential for increased systemic absorption. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Benzyl Alcohol Toxicity



  NATROBA Topical Suspension contains benzyl alcohol and is not recommended for use in neonates and infants below the age of 6 months. Systemic exposure to benzyl alcohol has been associated with serious adverse reactions and death in neonates and low birth-weight infants  [See  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
