<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="natrecor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3%) are hypotension, headache, nausea, and back pain. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Scios LLC at 1-877-462-8732 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. A causal relationship for NATRECOR  (r)  cannot be reliably established in individual cases.



 Adverse drug reactions that occurred at least &gt;=2% more frequently on NATRECOR  (r)  than on placebo during the first 24 hours of infusion (excluding the ASCEND-HF study) are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3: Adverse Drug ReactionsAdverse drug reaction is defined as an adverse event with a frequency in the NATRECOR(r) group &gt;=2% and occurred at a higher frequency than in the placebo group. Reported at &gt;=2% Frequency During the First 24 Hours After the Start of Infusion in Long Infusion TrialsTrials in which NATRECOR(r) was administered as a continuous infusion for &gt;=12 hours. of NATRECOR(r) at the Recommended Dose excluding ASCEND-HF Results 
 System Organ ClassAdverse Reaction  NATRECOR  (r)  (N=331)0.01 mcg/kg/min% (n)        Placebo (N=188)% (n)          
  
   Vascular Disorders                                                                                       
 Hypotension                                      12 (41)                             4 (7)                 
   GI Disorders                                                                                             
 Nausea                                           3 (11)                              1 (2)                 
   Musculoskeletal Disorders                                                                                
 Back pain                                        3 (11)                              1 (2)                 
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
 Headache                                         7 (24)                             6 (11)                 
 Dizziness                                         2 (8)                              2 (3)                 
         Laboratory adverse drug reactions that occurred in &gt;=2% of patients and collected during the first 14 days after the start of NATRECOR  (r)  infusion included: hypoglycemia.
 

   Worsening Renal Function



 In the ASCEND-HF trial, through Day 30, the incidence of renal impairment as measured by a &gt;25% decrease in glomerular filtration rate (calculated based on serum creatinine) was observed in 31.4% and 29.5% in the NATRECOR  (r)  and placebo groups, respectively. Other metrics of decompensated renal function such as an increase in creatinine of &gt; 0.5 mg/dl, a 50% increase in creatinine or a value of &gt;= 2 or 100% increase in creatinine were more frequent in the NATRECOR  (r)  group. At 30 days post enrollment, more subjects in the NATRECOR  (r)  group had elevated levels of creatinine of 50% greater than baseline compared to placebo 4.6% versus 3.3%. In the ASCEND-HF study there were relatively few subjects requiring either hemofiltration or dialysis.



 In the PRECEDENT trial, the incidence of elevations in serum creatinine to &gt;0.5 mg/dL above baseline through Day 14 was higher in the NATRECOR  (r)  0.015 mcg/kg/min group (17%) and the NATRECOR  (r)  0.03 mcg/kg/min group (19%) than with standard therapy (11%). In the VMAC trial, through Day 30, the incidence of elevations in creatinine to &gt;0.5 mg/dL above baseline was 28% and 21% in the NATRECOR  (r)  (2 mcg/kg bolus followed by 0.01 mcg/kg/min) and nitroglycerin groups, respectively.



   Neutral Effect on Mortality



 A meta-analysis performed of seven clinical trials demonstrated NATRECOR  (r)  did not increase mortality in patients with acute decompensated heart failure (ADHF) at Day 30 or Day 180 (see  Figures 1  and  2  ). Data from seven studies in which 30-day data were collected are presented in Figure 1. The data depict hazard ratios (HR) and confidence intervals (CI) of mortality data for randomized and treated patients with NATRECOR  (r)  relative to active or placebo controls through Day 30 for each of the seven individual studies along with the overall combined estimate (Studies 311, 325, 326, 329 [PRECEDENT], 339 [VMAC], 341 [PROACTION], and A093 [ASCEND-HF]).



 Figure 1 (on logarithmic scale) also contains an estimate for the seven studies combined (n=8514). The results indicate that there is no increased mortality risk for NATRECOR  (r)  at Day 30 (seven studies pooled: HR=0.99; 95% CI: 0.80, 1.22). The percentages are the Kaplan-Meier estimates.




 *Studies 704.311, 704.325, 704.326, 704.329, 704.339, 704.341 and ASCEND-HF                            
  
   Figure 1: 30-Day All-Cause Mortality Hazard Ratios                                                   
                                                                                                        
       Figure 2 presents 180-day mortality hazard ratios from all six individual studies where 180-day data were collected (Studies 325, 326, 329, 339, 341 and A093 [ASCEND-HF]). The results indicate that with the addition of the ASCEND-HF data, there is no increased mortality risk for NATRECOR  (r)  at Day 180 (six studies pooled: HR=0.98; 95% CI: 0.88, 1.10).
 


 *Studies 704.325, 704.326, 704.329, 704.339, 704.341 and ASCEND-HF                                     
  
   Figure 2: 180-Day All-Cause Mortality Hazard Ratios                                                  
                                                                                                        
        Figure 1  Figure 2   6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of NATRECOR  (r)  . Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to estimate their frequency reliably or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  Hypersensitivity reactions 
 *  Infusion site extravasation 
 *  Pruritus 
 *  Rash 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypotension: Not recommended for patients for whom vasodilating agents are not appropriate, or other conditions in which cardiac output is dependent upon venous return, or for patients suspected to have low cardiac filling pressures. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Worsening renal impairment. Monitor serum creatinine both during and after NATRECOR  (r)  administration. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity: Serious hypersensitivity/allergic reactions have been reported. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypotension



  NATRECOR  (r)  may cause hypotension. In the ASCEND-HF trial, the incidence of symptomatic hypotension was 7.1% in NATRECOR  (r)  -treated patients compared to 4.0% in placebo-treated patients on a background of standard care. The risk of hypotension may be increased by the concomitant use of NATRECOR  (r)  with drugs affecting the renin-angiotensin system (i.e., angiotensin receptor blockers and/or angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors) or other afterload reducers. In the VMAC trial, in patients given the recommended dose (2 mcg/kg bolus followed by a 0.01 mcg/kg/min infusion) or the adjustable dose, the incidence of symptomatic hypotension in the first 24 hours was similar for NATRECOR  (r)  (4%) and IV nitroglycerin (5%). When hypotension occurred, however, the duration of symptomatic hypotension was longer with NATRECOR  (r)  (mean duration was 2.2 hours) than with nitroglycerin (mean duration was 0.7 hours).



 Administer NATRECOR  (r)  only in settings where blood pressure can be monitored closely and hypotension aggressively treated. Reduce the dose of or discontinue NATRECOR  (r)  in patients who develop hypotension [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  .



 Avoid administration of NATRECOR  (r)  in patients suspected of having, or known to have, low cardiac filling pressures.



 NATRECOR  (r)  is not recommended for patients for whom vasodilating agents are not appropriate, such as patients with significant valvular stenosis, restrictive or obstructive cardiomyopathy, constrictive pericarditis, pericardial tamponade, or other conditions in which cardiac output is dependent upon venous return, or for patients suspected to have low cardiac filling pressures [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.2 Worsening of Renal Function



  NATRECOR  (r)  may decrease renal function as judged by increases in serum creatinine. Monitor serum creatinine both during and after therapy has been completed. Monitor serum creatinine until values have stabilized. In patients with severe heart failure whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin aldosterone system, treatment with NATRECOR  (r)  may be associated with azotemia. When NATRECOR  (r)  was initiated at doses higher than 0.01 mcg/kg/min (0.015 and 0.03 mcg/kg/min), there was an increased rate of elevated serum creatinine over baseline compared with standard therapies, although the rate of acute renal failure and need for dialysis was not increased.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity



  Serious hypersensitivity/allergic reactions following administration of NATRECOR  (r)  have been reported.



 These reactions are more likely to occur in individuals with a history of sensitivity to recombinant peptides. Before therapy with NATRECOR  (r)  is instituted, careful inquiry should be made to determine whether the patient has had a previous hypersensitivity reaction to other recombinant peptides. If an allergic reaction to NATRECOR  (r)  occurs, discontinue the drug. Some serious hypersensitivity/allergic reactions may require treatment with epinephrine, oxygen, IV fluids, antihistamines, corticosteroids, pressor amines and airway management, as clinically indicated.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
