<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="navelbine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions, which may include fatalities, are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Myelosuppression [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1     )   ]  
 *  Pulmonary Toxicity and Respiratory Failure [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]  
 *  Constipation and Bowel Obstruction [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]  
 *  Extravasation Tissue Injury [see     Wa      rnings and Precautions (5.4     )   ]  
 *  Neurologic Toxicity [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ]  
 *  Hepatic Toxicity [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.6     )   ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 20%) are neutropenia, anemia, liver enzyme elevation, nausea, vomiting, asthenia, constipation, injection site reaction, and peripheral neuropathy (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pierre Fabre Pharmaceuticals at 1- 855-PFPHARM (1-855-737-4276) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under varying designs and in different patient populations, the adverse reaction rates reported in one clinical trial may not be easily compared to those rates reported in another clinical trial, and may not reflect the rates actually observed in clinical practice.



   Single Agent  



 The data below reflect exposure to NAVELBINE as a single agent administered at a dose of 30 mg/m2 on a weekly basis to 365 patients enrolled in 3 controlled studies for metastatic NSCLC and advanced breast cancer.  The population included 143 previously untreated metastatic NSCLC patients (Study 3) who received a median of 8 doses of NAVELBINE. The patients were aged 32 to 79 (median 61 years), 71% were male, 91% Caucasian, 48% had adenocarcinoma histology.  The data also reflect exposure to NAVELBINE in 222 patients with previously treated advanced breast cancer who received a median of 10 doses of NAVELBINE.  NAVELBINE is not indicated for the treatment of breast cancer.



 Selected adverse reactions reported in these studies are provided in Tables 1 and 2.  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 20%) of single agent NAVELBINE were leukopenia, neutropenia, anemia, Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) elevation, nausea, vomiting, constipation, asthenia, injection site reaction, and peripheral neuropathy.  The most common (&gt;= 5%) Grade 3 or 4 adverse reactions were neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, increased total bilirubin, AST elevation, injection site reaction and asthenia. Approximately 49% of NSCLC patients treated with Navelbine experienced at least one dose reduction due to an adverse reaction. Thirteen percent of patients discontinued NAVELBINE due to adverse reactions. The most frequent adverse reactions leading to NAVELBINE discontinuation were asthenia, dyspnea, nausea, constipation, anorexia, myasthenia and fever.



   Table 1: Hematologic Adverse Reactions Experienced in &gt; 5% of Patients Receiving NAVELBINE*:  




                   All patients (n=365)    NSCLC (n= 143)    
   Laboratory                                        
   Hematologic                                       
      Neutropenia  &lt; 2,000 cells/mm  3    90%              80%               
                  &lt; 500 cells/mm  3    36%              29%               
       Leukopenia  &lt; 4,000 cells/mm  3    92%              81%               
                  &lt; 1,000 cells/mm  3    15%              12%               
      Thrombocytopenia  &lt; 100,000 cells/mm  3    5%               4%                
       Anemia     &lt; 11 g/dl        83%              77%               
                   &lt; 8 g/dl        9%               1%                
   Hospitalizations due to neutropenic complications   9%               8%                
          *Grade based on modified criteria from the National Cancer Institute version 1.
 

 Patients with NSCLC had not received prior chemotherapy. The majority of the remaining patients had received prior chemotherapy.



   Table 2: Non-hematologic Adverse Reactions Experienced in  &gt;  5% of Patients Receiving NAVELBINE*:  




                   All grades       Grades 3+4       
                   All Patients       NSCLC          All Patients        NSCLC         
    Laboratory     
        Hepatic     
        AST increased (n=346)   67%             54%               6%              3%                
        bilirubin increased (n=351)   13%             9%               7%               5%                
                   
    Clinical       
        Nausea     44%              34%              2%               1%               
        Asthenia   36%              27%              7%               5%               
        Constipation   35%              29%              3%               2%               
        Injection site reaction   28%              38%              2%               5%               
        Injection site pain   16%              13%              2%               1%               
        Neuropathy peripheral?   25%              20%              &lt;2%              1%               
        Vomiting   20%              15%              2%               1%               
        Diarrhea   17%              13%              1%               1%               
        Alopecia   12%              12%                &lt;  1%          1%               
        Phlebitis   7%               10%              &lt;1%              1%               
        Dyspnea    7%               3%               3%               2%               
           *Grade based on modified criteria from the National Cancer Institute version 1.
 

 Patients with NSCLC had not received prior chemotherapy. The majority of the remaining patients had received prior chemotherapy.



 ? Incidence of paresthesia plus hypesthesia.



   Myelosuppression:  In clinical trials, Grade 3-4 neutropenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia occurred in 69%, 9% and 1%, respectively of patients receiving single-agent NAVELBINE.  Neutropenia is the major dose-limiting toxicity.



   Neurotoxicity  : neurotoxicity was most commonly manifested as constipation, paresthesia, hypersthesia, and hyporeflexia.  Grade 3 and 4 neuropathy was observed in 1% of the patients receiving single-agent NAVELBINE.                    



   Injection site reactions:   Injection site reactions, including erythema, pain at injection site, and vein discoloration, occurred in approximately one third of patients; 5% were severe. Phlebitis (chemical phlebitis) along the vein proximal to the site of injection was reported in 10% of patients.



   Cardiovascular toxicity:  Chest pain occurred in 5% of patients;  myocardial infarction occurred in less than 0.1% of patients.



   Pulmonary Toxicity and Respiratory Failure:  Dyspnea (shortness of breath) was reported in 3% of patients; it was severe in 2%. Interstitial pulmonary changes were documented.



   Other:  Hemorrhagic cystitis and the syndrome of inappropriate ADH secretion were each reported in &lt;1% of patients.



   In Combination with Cisplatin  



 Table 3 presents the incidence of selected adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;= 10% of NAVELBINE treated patients reported in a randomized trial comparing the combination of NAVELBINE 25 mg/m  2  administered every week of each 28-day cycle and cisplatin 100 mg/m  2  administered on day 1 of each 28-day cycle versus cisplatin alone at the same dose and schedule in patients with previously untreated NSCLC (Study 1).



 Patients randomized to NAVELBINE plus cisplatin received a median of 3 cycles of treatment and those randomized to cisplatin alone received a median of 2 cycles of treatment.  Thirty-Five percent of the eligible patients in the combination arm required treatment discontinuation due to an adverse reaction compared to 19% in the cisplatin alone arm. The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 neutropenia was significantly higher in the NAVELBINE plus cisplatin arm (82%) compared to the cisplatin alone arm (5%).  Four patients in the NAVELBINE plus cisplatin arm died of neutropenic sepsis.  Seven additional deaths were reported in the combination arm: 2 from cardiac ischemia, 1 cerebrovascular accident, 1 multisystem failure due to an overdose of NAVELBINE, and 3 from febrile neutropenia.



   Table 3: Adverse Reactions Experienced by   &gt;  10% of Patients on NAVELBINE plus Cisplatin versus Single-Agent Cisplatin*  




                    NAVELBINE  25mg/m  2  plus  Cisplatin 100mg/m  2      
 Cisplatin 100 mg/m  2  (N=212)   (n=210)           
  All Grades       Grades 3+4         All Grades        Grades 3+4      
   Laboratory        Hematologic     
        Neutropenia    89%              82%              26%              5%               
        Anemia     89%              24%              72%              &lt;8%              
        Leukopenia    88%              58%              31%              &lt;1%              
        Thrombocytopenia    29%              5%               21%              &lt;2%              
        Febrile neutropenia     N/A              11%              N/A              0%               
       Renal       
       Blood creatinine increased   37%              4%               28%              &lt;5%              
    Clinical       
        Malaise/Fatigue/Lethargy    67%              12%              49%              8%               
        Vomiting    60%              13%              60%              14%              
        Nausea     58%              14%              57%              12%              
        Decreased apetite    46%              0%               37%              0%               
        Constipation    35%              3%               16%              1%               
        Alopecia    34%              0%               14%              0%               
        Weight decreased    34%              1%               21%              &lt;1%              
        Fever without infection    20%              2%               4%               0%               
        Hearing impaired    18%              4%               18%              &lt;4%              
        Injection site reaction    17%              &lt;1%              1%               0%               
        Diarrhea    17%              &lt;3%              11%              &lt;2%              
        Paraesthesia    17%              &lt;1%              10%              &lt;1%              
        Taste alterations    17%              0%               15%              0%               
        Peripheral numbness    11%              2%               7%               &lt;1%              
        Myalgia/Arthralgia    12%              &lt;1%              3%               &lt;1%              
        Phlebitis/Thrombosis/Embolism    10%              3%               &lt;1%              &lt;1%              
        Weakness    12%              &lt;3%              7%               2%               
        Infection    11%              &lt;6%              &lt;1%              &lt;1%              
        Respiratory tract infection    10%              &lt;5%              3%               3%               
           *Graded according to the standard SWOG criteria version 1.
 

 Categorical toxicity grade not specified



 Table 4 presents the incidence of selected adverse reactions, occurring in &gt;= 10% of NAVELBINE treated patients reported in a randomized trial of NAVELBINE plus cisplatin, vindesine plus cisplatin and NAVELBINE alone in patients with stage III or IV NSCLC who had not received prior chemotherapy.  A total of 604 patients received either NAVELBINE 30 mg/m  2  every week plus cisplatin 120 mg/m  2  on Day 1 and Day 29, then every 6 weeks thereafter (N=207), vindesine 3 mg/m  2  for 6 weeks, then every other week thereafter plus cisplatin 120 mg/m  2  on Days 1 and Day 29, then every 6 weeks thereafter (N=193) or NAVELBINE 30mg/m  2  every week (N=204).



 Patients randomized to NAVELBINE plus cisplatin received a median of 15 weeks of treatment, vindesine plus cisplatin 12 weeks and NAVELBINE received 13 weeks.  Study discontinuation due to an adverse reaction was required in 27, 22 and 10% of the patients randomized to NAVELBINE plus cisplatin, vindesine plus cisplatin and cisplatin alone arms, respectively.  Grade 3 and 4 neutropenia was significantly greater in the NAVELBINE plus cisplatin arm (78%) compared to vindesine plus cisplatin (48%) and NAVELBINE alone (53%).  Neurotoxicity, including peripheral neuropathy and constipation was reported in 44% (Grades 3-4, 7%) of the patients receiving NAVELBINE plus cisplatin, 58% (Grades 3-4, 17%) of the patients receiving vindesine and cisplatin and 44% (Grades 3-4, 8.5%) of the patients receiving NAVELBINE alone.



   Table 4: Adverse Reactions Experienced by  &gt;  10 % of Patients from a Comparative Trial of NAVELBINE Plus Cisplatin versus Vindesine Plus Cisplatin versus Single-Agent NAVELBINE*  




                     NAVELBINE  /Cisplatin     Vindesine/Cisplatin        NAVELBINE  S   
  All Grades       Grades 3+4       All Grades       Grades 3+4       All Grades       Grades 3+4       
    Laboratory     
      Hematologic     
       Neutropenia   95%              78%             79%               48%              85%              53%              
       Leukopenia   94%              57%              82%              27%              83%              32%              
       Thrombocytopenia   15%              4%               10%              3.5%             3%               0%               
      Renal        
       Blood creatinine increased |   46%              N/A              37%              N/A              13%              N/A              
     Clinical      
       Nausea/Vomiting   74%              30%              72%              25%              31%              2%               
       Alopecia    51%              7.5%             56%              14%              30%              2%               
       Neurotoxicity     44%              7%               58%              17%              44%              8.5%             
       Diarrhea    25%              1.5%             24%              1%               12%              0.5%             
       Injection site reaction   17%              2.5%             7%               0%               22%              2%               
       Ototoxicity   10%             2%                14%             1%                1%               0%               
             * Grade based on criteria from the World Health Organization (WHO).
 

  n=194 to 207; all patients receiving NAVELBINE/cisplatin with laboratory and non-laboratory data.



 ? n=173 to 192; all patients receiving vindesine/cisplatin with laboratory and non-laboratory data.



 S n=165 to 201; all patients receiving NAVELBINE with laboratory and non-laboratory data.



 | Categorical toxicity grade not specified.



   Neurotoxicity includes peripheral neuropathy and constipation.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of NAVELBINE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Infections and infestations:  pneumonia



   Immune system disorders:  anaphylactic reaction, pruritus, urticaria, angioedema



   Nervous system disorders:  loss of deep tendon reflexes, muscular weakness, gait disturbance, headache



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  vestibular disorder, hearing impaired



   Cardiac disorders:  tachycardia



   Respiratory disorders:  pulmonary edema



   Vascular disorders:  pulmonary embolism, deep vein thrombosis, hypertension, hypotension, flushing, vasodilatation



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  mucosal inflammation, dysphagia, pancreatitis



   Skin disorders:  generalized cutaneous reactions (rash)



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  jaw pain, myalgia, arthralgia



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  injection site rash, urticaria, blistering, sloughing of skin



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications:  radiation recall phenomenon, dermatitis, esophagitis



   Laboratory abnormalities:  electrolyte imbalance including hyponatremia



   Other:  tumor pain, back pain, abdominal pain
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: MYELOSUPPRESSION

    WARNING: MYELOSUPPRESSION  

    *  Severe myelosuppression resulting in serious infection, septic shock, hospitalization and death may occur [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Decrease the dose or withhold NAVELBINE in accord with recommended dose modifications [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:       WARNING: MYELOSUPPRESSION    
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning      .  



 *  Severe myelosuppression resulting in serious infection, septic shock, and death may occur (5.1).  
 *  Decrease the dose or withhold NAVELBINE in accord with recommended dose modifications (2.2). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Hepatic toxicity: monitor liver function during treatment (  5.2  ) 
 *  Severe constipation and bowel obstruction including necrosis and perforation can occur. Institute a prophylactic bowel regimen to mitigate potential constipation. Monitor for abdominal pain and severe constipation (  5.3  ) 
 *  Extravasation can result in severe tissue injury, necrosis and/or thrombophlebitis. Immediately stop NAVELBINE and institute recommended management procedures (  5.4  ) 
 *   Neurologic toxicity: severe sensory and motor neuropathies can occur. Monitor patients for new or worsening signs and symptoms of neuropathy (  5.5  )



 
 *   Pulmonary toxicity and respiratory failure can occur with use of NAVELBINE. Monitor patients respiratory disorders: dyspnea and  bronchospasm Interrupt NAVELBINE in patients who develop unexplained dyspnea (  5.6  )



 
 *  Embryo-fetal toxicity: can cause fetal harm. Advise females of reproductive potential of potential risk to the fetus (  5.7  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myelosuppression



  Myelosuppression manifested by neutropenia, anemia and thrombocytopenia occur with NAVELBINE(r) as a single agent and in combination with cisplatin [see         Adverse Reactions       (6.1         and 6.2)     ]  . Neutropenia is the major dose-limiting toxicity with NAVELBINE.  Grade 3-4 neutropenia occurred in 53% of patients treated with NAVELBINE at 30 mg/m  2  per week. Dose adjustment due to myelosuppression occurred in 51% of patients (Study 2). In clinical trials with NAVELBINE administered at 30 mg/m  2  per week, neutropenia resulted in hospitalizations for pyrexia and/or sepsis in 8% of patients. Death due to sepsis occurred in 1% of patients.  Neutropenia nadirs occur between 7 and 10 days after dosing with neutropenia count recovery usually occurring within the following 7 to 14 days.



 Monitor complete blood counts prior to each dose of NAVELBINE. Do not administer NAVELBINE to patients with neutrophil counts &lt;1,000 cells/mm  3  .  Adjustments in the dosage of NAVELBINE should be based on neutrophil counts obtained on the day of treatment [ see     Dosage and Administration (2.2)     ].  



    5.2 Hepatic Toxicity



  Drug-induced liver injury manifest by elevations of aspartate aminotransferase and bilirubin can occur in patients receiving NAVELBINE alone or in combination with cytotoxic agents. Assess hepatic function prior to initiation of NAVELBINE and periodically during treatment.  Reduce the dose of NAVELBINE for patients who develop elevations in total bilirubin &gt;   2 times upper limit of normal [see      Dosage and Administration (2.2)      and      Use in Specific Populations (8.5)     ].  



    5.3 Severe Constipation and Bowel Obstruction



  Severe and fatal paralytic ileus, constipation, intestinal obstruction, necrosis, and perforation occur with NAVELBINE administration. Institute a prophylactic bowel regimen to mitigate potential constipation, bowel obstruction and/or paralytic ileus, considering adequate dietary fiber intake, hydration, and routine use of stool softeners.



    5.4 Extravasation and Tissue Injury



  Extravasation of NAVELBINE can result in severe irritation, local tissue necrosis and/or thrombophlebitis. If signs or symptoms of extravasation occur, immediately stop administration of NAVELBINE and institute recommended management procedures [see      Dosage and Administration (2.2)     and     Adverse Reaction (6.1)     ].  



    5.5 Neurologic Toxicity



  Sensory and motor neuropathies, including severe neuropathies, occur in patients receiving NAVELBINE. Monitor patients for new or worsening signs and symptoms of neuropathy such as paresthesia, hyperesthesia, hyporeflexia and muscle weakness while receiving NAVELBINE.  Discontinue NAVELBINE for NCI CTCAE Grade 2 or greater neuropathy [see     Dosage and Administration (2.2)      and      Adverse Reaction (6.1)     ].  



    5.6 Pulmonary Toxicity and Respiratory Failure



  Pulmonary toxicity, including severe acute bronchospasm, interstitial pneumonitis, acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) occurs with use of NAVELBINE.  Interstitial pneumonitis and ARDS included fatalities.  The mean time to onset of interstitial pneumonitis and ARDS after vinorelbine administration was one week (range 3 to 8 days) [see     Adverse Reactions (6.1)     ].  



 Interrupt NAVELBINE in patients who develop unexplained dyspnea, or have any evidence of pulmonary toxicity. Permanently discontinue NAVELBINE for confirmed interstitial pneumonitis or ARDS.



    5.7 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  NAVELBINE can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. In animal reproduction studies in mice and rabbits, embryo and fetal toxicity were observed with administration of vinorelbine at doses approximately 0.33 and 0.18 times the human therapeutic dose, respectively.  If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, apprise the patient of the potential hazard to a fetus.  Advise females of reproductive potential to use highly effective contraception during therapy with NAVELBINE [see     Use in Specific Populations        (8.1,        8.7)     ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
