<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nebupent" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most frequently reported unsolicited adverse events (1 to 5%) in clinical trials, regardless of their relation to NebuPent therapy were as follows (n=931):



      Body as a Whole:    Night sweats.



      Gastrointestinal:    Diarrhea and nausea.



      Hematologic:    Anemia.



      Infection:    Bronchitis, non-specific herpes, -herpes zoster, non-specific influenza, oral Candida, pharyngitis, sinusitis, and upper -respiratory tract.



      Nervous System:    Headache.



      Respiratory System:    Chest pain, cough, and wheezing.



      Special Senses:    Bad taste.



 Adverse events of less than 1% incidence were as follows (No causal relationship to treatment has been established for these adverse events):



      Body as a Whole:    Allergic reaction, non-specific allergy, body odor, facial edema, fever, leg edema, lethargy, low body temperature, and temperature abnormality.



      Cardiovascular:    Cerebrovascular accident, hypotension, hypertension, palpitations, poor circulation, syncope, tachycardia, vasodilatation and vasculitis.



      Gastrointestinal:    Abdominal cramps, abdominal pain, constipation, dry mouth, dyspepsia, gastritis, gastric ulcer, gingivitis, hiatal hernia, hypersalivation, oral ulcer/abscess, splenomegaly, and vomiting.



      Hematological:    Eosinophilia, neutropenia, non-specific cytopenia, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia.



      Hepatic:    Hepatitis, hepatomegaly, and hepatic dysfunction.



      Infection:    Bacterial pneumonia, central venous line related sepsis, cryptococcal meningitis, cytomegalovirus (CMV) colitis, CMV retinitis, esophageal Candida, histoplasmosis, Kaposi's sarcoma, non-specific mycoplasma, oral herpes, non-specific otitis, non-specific pharyngitis, pharyngeal herpes, non-specific serious infection, tonsillitis, tuberculosis, and viral encephalitis.



      Metabolic:    Hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia, and hypocalcemia.



      Musculoskeletal:    Arthralgia, gout, and myalgia.



      Neurological:    Anxiety, confusion, depression, drowsiness, emotional lability, hallucination, hypesthesia, insomnia, memory loss, neuralgia, neuropathy, non-specific neuropathy, nervousness, paranoia, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, seizure, tremors, unsteady gait, and vertigo.



      Reproductive:    Miscarriage.



      Respiratory system:    Asthma, bronchitis, bronchospasm, chest congestion, chest tightness, coryza, cyanosis, eosinophilic or interstitial pneumonitis, gagging, hemoptysis, hyperventilation, laryngitis, laryngospasm, non-specific lung disorder, nasal congestion, pleuritis, pneumothorax, rales, rhinitis, shortness of breath, non-specific sputum, and tachypnea.



      Skin:    Desquamation, dry and breaking hair, dry skin, erythema, non-specific dermatitis, pruritus, rash, and urticaria.



      Special senses:    Blepharitis, blurred vision, conjunctivitis, contact lens discomfort, eye pain or discomfort, hemianopsia, loss of taste, non-specific odor, and smell.



      Urogenital:    Flank pain, incontinence, nephritis, renal failure, and renal pain.



 In a clinical trial where some adverse events were solicited by investigators, the incidences were as follows:



 Cough (62.7%)



 Decreased appetite (50.0%)



 Dizziness or light-headedness (45.1%)



 Fatigue (65.7%)



 Fever (51.0%)



 Non-specific serious infection (15.2%)



 Shortness of breath (48.3%)



 Wheezing (32.4%)



 From post-marketing clinical experience with NebuPent the following spontaneous adverse events have been reported: anaphylaxis, colitis, diabetes, dyspnea, esophigitis, hematochezia, increased blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine levels, melena, pancreatitis (see      WARNINGS      ), syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone (SIADH), and torsade de pointes.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
