<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="neoral1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Kidney, Liver, and Heart Transplantation

  The principal adverse reactions of cyclosporine therapy are renal dysfunction, tremor, hirsutism, hypertension, and gum hyperplasia.



 Hypertension



 Hypertension, which is usually mild to moderate, may occur in approximately 50% of patients following renal transplantation and in most cardiac transplant patients.



 Glomerular Capillary Thrombosis



 Glomerular capillary thrombosis has been found in patients treated with cyclosporine and may progress to graft failure. The pathologic changes resembled those seen in the hemolytic-uremic syndrome and included thrombosis of the renal microvasculature, with platelet-fibrin thrombi occluding glomerular capillaries and afferent arterioles, microangiopathic hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, and decreased renal function. Similar findings have been observed when other immunosuppressives have been employed post-transplantation.



 Hypomagnesemia



 Hypomagnesemia has been reported in some, but not all, patients exhibiting convulsions while on cyclosporine therapy. Although magnesium-depletion studies in normal subjects suggest that hypomagnesemia is associated with neurologic disorders, multiple factors, including hypertension, high dose methylprednisolone, hypocholesterolemia, and nephrotoxicity associated with high plasma concentrations of cyclosporine appear to be related to the neurological manifestations of cyclosporine toxicity.



 Clinical Studies



 In controlled studies, the nature, severity, and incidence of the adverse events that were observed in 493 transplanted patients treated with Neoral  (r)  were comparable with those observed in 208 transplanted patients who received Sandimmune  (r)  in these same studies when the dosage of the two drugs was adjusted to achieve the same cyclosporine blood trough concentrations.



 Based on the historical experience with Sandimmune  (r)  , the following reactions occurred in 3% or greater of 892 patients involved in clinical trials of kidney, heart, and liver transplants.




                                        Randomized Kidney Patients    Cyclosporine Patients (Sandimmune(r))    
                                        Sandimmune(r)     Azathioprine     Kidney        Heart         Liver        
  Body System       Adverse Reactions    (N=227)%          (N=228)%         (N=705)%      (N=112)%      (N=75)%      
  Genitourinary     Renal Dysfunction    32                6                25            38            37           
  Cardiovascular    Hypertension        26                18               13            53            27           
                    Cramps              4                 &lt;1               2             &lt;1            0            
  Skin              Hirsutism           21                &lt;1               21            28            45           
                    Acne                6                 8                2             2             1            
  Central Nervous System    Tremor              12                0                21            31            55           
                    Convulsions         3                 1                1             4             5            
                    Headache            2                 &lt;1               2             15            4            
  Gastrointestinal    Gum Hyperplasia     4                 0                9             5             16           
                    Diarrhea            3                 &lt;1               3             4             8            
                    Nausea/Vomiting     2                 &lt;1               4             10            4            
                    Hepatotoxicity      &lt;1                &lt;1               4             7             4            
                    Abdominal Discomfort    &lt;1                0                &lt;1            7             0            
  Autonomic Nervous System    Paresthesia         3                 0                1             2             1            
                    Flushing            &lt;1                0                4             0             4            
  Hematopoietic     Leukopenia          2                 19               &lt;1            6             0            
                    Lymphoma            &lt;1                0                1             6             1            
  Respiratory       Sinusitis           &lt;1                0                4             3             7            
  Miscellaneous     Gynecomastia        &lt;1                0                &lt;1            4             3            
             Among 705 kidney transplant patients treated with cyclosporine oral solution (Sandimmune  (r))  in clinical trials, the reason for treatment discontinuation was renal toxicity in 5.4%, infection in 0.9%, lack of efficacy in 1.4%, acute tubular necrosis in 1.0%, lymphoproliferative disorders in 0.3%, hypertension in 0.3%, and other reasons in 0.7% of the patients.
 

 The following reactions occurred in 2% or less of cyclosporine-treated patients: allergic reactions, anemia, anorexia, confusion, conjunctivitis, edema, fever, brittle fingernails, gastritis, hearing loss, hiccups, hyperglycemia, migraine (Neoral  (r)  ), muscle pain, peptic ulcer, thrombocytopenia, tinnitus.



 The following reactions occurred rarely: anxiety, chest pain, constipation, depression, hair breaking, hematuria, joint pain, lethargy, mouth sores, myocardial infarction, night sweats, pancreatitis, pruritus, swallowing difficulty, tingling, upper GI bleeding, visual disturbance, weakness, weight loss.



 Patients receiving immunosuppressive therapies, including cyclosporine and cyclosporine -containing regimens, are at increased risk of infections (viral, bacterial, fungal, parasitic). Both generalized and localized infections can occur. Pre-existing infections may also be aggravated. Fatal outcomes have been reported. (  See WARNINGS  )




  Infectious Complications in Historical Randomized Studies in Renal Transplant Patients Using Sandimmune(r)    
                                      Cyclosporine Treatment             Azathioprine with Steroids*        
                                      (N=227)                            (N=228)                            
  Complication                        % of Complications                 % of Complications                 
  Septicemia                          5.3                                4.8                                
  Abscesses                           4.4                                5.3                                
  Systemic Fungal Infection           2.2                                3.9                                
  Local Fungal Infection              7.5                                9.6                                
  Cytomegalovirus                     4.8                                12.3                               
  Other Viral Infections              15.9                               18.4                               
  Urinary Tract Infections            21.1                               20.2                               
  Wound and Skin Infections           7.0                                10.1                               
  Pneumonia                           6.2                                9.2                                
  *Some patients also received ALG.    
           Postmarketing Experience, Kidney, Liver and Heart Transplantation
   Hepatotoxicity



 Cases of hepatotoxicity and liver injury including cholestasis, jaundice, hepatitis and liver failure; serious and/or fatal outcomes have been reported.  (See WARNINGS, Hepatotoxicity)  



 Increased Risk of Infections



 Cases of JC virus-associated progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), sometimes fatal; and polyoma virus-associated nephropathy (PVAN), especially BK virus resulting in graft loss have been reported.  (See WARNINGS, Polyoma Virus Infection)  



 Headache, including Migraine



     Cases of migraine have been reported. In some cases, patients have been unable to continue cyclosporine, however, the final decision on treatment discontinuation should be made by the treating physician following the careful assessment of benefits versus risks.    



   Rheumatoid Arthritis

  The principal adverse reactions associated with the use of cyclosporine in rheumatoid arthritis are renal dysfunction  (See WARNINGS)  , hypertension  (See PRECAUTIONS)  , headache, gastrointestinal disturbances, and hirsutism/hypertrichosis.



 In rheumatoid arthritis patients treated in clinical trials within the recommended dose range, cyclosporine therapy was discontinued in 5.3% of the patients because of hypertension and in 7% of the patients because of increased creatinine. These changes are usually reversible with timely dose decrease or drug discontinuation. The frequency and severity of serum creatinine elevations increase with dose and duration of cyclosporine therapy. These elevations are likely to become more pronounced without dose reduction or discontinuation.



 The following adverse events occurred in controlled clinical trials:




  Neoral(r)/Sandimmune(r) Rheumatoid Arthritis    
  Percentage of Patients with Adverse Events &gt;=3% in any Cyclosporine Treated Group    
                             Studies         Study           Study    Study          Study    Studies      
                             651+652+2008    302             654    654            302    651+652+2008    
  Body      Preferred        Sandimmune(r)    Sandimmune(r)     Methotrexate &amp; Sandimmune(r)    Methotrexate &amp; Placebo    Neoral(r)    Placebo      
  System    Term             (N=269)         (N=155)         (N=74)    (N=73)         (N=143)    (N=201)      
  Autonomic Nervous System Disorders    
            Flushing         2%              2%              3%    0%             5%    2%           
  Body As A Whole-General Disorders    
            Accidental Trauma    0%              1%              10%    4%             4%    0%           
            Edema NOS*       5%              14%             12%    4%             10%    &lt;1%          
            Fatigue          6%              3%              8%    12%            3%    7%           
            Fever            2%              3%              0%    0%             2%    4%           
            Influenza-like symptoms    &lt;1%             6%              1%    0%             3%    2%           
            Pain             6%              9%              10%    15%            13%    4%           
            Rigors           1%              1%              4%    0%             3%    1%           
  Cardiovascular Disorders    
            Arrhythmia       2%              5%              5%    6%             2%    1%           
            Chest Pain       4%              5%              1%    1%             6%    1%           
            Hypertension     8%              26%             16%    12%            25%    2%           
  Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders    
            Dizziness        8%              6%              7%    3%             8%    3%           
            Headache         17%             23%             22%    11%            25%    9%           
            Migraine         2%              3%              0%    0%             3%    1%           
            Paresthesia      8%              7%              8%    4%             11%    1%           
            Tremor           8%              7%              7%    3%             13%    4%           
  Gastrointestinal System Disorders    
            Abdominal Pain    15%             15%             15%    7%             15%    10%          
            Anorexia         3%              3%              1%    0%             3%    3%           
            Diarrhea         12%             12%             18%    15%            13%    8%           
            Dyspepsia        12%             12%             10%    8%             8%    4%           
            Flatulence       5%              5%              5%    4%             4%    1%           
            Gastrointestinal Disorder NOS*    0%              2%              1%    4%             4%    0%           
            Gingivitis       4%              3%              0%    0%             0%    1%           
            Gum Hyperplasia    2%              4%              1%    3%             4%    1%           
            Nausea           23%             14%             24%    15%            18%    14%          
            Rectal Hemorrhage    0%              3%              0%    0%             1%    1%           
            Stomatitis       7%              5%              16%    12%            6%    8%           
            Vomiting         9%              8%              14%    7%             6%    5%           
  Hearing and Vestibular Disorders    
            Ear Disorder NOS*    0%              5%              0%    0%             1%    0%           
  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders    
            Hypomagnesemia    0%              4%              0%    0%             6%    0%           
  Musculoskeletal System Disorders    
            Arthropathy      0%              5%              0%    1%             4%    0%           
            Leg Cramps / Involuntary Muscle Contractions    2%              11%             11%    3%             12%    1%           
  Psychiatric Disorders    
            Depression       3%              6%              3%    1%             1%    2%           
            Insomnia         4%              1%              1%    0%             3%    2%           
  Renal     
            Creatinine elevations &gt;=30%    43%             39%             55%    19%            48%    13%          
            Creatinine elevations &gt;=50%    24%             18%             26%    8%             18%    3%           
  Reproductive Disorders, Female    
            Leukorrhea       1%              0%              4%    0%             1%    0%           
            Menstrual Disorder    3%              2%              1%    0%             1%    1%           
  Respiratory System Disorders    
            Bronchitis       1%              3%              1%    0%             1%    3%           
            Coughing         5%              3%              5%    7%             4%    4%           
            Dyspnea          5%              1%              3%    3%             1%    2%           
            Infection NOS*    9%              5%              0%    7%             3%    10%          
            Pharyngitis      3%              5%              5%    6%             4%    4%           
            Pneumonia        1%              0%              4%    0%             1%    1%           
            Rhinitis         0%              3%              11%    10%            1%    0%           
            Sinusitis        4%              4%              8%    4%             3%    3%           
            Upper Respiratory Tract    0%              14%             23%    15%            13%    0%           
  Skin and Appendages Disorders    
            Alopecia         3%              0%              1%    1%             4%    4%           
            Bullous Eruption    1%              0%              4%    1%             1%    1%           
            Hypertrichosis    19%             17%             12%    0%             15%    3%           
            Rash             7%              12%             10%    7%             8%    10%          
            Skin Ulceration    1%              1%              3%    4%             0%    2%           
  Urinary System Disorders    
            Dysuria          0%              0%              11%    3%             1%    2%           
            Micturition Frequency    2%              4%              3%    1%             2%    2%           
            NPN, Increased    0%              19%             12%    0%             18%    0%           
            Urinary Tract Infection    0%              3%              5%    4%             3%    0%           
  Vascular (Extracardiac) Disorders    
            Purpura          3%              4%              1%    1%             2%    0%           
   Includes patients in 2.5 mg/kg/day dose group only.       *NOS=Not Otherwise Specified.    
                 In addition, the following adverse events have been reported in 1% to &lt;3% of the rheumatoid arthritis patients in the cyclosporine treatment group in controlled clinical trials.
 

     Autonomic Nervous System:    dry mouth, increased sweating



     Body as a Whole:    allergy, asthenia, hot flushes, malaise, overdose, procedure NOS*, tumor NOS*, weight decrease, weight increase



     Cardiovascular:     abnormal heart sounds, cardiac failure, myocardial infarction, peripheral ischemia



     Central and Peripheral Nervous System:    hypoesthesia, neuropathy, vertigo



     Endocrine:     goiter



     Gastrointestinal:     constipation, dysphagia, enanthema, eructation, esophagitis, gastric ulcer, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gingival bleeding, glossitis, peptic ulcer, salivary gland enlargement, tongue disorder, tooth disorder



     Infection:     abscess, bacterial infection, cellulitis, folliculitis, fungal infection, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, renal abscess, moniliasis, tonsillitis, viral infection



     Hematologic:     anemia, epistaxis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy



     Liver and Biliary System:    bilirubinemia



     Metabolic and Nutritional:    diabetes mellitus, hyperkalemia, hyperuricemia, hypoglycemia



     Musculoskeletal System:    arthralgia, bone fracture, bursitis, joint dislocation, myalgia, stiffness, synovial cyst, tendon disorder



     Neoplasms:     breast fibroadenosis, carcinoma



     Psychiatric:     anxiety, confusion, decreased libido, emotional lability, impaired concentration, increased libido, nervousness, paroniria, somnolence



     Reproductive (Female):    breast pain, uterine hemorrhage



     Respiratory System:    abnormal chest sounds, bronchospasm



     Skin and Appendages:    abnormal pigmentation, angioedema, dermatitis, dry skin, eczema, nail disorder, pruritus, skin disorder, urticaria



     Special Senses:    abnormal vision, cataract, conjunctivitis, deafness, eye pain, taste perversion, tinnitus, vestibular disorder



     Urinary System:    abnormal urine, hematuria, increased BUN, micturition urgency, nocturia, polyuria, pyelonephritis, urinary incontinence



 *NOS=Not Otherwise Specified



   Psoriasis

  The principal adverse reactions associated with the use of cyclosporine in patients with psoriasis are renal dysfunction, headache, hypertension, hypertriglyceridemia, hirsutism/hypertrichosis, paresthesia or hyperesthesia, influenza-like symptoms, nausea/vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal discomfort, lethargy, and musculoskeletal or joint pain.



 In psoriasis patients treated in US controlled clinical studies within the recommended dose range, cyclosporine therapy was discontinued in 1.0% of the patients because of hypertension and in 5.4% of the patients because of increased creatinine. In the majority of cases, these changes were reversible after dose reduction or discontinuation of cyclosporine.



 There has been one reported death associated with the use of cyclosporine in psoriasis. A 27-year-old male developed renal deterioration and was continued on cyclosporine. He had progressive renal failure leading to death.



 Frequency and severity of serum creatinine increases with dose and duration of cyclosporine therapy. These elevations are likely to become more pronounced and may result in irreversible renal damage without dose reduction or discontinuation.




  Adverse Events Occurring in 3% or More of Psoriasis Patients in Controlled Clinical Trials    
  Body System*                   Preferred Term                   Neoral(r) (N=182)    Sandimmune(r) (N=185)    
  Infection or Potential Infection                                     24.7%               24.3%                   
                                 Influenza-Like Symptoms          9.9%                8.1%                    
                                 Upper Respiratory Tract Infections    7.7%                11.3%                   
  Cardiovascular System                                           28.0%               25.4%                   
                                 Hypertension**                   27.5%               25.4%                   
  Urinary System                                                  24.2%               16.2%                   
                                 Increased Creatinine             19.8%               15.7%                   
  Central and Peripheral Nervous System                                     26.4%               20.5%                   
                                 Headache                         15.9%               14.0%                   
                                 Paresthesia                      7.1%                4.8%                    
  Musculoskeletal System                                          13.2%               8.7%                    
                                 Arthralgia                       6.0%                1.1%                    
  Body As a Whole-General                                         29.1%               22.2%                   
                                 Pain                             4.4%                3.2%                    
  Metabolic and Nutritional                                       9.3%                9.7%                    
  Reproductive, Female                                            8.5% (4 of 47 females)    11.5% (6 of 52 females)    
  Resistance Mechanism                                            18.7%               21.1%                   
  Skin and Appendages                                             17.6%               15.1%                   
                                 Hypertrichosis                   6.6%                5.4%                    
  Respiratory System                                              5.0%                6.5%                    
                                 Bronchospasm, Coughing, Dyspnea, Rhinitis    5.0%                4.9%                    
  Psychiatric                                                     5.0%                3.8%                    
  Gastrointestinal System                                         19.8%               28.7%                   
                                 Abdominal Pain                   2.7%                6.0%                    
                                 Diarrhea                         5.0%                5.9%                    
                                 Dyspepsia                        2.2%                3.2%                    
                                 Gum Hyperplasia                  3.8%                6.0%                    
                                 Nausea                           5.5%                5.9%                    
  White cell and RES                                              4.4%                2.7%                    
  *Total percentage of events within the system**Newly occurring hypertension = SBP&gt;=160 mm Hg and/or DBP&gt;=90 mm Hg    
          The following events occurred in 1% to less than 3% of psoriasis patients treated with cyclosporine:
 

     Body as a Whole:     fever, flushes, hot flushes



     Cardiovascular:     chest pain



     Central and Peripheral Nervous System:     appetite increased, insomnia, dizziness, nervousness, vertigo



     Gastrointestinal:     abdominal distention, constipation, gingival bleeding



     Liver and Biliary System:     hyperbilirubinemia



     Neoplasms:     skin malignancies [squamous cell (0.9%) and basal cell (0.4%) carcinomas]



     Reticuloendothelial:     platelet, bleeding, and clotting disorders, red blood cell disorder



     Respiratory:    infection, viral and other infection



     Skin and Appendages:     acne, folliculitis, keratosis, pruritus, rash, dry skin



     Urinary System:     micturition frequency



     Vision:     abnormal vision



 Mild hypomagnesemia and hyperkalemia may occur but are asymptomatic. Increases in uric acid may occur and attacks of gout have been rarely reported. A minor and dose related hyperbilirubinemia has been observed in the absence of hepatocellular damage. Cyclosporine therapy may be associated with a modest increase of serum triglycerides or cholesterol. Elevations of triglycerides (&gt;750 mg/dL) occur in about 15% of psoriasis patients; elevations of cholesterol (&gt;300 mg/dL) are observed in less than 3% of psoriasis patients. Generally these laboratory abnormalities are reversible upon dose reduction or discontinuation of cyclosporine.



   Postmarketing Experience, Psoriasis  



 Cases of transformation to erythrodermic psoriasis or generalized pustular psoriasis upon either withdrawal or reduction of cyclosporine in patients with chronic plaque psoriasis have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

  WARNING

  Only physicians experienced in management of systemic immunosuppressive therapy for the indicated disease should prescribe Neoral  (r)  . At doses used in solid organ transplantation, only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant recipients should prescribe Neoral  (r)  . Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physician responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient.



 Neoral  (r)  , a systemic immunosuppressant, may increase the susceptibility to infection and the development of neoplasia. In kidney, liver, and heart transplant patients Neoral  (r)   may be administered with other immunosuppressive agents. Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of lymphoma and other neoplasms may result from the increase in the degree of immunosuppression in transplant patients.



 Neoral  (r)   Soft Gelatin Capsules (cyclosporine capsules, USP) MODIFIED and Neoral  (r)   Oral Solution (cyclosporine oral solution, USP) MODIFIED have increased bioavailability in comparison to Sandimmune  (r)   Soft Gelatin Capsules (cyclosporine capsules, USP) and Sandimmune  (r)   Oral Solution (cyclosporine oral solution, USP). Neoral  (r)   and Sandimmune  (r)   are not bioequivalent and cannot be used interchangeably without physician supervision. For a given trough concentration, cyclosporine exposure will be greater with Neoral  (r)   than with Sandimmune  (r)  . If a patient who is receiving exceptionally high doses of Sandimmune  (r)   is converted to Neoral  (r)  , particular caution should be exercised. Cyclosporine blood concentrations should be monitored in transplant and rheumatoid arthritis patients taking Neoral  (r)   to avoid toxicity due to high concentrations. Dose adjustments should be made in transplant patients to minimize possible organ rejection due to low concentrations. Comparison of blood concentrations in the published literature with blood concentrations obtained using current assays must be done with detailed knowledge of the assay methods employed.



 





    BOXED WARNING: For Psoriasis Patients (See also BOXED WARNING above)

  For Psoriasis Patients   (See also BOXED WARNING above)  

  Psoriasis patients previously treated with PUVA and to a lesser extent, methotrexate or other immunosuppressive agents, UVB, coal tar, or radiation therapy, are at an increased risk of developing skin malignancies when taking Neoral  (r)  .



 Cyclosporine, the active ingredient in Neoral  (r)  , in recommended dosages, can cause systemic hypertension and nephrotoxicity. The risk increases with increasing dose and duration of cyclosporine therapy. Renal dysfunction, including structural kidney damage, is a potential consequence of cyclosporine, and therefore, renal function must be monitored during therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
