<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="neupro" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Sulfite Sensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Hallucinations/Psychosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Symptomatic Hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Syncope [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Elevation of Blood Pressure and Heart Rate [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Weight Gain and Fluid Retention [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Dyskinesia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Application Site Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Melanoma [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Augmentation and Rebound in RLS [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Hyperpyrexia and Confusion [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ]  
 *  Fibrotic Complications [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.16)  ]  
   *  Parkinson's disease: Most common adverse reactions (at least 5% greater than placebo) were nausea, vomiting, somnolence, application site reactions, dizziness, anorexia, disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep, hyperhidrosis, visual disturbance, peripheral edema, and dyskinesia. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Restless Legs Syndrome: Most common adverse reactions (at least 5% greater than placebo) were application site reactions, nausea, disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep, somnolence, and headache. (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact UCB, Inc. at 1-844-599-2273 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the incidence of adverse reactions (number of unique patients experiencing an adverse reaction associated with treatment/total number of patients treated) observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to incidence of adverse reactions in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the incidence of adverse reactions observed in practice.



     Adverse Reactions in Early-Stage Parkinson's Disease  



 The safety of NEUPRO was evaluated in a total of 649 early-stage Parkinson's disease patients who participated in three double-blind, placebo-controlled studies with durations of 3 to 9 months. Additional safety information was collected in short-term studies and two open-label extension studies in patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease.



 In the double-blind, placebo-controlled, dose-response study in patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease, the most common adverse reactions (at least 5% greater than placebo) for the maximum recommended dose of NEUPRO (6 mg/24 hours) were nausea, vomiting, somnolence, application site reactions, dizziness, anorexia, disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep, hyperhidrosis, and visual disturbance.



 In this trial, 12% of patients treated with the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose (6 mg/24 hours) discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions, compared with 6% of patients who received placebo.



 Table 1 summarizes the adverse reactions that occurred in greater than 2% of NEUPRO-treated patients and more frequent than in placebo-treated patients in a double-blind, placebo-controlled, fixed-dose trial in patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease. Incidences for the non-recommended 8 mg/24 hours dose are also shown.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions in a Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose Trial in Patients with Early-Stage Parkinson's Disease 
 Adverse Reaction           PlaceboN=64%       NEUPRO Dose     
 2 mg/24hN=67%             4 mg/24hN=63%      6 mg/24hN=65%    8 mg/24hN=70%    
  
 Nausea                          13                34               38               48               41          
 Vomiting                        3                 10               16               20               11          
 Somnolence                      3                 12               14               19               20          
 Application and instillation site reactions          19                21               19               32               43          
 Dizziness                       11                21               14               22               20          
 Anorexia                        0                  2                2                9                4          
 Disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep          6                  6               11               14               11          
 Hyperhidrosis                   3                  3                3               11                3          
 Visual disturbance              0                  0                0                5                3          
 Abnormal dreams                 0                  2                5                3                7          
 Abnormal Electrocardiogram T wave          0                  0                2                3                0          
 Balance disorder                0                  0                2                3                0          
 Dyspepsia                       0                  2                2                3                0          
 Fatigue                         3                  8               18                6               13          
 Tinnitus                        0                  0                2                3                0          
 Constipation                    3                  2                3                5                6          
 Erythema                        3                  3                6                5                6          
 Hallucinations                  2                  0                2                3                3          
 Muscle spasms                   2                  3                2                3                4          
 Paresthesia                     2                  3                3                3                0          
 Peripheral edema                2                  2                3                3                4          
 White blood cells urine positive          2                  3                3                3                1          
            The incidence of certain adverse reactions with NEUPRO was notably increased compared to placebo treatment (i.e., at least 5% greater than placebo) in either the titration or maintenance phases of the dose-response trial. During the titration phase, this increased incidence of a treatment difference was observed for nausea, somnolence, vomiting, application site reactions (ASRs), dizziness, sweating increased, anorexia, and visual disturbance. During the maintenance phase, an increased incidence was observed for nausea and ASRs. Some adverse reactions developing in the titration phase persisted (at least 7 days) into the maintenance phase. These "persistent" adverse reactions included ASRs, anorexia, somnolence, and nausea.
 

     Adverse Reactions in Advanced-Stage Parkinson's Disease  



 The safety evaluation of NEUPRO was based on a total of 672 NEUPRO-treated patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease who participated in three double-blind, placebo-controlled studies (two fixed-dose trials and one flexible-dose trial) with durations of 3 to 7 months. Patients received concomitant levodopa in these studies. Additional safety information was collected in earlier short-term studies and two open-label extension studies in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease.



 In the dose-response, placebo-controlled trial for advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, the most common adverse reactions (at least 5% greater than placebo) for the maximum recommended dose of NEUPRO (8 mg/24 hours) were application site reactions, nausea, peripheral edema, dizziness, and dyskinesia.



 In this trial, approximately 15% of patients treated with the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose (8 mg/24 hours) discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions, compared with 9% of patients who received placebo.



 Table 2 summarizes the adverse reactions that occurred in greater than 2% of NEUPRO-treated patients and more frequent than in placebo-treated patients in a double-blind, placebo-controlled, fixed-dose trial in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease. Incidences for the non-recommended 12 mg/24 hours dose are also shown.



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions in a Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose Trial in Patients with Advanced-Stage Parkinson's Disease 
 Adverse Reaction                        PlaceboN=120%            NEUPRO Dose         
 8 mg/24hN=118%                         12 mg/24hN=111%       
  
 Application and instillation site reactions            13                      36                      46             
 Nausea                                        19                      28                      22             
 Peripheral edema                              1                       9                       14             
 Dizziness                                     15                      23                      14             
 Dyskinesia                                    7                       14                      17             
 Somnolence                                    28                      32                      32             
 Vomiting                                      6                       10                      8              
 Arthralgia                                    7                       11                      8              
 Hallucinations                                3                       7                       13             
 Hyperhidrosis                                 0                       3                       1              
 Sinus congestion                              0                       3                       2              
 Constipation                                  6                       9                       5              
 Disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep            6                       9                       14             
 First degree atrioventricular block            0                       3                       0              
 Herpes simplex                                0                       3                       0              
 Hypertension                                  0                       3                       5              
 Influenza                                     0                       3                       1              
 Nasal congestion                              0                       3                       3              
 Headache                                      8                       10                      8              
 Diarrhea                                      5                       7                       5              
 Basal cell carcinoma                          1                       3                       0              
 Cough                                         1                       3                       3              
 Dyspepsia                                     2                       3                       0              
 Erythema                                      1                       3                       2              
 Hot flush                                     1                       3                       0              
 Paresthesias                                  3                       4                       3              
 Tremor                                        3                       4                       3              
 Hypoaesthesia                                 2                       3                       3              
 Nightmare                                     2                       3                       5              
          The incidence of certain adverse reactions with NEUPRO was notably increased compared to placebo treatment (i.e., at least 5% greater than placebo) in either the titration or maintenance phases of the dose-response trial. During the titration phase, an increased incidence was observed for application site reactions (ASRs), nausea, hallucinations, constipation, dyskinesia, and dizziness. During the maintenance phase, an increased incidence was observed for ASRs and peripheral edema. Some adverse reactions developing in the titration phase persisted (at least 7 days) into the maintenance phase. A notably "persistent" adverse reaction was ASRs.
 

     Adverse Reactions in Restless Legs Syndrome  



 The safety evaluation of NEUPRO was based on 745 NEUPRO-treated patients with Restless Legs Syndrome who participated in two double-blind, placebo-controlled studies with maintenance durations of 6 months. Additional safety information was collected in earlier short-term studies and three open-label extension studies in patients with RLS.



 In the two double-blind, placebo-controlled, fixed-dose trials for RLS, the most common adverse reactions (at least 5% greater than placebo) for the maximum recommended dose of NEUPRO (3 mg/24 hours) were application site reactions, nausea, disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep, somnolence, and headache.



 In the two fixed-dose, placebo-controlled trials, 24% of patients treated with the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose (3 mg/24 hours) discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions, compared with 3% of patients who received placebo.



 Table 3 summarizes the adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of NEUPRO-treated patients and more frequent than in placebo-treated patients in two double-blind, placebo-controlled, fixed-dose trials in patients with Restless Legs Syndrome.



 Table 3 Adverse Reactions in Pooled Placebo-Controlled, Fixed-Dose Trials of Patients with Restless Legs Syndrome 
 Adverse Reaction          PlaceboN=217%       NEUPRO Dose     
 0.5 mg/24hN=99%           1 mg/24hN=215%    2 mg/24hN=211%   3 mg/24hN=220%    
  
 Application and instillation site reactions          4                 23               27               38               43          
 Nausea                          10                18               15               23               21          
 Disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep          3                  2                4                3               10          
 Headache                        11                21               15               18               16          
 Asthenic conditions             8                 11                7               14               12          
 Somnolence                      4                  8                5                8               10          
 Hypertension                    0                  3                1                1                4          
 Pruritus                        3                  9                4                3                7          
 Dry mouth                       4                  3                3                3                7          
 Vomiting                        1                  2                2                4                4          
 Dizziness                       6                  7                5                9                6          
 Hyperhidrosis                   2                  1                3                5                3          
 Abnormal dreams                 0                  2                1                2                3          
 Irritability                    0                  0                1                3                1          
 Muscle spasms                   1                  3                1                4                1          
 Dyspepsia                       1                  2                1                2                3          
 Hot flush                       1                  4                1                3                0          
 Menstrual disorder              0                  0                0                2                1          
 Sleep disorder                  1                  0                2                3                3          
 Viral gastroenteritis           0                  1                1                2                1          
 Sleep attacks                   0                  0                1                0                2          
 Sexual desire disorder          3                  6                4                4                5          
 Depression                      1                  3                1                2                1          
 Decreased serum ferritin          1                  2                1                1                2          
 Vertigo                         1                  0                4                3                1          
 Constipation                    3                  6                3                2                5          
 Erythema                        1                  1                1                0                2          
 Sinusitis                       1                  2                1                2                3          
 Diarrhea                        4                  6                4                5                4          
 Increased weight                1                  3                1                1                2          
 Nasopharyngitis                 7                  5               10                7                8          
            The incidence of certain adverse reactions with NEUPRO treatment was increased compared to placebo (i.e., at least 5% greater than placebo) in either the titration or maintenance phases of the dose-response trials. During the titration phase, an increased incidence was observed for application site reactions (ASRs), nausea, headache, asthenic conditions, and disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep. During the maintenance phase, an increased incidence was observed for ASRs. Some adverse reactions developing in the titration phase persisted (at least 7 days) into the maintenance phase. These "persistent" adverse reactions were ASRs, nausea, and disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep.
 

   6.2 Laboratory Changes

  Some clinical laboratory analytes were abnormal in patients treated with the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose in the fixed-dose, placebo-controlled, dose-response trials for patients with early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease and with RLS.



 Patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease receiving NEUPRO had an increased risk for low hemoglobin below the normal reference range (NEUPRO 8% vs. placebo 2%) and for decreased hematocrit below the normal reference range (NEUPRO 8% vs. placebo 5%). Patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease receiving NEUPRO had an increased risk for a low hemoglobin below the normal reference range (NEUPRO 15% vs. placebo 11%) and for decreased hematocrit below the normal reference range (NEUPRO 17% vs. placebo 14%). Patients with RLS receiving NEUPRO had an increased risk for a decreased hemoglobin below the normal reference range (NEUPRO 15% vs. placebo 12%). There was also an increased risk for markedly decreased hemoglobin and hematocrit (NEUPRO 2% vs. placebo 0%) in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease receiving NEUPRO and for markedly decreased hematocrit (NEUPRO 1% vs. placebo 0%) in patients with RLS receiving NEUPRO.



 Patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease receiving NEUPRO had an increased risk for elevated serum blood urea nitrogen (BUN) above the normal reference range (NEUPRO 11% vs. placebo 2%). There was also an increased risk for markedly elevated serum BUN (NEUPRO 3% vs. placebo 2%) in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease receiving NEUPRO.



 There was an increased risk for low serum glucose below the normal reference range in patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease receiving NEUPRO (NEUPRO 15% vs. placebo 6%) and in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease (NEUPRO 10% vs. placebo 7%). There was also an increased risk for markedly decreased serum glucose (NEUPRO 1% vs. placebo 0%) in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease receiving NEUPRO.



 Serum creatine phosphokinase (CPK) was elevated in Japanese patients taking NEUPRO for early- or advanced-stage Parkinson's disease in placebo-controlled, flexible-dose studies conducted in Japan. The frequency of CPK elevation observed in patients receiving NEUPRO for early-stage Parkinson's disease was 40% (35/88) in the NEUPRO group compared to 17% (15/89) in the placebo group. The frequency of CPK elevation observed in patients receiving NEUPRO for advanced-stage Parkinson's disease was 39% (99/253) in the NEUPRO group compared to 20% (34/171) in the placebo group using pooled data from two studies. Increased CPK occurred at any time during the respective studies, and in some instances increased CPK was observed at two or more consecutive visits. The total daily dose of NEUPRO taken by patients with early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease ranged between 2 mg/24 hours to 16 mg/24 hours. Studies of NEUPRO conducted outside of Japan did not include assessments of serum CPK in patients treated for Parkinson's disease  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Contains sodium metabisulfite that may cause allergic-type reactions in those with sulfite sensitivity. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Falling asleep during activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, and somnolence may occur. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hallucinations/psychosis and dyskinesia may occur. (  5.3  ,  5.9  ) 
 *  Symptomatic postural hypotension and syncope may occur, especially during dose escalation. (  5.4  ,  5.5  ) 
 *  Consider dose reduction or stopping NEUPRO if patient develops compulsive behaviors. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Elevation of blood pressure and heart rate may occur. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Application site reactions can occur and may be severe. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Hyperpyrexia and confusion may occur with sudden discontinuation or dose reduction. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Sulfite Sensitivity



  NEUPRO contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfite that may cause allergic-type reactions including anaphylactic symptoms and life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in certain susceptible people. The overall prevalence of sulfite sensitivity in the general population is unknown. Sulfite sensitivity is seen more frequently in asthmatic than in nonasthmatic people.



    5.2 Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence



  Patients with early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease and with Restless Legs Syndrome treated with NEUPRO have reported falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, which sometimes resulted in accidents. Although many of these patients reported somnolence while on NEUPRO, some did not perceive warning signs, such as excessive drowsiness, and believed that they were alert immediately prior to the event. Some of these events have been reported as late as one year after initiation of treatment. In clinical trials in patients with Restless Legs Syndrome, 2% of patients treated with the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose (3 mg/24 hours) reported sleep attacks compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients.



 It has been reported that falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living always occurs in a setting of pre-existing somnolence, although patients may not give such a history. For this reason, prescribers should reassess patients for drowsiness or sleepiness especially since some of the events occur well after the start of treatment.



 Somnolence is a common occurrence in patients receiving NEUPRO. In patients taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose, there was an increased risk of somnolence for early-stage Parkinson's disease (NEUPRO 19%, placebo 3%), for advanced-stage Parkinson's disease (NEUPRO 32%, placebo 28%), and for Restless Legs Syndrome (NEUPRO 10%, placebo 4%). Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge drowsiness or sleepiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities. Patients should be advised to exercise caution while driving, operating machines, or working at heights during treatment with NEUPRO. Patients who have already experienced somnolence and/or an episode of sudden sleep onset should not participate in these activities while taking NEUPRO.



 Before initiating treatment with NEUPRO, patients should be advised of the potential to develop drowsiness and specifically asked about factors that may increase this risk with NEUPRO such as concomitant sedating medications and the presence of sleep disorders. If a patient develops daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require active participation (e.g., conversations, eating, etc.), NEUPRO should ordinarily be discontinued [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



 If a decision is made to continue NEUPRO, patients should be advised not to drive and to avoid other potentially dangerous activities. There is insufficient information to establish whether dose reduction will eliminate episodes of falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living.



    5.3 Hallucinations/Psychosis



  There was an increased risk for hallucinations in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease treated with NEUPRO. In patients taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose, the incidence of hallucinations was 7% for NEUPRO and 3% for placebo, and this treatment difference increased with increasing dose. Hallucinations were of sufficient severity to cause discontinuation of treatment (mainly during the dose escalation/titration period) in 3% of advanced-stage Parkinson's disease patients treated with the maximum recommended dose of NEUPRO compared with 1% of placebo-treated patients. Hallucinations have also been reported in post-marketing reports.



 Post-marketing reports indicate that patients may experience new or worsening mental status and behavioral changes, which may be severe, including psychotic behavior during NEUPRO treatment or after starting or increasing the dose of NEUPRO. Other drugs prescribed to improve the symptoms of Parkinson's disease can have similar effects on thinking and behavior. This abnormal thinking and behavior may consist of one or more of the following: paranoid ideation, delusions, hallucinations, confusion, disorientation, aggressive behavior, agitation, and delirium. These various manifestations of psychotic behavior were also observed during the clinical development of NEUPRO for early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease and Restless Legs Syndrome.



 Patients with a major psychotic disorder should ordinarily not be treated with NEUPRO because of the risk of exacerbating psychosis. In addition, certain medications used to treat psychosis may exacerbate the symptoms of Parkinson's disease and may decrease the effectiveness of NEUPRO [  see   Drug Interactions (7.1)  ].  



    5.4 Symptomatic Hypotension



  Dopaminergic agonists, in clinical studies and clinical experience, appear to impair the systemic regulation of blood pressure, resulting in postural/orthostatic hypotension, especially during dose escalation. Parkinson's disease patients, in addition, appear to have an impaired capacity to respond to a postural challenge. For these reasons, both Parkinson's and Restless Legs Syndrome patients being treated with dopaminergic agonists ordinarily (1) require careful monitoring for signs and symptoms of postural hypotension, especially during dose escalation, and (2) should be informed of this risk.



 An increased risk for decreases in systolic and diastolic blood pressure were observed when supine, standing, and changing from supine to standing position in patients treated with NEUPRO. In patients taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose, orthostatic (change from supine to standing) decreases in systolic blood pressure (at least 20 mm Hg or greater) was 16% for NEUPRO and 14% for placebo in patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease, 32% for NEUPRO and 27% for placebo in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, and 13% for NEUPRO and 11% for placebo in patients with Restless Legs Syndrome. More severe decreases in systolic blood pressure (40 mm Hg or greater) and in diastolic blood pressure (20 mm Hg or greater) also occurred more frequently (NEUPRO incidence at least 2% greater than placebo) in patients with early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease during measurements when supine, standing, or changing from supine to standing position. Patients experienced dose-related decreases in blood pressure at different times throughout the trial including the final visit.



 An analysis using a variety of adverse reaction terms suggestive of orthostatic hypotension, including dizziness/postural dizziness and others, showed an increased risk for all patients treated with NEUPRO. For the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose, the incidence of adverse reactions suggestive of hypotension/orthostatic hypotension was 29% for NEUPRO and 11% for placebo in early-stage Parkinson's disease, 27% for NEUPRO and 23% for placebo in advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, and 8% for NEUPRO and 7% for placebo in Restless Legs Syndrome.



 This increased risk for symptomatic hypotension and decreases in blood pressure was observed in a setting in which patients were very carefully titrated, and patients with clinically relevant cardiovascular disease or symptomatic orthostatic hypotension at baseline had been excluded from this study. The increased risk for significant decreases in blood pressure or orthostatic hypotension occurred especially in the dose escalation/titration period.



    5.5 Syncope



  Syncope has been reported in patients using dopamine agonists, and for this reason patients should be alerted to the possibility of syncope. Because the studies of NEUPRO excluded patients with clinically relevant cardiovascular disease, patients with severe cardiovascular disease should be asked about symptoms of syncope and pre-syncope.



    5.6 Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors



  Patients may experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money, binge eating, and/or other intense urges, and the inability to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications, including NEUPRO, that increase central dopaminergic tone and that are generally used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease. In some cases, although not all, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose was reduced or the medication was discontinued. Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal, it is important for prescribers to specifically ask patients or their caregivers about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending, or other urges while being treated with NEUPRO. Physicians should consider dose reduction or stopping the medication if a patient develops such urges while taking NEUPRO .  



    5.7 Elevation of Blood Pressure and Heart Rate



  Some patients treated with NEUPRO exhibited increases in systolic blood pressure (greater than 180 mm Hg) and/or diastolic blood pressure (greater than 105 mm Hg) while supine or standing. In patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, this increased risk for systolic blood pressure greater than 180 mm Hg was 5% for NEUPRO and 3% for placebo and for diastolic blood pressure greater than 105 mm Hg was 4% for NEUPRO and 0% for placebo. In patients with Restless Legs Syndrome, this increased risk for diastolic blood pressure greater than 105 mm Hg was 8% for NEUPRO and 4% for placebo.



 Increases in systolic blood pressure (at least 20 mm Hg or more) and in diastolic blood pressure (at least 10 mm Hg or more) occurred more frequently (incidence at least 5% greater than placebo) in all patients (i.e., early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease and Restless Legs Syndrome) taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose. These increases in systolic and diastolic blood pressure were observed when supine, standing, and changing from supine to standing position. More severe increases in systolic blood pressure (40 mm Hg or more) and in diastolic blood pressure (20 mm Hg or more) also occurred more frequently (incidence at least 2% greater than placebo) in NEUPRO-treated patients with early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease and with Restless Legs Syndrome during measurements when supine, standing, and/or changing from supine to standing position.



 In the placebo-controlled trials, there was an increased risk for hypertension as an adverse reaction with the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease (NEUPRO 3% vs. placebo 0%) and Restless Legs Syndrome (NEUPRO 4% vs. placebo 0%).



 Some patients treated with NEUPRO exhibited increased pulse (greater than 100 beats per minute) while supine and/or standing. In patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, there was an increased risk (at least 2% greater than placebo) of increased pulse for patients taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose. In patients with Restless Legs Syndrome, there was an increased risk (at least 5% greater than placebo) of increased pulse for patients taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose.



 These findings of blood pressure and heart rate elevations should be considered when treating patients with cardiovascular disease.



    5.8 Weight Gain and Fluid Retention



  Patients taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose for early-stage Parkinson's disease had a higher incidence (2%) of substantial weight gain (more than 10% of baseline weight) than patients taking placebo (0%). In advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, the incidence of weight gain more than 10% of baseline weight was 9% in NEUPRO-treated patients (for the maximum recommended dose) and 1% in placebo-treated patients. This weight gain was frequently associated with the development of peripheral edema in patients with Parkinson's disease, suggesting that NEUPRO may cause fluid retention in some Parkinson's patients. In patients taking the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose, the incidence of peripheral edema was 3% for NEUPRO and 2% for placebo in early-stage Parkinson's disease and 9% for NEUPRO and 1% for placebo in advanced-stage Parkinson's disease. These treatment differences increased further with treatment at NEUPRO dosing above the maximum recommended doses. Monitor for weight gain and fluid retention when treating patients with concomitant illnesses such as congestive heart failure or renal insufficiency.



    5.9 Dyskinesia



  NEUPRO may potentiate the dopaminergic side effects of levodopa and may cause or exacerbate pre-existing dyskinesia. For the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose, the incidence of dyskinesia was increased for NEUPRO (NEUPRO 14% vs. placebo 7%) in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, and this incidence increased with increasing dose. Patients treated with the maximum recommended dose of NEUPRO also had an increased risk (NEUPRO 3% vs. placebo 0%) for early discontinuation from the study because of dyskinesia.



    5.10 Application Site Reactions



  Application site reactions (ASRs) occurred at a greater frequency in the NEUPRO-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients in the double-blind, placebo-controlled, dose-response studies with NEUPRO. For the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose, the incidence of application site reactions was 32% for NEUPRO and 19% for placebo in patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease, 36% for NEUPRO and 13% for placebo in patients with advanced-stage Parkinson's disease, and 43% for NEUPRO and 4% for placebo in patients with Restless Legs Syndrome. ASRs exhibited a dose-dependent relationship for all doses for patients with early- and advanced-stage Parkinson's disease and Restless Legs Syndrome. ASRs were also of sufficient severity to cause study discontinuation for patients with early-stage Parkinson's disease (NEUPRO 3% vs. placebo 0%), advanced-stage Parkinson's disease (NEUPRO 2% vs. placebo 0%), and Restless Legs Syndrome (NEUPRO 12% vs. placebo 0%) who were treated with the maximum recommended NEUPRO dose.



 The signs and symptoms of these reactions generally were localized erythema, edema, or pruritus limited to the patch area and usually did not lead to dose reduction. Generalized skin reactions (e.g., allergic rash, including erythematous, macular-papular rash, or pruritus) have been reported at lower rates than ASRs during the development of NEUPRO.



 In a clinical study designed to investigate the cumulative skin irritation of NEUPRO, daily rotation of NEUPRO application sites has been shown to reduce the incidence of ASRs in comparison to repetitive application to the same site. In a clinical study investigating the skin sensitizing potential of NEUPRO in 221 healthy subjects, no case of contact sensitization was observed. Localized sensitization reactions were observed in a study with healthy subjects by continuously rotating a 0.5 mg/24 hours transdermal system, after induction of maximal irritational stress was achieved by repetitive transdermal system application to the same site.



 If a patient reports a persistent application site reaction (of more than a few days), reports an increase in severity, or reports a skin reaction spreading outside the application site, an assessment of the risk and benefits for the individual patient should be conducted. If a generalized skin reaction associated with the use of NEUPRO is observed, NEUPRO should be discontinued.



    5.11 Melanoma



  Epidemiological studies have shown that patients with Parkinson's disease have a higher risk (approximately 6-fold higher) of developing melanoma than the general population. Whether the increased risk observed was due to Parkinson's disease or other factors, such as drugs used to treat Parkinson's disease, is unclear.



 For the reasons stated above, patients and providers are advised to monitor for melanomas frequently and on a regular basis when using NEUPRO for any indication. Ideally, periodic skin examinations should be performed by appropriately qualified individuals (e.g., dermatologists).



    5.12 Augmentation and Rebound in RLS



  Augmentation is a worsening of RLS symptoms during treatment, leading to an increase in overall symptom severity or earlier time of symptom onset each day compared to before initiation of treatment. Use of dopaminergic medications, including NEUPRO, may result in augmentation.



 Rebound, an exacerbation of RLS symptoms, is considered to be an end of dose effect, related to the half-life of the therapeutic agent. Reports in the published literature indicate discontinuation or wearing off of dopaminergic medications can result in rebound.



    5.13 Magnetic Resonance Imaging and Cardioversion



  The backing layer of NEUPRO contains aluminum. To avoid skin burns, NEUPRO should be removed prior to magnetic resonance imaging or cardioversion.



    5.14 Heat Application



  The effect of application of heat to the transdermal system has not been studied. However, heat application has been shown to increase absorption several fold with other transdermal products. Patients should be advised to avoid exposing the NEUPRO application site to external sources of direct heat, such as heating pads or electric blankets, heat lamps, saunas, hot tubs, heated water beds, and prolonged direct sunlight.



    5.15 Hyperpyrexia and Confusion



  A symptom complex resembling the neuroleptic malignant syndrome (characterized by elevated temperature, muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, rhabdomyolysis, and/or autonomic instability), with no other obvious etiology, has been reported in association with rapid dose reduction, withdrawal of, or changes in anti-Parkinsonian therapy. Therefore, it is recommended that the dose be tapered at the end of NEUPRO treatment [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ].  



    5.16 Fibrotic Complications



  Cases of retroperitoneal fibrosis, pulmonary infiltrates, pleural effusion, pleural thickening, pericarditis, and cardiac valvulopathy have been reported in some patients treated with ergot-derived dopaminergic agents. While these complications may resolve when the drug is discontinued, complete resolution does not always occur.



 Although these adverse events are believed to be related to the ergoline structure of these compounds, whether other, nonergot-derived dopamine agonists can cause them is unknown.



    5.17 Binding to Melanin



  As has been reported with other dopamine agonists, binding to melanin-containing tissues (i.e., eyes) in the pigmented rat and monkey was evident after a single dose of rotigotine, but was slowly cleared over the 14-day observation period.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
