<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nexavar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Cardiac ischemia, infarction [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Hemorrhage [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    Hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    Hand-foot skin reaction, rash, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    Gastrointestinal perforation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *    QT Interval Prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  
 *    Drug-Induced Hepatitis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *    Impairment of TSH suppression in DTC [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
 *     Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. 
 *     The data described in sections 6.1, 6.2 and 6.3 reflect exposure to NEXAVAR in 955 patients who participated in placebo controlled studies in hepatocellular carcinoma (N=297), advanced renal cell carcinoma (N=451), or differentiated thyroid carcinoma (N = 207). 
 *     The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=20%), which were considered to be related to NEXAVAR, in patients with HCC, RCC or DTC are diarrhea, fatigue, infection, alopecia, hand-foot skin reaction, rash, weight loss, decreased appetite, nausea, gastrointestinal and abdominal pains, hypertension, and hemorrhage. 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=20%) for NEXAVAR are diarrhea, fatigue, infection, alopecia, hand-foot skin reaction, rash, weight loss, decreased appetite, nausea, gastrointestinal and abdominal pains, hypertension, and hemorrhage. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-888-842-2937, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Adverse Reactions in HCC Study

  Table 4 shows the percentage of patients with HCC experiencing adverse reactions that were reported in at least 10% of patients and at a higher rate in the NEXAVAR arm than the placebo arm. CTCAE Grade 3 adverse reactions were reported in 39% of patients receiving NEXAVAR compared to 24% of patients receiving placebo. CTCAE Grade 4 adverse reactions were reported in 6% of patients receiving NEXAVAR compared to 8% of patients receiving placebo.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions Reported in at Least 10% of Patients and at a Higher Rate in NEXAVAR Arm than the Placebo Arm - HCC Study 
                                   NEXAVARN=297    PlaceboN=302    
  Adverse Reaction NCI- CTCAE v3 Category/Term    AllGrades%    Grade 3%     Grade4%      AllGrades%    Grade3%      Grade4%      
  Any Adverse Reaction             98           39           6            96           24           8            
  Constitutional symptoms                                                                                        
  Fatigue                          46           9            1            45           12           2            
  Weight loss                      30           2            0            10           1            0            
  Dermatology/skin                                                                                               
  Rash/desquamation                19           1            0            14           0            0            
  Pruritus                         14           &lt;1           0            11           &lt;1           0            
  Hand-foot skin reaction          21           8            0            3            &lt;1           0            
  Dry skin                         10           0            0            6            0            0            
  Alopecia                         14           0            0            2            0            0            
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                               
  Diarrhea                         55           10           &lt;1           25           2            0            
  Anorexia                         29           3            0            18           3            &lt;1           
  Nausea                           24           1            0            20           3            0            
  Vomiting                         15           2            0            11           2            0            
  Constipation                     14           0            0            10           0            0            
  Hepatobiliary/pancreas                                                                                         
  Liver dysfunction                11           2            1            8            2            1            
  Pain                                                                                                           
  Pain, abdomen                    31           9            0            26           5            1            
             Hypertension was reported in 9% of patients treated with NEXAVAR and 4% of those treated with placebo. CTCAE Grade 3 hypertension was reported in 4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 1% of placebo-treated patients. No patients were reported with CTCAE Grade 4 reactions in either treatment group.
 

 Hemorrhage/bleeding was reported in 18% of those receiving NEXAVAR and 20% of placebo-treated patients. The rates of CTCAE Grade 3 and 4 bleeding were also higher in the placebo-treated group (CTCAE Grade 3 - 3% NEXAVAR and 5% placebo and CTCAE Grade 4 - 2% NEXAVAR and 4% placebo). Bleeding from esophageal varices was reported in 2.4% in NEXAVAR-treated patients and 4% of placebo-treated patients.



 Renal failure was reported in &lt;1% of patients treated with NEXAVAR and 3% of placebo-treated patients.



 The rate of adverse reactions (including those associated with progressive disease) resulting in permanent discontinuation was similar in both the NEXAVAR and placebo-treated groups (32% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 35% of placebo-treated patients).



   Laboratory Abnormalities

  The following laboratory abnormalities were observed in patients with HCC:



 Hypophosphatemia was a common laboratory finding, observed in 35% of NEXAVAR-treated patients compared to 11% of placebo-treated patients; CTCAE Grade 3 hypophosphatemia (1-2 mg/dL) occurred in 11% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 2% of patients in the placebo-treated group; there was 1 case of CTCAE Grade 4 hypophosphatemia (&lt;1 mg/dL) reported in the placebo-treated group. The etiology of hypophosphatemia associated with NEXAVAR is not known.



 Elevated lipase was observed in 40% of patients treated with NEXAVAR compared to 37% of patients in the placebo-treated group. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 lipase elevations occurred in 9% of patients in each group. Elevated amylase was observed in 34% of patients treated with NEXAVAR compared to 29% of patients in the placebo-treated group. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 amylase elevations were reported in 2% of patients in each group. Many of the lipase and amylase elevations were transient, and in the majority of cases NEXAVAR treatment was not interrupted. Clinical pancreatitis was reported in 1 of 297 NEXAVAR-treated patients (CTCAE Grade 2).



 Elevations in liver function tests were comparable between the 2 arms of the study. Hypoalbuminemia was observed in 59% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 47% of placebo-treated patients; no CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 hypoalbuminemia was observed in either group.



 INR elevations were observed in 42% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 34% of placebo-treated patients; CTCAE Grade 3 INR elevations were reported in 4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 2% of placebo-treated patients; there was no CTCAE Grade 4 INR elevation in either group.



 Lymphopenia was observed in 47% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 42% of placebo-treated patients.



 Thrombocytopenia was observed in 46% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 41% of placebo-treated patients; CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 thrombocytopenia was reported in 4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and less than 1% of placebo-treated patients.



 Hypocalcemia was reported in 27% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 15% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 3 hypocalcemia (6-7 mg /dL) occurred in 2% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 1% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 4 hypocalcemia (&lt;6 mg/dL) occurred in 0.4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and in no placebo-treated patients.



 Hypokalemia was reported in 9.5% of NEXAVAR- treated patients compared to 5.9% of placebo-treated patients. Most reports of hypokalemia were low grade (CTCAE Grade 1). CTCAE Grade 3 hypokalemia occurred in 0.4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 0.7% of placebo-treated patients. There were no reports of Grade 4 hypokalemia.



   6.2 Adverse Reactions in RCC Study 1

  Table 5 shows the percentage of patients with RCC experiencing adverse reactions that were reported in at least 10% of patients and at a higher rate in the NEXAVAR arm than the placebo arm. CTCAE Grade 3 adverse reactions were reported in 31% of patients receiving NEXAVAR compared to 22% of patients receiving placebo. CTCAE Grade 4 adverse reactions were reported in 7% of patients receiving NEXAVAR compared to 6% of patients receiving placebo.



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions Reported in at Least 10% of Patients and at a Higher Rate in NEXAVAR Arm than the Placebo Arm - RCC Study 1 
                                     NEXAVAR  N=451    Placebo  N=451    
  Adverse ReactionsNCI- CTCAE v3Category/Term    AllGrades%    Grade3%    Grade4%    AllGrades%    Grade3%    Grade4%    
  Any Adverse Reactions              95          31        7         86          22        6         
  Cardiovascular, General                                                                            
  Hypertension                       17          3         &lt;1        2           &lt;1        0         
  Constitutional symptoms                                                                            
  Fatigue                            37          5         &lt;1        28          3         &lt;1        
  Weight loss                        10          &lt;1        0         6           0         0         
  Dermatology/skin                                                                                   
  Rash/desquamation                  40          &lt;1        0         16          &lt;1        0         
  Hand-foot skin reaction            30          6         0         7           0         0         
  Alopecia                           27          &lt;1        0         3           0         0         
  Pruritus                           19          &lt;1        0         6           0         0         
  Dry skin                           11          0         0         4           0         0         
  Gastrointestinal symptoms                                                                          
  Diarrhea                           43          2         0         13          &lt;1        0         
  Nausea                             23          &lt;1        0         19          &lt;1        0         
  Anorexia                           16          &lt;1        0         13          1         0         
  Vomiting                           16          &lt;1        0         12          1         0         
  Constipation                       15          &lt;1        0         11          &lt;1        0         
  Hemorrhage/bleeding                                                                                
  Hemorrhage - all sites             15          2         0         8           1         &lt;1        
  Neurology                                                                                          
  Neuropathy-sensory                 13          &lt;1        0         6           &lt;1        0         
  Pain                                                                                               
  Pain, abdomen                      11          2         0         9           2         0         
  Pain, joint                        10          2         0         6           &lt;1        0         
  Pain, headache                     10          &lt;1        0         6           &lt;1        0         
  Pulmonary                                                                                          
  Dyspnea                            14          3         &lt;1        12          2         &lt;1        
             The rate of adverse reactions (including those associated with progressive disease) resulting in permanent discontinuation was similar in both the NEXAVAR and placebo-treated groups (10% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 8% of placebo-treated patients).
 

   Laboratory Abnormalities

  The following laboratory abnormalities were observed in patients with RCC in Study 1:



 Hypophosphatemia was a common laboratory finding, observed in 45% of NEXAVAR-treated patients compared to 11% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 3 hypophosphatemia (1-2 mg/dL) occurred in 13% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 3% of patients in the placebo-treated group. There were no cases of CTCAE Grade 4 hypophosphatemia (&lt;1 mg/dL) reported in either NEXAVAR or placebo-treated patients. The etiology of hypophosphatemia associated with NEXAVAR is not known.



 Elevated lipase was observed in 41% of patients treated with NEXAVAR compared to 30% of patients in the placebo-treated group. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 lipase elevations occurred in 12% of patients in the NEXAVAR-treated group compared to 7% of patients in the placebo-treated group. Elevated amylase was observed in 30% of patients treated with NEXAVAR compared to 23% of patients in the placebo-treated group. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 amylase elevations were reported in 1% of patients in the NEXAVAR-treated group compared to 3% of patients in the placebo-treated group. Many of the lipase and amylase elevations were transient, and in the majority of cases NEXAVAR treatment was not interrupted. Clinical pancreatitis was reported in 3 of 451 NEXAVAR-treated patients (one CTCAE Grade 2 and two Grade 4) and 1 of 451 patients (CTCAE Grade 2) in the placebo-treated group.



 Lymphopenia was observed in 23% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 13% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 lymphopenia was reported in 13% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 7% of placebo-treated patients. Neutropenia was observed in 18% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 10% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia was reported in 5% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 2% of placebo-treated patients.



 Anemia was observed in 44% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 49% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 anemia was reported in 2% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 4% of placebo-treated patients.



 Thrombocytopenia was observed in 12% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 5% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 thrombocytopenia was reported in 1% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and in no placebo-treated patients.



 Hypocalcemia was reported in 12% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 8% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 3 hypocalcemia (6-7 mg/dL) occurred in 1% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 0.2% of placebo-treated patients, and CTCAE Grade 4 hypocalcemia (&lt;6 mg/dL) occurred in 1% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 0.5% of placebo-treated patients.



 Hypokalemia was reported in 5.4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients compared to 0.7% of placebo-treated patients. Most reports of hypokalemia were low grade (CTCAE Grade 1). CTCAE Grade 3 hypokalemia occurred in 1.1% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 0.2% of placebo-treated patients. There were no reports of Grade 4 hypokalemia.



   6.3 Adverse Reactions in DTC Study

  The safety of NEXAVAR was evaluated in 416 patients with locally recurrent or metastatic, progressive differentiated thyroid carcinoma (DTC) refractory to radioactive iodine (RAI) treatment randomized to receive 400 mg twice daily NEXAVAR (n=207) or matching placebo (n=209) until disease progression or intolerable toxicity in a double-blind trial  [see Clinical Studies (14.3)].  The data described below reflect a median exposure to NEXAVAR for 46 weeks (range 0.3 to 135). The population exposed to NEXAVAR was 50% male, and had a median age of 63 years.



 Dose interruptions for adverse reactions were required in 66% of patients receiving NEXAVAR and 64% of patients had their dose reduced. Drug-related adverse reactions that resulted in treatment discontinuation were reported in 14% of NEXAVAR-treated patients compared to 1.4% of placebo-treated patients.



 Table 6 shows the percentage of DTC patients experiencing adverse reactions at a higher rate in NEXAVAR-treated patients than placebo-treated patients in the double-blind phase of the DTC study. CTCAE Grade 3 adverse reactions occurred in 53% of NEXAVAR-treated patients compared to 23% of placebo-treated patients. CTCAE Grade 4 adverse reactions occurred in 12% of NEXAVAR-treated patients compared to 7% of placebo-treated patients.



 Table 6: Per-Patient Incidence of Selected Adverse Reactions Occurring at a Higher Incidence in NEXAVAR-Treated Patients [Between Arm Difference of &gt;= 5% (All Grades)1 or &gt;= 2% (Grades 3 and 4)] 
   MedDRA Primary System Organ Class &amp; Preferred Term      NEXAVARN = 207                   PlaceboN = 209     
   All Grades(%)      Grades 3 and 4(%)                All Grades(%)      Grades 3 and 4(%)     
  
  Gastrointestinal disorders    
      Diarrhea                         68    6                 15    1                 
      Nausea                           21    0                 12    0                 
      Abdominal pain2                  20    1                 7    1                 
      Constipation                     16    0                 8    0.5               
      Stomatitis3                      24    2                 3    0                 
      Vomiting                         11    0.5               6    0                 
      Oral pain4                       14    0                 3    0                 
  General disorders and administration site conditions    
      Fatigue                          41    5                 20    1                 
      Asthenia                         12    0                 7    0                 
      Pyrexia                          11    1                 5    0                 
  Investigations    
      Weight loss                      49    6                 14    1                 
  Metabolism and nutrition disorders    
      Decreased appetite               30    2                 5    0                 
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders    
      Pain in extremity                15    1                 7    0                 
      Muscle spasms                    10    0                 3    0                 
  Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified    
      Squamous cell carcinoma of skin    3    3                 0    0                 
  Nervous system disorders    
      Headache                         17    0                 6    0                 
      Dysgeusia                        6    0                 0    0                 
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders    
      Dysphonia                        13    0.5               3    0                 
      Epistaxis                        7    0                 1    0                 
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders    
      PPES5                            69    19                8    0                 
      Alopecia                         67    0                 8    0                 
      Rash                             35    5                 7    0                 
      Pruritus                         20    0.5               11    0                 
      Dry skin                         13    0.5               5    0                 
      Erythema                         10    0                 0.5    0                 
      Hyperkeratosis                   7    0                 0    0                 
  Vascular disorders    
      Hypertension6                    41    10                12    2                 
                                        2  Includes the following terms: abdominal pain, abdominal discomfort, hepatic pain, esophageal pain, esophageal discomfort, abdominal pain lower, abdominal pain upper, abdominal tenderness, abdominal rigidity 
                                   1 National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Version 3.0  3 Includes the following terms: stomatitis, aphthous stomatitis, mouth ulceration, mucosal inflammation  4 Includes the following terms: oral pain, oropharyngeal discomfort, glossitis, burning mouth syndrome, glossodynia  5 Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome (Hand-foot skin reaction)  6 Includes the following terms: hypertension, blood pressure increased, blood pressure systolic increased    
                  Laboratory Abnormalities
   Elevated TSH levels are discussed elsewhere in the labeling  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.12)].  The relative increase for the following laboratory abnormalities observed in NEXAVAR-treated DTC patients as compared to placebo-treated patients is similar to that observed in the RCC and HCC studies: lipase, amylase, hypokalemia, hypophosphatemia, neutropenia, lymphopenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia  [see Adverse Reactions (6.1, 6.2)]  .



 Serum ALT and AST elevations were observed in 59% and 54% of the NEXAVAR-treated patients as compared to 24% and 15% of placebo-treated patients, respectively. High grade (&gt;= 3) ALT and AST elevations were observed in 4% and 2%, respectively, in the NEXAVAR-treated patients as compared to none of the placebo-treated patients.



 Hypocalcemia was more frequent and more severe in patients with DTC, especially those with a history of hypoparathyroidism, compared to patients with RCC or HCC. Hypocalcemia was observed in 36% of DTC patients receiving NEXAVAR (with 10% &gt;= Grade 3) as compared with 11% of placebo-treated patients (3% &gt;= Grade 3). In the DTC study, serum calcium levels were monitored monthly.



   6.4 Additional Data from Multiple Clinical Trials

  The following additional drug-related adverse reactions and laboratory abnormalities were reported from clinical trials of NEXAVAR (  very common  10% or greater,  common  1 to less than 10%,  uncommon  0.1% to less than 1%,  rare  less than 0.1 %):



   Cardiovascular:     Common  : congestive heart failure*    , myocardial ischemia and/or infarction  Uncommon:  hypertensive crisis*  Rare:  QT prolongation*



   Dermatologic:     Very common:  erythema  Common:  exfoliative dermatitis, acne, flushing, folliculitis, hyperkeratosis  Uncommon:  eczema, erythema multiforme



   Digestive:     Very common:  increased lipase, increased amylase  Common:  mucositis, stomatitis (including dry mouth and glossodynia), dyspepsia, dysphagia, gastrointestinal reflux  Uncommon:  pancreatitis, gastritis, gastrointestinal perforations*, cholecystitis, cholangitis



 Note that elevations in lipase are very common (41%, see below); a diagnosis of pancreatitis should not be made solely on the basis of abnormal laboratory values



   General Disorders:     Very common:  infection, hemorrhage (including gastrointestinal* and respiratory tract* and uncommon cases of cerebral hemorrhage*), asthenia, pain (including mouth, bone, and tumor pain), pyrexia, decreased appetite  Common:  influenza-like illness



   Hematologic:     Very common:  leukopenia, lymphopenia  Common:  anemia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia  Uncommon:  INR abnormal



   Hepatobiliary disorders:     Rare:  drug-induced hepatitis (including hepatic failure and death)



   Hypersensitivity:     Uncommon:  hypersensitivity reactions (including skin reactions and urticaria), anaphylactic reaction



   Metabolic and Nutritional:     Very common:  hypophosphatemia  Common:  transient increases in transaminases, hypocalcemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypothyroidism  Uncommon:  dehydration, transient increases in alkaline phosphatase, increased bilirubin (including jaundice), hyperthyroidism



   Musculoskeletal:     Very common:  arthralgia  Common:  myalgia, muscle spasms



   Nervous System and Psychiatric:     Common:  depression, dysgeusia  Uncommon:  tinnitus, reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy*



   Renal and Genitourinary:     Common  : renal failure, proteinuria  Rare:  nephrotic syndrome



   Reproductive:     Common:  erectile dysfunction  Uncommon:  gynecomastia



   Respiratory:     Common:  rhinorrhea  Uncommon:  interstitial lung disease-like events (includes reports of pneumonitis, radiation pneumonitis, acute respiratory distress, interstitial pneumonia, pulmonitis and lung inflammation)



 In addition, the following medically significant adverse reactions were uncommon during clinical trials of NEXAVAR: transient ischemic attack, arrhythmia, and thromboembolism. For these adverse reactions, the causal relationship to NEXAVAR has not been established.



 *adverse reactions may have a life-threatening or fatal outcome.



     reported in 1.9% of patients treated with NEXAVAR (N= 2276).



   6.5 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse drug reactions have been identified during post-approval use of NEXAVAR. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Dermatologic:  Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN)



   Hypersensitivity:  Angioedema



   Musculoskeletal:  Rhabdomyolysis, osteonecrosis of the jaw



   Respiratory:  Interstitial lung disease-like events (which may have a life-threatening or fatal outcome)
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Cardiac Ischemia and/or Infarction: Consider temporary or permanent discontinuation of NEXAVAR. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Bleeding: Discontinue NEXAVAR if needed. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Hypertension: Monitor blood pressure weekly during the first 6 weeks and periodically thereafter. (  5.3)   
 *    Dermatologic Toxicities: Interrupt and/or decrease dose. Discontinue for severe or persistent reactions, or if Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis is suspected. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Gastrointestinal Perforation: Discontinue NEXAVAR. (  5.5  ) 
 *    QT Prolongation: Monitor electrocardiograms and electrolytes in patients at increased risk for ventricular arrhythmias. (  5.9  ,  12.2  ) 
 *    Drug-Induced Hepatitis: Monitor liver function tests regularly; discontinue for unexplained transaminase elevations. (  5.10  ) 
 *    Embryofetal Toxicity: Advise women of potential risk to fetus and to avoid becoming pregnant. (  5.11  ,  8.1  ) 
 *    Impairment of TSH suppression in DTC: Monitor TSH monthly and adjust thyroid replacement therapy in patients with thyroid cancer. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Cardiac Ischemia and/or Infarction



  In the HCC study, the incidence of cardiac ischemia/infarction was 2.7% in NEXAVAR-treated patients compared with 1.3% in the placebo-treated group, in RCC Study 1, the incidence of cardiac ischemia/infarction was higher in the NEXAVAR-treated group (2.9%) compared with the placebo-treated group (0.4%), and in the DTC study, the incidence of cardiac ischemia/infarction was 1.9% in the NEXAVAR-treated group compared with 0% in the placebo-treated group. Patients with unstable coronary artery disease or recent myocardial infarction were excluded from this study. Temporary or permanent discontinuation of NEXAVAR should be considered in patients who develop cardiac ischemia and/or infarction.



    5.2 Risk of Hemorrhage



  An increased risk of bleeding may occur following NEXAVAR administration. In the HCC study, an excess of bleeding regardless of causality was not apparent and the rate of bleeding from esophageal varices was 2.4% in NEXAVAR-treated patients and 4% in placebo-treated patients. Bleeding with a fatal outcome from any site was reported in 2.4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 4% in placebo-treated patients. In RCC Study 1, bleeding regardless of causality was reported in 15.3% of patients in the NEXAVAR-treated group and 8.2% of patients in the placebo-treated group. The incidence of CTCAE Grade 3 and 4 bleeding was 2% and 0%, respectively, in NEXAVAR-treated patients, and 1.3% and 0.2%, respectively, in placebo-treated patients. There was one fatal hemorrhage in each treatment group in RCC Study 1. In the DTC study, bleeding was reported in 17.4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 9.6% of placebo-treated patients; however the incidence of CTCAE Grade 3 bleeding was 1% in NEXAVAR-treated patients and 1.4% in placebo-treated patients. There was no Grade 4 bleeding reported and there was one fatal hemorrhage in a placebo-treated patient. If any bleeding necessitates medical intervention, permanent discontinuation of NEXAVAR should be considered. Due to the potential risk of bleeding, tracheal, bronchial, and esophageal infiltration should be treated with local therapy prior to administering NEXAVAR in patients with DTC.



    5.3 Risk of Hypertension



  Monitor blood pressure weekly during the first 6 weeks of NEXAVAR. Thereafter, monitor blood pressure and treat hypertension, if required, in accordance with standard medical practice. In the HCC study, hypertension was reported in approximately 9.4% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 4.3% of patients in the placebo-treated group. In RCC Study 1, hypertension was reported in approximately 16.9% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 1.8% of patients in the placebo-treated group. In the DTC study, hypertension was reported in 40.6% of NEXAVAR-treated patients and 12.4% of placebo-treated patients. Hypertension was usually mild to moderate, occurred early in the course of treatment, and was managed with standard antihypertensive therapy. In cases of severe or persistent hypertension despite institution of antihypertensive therapy, consider temporary or permanent discontinuation of NEXAVAR. Permanent discontinuation due to hypertension occurred in 1 of 297 NEXAVAR-treated patients in the HCC study, 1 of 451 NEXAVAR-treated patients in RCC Study 1, and 1 of 207 NEXAVAR-treated patients in the DTC study.



    5.4 Risk of Dermatologic Toxicities



  Hand-foot skin reaction and rash represent the most common adverse reactions attributed to NEXAVAR. Rash and hand-foot skin reaction are usually CTCAE Grade 1 and 2 and generally appear during the first six weeks of treatment with NEXAVAR. Management of dermatologic toxicities may include topical therapies for symptomatic relief, temporary treatment interruption and/or dose modification of NEXAVAR, or in severe or persistent cases, permanent discontinuation of NEXAVAR [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )].  Permanent discontinuation of therapy due to hand-foot skin reaction occurred in 4 (1.3%) of 297 NEXAVAR-treated patients with HCC, 3 (0.7%) of 451 NEXAVAR-treated patients with RCC, and 11 (5.3%) of 207 NEXAVAR-treated patients with DTC.



 There have been reports of severe dermatologic toxicities, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN). These cases may be life-threatening. Discontinue NEXAVAR if SJS or TEN are suspected.



    5.5 Risk of Gastrointestinal Perforation



  Gastrointestinal perforation is an uncommon adverse reaction and has been reported in less than 1% of patients taking NEXAVAR. In some cases this was not associated with apparent intra-abdominal tumor. In the event of a gastrointestinal perforation, discontinue NEXAVAR.



    5.6 Warfarin



  Infrequent bleeding or elevations in the International Normalized Ratio (INR) have been reported in some patients taking warfarin while on NEXAVAR. Monitor patients taking concomitant warfarin regularly for changes in prothrombin time (PT), INR or clinical bleeding episodes.



    5.7 Wound Healing Complications



  No formal studies of the effect of NEXAVAR on wound healing have been conducted. Temporary interruption of NEXAVAR is recommended in patients undergoing major surgical procedures. There is limited clinical experience regarding the timing of reinitiation of NEXAVAR following major surgical intervention. Therefore, the decision to resume NEXAVAR following a major surgical intervention should be based on clinical judgment of adequate wound healing.



    5.8 Increased Mortality Observed with NEXAVAR Administered in Combination with Carboplatin/Paclitaxel and Gemcitabine/Cisplatin in Squamous Cell Lung Cancer



  In a subset analysis of two randomized controlled trials in chemo-naive patients with Stage IIIB-IV non-small cell lung cancer, patients with squamous cell carcinoma experienced higher mortality with the addition of NEXAVAR compared to those treated with carboplatin/paclitaxel alone (HR 1.81, 95% CI 1.19-2.74) and gemcitabine/cisplatin alone (HR 1.22, 95% CI 0.82-1.80). The use of NEXAVAR in combination with carboplatin/paclitaxel is contraindicated in patients with squamous cell lung cancer. NEXAVAR in combination with gemcitabine/cisplatin is not recommended in patients with squamous cell lung cancer. The safety and effectiveness of NEXAVAR has not been established in patients with non-small cell lung cancer.



    5.9 Risk of QT Interval Prolongation



  NEXAVAR can prolong the QT/QTc interval. QT/QTc interval prolongation increases the risk for ventricular arrhythmias.   Avoid NEXAVAR in patients with congenital long QT syndrome. Monitor electrolytes and electrocardiograms in patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, drugs known to prolong the QT interval, including Class Ia and III antiarrhythmics. Correct electrolyte abnormalities (magnesium, potassium, calcium). Interrupt NEXAVAR if QTc interval is greater than 500 milliseconds or for an increase from baseline of 60 milliseconds or greater [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )].  



    5.10 Drug-Induced Hepatitis



  Sorafenib-induced hepatitis is characterized by a hepatocellular pattern of liver damage with significant increases of transaminases which may result in hepatic failure and death. Increases in bilirubin and INR may also occur. The incidence of severe drug-induced liver injury, defined as elevated transaminase levels above 20 times the upper limit of normal or transaminase elevations with significant clinical sequelae (for example, elevated INR, ascites, fatal, or transplantation), was two of 3,357 patients (0.06%) in a global monotherapy database. Monitor liver function tests regularly. In case of significantly increased transaminases without alternative explanation, such as viral hepatitis or progressing underlying malignancy, discontinue NEXAVAR.



    5.11 Embryofetal Risk



  Based on its mechanism of action and findings in animals, NEXAVAR may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Sorafenib caused embryo-fetal toxicities in animals at maternal exposures that were significantly lower than the human exposures at the recommended dose of 400 mg twice daily. Advise women of childbearing potential to avoid becoming pregnant while on NEXAVAR because of the potential hazard to the fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )].  



    5.12 Impairment of Thyroid Stimulating Hormone Suppression in Differentiated Thyroid Carcinoma  



  NEXAVAR impairs exogenous thyroid suppression. In the DTC study, 99% of patients had a baseline thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) level less than 0.5 mU/L. Elevation of TSH level above 0.5 mU/L was observed in 41% of NEXAVAR-treated patients as compared with 16% of placebo-treated patients. For patients with impaired TSH suppression while receiving NEXAVAR, the median maximal TSH was 1.6 mU/L and 25% had TSH levels greater than 4.4 mU/L.



 Monitor TSH levels monthly and adjust thyroid replacement medication as needed in patients with DTC.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
