<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nexium1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (  &gt;  1%) are headache, flatulence, nausea, abdominal pain, injection site reaction, diarrhea, dry mouth, dizziness/vertigo, constipation and pruritus.  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience with Intravenous NEXIUM

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adults    



 The safety of intravenous esomeprazole is based on results from clinical trials conducted in four different populations including patients having symptomatic GERD with or without a history of erosive esophagitis (n=199), patients with erosive esophagitis (n=160), healthy subjects (n=204) and patients with bleeding gastric or duodenal ulcers (n=375).



   Symptomatic GERD and Erosive Esophagitis Trials  



 The data described below reflect exposure to NEXIUM I.V. for Injection in 359 patients. NEXIUM I.V. for Injection was studied only in actively-controlled trials. The population was 18 to 77 years of age; 45% Male, 52% Caucasian, 17% Black, 3% Asian, 28% Other, and had either erosive reflux esophagitis (44%) or GERD (56%). Most patients received doses of either 20 or 40 mg either as an infusion or an injection. Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;= 1% of patients treated with intravenous esomeprazole (n=359) in clinical trials are listed below:



 



 Table 2 Adverse reactions occurring at an incidence &gt;= 1% in the NEXIUM I.V. group 
   Adverse Reactions       % of patients    Esomeprazole    Intravenous    (n=359)     
  
  Headache                10.9              
  Flatulence              10.3              
  Nausea                  6.4               
  Abdominal pain          5.8               
  Diarrhea                3.9               
  Mouth dry               3.9               
  Dizziness/vertigo       2.8               
  Constipation            2.5               
  Injection site reaction    1.7               
  Pruritus                1.1               
        Intravenous treatment with esomeprazole 20 and 40 mg-administered as an injection or as an infusion was found to have a safety profile similar to that of oral administration of esomeprazole.
 

     Pediatric    



 A randomized, open-label, multi-national study to evaluate the pharmacokinetics of repeated intravenous doses of once daily esomeprazole in pediatric patients 1 month to 17 years old, inclusive was performed. The safety results are consistent with the known safety profile of esomeprazole and no unexpected safety signals were identified [  see      Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



   Risk Reduction of Rebleeding of Gastric or Duodenal Ulcers in Adults  



 The data described below reflect exposure to NEXIUM I.V. for Injection in 375 patients. NEXIUM I.V. for Injection was studied in a placebo-controlled trial. Patients were randomized to receive NEXIUM I.V. for Injection (n=375) or placebo (n=389). The population was 18 to 98 years old; 68% Male, 87% Caucasian, 1% Black, 7% Asian, 4% other, who presented with endoscopically confirmed gastric or duodenal ulcer bleeding. Following endoscopic hemostasis, patients received either 80 mg esomeprazole as an intravenous infusion over 30 minutes followed by a continuous infusion of 8 mg per hour or placebo for a total treatment duration of 72 hours. After the initial 72-hour period, all patients received oral proton pump inhibitor (PPI) for 27 days.



 Table 3 Incidence (%) of adverse reactions that occurred in greater than 1% of patients within 72 hours after start of treatmentIncidence &gt;=1% in the esomeprazole group and greater than placebo group safety population 
                                          Number (%) of patients    
                                          Esomeprazole  (n=375)    Placebo  (n=389)    
  Duodenal ulcer haemorrhage              16 (4.3%)           16 (4.1%)           
  Injection site reactionInjection site reactions included erythema, swelling, inflammation, pruritus, phlebitis, thrombophlebitis and superficial phlebitis.    16 (4.3%)           2 (0.5%)            
  Pyrexia                                 13 (3.5%)           11 (2.8%)           
  Cough                                   4 (1.1%)            1 (0.3%)            
  Dizziness                               4 (1.1%)            3 (0.8%)            
         With the exception of injection site reactions described above, intravenous treatment with esomeprazole administered as an injection or as an infusion was found to have a safety profile similar to that of oral administration of esomeprazole.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of NEXIUM. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Postmarketing Reports - There have been spontaneous reports of adverse events with postmarketing use of esomeprazole. These reports occurred rarely and are listed below by body system:



     Blood And Lymphatic System Disorders:    agranulocytosis, pancytopenia;    Eye Disorders:    blurred vision;    Gastrointestinal Disorders:    pancreatitis; stomatitis; microscopic colitis;    Hepatobiliary Disorders:    hepatic failure, hepatitis with or without jaundice;    Immune System Disorders:    anaphylactic reaction/shock;    Infections and Infestations:    GI candidiasis;    Metabolism and nutritional disorders:    hypomagnesemia with or without hypocalcemia and/or hypokalemia;    Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders:    muscular weakness, myalgia, bone fracture;    Nervous System Disorders:    hepatic encephalopathy, taste disturbance;    Psychiatric Disorders:    aggression, agitation, depression, hallucination;    Renal and Urinary Disorders:    interstitial nephritis;    Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:    gynecomastia;    Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:    bronchospasm;    Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    alopecia, erythema multiforme, hyperhidrosis, photosensitivity, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN, some fatal).



 Other adverse events not observed with NEXIUM, but occurring with omeprazole can be found in the omeprazole package insert,  ADVERSE REACTIONS  section.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Symptomatic response to therapy with NEXIUM does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.  (5.1)   
 *    Atrophic gastritis has been noted with long-term omeprazole therapy.  (5.2)   
 *    Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs. (  5.3  ) 
 *    PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Avoid concomitant use of NEXIUM I.V. with clopidogrel. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Bone Fracture: Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Avoid concomitant use of NEXIUM with St. John's Wort or rifampin due to the potential reduction in esomeprazole levels (  5.8  ,  7.2  ) 
 *    Interactions with diagnostic investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors: Increases in intragastric pH may result in hypergastrinemia and enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia and increased chromogranin A levels which may interfere with diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. (  5.9  ,  12.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Concomitant Gastric Malignancy



  Symptomatic response to therapy with NEXIUM does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



    5.2 Atrophic Gastritis



  Atrophic gastritis has been noted occasionally in gastric corpus biopsies from patients treated long-term with omeprazole, of which esomeprazole is an enantiomer.



     5.3 Acute Interstitial Nephritis  



   Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including NEXIUM I.V.. Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue NEXIUM I.V. if acute interstitial nephritis develops [ see       Contraindications (4)     ].  



    5.4 Clostridium difficile  Associated Diarrhea



  Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like NEXIUM may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



 Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.



    5.5 Interaction with Clopidogrel



  Avoid concomitant use of NEXIUM I.V. with clopidogrel. Clopidogrel is a prodrug. Inhibition of platelet aggregation by clopidogrel is entirely due to an active metabolite. The metabolism of clopidogrel to its active metabolite can be impaired by use with concomitant medications, such as esomeprazole, that inhibit CYP2C19 activity. Concomitant use of clopidogrel with 40 mg esomeprazole reduces the pharmacological activity of clopidogrel. When using NEXIUM I.V. consider alternative anti-platelet therapy [ see     Drug Interactions (7)    ,   Pharmacokinetics (12.3)    ].



    5.6 Bone Fracture



  Several published observational studies suggest that proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines [ see     Dosage and Administration (2)     and     Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



    5.7 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), health care professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically [ see     Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



    5.8 Concomitant use of NEXIUM with St. John's Wort or Rifampin



  Drugs which induce CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 (such as St. John's Wort or rifampin) can substantially decrease esomeprazole concentrations [ see     Drug Interactions (7)    ]. Avoid concomitant use of NEXIUM with St. John's Wort or rifampin.



    5.9 Interactions with Investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors



  Serum chromogranin A (CgA) levels increase secondary to drug-induced decreases in gastric acidity. The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. Healthcare providers should temporarily stop esomeprazole treatment at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels and consider  repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high. If serial tests are performed (e.g. for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary [ see     Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ].



    5.10 Concomitant use of NEXIUM with Methotrexate



  Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients [ see     Drug Interactions (7.3)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
