<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nexterone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described in Warnings and Precautions: hypotension, rhythm disturbances, hepatic injury, pulmonary injury, thyroid injury, hypersensitivity.



    EXCERPT:    *    The most common adverse reactions (1-2%) leading to discontinuation of intravenous amiodarone therapy are hypotension, asystole/cardiac arrest/pulseless electrical activity, VT, and cardiogenic shock.  (6)   
 *    Other important adverse reactions are torsade de pointes, congestive heart failure, and liver function test abnormalities.  (6)   
    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare at 1-866-888-2472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a total of 1836 patients in controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials, 14% of patients received intravenous amiodarone for at least one week, 5% received it for at least 2 weeks, 2% received it for at least 3 weeks, and 1% received it for more than 3 weeks, without an increased incidence of severe adverse reactions. The mean duration of therapy in these studies was 5.6 days; median exposure was 3.7 days.



 The most important adverse reactions were hypotension, asystole/cardiac arrest/pulseless electrical activity (PEA), cardiogenic shock, congestive heart failure, bradycardia, liver function test abnormalities, VT, and AV block. Overall, treatment was discontinued for about 9% of the patients because of adverse reactions. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of intravenous amiodarone therapy were hypotension (1.6%), asystole/cardiac arrest/PEA (1.2%), VT (1.1%), and cardiogenic shock (1%).



 Table 4 lists the most common (incidence &gt;=2%) adverse reactions during intravenous amiodarone therapy considered at least possibly drug-related. These data were collected in clinical trials involving 1836 patients with life-threatening VT/VF. Data from all assigned treatment groups are pooled because none of the adverse reactions appeared to be dose-related.



 Table 4: ADVERSE REACTIONS IN PATIENTS RECEIVING INTRAVENOUS AMIODARONE IN CONTROLLED AND OPEN-LABEL STUDIES (&gt;= 2% INCIDENCE) 
  Study Event             ControlledStudies(n = 814)    Open-LabelStudies(n = 1022)    Total(n = 1836)    
  Body as a whole         
  Fever                   24          (2.9%)        13            (1.2%)            37             (2.0%)            
  Cardiovascular System    
  Bradycardia             49          (6.0%)        41            (4.0%)            90             (4.9%)            
  Congestive heart failure    18          (2.2%)        21            (2.0%)            39             (2.1%)            
  Heart arrest            29          (3.5%)        26            (2.5%)            55             (2.9%)            
  Hypotension             165         (20.2%)       123           (12.0%)           288            (15.6%)           
  Ventricular tachycardia    15          (1.8%)        30            (2.9%)            45             (2.4%)            
  Digestive System        
  Liver function tests abnormal    35          (4.2%)        29            (2.8%)            64             (3.4%)            
  Nausea                  29          (3.5%)        43            (4.2%)            72             (3.9%)            
             Other adverse reactions reported in less than 2% of patients receiving intravenous amiodarone in controlled and uncontrolled studies included the following: abnormal kidney function, atrial fibrillation, diarrhea, increased ALT, increased AST, lung edema, nodal arrhythmia, prolonged QT interval, atrioventricular block, respiratory disorder, shock, sinus bradycardia, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, thrombocytopenia, VF, and vomiting.
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported in the post-marketing experience during or in close temporal relationship to intravenous amiodarone administration. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  pancytopenia, neutropenia, hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia, thrombocytopenia, and granulocytosis.



   Cardiac Disorders:  sinus node dysfunction (sinus arrest, sinoatrial block), intraventricular conduction disorders including bundle branch block and infra-HIS block, bradycardia (sometimes fatal), ventricular extrasystoles, and antegrade conduction via an accessory pathway.



   Endocrine Disorders:  syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH)



   Eye Disorders:  visual field defect and blurred vision.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  pancreatitis.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  infusion site reactions, including thombosis, phlebitis, thrombophlebitis, cellulitis, pain, induration, edema, inflammation, urticaria, pruritus, erythema, pigment changes, hypoesthesia, skin sloughing, extravasation possibly leading to venous/infusion site necrosis, intravascular amiodarone deposition/mass (developed in the superior vena cava around acentral venous catheter after long - term [28 days] amiodarone therapy administered through a central line), and granuloma.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  cholestasis, cirrhosis, jaundice, alkaline phosphatase and blood lactate dehydrogenase increase.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  myopathy, muscle weakness, rhabdomyolysis, muscle spasms, and back pain.



   Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (incl cysts and polyps) Disorders:  thyroid nodules/thyroid cancer.



   Nervous System Disorders:  intracranial pressure increased, pseudotumor cerebri, tremor, dizziness and hypoesthesia.



   Psychiatric Disorders:  confusional state, hallucination, disorientation, and delirium.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  acute renal failure (sometimes fatal), renal impairment, renal insufficiency, and blood creatinine increased.



   Reproductive Disorders and Breast Disorders:  Epididymitis



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  interstitial pneumonitis, bronchiolitis obliterans organizing pneumonia (possibly fatal), pulmonary alveolar hemorrhage, pulmonary phospholipidoisis, pleural effusion, bronchospasm, dyspnea, cough, hemoptysis, wheezing, and hypoxia.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  toxic epidermal necrolysis (sometimes fatal), Stevens-Johnson syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme, skin cancer, pruritus, angioedema, and urticaria.



   Vascular Disorders:  vasculitis and flushing.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  NEXTERONE should be administered only by physicians who are experienced in the treatment of life-threatening arrhythmias, who are thoroughly familiar with the risks and benefits of amiodarone therapy, and who have access to facilities adequate for monitoring the effectiveness and side effects of treatment.



 Because of the long half-life of amiodarone and its metabolite desethylamiodarone, the potential for adverse reactions or interactions, as well as observed adverse effects, can persist following amiodarone withdrawal.



    EXCERPT:    *    Hypotension: Slow the infusion; as needed, add vasopressor drugs, positive inotropic agents, and volume expansion.  (5.1)   
 *    Bradycardia and AV block: Slow the infusion or discontinue. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypotension



  Hypotension is the most common adverse reaction seen with intravenous amiodarone. In clinical trials, treatment-emergent, drug-related hypotension was reported as an adverse effect in 288 (16%) of 1836 patients treated with intravenous amiodarone. Clinically significant hypotension during infusions was seen most often in the first several hours of treatment and was not dose related, but appeared to be related to the rate of infusion. Hypotension necessitating alterations in intravenous amiodarone therapy was reported in 3% of patients, with permanent discontinuation required in less than 2% of patients.



 Treat hypotension initially by slowing the infusion; additional standard therapy may be needed, including the following: vasopressor drugs, positive inotropic agents, and volume expansion. Monitor the initial rate of infusion closely and do not exceed the recommended rate [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ].



 In some cases, hypotension may be refractory and result in a fatal outcome [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].



    5.2 Bradycardia and Atrio-ventricular Block



  In 90 (4.9%) of 1836 patients in clinical trials, drug-related bradycardia that was not dose-related occurred while they were receiving intravenous amiodarone for life-threatening VT/VF. Treat bradycardia by slowing the infusion rate or discontinuing NEXTERONE. In some patients, inserting a pacemaker is required. Despite such measures, bradycardia was progressive and terminal in 1 patient during the controlled trials. Treat patients with a known predisposition to bradycardia or AV block with NEXTERONE in a setting where a temporary pacemaker is available.



    5.3 Hepatic Injury



  Elevations of blood hepatic enzyme values [alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT)] are commonly seen in patients with immediately life-threatening VT/VF. Interpreting elevated AST activity can be difficult because the values may be elevated in patients who have had recent myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, or multiple electrical defibrillations. Approximately 54% of patients receiving intravenous amiodarone in clinical studies had baseline liver enzyme elevations, and 13% had clinically significant elevations. In 81% of patients with both baseline and on-therapy data available, the liver enzyme elevations either improved during therapy or remained at baseline levels. Baseline abnormalities in hepatic enzymes are not a contraindication to treatment. Elevated bilirubin levels have been reported in patients administered intravenous amiodarone.



 Acute, centrolobular confluent hepatocellular necrosis leading to hepatic coma, acute renal failure, and death has been associated with the administration of intravenous amiodarone (see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ).



 In patients with life-threatening arrhythmias, the potential risk of hepatic injury should be weighed against the potential benefit of NEXTERONE therapy. Carefully monitor patients receiving NEXTERONE for evidence of progressive hepatic injury. In such cases, consider reducing the rate of administration or withdrawing NEXTERONE.



    5.4 Proarrhythmia



  Like all antiarrhythmic agents, NEXTERONE may cause a worsening of existing arrhythmias or precipitate a new arrhythmia, sometimes leading to fatal outcomes [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]. Proarrhythmia, primarily torsade de pointes (TdP), has been associated with prolongation, by intravenous amiodarone, of the QTc interval to 500 ms or greater. Although QTc prolongation occurred frequently in patients receiving intravenous amiodarone, TdP or new-onset VF occurred infrequently (less than 2%). Monitor patients for QTc prolongation during infusion with NEXTERONE. Reserve the combination of amiodarone with other antiarrhythmic therapies that prolong the QTc to patients with life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias who are incompletely responsive to a single agent.



 Correct hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia or hypocalcemia whenever possible before initiating treatment with NEXTERONE, as these disorders can exaggerate the degree of QTc prolongation and increase the potential for TdP. Give special attention to electrolyte and acid-base balance in patients experiencing severe or prolonged diarrhea or in patients receiving concomitant diuretics and laxatives.



 Amiodarone causes thyroid dysfunction in some patients, which may lead to potentially fatal breakthrough or exacerbated arrhythmias.



    5.5 Pulmonary Injury



   Early-onset Pulmonary Toxicity



  There have been postmarketing reports of acute-onset (days to weeks) pulmonary injury in patients treated with intravenous amiodarone. Findings have included pulmonary infiltrates and masses on X-ray, bronchospasm, wheezing, fever, dyspnea, cough, hemoptysis, and hypoxia. Some cases have progressed to respiratory failure or death.



     ARDS  



  Two percent (2%) of patients were reported to have adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) during clinical studies involving 48 hours of therapy.



    Pulmonary Fibrosis



  There have been reports of early development of pulmonary fibrosis (within 1 to 3 months) following initiation of amiodarone treatment. Only 1 of more than 1000 patients treated with intravenous amiodarone in clinical studies developed pulmonary fibrosis. In that patient, the condition was diagnosed 3 months after treatment with intravenous amiodarone, during which time the patient received oral amiodarone. Pulmonary toxicity is a well-recognized complication of long-term amiodarone use (see package insert for oral amiodarone).



    5.6 Loss of Vision



  Cases of optic neuropathy and optic neuritis, usually resulting in visual impairment, have been reported in patients treated with oral amiodarone or intravenous amiodarone. In some cases, visual impairment has progressed to permanent blindness. Optic neuropathy and neuritis may occur at any time following initiation of therapy. A causal relationship to the drug has not been clearly established. Perform an ophthalmic examination if symptoms of visual impairment appear, such as changes in visual acuity and decreases in peripheral vision. Re-evaluate the necessity of amiodarone therapy if optic neuropathy or neuritis is suspected. Perform regular ophthalmic examination, including fundoscopy and slit-lamp examination, during administration of NEXTERONE.



    5.7 Thyroid Abnormalities



  Amiodarone inhibits peripheral conversion of thyroxine (T4) to triiodothyronine (T3) and may cause increased T4 levels, decreased T3 levels, and increased levels of inactive reverse T3 (rT3) in clinically euthyroid patients. Amiodarone is also a potential source of large amounts of inorganic iodine and can cause either hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism. Evaluate thyroid function prior to treatment and periodically thereafter, particularly in elderly patients, and in any patient with a history of thyroid nodules, goiter, or other thyroid dysfunction. Because of the slow elimination of amiodarone and its metabolites, high plasma iodide levels, altered thyroid function, and abnormal thyroid-function tests may persist for several weeks or even months following NEXTERONE withdrawal.



 There have been postmarketing reports of thyroid nodules/thyroid cancer in patients treated with amiodarone. In some instances hyperthyroidism was also present.



    Hyperthyroidism and Thyrotoxicosis



  Amiodarone causes hyperthyroidism in about 2% of patients. Thyrotoxicosis and arrhythmia with fatal outcome has been reported in the presence of pre-existing hyperthyroidism even following a single intravenous amiodarone dose. Consider the possibility of hyperthyroidism if any new signs of arrhythmia appear.



 Hyperthyroidism may result from iodine load (type 1 amiodarone-induced thyrotoxicosis [type 1 AIT]; in particular in patients with underlying autonomous thyroid nodules or latent Grave's disease). Hyperthyroidism may also result from direct amiodarone-induced destructive thyroiditis that occurs in individuals with no underlying thyroid disease (type 2 AIT), resulting in the release of preformed thyroid hormone into the bloodstream from damaged thyroid follicular epithelium. Mixed forms of hyperthyroidism as a result of both pathogenic mechanisms (excessive thyroid hormone production and thyroid destruction) can also occur. The risk of hyperthyroidism may be higher among patients with prior inadequate dietary iodine intake.



 Identify hyperthyroidism by relevant clinical signs and symptoms, subnormal serum levels of thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH), abnormally elevated serum free T4, and elevated or normal serum T3. Since arrhythmia breakthroughs may accompany amiodarone-induced hyperthyroidism, aggressive medical treatment is indicated, including, if possible, dose reduction or withdrawal of amiodarone. Amiodarone hyperthyroidism may be followed by a transient period of hypothyroidism.



 The institution of antithyroid drugs, beta-adrenergic blockers or temporary corticosteroid therapy may be necessary. The action of antithyroid drugs may be especially delayed in amiodarone-induced thyrotoxicosis because of substantial quantities of preformed thyroid hormones stored in the gland. Radioactive iodine therapy is not recommended because of the low radioiodine uptake associated with amiodarone-induced hyperthyroidism.



 When aggressive treatment of amiodarone-induced thyrotoxicosis has failed or amiodarone cannot be discontinued because it is the only drug effective against the resistant arrhythmia, surgical management may be an option. Experience with thyroidectomy as a treatment for amiodarone-induced thyrotoxicosis is limited, and this form of therapy could induce thyroid storm. Therefore, surgical and anesthetic management require careful planning.



    Hypothyroidism



  Hypothyroidism has been reported in 2 to 10% of patients receiving amiodarone and may be primary or subsequent to resolution of preceding amiodarone-induced hyperthyroidism. This condition may be identified by clinical symptoms and elevated serum TSH levels. Cases of severe hypothyroidism and myxedema coma, sometimes fatal, have been reported in association with amiodarone therapy. In some clinically hypothyroid amiodarone-treated patients, free thyroxine index values may be normal. Manage hypothyroidism by reducing the dose of or discontinuing NEXTERONE and considering the need for thyroid hormone supplement.



    5.8 Neonatal Injury



  Amiodarone can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Fetal exposure may increase the potential for adverse experiences including cardiac, thyroid, neurodevelopmental, neurological and growth effects in neonate. Inform the patient of the potential hazard to the fetus if NEXTERONE is administered during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking NEXTERONE [See  Pregnancy (8.1)  ].  



    5.9 Exaggerated Effects of Perisurgical Therapy



  Perform close perioperative monitoring in patients undergoing general anesthesia who are on amiodarone therapy as they may be more sensitive to the myocardial depressant and conduction defects of halogenated inhalational anesthetics.



    5.10 Interference with Corneal Refractive Laser Surgery



  Advise patients that most manufacturers of corneal refractive laser surgery devices contraindicate corneal refractive laser surgery in patients taking amiodarone.



    5.11 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions have been reported with intravenous amiodarone including shock (sometimes fatal), cardiac arrest, and the following manifestations: hypotension, tachycardia, hypoxia, cyanosis, rash, flushing, hyperhidrosis and cold sweat. Since NEXTERONE contains dextrose, patients with allergy to corn or corn products are at risk for allergic reaction.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
