<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nifedipine1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Over 1000 patients from both controlled and open trials with nifedipine extended-release tablets in hypertension and angina were included in the evaluation of adverse experiences. All side effects reported during nifedipine extended-release tablet therapy were tabulated independent of their causal relation to medication. The most common side effect reported with nifedipine extended-release was edema which was dose related and ranged in frequency from approximately 10% to about 30% at the highest dose studied (180 mg). Other common adverse experiences reported in placebo-controlled trials include:




 NIFEDIPINEEXTENDED-RELEASETABLETS (%)   
 Adverse Effect                                  (N=707)                       Placebo (%)(N=266)           
  
 Headache                                          15.8                                9.8                  
 Fatigue                                           5.9                                 4.1                  
 Dizziness                                         4.1                                 4.5                  
 Constipation                                      3.3                                 2.3                  
 Nausea                                            3.3                                 1.9                  
         Of these, only edema and headache were more common in nifedipine extended-release patients than placebo patients.
 

 The following adverse reactions occurred with an incidence of less than 3.0%. With the exception of leg cramps, the incidence of these side effects was similar to that of placebo alone.



   Body as a Whole/Systemic:  asthenia, flushing, pain  Cardiovascular:  palpitations  Central Nervous System:  insomnia, nervousness, paresthesia, somnolence  Dermatologic:  pruritus, rash  Gastrointestinal:  abdominal pain, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, flatulence  Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, leg cramps  Respiratory:  chest pain (nonspecific), dyspnea  Urogenital:  impotence, polyuria



 Other adverse reactions were reported sporadically with an incidence of 1.0% or less. These include:



   Body as a Whole/Systemic:  face edema, fever, hot flashes, malaise, periorbital edema, rigors  Cardiovascular:  arrhythmia, hypotension, increased angina, tachycardia, syncope  Central Nervous System:  anxiety, ataxia, decreased libido, depression, hypertonia, hypoesthesia, migraine, paroniria, tremor, vertigo  Dermatologic:  alopecia, increased sweating, urticaria, purpura  Gastrointestinal:  eructation, gastroesophageal reflux, gum hyperplasia, melena, vomiting, weight increase  Musculoskeletal:  back pain, gout, myalgias  Respiratory:  coughing, epistaxis, upper respiratory tract infection, respiratory disorder, sinusitis  Special Senses:  abnormal lacrimation, abnormal vision, taste perversion, tinnitus  Urogenital/Reproductive:  breast pain, dysuria, hematuria, nocturia



 Adverse experiences which occurred in less than 1 in 1000 patients cannot be distinguished from concurrent disease states or medications.



 The following adverse experiences, reported in less than 1% of patients, occurred under conditions (e.g., open trials, marketing experience) where a causal relationship is uncertain: gastrointestinal irritation, gastrointestinal bleeding, gynecomastia.



 In multiple-dose U.S. and foreign controlled studies with nifedipine capsules in which adverse reactions were reported spontaneously, adverse effects were frequent but generally not serious and rarely required discontinuation of therapy or dosage adjustment. Most were expected consequences of the vasodilator effects of nifedipine.




                                    NIFEDIPINEIMMEDIATE-RELEASECAPSULES (%)             Placebo (%)              
 Adverse Effect                                  (N=226)                             (N=235)                
  
 Dizziness, lightheadedness, giddiness                  27                                 15                   
 Flushing, heat sensation                           25                                  8                   
 Headache                                           23                                 20                   
 Weakness                                           12                                 10                   
 Nausea, heartburn                                  11                                  8                   
 Muscle cramps, tremor                              8                                   3                   
 Peripheral edema                                   7                                   1                   
 Nervousness, mood changes                          7                                   4                   
 Palpitation                                        7                                   5                   
 Dyspnea, cough, wheezing                           6                                   3                   
 Nasal congestion, sore throat                      6                                   8                   
         There is also a large uncontrolled experience in over 2100 patients in the United States. Most of the patients had vasospastic or resistant angina pectoris, and about half had concomitant treatment with beta-adrenergic blocking agents. The relatively common adverse events were similar in nature to those seen with nifedipine extended-release.
 

 In addition, more serious adverse events were observed, not readily distinguishable from the natural history of the disease in these patients. It remains possible, however, that some or many of these events were drug related. Myocardial infarction occurred in about 4% of patients and congestive heart failure or pulmonary edema in about 2%. Ventricular arrhythmias or conduction disturbances each occurred in fewer than 0.5% of patients.



 In a subgroup of over 1000 patients receiving nifedipine immediate-release with concomitant beta blocker therapy, the pattern and incidence of adverse experiences was not different from that of the entire group of nifedipine immediate-release treated patients. (See  PRECAUTIONS  .)



 In a subgroup of approximately 250 patients with a diagnosis of congestive heart failure as well as angina, dizziness or lightheadedness, peripheral edema, headache or flushing each occurred in one in eight patients. Hypotension occurred in about one in 20 patients. Syncope occurred in approximately one patient in 250. Myocardial infarction or symptoms of congestive heart failure each occurred in about one patient in 15. Atrial or ventricular dysrhythmias each occurred in about one patient in 150.



 In post-marketing experience, there have been rare reports of exfoliative dermatitis caused by nifedipine. There have been rare reports of exfoliative or bullous skin adverse events (such as erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis) and photosensitivity reactions.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    Rx only  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
