<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nifedipine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The incidence of adverse events during treatment with nifedipine extended-release in doses up to 90 mg daily were derived from multi-center placebo-controlled clinical trials in 370 hypertensive patients. Atenolol 50 mg once daily was used concomitantly in 187 of the 370 patients on nifedipine extended-release and in 64 of the 126 patients on placebo. All adverse events reported during nifedipine extended-release therapy were tabulated independently of their causal relationship to medication.



 The most common adverse event reported with nifedipine extended-release was peripheral edema. This was dose related and the frequency was 18% on nifedipine extended-release 30 mg daily, 22% on nifedipine extended-release 60 mg daily and 29% on nifedipine extended-release 90 mg daily versus 10% on placebo.



 Other common adverse events reported in the above placebo-controlled trials include:




                                             NIFEDIPINE EXTENDED-RELEASE (%)      PLACEBO (%)                    
                                             (n=370)                         (n=126)                        
   Adverse Event                                                                                            
  
  Headache                                  19                              13                              
  Flushing/heat sensation                   4                               0                               
  Dizziness                                 4                               2                               
  Fatigue/asthenia                          4                               4                               
  Nausea                                    2                               1                               
  Constipation                              1                               0                               
         Where the frequency of adverse events with nifedipine extended-release and placebo is similar, causal relationship cannot be established.
 

 The following adverse events were reported with an incidence of 3% or less in daily doses up to 90 mg:



 chest pain, leg pain  Body as a Whole/Systemic:  



 paresthesia, vertigo  Central Nervous System:  



 rash  Dermatologic:  



 constipation  Gastrointestinal:  



 leg cramps  Musculoskeletal:  



 epistaxis, rhinitis  Respiratory:  



 impotence, urinary frequency  Urogenital:  



 Other adverse events reported with an incidence of less than 1.0% were:



 allergic reaction, asthenia, cellulitis, substernal chest pain, chills, facial edema, lab test abnormal, malaise, neck pain, pelvic pain, pain, photosensitivity reaction  Body as a Whole/Systemic:  



 atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, cardiac arrest, extrasystole, hypotension, migraine, palpitations, phlebitis, postural hypotension, tachycardia, cutaneous angiectases  Cardiovascular:  



 anxiety, confusion, decreased libido, depression, hypertonia, hypesthesia, insomnia, somnolence  Central Nervous System:  



 angioedema, petechial rash, pruritus, sweating  Dermatologic:  



 abdominal pain, diarrhea, dry mouth, dysphagia, dyspepsia, eructation, esophagitis, flatulence, gastrointestinal disorder, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, GGT increased, gum disorder, gum hemorrhage, vomiting  Gastrointestinal:  



 eosinophilia, lymphadenopathy  Hematologic:  



 gout, weight loss  Metabolic:  



 arthralgia, arthritis, joint disorder, myalgia, myasthenia  Musculoskeletal:  



 dyspnea, increased cough, rales, pharyngitis, stridor  Respiratory:  



 abnormal vision, amblyopia, conjunctivitis, diplopia, eye disorder, eye hemorrhage, tinnitus  Special Senses:  



 dysuria, kidney calculus, nocturia, breast engorgement, polyuria, urogenital disorder, erectile dysfunction (ED)  Urogenital/Reproductive:  



 The following adverse events have been reported rarely in patients given nifedipine in coat core or other formulations: allergenic hepatitis, alopecia, anaphylactic reaction, anemia, arthritis with ANA (+), depression, erythromelalgia, exfoliative dermatitis, fever, gingival hyperplasia, gynecomastia, hyperglycemia, jaundice, leukopenia, mood changes, muscle cramps, nervousness, paranoid syndrome, purpura, shakiness, sleep disturbances, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, syncope, taste perversion, thrombocytopenia, toxic epidermal necrolysis, transient blindness at the peak of plasma level, tremor and urticaria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
