<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="niravam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Side effects to alprazolam, if they occur, are generally observed at the beginning of therapy and usually disappear upon continued medication. In the usual patient, the most frequent side effects are likely to be an extension of the pharmacological activity of alprazolam, eg, drowsiness or lightheadedness.



 The data cited in the two tables below are estimates of untoward clinical event incidence among patients who participated under the following clinical conditions: relatively short duration (ie, four weeks) placebo-controlled clinical studies with dosages up to 4 mg/day of alprazolam (for the management of anxiety disorders or for the short-term relief of the symptoms of anxiety) and short-term (up to ten weeks) placebo-controlled clinical studies with dosages up to 10 mg/day of alprazolam in patients with panic disorder, with or without agoraphobia.



 These data cannot be used to predict precisely the incidence of untoward events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics, and other factors often differ from those in clinical trials. These figures cannot be compared with those obtained from other clinical studies involving related drug products and placebo as each group of drug trials are conducted under a different set of conditions.



 Comparison of the cited figures, however, can provide the prescriber with some basis for estimating the relative contributions of drug and non-drug factors to the untoward event incidence in the population studied. Even this use must be approached cautiously, as a drug may relieve a symptom in one patient but induce it in others. (For example, an anxiolytic drug may relieve dry mouth [a symptom of anxiety] in some subjects but induce it [an untoward event] in others.)



 Additionally, for anxiety disorders the cited figures can provide the prescriber with an indication as to the frequency with which physician intervention (eg, increased surveillance, decreased dosage or discontinuation of drug therapy) may be necessary because of the untoward clinical event.



 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Reported in Placebo-Controlled Trials of Anxiety Disorders 
                                ANXIETY DISORDERS                                  
                            Treatment-EmergentSymptom Incidence  Incidence of Intervention Because of Symptom   
                                   ALPRAZOLAM                   PLACEBO                  ALPRAZOLAM           
  
  Number of Patients  % of Patients Reporting:             565                        505                        565              
   Central Nervous System                                                                                      
         Drowsiness                   41.0                       21.6                       15.1              
       Lightheadedness                20.8                       19.3                        1.2              
         Depression                   13.9                       18.1                        2.4              
          Headache                    12.9                       19.6                        1.1              
          Confusion                    9.9                       10.0                        0.9              
          Insomnia                     8.9                       18.4                        1.3              
         Nervousness                   4.1                       10.3                        1.1              
           Syncope                     3.1                        4.0                                         
          Dizziness                    1.8                        0.8                        2.5              
          Akathisia                    1.6                        1.2                                         
    Tiredness/Sleepiness                                                                     1.8              
     Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
          Dry Mouth                   14.7                       13.3                        0.7              
        Constipation                  10.4                       11.4                        0.9              
          Diarrhea                    10.1                       10.3                        1.2              
       Nausea/Vomiting                 9.6                       12.8                        1.7              
    Increased Salivation               4.2                        2.4                                         
      Cardiovascular                                                                                          
   Tachycardia/Palpitations             7.7                       15.6                        0.4              
         Hypotension                   4.7                        2.2                                         
          Sensory                                                                                             
       Blurred Vision                  6.2                        6.2                        0.4              
      Musculoskeletal                                                                                         
          Rigidity                     4.2                        5.3                                         
           Tremor                      4.0                        8.8                        0.4              
         Cutaneous                                                                                            
     Dermatitis/Allergy                3.8                        3.1                        0.6              
           Other                                                                                              
      Nasal Congestion                 7.3                        9.3                                         
         Weight Gain                   2.7                        2.7                                         
         Weight Loss                   2.3                        3.0                                         
          In addition to the relatively common (ie, greater than 1%) untoward events enumerated in the table above, the following adverse events have been reported in association with the use of benzodiazepines: dystonia, irritability, concentration difficulties, anorexia, transient amnesia or memory impairment, loss of coordination, fatigue, seizures, sedation, slurred speech, jaundice, musculoskeletal weakness, pruritus, diplopia, dysarthria, changes in libido, menstrual irregularities, incontinence and urinary retention.
 

 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Reported in Placebo-Controlled Trials of Panic Disorder 
              PANIC DISORDER                
                                           Treatment-EmergentSymptom Incidence   
                                                     ALPRAZOLAM                       PLACEBO               
  
  Number of Patients % of Patients Reporting:               1388                            1231                
                                                                                                            
          Central Nervous System                                                                            
                 Drowsiness                             76.8                            42.7                
           Fatigue and Tiredness                        48.6                            42.3                
           Impaired Coordination                        40.1                            17.9                
                Irritability                            33.1                            30.1                
             Memory Impairment                          33.1                            22.1                
         Lightheadedness/Dizziness                      29.8                            36.9                
                  Insomnia                              29.4                            41.8                
                  Headache                              29.2                            35.6                
             Cognitive Disorder                         28.8                            20.5                
                 Dysarthria                             23.3                            6.3                 
                  Anxiety                               16.6                            24.9                
       Abnormal Involuntary Movement                    14.8                            21.0                
              Decreased Libido                          14.4                            8.0                 
                 Depression                             13.8                            14.0                
             Confusional State                          10.4                            8.2                 
             Muscular Twitching                         7.9                             11.8                
              Increased Libido                          7.7                             4.1                 
      Change in Libido (Not Specified)                  7.1                             5.6                 
                  Weakness                              7.1                             8.4                 
           Muscle Tone Disorders                        6.3                             7.5                 
                  Syncope                               3.8                             4.8                 
                 Akathisia                              3.0                             4.3                 
                 Agitation                              2.9                             2.6                 
               Disinhibition                            2.7                             1.5                 
                Paresthesia                             2.4                             3.2                 
               Talkativeness                            2.2                             1.0                 
           Vasomotor Disturbances                       2.0                             2.6                 
               Derealization                            1.9                             1.2                 
            Dream Abnormalities                         1.8                             1.5                 
                    Fear                                1.4                             1.0                 
                Feeling Warm                            1.3                             0.5                 
             Gastrointestinal                                                                               
            Decreased Salivation                        32.8                            34.2                
                Constipation                            26.2                            15.4                
              Nausea/Vomiting                           22.0                            31.8                
                  Diarrhea                              20.6                            22.8                
             Abdominal Distress                         18.3                            21.5                
            Increased Salivation                        5.6                             4.4                 
            Cardio-Respiratory                                                                              
              Nasal Congestion                          17.4                            16.5                
                Tachycardia                             15.4                            26.8                
                 Chest Pain                             10.6                            18.1                
              Hyperventilation                          9.7                             14.5                
        Upper Respiratory Infection                     4.3                             3.7                 
                 Sensory                                                                                    
               Blurred Vision                           21.0                            21.4                
                  Tinnitus                              6.6                             10.4                
             Musculoskeletal                                                                                
              Muscular Cramps                           2.4                             2.4                 
              Muscle Stiffness                          2.2                             3.3                 
                Cutaneous                                                                                   
                  Sweating                              15.1                            23.5                
                    Rash                                10.8                            8.1                 
                  Other                                                                                     
             Increased Appetite                         32.7                            22.8                
             Decreased Appetite                         27.8                            24.1                
                Weight Gain                             27.2                            17.9                
                Weight Loss                             22.6                            16.5                
          Micturition Difficulties                      12.2                            8.6                 
            Menstrual Disorders                         10.4                            8.7                 
             Sexual Dysfunction                         7.4                             3.7                 
                   Edema                                4.9                             5.6                 
                Incontinence                            1.5                             0.6                 
                 Infection                              1.3                             1.7                 
         In addition to the relatively common (ie, greater than 1%) untoward events enumerated in the table above, the following adverse events have been reported in association with the use of alprazolam: seizures, hallucinations, depersonalization, taste alterations, diplopia, elevated bilirubin, elevated hepatic enzymes, and jaundice.
 

 Panic disorder has been associated with primary and secondary major depressive disorders and increased reports of suicide among untreated patients (see  PRECAUTIONS, General  ).



   Adverse Events Reported as Reasons for Discontinuation in Treatment of Panic Disorder in Placebo-Controlled Trials

  In a larger database comprised of both controlled and uncontrolled studies in which 641 patients received alprazolam, discontinuation-emergent symptoms which occurred at a rate of over 5% in patients treated with alprazolam and at a greater rate than the placebo-treated group were as follows:



 DISCONTINUATION-EMERGENT SYMPTOM INCIDENCE 
 Percentage of 641 Alprazolam-Treated Panic DisorderPatients Reporting Events   
  
     Body System/Event                      
     Neurologic                                                 Gastrointestinal                                   
 Insomnia                                           29.5    Nausea/Vomiting                                 16.5   
 Lightheadedness                                    19.3    Diarrhea                                        13.6   
 Abnormal involuntary movement                      17.3    Decreased salivation                            10.6   
 Headache                                           17.0                                                           
 Muscular twitching                                  6.9        Metabolic-Nutritional                              
 Impaired coordination                               6.6    Weight loss                                     13.3   
 Muscle tone disorders                               5.9    Decreased appetite                              12.8   
 Weakness                                            5.8                                                           
                                                                Dermatological                                     
     Psychiatric                                            Sweating                                        14.4   
 Anxiety                                            19.2                                                           
 Fatigue and Tiredness                              18.4        Cardiovascular                                     
 Irritability                                       10.5    Tachycardia                                     12.2   
 Cognitive Disorder                                 10.3                                                           
 Memory Impairment                                   5.5        Special Senses                                     
 Depression                                          5.1    Blurred vision                                  10.0   
 Confusional state                                   5.0                                                           
          From the studies cited, it has not been determined whether these symptoms are clearly related to the dose and duration of therapy with alprazolam in patients with panic disorder. There have also been reports of withdrawal seizures upon rapid decrease or abrupt discontinuation of alprazolam (see  WARNINGS  ).
 

 To discontinue treatment in patients taking NIRAVAM  (r)  , the dosage should be reduced slowly in keeping with good medical practice. It is suggested that the daily dosage of NIRAVAM  (r)  be decreased by no more than 0.5 mg every three days (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ). Some patients may benefit from an even slower dosage reduction. In a controlled postmarketing discontinuation study of panic disorder patients which compared this recommended taper schedule with a slower taper schedule, no difference was observed between the groups in the proportion of patients who tapered to zero dose; however, the slower schedule was associated with a reduction in symptoms associated with a withdrawal syndrome.



 As with all benzodiazepines, paradoxical reactions such as stimulation, increased muscle spasticity, sleep disturbances, hallucinations and other adverse behavioral effects such as agitation, rage, irritability, and aggressive or hostile behavior have been reported rarely. In many of the spontaneous case reports of adverse behavioral effects, patients were receiving other CNS drugs concomitantly and/or were described as having underlying psychiatric conditions. Should any of the above events occur, alprazolam should be discontinued. Isolated published reports involving small numbers of patients have suggested that patients who have borderline personality disorder, a prior history of violent or aggressive behavior, or alcohol or substance abuse may be at risk for such events. Instances of irritability, hostility, and intrusive thoughts have been reported during discontinuation of alprazolam in patients with posttraumatic stress disorder.



     Post Introduction Reports    : Various adverse drug reactions have been reported in association with the use of alprazolam since market introduction. The majority of these reactions were reported through the medical event voluntary reporting system. Because of the spontaneous nature of the reporting of medical events and the lack of controls, a causal relationship to the use of alprazolam cannot be readily determined. Reported events include: liver enzyme elevations, hepatitis, hepatic failure, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, hyperprolactinemia, gynecomastia, and galactorrhea.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
