<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nisoldipine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE EXPERIENCES

  More that 6000 patients world-wide have received nisoldipine in clinical trials for the treatment of hypertension, either as the immediate release or the Nisoldipine extended release formulation. Of about 1,500 patients who received Nisoldipine in hypertension studies, about 55% were exposed for at least 2 months and about one third were exposed for over 6 months, the great majority at doses equivalent to 17 mg and above.



 Nisoldipine is generally well-tolerated. In the U.S. clinical trials of Nisoldipine in hypertension, 10.9% of the 921 Nisoldipine patients discontinued treatment due to adverse events compared with 2.9% of 280 placebo patients. The frequency of discontinuations due to adverse experiences was related to dose, with a 5.4% and 10.9% discontinuation rate at the lowest and highest daily dose, respectively.



 The most frequently occurring adverse experiences with Nisoldipine are those related to its vasodilator properties; these are generally mild and only occasionally lead to patient withdrawal from treatment. The table below, from U.S. placebo-controlled parallel dose response trials of Nisoldipine using doses across the clinical dosage range in patients with hypertension, lists all of the adverse events, regardless of the causal relationship to Nisoldipine, for which the overall incidence on Nisoldipine was both &gt;1% and greater with Nisoldipine than with placebo.




           Adverse Event                  Nisoldipine (%) (n=663)              Placebo (%) (n=280)          
  
          Peripheral Edema                          22                                 10                   
              Headache                              22                                 15                   
             Dizziness                               5                                  4                   
            Pharyngitis                              5                                  4                   
            Vasodilation                             4                                  2                   
             Sinusitis                               3                                  2                   
            Palpitation                              3                                  1                   
             Chest Pain                              2                                  1                   
               Nausea                                2                                  1                   
                Rash                                 2                                  1                   
       
                  Only peripheral edema possibly dizzinessappear to be dose related.                    
     
       Adverse Event        Nisoldipine, dose bioequivalent to:   
       (Rates in %)          PlaceboN=280      8.5 mgN=30       17 mgN=170      25.5 mgN=105      34 mgN=139      
  
     Peripheral Edema             10                7               15               20               27          
         Dizziness                 4                7                3                3                4          
            The common adverse events occurred at about the same rate in men as in women, and at a similar rate in patients over age 65 as in those in under that age, except that headache was much less common in older patients. Except for peripheral edema and vasodilation, which were more common in whites, adverse event rates were similar in blacks and whites.
 

 The following adverse events occurred in &amp;lt;1% of all patients treated for hypertension in U.S. and foreign clinical trials, or with unspecified incidence in other studies. Although a causal relationship of Nisoldipine to these events cannot be established, they are listed to alert the physician to a possible relationship with Nisoldipine treatment.



 Body As A Whole: cellulitis, chills, facial edema, fever, flu syndrome, malaise



 Cardiovascular: atrial fibrillation, cerebrovascular accident, congestive heart failure, first degree AV block, hypertension, hypotension, jugular venous distension, migraine, myocardial infarction, postural hypotension, ventricular extrasystoles, supraventricular tachycardia, syncope, systolic ejection murmur, T wave abnormalities on ECG (flattening, inversion, nonspecific changes), venous insufficiency



 Digestive: abnormal liver function tests, anorexia, colitis, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, dysphagia, flatulence, gastritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gingival hyperplasia, glossitis, hepatomegaly, increased appetite, melena, mouth ulceration.



 Endocrine: diabetes mellitus, thyroiditis



 Hemic and Lymphatic: anemia, ecchymoses, leukopenia, petechiae



 Metabolic and Nutritional: gout, hypokalemia, increased serum creatine kinase, increased nonprotein nitrogen, weight gain, weight loss



 Musculoskeletal: arthralgia, arthritis, leg cramps, myalgia, myasthenia, myositis, tenosynovitis



 Nervous: abnormal dreams, abnormal thinking and confusion, amnesia, anxiety, ataxia, cerebral ischemia, decreased libido, depression, hypesthesia, hypertonia, insomnia, nervousness, paresthesia, somnolence, tremor, vertigo



 Respiratory: asthma, dyspnea, end inspiratory wheeze and fine rales, epistaxis, increased cough, laryngitis, pharyngitis, pleural effusion, rhinitis, sinusitis



 Skin and Appendages: acne, alopecia, dry skin, exfoliative dermatitis, fungal dermatitis, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, maculopapular rash, pruritus, pustular rash, skin discoloration, skin ulcer, sweating, urticaria



 Special Senses: abnormal vision, amblyopia, blepharitis, conjunctivitis, ear pain, glaucoma, itchy eyes, keratoconjunctivitis, otitis media, retinal detachment, tinnitus, watery eyes, taste disturbance, temporary unilateral loss of vision, vitreous floater



 Urogenital: dysuria, hematuria, nocturia, urinary frequency, increased BUN and serum creatinine, vaginal hemorrhage, vaginitis.



 The following postmarketing event has been reported very rarely in patients receiving Nisoldipine: systemic hypersensitivity reaction, which may include one or more of the following: angioedema, shortness of breath, tachycardia, chest tightness, hypotension, and rash. A definite causal relationship with Nisoldipine has not been established. An unusual event observed with immediate release nisoldipine but not observed with Nisoldipine extended release was one case of photosensitivity. Gynecomastia has been associated with the use of calcium channel blockers.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
