<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nitrolingual" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions occurring at a frequency greater than 2% are headache, dizzinesss and paresthesia (  6  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Arbor Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-866-516-4950 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Adverse reactions occurring at a frequency greater than 2% and greater than placebo included: headache, dizziness, and paresthesia.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Nitrolingual Pumpspray and other nitroglycerin drugs. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate their frequency reliably or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Neurologic:  weakness, drowsiness



   Dermatologic:  cutaneous vasodilation, flushing, drug rash, exfoliative dermatitits



   Gastrointestinal:  nausea, vomiting



   Respiratory:  transient hypoxemia



   Cardiovascular:  tachycardia,
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:    Tolerance:  Excessive use may lead to tolerance. (  5.1  )



  Hypotension:  Severe hypotension may occur. (  5.2  )



 



   5.1 Tolerance



  Excessive use may lead to the development of tolerance. Only the smallest number of doses required for effective relief of the acute angina attack should be used [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ].  



    5.2 Hypotension



  Severe hypotension, particularly with upright posture, may occur even with small doses of nitroglycerin particularly in patients with constrictive pericarditis, aortic or mitral stenosis, patientswho may be volume-depleted, or are already hypotensive. Hypotension induced by nitroglycerin may be accompanied by paradoxical bradycardia and increased angina pectoris. Symptoms of severe hypotension (nausea, vomiting, weakness, pallor, perspiration and collapse/syncope) may occur even with therapeutic doses.



    5.3 Hypertrophic Obstructive Cardiomyopathy



  Nitrate therapy may aggravate the angina caused by hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy.



    5.4 Headache



  Nitroglycerin produces dose-related headaches, especially at the start of nitroglycerin therapy, which may be severe and persistent but usually subside with continued use.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
