<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="norvasc" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are headache and edema which occurred in a dose related manner. Other adverse experiences not dose related but reported with an incidence &gt;1.0% are headache, fatigue, nausea, abdominal pain, and somnolence. (6)



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer at 1-800-438-1985 or  www.pfizer.com  or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 NORVASC has been evaluated for safety in more than 11,000 patients in U.S. and foreign clinical trials. In general, treatment with NORVASC was well-tolerated at doses up to 10 mg daily. Most adverse reactions reported during therapy with NORVASC were of mild or moderate severity. In controlled clinical trials directly comparing NORVASC (N=1730) at doses up to 10 mg to placebo (N=1250), discontinuation of NORVASC due to adverse reactions was required in only about 1.5% of patients and was not significantly different from placebo (about 1%). The most common side effects are headache and edema. The incidence (%) of side effects that occurred in a dose related manner are as follows:




 Adverse Event                2.5 mg                5.0 mg               10.0 mg               Placebo          
                              N=275                 N=296                 N=268                 N=520           
  
 Edema                         1.8                   3.0                   10.8                  0.6            
 Dizziness                     1.1                   3.4                   3.4                   1.5            
 Flushing                      0.7                   1.4                   2.6                   0.0            
 Palpitation                   0.7                   1.4                   4.5                   0.6            
           Other adverse experiences that were not clearly dose related but were reported with an incidence greater than 1.0% in placebo-controlled clinical trials include the following:
 

 Placebo-Controlled Studies 
                                               NORVASC (%)                        Placebo (%)               
                                                (N=1730)                            (N=1250)                
  
 Headache                                          7.3                                7.8                   
 Fatigue                                           4.5                                2.8                   
 Nausea                                            2.9                                1.9                   
 Abdominal Pain                                    1.6                                0.3                   
 Somnolence                                        1.4                                0.6                   
         For several adverse experiences that appear to be drug and dose related, there was a greater incidence in women than men associated with amlodipine treatment as shown in the following table:
 


                             NORVASC               Placebo          
 Adverse Event                Male=%               Female=%               Male=%               Female=%         
                             (N=1218)              (N=512)               (N=914)               (N=336)          
  
 Edema                         5.6                   14.6                  1.4                   5.1            
 Flushing                      1.5                   4.5                   0.3                   0.9            
 Palpitations                  1.4                   3.3                   0.9                   0.9            
 Somnolence                    1.3                   1.6                   0.8                   0.3            
           The following events occurred in &lt;1% but &gt;0.1% of patients in controlled clinical trials or under conditions of open trials or marketing experience where a causal relationship is uncertain; they are listed to alert the physician to a possible relationship:
 

   Cardiovascular:  arrhythmia (including ventricular tachycardia and atrial fibrillation), bradycardia, chest pain, hypotension, peripheral ischemia, syncope, tachycardia, postural dizziness, postural hypotension, vasculitis.



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  hypoesthesia, neuropathy peripheral, paresthesia, tremor, vertigo.



    Gastrointestinal:  anorexia, constipation, dyspepsia, (These events occurred in less than 1% in placebo-controlled trials, but the incidence of these side effects was between 1% and 2% in all multiple dose studies.) dysphagia, diarrhea, flatulence, pancreatitis, vomiting, gingival hyperplasia.
 

   General:  allergic reaction, asthenia,back pain, hot flushes, malaise, pain, rigors, weight gain, weight decrease.



   Musculoskeletal System:  arthralgia, arthrosis, muscle cramps,myalgia.



   Psychiatric:  sexual dysfunction (maleand female), insomnia, nervousness, depression, abnormal dreams, anxiety, depersonalization.



   Respiratory System:  dyspnea,epistaxis.



   Skin and Appendages:  angioedema, erythema multiforme, pruritus,rash,rash erythematous, rash maculopapular.



   Special Senses:  abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, diplopia, eye pain, tinnitus.



   Urinary System:  micturition frequency, micturition disorder, nocturia.



   Autonomic Nervous System:  dry mouth, sweating increased.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  hyperglycemia, thirst.



   Hemopoietic:  leukopenia, purpura, thrombocytopenia.



 The following events occurred in &lt;0.1% of patients: cardiac failure, pulse irregularity, extrasystoles, skin discoloration, urticaria, skin dryness, alopecia, dermatitis, muscle weakness, twitching, ataxia, hypertonia, migraine, cold and clammy skin, apathy, agitation, amnesia, gastritis, increased appetite, loose stools, coughing, rhinitis, dysuria, polyuria, parosmia, taste perversion, abnormal visual accommodation, and xerophthalmia.



 Other reactions occurred sporadically and cannot be distinguished from medications or concurrent disease states such as myocardial infarction and angina.



 NORVASC therapy has not been associated with clinically significant changes in routine laboratory tests. No clinically relevant changes were noted in serum potassium, serum glucose, total triglycerides, total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, uric acid, blood urea nitrogen, or creatinine.



 In the CAMELOT and PREVENT studies  [see  Clinical Studies (14.4)  ]  , the adverse event profile was similar to that reported previously (see above), with the most common adverse event being peripheral edema.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following postmarketing event has been reported infrequently where a causal relationship is uncertain: gynecomastia. In postmarketing experience, jaundice and hepatic enzyme elevations (mostly consistent with cholestasis or hepatitis), in some cases severe enough to require hospitalization, have been reported in association with use of amlodipine.



 NORVASC has been used safely in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, well-compensated congestive heart failure, coronary artery disease, peripheral vascular disease, diabetes mellitus, and abnormal lipid profiles.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Symptomatic hypotension is possible, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis. However, because of the gradual onset of action, acute hypotension is unlikely. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Worsening angina and acute myocardial infarction can develop after starting or increasing the dose of NORVASC, particularly in patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Titrate slowly when administering calcium channel blockers to patients with severe hepatic impairment. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypotension



  Symptomatic hypotension is possible, particularly in patients with severe aortic stenosis. Because of the gradual onset of action, acute hypotension is unlikely.



    5.2 Increased Angina or Myocardial Infarction



  Worsening angina and acute myocardial infarction can develop after starting or increasing the dose of NORVASC, particularly in patients with severe obstructive coronary artery disease.



    5.3 Beta-Blocker Withdrawal



  NORVASC is not a beta-blocker and therefore gives no protection against the dangers of abrupt beta-blocker withdrawal; any such withdrawal should be by gradual reduction of the dose of beta-blocker.



    5.4 Patients with Hepatic Failure



  Because NORVASC is extensively metabolized by the liver and the plasma elimination half-life (t1/2) is 56 hours in patients with impaired hepatic function, titrate slowly when administering NORVASC to patients with severe hepatic impairment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
