<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="novolog1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

      Clinical Trial Experience    



 Clinical trials are conducted under widely varying designs, therefore, the adverse reaction rates reported in one clinical trial may not be easily compared to those rates reported in another clinical trial, and may not reflect the rates actually observed in clinical practice.



 *      Hypoglycemia   
    Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin, including NovoLog Mix 70/30    [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]    . NovoLog Mix 70/30 should not be used during episodes of hypoglycemia    [see Contraindications (4)    and    Warnings and Precautions (5)]    .
 

 *      Insulin initiation and glucose control intensification   
    Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. However, long-term glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.
 

 *      Lipodystrophy   
    Long-term use of insulin, including NovoLog Mix 70/30, can cause lipodystrophy at the site of repeated insulin injections. Lipodystrophy includes lipohypertrophy (thickening of adipose tissue) and lipoatrophy (thinning of adipose tissue), and may affect insulin absorption. Rotate insulin injection sites within the same region to reduce the risk of lipodystrophy.
 

 *      Weight gain   
    Weight gain can occur with some insulin therapies, including NovoLog Mix 70/30, and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin and the decrease in glycosuria.
 

 *      Peripheral Edema   
    Insulin may cause sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy.
 

 *      Frequencies of adverse drug reactions   
    The frequencies of adverse drug reactions during a clinical trial with NovoLog Mix 70/30 in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus are listed in the tables below. The trial was a three-month, open-label trial in patients with type 1 or type 2 diabetes who were treated twice daily (before breakfast and before supper) with NovoLog Mix 70/30.
 

 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events in Patients with Type 1 diabetes mellitus (Adverse events with frequency &gt;= 5% are included.) 
                                        NovoLog Mix 70/30  (N=55)    Novolin 70/30  (N=49)    
  Preferred Term                        N                        %          N                        %          
  Hypoglycemia                          38                       69         37                       76         
  Headache                              19                       35         6                        12         
  Influenza-like symptoms               7                        13         1                        2          
  Dyspepsia                             5                        9          3                        6          
  Back pain                             4                        7          2                        4          
  Diarrhea                              4                        7          3                        6          
  Pharyngitis                           4                        7          1                        2          
  Rhinitis                              3                        5          6                        12         
  Skeletal pain                         3                        5          2                        4          
  Upper respiratory tract infection     3                        5          1                        2          
          Table 2: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events in Patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus (Adverse events with frequency &gt;= 5% are included.) 
                                         NovoLog Mix 70/30  (N=85)    Novolin 70/30  (N=102)    
  Preferred Term                         N                        %         N                        %           
  Hypoglycemia                           40                       47        51                       50          
  Upper respiratory tract infection      10                       12        6                        6           
  Headache                               8                        9         8                        8           
  Diarrhea                               7                        8         2                        2           
  Neuropathy                             7                        8         2                        2           
  Pharyngitis                            5                        6         4                        4           
  Abdominal pain                         4                        5         0                        0           
  Rhinitis                               4                        5         2                        2           
               Postmarketing Data    
 

 Additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of NovoLog Mix 70/30. Because these adverse reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency. They include medication errors in which other insulins have been accidentally substituted for NovoLog Mix 70/30    [see Patient Counseling Information (17)]    .



   EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions observed with insulin therapy include hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, local injection site reactions, lipodystrophy, rash and pruritus  (6)  .



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novo Nordisk Inc. at 1-800-727-6500 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Never share a NovoLog Mix 70/30 FlexPen between patients, even if the needle is changed  (5.1)  . 
 *    NovoLog Mix 70/30 should not be mixed with any other insulin product  (5.2)  . 
 *    Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse effect of insulin therapy. Glucose monitoring is recommended for all patients with diabetes. Any change of insulin dose should be made cautiously and only under medical supervision  (5.2  ,  5.3)  . 
 *    Insulin, particularly when given in settings of poor glycemic control, can cause hypokalemia. Use caution in patients predisposed to hypokalemia  (5.4)  . 
 *    Like all insulins, NovoLog Mix 70/30 requirements may be reduced in patients with renal impairment or hepatic impairment  (5.5  ,  5.6)  . 
 *    Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, may occur with insulin products, including NovoLog Mix 70/30  (5.7)  . 
 *    Fluid retention and heart failure can occur with concomitant use of thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are PPAR-gamma agonists, and insulin, including NovoLog Mix 70/30  (5.9)  . 
    
 

   5.1 Never Share a NovoLog Mix 70/30 FlexPen Between Patients



   NovoLog Mix 70/30 FlexPens must never be shared between patients, even if the needle is changed. Pen-sharing poses a risk for transmission of blood-borne pathogens.  



    5.2 Administration



  The short and long-acting components of insulin mixes, including NovoLog Mix 70/30, cannot be titrated independently. Because NovoLog Mix 70/30 has peak pharmacodynamic activity between 1-4 hours after injection, it should be administered within 15 minutes of meal initiation   [see Clinical Pharmacology (12)]    . The dose of insulin required to provide adequate glycemic control for one of the meals may result in hyper- or hypoglycemia for the other meal. The pharmacodynamic profile may also be inadequate for patients who require more frequent meals.



 NovoLog Mix 70/30 should not be mixed with any other insulin product.



 NovoLog Mix 70/30 should not be used intravenously.



 NovoLog Mix 70/30 should not be used in insulin infusion pumps.



 Glucose monitoring is recommended for all patients with diabetes. Any change of insulin dose should be made cautiously and only under medical supervision. Changing from one insulin product to another or changing the insulin strength may result in the need for a change in dosage. Changes may also be necessary during illness, emotional stress, and other physiologic stress in addition to changes in meals and exercise.



 The pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profiles of all insulins may be altered by the site used for injection and the degree of vascularization of the site. Smoking, temperature, and exercise contribute to variations in blood flow and insulin absorption. These and other factors contribute to inter- and intra-patient variability.



    5.3 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse effect of insulin therapy, including NovoLog Mix 70/30. Severe hypoglycemia may lead to unconsciousness and/or convulsions and may result in temporary or permanent impairment of brain function or even death. Severe hypoglycemia requiring the assistance of another person and/or parenteral glucose infusion or glucagon administration has been observed in clinical trials with insulin, including trials with NovoLog Mix 70/30.



 The timing of hypoglycemia may reflect the time-action profile of the insulin formulation   [see Clinical Pharmacology (12)]    . Other factors, such as changes in dietary intake (e.g., amount of food or timing of meals), injection site, exercise, and concomitant medications may also alter the risk of hypoglycemia   [see Drug Interactions (7)]    . As with all insulins, use caution in patients with hypoglycemia unawareness and in patients who may be predisposed to hypoglycemia (e.g. patients who are fasting or have erratic food intake). The patient's ability to concentrate and react may be impaired as a result of hypoglycemia. This may present a risk in situations where these abilities are especially important, such as driving or operating machinery.



 Rapid changes in serum glucose levels may induce symptoms of hypoglycemia in persons with diabetes, regardless of the glucose value. Early warning symptoms of hypoglycemia may be different or less pronounced under certain conditions, such as long duration of diabetes, diabetic nerve disease, use of medications such as beta-blockers, or intensified diabetes control   [see Drug Interactions (7)]    .



    5.4 Hypokalemia



  All insulin products, including NovoLog Mix 70/30, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia that, if left untreated, may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Use caution in patients who may be at risk for hypokalemia (e.g. patients using potassium-lowering medications or patients taking medications sensitive to potassium concentrations).



    5.5 Renal Impairment



  Clinical or pharmacology studies with NovoLog Mix 70/30 in diabetic patients with various degrees of renal impairment have not been conducted. As with other insulins, the requirements for NovoLog Mix 70/30 may be reduced in patients with renal impairment   [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]    .



    5.6 Hepatic Impairment



  Clinical or pharmacology studies with NovoLog Mix 70/30 in diabetic patients with various degrees of hepatic impairment have not been conducted. As with other insulins, the requirements for NovoLog Mix 70/30 may be reduced in patients with hepatic impairment   [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]    .



    5.7 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions



   Local Reactions-  As with other insulin therapy, patients may experience reactions such as erythema, edema or pruritus at the site of NovoLog Mix 70/30 injection. These reactions usually resolve in a few days to a few weeks, but in some occasions, may require discontinuation of NovoLog Mix 70/30. In some instances, these reactions may be related to the insulin molecule, other components in the insulin preparation including protamine and cresol, components in skin cleansing agents, or injection techniques. Localized reactions and generalized myalgias have been reported with the use of cresol as an injectable excipient.



  Systemic Reactions  - Less common, but potentially more serious, is generalized allergy to insulin, which may cause rash (including pruritus) over the whole body, shortness of breath, wheezing, reduction in blood pressure, rapid pulse, or sweating. Severe cases of generalized allergy, including anaphylactic reaction, may be life threatening.



    5.8 Antibody Production



  Specific anti-insulin antibodies as well as cross-reacting anti-insulin antibodies were monitored in a 3-month, open-label comparator trial as well as in a long-term extension trial. Changes in cross-reactive antibodies were more common after NovoLog Mix 70/30 than with Novolin 70/30 but these changes did not correlate with change in HbA1c or increase in insulin dose. In this study, antibodies did not increase further after long-term exposure (&gt;6 months) to NovoLog Mix 70/30. The presence of such insulin antibodies may necessitate adjustment of the insulin dose in order to correct a tendency towards hyperglycemia or hypoglycemia.



    5.9 Fluid Retention and Heart Failure Can Occur with Concomitant Use of PPAR-gamma Agonists



  Thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists, can cause dose-related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate heart failure. Patients treated with insulin, including NovoLog Mix 70/30, and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of heart failure. If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care, and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
