<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="novolin2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    *      Hypoglycemia   
    Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin, including Novolin R [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ].
 

 *      Insulin initiation and glucose control intensification   
    Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with a transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. Over the long-term, improved glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.
 

 *      Lipodystrophy   
    Long-term use of insulin, including Novolin R, can cause lipodystrophy at the site of repeated insulin injections. Lipodystrophy includes lipohypertrophy (thickening of adipose tissue) and lipoatrophy (thinning of adipose tissue), and may affect insulin absorption. Rotate insulin injection sites within the same region to reduce the risk of lipodystrophy.
 

 *      Weight gain   
    Weight gain can occur with insulin therapies, including Novolin R, and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin and the decrease in glucosuria.
 

 *      Peripheral edema   
    Insulin may cause sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy. These symptoms are usually transitory.
 

 *      Allergic reactions   
    As with other insulins, Novolin R can cause injection site reactions. Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis may occur with any insulin, including Novolin R [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )  ].
 

     Clinical Trial Experience    



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying designs, the adverse reaction rates reported in one clinical trial may not be easily compared to those rates reported in another clinical trial, and may not reflect the rates actually observed in clinical practice.



   Adults with type 1 or type 2 diabetes  



 The incidence of adverse reactions during clinical trials comparing Novolin R and insulin aspart in adults with type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus are listed in the tables below.



   Table 1: Adverse Reactions in a 24-Week Trial Comparing Novolin R and Insulin Aspart in Adults with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Also Treated with NPH Insulin (adverse reactions with an incidence &gt;= 5% in the Novolin R treatment group are listed)  




                                          Novolin R + NPH    N= 286      Insulin aspart + NPH    N=596     
  
                                         %                    %                        
  HypoglycemiaHypoglycemia was defined as an episode of blood glucose concentration &lt;45 mg/dL, with or without symptoms.    72                   75                       
           Table 2: Adverse Reactions in a 24-Week Trial Comparing Novolin R and Insulin Aspart in Adults with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus Also Treated with NPH Insulin (adverse reactions with an incidence &gt;= 5% in the Novolin R treatment group are listed)  
 


                                    Novolin R + NPH    N= 91          Insulin aspart + NPH    N= 91     
                                    (%)                               (%)                      
  
  HypoglycemiaHypoglycemia was defined as an episode of blood glucose concentration &lt;45 mg/dL, with or without symptoms.    36                                27                        
           Children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes  
 

 The incidence of adverse reactions during a 24-week clinical trial comparing Novolin R and insulin aspart in children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus are listed in the table below.



   Table 3: Adverse Reactions in a 24-Week Trial Comparing Novolin R and Insulin Aspart in Children and Adolescents with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Also Treated with NPH Insulin (adverse reactions with an incidence &gt;=5% in the Novolin R treatment group are listed)  




                                    Novolin R + NPH    N= 96          Insulin aspart + NPH    N= 187     
                                    (%)                               (%)                      
  
  HypoglycemiaHypoglycemia was defined as an episode of blood glucose concentration &lt;50 mg/dL, with or without symptoms.    85                                79                        
  Injection site hypertrophy       8                                 8                         
           Severe Hypoglycemia  
 

 Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin, including Novolin R  [See Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )].  Tables 4 and 5 summarize the incidence of severe hypoglycemia in the Novolin R clinical trials. Severe hypoglycemia was defined as hypoglycemia associated with central nervous system symptoms and requiring intervention of another person or hospitalization. The rates of severe hypoglycemia in the Novolin R clinical trials (see Section 14 for a description of the study designs) were comparable for all treatment regimens (see Tables 4 and 5).



   Table 4: Severe Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 1 Diabetes  




                     Type 1 Diabetes  Adults  24 weeks in combination with NPH insulin    Type 1 Diabetes  Children and Adolescents  (age 6-18)  24 weeks in combination with NPH insulin    Type 1 Diabetes  Children  (age 2-6)  24 weeks in combination with NPH insulin    
                     Novolin R     Insulin aspart    Novolin R     Insulin aspart    Novolin R     Insulin aspart    
  Percent of patients (n/total N)    19  (55/286)    18  (105/596)    9  (9/96)     6  (11/187)    12  (3/25)    8  (2/26)    
  Event/patient/  year    1.1           0.9          0.3           0.2          0.5           0.3          
               Table 5: Severe Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes  
 


                      Type 2 Diabetes  Adults  24 weeks in combination with  NPH insulin    
                      Novolin R          Insulin aspart     
  Percent of patients  (n/total N)    5  (5/91)          10  (9/91)         
  Event/patient/  year    0.2                0.3                
           EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions observed with Novolin R include hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, injection site reactions, lipodystrophy, weight gain and edema (  6  )  .  
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novo Nordisk Inc. at 1-800-727-6500 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypoglycemia: Most common adverse reaction of insulin therapy and may be life-threatening. Closely monitor blood glucose. Changes in insulin or dosage should be made cautiously and only under medical supervision (  5.2  ). 
 *    Hypokalemia: Particularly when insulin is given intravenously or in settings of poor glycemic control. Use caution in patients predisposed to hypokalemia (  5.3  ). 
 *    Renal or hepatic impairment: As with other insulins, the dose requirements for Novolin R may be reduced (  5.5  ). 
 *    Allergic reactions: Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, may occur (  5.6  ). 
 *    Mixing: Do not mix Novolin R with any insulin for intravenous use. Do not mix with insulins other than NPH insulin for subcutaneous use (  5.7  ). 
 *    Fluid retention and heart failure can occur with concomitant use of thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are PPAR-gamma agonists, and insulin, including Novolin R (  5.9  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Administration



  Subcutaneous injection of Novolin R should be followed by a meal. Patients should wait approximately 30 minutes after injection before starting the meal [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



 Any change of insulin dose should be made cautiously and only under medical supervision. Changing from one insulin product to another or changing the insulin strength may result in the need for a change in dosage. As with all insulin preparations, the time course of Novolin R action may vary in different individuals or at different times in the same individual and is dependent on many conditions, including dosage, the site of injection, local blood supply, temperature, and physical activity. Patients who change their level of physical activity or meal plan may require adjustment of insulin dosages. Insulin requirements may be altered during illness, emotional disturbances, or other stresses.



    5.2 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction of all insulin therapies, including Novolin R. Severe hypoglycemia may lead to unconsciousness, convulsions, temporary or permanent impairment of brain function or death. Severe hypoglycemia requiring the assistance of another person, parenteral glucose infusion, and glucagon administration has been observed in clinical trials with insulin, including trials with Novolin R.



 The timing of hypoglycemia usually reflects the time-action profile of the administered insulin formulations [ see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  ,  12.3  )  ]. Other factors such as changes in food intake (e.g., amount of food or timing of meals), injection site, exercise, and concomitant medications may also alter the risk of hypoglycemia [ see Drug Interactions (  7  )  ]. As with all insulins, use caution in patients with hypoglycemia unawareness and in patients who may be predisposed to hypoglycemia (e.g., patients who are fasting or have erratic food intake, pediatric patients, and the elderly). The patient's ability to concentrate and react may be impaired as a result of hypoglycemia. This may present a risk in situations where these abilities are especially important, such as driving or operating other machinery.



 Rapid changes in serum glucose concentrations may induce symptoms of hypoglycemia in patients with diabetes, regardless of the glucose value. Early warning symptoms of hypoglycemia may be different or less pronounced under certain conditions, such as longstanding diabetes, diabetic neuropathy, use of medications such as beta-blockers, or intensified glycemic control [ see Drug Interactions (  7  )  ]. These situations may result in severe hypoglycemia (and, possibly, loss of consciousness) prior to the patient's awareness of hypoglycemia. Intravenously administered insulin has a more rapid onset of action than subcutaneously administered insulin, requiring more close monitoring for hypoglycemia.



    5.3 Hypokalemia



  All insulins, including Novolin R, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia that, if left untreated, may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Use caution in patients who may be at risk for hypokalemia (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications and patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations). Monitor glucose and potassium frequently when Novolin R is administered intravenously.



    5.4 Hyperglycemia, Diabetic Ketoacidosis, and Hyperosmolar Hyperglycemic Non-Ketotic Syndrome



  Hyperglycemia, diabetic ketoacidosis, or hyperosmolar hyperglycemic non-ketotic syndrome may develop in patients who take less insulin than needed to control blood glucose. These conditions can be precipitated by illness, infection, dietary indiscretion, or omission or improper administration of the prescribed insulin dose.



    5.5 Renal or Hepatic Impairment



  As with other insulins, the dose requirements for Novolin R may be reduced in patients with renal or hepatic impairment.



    5.6 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions



   Local Reactions  - As with other insulins, patients may experience redness, swelling, or itching at the site of injection of Novolin R. These reactions usually resolve in a few days to a few weeks, but in some occasions, may require discontinuation of Novolin R. In some instances, these reactions may be related to factors other than insulin, such as irritants in a skin cleansing agent or poor injection technique. Localized reactions and generalized myalgias have been reported with the use of meta-cresol, which is an excipient in Novolin R.



  Systemic Reactions  - Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis may occur with any insulin, including Novolin R. Generalized allergy to insulin may manifest as a whole body rash (including pruritus), dyspnea, wheezing, hypotension ,  tachycardia, or diaphoresis.



    5.7 Mixing of Insulins



  If Novolin R is mixed with NPH human insulin, Novolin R should be drawn into the syringe first and the mixture should be injected immediately after mixing. Insulin mixtures should not be administered intravenously.



    5.8 Antibody Production



  Increases in titers of anti-insulin antibodies that react with human insulin have been observed in patients treated with Novolin R. Data from a 12-month controlled trial in patients with type 1 diabetes suggest that the increase in these antibodies is transient. The clinical significance of these antibodies is not known but does not appear to cause deterioration in glycemic control or necessitate increases in insulin dose.



    5.9 Fluid retention and heart failure with concomitant use of PPAR-gamma agonists



  Thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists, can cause dose-related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate heart failure. Patients treated with insulin, including NOVOLIN R, and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of heart failure. If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care, and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
