<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="novolin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE EFFECTS

    What are the possible side effects of Novolin 70/30?  (r)    



 *    Symptoms of hypoglycemia (low blood sugar) may include: Low blood sugar (hypoglycemia).  
  
                                                     sweating                                           
                                                     dizziness or lightheadedness                       
                                                     shakiness                                          
                                                     hunger                                             
                                                     fast heart beat                                    
                                                     tingling of lips and tongue                        
                                                                                                                                                             trouble concentrating or confusion                 
                                                     blurred vision                                     
                                                     slurred speech                                     
                                                     anxiety, irritability or mood changes              
                                                     headache                                           
                                                                                                          
        Severe low blood sugar (hypoglycemia) can cause unconsciousness (passing out), seizures, and death. Know your symptoms of low blood sugar. Follow your healthcare provider's instructions for treating low blood sugar. Talk to your healthcare provider if low blood sugar is a problem for you.
 

 *    a rash over your whole body, have trouble breathing, a fast heartbeat, or sweating. Serious allergic reaction (whole body reaction). Get medical help right away if you develop  
 *    You may get redness, swelling, and itching at the injection site. If you keep having skin reactions, or they are serious, talk to your healthcare provider. You may need to stop using Novolin 70/30 and use a different insulin. Do not inject insulin into skin that is red, swollen, or itchy. Reactions at the injection site (local allergic reaction).   (r)   
 *    Change (rotate) where you inject your insulin to help prevent these skin changes from happening. Do not inject insulin into this type of skin. Skin thickens or pits at the injection site (lipodystrophy).  
 *     Swelling of your hands and feet  
 *    *  ?  shortness of breath 
 *  ?  swelling of your ankles or feet 
 *  ?  sudden weight gain 
   Taking certain diabetes pills called thiazolidinediones or "TZDs" with Novolin 70/30 may cause heart failure in some people. This can happen even if you have never had heart failure or heart problems before. If you already have heart failure it may get worse while you take TZDs with Novolin 70/30. Your healthcare provider should monitor you closely while you are taking TZDs with Novolin 70/30. Tell your healthcare provider if you have any new or worse symptoms of heart failure including: Heart Failure.   (r)    (r)    (r)   
    Treatment with TZDs and Novolin 70/30 may need to be adjusted or stopped by your healthcare provider if you have new or worse heart failure.  (r)      
 

 *     Vision changes  
 *     Low potassium in your blood (hypokalemia)  
    These are not all of the possible side effects from Novolin 70/30. Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for more information.  (r)  
 

  Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
