<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="noxafil" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Common treatment-emergent adverse reactions in studies with posaconazole are diarrhea, nausea, fever, vomiting, headache, coughing, and hypokalemia. (  6.2  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    
 

 

  6.1 Serious and Otherwise Important Adverse Reactions

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse reactions are discussed in detail in another section of the labeling:



 *  Hypersensitivity [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  
 *  Arrhythmias and QT Prolongation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Hepatic Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
      6.2 Clinical Trials Experience
   Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of Noxafil cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. In clinical trials, the type of adverse reactions reported for posaconazole injection and posaconazole delayed-release tablets were generally similar to that reported in trials of posaconazole oral suspension.



     Clinical Trial Experience with Posaconazole Injection  



 Multiple doses of posaconazole injection administered via a peripheral venous catheter were associated with thrombophlebitis (60% incidence). Therefore, in subsequent studies, posaconazole injection was administered via central venous catheter.



 The safety of posaconazole injection has been assessed in 268 patients in a clinical trial. Patients were enrolled in a non-comparative pharmacokinetic and safety trial of posaconazole injection when given as antifungal prophylaxis (Posaconazole Injection Study 1). Patients were immunocompromised with underlying conditions including hematological malignancy, neutropenia post-chemotherapy, GVHD, and post HSCT. This patient population was 55% male, had a mean age of 51 years (range 18-82 years, 19% of patients were &gt;=65 years of age), and were 95% white and 8% Hispanic. Ten patients received a single dose of 200 mg posaconazole injection, 21 patients received 200 mg daily dose for a median of 14 days, and 237 patients received 300 mg daily dose for a median of 9 days.



   Table 4  presents treatment-emergent adverse reactions observed in patients treated with posaconazole injection 300 mg daily dose in the posaconazole injection study. Each patient received a loading dose, 300 mg twice on Day 1. Following posaconazole intravenous therapy, patients received posaconazole oral suspension to complete 28 days of total posaconazole therapy.



 Table 4: Posaconazole Injection Study 1: Number (%) of Subjects Treated with Posaconazole Injection 300 mg Daily Dose Reporting Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Frequency of at Least 10% 
   Body System  Preferred Term                             Posaconazole Injection Treatment Phasen=237 (%)  Posaconazole Injection Treatment Phase or Subsequent Oral Suspension Treatment Phasen=237(%)   
  
 Subjects Reporting any Adverse Reaction                       220         (93)          235         (99)       
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorder                      
 Anemia                                                        16           (7)          23          (10)       
 Thrombocytopenia                                              17           (7)          25          (11)       
 Gastrointestinal Disorders                                 
 Abdominal Pain Upper                                          15           (6)          25          (11)       
 Abdominal Pain                                                30          (13)          41          (17)       
 Constipation                                                  18           (8)          31          (13)       
 Diarrhea                                                      75          (32)          93          (39)       
 Nausea                                                        46          (19)          70          (30)       
 Vomiting                                                      29          (12)          45          (19)       
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                               
 Fatigue                                                       19           (8)          24          (10)       
 Chills                                                        28          (12)          38          (16)       
 Edema Peripheral                                              28          (12)          35          (15)       
 Pyrexia                                                       49          (21)          73          (31)       
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                 
 Decreased appetite                                            23          (10)          29          (12)       
 Hypokalemia                                                   51          (22)          67          (28)       
 Hypomagnesemia                                                25          (11)          30          (13)       
   Nervous System Disorders                                                           
 Headache                                                      33          (14)          49          (21)       
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                    
 Cough                                                         21           (9)          31          (13)       
 Dyspnea                                                       16           (7)          24          (10)       
 Epistaxis                                                     34          (14)          40          (17)       
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                             
 Petechiae                                                     20           (8)          24          (10)       
 Rash                                                          35          (15)          56          (24)       
 Vascular Disorders                                                                   
 Hypertension                                                  20           (8)          26          (11)       
           The most frequently reported adverse reactions with an onset during the posaconazole intravenous phase of dosing with 300 mg once daily were diarrhea (32%), hypokalemia (22%), pyrexia (21%), and nausea (19%). These adverse reactions were consistent with those seen in studies with Noxafil oral suspension.
 

     Clinical Trial Experience with Posaconazole Delayed-Release Tablets  



 The safety of posaconazole delayed-release tablets has been assessed in 230 patients in clinical trials. Patients were enrolled in a non-comparative pharmacokinetic and safety trial of posaconazole delayed-release tablets when given as antifungal prophylaxis (Delayed-Release Tablet Study 1). Patients were immunocompromised with underlying conditions including hematological malignancy, neutropenia post-chemotherapy, GVHD, and post HSCT. This patient population was 62% male, had a mean age of 51 years (range 19-78 years, 17% of patients were &gt;=65 years of age), and were 93% white and 16% Hispanic. Posaconazole therapy was given for a median duration of 28 days  .  Twenty patients received 200 mg daily dose and 210 patients received 300 mg daily dose (following twice daily dosing on Day 1 in each cohort).  Table 5  presents treatment-emergent adverse reactions observed in patients treated with 300 mg daily dose at an incidence of &gt;=10% in posaconazole delayed-release tablet study.



 Table 5: Posaconazole Delayed-Release Tablet Study 1: Number (%) of Subjects Treated with 300 mg Daily Dose Reporting Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Frequency of at Least 10% 
   Body System  Preferred Term                                                 Posaconazole delayed-release tablet (300 mg)(n=210)   
  
 Subjects Reporting any Adverse Reaction                                           201           (99)       
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorder                                          
 Anemia                                                                             22           (10)       
 Thrombocytopenia                                                                   29           (14)       
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                   
 Abdominal Pain                                                                     23           (11)       
 Constipation                                                                       20           (10)       
 Diarrhea                                                                           61           (29)       
 Nausea                                                                             56           (27)       
 Vomiting                                                                           28           (13)       
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                         
 Asthenia                                                                           20           (10)       
 Chills                                                                             22           (10)       
 Mucosal Inflammation                                                               29           (14)       
 Edema Peripheral                                                                   33           (16)       
 Pyrexia                                                                            59           (28)       
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                           
 Hypokalemia                                                                        46           (22)       
 Hypomagnesemia                                                                     20           (10)       
   Nervous System Disorders                                                     
 Headache                                                                           30           (14)       
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                              
 Cough                                                                              35           (17)       
 Epistaxis                                                                          30           (14)       
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                       
 Rash                                                                               34           (16)       
   Vascular Disorders                                                           
 Hypertension                                                                       23           (11)       
         The most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;25%) with posaconazole delayed-release tablets 300 mg once daily were diarrhea, pyrexia, and nausea.
 

 The most common adverse reaction leading to discontinuation of posaconazole delayed-release tablets 300 mg once daily was nausea (2%).



     Clinical Trial Safety Experience with Posaconazole Oral Suspension  



 The safety of posaconazole oral suspension has been assessed in 1844 patients. This includes 605 patients in the active-controlled prophylaxis studies, 557 patients in the active-controlled OPC studies, 239 patients in refractory OPC studies, and 443 patients from other indications. This represents a heterogeneous population, including immunocompromised patients, e.g., patients with hematological malignancy, neutropenia post-chemotherapy, GVHD post HSCT, and HIV infection, as well as non-neutropenic patients. This patient population was 71% male, had a mean age of 42 years (range 8-84 years, 6% of patients were &gt;=65 years of age and 1% was &lt;18 years of age), and were 64% white, 16% Hispanic, and 36% non-white (including 14% black). Posaconazole therapy was given to 171 patients for &gt;=6 months, with 58 patients receiving posaconazole therapy for &gt;=12 months.  Table 6  presents treatment-emergent adverse reactions observed at an incidence of &gt;10% in posaconazole prophylaxis studies.  Table 7  presents treatment-emergent adverse reactions observed at an incidence of at least 10% in the OPC/rOPC studies.



     Prophylaxis of Aspergillus and Candida:  In the 2 randomized, comparative prophylaxis studies (Oral Suspension Studies 1 and 2), the safety of posaconazole oral suspension 200 mg three times a day was compared to fluconazole 400 mg once daily or itraconazole 200 mg twice a day in severely immunocompromised patients.



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;30%) in the prophylaxis clinical trials were fever, diarrhea, and nausea.



 The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of posaconazole in the prophylaxis studies were associated with GI disorders, specifically, nausea (2%), vomiting (2%), and hepatic enzymes increased (2%).



 Table 6: Posaconazole Oral Suspension Study 1 and Study 2. Number (%) of Randomized Subjects Reporting Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Frequency of at Least 10% in the Posaconazole Oral Suspension or Fluconazole Treatment Groups (Pooled Prophylaxis Safety Analysis) 
   Body System  Preferred Term                   Posaconazole(n=605)  Fluconazole(n=539)  Itraconazole(n=58)   
  
 Subjects Reporting any Adverse Reaction            595       (98)        531       (99)        58        (100)     
   Body as a Whole - General Disorders            
 Fever                                              274       (45)        254       (47)        32        (55)      
 Headache                                           171       (28)        141       (26)        23        (40)      
 Rigors                                             122       (20)        87        (16)        17        (29)      
 Fatigue                                            101       (17)        98        (18)         5         (9)      
 Edema Legs                                         93        (15)        67        (12)        11        (19)      
 Anorexia                                           92        (15)        94        (17)        16        (28)      
 Dizziness                                          64        (11)        56        (10)         5         (9)      
 Edema                                              54         (9)        68        (13)         8        (14)      
 Weakness                                           51         (8)        52        (10)         2         (3)      
   Cardiovascular Disorders, General              
 Hypertension                                       106       (18)        88        (16)         3         (5)      
 Hypotension                                        83        (14)        79        (15)        10        (17)      
   Disorders of Blood and Lymphatic System        
 Anemia                                             149       (25)        124       (23)        16        (28)      
 Neutropenia                                        141       (23)        122       (23)        23        (40)      
   Disorders of the Reproductive System and Breast     
 Vaginal Hemorrhage                                 24        (10)        20         (9)         3        (12)      
   Gastrointestinal System Disorders              
 Diarrhea                                           256       (42)        212       (39)        35        (60)      
 Nausea                                             232       (38)        198       (37)        30        (52)      
 Vomiting                                           174       (29)        173       (32)        24        (41)      
 Abdominal Pain                                     161       (27)        147       (27)        21        (36)      
 Constipation                                       126       (21)        94        (17)        10        (17)      
 Dyspepsia                                          61        (10)        50         (9)         6        (10)      
   Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders                
 Tachycardia                                        72        (12)        75        (14)         3         (5)      
   Infection and Infestations                     
 Pharyngitis                                        71        (12)        60        (11)        12        (21)      
   Liver and Biliary System Disorders             
 Bilirubinemia                                      59        (10)        51         (9)        11        (19)      
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders            
 Hypokalemia                                        181       (30)        142       (26)        30        (52)      
 Hypomagnesemia                                     110       (18)        84        (16)        11        (19)      
 Hyperglycemia                                      68        (11)        76        (14)         2         (3)      
 Hypocalcemia                                       56         (9)        55        (10)         5         (9)      
   Musculoskeletal System Disorders               
 Musculoskeletal Pain                               95        (16)        82        (15)         9        (16)      
 Arthralgia                                         69        (11)        67        (12)         5         (9)      
 Back Pain                                          63        (10)        66        (12)         4         (7)      
   Platelet, Bleeding and Clotting Disorders      
 Thrombocytopenia                                   175       (29)        146       (27)        20        (34)      
 Petechiae                                          64        (11)        54        (10)         9        (16)      
   Psychiatric Disorders                          
 Insomnia                                           103       (17)        92        (17)        11        (19)      
   Respiratory System Disorders                   
 Coughing                                           146       (24)        130       (24)        14        (24)      
 Dyspnea                                            121       (20)        116       (22)        15        (26)      
 Epistaxis                                          82        (14)        73        (14)        12        (21)      
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders         
 Rash                                               113       (19)        96        (18)        25        (43)      
 Pruritus                                           69        (11)        62        (12)        11        (19)      
                 HIV Infected Subjects with OPC    :  In 2 randomized comparative studies in OPC, the safety of posaconazole oral suspension at a dose of less than or equal to 400 mg QD in 557 HIV-infected patients was compared to the safety of fluconazole in 262 HIV-infected patients at a dose of 100 mg QD.
 

 An additional 239 HIV-infected patients with refractory OPC received posaconazole oral suspension in 2 non-comparative trials for refractory OPC (rOPC). Of these subjects, 149 received the 800-mg/day dose and the remainder received the less than or equal to 400-mg QD dose.



 In the OPC/rOPC studies, the most common adverse reactions were fever, diarrhea, nausea, headache, vomiting, and coughing.



 The most common adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation of posaconazole in the Controlled OPC Pool included respiratory impairment (1%) and pneumonia (1%). In the refractory OPC pool, the most common adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation of posaconazole were AIDS (7%) and respiratory impairment (3%).



 Table 7: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions with Frequency of at Least 10% in OPC Studies with Posaconazole Oral Suspension (Treated Population) 
 Body System  Preferred Term               Number (%) of Subjects   
 Controlled OPC Pool                       Refractory OPC Pool   
 Posaconazole                                 Fluconazole         Posaconazole      
 n=557                                           n=262               n=239          
  
 OPC=oropharyngeal candidiasis              
  
 Subjects Reporting any Adverse Reaction        356 (64)            175 (67)               221 (92)           
 Body as a Whole - General Disorders        
   Fever                                         34 (6)              22 (8)                82 (34)            
   Headache                                      44 (8)              23 (9)                47 (20)            
   Anorexia                                      10 (2)              4 (2)                 46 (19)            
   Fatigue                                       18 (3)              12 (5)                31 (13)            
   Asthenia                                      9 (2)               5 (2)                 31 (13)            
   Rigors                                        2 (&lt;1)              4 (2)                 29 (12)            
   Pain                                          4 (1)               2 (1)                 27 (11)            
 Disorders of Blood and Lymphatic System    
   Neutropenia                                   21 (4)              8 (3)                 39 (16)            
   Anemia                                        11 (2)              5 (2)                 34 (14)            
 Gastrointestinal System Disorders          
   Diarrhea                                     58 (10)             34 (13)                70 (29)            
   Nausea                                        48 (9)             30 (11)                70 (29)            
   Vomiting                                      37 (7)              18 (7)                67 (28)            
   Abdominal Pain                                27 (5)              17 (6)                43 (18)            
 Infection and Infestations                 
   Candidiasis, Oral                             3 (1)               1 (&lt;1)                28 (12)            
   Herpes Simplex                                16 (3)              8 (3)                 26 (11)            
   Pneumonia                                     17 (3)              6 (2)                 25 (10)            
 Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders        
   Weight Decrease                               4 (1)               2 (1)                 33 (14)            
   Dehydration                                   4 (1)               7 (3)                 27 (11)            
 Psychiatric Disorders                      
   Insomnia                                      8 (1)               3 (1)                 39 (16)            
 Respiratory System Disorders               
   Coughing                                      18 (3)              11 (4)                60 (25)            
   Dyspnea                                       8 (1)               8 (3)                 28 (12)            
 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders     
   Rash                                          15 (3)              10 (4)                36 (15)            
   Sweating Increased                            13 (2)              5 (2)                 23 (10)            
          Adverse reactions were reported more frequently in the pool of patients with refractory OPC. Among these highly immunocompromised patients with advanced HIV disease, serious adverse reactions (SARs) were reported in 55% (132/239). The most commonly reported SARs were fever (13%) and neutropenia (10%).
 

     Less Common Adverse Reactions:  Clinically significant adverse reactions reported during clinical trials in prophylaxis, OPC/rOPC or other trials with posaconazole which occurred in less than 5% of patients are listed below:



 *   Blood and lymphatic system disorders: hemolytic uremic syndrome, thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura, neutropenia aggravated 
 *   Endocrine disorders: adrenal insufficiency 
 *   Nervous system disorders: paresthesia 
 *   Immune system disorders: allergic reaction [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  
 *   Cardiac disorders: Torsades de pointes [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *   Vascular disorders: pulmonary embolism 
 *   Liver and Biliary System Disorders: bilirubinemia, hepatic enzymes increased, hepatic function abnormal, hepatitis, hepatomegaly, jaundice, AST Increased, ALT Increased 
 *   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders: hypokalemia 
 *   Platelet, Bleeding, and Clotting Disorders: thrombocytopenia 
 *   Renal &amp; Urinary System Disorders: renal failure acute 
        Clinical Laboratory Values:  In healthy volunteers and patients, elevation of liver function test values did not appear to be associated with higher plasma concentrations of posaconazole.
 

 For the prophylaxis studies, the number of patients with changes in liver function tests from Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) Grade 0, 1, or 2 at baseline to Grade 3 or 4 during the study is presented in  Table 8.  



 Table 8: Posaconazole Oral Suspension Study 1 and Study 2. Changes in Liver Function Test Results from CTC Grade 0, 1, or 2 at Baseline to Grade 3 or 4 
 Number (%) of Patients With Change   
  
 CTC = Common Toxicity Criteria; AST= Aspartate Aminotransferase;   
 ALT= Alanine Aminotransferase.       
  
 Oral Suspension Study 1              
 Laboratory Parameter                       Posaconazolen=301                   Fluconazolen=299            
   AST                                          11/266 (4)                         13/266 (5)               
   ALT                                         47/271 (17)                        39/272 (14)               
   Bilirubin                                    24/271 (9)                         20/275 (7)               
   Alkaline Phosphatase                         9/271 (3)                          8/271 (3)                
 Oral Suspension Study 2              
 Laboratory Parameter                      Posaconazole(n=304)          Fluconazole/Itraconazole(n=298)     
   AST                                          9/286 (3)                          5/280 (2)                
   ALT                                          18/289 (6)                         13/284 (5)               
   Bilirubin                                    20/290 (7)                         25/285 (9)               
   Alkaline Phosphatase                         4/281 (1)                          1/276 (&lt;1)               
         The number of patients treated for OPC with clinically significant liver function test (LFT) abnormalities at any time during the studies is provided in  Table 9  (LFT abnormalities were present in some of these patients prior to initiation of the study drug).
 

 Table 9: Posaconazole Oral Suspension Studies: Clinically Significant Laboratory Test Abnormalities without Regard to Baseline Value 
 Laboratory Test                                Controlled            Refractory        
 Posaconazole                                  Fluconazole           Posaconazole       
 n=557(%)                                        n=262(%)              n=239(%)         
  
 ALT= Alanine Aminotransferase; AST= Aspartate Aminotransferase.   
  
 ALT &gt; 3.0 * ULN                                16/537 (3)           13/254 (5)            25/226 (11)        
 AST &gt; 3.0 * ULN                                33/537 (6)           26/254 (10)           39/223 (17)        
 Total Bilirubin &gt; 1.5 * ULN                    15/536 (3)            5/254 (2)             9/197 (5)         
 Alkaline Phosphatase &gt; 3.0 * ULN               17/535 (3)           15/253 (6)            24/190 (13)        
            6.3 Postmarketing Experience
   No clinically significant postmarketing adverse reactions were identified that have not previously been reported during clinical trials experience.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Calcineurin Inhibitor Toxicity: Noxafil increases concentrations of cyclosporine or tacrolimus; reduce dose of cyclosporine and tacrolimus and monitor concentrations frequently. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Arrhythmias and QTc Prolongation: Noxafil has been shown to prolong the QTc interval and cause cases of TdP. Administer with caution to patients with potentially proarrhythmic conditions. Do not administer with drugs known to prolong QTc interval and metabolized through CYP3A4. Correct K  +  , Mg  ++  , and Ca  ++  before starting Noxafil. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hepatic Toxicity: Elevations in LFTs may occur. Discontinuation should be considered in patients who develop abnormal LFTs or monitor LFTs during treatment. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Noxafil injection should be avoided in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;50 mL/min), unless an assessment of the benefit/risk to the patient justifies the use of Noxafil injection. (  5.4  ,  8.6  ) 
 *  Midazolam: Noxafil can prolong hypnotic/sedative effects. Monitor patients and benzodiazepine receptor antagonists should be available. (  5.5  ,  7.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Calcineurin-Inhibitor Drug Interactions



  Concomitant administration of Noxafil with cyclosporine or tacrolimus increases the whole blood trough concentrations of these calcineurin-inhibitors [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . Nephrotoxicity and leukoencephalopathy (including deaths) have been reported in clinical efficacy studies in patients with elevated cyclosporine or tacrolimus concentrations. Frequent monitoring of tacrolimus or cyclosporine whole blood trough concentrations should be performed during and at discontinuation of posaconazole treatment and the tacrolimus or cyclosporine dose adjusted accordingly.



    5.2 Arrhythmias and QT Prolongation



  Some azoles, including posaconazole, have been associated with prolongation of the QT interval on the electrocardiogram. In addition, cases of torsades de pointes have been reported in patients taking posaconazole.



 Results from a multiple time-matched ECG analysis in healthy volunteers did not show any increase in the mean of the QTc interval. Multiple, time-matched ECGs collected over a 12-hour period were recorded at baseline and steady-state from 173 healthy male and female volunteers (18-85 years of age) administered posaconazole oral suspension 400 mg BID with a high-fat meal. In this pooled analysis, the mean QTc (Fridericia) interval change from baseline was -5 msec following administration of the recommended clinical dose. A decrease in the QTc(F) interval (-3 msec) was also observed in a small number of subjects (n=16) administered placebo. The placebo-adjusted mean maximum QTc(F) interval change from baseline was &lt;0 msec (-8 msec). No healthy subject administered posaconazole had a QTc(F) interval &gt;=500 msec or an increase &gt;=60 msec in their QTc(F) interval from baseline.



 Posaconazole should be administered with caution to patients with potentially proarrhythmic conditions. Do not administer with drugs that are known to prolong the QTc interval and are metabolized through CYP3A4 [see  Contraindications (4.3)  and  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  . Rigorous attempts to correct potassium, magnesium, and calcium should be made before starting posaconazole.



    5.3 Hepatic Toxicity



  Hepatic reactions (e.g., mild to moderate elevations in alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase, total bilirubin, and/or clinical hepatitis) have been reported in clinical trials. The elevations in liver function tests were generally reversible on discontinuation of therapy, and in some instances these tests normalized without drug interruption. Cases of more severe hepatic reactions including cholestasis or hepatic failure including deaths have been reported in patients with serious underlying medical conditions (e.g., hematologic malignancy) during treatment with posaconazole. These severe hepatic reactions were seen primarily in subjects receiving the posaconazole oral suspension 800 mg daily (400 mg BID or 200 mg QID) in clinical trials.



 Liver function tests should be evaluated at the start of and during the course of posaconazole therapy. Patients who develop abnormal liver function tests during posaconazole therapy should be monitored for the development of more severe hepatic injury. Patient management should include laboratory evaluation of hepatic function (particularly liver function tests and bilirubin). Discontinuation of posaconazole must be considered if clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop that may be attributable to posaconazole.



    5.4 Renal Impairment



  Due to the variability in exposure with Noxafil delayed-release tablets and oral suspension, patients with severe renal impairment should be monitored closely for breakthrough fungal infections [see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ].  



 Noxafil injection should be avoided in patients with moderate or severe renal impairment (eGFR &lt;50 mL/min), unless an assessment of the benefit/risk to the patient justifies the use of Noxafil injection. In patients with moderate or severe renal impairment (eGFR &lt;50 mL/min), receiving the Noxafil injection, accumulation of the intravenous vehicle, SBECD, is expected to occur. Serum creatinine levels should be closely monitored in these patients, and, if increases occur, consideration should be given to changing to oral Noxafil therapy [see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ]  .



    5.5 Use with Midazolam



  Concomitant administration of Noxafil with midazolam increases the midazolam plasma concentrations by approximately 5-fold. Increased plasma midazolam concentrations could potentiate and prolong hypnotic and sedative effects. Patients must be monitored closely for adverse effects associated with high plasma concentrations of midazolam and benzodiazepine receptor antagonists must be available to reverse these effects [see  Drug Interactions (7.5)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
