<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nuedexta" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6    ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  A total of 946 patients participated in four Phase 3 controlled and uncontrolled PBA studies and received at least one dose of the combination product of dextromethorphan hydrobromide/quinidine sulfate in various strengths at the recommended or higher than the recommended dose. Of those patients, 393 patients were exposed for at least 180 days and 294 patients were exposed for at least one year. Median exposure was 168 days.



 Controlled trials enrolled only patients with either ALS or MS. Uncontrolled studies enrolled 136 patients with PBA secondary to a wide variety of underlying neurological conditions including stroke (45 patients) and traumatic brain injury (23 patients). Consequently, patients with other underlying neurologic diseases may experience other adverse reactions not described below.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence of &gt;= 3% and two-fold greater than placebo) in patients taking NUEDEXTA are diarrhea, dizziness, cough, vomiting, asthenia, peripheral edema, urinary tract infection, influenza, increased gamma-glutamyltransferase, and flatulence. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Avanir Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-855-4NUEDEX (468-3339) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

    6.1    Clinical Trial    s    Experience  

  A 12-week, placebo-controlled study evaluated NUEDEXTA (dextromethorphan hydrobromide 20 mg/quinidine sulfate 10 mg) (N=107) and a dextromethorphan hydrobromide 30 mg/ quinidine sulfate 10 mg combination (N=110) compared to placebo (N=109). Approximately 60% of patients had ALS and 40% had MS.  Patients were 25 to 80 years of age, with a mean age of approximately 51 years. Three (3) ALS patients in each drug treatment arm and 1 ALS patient in the placebo arm died during the 12-week placebo-control period. All deaths were consistent with the natural progression of ALS.  



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  The most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 2%  and greater than placebo) that led to discontinuation with the dextromethorphan hydrobromide 20 mg/ quinidine sulfate 10 mg twice daily dose were muscle spasticity (3%), respiratory failure (1%), abdominal pain (2%), asthenia (2%), dizziness (2%), fall (1%), and muscle spasms (2%).



   Most Common Adverse Reactions  Adverse drug reactions that occurred in &gt;= 3%  of patients receiving the dextromethorphan hydrobromide 20 mg/ quinidine sulfate 10 mg twice daily dose, and at an incidence of &gt;= 2 times placebo in short-term clinical trials in ALS and MS are provided in Table 1. Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Table 1: Adverse Drug Reactions with an Incidence of &gt;= 3% of Patients and &gt;= 2x Placebo in NUEDEXTA-treated Patients by System-Organ Class and Preferred Term 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                NUEDEXTA N=107 %                                                                                                                                                                                          PlaceboN=109 %                                                                                                                                                                                            
 Diarrhea                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      13                                                                                                                                                                                                        6                                                                                                                                                                                                          
 Dizziness                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      10                                                                                                                                                                                                        5                                                                                                                                                                                                         
 Cough                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          5                                                                                                                                                                                                         2                                                                                                                                                                                                         
 Vomiting                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       5                                                                                                                                                                                                         1                                                                                                                                                                                                         
 Asthenia                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       5                                                                                                                                                                                                         2                                                                                                                                                                                                         
 Peripheral edema                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               5                                                                                                                                                                                                         1                                                                                                                                                                                                         
 Urinary tract infection                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        4                                                                                                                                                                                                         1                                                                                                                                                                                                         
 Influenza                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      4                                                                                                                                                                                                         1                                                                                                                                                                                                         
 Increased gamma-glutamyltransferase                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               3                                                                                                                                                                                                         0                                                                                                                                                                                                      
 Flatulence                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    3                                                                                                                                                                                                          1                                                                                                                                                                                                         
             6.2    Long-Term Exposure with    NUEDEXTA  
   The experience in open-label clinical trials is consistent with the safety profile observed in the placebo-controlled clinical trials.



     6.3    Safety    Experience    of Individual Components       

  The following adverse reactions have been reported with the use of the individual components of NUEDEXTA, dextromethorphan and quinidine, from post-marketing experience. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Dextromethorphan  



 Drowsiness, dizziness, nervousness or restlessness, nausea, vomiting, and stomach pain. 



   Quinidine  



 Cinchonism is most often a sign of chronic quinidine toxicity, but it may appear in sensitive patients after a single moderate dose of several hundred milligrams. Cinchonism is characterized by nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, headache, tinnitus, hearing loss, vertigo, blurred vision, diplopia, photophobia, confusion, and delirium.



 Convulsions, apprehension, and ataxia have been reported with quinidine therapy, but it is not clear that these were not simply the results of hypotension and consequent cerebral hypoperfusion in patients being treated for cardiovascular indications. Acute psychotic reactions have been reported to follow the first dose of quinidine, but these reactions appear to be extremely rare. Other adverse reactions occasionally reported with quinidine therapy include depression, mydriasis, disturbed color perception, night blindness, scotomata, optic neuritis, visual field loss, photosensitivity, keratopathy, and abnormalities of skin pigmentation. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *   Thrombocytopenia or other hypersensitivity reactions: Discontinue if occurs. (  5.1  )



 
 *   Hepatitis: Discontinue if occurs. (  5.2  )



 
 *   QT Prolongation: Monitor ECG if concomitant use of drugs that prolong QT interval cannot be avoided or if concomitant CYP3A4 inhibitors used. (  5.3  ).



 
 *   Left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH) or left ventricular dysfunction (LVD): Monitor ECG in patients with LVH or LVD. (  5.3  )



 
   *   CYP2D6 substrate: NUEDEXTA inhibits CYP2D6. Accumulation of parent drug and/or failure of metabolite formation may decrease safety and/or efficacy of concomitant CYP2D6 metabolized drugs. Adjust dose of CYP2D6 substrate or use alternative treatment when clinically indicated. (  5.4  ,  12.4  )



 
 *   Dizziness: Take precautions to reduce falls. (  5.5  )



 
 *   Serotonin syndrome: Use of NUEDEXTA with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRIs) or tricyclic antidepressants increases the risk. Discontinue if occurs. (  5.6  ,  7.4  )



 
 *   Anticholinergic effects of quinidine: Monitor for worsening in myasthenia gravis and other sensitive conditions. (  5.7  )



 
    



    5.1   Thrombocytopenia and   Other   Hypersensitivity   Reactions  



  Quinidine can cause immune-mediated thrombocytopenia that can be severe or fatal. Non-specific symptoms, such as lightheadedness, chills, fever, nausea, and vomiting, can precede or occur with thrombocytopenia. NUEDEXTA should be discontinued immediately if thrombocytopenia occurs, unless the thrombocytopenia is clearly not drug-related, as continued use increases the risk for fatal hemorrhage. Likewise, NUEDEXTA should not be restarted in sensitized patients, because more rapid and more severe thrombocytopenia than the original episode can occur. NUEDEXTA should not be used if immune-mediated thrombocytopenia from structurally related drugs including quinine and mefloquine is suspected, as cross-sensitivity can occur. Quinidine-associated thrombocytopenia usually, but not always, resolves within a few days of discontinuation of the sensitizing drug.



 Quinidine has also been associated with a lupus-like syndrome involving polyarthritis, sometimes with a positive antinuclear antibody test. Other associations include rash, bronchospasm, lymphadenopathy, hemolytic anemia, vasculitis, uveitis, angioedema, agranulocytosis, the sicca syndrome, myalgia, elevation in serum levels of skeletal-muscle enzymes, and pneumonitis.



     5.2   Hepatotoxicity  



  Hepatitis, including granulomatous hepatitis, has been reported in patients receiving quinidine, generally during the first few weeks of therapy. Fever may be a presenting symptom, and thrombocytopenia or other signs of hypersensitivity may also occur. Most cases remit when quinidine is withdrawn.



     5.3   Cardiac Effects  



  NUEDEXTA causes dose-dependent QTc prolongation [ see    Clinical Pharmacology  (   12.2     )  ]. QT prolongation can cause torsades de pointes-type ventricular tachycardia, with the risk increasing as the degree of prolongation increases. When initiating NUEDEXTA in patients at risk of QT prolongation and torsades de pointes, electrocardiographic (ECG) evaluation of QT interval should be conducted at baseline and 3-4 hours after the first dose. This includes patients concomitantly taking/initiating drugs that prolong the QT interval or that are strong or moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors, and patients with left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH) or left ventricular dysfunction (LVD). LVH and LVD are more likely to be present in patients with chronic hypertension, known coronary artery disease, or history of stroke. LVH and LVD can be diagnosed utilizing echocardiography or another suitable cardiac imaging modality. 



 Strong and moderate CYP3A inhibitors include, but are not limited to, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, ketoconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, ritonavir, saquinavir, telithromycin, amprenavir, aprepitant, diltiazem, erythromycin, fluconazole, fosamprenavir, grapefruit juice, and verapamil.



 Reevaluate ECG if risk factors for arrhythmia change during the course of treatment with NUEDEXTA. Risk factors include concomitant use of drugs associated with QT prolongation, electrolyte abnormality (hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia), bradycardia, and family history of QT abnormality. Hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia should be corrected prior to initiation of therapy with NUEDEXTA, and should be monitored during treatment.



 If patients taking NUEDEXTA experience symptoms that could indicate the occurrence of cardiac arrhythmias, e.g., syncope or palpitations, NUEDEXTA should be discontinued and the patient further evaluated.



     5.4   Concomitant u   se of   CYP2D6 S   ubstrate   s  



  The quinidine in NUEDEXTA inhibits CYP2D6 in patients in whom CYP2D6 is not otherwise genetically absent or its activity otherwise pharmacologically inhibited [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  ), (  12.5  )]  . Because of this effect on CYP2D6, accumulation of parent drug and/or failure of active metabolite formation may decrease the safety and/or the efficacy of drugs used concomitantly with NUEDEXTA that are metabolized by CYP2D6 [see Drug Interactions (   7.5       )]  .



     5.5       Dizziness  



  NUEDEXTA may cause dizziness  [see    Adverse Reactions   (     6.1     )]  . Precautions to reduce the risk of falls should be taken, particularly for patients with motor impairment affecting gait or a history of falls. In a controlled trial of NUEDEXTA, 10% of patients on NUEDEXTA and 5% on placebo experienced dizziness.



     5.6   Serotonin Syndrome  



  When used with SSRIs (such as fluoxetine) or tricyclic antidepressants (such as clomipramine and imipramine), NUEDEXTA may cause "serotonin syndrome", with changes including altered mental status, hypertension, restlessness, myoclonus, hyperthermia, hyperreflexia, diaphoresis, shivering, and tremor  [see Drug Interactions (     7.4     ), Overdosage (     10     )].  



     5.7   Anticholinergic E   ffects   of Q   uinidine  



  Monitor for worsening clinical condition in myasthenia gravis and other conditions that may be adversely affected by anticholinergic effects.



     5.8   CYP2D6 Poor Metabolizers  



  The quinidine component of NUEDEXTA is intended to inhibit CYP2D6 so that higher exposure to dextromethorphan can be achieved compared to when dextromethorphan is given alone [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  ), (  12.5  )]  . Approximately 7-10% of Caucasians and 3-8% of African Americans lack the capacity to metabolize CYP2D6 substrates and are classified as poor metabolizers (PMs). The quinidine component of NUEDEXTA is not expected to contribute to the effectiveness of NUEDEXTA in PMs, but adverse events of the quinidine are still possible. In those patients who may be at risk of significant toxicity due to quinidine, genotyping to determine if they are PMs should be considered prior to making the decision to treat with NUEDEXTA.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
