<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nuplazid" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  QT Interval Prolongation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and twice the rate of placebo): peripheral edema and confusional state. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ACADIA Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-844-422-2342 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The clinical trial database for NUPLAZID consists of over 1200 subjects and patients exposed to one or more doses of NUPLAZID. Of these, 616 were patients with hallucinations and delusions associated with Parkinson's disease psychosis (PDP). In the placebo-controlled setting, the majority of experience in patients comes from studies evaluating once-daily NUPLAZID doses of 34 mg (N=202) compared to placebo (N=231) for up to 6 weeks. In the controlled trial setting, the study population was approximately 64% male and 91% Caucasian, and the mean age was about 71 years at study entry. Additional clinical trial experience in patients with hallucinations and delusions associated with PDP comes from two open-label, safety extension studies (total N=497). The majority of patients receiving long-term treatment received 34 mg once-daily (N=459). Over 300 patients have been treated for more than 6 months; over 270 have been treated for at least 12 months; and over 150 have been treated for at least 24 months.



 The following adverse reactions are based on the 6-week, placebo-controlled studies in which NUPLAZID was administered once daily to patients with hallucinations and delusions associated with PDP.



 Common Adverse Reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice the rate of placebo): peripheral edema (7% NUPLAZID 34 mg vs. 2% placebo) and confusional state (6% NUPLAZID 34 mg vs. 3% placebo).



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment  



 A total of 8% (16/202) of NUPLAZID 34 mg-treated patients and 4% (10/231) of placebo-treated patients discontinued because of adverse reactions. The adverse reactions that occurred in more than one patient and with an incidence at least twice that of placebo were hallucination (2% NUPLAZID vs. &lt;1% placebo), urinary tract infection (1% NUPLAZID vs. &lt;1% placebo), and fatigue (1% NUPLAZID vs. 0% placebo).



 Adverse reactions that occurred in 6-week, placebo-controlled studies and that were reported at an incidence of &gt;=2% and &gt;placebo are presented in  Table 1  .



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Studies of 6-Week Treatment Duration and Reported in &gt;=2% and &gt;Placebo 
 Percentage of Patients Reporting Adverse Reaction    
                                                             NUPLAZID 34 mg                Placebo          
 N=202                                                           N=231                
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                         
   Nausea                                                          7%                         4%            
   Constipation                                                    4%                         3%            
   General disorders                                  
   Peripheral edema                                                7%                         2%            
   Gait disturbance                                                2%                        &lt;1%            
   Psychiatric disorders                              
   Hallucination                                                   5%                         3%            
   Confusional state                                               6%                         3%            
             Adverse Reactions in Demographic Subgroups  
 

 Examination of population subgroups in the 6-week, placebo-controlled studies did not reveal any differences in safety on the basis of age (&lt;=75 vs. &gt;75 years) or sex. Because the study population was predominantly Caucasian (91%; consistent with reported demographics for PD/PDP), racial or ethnic differences in the safety profile of NUPLAZID could not be assessed. In addition, in the 6-week, placebo-controlled studies, no clinically relevant differences in the incidence of adverse reactions were observed among those with a Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) score at entry of &lt;25 versus those with scores &gt;=25.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  

    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. NUPLAZID is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis unrelated to the hallucinations and delusions associated with Parkinson's disease psychosis   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. 
 *  NUPLAZID is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis unrelated to the hallucinations and delusions associated with Parkinson's disease psychosis. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  QT Interval Prolongation: Increases in QT interval; avoid use with drugs that also increase the QT interval and in patients with risk factors for prolonged QT interval. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Antipsychotic drugs increase the all-cause risk of death in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis. Analyses of 17 dementia-related psychosis placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks and largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs) revealed a risk of death in the drug-treated patients of between 1.6- to 1.7-times that in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in placebo-treated patients.



 Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. NUPLAZID is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis unrelated to the hallucinations and delusions associated with Parkinson's disease psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  ].  



    5.2 QT Interval Prolongation



  NUPLAZID prolongs the QT interval. The use of NUPLAZID should be avoided in patients with known QT prolongation or in combination with other drugs known to prolong QT interval including Class 1A antiarrhythmics (e.g., quinidine, procainamide) or Class 3 antiarrhythmics (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol), certain antipsychotic medications (e.g., ziprasidone, chlorpromazine, thioridazine), and certain antibiotics (e.g., gatifloxacin, moxifloxacin) [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  . NUPLAZID should also be avoided in patients with a history of cardiac arrhythmias, as well as other circumstances that may increase the risk of the occurrence of torsade de pointes and/or sudden death, including symptomatic bradycardia, hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia, and the presence of congenital prolongation of the QT interval [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
