<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nutrilipid" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse Reactions described elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Death in Preterm Infants [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Infections [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Fat Overload Syndrome [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Refeeding Syndrome [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Aluminum Toxicity [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *  Risk of Parenteral Nutrition Associated Liver Disease [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *  Hypertriglyceridemia [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.10)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions have included hyperlipidemia, hypercoagulability, thrombophlebitis, thrombocytopenia (  6.1  ) 
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact B. Braun Medical Inc. at 1-800-227-2862 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reactions reported with other intravenous lipid emulsions include hyperlipidemia, hypercoagulability, thrombophlebitis, and thrombocytopenia.



 Adverse reactions reported in long-term use with other intravenous lipid emulsions include hepatomegaly, jaundice due to central lobular cholestasis, splenomegaly, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, abnormalities in liver function tests, brown pigmentation of the liver and overloading syndrome (focal seizures, fever, leukocytosis, hepatomegaly, splenomegaly and shock).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: DEATH IN PRETERM INFANTS

  WARNING: DEATH IN PRETERM INFANTS

    *  Deaths in preterm infants after infusion of intravenous lipid emulsions have been reported in the medical literature. 
 *  Autopsy findings included intravascular fat accumulation in the lungs. 
 *  Preterm infants and low birth weight infants have poor clearance of intravenous lipid emulsion and increased free fatty acid plasma levels following lipid emulsion infusion. 
                  [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)     and     Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ]              
 

   EXCERPT:     WARNING: DEATH IN PRETERM INFANTS   



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Deaths in preterm infants have been reported in literature. (5.1, 8.4) 
 *  Autopsy findings included intravascular fat accumulation in the lungs. (5.1, 8.4) 
 *  Preterm and low birth weight infants have poor clearance of intravenous lipid emulsion and increased free fatty acid plasma levels following lipid emulsion infusion. (5.1, 8.4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hypersensitivity reactions:   Monitor for signs or symptoms and discontinue infusion if reactions occur (  5.2  ) 
 *   Infection, fat overload, and refeeding complications:    Monitor for signs and symptoms; monitor laboratory parameters (  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Death in Preterm Infants



  Deaths in preterm infants after infusion of intravenous lipid emulsions have been reported. Autopsy findings included intravascular lipid accumulation in the lungs.



 Base the decision to treat preterm and small for gestational age infants with intravenous lipid emulsion upon careful benefit-risk assessment. Strictly adhere to the recommended total daily dose; hourly infusion rate should be as slow as possible and should not exceed 0.75 mL/kg/hour [see   Dosage and Administration (2.4)    ].



 Preterm and small for gestational age infants have poor clearance of intravenous lipid emulsion and increased free fatty acid plasma levels following fat emulsion infusion; therefore, seriously consider administration of less than the maximum recommended doses in these patients in order to decrease the likelihood of intravenous fat overload.



 Carefully monitor the infant's ability to eliminate the infused lipids from the circulation (such as serum triglycerides and/or plasma free fatty acid levels) [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.10)    ].



 Because of the risk of thrombocytopenia, monitor platelet counts frequently in neonatal patients receiving parenteral nutrition with Nutrilipid(r) 20%.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Stop infusion immediately and treat patient accordingly if signs or symptoms of a hypersensitivity or allergic reaction develop. Signs or symptoms may include: tachypnea, dyspnea, hypoxia, bronchospasm, tachycardia, hypotension, cyanosis, vomiting, nausea, headache, sweating, dizziness, altered mentation, flushing, rash, urticaria, erythema, pyrexia, and chills.



    5.3 Infections



  Patients who require parenteral nutrition are at high risk of infections due to malnutrition and their underlying disease state.



 Infection and sepsis may occur as a result of the use of intravenous catheters to administer parenteral nutrition, poor maintenance of catheters, or immunosuppressive effects of illness, drugs, and parenteral formulations.



 Decrease the risk of septic complications with heightened emphasis on aseptic technique in catheter placement and maintenance, as well as aseptic technique in the preparation of the nutritional formula.



 Carefully monitor for signs and symptoms (including fever and chills) of early infections, including laboratory test results (including leukocytosis and hyperglycemia) and frequent checks of the parenteral access device.



    5.4 Fat Overload Syndrome



  Fat overload syndrome is a rare condition that has been reported with intravenous lipid formulations. A reduced or limited ability to metabolize the lipids contained in Nutrilipid(r) 20% accompanied by prolonged plasma clearance may result in a syndrome characterized by a sudden deterioration in the patient's condition accompanied by fever, anemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, coagulation disorders, hyperlipidemia, liver fatty infiltration (hepatomegaly), deteriorating liver function, and central nervous system manifestations (e.g., coma). The cause of the fat overload syndrome is unclear. The syndrome is usually reversible when the infusion of the lipid emulsion is stopped. Although it has been most frequently observed when the recommended lipid dose was exceeded, cases have also been described where the lipid formulation was administered according to instructions.



    5.5 Refeeding Syndrome



  Refeeding severely undernourished patients with parenteral nutrition may result in the refeeding syndrome, characterized by the intracellular shift of potassium, phosphorus, and magnesium as the patient becomes anabolic. Thiamine deficiency and fluid retention may also develop. Carefully monitor severely undernourished patients and slowly increase their nutrient intakes, while avoiding overfeeding, to prevent these complications.



    5.6 Monitoring / Laboratory Tests



  Monitor fluid status closely in patients with pulmonary edema or heart failure.



 Monitor serum triglycerides [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.10)    ], fluid and electrolyte status, serum osmolarity, blood glucose, liver and kidney function, blood count (including platelets), and coagulation parameters throughout treatment.



    5.7 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  Content of Vitamin K may counteract anticoagulant activity [see   Drug Interactions (7)    ].



 The lipids contained in this emulsion may interfere with the results of certain laboratory tests if the blood sample is taken before the lipids are eliminated from the serum (these are generally eliminated after a period of 5 to 6 hours without receiving lipids).



    5.8 Aluminum Toxicity



  Nutrilipid(r) 20% contains no more than 25 mcg/L of aluminum.



 The aluminum contained in Nutrilipid(r) 20% may reach toxic levels with prolonged administration in patients with impaired kidney function. Preterm infants are at greater risk because their kidneys are immature, and they require large amounts of calcium and phosphate solutions that contain aluminum.



 Patients with impaired kidney function, including preterm infants, who receive parenteral levels of aluminum at greater than 4 to 5 mcg/kg/day, accumulate aluminum at levels associated with central nervous system and bone toxicity. Tissue loading may occur at even lower rates of administration of total parenteral nutrition products.



    5.9 Risk of Parenteral Nutrition Associated Liver Disease



  Parenteral Nutrition Associated Liver Disease (PNALD) has been reported in patients who receive parenteral nutrition for extended periods of time, especially preterm infants, and can present as cholestasis or steatohepatitis . The exact etiology is unknown and is likely multifactorial. Intravenously administered phytosterols (plant sterols) contained in plant-derived lipid formulations have been associated with development of PNALD although a causal relationship has not been clearly established.



 If Nutrilipid(r) 20% treated patients develop liver test abnormalities consider discontinuation or dose reduction.



    5.10 Hypertriglyceridemia



  To evaluate the patient's capacity to eliminate and metabolize the infused lipid emulsion, measure serum triglycerides before the start of infusion (baseline value), with each increase in dosage, and regularly throughout treatment.



 Reduce dose of Nutrilipid(r) 20% and monitor serum triglyceride levels in patients with serum triglyceride concentrations above 400 mg/dL to avoid the clinical consequences associated with hypertriglyceridemia. Serum triglyceride levels above 1000 mg/dL have been associated with an increased risk of pancreatitis.



 Impaired lipid metabolism with hypertriglyceridemia may occur in conditions such as inherited lipid disorders, obesity, diabetes mellitus, and metabolic syndrome. In these cases, increased triglycerides can also be increased by glucose and/or overfeeding. Monitor overall energy intake and other sources of fat and glucose, as well as drugs that may interfere with lipid and glucose metabolism.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
