<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nutropin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common somatropin-related adverse reactions include injection site reactions. Additional common adverse reactions in adults include edema, arthralgias, and carpal tunnel syndrome (  6.1  ,  6.2  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genentech at 1-888-835-2555 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Most Serious and/or Most Frequently Observed Adverse Reactions

  This list presents the most serious  a  and/or most frequently observed  b  adverse reactions during treatment with somatropin:



 *    a  Sudden death in pediatric patients with Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS) with risk factors including severe obesity, history of upper airway obstruction or sleep apnea and unidentified respiratory infection [see  Contraindications (4.2)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] . 
 *    a  Intracranial tumors, in particular meningiomas, in teenagers/young adults treated with radiation to the head as children for a first neoplasm and somatropin [see  Contraindications (4.3)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  
 *    a  Pancreatitis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ]  
 *    a,b  Glucose intolerance including impaired glucose tolerance/impaired fasting glucose as well as overt diabetes mellitus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].  
 *    a  Intracranial hypertension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ] . 
 *    a  Significant diabetic retinopathy [see  Contraindications (4.4)  ].  
 *    a  Slipped capital femoral epiphysis in pediatric patients [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ].  
 *    a  Progression of preexisting scoliosis in pediatric patients [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ].  
 *    b  Fluid retention manifested by edema, arthralgia, myalgia, nerve compression syndromes including carpal tunnel syndrome/paraesthesias [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ].  
 *    a  Unmasking of latent central hypothyroidism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ].  
 *    a  Injection site reactions/rashes and lipoatrophy (as well as rare generalized hypersensitivity reactions) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ].  
      6.2 Clinical Trials Experience
   Because clinical trials are conducted under varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed during the clinical trials performed with one somatropin formulation cannot always be directly compared to the rates observed during the clinical trials performed with a second somatropin formulation, and may not reflect the adverse reaction rates observed in practice.



     Pediatric Patients  



     Growth Hormone Deficiency (GHD)  



 Injection site discomfort has been reported. This is more commonly observed in children switched from another somatropin product to Nutropin AQ.



     Turner Syndrome  



 In a randomized, controlled trial, there was a statistically significant increase, as compared to untreated controls, in otitis media (43% vs. 26%) and ear disorders (18% vs. 5%) in patients receiving somatropin.



     Idiopathic Short Stature (ISS)  



 In a post-marketing surveillance study, the National Cooperative Growth Study (NCGS), the pattern of adverse events in over 8,000 patients with ISS was consistent with the known safety profile of growth hormone (GH), and no new safety signals attributable to GH were identified. The frequency of protocol-defined targeted adverse events is described in the table, below.



 Table 1 Protocol-Defined Targeted Adverse Events in the ISS NCGS Cohort 
 Reported Events                                                                   NCGS(N = 8018)         
  
 AVN = avascular necrosis; SCFE = slipped capital femoral epiphysis.Data obtained with several rhGH products (Nutropin, Nutropin AQ, Nutropin Depot and Protropin).   
  
   Any Adverse Even  t                                                                                    
   Overall                                                                           103 (1.3%)           
   Targeted Adverse Event                                                                                 
   Overall                                                                           103 (1.3%)           
   Injection-site reaction                                                            28 (0.3%)           
   New onset or progression of scoliosis                                              16 (0.2%)           
   Gynecomastia                                                                       12 (0.1%)           
   Any new onset or recurring tumor (benign)                                          12 (0.1%)           
   Arthralgia or arthritis                                                            10 (0.1%)           
   Diabetes mellitus                                                                  5 (0.1%)            
   Edema                                                                              5 (0.1%)            
   Cancer, neoplasm (new onset or recurrence)                                         4 (0.0%)            
   Fracture                                                                           4 (0.0%)            
   Intracranial hypertension                                                          4 (0.0%)            
   Abnormal bone or other growth                                                      3 (0.0%)            
   Central nervous system tumor                                                       2 (0.0%)            
   New or recurrent SCFE or AVN                                                       2 (0.0%)            
   Carpal tunnel syndrome                                                             1 (0.0%)            
        In subjects treated in a long-term study of Nutropin for ISS, mean fasting and postprandial insulin levels increased, while mean fasting and postprandial glucose levels remained unchanged. Mean hemoglobin A1c(A1C) levels rose slightly from baseline as expected during adolescence; sporadic values outside normal limits occurred transiently.
 

     Adult Patients  



     Growth Hormone Deficiency  



 In clinical studies with Nutropin AQ in GHD adults, edema or peripheral edema was reported in 41% of GH-treated patients and 25% of placebo-treated patients. In GHD adults, arthralgias and other joint disorders were reported in 27% of GH-treated patients and 15% of placebo-treated patients.



 Nutropin therapy in adults with GHD of adult-onset was associated with an increase of median fasting insulin level in the Nutropin 0.0125 mg/kg/day group from 9.0 uU/mL at baseline to 13.0 uU/mL at Month 12 with a return to the baseline median level after a 3-week post-washout period of GH therapy. In the placebo group there was no change from 8.0 uU/mL at baseline to Month 12, and after the post-washout period, the median level was 9.0 uU/mL. The between-treatment group difference on the change from baseline to Month 12 in median fasting insulin level was significant, p &lt; 0.0001. In childhood-onset subjects, there was an increase of median fasting insulin level in the Nutropin 0.025 mg/kg/day group from 11.0 uU/mL at baseline to 20.0 uU/mL at Month 12, in the Nutropin 0.0125 mg/kg/day group from 8.5 uU/mL to 11.0 uU/mL, and in the placebo group from 7.0 uU/mL to 8.0 uU/mL. The between-treatment group differences for these changes were significant, p = 0.0007.



 In subjects with adult-onset GHD, there were no between-treatment group differences on change from baseline to Month 12 in mean A1C level, p = 0.08. In childhood-onset GHD, the mean A1C level increased in the Nutropin 0.025 mg/kg/day group from 5.2% at baseline to 5.5% at Month 12, and did not change in the Nutropin 0.0125 mg/kg/day group from 5.1% at baseline or in the placebo group from 5.3% at baseline. The between-treatment group differences were significant, p = 0.009.



   6.3 Post-Marketing Experience

  Because these adverse events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The adverse events reported during post-marketing surveillance do not differ from those listed/discussed above in  Sections 6.1  and  6.2  in children and adults.



 Leukemia has been reported in a small number of GHD children treated with somatropin, somatrem (methionylated rhGH) and GH of pituitary origin. It is uncertain whether these cases of leukemia are related to GH therapy, the pathology of GHD itself, or other associated treatments such as radiation therapy. On the basis of current evidence, experts have not been able to conclude that GH therapy per se was responsible for these cases of leukemia. The risk for children with GHD, CKD, or TS, if any, remains to be established  [see  Contraindications (4.3)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .



 The following additional adverse reactions have been reported in GH-treated patients: gynecomastia (children), and pancreatitis [  (Children and adults, see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ].  



   6.4 Immunogenicity

  As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to Nutropin with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading. In the case of GH, antibodies with binding capacities lower than 2 mg/L have not been associated with growth attenuation. In a very small number of patients treated with somatropin, when binding capacity was greater than 2 mg/L, interference with the growth response was observed.



 In clinical studies of pediatric patients that were treated with Nutropin for the first time, 0/107 GHD patients, 0/125 CKD patients, 0/112 TS, and 0/117 ISS patients screened for antibody production developed antibodies with binding capacities &gt;= 2 mg/L at six months. In a clinical study of patients that were treated with Nutropin AQ for the first time, 0/38 GHD patients screened for antibody production for up to 15 months developed antibodies with binding capacities &gt;= 2 mg/L.



 Additional short-term immunologic and renal function studies were carried out in a group of pediatric patients with CKD after approximately one year of treatment to detect other potential adverse effects of antibodies to GH. Testing included measurements of C1q, C3, C4, rheumatoid factor, creatinine, creatinine clearance, and blood urea nitrogen (BUN). No adverse effects of GH antibodies were noted  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute critical illness: Evaluate potential benefit of treatment continuation against potential risk (  5.1  ). 
 *  PWS: Evaluate for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiating therapy. Discontinue treatment if these signs occur. (  5.2  ). 
 *  Neoplasm: Monitor patients with preexisting tumors for progression or reoccurrence. Increased risk of a second neoplasm in childhood cancer survivors treated with somatropin - in particular meningiomas in patients treated with radiation to the head for their first neoplasm. (  5.3  ). 
 *  Impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) and Diabetes Mellitus (DM): Periodically monitor glucose levels in all patients, as IGT and DM may be unmasked during somatropin therapy. Doses of concurrent antihyperglycemic drugs in patients with DM may require adjustment. (  5.4  ). 
 *  Intracranial hypertension (IH): Exclude preexisting papilledema. IH may develop, but is usually reversible after discontinuation or dose reduction (  5.5  ). 
 *  Fluid retention (e.g., edema, arthralgia, carpal tunnel syndrome- especially in adults): Reduce dose as necessary if such signs develop (  5.6  ). 
 *  Hypopituitarism: Closely monitor other hormone replacement therapies (  5.7  ). 
 *  Hypothyroidism: Monitor thyroid function periodically as it may first become evident or worsen after initiation of somatropin (  5.8  ). 
 *  Slipped capital femoral epiphysis (SCFE): Evaluate any child with onset of a limp or hip/knee pain for possible SCFE (  5.9  ). 
 *  Progression of preexisting scoliosis: Monitor any child with scoliosis for progression of the curve (  5.10  ). 
 *  Pancreatitis: Consider pancreatitis in patients with persistent severe abdominal pain (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Critical Illness



  Increased mortality in patients with acute critical illnesses due to complications following open heart surgery, abdominal surgery or multiple accidental trauma, or those with acute respiratory failure has been reported after treatment with pharmacologic amounts of somatropin [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  . The safety of continuing somatropin treatment in patients receiving replacement doses for approved indications who concurrently develop these illnesses has not been established. Therefore, the potential benefit of treatment continuation with somatropin in patients having acute critical illnesses should be weighed against the potential risk.



    5.2 Prader-Willi Syndrome (PWS) in Children



  There have been reports of fatalities after initiating therapy with somatropin in pediatric patients with PWS who had one or more of the following risk factors: severe obesity, history of upper airway obstruction or sleep apnea, or unidentified respiratory infection. Male patients with one or more of these factors may be at greater risk than females. Patients with PWS syndrome should be evaluated for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiation of treatment with somatropin. If during treatment with somatropin, patients show signs of upper airway obstruction (including onset of or increased snoring) and/or new onset sleep apnea, treatment should be interrupted. All patients with PWS treated with somatropin should also have effective weight control and be monitored for signs of respiratory infection, which should be diagnosed as early as possible and treated aggressively [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ]  . Nutropin AQ is not indicated for the treatment of pediatric patients who have growth failure due to genetically confirmed PWS.



    5.3 Neoplasms



   In childhood cancer survivors who were treated with radiation to the brain/head for their first neoplasm and who developed subsequent GHD and were treated with somatropin, an increased risk of a second neoplasm has been reported. Intracranial tumors, in particular meningiomas, were the most common of these second neoplasms. In adults, it is unknown whether there is any relationship between somatropin replacement therapy and CNS tumor recurrence [see  Contraindications (4.3)  ]  . Monitor all patients with a history of GHD secondary to an intracranial neoplasm routinely while on somatropin therapy for progression or recurrence of the tumor.  



 Because children with certain rare genetic causes of short stature have an increased risk of developing malignancies, practitioners should thoroughly consider the risks and benefits of starting somatropin in these patients. If treatment with somatropin is initiated, these patients should be carefully monitored for development of neoplasms.



 Monitor patients on somatropin therapy carefully for increased growth, or potential malignant changes, of preexisting nevi.



    5.4 Glucose Intolerance and Diabetes Mellitus



  Treatment with somatropin may decrease insulin sensitivity, particularly at higher doses in susceptible patients. As a result, previously undiagnosed impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) and overt diabetes mellitus may be unmasked during somatropin treatment, and new onset type 2 diabetes mellitus has been reported in patients taking somatropin. Therefore, glucose levels should be monitored periodically in all patients treated with somatropin, especially in those with risk factors for diabetes, such as obesity, Turner syndrome (TS), or a family history of diabetes mellitus. Patients with preexisting type 1 or type 2 diabetes mellitus or IGT should be monitored closely during somatropin therapy. The doses of antihyperglycemic drugs (i.e. insulin or oral/injectable agents) may require adjustment when somatropin therapy is instituted in these patients.



    5.5 Intracranial Hypertension



  Intracranial Hypertension (IH) with papilledema, visual changes, headache, nausea, and/or vomiting has been reported in a small number of patients treated with somatropin products. Symptoms usually occurred within the first eight (8) weeks after the initiation of somatropin therapy. In all reported cases, IH-associated signs and symptoms rapidly resolved after cessation of therapy or a reduction of the somatropin dose. Funduscopic examination should be performed routinely before initiating treatment with somatropin to exclude preexisting papilledema, and periodically during the course of somatropin therapy. If papilledema is observed by funduscopy during somatropin treatment, treatment should be stopped. If somatropin-induced IH is diagnosed, treatment with somatropin can be restarted at a lower dose after IH-associated signs and symptoms have resolved. Patients with TS, chronic kidney disease (CKD), and PWS may be at increased risk for the development of IH.



    5.6 Fluid Retention



  Fluid retention during somatropin replacement therapy in adults may occur. Clinical manifestations of fluid retention are usually transient and dose dependent.



    5.7 Hypopituitarism



  Patients with hypopituitarism (multiple hormone deficiencies) should have their other hormonal replacement treatments closely monitored during somatropin treatment.



    5.8 Hypothyroidism



  Undiagnosed/untreated hypothyroidism may prevent an optimal response to somatropin, in particular, the growth response in children. Patients with TS have an inherently increased risk of developing autoimmune thyroid disease and primary hypothyroidism. In patients with GHD, central (secondary) hypothyroidism may first become evident or worsen during somatropin treatment. Therefore, patients treated with somatropin should have periodic thyroid function tests and thyroid hormone replacement therapy should be initiated or appropriately adjusted when indicated.



    5.9 Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis (SCFE) in Pediatric Patients



  SCFE may occur more frequently in patients with endocrine disorders (including GHD and TS) or in patients undergoing rapid growth. Any pediatric patient with the onset of a limp or complaints of hip or knee pain during somatropin therapy should be carefully evaluated.



    5.10 Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis in Pediatric Patients



  Progression of scoliosis can occur in patients who experience rapid growth. Because somatropin increases growth rate, patients with a history of scoliosis who are treated with somatropin should be monitored for progression of scoliosis. However, somatropin has not been shown to increase the occurrence of scoliosis. Skeletal abnormalities including scoliosis are commonly seen in untreated TS patients. Scoliosis is also commonly seen in untreated patients with PWS. Physicians should be alert to these abnormalities, which may manifest during somatropin therapy.



    5.11 Otitis Media and Cardiovascular Disorders in Patients with Turner Syndrome



  Patients with TS should be evaluated carefully for otitis media and other ear disorders, as these patients have an increased risk of ear and hearing disorders. Somatropin treatment may increase the occurrence of otitis media in patients with TS. In addition, patients with TS should be monitored closely for cardiovascular disorders (e.g., hypertension, aortic aneurysm or dissection, stroke) as these patients are also at increased risk for these conditions.



    5.12 Chronic Kidney Disease in Pediatric Patients



  Children with growth failure secondary to CKD should be examined periodically for evidence of progression of renal osteodystrophy. SCFE or avascular necrosis of the femoral head may be seen in children with advanced renal osteodystrophy, and it is uncertain whether these problems are affected by somatropin therapy. X-rays of the hip should be obtained prior to initiating somatropin therapy in CKD patients and physicians and parents should be alert to the development of a limp or complaints of hip or knee pain in these patients treated with Nutropin AQ. No studies have been completed evaluating Nutropin AQ therapy in patients who have received renal transplants. Currently, treatment of patients with functioning renal allografts is not indicated.



    5.13 Local and Systemic Reactions



  When somatropin is administered subcutaneously at the same site over a long period of time, tissue atrophy may result. This can be avoided by rotating the injection site [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  . As with any protein, local or systemic allergic reactions may occur. Parents/patients should be informed that such reactions are possible and that prompt medical attention should be sought if allergic reactions occur.



    5.14 Laboratory Tests



  Serum levels of inorganic phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase, and parathyroid hormone (PTH), and IGF-1 may increase during somatropin therapy.



    5.15 Pancreatitis



  Cases of pancreatitis have been reported rarely in children and adults receiving somatropin treatment, with some evidence supporting a greater risk in children compared with adults. Published literature indicates that girls who have TS may be at greater risk than other somatropin-treated children. Pancreatitis should be considered in any somatropin-treated patient, especially a child, who develops persistent severe abdominal pain.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
