<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="nuvigil" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Armodafinil has been evaluated for safety in over 1100 patients with excessive sleepiness associated with primary disorders of sleep and wakefulness. In clinical trials, NUVIGIL has been found to be generally well tolerated and most adverse experiences were mild to moderate.



 In the placebo-controlled clinical studies, the most commonly observed adverse events (&gt;= 5%) associated with the use of NUVIGIL occurring more frequently than in the placebo-treated patients were headache, nausea, dizziness, and insomnia. The adverse event profile was similar across the studies.



 In the placebo-controlled clinical trials, 44 of the 645 patients (7%) who received NUVIGIL discontinued due to an adverse experience compared to 16 of the 445 (4%) of patients that received placebo. The most frequent reason for discontinuation was headache (1%).



   Incidence in Controlled Trials

  The following table (Table 3) presents the adverse experiences that occurred at a rate of 1% or more and were more frequent in patients treated with NUVIGIL than in placebo group patients in the placebo-controlled clinical trials.



 The prescriber should be aware that the figures provided below cannot be used to predict the frequency of adverse experiences in the course of usual medical practice, where patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those occurring during clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be directly compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, or investigators. Review of these frequencies, however, provides prescribers with a basis to estimate the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the incidence of adverse events in the population studied.



  



   Table 3. Incidence &gt; 1% (In Percent) Of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experiences In Parallel-Group, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trialsa In OSA, Narcolepsy and SWD With NUVIGIL (150 mg and 250 mg)  




   System Organ ClassMedDRA preferred term                      NUVIGIL(Percent, N=645)      Placebo(Percent, N=445)     
 Cardiac Disorders                                                                                         
    Palpitations                                              2                     1                      
 Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                
    Nausea                                                    7                     3                      
    Diarrhea                                                  4                     2                      
    Dry Mouth                                                 4                     1                      
    Dyspepsia                                                 2                     0                      
 Abdominal Pain Upper                                         2                     1                      
 Constipation                                                 1                     0                      
 Vomiting                                                     1                     0                      
 Loose Stools                                                 1                     0                      
 General Disorders And Administration Site Conditions                                                      
 Fatigue                                                      2                     1                      
 Thirst                                                       1                     0                      
 Influenza-Like Illness                                       1                     0                      
 Pain                                                         1                     0                      
 Pyrexia                                                      1                     0                      
 Immune System Disorders                                                                                   
 Seasonal Allergy                                             1                     0                      
 Investigations                                                                                            
 Gamma-Glutamyltransferase Increased                          1                     0                      
 Heart Rate Increased                                         1                     0                      
 Metabolism And Nutrition Disorders                                                                        
 Anorexia                                                     1                     0                      
 Decreased Appetite                                           1                     0                      
 Nervous System Disorders                                                                                  
 Headache                                                     17                    9                      
 Dizziness                                                    5                     2                      
 Disturbance In Attention                                     1                     0                      
 Tremor                                                       1                     0                      
 Migraine                                                     1                     0                      
 Paresthesia                                                  1                     0                      
 Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                     
 Insomnia                                                     5                     1                      
 Anxiety                                                      4                     1                      
 Depression                                                   2                     0                      
 Agitation                                                    1                     0                      
 Nervousness                                                  1                     0                      
 Depressed Mood                                               1                     0                      
 Renal And Urinary Disorders                                                                               
 Polyuria                                                     1                     0                      
 Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders                                                           
 Dyspnea                                                      1                     0                      
 Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                    
 Rash                                                         2                     0                      
 Contact Dermatitis                                           1                     0                      
 Hyperhydrosis                                                1                     0                      
   a   Four double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical studies in SWD, OSA, and narcolepsy; incidence is rounded to the nearest whole percent. Included are only those events for which NUVIGIL incidence is greater than that of placebo.   
           Dose Dependency of Adverse Events
   In the placebo-controlled clinical trials which compared doses of 150 mg/day and 250 mg/day of NUVIGIL and placebo, the only adverse events that appeared to be dose-related were headache, rash, depression, dry mouth, insomnia, and nausea.



   Table 4. Incidence (In Percent) Of Dose-Dependent , Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experiences By Dose and By Treatment In Parallel-Group, Placebo-Controlled    Clinical Trials  a  In OSA, Narcolepsy and SWD With NUVIGIL (150 mg and 250 mg)  




  System Organ Class MedDRA preferred term     NUVIGIL250 mg(Percent,N=198)      NUVIGIL150 mg(Percent, N=447)      NUVIGIL Combined(Percent, N=645)      Placebo(Percent,N=445)     
 Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                  
    Nausea                            9                6                7                  3                 
    Dry Mouth                         7                2                4                  &lt;1                
 Nervous System Disorders                                                                                    
 Headache                             23               14               17                 9                 
 Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                       
 Insomnia                             6                4                5                  1                 
 Depression                           3                1                2                  &lt;1                
 Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                         
 Rash                                 4                1                2                  &lt;1                
   a  Four double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical studies in SWD, OSA, and narcolepsy.   
             Vital Sign Changes
   There were small, but consistent, increases in average values for mean systolic and diastolic blood pressure in controlled trials (See    PRECAUTIONS    ). There was a small, but consistent, average increase in pulse rate over placebo in controlled trials. This increase varied from 0.9 to 3.5 BPM. 



   Laboratory Changes

  Clinical chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis parameters were monitored in the studies. Mean plasma levels of gamma glutamyltransferase (GGT) and alkaline phosphatase (AP) were found to be higher following administration of NUVIGIL, but not placebo. Few subjects, however, had GGT or AP elevations outside of the normal range. No differences were apparent in alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, total protein, albumin, or total bilirubin, although there were rare cases of isolated elevations of AST and/or ALT. A single case of mild pancytopenia was observed after 35-days of treatment and resolved with drug discontinuation. A small mean decrease from baseline in serum uric acid compared to placebo was seen in clinical trials. The clinical significance of this finding is unknown.



  



   ECG Changes

  No pattern of ECG abnormalities could be attributed to NUVIGIL administration in placebo-controlled clinical trials.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
