<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ocaliva" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following clinically significant adverse reactions are described elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Liver-Related Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Severe Pruritus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Reduction in HDL-C [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5%) are: pruritus, fatigue, abdominal pain and discomfort, rash, oropharyngeal pain, dizziness, constipation, arthralgia, thyroid function abnormality, and eczema. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Intercept Pharmaceuticals at 1-844-782-ICPT or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 432 patients with PBC were studied in three double-blind placebo-controlled trials. Of these patients, 290 were treated with OCALIVA for at least 6 months, 232 were treated for at least 12 months, and 70 were treated for at least 2 years. There were 131 patients who received OCALIVA 10 mg once daily and 70 who received OCALIVA 5 mg once daily.



 In Trial 1, 216 patients were randomized (1:1:1) to receive either:



 *  OCALIVA 10 mg once daily for the entire 12 months of the trial (n=73); 
 *  OCALIVA titration (5 mg once daily for the initial 6 months, with the option to increase to 10 mg once daily for the last 6 months, in patients who were tolerating OCALIVA, but had ALP 1.67-times ULN or greater, and/or total bilirubin greater than ULN, or less than 15% ALP reduction) (n=70); or 
 *  placebo (n=73). 
    During the trial, OCALIVA or placebo was administered in combination with UDCA in 93% of patients and as monotherapy in 7% of patients who were unable to tolerate UDCA. The overall discontinuation rate was 12% in the OCALIVA 10 mg arm, 10% in the OCALIVA titration arm, and 4% in the placebo arm.
 

 The recommended starting dosage of OCALIVA is 5 mg orally once daily for 3 months with titration to 10 mg once daily based upon tolerability and response  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ].  Initiation of therapy with OCALIVA 10 mg once daily is not recommended due to an increased risk of pruritus  .  



 The most common adverse reactions in Trial 1 occurring in at least 5% of patients in either OCALIVA treatment arm and at an incidence at least 1% higher than the placebo treatment arm are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Most Common Adverse Reactions in Adult Patients with PBC in Trial 1 by Treatment Arm with or without UDCAIn the trial there were 16 patients (7%) who were intolerant and did not receive concomitant UDCA: 6 patients (8%) in the OCALIVA 10 mg arm, 5 patients (7%) in the OCALIVA titration arm, and 5 patients (7%) in the placebo arm. 
                                                     PlaceboN = 73%     
 Adverse Reaction                                   OCALIVA 10 mgN = 73%  OCALIVA TitrationN = 70%   
  
 Pruritus                                                  70                 56                 38           
 Fatigue                                                   25                 19                 15           
 Abdominal pain and discomfort                             10                 19                 14           
 Rash                                                      10                  7                  8           
 Arthralgia                                                10                  6                  4           
 Oropharyngeal pain                                         8                  7                  1           
 Dizziness                                                  7                  7                  5           
 Constipation                                               7                  7                  5           
 Peripheral Edema                                           7                  3                  3           
 Palpitations                                               7                  3                  1           
 Pyrexia                                                    7                  0                  1           
 Thyroid function abnormality                               4                  6                  3           
 Eczema                                                     3                  6                  0           
              Liver-Related Adverse Reactions  
 

 In Trial 1, the following serious or otherwise clinically significant liver-related adverse reactions were reported at the recommended dosage of OCALIVA: one patient in the OCALIVA 10 mg treatment arm experienced ascites; one patient in the OCALIVA titration treatment arm experienced two episodes of ascites and four episodes of hepatic encephalopathy; one patient in the placebo treatment arm experienced variceal bleeding.



     Pruritus  



 Approximately 60% of patients had a history of pruritus upon enrollment in Trial 1. Treatment-emergent pruritus, including all the terms described in Table 1, generally started within the first month following the initiation of treatment with OCALIVA.



 The incidence of pruritus was higher in patients who started on OCALIVA 10 mg once daily relative to the OCALIVA titration arm, 70% and 56%, respectively. Discontinuation rates due to pruritus were also higher in patients who started on OCALIVA 10 mg once daily relative to the OCALIVA titration arm, 10% and 1%, respectively.



 The number of patients with pruritus who required an intervention (e.g., dosage adjustment, treatment interruption, or initiation of bile acid binding resin or antihistamine) was 30 of 51 patients (59%) in the OCALIVA 10 mg arm, 24 of 39 patients (62%) in the OCALIVA titration arm, and 14 of 28 patients (50%) in the placebo arm.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Liver-Related Adverse Reactions : Monitor for elevations in liver biochemical tests and development of liver-related adverse reactions; weigh the potential risk against the benefits of continuing treatment. Do not exceed 10 mg once daily. Adjust the dosage for patients with moderate or severe hepatic impairment. Discontinue in patients who develop complete biliary obstruction. (  2.3  ,  4  ,  5.1  ) 
 *   Severe Pruritus : Management strategies include the addition of bile acid binding resins or antihistamines; OCALIVA dosage reduction and/or temporary dosing interruption. (  2.2  ,  5.2  ) 
 *   Reduction in HDL-C : Monitor for changes in serum lipid levels during treatment. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Liver-Related Adverse Reactions



  In two 3-month, placebo-controlled clinical trials a dose-response relationship was observed for the occurrence of liver-related adverse reactions including jaundice, worsening ascites and primary biliary cholangitis flare with dosages of OCALIVA of 10 mg once daily to 50 mg once daily (up to 5-times the highest recommended dosage), as early as one month after starting treatment with OCALIVA [see  Overdosage (10)  ]  .



 In a pooled analysis of three placebo-controlled trials in patients with PBC, the exposure-adjusted incidence rates for all serious and otherwise clinically significant liver-related adverse reactions, and isolated elevations in liver biochemical tests, per 100 patient exposure years (PEY) were: 5.2 in the OCALIVA 10 mg group (highest recommended dosage), 19.8 in the OCALIVA 25 mg group (2.5 times the highest recommended dosage) and 54.5 in the OCALIVA 50 mg group (5 times the highest recommended dosage) compared to 2.4 in the placebo group.



 Monitor patients during treatment with OCALIVA for elevations in liver biochemical tests and for the development of liver-related adverse reactions. Weigh the potential risks against the benefits of continuing treatment with OCALIVA in patients who have experienced clinically significant liver-related adverse reactions. The maximum recommended dosage of OCALIVA is 10 mg once daily [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ]  . Adjust the dosage for patients with moderate or severe hepatic impairment [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ].  



 Discontinue OCALIVA in patients who develop complete biliary obstruction [see  Contraindications (4)  ].  



    5.2 Severe Pruritus



  Severe pruritus was reported in 23% of patients in the OCALIVA 10 mg arm, 19% of patients in the OCALIVA titration arm, and 7% of patients in the placebo arm in Trial 1, a 12-month double-blind randomized controlled trial of 216 patients [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Severe pruritus was defined as intense or widespread itching, interfering with activities of daily living, or causing severe sleep disturbance, or intolerable discomfort, and typically requiring medical interventions. In the subgroup of patients in the OCALIVA titration arm who increased their dosage from 5 mg once daily to 10 mg once daily after 6 months of treatment (n=33), the incidence of severe pruritus was 0% from Months 0 to 6 and 15% from Months 6 to 12. The median time to onset of severe pruritus was 11, 158, and 75 days for patients in the OCALIVA 10 mg, OCALIVA titration, and placebo arms, respectively.



 Management strategies include the addition of bile acid resins or antihistamines, OCALIVA dosage reduction, and/or temporary interruption of OCALIVA dosing [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ].  



    5.3 Reduction in HDL-C



  Patients with PBC generally exhibit hyperlipidemia characterized by a significant elevation in total cholesterol primarily due to increased levels of high density lipoprotein-cholesterol (HDL-C). In Trial 1, dose-dependent reductions from baseline in mean HDL-C levels were observed at 2 weeks in OCALIVA-treated patients, 20% and 9% in the 10 mg and titration arms, respectively, compared to 2% in the placebo arm. At month 12, the reduction from baseline in mean HDL-C level was 19% in the OCALIVA 10 mg arm, 12% in the OCALIVA titration arm, and 2% in the placebo arm. Nine patients in the OCALIVA 10 mg arm, 6 patients in the OCALIVA titration arm, versus 3 patients in the placebo arm had reductions in HDL-C to less than 40 mg/dL.



 Monitor patients for changes in serum lipid levels during treatment. For patients who do not respond to OCALIVA after 1 year at the highest recommended dosage that can be tolerated (maximum of 10 mg once daily), and who experience a reduction in HDL-C, weigh the potential risks against the benefits of continuing treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
