<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="odefsey" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis [See  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Severe Acute Exacerbations of Hepatitis B [See  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Skin and Hypersensitivity Reactions [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Depressive Disorders [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Hepatotoxicity [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Immune Reconstitution Syndrome [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Bone Loss and Mineralization Defects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
      EXCERPT:     Rilpivirine  : Most common adverse reactions to RPV (incidence greater than or equal to 2%, Grades 2-4) are depressive disorders, insomnia, and headache. (  6.1  )
 

   Emtricitabine &amp; Tenofovir Alafenamide  : Most common adverse reaction (incidence greater than or equal to 10%, all grades) is nausea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc. at 1-800-GILEAD-5 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug (or a drug given in various combinations with other concomitant therapy) cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug (or drug given in the same or different combination therapy) and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials of RPV-Containing Regimens in Adult Subjects with HIV-1 Infection  



 In pooled 96-week trials of antiretroviral treatment-naive HIV-1 infected adult subjects, the most common adverse reactions in subjects treated with RPV+FTC/TDF (N=550) (incidence greater than or equal to 2%, Grades 2-4) were headache, depressive disorders, and insomnia. The proportion of subjects who discontinued treatment with RPV+FTC/TDF due to adverse reactions, regardless of severity, was 2%. The most common adverse reactions that led to discontinuation in this treatment group were psychiatric disorders (1.6%) and rash (0.2%). Although the safety profile was similar in virologically-suppressed adults with HIV-1 infection who were switched to RPV and other antiretroviral drugs, the frequency of adverse events increased by 20% (N=317).



     Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI in Adult Subjects with HIV-1 Infection  



 In pooled 48-week trials of antiretroviral treatment-naive HIV-1 infected adult subjects, the most common adverse reaction in subjects treated with FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI (N=866) (incidence greater than or equal to 10%, all grades) was nausea (10%). In this treatment group, 0.9% of subjects discontinued FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI due to adverse event  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . The safety profile was similar in virologically-suppressed adults with HIV-1 infection who were switched to FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI (N=799). Antiretroviral treatment-naive adult subjects treated with FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI experienced mean increases of 30 mg/dL of total cholesterol, 15 mg/dL of LDL cholesterol, 7 mg/dL of HDL cholesterol and 29 mg/dL of triglycerides after 48 weeks of use.



     Renal Laboratory Tests  



 In two 48-week trials in antiretroviral treatment-naive HIV-1 infected adults treated with FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI (N=866) with a median baseline eGFR of 115 mL per minute, mean serum creatinine increased by 0.1 mg per dL from baseline to Week 48. Median urine protein-to-creatinine ratio (UPCR) was 44 mg per gram at baseline and at Week 48. In a 48-week trial in virologically-suppressed TDF-treated adults who switched to FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI (N=959) with a mean baseline eGFR of 112 mL per minute, mean serum creatinine was similar to baseline and median UPCR was 61 mg per gram at baseline and 46 mg per gram at Week 48. In a 24-week trial in adults with renal impairment (baseline eGFR 30 to 69 mL per minute) who received FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI (N=248), mean serum creatinine was 1.5 mg per dL at both baseline and Week 24. Median UPCR was 161 mg per gram at baseline and 93 mg per gram at Week 24.



     Bone Mineral Density Effects  



 In the pooled analysis of two 48-week trials of antiretroviral treatment-naive HIV-1 infected adult subjects, bone mineral density (BMD) from baseline to Week 48 was assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA). Mean BMD decreased from baseline to Week 48 by -1.30% with FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI at the lumbar spine and -0.66% at the total hip. BMD declines of 5% or greater at the lumbar spine were experienced by 10% of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI subjects. BMD declines of 7% or greater at the femoral neck were experienced by 7% of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI subjects. The long-term clinical significance of these BMD changes is not known. Fractures (excluding fingers and toes) were reported in 7 (0.8%) subjects in the FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI group.



 In 799 virologically-suppressed TDF-treated adult subjects that switched to FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI, at Week 48 mean BMD increased (1.86% lumbar spine, 1.95% total hip). BMD declines of 5% or greater at the lumbar spine were experienced by 1% of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI subjects. BMD declines of 7% or greater at the femoral neck were experienced by 1% of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI subjects.



     Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials in Pediatric Subjects with HIV-1 Infection  



 In an open-label 48-week trial of 36 antiretroviral treatment-naive HIV-1 infected pediatric subjects 12 to less than 18 years old (weighing at least 32 kg) treated with 25 mg per day of RPV and other antiretrovirals, the most common adverse reactions were headache (19%), depression (19%), somnolence (14%), nausea (11%), dizziness (8%), abdominal pain (8%), vomiting (6%) and rash (6%).



 In a 24-week, open-label trial of 23 antiretroviral treatment-naive HIV-1 infected pediatric subjects aged 12 to less than 18 years old (weighing at least 35 kg) who received FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI, the safety of this combination was similar to that of adults. Among these pediatric subjects, mean BMD increased from baseline to Week 24, +1.7% at the lumbar spine and +0.8% for the total body less head. Mean changes from baseline BMD Z-scores were -0.10 for lumbar spine and -0.11 for total body less head at Week 24. Two subjects had significant (greater than 4%) lumbar spine BMD loss at Week 24.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing experience in patients receiving RPV-containing regimens. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  



 Weight increased



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  



 Severe skin and hypersensitivity reactions including DRESS (Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms)



     Renal and Urinary Disorders  



 Nephrotic syndrome
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B

    WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B  

    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs in combination with other antiretrovirals   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .  



   ODEFSEY is not approved for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection, and the safety and efficacy of ODEFSEY have not been established in patients coinfected with human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV-1) and HBV. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and have discontinued products containing emtricitabine (FTC) and/or tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF), and may occur with discontinuation of ODEFSEY.   



   Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and discontinue ODEFSEY. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS and POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs. (5.1) 
 *  ODEFSEY is not approved for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and have discontinued products containing emtricitabine (FTC) and/or tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF), and may occur with ODEFSEY. Hepatic function should be monitored closely in these patients. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Skin and Hypersensitivity Reactions: Severe skin and hypersensitivity reactions have been reported during postmarketing experience with RPV-containing regimens, including cases of Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS). Immediately discontinue treatment if hypersensitivity or rash with systemic symptoms or elevations in hepatic serum biochemistries develops and closely monitor clinical status, including hepatic serum biochemistries. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Concomitant use of ODEFSEY with other drugs that may reduce the exposure of RPV may lead to loss of therapeutic effect of ODEFSEY and possible development of resistance. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Concomitant use of ODEFSEY with drugs with a known risk to prolong the QTc interval of the electrocardiogram may increase the risk of Torsade de Pointes. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Depressive disorders: Severe depressive disorders have been reported. Immediate medical evaluation is recommended for severe depressive disorders. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Hepatic adverse events have been reported in patients receiving an RPV-containing regimen. Monitor liver-associated tests before and during treatment with ODEFSEY in patients with underlying hepatic disease or marked elevations in liver-associated tests. Also consider monitoring liver-associated tests in patients without risk factors. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat: Observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Immune reconstitution syndrome: May necessitate further evaluation and treatment. (  5.9  ) 
 *  New onset or worsening renal impairment: Assess creatinine clearance, urine glucose, and urine protein in all patients before initiating ODEFSEY therapy and monitor during therapy. Monitor serum phosphorus in patients with chronic kidney disease. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Bone loss and mineralization defects: Consider monitoring BMD in patients with a history of pathologic fracture or other risk factors of osteoporosis or bone loss. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs in combination with other antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged nucleoside exposure may be risk factors. Particular caution should be exercised when administering nucleoside analogs to any patient with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors. Given that ODEFSEY contains two nucleos(t)ide analogs (i.e., FTC and TAF), ODEFSEY should be discontinued in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.2 Severe Acute Exacerbation of Hepatitis B in Patients Coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV



  Patients with HIV-1 should be tested for the presence of hepatitis B virus (HBV) before initiating antiretroviral therapy [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ]  . ODEFSEY is not approved for the treatment of chronic HBV infection, and the safety and efficacy of ODEFSEY have not been established in patients coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV.



 Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B (e.g., liver decompensation and liver failure) have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV and have discontinued products containing FTC and/or TDF, and may occur with discontinuation of ODEFSEY. Patients coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV who discontinue ODEFSEY should be closely monitored with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months after stopping treatment. If appropriate, initiation of antihepatitis B therapy may be warranted, especially in patients with advanced liver disease or cirrhosis, since post treatment exacerbation of hepatitis may lead to hepatic decompensation and liver failure.



    5.3 Skin and Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Severe skin and hypersensitivity reactions, including cases of Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS), have been reported during postmarketing experience with RPV-containing regimens. While some skin reactions were accompanied by constitutional symptoms such as fever, other skin reactions were associated with organ dysfunction, including elevations in hepatic serum biochemistries. During Phase 3 clinical trials of RPV, treatment-related rashes with at least Grade 2 severity were reported in 1% of subjects. Overall, most rashes were Grade 1 or 2 and occurred in the first four to six weeks of therapy [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  .



 Discontinue ODEFSEY immediately if signs or symptoms of severe skin or hypersensitivity reactions develop, including but not limited to, severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, blisters, mucosal involvement, conjunctivitis, facial edema, angioedema, hepatitis, or eosinophilia. Clinical status including laboratory parameters should be monitored and appropriate therapy should be initiated.



    5.4 Loss of Virologic Response Due to Drug Interactions



  The concomitant use of ODEFSEY and other drugs may result in known or potentially significant drug interactions, some of which may lead to loss of therapeutic effect of ODEFSEY and possible development of resistance due to reduced exposure of RPV.



 See  Table 1  for steps to prevent or manage these possible and known significant drug interactions, including dosing recommendations [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  Consider the potential for drug interactions prior to and during ODEFSEY therapy; review concomitant medications during ODEFSEY therapy; and monitor for the adverse reactions associated with the concomitant drugs.



    5.5 Prolongation of QTc Interval with Higher Than Recommended Dosages



  In healthy subjects, higher than recommended doses of RPV (75 mg once daily and 300 mg once daily - 3 and 12 times the recommended dosages, respectively) have been shown to prolong the QTc interval of the electrocardiogram [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  . Consider alternatives to ODEFSEY when coadministered with a drug with a known risk of Torsade de Pointes or when administered to patients at higher risk of Torsades de Pointes.



    5.6 Depressive Disorders



  Depressive disorders (including depressed mood, depression, dysphoria, major depression, mood altered, negative thoughts, suicide attempt, suicidal ideation) have been reported with RPV. Promptly evaluate patients with severe depressive symptoms to assess whether the symptoms are related to ODEFSEY, and to determine whether the risks of continued therapy outweigh the benefits.



 In Phase 3 trials of RPV in adult subjects (N=1368) through 96 weeks, the incidence of depressive disorders (regardless of causality, severity) reported among RPV-treated subjects (n=686) was 9%. Most events were mild or moderate in severity. In RPV-treated subjects, the incidence of Grades 3 and 4 depressive disorders (regardless of causality) was 1%, the incidence of discontinuation due to depressive disorders was 1%, and suicidal ideation and suicide attempt was reported in 4 and 2 subjects, respectively.



 During the Phase 2 trial in RPV-treated pediatric subjects 12 to less than 18 years of age (N=36), the incidence of depressive disorders (regardless of causality, severity) was 19% (7/36) through 48 weeks. Most events were mild or moderate in severity. The incidence of Grade 3 and 4 depressive disorders (regardless of causality) was 6% (2/36). None of the subjects discontinued due to depressive disorders. Suicidal ideation and suicide attempt were reported in 1 subject.



    5.7 Hepatotoxicity



  Hepatic adverse events have been reported in patients receiving an RPV-containing regimen. Patients with underlying hepatitis B or C, or marked elevations in liver-associated tests prior to treatment, may be at increased risk for worsening or development of liver-associated test elevations with use of ODEFSEY. A few cases of hepatic toxicity have been reported in adult patients receiving a RPV-containing regimen who had no preexisting hepatic disease or other identifiable risk factors. Appropriate laboratory testing prior to initiating therapy and monitoring for hepatotoxicity during therapy with ODEFSEY is recommended in patients with underlying hepatic disease such as hepatitis B or C, or in patients with marked elevations in liver-associated tests prior to treatment initiation. Liver-associated test monitoring should also be considered for patients without preexisting hepatic dysfunction or other risk factors.



    5.8 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution or accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.9 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including FTC and RPV, both components of ODEFSEY. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections [such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia (PCP), or tuberculosis], which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.10 New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment



  Renal impairment, including cases of acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome (renal tubular injury with severe hypophosphatemia), has been reported with the use of tenofovir prodrugs in both animal toxicology studies and human trials. In clinical trials of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI, there have been no cases of Fanconi syndrome or proximal renal tubulopathy (PRT). In clinical trials of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI in treatment-naive subjects and in virally suppressed subjects switched to FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI with eGFRs greater than 50 mL per minute, renal serious adverse events or discontinuations due to renal adverse reactions were encountered in less than 1% of participants treated with FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI. In a study of virally suppressed subjects with baseline eGFRs between 30 and 69 mL per minute treated with FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI for a median duration of 43 weeks, FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI was permanently discontinued due to worsening renal function in two of 80 (3%) subjects with a baseline eGFR between 30 and 50 mL per minute [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . ODEFSEY is not recommended in patients with estimated creatinine clearance below 30 mL per minute because data in this population are insufficient.



 Patients taking tenofovir prodrugs who have impaired renal function and those taking nephrotoxic agents, including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs are at increased risk of developing renal-related adverse reactions.



 Estimated creatinine clearance, urine glucose and urine protein should be assessed before initiating ODEFSEY therapy and should be monitored during therapy in all patients. Serum phosphorus should be monitored in patients with chronic kidney disease because these patients are at greater risk of developing Fanconi syndrome on tenofovir prodrugs. Discontinue ODEFSEY in patients who develop clinically significant decreases in renal function or evidence of Fanconi syndrome.



    5.11 Bone Loss and Mineralization Defects



   Decrease in Bone Mineral Density (BMD):  



 In animal toxicology studies and human clinical trials, TAF and tenofovir have been associated with decreases in BMD and increases in biochemical markers of bone metabolism suggestive of increased bone turnover. In clinical trials in HIV-1 infected treatment-naive adults, a significant decline in BMD was observed in 15% of subjects treated with FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . The long-term clinical significance of these changes has not been established.



 Assessment of BMD should be considered for adults and pediatric patients treated with ODEFSEY who have a history of pathologic bone fracture or other risk factors for osteoporosis or bone loss. Calcium and vitamin D supplementation may be beneficial for all patients. If bone abnormalities are suspected then appropriate consultation should be obtained.



    Mineralization Defects:  



 Cases of osteomalacia associated with proximal renal tubulopathy (PRT), manifested as bone pain or pain in extremities and which may contribute to fractures, have been reported in association with the use of TDF-containing products. Hypophosphatemia and osteomalacia secondary to PRT have occurred in patients at risk of renal dysfunction who present with persistent or worsening bone or muscle symptoms while receiving products containing TDF [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  . While not observed in clinical studies of FTC+TAF with EVG+COBI, the risk of osteomalacia with ODEFSEY is not known.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
