<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="odomzo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Musculoskeletal Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=10% of patients are muscle spasms, alopecia, dysgeusia, fatigue, nausea, musculoskeletal pain, diarrhea, decreased weight, decreased appetite, myalgia, abdominal pain, headache, pain, vomiting, and pruritus. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1     Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of ODOMZO was evaluated in Study 1, a randomized, double-blind, multiple cohort trial in which 229 patients received ODOMZO at either 200 mg (n=79) or 800 mg (n=150) daily. The frequency of common adverse reactions including muscle spasms, alopecia, dysgeusia, fatigue, nausea, decreased weight, decreased appetite, myalgia, pain, and vomiting was greater in patients treated with ODOMZO 800 mg as compared to 200 mg.



 The data described below reflect exposure to ODOMZO 200 mg daily in 79 patients with locally advanced BCC (laBCC; n=66) or metastatic BCC (mBCC; n=13) enrolled in Study 1. Patients were followed for at least 18 months unless discontinued earlier. The median duration of treatment with ODOMZO was 11.0 months (range 1.3 to 33.5 months). The study population characteristics were: median age of 67 years (range 25 to 92; 59% were &gt;=65 years), 61% male, and 90% white. The majority of patients had prior surgery (75%), radiotherapy (24%), systemic chemotherapy (4%), or topical or photodynamic therapies (18%) for treatment of BCC. No patient had prior exposure to a hedgehog pathway inhibitor.



 ODOMZO was permanently discontinued in 34% of patients or temporarily interrupted in 20% of patients for adverse reactions. Adverse reactions reported in at least two patients that led to discontinuation of the drug were: muscle spasms and dysgeusia (each 5%), asthenia, increased lipase, and nausea (each 4%), fatigue, decreased appetite, alopecia, and decreased weight (each 3%). Serious adverse reactions occurred in 18% of patients.



 The most common adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=10% of patients treated with ODOMZO 200 mg were muscle spasms, alopecia, dysgeusia, fatigue, nausea, musculoskeletal pain, diarrhea, decreased weight, decreased appetite, myalgia, abdominal pain, headache, pain, vomiting, and pruritus (Table 1).



 The key laboratory abnormalities are described in Table 2.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=10% of Patients in Study 1 
   a  No Grade 4 adverse reactions were reported.   
  
   Adverse Reaction      ODOMZO 200 mg(N=79)     
   All Grades  a  %      Grade 3%        
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
     Muscle spasms  54               3                 
     Musculoskeletal pain  32               1                 
     Myalgia      19               0                 
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorder     
     Alopecia     53               0                 
     Pruritus     10               0                 
   Nervous system disorders     
     Dysgeusia    46               0                 
     Headache     15               1                 
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
     Fatigue      41               4                 
     Pain         14               1                 
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
     Nausea       39               1                 
     Diarrhea     32               1                 
     Abdominal pain  18               0                 
     Vomiting     11               1                 
   Investigations     
     Decreased weight  30               3                 
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders     
     Decreased appetite  23               1                 
        Table 2: Key Laboratory Abnormalitiesa 
   a  Based on worst post-treatment laboratory value regardless of baseline; grading by CTCAE v4.03.  b  The serum creatinine level remained within normal range in 76% (60/79) of patients.   
  
   Laboratory Test      ODOMZO 200 mg(N=79)     
   All Grades %      Grades 3-4%     
   Chemistry       
     Increased serum creatinine  92  b            0                 
     Increased serum creatine kinase (CK)  61               8                 
     Hyperglycemia  51               4                 
     Increased lipase  43               13                
     Increased alanine aminotransferase  19               4                 
     Increased aspartate aminotransferase  19               4                 
     Increased amylase  16               1                 
   Hematology      
     Anemia       32               0                 
     Lymphopenia  28               3                 
           Amenorrhea  
 

 Amenorrhea lasting for at least 18 months occurred in two of 14 pre-menopausal women treated with ODOMZO 200 mg or 800 mg once daily.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY  

    *  ODOMZO can cause embryo-fetal death or severe birth defects when administered to a pregnant woman. ODOMZO is embryotoxic, fetotoxic, and teratogenic in animals [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]. 
 *  Verify the pregnancy status of females of reproductive potential prior to initiating therapy. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with ODOMZO and for at least 20 months after the last dose [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.3)]. 
 *  Advise males of the potential risk of exposure through semen and to use condoms with a pregnant partner or a female partner of reproductive potential during treatment with ODOMZO and for at least 8 months after the last dose [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.3)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  ODOMZO can cause embryo-fetal death or severe birth defects when administered to a pregnant woman and is embryotoxic, fetotoxic, and teratogenic in animals. (5.1, 8.1) 
 *  Verify the pregnancy status of females of reproductive potential prior to initiating therapy. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with ODOMZO and for at least 20 months after the last dose. (5.1, 8.3) 
 *  Advise males of the potential risk of exposure through semen and to use condoms with a pregnant partner or a female partner of reproductive potential during treatment with ODOMZO and for at least 8 months after the last dose. (5.1, 8.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Blood donation: Advise patients not to donate blood or blood products during treatment with ODOMZO and for at least 20 months after the last dose. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Musculoskeletal adverse reactions: Obtain serum creatine kinase (CK) and creatinine levels prior to initiating therapy, periodically during treatment, and as clinically indicated. Temporary dose interruption or discontinuation of ODOMZO may be required based on the severity of musculoskeletal adverse reactions. (  2.2  ,  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  ODOMZO can cause embryo-fetal death or severe birth defects when administered to a pregnant woman. In animal reproduction studies, sonidegib was embryotoxic, fetotoxic, and teratogenic at maternal exposures below the recommended human dose of 200 mg. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  .



  Females of Reproductive Potential  



 Verify pregnancy status of females of reproductive potential prior to initiating ODOMZO treatment. Advise females to use effective contraception during treatment with ODOMZO and for at least 20 months after the last dose [see Use in Specific Populations (8.3)]  .



  Males  



 Advise male patients with female partners to use condoms, even after a vasectomy, during treatment with ODOMZO and for at least 8 months after the last dose to avoid potential drug exposure in pregnant females or females of reproductive potential [see Use in Specific Populations (8.3)]  .



  Blood Donation  



 Advise patients not to donate blood or blood products while taking ODOMZO and for at least 20 months after the last dose of ODOMZO because their blood or blood products might be given to a female of reproductive potential.



    5.2     Musculoskeletal Adverse Reactions



  Musculoskeletal adverse reactions, which may be accompanied by serum creatine kinase (CK) elevations, occur with ODOMZO and other drugs which inhibit the hedgehog pathway.



 In a pooled safety analysis of 12 clinical studies involving 571 patients with various advanced cancers treated with ODOMZO at doses ranging from 100 mg to 3000 mg, rhabdomyolysis (defined as serum CK increase of more than ten times the baseline value with a concurrent 1.5-fold or greater increase in serum creatinine above baseline value) occurred in one patient (0.2%) treated with ODOMZO 800 mg.



 In Study 1, musculoskeletal adverse reactions occurred in 68% (54/79) of patients treated with ODOMZO 200 mg daily with 9% (7/79) reported as Grade 3 or 4. The most frequent manifestations of musculoskeletal adverse reactions reported as an adverse event were muscle spasms (54%), musculoskeletal pain (32%), and myalgia (19%). Increased serum CK laboratory values occurred in 61% (48/79) of patients with 8% (6/79) of patients having Grade 3 or 4 serum CK elevations. Musculoskeletal pain and myalgia usually preceded serum CK elevation. Among patients with Grade 2 or higher CK elevations, the median time to onset was 12.9 weeks (range: 2 to 39 weeks) and the median time to resolution (to &lt;= Grade 1) was 12 days (95% CI: 8 to 14 days). ODOMZO was temporarily interrupted in 8% of patients or permanently discontinued in 8% of patients for musculoskeletal adverse reactions. The incidence of musculoskeletal adverse reactions requiring medical intervention (magnesium supplementation, muscle relaxants, and analgesics or narcotics) was 29%, including four patients (5%) who received intravenous hydration or were hospitalized.



 Obtain baseline serum CK and creatinine levels prior to initiating ODOMZO, periodically during treatment, and as clinically indicated (e.g., if muscle symptoms are reported). Obtain serum creatinine and CK levels at least weekly in patients with musculoskeletal adverse reactions with concurrent serum CK elevation greater than 2.5 times ULN until resolution of clinical signs and symptoms. Depending on the severity of symptoms, temporary dose interruption or discontinuation may be required for musculoskeletal adverse reactions or serum CK elevation [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)]  . Advise patients starting therapy with ODOMZO of the risk of muscle-related adverse reactions. Advise patients to report promptly any new unexplained muscle pain, tenderness or weakness occurring during treatment or that persists after discontinuing ODOMZO.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
