<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ofirmev" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Hepatic Injury [ see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (  5.1  ) ] 
 *    Serious Skin Reactions [ see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (  5.2  ) ] 
 *    Allergy and Hypersensitivity [ see WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS (  5.4  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in patients treated with OFIRMEV were nausea, vomiting, headache, and insomnia in adult patients and nausea, vomiting, constipation, pruritus, agitation, and atelectasis in pediatric patients. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Mallinckrodt Hospital Products Inc. at 1-800-778-7898 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



       Adult Population    



 A total of 1020 adult patients have received OFIRMEV in clinical trials, including 37.3% (n=380) who received 5 or more doses, and 17.0% (n=173) who received more than 10 doses. Most patients were treated with OFIRMEV 1000 mg every 6 hours. A total of 13.1% (n=134) received OFIRMEV 650 mg every 4 hours.



 All adverse reactions that occurred in adult patients treated with either OFIRMEV or placebo in repeated dose, placebo-controlled clinical trials at an incidence &gt;= 3% and at a greater frequency than placebo are listed in Table 3. The most common adverse events in adult patients treated with OFIRMEV (incidence &gt;= 5% and greater than placebo) were nausea, vomiting, headache, and insomnia.



 Table 3. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring &gt;= 3% of OFIRMEV-treated Patients and at a greater frequency than Placebo in Placebo-Controlled, Repeated Dose Studies 
   System Organ Class - Preferred Term     OFIRMEV(N=402)n (%)     Placebo(N=379)n (%)    
   Gastrointestinal Disorders    Nausea    Vomiting     138 (34)62 (15)     119 (31)42 (11)    
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    Pyrexia*     22 (5)          52 (14)     
   Nervous System Disorders    Headache     39 (10)         33 (9)      
   Psychiatric Disorders    Insomnia     30 (7)          21 (5)      
          
 

     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Clinical Studies of OFIRMEV in Adults  



 *     The following additional treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported by adult subjects treated with OFIRMEV in all clinical trials (n=1020) that occurred with an incidence of at least 1% and at a frequency greater than placebo (n=525). 
 *      Blood and lymphatic system disorders : anemia 
 *      General disorders and administration site conditions : fatigue, infusion site pain, edema peripheral 
 *      Investigations : aspartate aminotransferase increased, breath sounds abnormal 
 *      Metabolism and nutrition disorders : hypokalemia 
 *      Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders : muscle spasms, trismus 
 *      Psychiatric disorders : anxiety 
 *      Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders : dyspnea 
 *      Vascular disorders : hypertension, hypotension 
          Pediatric Population    
 

 *     A total of 355 pediatric patients (47 neonates, 64 infants, 171 children, and 73 adolescents) have received OFIRMEV in active-controlled (n=250) and open-label clinical trials (n=225), including 59.7% (n=212) who received 5 or more doses and 43.1% (n=153) who received more than 10 doses. Pediatric patients received OFIRMEV doses up to 15 mg/kg on an every 4 hours, every 6 hours, or every 8 hours schedule. The maximum exposure was 7.7, 6.4, 6.8, and 7.1 days in neonates, infants, children, and adolescents, respectively. 
 *     The most common adverse events (incidence &gt;= 5%) in pediatric patients treated with OFIRMEV were nausea, vomiting, constipation, pruritus, agitation, and atelectasis. 
        Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Clinical Studies of OFIRMEV in Pediatrics  
 

 *     The following additional treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported by pediatric subjects treated with OFIRMEV (n=355) that occurred with an incidence of at least 1%. 
 *      Blood and lymphatic system disorders : anemia 
 *      Cardiac disorders : tachycardia 
 *      Gastrointestinal disorders : abdominal pain, diarrhea 
 *      General disorders and administration site conditions : injection site pain, edema peripheral, pyrexia 
 *      Investigations : hepatic enzyme increase 
 *      Metabolism and nutrition disorders : hypoalbuminemia, hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, hypophosphatemia, hypervolemia 
 *      Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders : muscle spasm, pain in extremity 
 *      Nervous system disorders : headache 
 *      Psychiatric disorders : insomnia 
 *      Renal and urinary disorders : oliguria 
 *      Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders : pulmonary edema, hypoxia, pleural effusion, stridor, wheezing 
 *      Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders : periorbital edema, rash 
 *      Vascular disorders : hypertension, hypotension 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: Risk of Medication Errors and Hepatotoxicity

  WARNING: Risk of Medication Errors and Hepatotoxicity

    Take care when prescribing, preparing, and administering OFIRMEV Injection to avoid dosing errors which could result in accidental overdose and death. In particular, be careful to ensure that:  



 *  the dose in milligrams (mg) and milliliters (mL) is not confused; 
 *  the dosing is based on weight for patients under 50 kg; 
 *  infusion pumps are properly programmed; and 
 *  the total daily dose of acetaminophen from all sources does not exceed maximum daily limits. 
       OFIRMEV contains acetaminophen. Acetaminophen has been associated with cases of acute liver failure, at times resulting in liver transplant and death. Most of the cases of liver injury are associated with the use of acetaminophen at doses that exceed the maximum daily limits, and often involve more than one acetaminophen-containing product   [see Warnings and Precautions   (      5.1    )]      .  
 

   EXCERPT:   WARNING: 



   RISK OF MEDICATION ERRORS AND HEPATOTOXICITY  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   Take care when prescribing, preparing, and administering OFIRMEV Injection to avoid dosing errors which could result in accidental overdose and death.  



   OFIRMEV contains acetaminophen.  Acetaminophen has been associated with cases of acute liver failure, at times resulting in liver transplant and death.  Most of the cases of liver injury are associated with the use of acetaminophen at doses that exceed the recommended maximum daily limits, and often involve more than one acetaminophen-containing product (  5.1  ).  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Administration of acetaminophen in doses higher than recommended (by all routes of administration and from all acetaminophen-containing products including combination products) may result in hepatic injury, including the risk of liver failure and death. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Do not exceed the maximum recommended daily dose of acetaminophen (by all routes of administration and all acetaminophen-containing products including combination products). (  5.1  ) 
 *    Take care when prescribing, preparing, and administering OFIRMEV injection to avoid dosing errors which could result in accidental overdose and death. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Use caution when administering acetaminophen in patients with the following conditions: hepatic impairment or active hepatic disease, in cases of alcoholism, chronic malnutrition, severe hypovolemia, or severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;= 30 mL/min). (  5.1  ) 
 *    Discontinue OFIRMEV immediately at the first appearance of skin rash and if symptoms associated with allergy or hypersensitivity occur. Do not use in patients with acetaminophen allergy. (  5.2  ,  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatic Injury



  Administration of acetaminophen in doses higher than recommended may result in hepatic injury, including the risk of liver failure and death [ see OVERDOSAGE (  10  )  ]. Do not exceed the maximum recommended daily dose of acetaminophen [ see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (  2  )  ]. The maximum recommended daily dose of acetaminophen includes all routes of acetaminophen administration and all acetaminophen-containing products administered, including combination products.



 Use caution when administering acetaminophen in patients with the following conditions: hepatic impairment or active hepatic disease, alcoholism, chronic malnutrition, severe hypovolemia (e.g., due to dehydration or blood loss), or severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;= 30 mL/min) [ see USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS (  8.6  ,  8.7  )  ].



    5.2 Serious Skin Reactions



  Rarely, acetaminophen may cause serious skin reactions such as acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis (AGEP), Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. Patients should be informed about the signs of serious skin reactions, and use of the drug should be discontinued at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity.



    5.3 Risk of Medication Errors



  Take care when prescribing, preparing, and administering OFIRMEV (acetaminophen) Injection in order to avoid dosing errors which could result in accidental overdose and death. In particular, be careful to ensure that:



 *    the dose in milligrams (mg) and milliliters (mL) is not confused; 
 *    the dosing is based on weight for patients under 50 kg; 
 *    infusion pumps are properly programmed; and 
 *    the total daily dose of acetaminophen from all sources does not exceed maximum daily limits [see DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (  2  )]. 
       5.4 Allergy and Hypersensitivity
 

  There have been post-marketing reports of hypersensitivity and anaphylaxis associated with the use of acetaminophen. Clinical signs included swelling of the face, mouth, and throat, respiratory distress, urticaria, rash, and pruritus. There were infrequent reports of life-threatening anaphylaxis requiring emergent medical attention. Discontinue OFIRMEV immediately if symptoms associated with allergy or hypersensitivity occur. Do not use OFIRMEV in patients with acetaminophen allergy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
