<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="omeprazole" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2%) are:



 Headache, abdominal pain, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, and flatulence (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Oceanside Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In the U.S. clinical trial population of 465 patients, the adverse reactions summarized in Table 2 were reported to occur in 1% or more of patients on therapy with omeprazole. Numbers in parentheses indicate percentages of the adverse reactions considered by investigators as possibly, probably or definitely related to the drug.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Occurring In 1% or More of Patients on Omeprazole Therapy 
                             Omeprazole  (n = 465)      Placebo  (n = 64)          Ranitidine  (n = 195)      
  Headache                   6.9 (2.4)                  6.3                        7.7 (2.6)                  
  Diarrhea                   3.0 (1.9)                  3.1 (1.6)                  2.1 (0.5)                  
  Abdominal Pain             2.4 (0.4)                  3.1                        2.1                        
  Nausea                     2.2 (0.9)                  3.1                        4.1 (0.5)                  
  URI                        1.9                        1.6                        2.6                        
  Dizziness                  1.5 (0.6)                  0.0                        2.6 (1.0)                  
  Vomiting                   1.5 (0.4)                  4.7                        1.5 (0.5)                  
  Rash                       1.5 (1.1)                  0.0                        0.0                        
  Constipation               1.1 (0.9)                  0.0                        0.0                        
  Cough                      1.1                        0.0                        1.5                        
  Asthenia                   1.1 (0.2)                  1.6 (1.6)                  1.5 (1.0)                  
  Back Pain                  1.1                        0.0                        0.5                        
          Table 3 summarizes the adverse reactions that occurred in 1% or more of omeprazole-treated patients from international double-blind, and open-label clinical trials in which 2,631 patients and subjects received omeprazole.
 

 Table 3: Incidence of Adverse Reactions &gt;=1% Causal Relationship not Assessed 
                                     Omeprazole  (n = 2631)             Placebo  (n = 120)                 
  Body as a Whole, site unspecified                                       
                                    Abdominal pain                    
                                                                        5.2                                3.3                                
                                    Asthenia                          
                                                                        1.3                                0.8                                
  Digestive System                                                                                         
                                    Constipation                      
                                                                        1.5                                0.8                                
                                    Diarrhea                          
                                                                        3.7                                2.5                                
                                    Flatulence                        
                                                                        2.7                                5.8                                
                                    Nausea                            
                                                                        4.0                                6.7                                
                                    Vomiting                          
                                                                        3.2                                10.0                               
                                    Acid regurgitation                
                                                                        1.9                                3.3                                
  Nervous System/Psychiatric                                                                               
                                    Headache                          
                                                                        2.9                                2.5                                
         A controlled clinical trial was conducted in 359 critically ill patients, comparing Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate 40 mg/1680 mg suspension once daily to I.V. cimetidine 1200 mg/day for up to 14 days. The incidence and total number of AEs experienced by &gt;=3% of patients in either group are presented in Table 4 by body system and preferred term.
 

 Table 4: Number (%) of Critically Ill Patients with Frequently Occurring (&gt;=3%) Adverse Events by Body System and Preferred Term 
                                         Omeprazole and  Sodium Bicarbonate(r)  (N=178)    Cimetidine  (N=181)                
  MedDRA                                                                                                    
  Body System                            All AEs                         All AEs                            
                                        Preferred Term                        
                                                                                n (%)                           n (%)                              
  BLOOD AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                       
                                        Anemia NOS                            
                                                                                14 (7.9)                        14 (7.7)                           
                                        Anemia NOS Aggravated                 
                                                                                4 (2.2)                         7 (3.9)                            
                                        Thrombocytopenia                      
                                                                                18 (10.1)                       11 (6.1)                           
  CARDIAC DISORDERS                                                                                         
                                        Atrial Fibrillation                   
                                                                                11 (6.2)                        7 (3.9)                            
                                        Bradycardia NOS                       
                                                                                7 (3.9)                         5 (2.8)                            
                                        Supraventricular Tachycardia          
                                                                                6 (3.4)                         2 (1.1)                            
                                        Tachycardia NOS                       
                                                                                6 (3.4)                         6 (3.3)                            
                                        Ventricular Tachycardia               
                                                                                8 (4.5)                         6 (3.3)                            
  GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERSClinically significant upper gastrointestinal bleeding was considered a serious adverse event but it is not included in this table.                                                                       
                                        Constipation                          
                                                                                8 (4.5)                         8 (4.4)                            
                                        Diarrhea NOS                          
                                                                                7 (3.9)                         15 (8.3)                           
                                        Gastric Hypomotility                  
                                                                                3 (1.7)                         6 (3.3)                            
  GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS                                                                       
                                        Hyperpyrexia                          
                                                                                8 (4.5)                         3 (1.7)                            
                                        Edema NOS                             
                                                                                5 (2.8)                         11 (6.1)                           
                                        Pyrexia                               
                                                                                36 (20.2)                       29 (16.0)                          
  INFECTIONS AND INFESTATIONS                                                                               
                                        Candidal Infection NOS                
                                                                                3 (1.7)                         7 (3.9)                            
                                        Oral Candidiasis                      
                                                                                7 (3.9)                         1 (0.6)                            
                                        Sepsis NOS                            
                                                                                9 (5.1)                         9 (5.0)                            
                                        Urinary Tract Infection NOS           
                                                                                4 (2.2)                         6 (3.3)                            
  INVESTIGATIONS                                                                                            
                                        Liver Function Tests NOS Abnormal     
                                                                                3 (1.7)                         6 (3.3)                            
  METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS                                                                        
                                        Fluid Overload                        
                                                                                9 (5.1)                         14 (7.7)                           
                                        Hyperglycaemia NOS                    
                                                                                19 (10.7)                       21 (11.6)                          
                                        Hyperkalaemia                         
                                                                                4 (2.2)                         6 (3.3)                            
                                        Hypernatraemia                        
                                                                                3 (1.7)                         9 (5.0)                            
                                        Hypocalcaemia                         
                                                                                11 (6.2)                        10 (5.5)                           
                                        Hypoglycaemia NOS                     
                                                                                6 (3.4)                         8 (4.4)                            
                                        Hypokalaemia                          
                                                                                22 (12.4)                       24 (13.3)                          
                                        Hypomagnesaemia                       
                                                                                18 (10.1)                       18 (9.9)                           
                                        Hyponatraemia                         
                                                                                7 (3.9)                         5 (2.8)                            
                                        Hypophosphataemia                     
                                                                                11 (6.2)                        7 (3.9)                            
  PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                                                                                     
                                        Agitation                             
                                                                                6 (3.4)                         16 (8.8)                           
  RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS                                                                       
                                        Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome   
                                                                                6 (3.4)                         7 (3.9)                            
                                        Nosocomial Pneumonia                  
                                                                                20 (11.2)                       17 (9.4)                           
                                        Pneumothorax NOS                      
                                                                                1 (0.6)                         8 (4.4)                            
                                        Respiratory Failure                   
                                                                                3 (1.7)                         6 (3.3)                            
  SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS                                                                       
                                        Decubitus Ulcer                       
                                                                                6 (3.4)                         5 (2.8)                            
                                        Rash NOS                              
                                                                                10 (5.6)                        11 (6.1)                           
  VASCULAR DISORDERS                                                                                        
                                        Hypertension NOS                      
                                                                                14 (7.9)                        6 (3.3)                            
                                        Hypotension NOS                       
                                                                                17 (9.6)                        12 (6.6)                           
  NOS = Not otherwise specified.         
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of omeprazole. Because these reactions are voluntarily reported from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their actual frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole:  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, anaphylactic shock, angioedema, bronchospasm, interstitial nephritis, urticaria (see also Skin below), fever, pain, fatigue, malaise.



   Cardiovascular:  Chest pain or angina, tachycardia, bradycardia, palpitation, elevated blood pressure, and peripheral edema.



   Gastrointestinal:  Pancreatitis (some fatal), anorexia, irritable colon, flatulence, fecal discoloration, esophageal candidiasis, mucosal atrophy of the tongue, dry mouth, stomatitis and abdominal swelling. During treatment with omeprazole, gastric fundic gland polyps have been noted rarely. These polyps are benign and appear to be reversible when treatment is discontinued. Gastroduodenal carcinoids have been reported in patients with Zollinger-Ellison syndrome on long-term treatment with omeprazole. This finding is believed to be a manifestation of the underlying condition, which is known to be associated with such tumors.



   Hepatic:  Mild and, rarely, marked elevations of liver function tests [ALT (SGPT), AST (SGOT), ?-glutamyl transpeptidase, alkaline phosphatase, and bilirubin (jaundice)]. In rare instances, overt liver disease has occurred, including hepatocellular, cholestatic, or mixed hepatitis, liver necrosis (some fatal), hepatic failure (some fatal), and hepatic encephalopathy.



   Infections and Infestations: Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea.



   Metabolism and Nutritional Disorders:  Hyponatremia, hypoglycemia, hypomagnesemia, and weight gain.



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle cramps, myalgia, muscle weakness, joint pain, bone fracture, and leg pain.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Psychic disturbances including depression, agitation, aggression, hallucinations, confusion, insomnia, nervousness, tremors, apathy, somnolence, anxiety, dream abnormalities; vertigo; paresthesia; and hemifacial dysesthesia.



   Respiratory:  Epistaxis, pharyngeal pain.



   Skin:  Severe generalized skin reactions including toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN; some fatal), Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and erythema multiforme (some severe); purpura and/or petechiae (some with rechallenge); skin inflammation, urticaria, angioedema, pruritus, photosensitivity, alopecia, dry skin, and hyperhidrosis.



   Special Senses:  Tinnitus, taste perversion.



   Ocular:  Blurred vision, ocular irritation, dry eye syndrome, optic atrophy, anterior ischemic optic neuropathy, optic neuritis and double vision.



   Urogenital:  Interstitial nephritis (some with positive rechallenge), urinary tract infection, microscopic pyuria, urinary frequency, elevated serum creatinine, proteinuria, hematuria, glycosuria, testicular pain, and gynecomastia.



   Hematologic:  Rare instances of pancytopenia, agranulocytosis (some fatal), thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, leucocytosis, and hemolytic anemia have been reported.



 The incidence of clinical adverse experiences in patients greater than 65 years of age was similar to that in patients 65 years of age or less.



 Additional adverse reactions that could be caused by sodium bicarbonate include metabolic alkalosis, seizures, and tetany.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Concomitant Gastric Malignancy: Symptomatic response to therapy with Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy (  5.1  ) 
 *    Atrophic Gastritis: Has been observed in gastric corpus biopsies from patients treated long-term with omeprazole (  5.2  ) 
 *    Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) Deficiency: Daily long-term use (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption or a deficiency of cyanocobalamin. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Buffer Content: contains sodium bicarbonate (  5.5  ) 
 *    PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Avoid concomitant use of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate with clopidogrel (  5.7  ) 
 *    Bone Fracture: Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs (  5.9  ) 
 *    Avoid concomitant use of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate with St John's Wort or rifampin due to the potential reduction in omeprazole concentrations (  5.10  ,  7.2  ) 
 *    Interactions with diagnostic investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors: Increases in intragastric pH may result in hypergastrinemia and enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia and increased Choromogranin A levels which may interfere with diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. (  5.11  ,  12.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Concomitant Gastric Malignancy



  Symptomatic response to therapy with omeprazole does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



    5.2 Atrophic Gastritis



  Atrophic gastritis has been noted occasionally in gastric corpus biopsies from patients treated long-term with omeprazole.



    5.3 Acute Interstitial Nephritis



  Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate. Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate if acute interstitial nephritis develops. [See  Contraindications (4)  ].  



    5.4 Cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) Deficiency



  Daily treatment with any acid-suppressing medications over a long period of time (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption of cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) caused by hypo- or achlorhydria. Rare reports of cyanocobalamin deficiency occurring with acid-suppressing therapy have been reported in the literature. This diagnosis should be considered if clinical symptoms consistent with cyanocobalamin deficiency are observed.



    5.5 Buffer Content



  Each Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate Capsule contains 1100 mg (13 mEq) of sodium bicarbonate. The total content of sodium in each capsule is 304 mg.



 Each packet of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate Powder for Oral Suspension contains 1680 mg (20 mEq) of sodium bicarbonate (equivalent to 460 mg of Na+).



 The sodium content of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate products should be taken into consideration when administering to patients on a sodium restricted diet.



 Because Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate products contain sodium bicarbonate, they should be used with caution in patients with Bartter's syndrome, hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, and problems with acid-base balance. Long-term administration of bicarbonate with calcium or milk can cause milk-alkali syndrome.



 Chronic use of sodium bicarbonate may lead to systemic alkalosis and increased sodium intake can produce edema and weight increase.



    5.6 Clostridium Difficile  Associated Diarrhea



  Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  



 Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.



    5.7 Interaction with Clopidogrel



  Avoid concomitant use of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate with clopidogrel. Clopidogrel is a prodrug. Inhibition of platelet aggregation by clopidogrel is entirely due to an active metabolite. The metabolism of clopidogrel to its active metabolite can be impaired by use with concomitant medications, such as omeprazole, that interfere with CYP2C19 activity. Concomitant use of clopidogrel with 80 mg omeprazole reduces the pharmacological activity of clopidogrel, even when administered 12 hours apart. When using Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate, consider alternative anti-platelet therapy. [See  Drug Interactions (7.5)  and  Pharmacokinetics (12.3)  ]  



    5.8 Bone Fracture



  Several published observational studies suggest that proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to the established treatment guidelines. [See  Dosage and Administration (2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  



    5.9 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), health care professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  



    5.10 Concomitant Use of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate with St John's Wort or Rifampin



  Drugs which induce CYP2C19 OR CYP34A (such as St John's Wort or rifampin) can substantially decrease omeprazole concentrations [See  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ].  Avoid concomitant use of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate with St John's Wort or rifampin.



    5.11 Interactions with Investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors



  Serum chromogranin A (CgA) levels increase secondary to drug-induced decreases in gastric acidity. The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. Providers should temporarily stop omeprazole treatment before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high. If serial tests are performed (e.g. for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary. [See  Pharmacodynamics (12.2)  ]  



    5.12 Concomitant Use of Omeprazole and Sodium Bicarbonate with Methotrexate



  Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients. [See  Drug Interactions (7.8)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
