<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="omnaris" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Adult and Adolescent Patients Aged 12 Years and Older:  



 In controlled clinical studies conducted in the US and Canada, a total of 1524 patients ages 12 years and older received treatment with ciclesonide administered intranasally. In studies of 2 to 6 weeks duration in patients 12 years and older, 546 patients were treated with OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg daily, and in a study of up to one year in duration, 441 patients were treated with OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg daily. The overall incidence of adverse events for patients treated with OMNARIS Nasal Spray was comparable to that in patients treated with placebo. Adverse events did not differ appreciably based on age, gender, or race. Approximately 2% of patients treated with OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg in clinical trials discontinued because of adverse events; this rate was similar for patients treated with placebo. Table 4 displays adverse events, irrespective of drug relationship, that occurred with an incidence of 2% or greater and more frequently with OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg than with placebo in clinical trials of 2 to 6 weeks in duration.



 Table 4 Adverse Events from Controlled Clinical Trials 2 to 6 Weeks in Duration in Patients 12 Years of Age and Older with Seasonal or Perennial Allergic Rhinitis 
 Adverse Event    OMNARIS Nasal Spray200 mcg Once Daily(N =546) %  Placebo(N = 544) %   
  
 Headache               6.0              4.6         
 Epistaxis              4.9              2.9         
 Nasopharyngitis        3.7              3.3         
 Ear Pain               2.2              0.6         
         In a 52-week long-term safety trial that included 663 adults and adolescent patients (441 treated with ciclesonide: 227 males and 436 females) with perennial allergic rhinitis, the adverse event profile over the treatment period was similar to the adverse event profile in trials of shorter duration. Adverse events considered likely or definitely related to OMNARIS Nasal Spray that were reported at an incidence of 1% or greater of patients and more commonly in OMNARIS Nasal Spray versus placebo were epistaxis, nasal discomfort, and headache. No patient experienced a nasal septal perforation or nasal ulcer during long-term use of OMNARIS Nasal Spray. While primarily designed to assess the long-term safety of OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg once daily, this 52-week trial demonstrated greater decreases in total nasal symptom scores with OMNARIS Nasal Spray versus placebo treated patients over the entire treatment period.
 

   Pediatric Patients Aged 6 to 11 Years:  



 Two controlled clinical studies 2 and 12 weeks in duration were conducted in the US and Canada and included a total of 1282 patients with allergic rhinitis ages 6 to 11 years, of which 913 were treated with OMNARIS (ciclesonide) Nasal Spray 200 mcg, 100 mcg or 25 mcg daily. The overall incidence of adverse events for patients treated with OMNARIS Nasal Spray was comparable to that in patients treated with placebo. Adverse events did not differ appreciably based on age, gender, or race. In clinical trials, 1.6% and 2.7% of patients treated with OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg or 100 mcg, respectively, discontinued because of adverse events; these rates were lower than the rate in patients treated with placebo (2.8%). Table 5 displays adverse events, irrespective of drug relationship, that occurred with an incidence of 3% or greater and more frequently with OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg than with placebo.



 Table 5 Adverse Events from Controlled Clinical Trials 2 to 12 Weeks in Duration in Patients 6 to 11 Years of Age and Older with Seasonal or Perennial Allergic Rhinitis 
 Adverse Event    OMNARIS Nasal Spray200 mcg Once Daily(N =380) %  Placebo(N = 369) %   
  
 Headache               6.6              5.7         
 Nasopharyngitis        6.6              5.4         
 Pharyngolaryngeal pain        3.4              3.3         
           Pediatric Patients Aged 2 to 5 Years:  
 

 Two controlled clinical studies 6 and 12 weeks in duration were conducted in the US and included a total of 258 patients 2 to 5 years of age with perennial allergic rhinitis, of which 183 were treated with OMNARIS Nasal Spray 200 mcg, 100 mcg or 25 mcg daily. The distribution of adverse events was similar to that seen in the 6 to 11 year old children.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
