<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="onivyde" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6          ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following adverse drug reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Severe Neutropenia [ see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)       and    Boxed Warning    ]  
 *  Severe Diarrhea [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)     and    Boxed Warning    ]  
 *  Interstitial Lung Disease [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]  
 *  Severe Hypersensitivity Reactions  [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 20%) of ONIVYDE: diarrhea, fatigue/asthenia, vomiting, nausea, decreased appetite, stomatitis, and pyrexia. The most common laboratory abnormalities (&gt;= 10% Grade 3 or 4) were lymphopenia and neutropenia. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merrimack Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-844-441-6225 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6.1          Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of ONIVYDE cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of other drugs and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety data described below are derived from patients with metastatic adenocarcinoma of the pancreas previously treated with gemcitabine-based therapy who received any part of protocol-specified therapy in Study 1, an international, randomized, active-controlled, open-label trial. Protocol-specified therapy consisted of ONIVYDE 70 mg/m  2  with leucovorin 400 mg/m  2  and fluorouracil 2400 mg/m  2  over 46 hours every 2 weeks (ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV; N=117), ONIVYDE 100 mg/m  2  every 3 weeks (N=147), or leucovorin 200 mg/m  2  and fluorouracil 2000 mg/m  2  over 24 hours weekly for 4 weeks followed by 2 week rest (5-FU/LV; N=134) [see     Clinical Studies (14)    ]. Serum bilirubin within the institutional normal range, albumin &gt;= 3 g/dL, and Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) &gt;= 70 were required for study entry. The median duration of exposure was 9 weeks in the ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV arm, 9 weeks in the ONIVYDE monotherapy arm, and 6 weeks in the 5-FU/LV arm.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 20%) of ONIVYDE were diarrhea, fatigue/asthenia, vomiting, nausea, decreased appetite, stomatitis, and pyrexia. The most common, severe laboratory abnormalities (&gt;= 10% Grade 3 or 4) were lymphopenia and neutropenia. The most common serious adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) of ONIVYDE were diarrhea, vomiting, neutropenic fever or neutropenic sepsis, nausea, pyrexia, sepsis, dehydration, septic shock, pneumonia, acute renal failure, and thrombocytopenia. 



 Adverse reactions led to permanent discontinuation     of ONIVYDE in 11% of patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV; the most frequent adverse reactions resulting in discontinuation of ONIVYDE were diarrhea, vomiting, and sepsis. Dose reductions of ONIVYDE for adverse reactions occurred in 33% of patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV; the most frequent adverse reactions requiring dose reductions were neutropenia, diarrhea, nausea, and anemia. ONIVYDE was withheld or delayed for adverse reactions in 62% of patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV; the most frequent adverse reactions requiring interruption or delays were neutropenia, diarrhea, fatigue, vomiting, and thrombocytopenia.



 Table 2 provides the frequency and severity of adverse reactions in Study 1 that occurred with higher incidence (&gt;=5% difference for Grades 1-4 or &gt;=2% difference for Grades 3-4) in patients who received ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV compared to patients who received 5-FU/LV. 



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions with Higher Incidence (&gt;=5% Difference for Grades 1-4 * or &gt;=2% Difference for Grades 3 and 4) in the ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV Arm  
   Adverse Reaction      ONIVYDE    /    5-FU/LV    N=117      5-FU/LV    N=134     
                    Grades 1-4    (%)      Grades 3    -    4    (%)      Grades 1-4    (%)      Grades 3    -    4    (%)     
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
   Diarrhea       59               13               26               4                 
      Early diarrhea      30               3                15               0                 
      Late diarrhea  ?    43               9                17               4                 
   Vomiting       52               11               26               3                 
   Nausea         51               8                34               4                 
   Stomatitis  S    32               4                12               1                 
   Infections and infestations    38               17               15               10                
   Sepsis         4                3                2                1                 
   Neutropenic fever/neutropenic  sepsis  ?    3                3                1                0                 
   Gastroenteritis  3                3                0                0                 
   Intravenous catheter-related  infection  3                3                0                0                 
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
   Fatigue/asthenia  56               21               43               10                
   Pyrexia        23               2                11               1                 
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders     
   Decreased appetite  44               4                32               2                 
   Weight loss    17               2                7                0                 
   Dehydration    8                4                7                2                 
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders     
   Alopecia       14               1                5                0                 
   *        NCI CTCAE v4.0          Early diarrhea: onset within 24 hours of ONIVYDE administration  ?        Late diarrhea: onset &gt;1 day after ONIVYDE administration  S        Includes stomatitis, aphthous stomatitis, mouth ulceration, mucosal inflammation.  ?        Includes febrile neutropenia   
             Cholinergic Reaction    s  : ONIVYDE can cause cholinergic reactions manifesting as rhinitis, increased salivation, flushing, bradycardia, miosis, lacrimation, diaphoresis, and intestinal hyperperistalsis with abdominal cramping and early onset diarrhea  .  In Study 1, Grade 1 or 2 cholinergic symptoms other than early diarrhea occurred in 12 (4.5%) ONIVYDE-treated patients. Six of these 12 patients received atropine and in 1 of the 6 patients, atropine was administered for cholinergic symptoms other than diarrhea.
 

   Infusion Reaction    s  : Infusion reactions, consisting of rash, urticaria, periorbital edema, or pruritus, occurring on the day of ONIVYDE administration were reported in 3% of patients receiving ONIVYDE or ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV.



 Laboratory abnormalities that occurred with higher incidence in the ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV arm compared to the 5-FU/LV arm (&gt;=5% difference) are summarized in the following table.



 Table 3: Laboratory Abnormalities with Higher Incidence (&gt;=5% Difference) in the ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV Arm *# 
   Laboratory abnormality      ONIVYDE    /5-FU/LV    N=117      5-FU/LV    N=134     
                    Grades 1-4    (%)      Grades 3    -    4    (%)      Grades 1-4    (%)      Grades 3    -    4    (%)     
   Hematology      
    Anemia        97               6                86               5                 
    Lymphopenia   81               27               75               17                
    Neutropenia   52               20               6                2                 
    Thrombocytopenia  41               2                33               0                 
   Hepatic         
    Increased alanine aminotransferase (ALT)  51               6                37               1                 
    Hypoalbuminemia  43               2                30               0                 
   Metabolic       
    Hypomagnesemia  35               0                21               0                 
    Hypokalemia   32               2                19               2                 
    Hypocalcemia  32               1                20               0                 
    Hypophosphatemia  29               4                18               1                 
    Hyponatremia  27               5                12               3                 
   Renal           
    Increased creatinine  18               0                13               0                 
   *  NCI CTCAE v4.0, worst grade shown.  #  Percent based on number of patients with a baseline and at least one post-baseline measurement.   
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SEVERE NEUTROPENIA AND SEVERE DIARRHEA 

    WARNING: SEVERE NEUTROPENIA AND SEVERE DIARRHEA   

    Fatal neutropenic sepsis occurred in 0.8% of patients receiving ONIVYDE. Severe or life-threatening neutropenic fever or sepsis occurred in 3% and severe or life-threatening neutropenia occurred in 20% of patients receiving ONIVYDE in combination with fluorouracil and leucovorin. Withhold ONIVYDE for absolute neutrophil count below 1500/mm3 or neutropenic fever. Monitor blood cell counts periodically during treatment [      see           Dosage and Administration (2.2)           and           Warnings and Precautions (5.1)          ]      .   



   Severe diarrhea occurred in 13% of patients receiving ONIVYDE in combination with fluorouracil and leucovorin. Do not administer ONIVYDE to patients with bowel obstruction. Withhold ONIVYDE for diarrhea of Grade 2-4 severity. Administer loperamide for late diarrhea of any severity. Administer atropine, if not contraindicated, for early diarrhea of any severity       [see           Dosage and Administration (2.2)           and           Warnings and Precautions (5.2)          ]      .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: SEVERE NEUTROPENIA AND SEVERE DIARRHEA  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning     



 *  Fatal neutropenic sepsis occurred in 0.8% of patients receiving ONIVYDE. Severe or life-threatening neutropenic fever or sepsis occurred in 3% and severe or life-threatening neutropenia occurred in 20% of patients receiving ONIVYDE in combination with fluorouracil and leucovorin. Withhold ONIVYDE for absolute neutrophil count below 1500/mm3 or neutropenic fever. Monitor blood cell counts periodically during treatment (2.2), (5.1). 
 *  Severe diarrhea occurred in 13% of patients receiving ONIVYDE in combination with fluorouracil and leucovorin. Do not administer ONIVYDE to patients with bowel obstruction. Withhold ONIVYDE for diarrhea of Grade 2-4 severity. Administer loperamide for late diarrhea of any severity. Administer atropine, if not contraindicated, for early diarrhea of any severity (2.2), (5.2). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5         WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Interstitial lung disease (ILD): Fatal ILD has occurred in patients receiving irinotecan HCl. Discontinue ONIVYDE if ILD is diagnosed. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Severe hypersensitivity reaction: Permanently discontinue ONIVYDE for severe hypersensitivity reactions. (  5.4  ,  4  ) 
 *  Embryo-fetal toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise females of reproductive potential of the potential risk to a fetus and to use effective contraception. (  5.5  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ) 
    
 

    5.1        Severe   Neutropenia  



  ONIVYDE can cause severe or life-threatening neutropenia and fatal neutropenic sepsis. In Study 1, the incidence of fatal neutropenic sepsis was 0.8% among patients receiving ONIVYDE, occurring in one of 117 patients in the ONIVYDE plus fluorouracil/leucovorin (ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV) arm and one of 147 patients receiving ONIVYDE as a single agent. Severe or life-threatening neutropenia occurred in 20% of patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV compared to 2% of patients receiving fluorouracil/leucovorin alone (5-FU/LV). Grade 3 or 4 neutropenic fever/neutropenic sepsis occurred in 3% of patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV, and did not occur in patients receiving 5-FU/LV.



 In patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV, the incidence of Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia was higher among Asian patients [18 of 33 (55%)] compared to White patients [13 of 73 (18%)]. Neutropenic fever/neutropenic sepsis was reported in 6% of Asian patients compared to 1% of White patients [see   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



 Monitor complete blood cell counts on Days 1 and 8 of every cycle and more frequently if clinically indicated. Withhold ONIVYDE if the absolute neutrophil count (ANC) is below 1500/mm  3  or if neutropenic fever occurs. Resume ONIVYDE when the ANC    is 1500/mm  3  or above. Reduce ONIVYDE dose for Grade 3-4 neutropenia or neutropenic fever following recovery in subsequent cycles [see   Dosage and Administration (2.2)    ].



     5.2        Severe   Diarrhea  



  ONIVYDE can cause severe and life-threatening diarrhea. Do not administer ONIVYDE to patients with bowel obstruction.



 Severe or life-threatening diarrhea followed one of two patterns: late onset diarrhea (onset more than 24 hours following chemotherapy) and early onset diarrhea (onset within 24 hours of chemotherapy, sometimes occurring with other symptoms of cholinergic reaction) [see   Cholinergic Reactions (6.1)    ]. An individual patient may experience both early and late-onset diarrhea.



 In Study 1, Grade 3 or 4 diarrhea occurred in 13% receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV compared to 4% receiving 5-FU/LV. The incidence of Grade 3 or 4 late onset diarrhea was 9% in patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV, compared to 4% in patients receiving 5-FU/LV. The incidence of Grade 3 or 4 early onset diarrhea was 3% in patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV, compared to no Grade 3 or 4 early onset diarrhea in patients receiving 5-FU/LV. Of patients receiving ONIVYDE/5-FU/LV in Study 1, 34% received loperamide for late-onset diarrhea and 26% received atropine for early-onset diarrhea. Withhold ONIVYDE for Grade 2-4 diarrhea. Initiate loperamide for late onset diarrhea of any severity. Administer intravenous or subcutaneous atropine 0.25 to 1 mg (unless clinically contraindicated) for early onset diarrhea of any severity. Following recovery to Grade 1 diarrhea, resume ONIVYDE at a reduced dose [see   Dosage and Administration (2.2)    ].



     5.   3        Interstitial Lung Disease  



  Irinotecan HCl can cause severe and fatal interstitial lung disease (ILD). Withhold ONIVYDE in patients with new or progressive dyspnea, cough, and fever, pending diagnostic evaluation. Discontinue ONIVYDE in patients with a confirmed diagnosis of ILD.



     5.   4         Severe Hypersensitivity   Reaction  



  Irinotecan HCl can cause severe hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic reactions. Permanently discontinue ONIVYDE in patients who experience a severe hypersensitivity reaction.



     5.   5         Embryo   -F   etal Toxicity  



  Based on animal data with irinotecan HCl and the mechanism of action of ONIVYDE, ONIVYDE can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Embryotoxicity and teratogenicity were observed following treatment with irinotecan HCl, at doses resulting in irinotecan exposures lower than those achieved with ONIVYDE 70 mg/m  2  in humans, administered to pregnant rats and rabbits during organogenesis. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment with ONIVYDE and for one month following the final dose [see Use in Specific Populations (     8.1    ,       8.3    ),    Clinical Pharmacology (12.1)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
