<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="opana" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Respiratory depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Misuse and abuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) and Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  
 *  CNS depressant effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions in &gt;=2% of  oxymorphone ER-treated patients in placebo-controlled trials:  nausea, constipation, dizziness, somnolence, vomiting, pruritus, headache, sweating increased, dry mouth, sedation, diarrhea, insomnia, fatigue, appetite decreased, and abdominal pain. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Endo Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-462-3636 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

    6.1   Clinical Trial Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of oxymorphone hydrochloride extended-release tablets was evaluated in a total of 2011 patients in controlled clinical trials.  The clinical trials consisted of patients with moderate to severe chronic non-malignant pain, cancer pain, and post surgical pain.



 Tables 1 and 2 list the most frequently occurring adverse reactions (in at least 5% of patients) from the placebo-controlled trials in patients with low back pain.  




  Table 1:Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients During the Open-Label Titration Period and Double-Blind Treatment Period by Preferred Term -Number (%) of Treated Patients (12-Week Study In Opioid-Naive Patients with Low Back Pain)    
                   Open-Label Titration Period    Double-Blind Treatment Period    
                   Oxymorphone Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets    Oxymorphone Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets    Placebo          
  Preferred Term    (N = 325)        (N = 105)        (N = 100)        
  Constipation     26%              7%               1%               
  Somnolence       19%              2%               0%               
  Nausea           18%              11%              9%               
  Dizziness        11%              5%               3%               
  Headache         11%              4%               2%               
  Pruritus         7%               3%               1%               
        
  Table 2. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients During the Open-Label Titration Period and Double-Blind Treatment Period by Preferred Term -Number (%) of Treated Patients (12-Week Study In Opioid-Experienced Patients with Low Back Pain)    
                   Open-Label Titration Period    Double-Blind Treatment Period    
                   Oxymorphone Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets    Oxymorphone Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets    Placebo          
  Preferred Term    (N = 250)        (N = 70)         (N = 72)         
  Nausea           20%              3%                  1%            
  Constipation     12%              6%                  1%            
  Headache         12%              3%                   0%           
  Somnolence       11%              3%                   0%           
  Vomiting           9%             0%                  1%            
  Pruritus           8%             0%                   0%           
  Dizziness          6%             0%                   0%           
          The following table lists adverse reactions that were reported in at least 2% of patients in placebo-controlled trials (N=5).
 


  Table 3: Adverse Reactions Reported in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials with Incidence &gt;=2% in Patients Receiving Oxymorphone Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets    
  MedDRA Preferred Term    Oxymorphone Hydrochloride Extended-Release Tablets  (N=1259)    Placebo (N=461)    
  Nausea           33%              13%              
  Constipation     28%              13%              
  Dizziness (Excl Vertigo)    18%              8%               
  Somnolence       17%              2%               
  Vomiting         16%              4%               
  Pruritus         15%              8%               
  Headache         12%              6%               
  Sweating increased    9%               9%               
  Dry mouth        6%               &lt;1%              
  Sedation         6%               8%               
  Diarrhea         4%               6%               
  Insomnia         4%               2%               
  Fatigue          4%               1%               
  Appetite decreased    3%               &lt;1%              
  Abdominal pain    3%               2%               
         The  common  (&gt;=1% to &lt;10%) adverse drug reactions reported at least once by patients treated with oxymorphone hydrochloride extended-release tablets in the clinical trials organized by MedDRA's (Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities) System Organ Class and not represented in Table 1:
 

   Eye disorders:  vision blurred  Gastrointestinal disorders:  diarrhea, abdominal pain, dyspepsia  General disorders and administration site conditions    :  dry mouth, appetite decreased, fatigue, lethargy,    weakness, pyrexia, dehydration, weight decreased, edema  Nervous system disorders:  insomnia   Psychiatric    disorders:  anxiety, confusion, disorientation, restlessness, nervousness, depression  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  dyspnea  Vascular disorders:  flushing and hypertension



 Other  less common  adverse reactions known with opioid treatment that were seen &lt;1% in the oxymorphone hydrochloride extended-release tablets trials include the following:



 Bradycardia, palpitation, syncope, tachycardia, postural hypotension, miosis, visual disturbance, abdominal distention, ileus, feeling jittery, hot flashes, allergic reactions, hypersensitivity, urticaria, oxygen saturation decreased, central nervous system depression, depressed level of consciousness, agitation, dysphoria, euphoric mood, hallucination, mental impairment, mental status changes, difficult micturition, urinary retention, hypoxia, respiratory depression, respiratory distress, respiratory rate decreased, clamminess, dermatitis, hypotension.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  POTENTIAL FOR ABUSE, IMPORTANCE OF PROPER PATIENT SELECTION AND LIMITATIONS OF USE

    WARNING:  POTENTIAL FOR ABUSE, IMPORTANCE OF PROPER PATIENT SELECTION AND LIMITATIONS OF USE  

    Potential for Abuse    OPANA ER contains oxymorphone, which is a morphine-like opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance, with an abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics. (  9  )  



   Oxymorphone can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing OPANA ER in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion. (  9.2  )  



   Proper Patient Selection    OPANA ER is an extended-release oral formulation of oxymorphone indicated for the management of moderate to severe pain when a continuous, around-the-clock opioid analgesic is needed for an extended period of time. (  1  )  



   Limitations of Use    OPANA ER is NOT intended for use as an as needed analgesic. (  1  )  



   OPANA ER     tablets are to be swallowed whole and are not to be cut, broken, chewed, dissolved, or crushed. Taking cut, broken, chewed, dissolved, or crushed OPANA ER tablets leads to rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of oxymorphone. (  2  )  



   Patients must not consume alcoholic beverages, or prescription or non-prescription medications containing alcohol, while on OPANA ER therapy.  The co-ingestion of alcohol with OPANA ER may result in increased plasma levels and a potentially fatal overdose of oxymorphone. (  2   )  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:  POTENTIAL FOR ABUSE, IMPORTANCE OF PROPER PATIENT SELECTION AND LIMITATIONS OF USE      See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  OPANA ER contains oxymorphone which is an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics. (9) 
 *  Oxymorphone can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit.  This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing OPANA ER in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion. (9) 
 *  OPANA ER is NOT intended for use as an as needed analgesic. (1) 
 *  OPANA ER tablets are to be swallowed whole and are not to be cut, broken, chewed, dissolved, or crushed as this leads to rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of oxymorphone. (2) 
 *  Patients must not consume alcoholic beverages, prescription or non-prescription medications containing alcohol. Co-ingestion of alcohol with OPANA ER may result in a potentially fatal overdose of oxymorphone. (2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



  EXCERPT:    See Boxed WARNINGS  



 *  Respiratory depression:  Increased risk in elderly, debilitated patients, and those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or decreased respiratory reserve. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Misuse, abuse, and diversion: OPANA ER is an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to morphine. (  5.3  ) 
 *  CNS effects: Additive CNS-depressive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Head Injury: Effects may be markedly exaggerated. Administer OPANA ER with extreme caution. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hypotensive effect: Increased risk with compromised ability to maintain blood pressure. Administer with caution to patients in circulatory shock. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Mild hepatic impairment: Use with caution and at lower doses due to higher plasma concentrations than in patients with normal hepatic function. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Prolonged gastric obstruction: May occur in patients with gastrointestinal obstruction. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Sphincter of Oddi: Administer with caution in patients with biliary tract disease. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Impaired mental/physical abilities: Caution must be used with potentially hazardous activities. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

    5.1   Information Essential for Safe Administration  



   OPANA ER tablets are to be swallowed whole, and are not to be cut, broken, chewed, crushed or dissolved. Taking cut, broken, chewed, dissolved, or crushed OPANA ER tablets could lead to the rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of oxymorphone [see  Boxed Warning  ]  .      



  Patients must not consume alcoholic beverages, or prescription or non-prescription medications containing alcohol, while on OPANA ER therapy.  The co-ingestion of alcohol with OPANA ER may result in increased plasma levels and a potentially fatal overdose of oxymorphone [see Pharmacokinetics (  12.3  )]  .  



  Instruct patients against use by individuals other than the patient for whom OPANA ER was prescribed, as such inappropriate use may have severe medical consequences, including death.  



     5.2   Respiratory Depression  



  Respiratory depression is the chief hazard of OPANA ER.  Respiratory depression is a potential problem in elderly or debilitated patients as well as in those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia or hypercapnia when even moderate therapeutic doses may dangerously decrease pulmonary ventilation.



 Administer OPANA ER with extreme caution to patients with conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or decreased respiratory reserve such as: asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, severe obesity, sleep apnea syndrome, myxedema, kyphoscoliosis, CNS depression or coma.  In these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of oxymorphone may decrease respiratory drive while simultaneously increasing airway resistance to the point of apnea.  Consider alternative non-opioid analgesics and use OPANA ER only under careful medical supervision at the lowest effective dose in such patients.



     5.3    Misuse, Abuse and Diversion of Opioids  



  OPANA ER contains oxymorphone, a mu opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to morphine.  Opioid agonists are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion.



 Oxymorphone can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. This issue should be considered when prescribing or dispensing oxymorphone in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion.



 OPANA ER tablets may be abused by crushing, chewing, snorting or injecting the product.  These practices will result in the less controlled delivery of the opioid and pose a significant risk to the abuser that could result in overdose and death [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  .



 OPANA ER may be targeted for theft and diversion.  Healthcare professionals should contact their State Medical Board, State Board of Pharmacy, or State Control Board for information on how to detect or prevent diversion of this product, and security requirements for storing and handling of OPANA ER.



 Healthcare professionals should advise patients to store OPANA ER in a secure place, preferably locked and out of the reach of children and other non-caregivers.



 Concerns about abuse, misuse, diversion and addiction should not prevent the proper management of pain.



     5.4   Interactions with Alcohol and other CNS Depressants  



  Patients receiving other opioid analgesics, general anesthetics, phenothiazines or other tranquilizers, sedatives, hypnotics, or other CNS depressants (including alcohol) concomitantly with oxymorphone may experience respiratory depression, hypotension, profound sedation, coma and death [see Drug Interactions(  7.2  )]  .  Avoid concurrent use of alcohol and OPANA ER [see Pharmacokinetics (  12.3  )]  .



     5.5  Use in Patients with Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure  



  In the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a preexisting increase in intracranial pressure, the possible respiratory depressant effects of opioid analgesics and their potential to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2 retention) may be markedly exaggerated.  Furthermore, opioid analgesics can produce effects on papillary response and consciousness, which may obscure neurologic signs of further increases in intracranial pressure in patients with head injuries.



 Administer OPANA ER with extreme caution to patients who may be particularly susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2 retention, such as those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or impaired consciousness. Opioids may obscure the clinical course of a patient with a head injury and should be used only if clinically warranted.



     5.6   Hypotensive Effect  



  OPANA ER may cause severe hypotension in a patient whose ability to maintain blood pressure has been compromised by a depleted blood volume, or after concurrent administration with drugs such as phenothiazines or other agents that compromise vasomotor tone.  Administer OPANA ER with caution to patients in circulatory shock, since vasodilation produced by the drug may further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure.



     5.7   Hepatic Impairment  



  A study of oxymorphone hydrochloride extended-release tablets in patients with hepatic disease indicated greater plasma concentrations than those with normal hepatic function [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12  )]  .  Use OPANA ER with caution in patients with mild impairment, starting with the lowest dose and titrating slowly while carefully monitoring for side effects [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )]  . OPANA ER is contraindicated in patients with moderate or severe hepatic impairment.



     5.8   Special Risk Groups  



  Use OPANA ER with caution in the following conditions: adrenocortical insufficiency (e.g., Addison"s disease), prostatic hypertrophy or urethral stricture, severe impairment of pulmonary or renal function, and toxic psychosis.



 Opioids may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings.



     5.9    Gastrointestinal Effects  



  OPANA ER decreases bowel motility. Opioids diminish propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract. Monitor for decreased bowel motility in post-operative patients receiving opioids. The administration of OPANA ER may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal conditions. OPANA ER is contraindicated in patients with paralytic ileus.



     5.10   Ambulatory Surgery and Post-Operative Use  



  OPANA ER is not indicated for pre-emptive analgesia (administration pre-operatively for the management of post-operative pain).



 OPANA ER is only indicated for postoperative use in the patient if the patient is already receiving the drug prior to surgery or if the postoperative pain is expected to be moderate to severe and persist for an extended period of time.  Physicians should individualize treatment, moving from parenteral to oral analgesics as appropriate (see American Pain Society Guidelines).



 Patients who are already receiving OPANA ER as part of ongoing analgesic therapy may be safely continued on the drug if appropriate dosage adjustments are made considering the procedure, other drugs given, and the temporary changes in physiology caused by the surgical intervention.



     5.11   Use in Pancreatic/Biliary Tract Disease  



  OPANA ER, like other opioids, may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and should be used with caution in patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis.



     5.12   Driving and Operating Machinery  



  Opioid analgesics, including OPANA ER, may impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
