<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="opana1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Respiratory depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Misuse and abuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) and Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  
 *  CNS depressant effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.
 

   EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions (&gt;=2% of patients): Nausea, pyrexia, somnolence, vomiting, pruritus, headache, dizziness, constipation, and confusion. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Endo Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-462-3636 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch      .  



 

    6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  

  A total of 591 patients were treated with OPANA in controlled clinical trials. The clinical trials consisted of patients with acute post-operative pain (n=557) and cancer pain (n=34) trials.



 The following table lists adverse reactions that were reported in at least 2% of patients receiving OPANA in placebo-controlled trials (acute post-operative pain (N=557)).



   Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Placebo-Controlled Trials  




    MedDRA Preferred Term       OPANA (N=557)       Placebo (N=270)     
  Nausea           19%              12%              
  Pyrexia          14%              8%               
  Somnolence       9%               2%               
  Vomiting         9%               7%               
  Pruritus         8%               4%               
  Headache         7%               4%               
  Dizziness (ExcudingVertigo)   7%               2%               
  Constipation     4%               1%               
  Confusion        3%               &lt;1%              
         The  common  (&gt;=1% - &gt;10%) adverse drug reactions reported at least once by patients treated with OPANA in the clinical trials organized by MedDRA's (Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities) System Organ Class were and not represented in Table 1:
 

        Cardiac disorders:  tachycardia       Gastrointestinal disorders:  dry mouth, abdominal distention, and flatulence       General disorders and administration site conditions:  sweating increased       Nervous system disorders:  anxiety and sedation       Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  hypoxia       Vascular disorders:  hypotension



 Other  less common  adverse reactions known with opioid treatment that were seen &lt;1% in the OPANA trials includes the following:Abdominal pain, ileus, diarrhea, agitation, disorientation, restlessness, feeling jittery, hypersensitivity, allergic reactions, bradycardia, central nervous system depression, depressed level of consciousness, lethargy, mental impairment, mental status changes, fatigue, depression, clamminess, flushing, hot flashes, dehydration, dermatitis, dyspepsia, dysphoria, edema, euphoric mood, hallucination, hypertension, insomnia, miosis, nervousness, palpitation, postural hypotension, syncope, dyspnea, respiratory depression, respiratory distress, respiratory rate decreased, oxygen saturation decreased, difficult micturition, urinary retention, urticaria, vision blurred, visual disturbances, weakness, appetite decreased, and weight decreased.



     6.2  Post-marketing Experience  

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of OPANA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Nervous system disorder:   amnesia, convulsion, memory impairment
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Respiratory depression: Increased risk in elderly, debilitated patients, and those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or decreased respiratory reserve. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Misuse, abuse, and diversion: OPANA is an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to morphine. (  5.2  ) 
 *  CNS effects: Additive CNS-depressive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Head injury: Effects may be markedly exaggerated. Administer with extreme caution. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hypotensive effect: Increased risk with compromised ability to maintain blood pressure. Administer with caution to patients in circulatory shock. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Mild hepatic impairment: Use with caution and at lower doses due to higher plasma concentrations than in patients with normal hepatic function (  5.6  ) 
 *  Prolonged gastric obstruction: May occur in patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, especially paralytic ileus. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Sphincter of Oddi: Administer with caution in patients with biliary tract disease. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Impaired mental/physical abilities: Caution must be used with potentially hazardous activities. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

    5.1 Respiratory Depression  



  Respiratory depression is the chief hazard of OPANA. Respiratory depression may occur more frequently in elderly or debilitated patients as well as in those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia or hypercapnia, when even moderate therapeutic doses may dangerously decrease pulmonary ventilation.



 Administer OPANA with extreme caution to patients with conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or decreased respiratory reserve such as: asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, severe obesity, sleep apnea syndrome, myxedema, kyphoscoliosis, CNS depression, or coma. In these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of oxymorphone may decrease respiratory drive while simultaneously increasing airway resistance to the point of apnea. Consider alternative non-opioid analgesics and use OPANA only under careful medical supervision at the lowest effective dose in such patients.



     5.2 Misuse, Abuse, and Diversion of Opioids  



  OPANA contains oxymorphone, a mu opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to morphine. Opioid agonists are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion.



 Oxymorphone can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. This issue should be considered when prescribing or dispensing oxymorphone in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion.



 OPANA tablets may be abused by crushing, chewing, snorting, or injecting the product. These practices pose a significant risk to the abuser that could result in overdose and death [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  .



 OPANA may be targeted for theft and diversion. Healthcare professionals should contact their State Medical Board, State Board of Pharmacy, or State Control Board for information on how to detect or prevent diversion of this product, and security requirements for storing and handling of OPANA.



 Healthcare professionals should advise patients to store OPANA in a secure place, preferably locked and out of the reach of children and other non-caregivers.



 Concerns about abuse, misuse, diversion and addiction should not prevent the proper management of pain.



     5.3 Additive CNS Depressant Effects  



  The concomitant use of other CNS depressants including other opioids, general anesthetics, phenothiazines, other tranquilizers, sedatives, hypnotics, and alcohol with oxymorphone may produce increased depressant effects including hypoventilation, hypotension, profound sedation, coma and death [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



     5.4 Use in Patients with Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure  



  In the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a preexisting increase in intracranial pressure, the respiratory depressant effects of opioid analgesics and their potential to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2retention) may be markedly exaggerated. Furthermore, opioid analgesics can produce effects on papillary response and consciousness, which may obscure neurologic signs of further increases in intracranial pressure in patients with head injuries.



 Administer OPANA with extreme caution in patients who may be particularly susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention, such as those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or impaired consciousness. Opioids may obscure the clinical course of a patient with a head injury and should be used only if clinically warranted.



     5.5 Hypotensive Effect  



  OPANA, like all opioid analgesics, may cause severe hypotension in a patient whose ability to maintain blood pressure has been compromised by a depleted blood volume, or after concurrent administration with drugs such as phenothiazines or other agents that compromise vasomotor tone. Administer OPANA with caution to patients in circulatory shock, since vasodilation produced by the drug may further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure.



     5.6 Hepatic Impairment  



  A study of extended-release oxymorphone tablets in patients with hepatic disease indicated greater plasma concentrations than in those with normal hepatic function [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )  ]. Use OPANA with caution in patients with mild impairment, starting with the lowest dose and titrating slowly while carefully monitoring for side effects [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  ,  2.5  )]  . OPANA is contraindicated in patients with moderate or severe hepatic impairment.



     5.7 Special Risk Groups  



  Use OPANA with caution in the following conditions: adrenocortical insufficiency (e.g., Addison's disease), prostatic hypertrophy or urethral stricture, severe impairment of pulmonary or renal function, and toxic psychosis.



 Opioids may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings.



     5.8 Gastrointestinal Effects  



  Opioids diminish propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract. Monitor for decreased bowel motility in post-operative patients receiving opioids. The administration of OPANA may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal conditions. OPANA is contraindicated in patients with paralytic ileus.



     5.9 Use in Pancreatic/Biliary Tract Disease  



  OPANA, like other opioids, may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and should be used with caution in patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis.



     5.10 Driving and Operating Machinery  



  Opioid analgesics impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
