<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="optiray1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions following the use of Optiray formulations are usually mild to moderate, of short duration and resolve spontaneously (without treatment). However, serious, life-threatening and fatal reactions, mostly of cardiovascular origin, have been associated with the administration of iodine-containing contrast media.



 Injections of contrast media are often associated with sensations of warmth and pain. In controlled double-blind clinical studies, significantly less warmth and pain were associated with the injection of Optiray than with iothalamate meglumine, diatrizoate meglumine, and diatrizoate meglumine and diatrizoate sodium.



 When Optiray was used for coronary arteriography and ventriculography in double-blind clinical trials, electrocardiographic and hemodynamic changes occurred with less frequency and severity with ioversol injection than with diatrizoate meglumine and diatrizoate sodium.



 Following coronary artery and left ventricular injection, electro-cardiographic parameters were affected less with Optiray (ioversol injection) than with diatrizoate meglumine and diatrizoate sodium injection. These parameters included the following: bradycardia, tachycardia, T-wave amplitude, ST depression and ST elevation.



 Optiray has also been shown to cause fewer changes in cardiac function and systemic blood pressure than conventional ionic media. These include cardiac output, left ventricular systolic and end-diastolic pressure, right ventricular systolic and pulmonary artery systolic pressures and decreases in systolic and diastolic blood pressures.



 The following table of incidence of reactions is based upon clinical trials with Optiray formulations in 2,098 patients. This listing includes all adverse reactions which were coincidental to the administration of ioversol regardless of their direct attributability to the drug or the procedure. Adverse reactions are listed by organ system and in decreasing order of occurrence. Significantly more severe reactions are listed before others in a system regardless of frequency.




  Adverse Reactions                   
  System                              &gt;1%                                    &lt;=1%                         
  Cardiovascular                      none                                   angina pectoris              
  hypotension                         
  blood pressure fluctuation          
  arterial spasm                      
  bradycardia                         
  conduction defect                   
  false aneurysm                      
  hypertension                        
  transient arrhythmia                
  vascular trauma                     
  Digestive                           nausea (1.2)                           vomiting                     
  dry mouth                           
  Nervous                             headache (1.1)                         cerebral infarct             
  blurred vision                      
  vertigo                             
  lightheadedness                     
  visual hallucination                
  vasovagal reaction                  
  disorientation                      
  paresthesia                         
  dysphasia                           
  muscle spasm                        
  syncope                             
  Respiratory                         none                                   laryngeal edema              
  pulmonary edema                     
  sneezing                            
  congestion                          
  coughing                            
  shortness of breath                 
  hypoxia                             
  Skin                                none                                   periorbital edema            
  urticaria                           
  pruritus                            
  facial edema                        
  flush                               
  erythema                            
  Miscellaneous                       none                                   extravasation                
  hematoma                            
  shaking chills                      
  bad taste                           
  general pain                        
  renal colic                         
  fever                               
  polyuria                            
  urinary retention                   
         Regardless of the contrast medium employed, the overall incidence of serious adverse reaction is higher with coronary arteriography than with other procedures. Cardiac decompensation, serious arrhythmias, myocardial ischemia or myocardial infarction may occur during coronary arteriography and left ventriculography.
 

   Pediatrics

  In controlled clinical trials involving 159 patients for pediatric angiocardiography, contrast enhanced computed tomographic imaging of the head and body, and intravenous excretory urography, adverse reactions reported were as follows: fever (1.3%), nausea (0.6%), muscle spasm (0.6%), LV pressure changes (0.6%).



   General Adverse Reactions to Contrast Media

  The following adverse reactions are possible with any parenterally administered iodinated contrast medium. Severe life-threatening reactions and fatalities, mostly of cardiovascular origin, have occurred. Most deaths occur during injection or 5 to 10 minutes later; the main feature being cardiac arrest with cardiovascular disease as the main aggravating factor. Isolated reports of hypotensive collapse and shock are found in the literature. Based upon clinical literature, reported deaths from the administration of conventional iodinated contrast agents range from 6.6 per 1 million (0.00066 percent) to 1 in 10,000 patients (0.01 percent).



 The reported incidence of adverse reactions to contrast media in patients with a history of allergy is twice that of the general population. Patients with a history of previous reactions to a contrast medium are three times more susceptible than other patients. However, sensitivity to contrast media does not appear to increase with repeated examinations.



 Adverse reactions to injectable contrast media fall into two categories: chemotoxic reactions and idiosyncratic reactions.



 Chemotoxic reactions result from the physiochemical properties of the contrast medium, the dose and the speed of injection. All hemodynamic disturbances and injuries to organs or vessels perfused by the contrast medium are included in this category.



 Idiosyncratic reactions include all other reactions. They occur more frequently in patients 20 to 40 years old. Idiosyncratic reactions may or may not be dependent on the dose injected, the speed of injection, the mode of injection and the radiographic procedure. Idiosyncratic reactions are subdivided into minor, intermediate and severe. The minor reactions are self-limited and of short duration; the severe reactions are life-threatening and treatment is urgent and mandatory.



 In addition to the adverse reactions reported for ioversol, the following additional adverse reactions have been reported with the use of other contrast agents and are possible with any water soluble, iodinated contrast agent.



   Nervous:  convulsions, aphasia, paralysis, visual field losses which are usually transient but may be permanent, coma and death.



   Cardiovascular:  angioneurotic edema, peripheral edema, vasodilation, thrombosis and rarely thrombophlebitis, disseminated intravascular coagulation and shock.



   Skin:  maculopapular rash, erythema, conjunctival symptoms, ecchymosis and tissue necrosis.



   Respiratory:  choking, dyspnea, wheezing which may be an initial manifestation of more severe and infrequent reactions including asthmatic attack, laryngospasm and bronchospasm, apnea and cyanosis. Rarely these allergic-type reactions can progress into anaphylaxis with loss of consciousness, coma, severe cardiovascular disturbances and death.



   Endocrine:  Thyroid function tests indicative of hypothyroidism or transient thyroid suppression have been uncommonly reported following iodinated contrast media administration to adult and pediatric patients, including infants. Some patients were treated for hypothyroidism.



   Miscellaneous:  hyperthermia, temporary anuria or other nephropathy.



 Other reactions may also occur with the use of any contrast agent as a consequence of the procedural hazard; these include hemorrhage or pseudoaneurysms at the puncture site, brachial plexus palsy following axillary artery injections, chest pain, myocardial infarction, and transient changes in hepatorenal chemistry tests. Arterial thrombosis, displacement of arterial plaques, venous thrombosis, dissection of the coronary vessels and transient sinus arrest are rare complications.



 (Adverse reactions for specific procedures receive comment in the Indications, Usage and Procedural Information section.)
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    WARNING  



   NOT FOR INTRATHECAL USE  



 





    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS

  WARNINGS

    SEVERE ADVERSE EVENTS - INADVERTENT INTRATHECAL ADMINISTRATION:   Serious adverse reactions have been reported due to the inadvertent intrathecal administration of iodinated contrast media that are not indicated for intrathecal use. These serious adverse reactions include: death, convulsions, cerebral hemorrhage, coma, paralysis, arachnoiditis, acute renal failure, cardiac arrest, seizures, rhabdomyolysis, hyperthermia, and brain edema. Special attention must be given to ensure that this drug product is not administered intrathecally.



 Nonionic iodinated contrast media inhibit blood coagulation, in vitro, less than ionic contrast media. Clotting has been reported when blood remains in contact with syringes containing nonionic contrast media.



 Serious, rarely fatal, thromboembolic events causing myocardial infarction and stroke have been reported during angiographic procedures with both ionic and nonionic contrast media. Therefore, meticulous intravascular administration technique is necessary, particularly during angiographic procedures, to minimize thromboembolic events. Numerous factors, including length of procedure, catheter and syringe material, underlying disease state, and concomitant medications may contribute to the development of thromboembolic events. For these reasons, meticulous angiographic techniques are recommended including close attention to guidewire and catheter manipulation, use of manifold systems and/or three-way stopcocks, frequent catheter flushing with heparinized saline solutions and minimizing the length of the procedure. The use of plastic syringes in place of glass syringes has been reported to decrease but not eliminate the likelihood of in vitro clotting.



 Serious or fatal reactions have been associated with the administration of iodine-containing radiopaque media. It is of utmost importance to be completely prepared to treat any contrast medium reaction.



 As with any contrast medium, serious neurologic sequelae, including permanent paralysis, can occur following cerebral arteriography, selective spinal arteriography and arteriography of vessels supplying the spinal cord. A cause-effect relationship to the contrast medium has not been established since the patients' pre-existing condition and procedural technique are causative factors in themselves. The arterial injection of a contrast medium should never be made following the administration of vasopressors since they strongly potentiate neurologic effects.



 Caution must be exercised in patients with severely impaired renal function, combined renal and hepatic disease, severe thyrotoxicosis, myelomatosis, or anuria, particularly when large doses are administered.



 Intravascularly administered iodine-containing radiopaque media are potentially hazardous in patients with multiple myeloma or other paraproteinemia, particularly in those with therapeutically resistant anuria. Myeloma occurs most commonly in persons over age 40. Although neither the contrast agent nor dehydration has been proved separately to be the cause of anuria in myelomatous patients, it has been speculated that the combination of both may be causative. The risk in myelomatous patients is not a contraindication to the procedure; however, special precautions, including maintenance of normal hydration and close monitoring, are required. Partial dehydration in the preparation of these patients prior to injection is not recommended since this may predispose the patient to precipitation of the myeloma protein.



 Administration of radiopaque materials to patients known or suspected of having pheochromocytoma should be performed with extreme caution. If, in the opinion of the physician, the possible benefits of such procedures outweigh the considered risks, the procedures may be performed; however, the amount of radiopaque medium injected should be kept to an absolute minimum. The blood pressure should be assessed throughout the procedure, and measures for treatment of a hypertensive crisis should be available.



 Contrast media may promote sickling in individuals who are homozygous for sickle cell disease when administered intravascularly.



 Reports of thyroid storm following the intravascular use of iodinated radiopaque agents in patients with hyperthyroidism or with an autonomously functioning thyroid nodule, suggest that this additional risk be evaluated in such patients before use of any contrast medium.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
