<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="optimark2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *  Nephrogenic Systemic Fibrosis [see Contraindications (4), Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions [see Contraindications (4) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;2%) are: headache, vasodilatation, taste perversion, dizziness, nausea and paresthesia. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS contact Mallinckrodt Inc. at 1-888-744-1414 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The adverse reactions described in this section were observed in a total of 1,309 subjects (24 healthy volunteers and 1,285 patients in clinical trials). Patients ranged in age from 12 to 85 years (mean age of 50 years) and 680 subjects (52%) were men. The ethnic distribution was 84% White, 9% Black, 3% Asian, and 4% other.



 Overall, 460 subjects (35%) reported at least one adverse reaction. Most adverse reactions were mild or moderate in severity. The most commonly noted adverse reactions were: injection associated discomfort (26%), headache (9.4%), vasodilatation (6.4%), taste perversion (6.2%), dizziness (3.7%), nausea (3.2%), and paresthesia (2.2%). Table 2 lists adverse reactions reported in 1% or greater of patients.




  Table 2   Adverse Reactions Experienced by &gt;=1% of Patients                                                                                                                                        
  Body System or Event                                                                                                                                                                               Optimark (N = 1309)                                                                                                                          
  Injection associated discomfort                                                                                                                                                                    26.4%                                                                                                                                        
  Headache                                                                                                                                                                                           9.4%                                                                                                                                         
  Vasodilatation                                                                                                                                                                                     6.4%                                                                                                                                         
  Taste Perversion                                                                                                                                                                                   6.2%                                                                                                                                         
  Dizziness                                                                                                                                                                                          3.7%                                                                                                                                         
  Nausea                                                                                                                                                                                             3.2%                                                                                                                                         
  Paresthesia                                                                                                                                                                                        2.2%                                                                                                                                         
  Diarrhea                                                                                                                                                                                           1.9%                                                                                                                                         
  Pain Abdomen                                                                                                                                                                                       1.8%                                                                                                                                         
  Asthenia                                                                                                                                                                                           1.5%                                                                                                                                         
  Injection Site Reaction                                                                                                                                                                            1.5%                                                                                                                                         
  Rhinitis                                                                                                                                                                                           1.5%                                                                                                                                         
  Dyspepsia                                                                                                                                                                                          1.2%                                                                                                                                         
  Pain Back                                                                                                                                                                                          1.2%                                                                                                                                         
  Pain                                                                                                                                                                                               1.0%                                                                                                                                         
        The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 1% of the patients:
 

   Body as a Whole  :             allergic reaction, facial edema, fever, malaise, neck rigidity, neck pain, pelvic pain, increased sweating



   Cardiovascular  :                arrhythmia, chest pain, hypertension, hypotension, pallor, palpitation, syncope, tachycardia, vasospasm



   Digestive  :                        anorexia, constipation, dry mouth, dysphagia, eructation, increased salivation, thirst, vomiting



   Metabolic and Nutritional  : increased creatinine, edema, hypercalcemia



   Musculoskeletal  :              arthralgia, leg cramps, myalgia, spasm



   Nervous System  :              agitation, anxiety, confusion, diplopia, dystonia, hypertonia, hypesthesia, somnolence, tremor, vertigo



   Respiratory System  :         cough, dyspnea, laryngismus, pharyngitis, sinusitis, voice alteration



   Skin and Appendages  :     erythema multiforme, pruritus, rash, thrombophlebitis, urticaria



   Special Senses  :               parosmia, tinnitus



   Urogenital  :                       oliguria



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Optimark. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to Optimark.



 *  Nephrogenic Systemic Fibrosis (NSF) 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions including bronchospasm and laryngeal/pharyngeal edema 
 *  Seizures 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:

NEPHROGENIC SYSTEMIC FIBROSIS

  WARNING:

NEPHROGENIC SYSTEMIC FIBROSIS

    Gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs) increase the risk for NSF among patients with impaired elimination of the drugs. Avoid use of GBCAs in these patients unless the diagnostic information is essential and not available with non-contrasted MRI or other modalities. NSF may result in fatal or debilitating fibrosis affecting the skin, muscle and internal organs.  



 *  Do not administer Optimark to patients with: 
   *  chronic, severe kidney disease (GFR &lt;30 mL/min/1.73m2), or 
 *  acute kidney injury [see Contraindications (4)]. 
   *  Screen patients for acute kidney injury and other conditions that may reduce renal function. For patients at risk for chronically reduced renal function (e.g. age &gt;60 years, hypertension or diabetes), estimate the glomerular filtration rate (GFR) through laboratory testing. 
 *  Do not exceed the recommended Optimark dose and allow a sufficient period of time for elimination of the drug from the body prior to any re-administration [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: NEPHROGENIC SYSTEMIC FIBROSIS (NSF)  
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



   Gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs) increase the risk for NSF among patients with impaired elimination of the drugs. Avoid use of GBCAs in these patients unless the diagnostic information is essential and not available with non-contrasted MRI or other modalities. NSF may result in fatal or debilitating fibrosis affecting the skin, muscle and internal organs (  5.1  ).  



 *  Do not administer Optimark to patients with:chronic, severe kidney disease (GFR &lt;30 mL/min/1.73m2), oracute kidney injury (4). 
 *  Screen patients for acute kidney injury and other conditions that may reduce renal function. For patients at risk for chronically reduced renal function (e.g. age &gt;60 years, hypertension or diabetes), estimate the glomerular filtration rate (GFR) through laboratory testing (5.1). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Nephrogenic Systemic Fibrosis (NSF) has occurred in patients with impaired elimination of Gadolinium Based Contrast Agents (GBCAs). Higher than recommended dosing or repeat dosing appears to increase the risk. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Acute Kidney Injury (AKI) has occurred in patients with preexisting renal insufficiency. Use the lowest necessary dose of Optimark in these patients. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions including fatal reactions have occurred, particularly in patients with history of allergy, drug reactions, or other hypersensitivity-like disorders. Monitor these patients closely during and after administration of Optimark. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Interference with laboratory measurements of serum iron, copper and zinc and in the measurement of serum calcium using the ortho-cresophthalin complexone (OCP) colorimetric method has occurred. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Nephrogenic Systemic Fibrosis (NSF)



  Gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs) increase the risk for NSF among patients with impaired elimination of the drugs. Avoid use of GBCAs among these patients unless the diagnostic information is essential and not available with non-contrast enhanced MRI or other modalities. The GBCA-associated NSF risk appears highest for patients with chronic, severe kidney disease (GFR &lt;30 mL/min/1.73m  2  ) as well as patients with acute kidney injury. Do not administer Optimark to these patients. The risk appears lower for patients with chronic, moderate kidney disease (GFR 30 to 59 mL/min/1.73m  2  ) and little, if any, for patients with chronic, mild kidney disease (GFR 60 to 89 mL/min/1.73m  2  ). NSF may result in fatal or debilitating fibrosis affecting the skin, muscle and internal organs. Report any diagnosis of NSF following Optimark administration to Mallinckrodt Inc. (1-800-778-7898) or FDA (1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch).



 Screen patients for acute kidney injury and other conditions that may reduce renal function. Features of acute kidney injury consist of rapid (over hours to days) and usually reversible decrease in kidney function, commonly in the setting of surgery, severe infection, injury, or drug-induced kidney toxicity. Serum creatinine levels and estimated GFR may not reliably assess renal function in the setting of acute kidney injury. For patients at risk for chronic kidney disease (e.g., age &gt;60 years, diabetes mellitus or chronic hypertension), estimate the GFR through laboratory testing.



 Among the factors that may increase the risk for NSF are repeated or higher than recommended doses of a GBCA and the degree of renal impairment at the time of exposure. Record the specific GBCA and the dose administered to a patient. When administering Optimark, do not exceed the recommended dose and allow a sufficient period of time for elimination of the drug prior to any re-administration [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )]  .



    5.2 Acute Kidney Injury (AKI)



  In patients with chronically reduced renal function, acute kidney injury requiring dialysis has occurred with the use of GBCAs. The risk of acute kidney injury may increase with increasing dose of the contrast agent; administer the lowest dose necessary for adequate imaging.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis have been observed with administration of gadolinium products including Optimark. Before administering Optimark ensure the availability of resuscitation equipment and personnel trained in resuscitation techniques. Patients with a history of allergy, drug reactions or other hypersensitivity-like disorders may be at greater risk and should be closely observed during the procedure and for several hours after drug administration.  If a reaction occurs, stop Optimark and immediately begin appropriate therapy including resuscitation.



    5.4 Interference with Laboratory Testing



  Interference by Optimark in the measurements of serum iron, copper and zinc has been observed. Optimark causes interference in the measurement of serum calcium using the ortho-cresophthalin complexone (OCP) colorimetric method. In the presence of Optimark, OCP produces an erroneous, low value for serum calcium. The magnitude of this artifact is proportional to the concentration of Optimark in the blood, and accurate values can be obtained approximately 90 minutes following injection. In patients with renal insufficiency, clearance of Optimark is slowed and the interference with calcium determination by OCP is prolonged. Neither the arsenazo III dye system nor the inductively coupled plasma mass spectroscopy methods for calcium assay are affected by Optimark.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
