<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="orap" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  General

    Extrapyramidal Reactions:  Neuromuscular (extrapyramidal) reactions during the administration of ORAP  (r)  (pimozide) have been reported frequently, often during the first few days of treatment. In most patients, these reactions involved Parkinson-like symptoms which, when first observed, were usually mild to moderately severe and usually reversible.



 Other types of neuromuscular reactions (motor restlessness, dystonia, akathisia, hyperreflexia, opisthotonos, oculogyric crises) have been reported far less frequently. Severe extrapyramidal reactions have been reported to occur at relatively low doses. Generally the occurrence and severity of most extrapyramidal symptoms are dose-related since they occur at relatively high doses and have been shown to disappear or become less severe when the dose is reduced. Administration of antiparkinson drugs such as benztropine mesylate or trihexyphenidyl hydrochloride may be required for control of such reactions. It should be noted that persistent extrapyramidal reactions have been reported and that the drug may have to be discontinued in such cases.



   Withdrawal Emergent Neurological Signs:  Generally, patients receiving short term therapy experience no problems with abrupt discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs. However, some patients on maintenance treatment experience transient dyskinetic signs after abrupt withdrawal. In certain of these cases the dyskinetic movements are indistinguishable from the syndrome described below under "Tardive Dyskinesia" except for duration. It is not known whether gradual withdrawal of antipsychotic drugs will reduce the rate of occurrence of withdrawal emergent neurological signs, but until further evidence becomes available, it seems reasonable to gradually withdraw use of ORAP.



   Tardive Dyskinesia:  ORAP may be associated with persistent dyskinesias. Tardive dyskinesia, a syndrome consisting of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements, may appear in some patients on long-term therapy or may occur after drug therapy has been discontinued. The risk appears to be greater in elderly patients on high-dose therapy, especially females. The symptoms are persistent and in some patients appear irreversible. The syndrome is characterized by rhythmical involuntary movements of tongue, face, mouth or jaw (e.g., protrusion of tongue, puffing of cheeks, puckering of mouth, chewing movements). Sometimes these may be accompanied by involuntary movements of extremities and the trunk.



 There is no known effective treatment for tardive dyskinesia; antiparkinson agents usually do not alleviate the symptoms of this syndrome. It is suggested that all antipsychotic agents be discontinued if these symptoms appear. Should it be necessary to reinstitute treatment, or increase the dosage of the agent, or switch to a different antipsychotic agent, this syndrome may be masked.



 It has been reported that fine vermicular movement of the tongue may be an early sign of tardive dyskinesia and if the medication is stopped at that time the syndrome may not develop.



   Electrocardiographic Changes:  Electrocardiographic changes have been observed in clinical trials of ORAP in Tourette's Disorder and schizophrenia. These have included prolongation of the QT interval, flattening, notching and inversion of the T wave and the appearance of U waves. Sudden, unexpected deaths and grand mal seizure have occurred at doses above 20 mg/day.



   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome:  Neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS) has been reported with ORAP. (See    WARNINGS    for further information concerning NMS.)



   Hyperpyrexia:  Hyperpyrexia has been reported with other antipsychotic drugs.



   Clinical Trials

  The following adverse reaction tabulation was derived from 20 patients in a 6-week long placebo-controlled clinical trial of ORAP in Tourette's Disorder.



   Body System/    Pimozide    Placebo  



   Adverse Reaction    (N = 20)    (N = 20)  



   Body as a Whole  



 Headache 1 2



   Gastrointestinal  



 Dry Mouth 5 1



 Diarrhea 1 0



 Nausea 0 2



 Vomiting 0 1



 Constipation 4 2



 Eructations 0 1



 Thirsty 1 0



 Appetite increase 1 0



   Endocrine  



 Menstrual disorder 0 1



 Breast secretions 0 1



   Musculoskeletal  



 Muscle cramps 0 1



 Muscle tightness 3 0



 Stooped posture 2 0



   CNS  



 Drowsiness 7 3



 Sedation 14 5



 Insomnia 2 2



 Dizziness 0 1



 Akathisia 8 0



 Rigidity 2 0



 Speech disorder 2 0



 Handwriting change 1 0



 Akinesia 8 0



   Psychiatric  



 Depression 2 3



 Excitement 0 1



 Nervous 1 0



 Adverse behavior effect 5 0



   Special Senses  



 Visual disturbance 4 0



 Taste change 1 0



 Sensitivity of eyes to light 1 0



 Decrease accommodation 4 1



 Spots before eyes 0 1



   Urogenital  



 Impotence 3 0



 The following adverse event tabulation was derived from 36 children (age 2 to 12) in a 24-week open trial of ORAP in Tourette's Disorder.



   Body System/ Number of Patients  



   Adverse Reaction    Experiencing Each Event (%)  



   All Events    Drug-Related  



   Events  



 (N=36) (N=36)



   Body as a Whole  



 *     Asthenia 9 (25.0) 5 (13.8) 
 *     Headache 8 (22.2) 1 (2.7) 
      Gastrointestinal  
 

 *     Dysphagia 1 (2.7) 1 (2.7) 
 *     Increased Salivation 5 (13.8) 2 (5.5) 
      Musculoskeletal  
 

 *     Myalgia 1 (2.7) 1 (2.7) 
      Central Nervous System  
 

 *     Dreaming Abnormal 1 (2.7) 1 (2.7) 
 *     Hyperkinesia 2 (5.5) 1 (2.7) 
 *     Somnolence 10 (27.7) 9 (25.0) 
 *     Torticollis 1 (2.7) 1 (2.7) 
 *     Tremor, Limbs 1 (2.7) 1 (2.7) 
      Psychiatric  
 

 *     Adverse Behavior Effect 10 (27.7) 8 (22.2) 
 *     Nervous 3 (8.3) 2 (5.5) 
      Skin  
 

 *     Rash 3 (8.3) 1 (2.7) 
      Special Senses  
 

 *     Visual Disturbance 2 (5.5) 1 (2.7) 
      Cardiovascular  
 

 *     ECG Abnormal 1 (2.7) 1 (2.7) 
    Because clinical investigational experience with ORAP in Tourette's Disorder is limited, uncommon adverse reactions may not have been detected. The physician should consider that other adverse reactions associated with antipsychotics may occur.
 

   Other Adverse Reactions

  In addition to the adverse reactions listed above, those listed below have been reported in U.S. clinical trials of ORAP in conditions other than Tourette's Disorder.



   Body as a Whole:  Asthenia, chest pain, periorbital edema



   Cardiovascular/Respiratory:  Postural hypotension, hypotension, hypertension, tachycardia, palpitations



   Gastrointestinal:  Increased salivation, nausea, vomiting, anorexia, GI distress



   Endocrine:  Loss of libido



   Metabolic/Nutritional:  Weight gain, weight loss



   Central Nervous System:  Dizziness, tremor, parkinsonism, fainting, dyskinesia



   Psychiatric:  Excitement



   Skin:  Rash, sweating, skin irritation



   Special Senses:  Blurred vision, cataracts



   Urogenital:  Nocturia, urinary frequency



   Postmarketing Reports

  The following experiences were described in spontaneous postmarketing reports. These reports do not provide sufficient information to establish a clear causal relationship with the use of ORAP.



   Gastrointestinal:  Gingival hyperplasia in one patient



   Hematologic:  Hemolytic anemia



   Metabolic/Nutritional:  Hyponatremia



   Other:  Seizure
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
