<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="oraqix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt; 15%) are application site reactions including pain, soreness, irritation, numbness, ulcerations, vesicles, edema, abscess and/or redness. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact DENTSPLY Pharmaceutical at 1-800-989-8826 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice  .  



 Although no major differences in adverse events between Oraqix and placebo-treated subjects were observed, all patients in the placebo-controlled studies received either Oraqix or a placebo gel (consisting of the vehicle in Oraqix without lidocaine or prilocaine). Therefore, it is not possible to determine if adverse events in each treatment group were attributable to the inactive ingredients comprising the Oraqix or vehicle or if adverse event rates were higher than expected background rates. Therefore, a causal relationship between the reported adverse reactions and Oraqix could neither be established nor ruled out.



 Following SRP treatment with Oraqix in 391 patients, the most frequent adverse events were local reactions in the oral cavity (see following  table  ). These events, which occurred in approximately 15% of patients, included pain, soreness, irritation, numbness, vesicles, ulcerations, edema and/or redness in the treated area. Of the 391 patients treated with Oraqix, five developed ulcerative lesions and two developed vesicles of mild to moderate severity near the site of SRP. In addition, ulcerative lesions in or near the treated area were also reported for three out of 168 patients who received placebo. Other symptoms reported in more than one patient were headache, taste perversion, nausea, fatigue, flu, respiratory infection, musculoskeletal pain and accident/injury.



 Table 1. Number (percent) of patients with adverse events occurring in more than one patient in any of the treatment groups. 
 Each patient is counted only once per adverse event. The occurrence in a single patient is included in this table if the same symptom has been seen in at least one patient in another group.   
 System Organ ClassPreferred Term          Oraqix gel(N = 391)n (%)  Placebo gel(N = 168)n (%)  Lidocaine injection(N = 170)n (%)   
  
   Muscular-Skeletal System Disorders  Myalgia          1(0)                  2(1)                                 
 Arthralgia and/or Arthropathy                     1(0)                  1(1)                                 
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System  Disorders                                                                     
 Headache                                          8(2)                  3(2)                  5(3)           
 Dizziness                                         1(0)                  1(1)                  1(1)           
   Special Senses Other, Disorders  Taste Perversion          8(2)                  1(1)                                 
   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders  Nausea          3(1)                                        1(1)           
   Respiratory System Disorders  Respiratory Infection          2(1)                                        1(1)           
 Rhinitis                                                               2 (1)                                 
   Body as a whole- General Disorders  Accident and/or Injury          2(1)                  2(1)                                 
 Fatigue                                           3(1)                                        2(1)           
 Flu-Like Disorder                                 2(1)                                                       
 Pain (remote from application site)               1(0)                  1(1)                  1(1)           
   Application Site Disorders  Anesthesia Local          2(1)                                                       
 Application Site Reaction                        52(13)                20(12)                                
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Methemoglobinemia (  5.1  ) 
 *  DO NOT INJECT (  5.2  ) 
 *  Allergic and anaphylactic reactions can occur (  5.3  ) 
 *  Avoid contact with eyes (  5.4  ) 
 *  Use with caution in patients with severe hepatic disease (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Methemoglobinemia



  Prilocaine in Oraqix can cause elevated methemoglobin levels particularly in conjunction with methemoglobin-inducing agents. Methemoglobinemia has also been reported in a few cases in association with lidocaine treatment. Patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency or congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia are more susceptible to drug-induced methemoglobinemia. Oraqix should not be used in those patients with congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia and in infants under the age of twelve months who are receiving treatment with methemoglobin-inducing agents. Signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia may be delayed some hours after exposure. Initial signs and symptoms of methemoglobinemia are characterized by a slate grey cyanosis seen in, e.g., buccal mucous membranes, lips and nail beds. In severe cases symptoms may include central cyanosis, headache, lethargy, dizziness, fatigue, syncope, dyspnea, CNS depression, seizures, dysrhythmia and shock. Methemoglobinemia should be considered if central cyanosis unresponsive to oxygen therapy occurs, especially if metHb-inducing agents have been used. Calculated oxygen saturation and pulse oximetry are inaccurate in the setting of methemoglobinemia. The diagnosis can be confirmed by an elevated methemoglobin level measured with co-oximetry. Normally, metHb levels are &lt;1%, and cyanosis may not be evident until a level of at least 10% is present. The development of methemoglobinemia is generally dose related. The individual maximum level of metHb in blood ranged from 0.8% to 1.7% following administration of the maximum dose of 8.5g Oraqix.



    Management of Methemoglobinemia  : Clinically significant symptoms of methemoglobinemia should be treated with a standard clinical regimen such as a slow intravenous infection of methylene blue at a dosage of 1to 2 mg/kg given over a five minute period.



 Patients taking drugs associated with drug-induced methemoglobinemia such as sulfonamides, acetaminophen, acetanilide, aniline dyes, benzocaine, chloroquine, dapsone, naphthalene, nitrates and nitrites, nitrofurantoin, nitroglycerin, nitroprusside, pamaquine, para-aminosalicylic acid, phenacetin, phenobarbital, phenytoin, primaquine, and quinine are also at greater risk for developing methemoglobinemia. Treatment with Oraqix should be avoided in patients with any of the above conditions or with a previous history of problems in connection with prilocaine treatment.



    5.2 DO NOT INJECT



  Oraqix should not be used with standard dental syringes. Only use this product with the Oraqix blunt-tipped applicator, which is available from DENTSPLY Pharmaceutical.



    5.3 Allergic/anaphylactic reactions



  Allergic and anaphylactic reactions associated with lidocaine or prilocaine in Oraqix can occur. These reactions may be characterized by urticaria, angioedema, bronchospasm, and shock. If these reactions occur they should be managed by conventional means.



    5.4 Avoid Contact with Eyes



  Oraqix coming in contact with the eye should be avoided because animal studies have demonstrated severe eye irritation. A loss of protective reflexes may allow corneal irritation and potential abrasion. If eye contact occurs, immediately rinse the eye with water or saline and protect it until normal sensation returns. In addition, the patient should be evaluated by an ophthalmologist, as indicated.



    5.5 History of Drug Sensitivity



  Patients allergic to paraminobenzoic acid derivatives (procaine, tetracaine, benzocaine, etc.) have not shown cross sensitivity to lidocaine and/or prilocaine. However, Oraqix should be used with caution in patients with a history of drug sensitivities, especially if the etiologic agent is uncertain.



    5.6 Severe Hepatic Disease



  Patients with severe hepatic disease, because of their inability to metabolize local anesthetics normally, are at greater risk of developing toxic plasma concentrations of lidocaine and prilocaine.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
