<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="orenitram" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;10%) reported in clinical studies with Orenitram are headache, nausea, and diarrhea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact United Therapeutics Corp. at 1-866-458-6479 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In a 12-week placebo-controlled monotherapy study (Study 1; WHO Group 1; functional class II-III), the most commonly reported adverse reactions that occurred in patients receiving Orenitram included: headache, nausea, and diarrhea. Table 1 lists the adverse reactions that occurred at a rate on Orenitram at least 5% higher than on placebo.



 Orenitram patients in Table 1 for Study 1 (N = 151) had access to 0.25 mg tablets at randomization. Approximately 91% of such patients experienced an adverse reaction, but only 4% discontinued therapy for an adverse reaction (compared to 3% receiving placebo). The overall discontinuation rate for any reason was 17% for active and 14% for placebo.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions with Rates at Least 5% Higher on Orenitram Monotherapy than on Placebo 
 Reaction                                          OrenitramN=151                   PlaceboN=77             
  
 Headache                                               63%                             19%                 
 Diarrhea                                               30%                             16%                 
 Nausea                                                 30%                             18%                 
 Flushing                                               15%                              6%                 
 Pain in jaw                                            11%                              4%                 
 Pain in extremity                                      14%                              8%                 
 Hypokalemia                                             9%                              3%                 
 Abdominal discomfort                                    6%                              0%                 
         Orenitram was studied in a long-term, open-label extension study in which 824 patients were dosed for a mean duration of approximately 2 years. About 70% of patients continued treatment with Orenitram for at least a year. The mean dose was 4.2 mg BID at one year. The adverse reactions were similar to those observed in the placebo-controlled trials.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Do not abruptly discontinue dosing. (  2.4  ,  5.1  ) 
 *  Increased risk of bleeding, particularly in patients receiving anticoagulants. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Do not take Orenitram with alcohol (  5.3  ) 
 *  In patients with diverticulosis Orenitram tablets can become lodged in a diverticulum. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Worsening PAH Symptoms upon Abrupt Withdrawal



  Abrupt discontinuation or sudden large reductions in dosage of Orenitram may result in worsening of PAH symptoms.



    5.2 Risk of Bleeding



  Orenitram inhibits platelet aggregation and increases the risk of bleeding.



    5.3 Increased Exposure with Alcohol



  Do not take Orenitram with alcohol as release of treprostinil from the tablet may occur at a faster rate than intended.



    5.4 Use in Patients with Blind-end Pouches



  The tablet shell does not dissolve. In patients with diverticulosis, Orenitram tablets can lodge in a diverticulum.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
