<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="orkambi" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  Use in Patients with Advanced Liver Disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Liver-related Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Respiratory Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions to ORKAMBI (occurring in &gt;=5% of patients with CF homozygous for the  F508del  mutation in the  CFTR  gene) were dyspnea, nasopharyngitis, nausea, diarrhea, upper respiratory tract infection, fatigue, respiration abnormal, blood creatine phosphokinase increased, rash, flatulence, rhinorrhea, influenza. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Vertex Pharmaceuticals Incorporated at 1-877-634-8789 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The overall safety profile of ORKAMBI is based on the pooled data from 1108 patients with CF 12 years and older who are homozygous for the  F508del  mutation in the  CFTR  gene and who received at least one dose of study drug in 2 double-blind, placebo-controlled, Phase 3 clinical trials, each with 24 weeks of treatment (Trials 1 and 2). Of the 1108 patients, 49% were female and 99% were Caucasian; 369 patients received ORKAMBI every 12 hours and 370 received placebo.



 The proportion of patients who prematurely discontinued study drug due to adverse events was 5% for patients treated with ORKAMBI and 2% for patients who received placebo.



 Serious adverse reactions, whether considered drug-related or not by the investigators, that occurred more frequently in patients treated with ORKAMBI included pneumonia, hemoptysis, cough, increased blood creatine phosphokinase, and transaminase elevations. These occurred in 1% or less of patients.



 Table 1 shows adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of patients with CF treated with ORKAMBI who are homozygous for the  F508del  mutation in the  CFTR  gene that also occurred at a higher rate than in patients who received placebo in the two double-blind, placebo-controlled trials.



 Table 1: Incidence of Adverse Drug Reactions in &gt;=5% of ORKAMBI-Treated Patients Who are Homozygous for the F508del Mutation in the CFTR Gene in 2 Placebo-Controlled Phase 3 Clinical Trials of 24 Weeks Duration 
 Adverse Reaction(Preferred Term)                 ORKAMBIN=369(%)                 PlaceboN=370(%)           
  
 Dyspnea                                              48 (13)                          29 (8)               
 Nasopharyngitis                                      48 (13)                         40 (11)               
 Nausea                                               46 (13)                          28 (8)               
 Diarrhea                                             45 (12)                          31 (8)               
 Upper respiratory tract infection                    37 (10)                          20 (5)               
 Fatigue                                               34 (9)                          29 (8)               
 Respiration abnormal                                  32 (9)                          22 (6)               
 Blood creatine phosphokinase increased                27 (7)                          20 (5)               
 Rash                                                  25 (7)                          7 (2)                
 Flatulence                                            24 (7)                          11 (3)               
 Rhinorrhea                                            21 (6)                          15 (4)               
 Influenza                                             19 (5)                          8 (2)                
             Description of Selected Adverse Drug Reactions  
 

     Liver-related Adverse Reactions  



 In Trials 1 and 2, the incidence of maximum transaminase (ALT or AST) levels &gt;8, &gt;5, and &gt;3 * ULN elevations was similar between patients treated with ORKAMBI and those who received placebo. Three patients who received ORKAMBI had liver-related serious adverse reactions, including 2 reported as transaminase elevations and 1 as hepatic encephalopathy, compared to none in the placebo group. Of these three, one had elevated transaminases (&gt;3 * ULN) associated with bilirubin elevation &gt;2 * ULN. Following discontinuation or interruption of ORKAMBI, transaminases decreased to &lt;3 * ULN.



 Among 6 patients with pre-existing cirrhosis and/or portal hypertension who received ORKAMBI, worsening liver function with increased ALT, AST, bilirubin, and hepatic encephalopathy was observed in one patient. The event occurred within 5 days of the start of dosing and resolved following discontinuation of ORKAMBI  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1  ,  5.2)  ]  .



     Respiratory Adverse Reactions  



 In Trials 1 and 2, the incidence of respiratory symptom-related adverse reactions (e.g., chest discomfort, dyspnea, and respiration abnormal) was more common in patients treated with ORKAMBI (22%) compared to patients who received placebo (14%). The incidence of these adverse reactions was more common in patients treated with ORKAMBI with lower pre-treatment FEV1. In patients treated with ORKAMBI, the majority of the events began during the first week of treatment  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



     Menstrual Abnormalities  



 In Trials 1 and 2, the incidence of combined menstrual abnormality adverse reactions (e.g., amenorrhea, dysmenorrhea, menorrhagia, menstrual irregular) was more common in female patients treated with ORKAMBI (10%) compared to placebo (2%). These events occurred more frequently in the subset of female patients treated with ORKAMBI who were using hormonal contraceptives (27%) compared to those not using hormonal contraceptives (3%)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.11)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Use in patients with advanced liver disease: ORKAMBI should be used with caution in these patients and only if the benefits are expected to outweigh the risks. If ORKAMBI is used in these patients, they should be closely monitored after the initiation of treatment and the dose should be reduced. (  2.2  ,  5.1  ,  6.1  ) 
 *  Liver-related events: Elevated transaminases (ALT/AST) have been observed in some cases associated with elevated bilirubin. Measure serum transaminases and bilirubin before initiating ORKAMBI, every 3 months during the first year of treatment, and annually thereafter. For patients with a history of ALT, AST, or bilirubin elevations, more frequent monitoring should be considered. Interrupt dosing in patients with ALT or AST &gt;5 * upper limit of normal (ULN), or ALT or AST &gt;3 * ULN with bilirubin &gt;2 * ULN. Following resolution, consider the benefits and risks of resuming dosing. (  5.2  ,  6.1  ) 
 *  Respiratory events: Chest discomfort, dyspnea, and respiration abnormal were observed more commonly during initiation of ORKAMBI. Clinical experience in patients with percent predicted FEV1(ppFEV1) &lt;40 is limited, and additional monitoring of these patients is recommended during initiation of therapy. (  5.3  ,  6.1  ) 
 *  Drug interactions: Use with sensitive CYP3A substrates or CYP3A substrates with a narrow therapeutic index may decrease systemic exposure of the medicinal products and co-administration is not recommended. Hormonal contraceptives should not be relied upon as an effective method of contraception and their use is associated with increased menstruation-related adverse reactions. Use with strong CYP3A inducers may diminish exposure of ivacaftor, which may diminish its effectiveness; therefore, co-administration is not recommended. (  5.4  ,  6.1  ,  7  ,  12.3  ) 
 *  Cataracts: Non-congenital lens opacities/cataracts have been reported in pediatric patients treated with ivacaftor, a component of ORKAMBI. Baseline and follow-up examinations are recommended in pediatric patients initiating ORKAMBI. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Use in Patients with Advanced Liver Disease



  Worsening of liver function, including hepatic encephalopathy, in patients with advanced liver disease has been reported in some patients with CF while receiving ORKAMBI. Use ORKAMBI with caution in patients with advanced liver disease and only if the benefits are expected to outweigh the risks. If ORKAMBI is used in these patients, they should be closely monitored after the initiation of treatment and the dose should be reduced [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.2 Liver-related Events



  Serious adverse reactions related to elevated transaminases have been reported in patients with CF receiving ORKAMBI. In some instances, these elevations have been associated with concomitant elevations in total serum bilirubin.



 It is recommended that ALT, AST, and bilirubin be assessed prior to initiating ORKAMBI, every 3 months during the first year of treatment, and annually thereafter. For patients with a history of ALT, AST, or bilirubin elevations, more frequent monitoring should be considered. Patients who develop increased ALT, AST, or bilirubin should be closely monitored until the abnormalities resolve.



 Dosing should be interrupted in patients with ALT or AST greater than 5 * upper limit of normal (ULN) when not associated with elevated bilirubin. Dosing should also be interrupted in patients with ALT or AST elevations greater than 3 * ULN when associated with bilirubin elevations greater than 2 * ULN. Following resolution of transaminase elevations, consider the benefits and risks of resuming dosing [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.3 Respiratory Events



  Respiratory events (e.g., chest discomfort, dyspnea, and respiration abnormal) were observed more commonly in patients during initiation of ORKAMBI compared to those who received placebo. Clinical experience in patients with percent predicted FEV1(ppFEV1) &lt;40 is limited, and additional monitoring of these patients is recommended during initiation of therapy [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.4 Drug Interactions



   Substrates of CYP3A  



 Lumacaftor is a strong inducer of CYP3A. Administration of ORKAMBI may decrease systemic exposure of medicinal products that are substrates of CYP3A, which may decrease therapeutic effect. Co-administration with sensitive CYP3A substrates or CYP3A substrates with a narrow therapeutic index is not recommended.



 ORKAMBI may substantially decrease hormonal contraceptive exposure, reducing their effectiveness and increasing the incidence of menstruation-associated adverse reactions, e.g., amenorrhea, dysmenorrhea, menorrhagia, menstrual irregular (27% in women using hormonal contraceptives compared with 3% in women not using hormonal contraceptives). Hormonal contraceptives, including oral, injectable, transdermal, and implantable, should not be relied upon as an effective method of contraception when co-administered with ORKAMBI [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ,  Drug Interactions (7.3  ,  7.11)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    Strong CYP3A Inducers  



 Ivacaftor is a substrate of CYP3A4 and CYP3A5 isoenzymes. Use of ORKAMBI with strong CYP3A inducers, such as rifampin, significantly reduces ivacaftor exposure, which may reduce the therapeutic effectiveness of ORKAMBI. Therefore, co-administration with strong CYP3A inducers (e.g., rifampin, St. John's wort) is not recommended [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.5 Cataracts



  Cases of non-congenital lens opacities have been reported in pediatric patients treated with ivacaftor, a component of ORKAMBI. Although other risk factors were present in some cases (such as corticosteroid use and exposure to radiation), a possible risk attributable to ivacaftor cannot be excluded [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2)  ]  . Baseline and follow-up ophthalmological examinations are recommended in pediatric patients initiating ORKAMBI treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
