<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="orthonovum0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  An increased risk of the following serious adverse reactions has been associated with the use of oral contraceptives (See  WARNINGS  ).



 *  Thrombophlebitis and venous thrombosis with or without embolism 
 *  Arterial thromboembolism 
 *  Pulmonary embolism 
 *  Myocardial infarction 
 *  Cerebral hemorrhage 
 *  Cerebral thrombosis 
 *  Hypertension 
 *  Gallbladder disease 
 *  Hepatic adenomas or benign liver tumors 
    There is evidence of an association between the following conditions and the use of oral contraceptives:
 

 *  Mesenteric thrombosis 
 *  Retinal thrombosis 
    The following adverse reactions have been reported in patients receiving oral contraceptives and are believed to be drug-related:
 

 *  Nausea 
 *  Vomiting 
 *  Gastrointestinal symptoms (such as abdominal cramps and bloating) 
 *  Breakthrough bleeding 
 *  Spotting 
 *  Change in menstrual flow 
 *  Amenorrhea 
 *  Temporary infertility after discontinuation of treatment 
 *  Edema 
 *  Melasma which may persist 
 *  Breast changes: tenderness, enlargement, secretion 
 *  Change in weight (increase or decrease) 
 *  Change in cervical erosion and secretion 
 *  Diminution in lactation when given immediately postpartum 
 *  Cholestatic jaundice 
 *  Migraine 
 *  Allergic reaction, including rash, urticaria, angioedema 
 *  Mental depression 
 *  Reduced tolerance to carbohydrates 
 *  Vaginal candidiasis 
 *  Change in corneal curvature (steepening) 
 *  Intolerance to contact lenses 
    The following adverse reactions have been reported in users of oral contraceptives and a causal association has been neither confirmed nor refuted:
 

 *  Pre-menstrual syndrome 
 *  Cataracts 
 *  Changes in appetite 
 *  Cystitis-like syndrome 
 *  Headache 
 *  Nervousness 
 *  Dizziness 
 *  Hirsutism 
 *  Loss of scalp hair 
 *  Erythema multiforme 
 *  Erythema nodosum 
 *  Hemorrhagic eruption 
 *  Vaginitis 
 *  Porphyria 
 *  Impaired renal function 
 *  Hemolytic uremic syndrome 
 *  Acne 
 *  Changes in libido 
 *  Colitis 
 *  Budd-Chiari Syndrome 
    The following adverse reactions were also reported in clinical trials or during post-marketing experience:  Gastrointestinal Disorders:  diarrhea, pancreatitis;  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  muscle spasms, back pain;  Reproductive System and Breast Disorders  vulvovaginal pruritus  ,  pelvic pain, dysmenorrhea, vulvovaginal dryness;  Psychiatric Disorders:  anxiety, mood swings, mood altered;  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  pruritus, photosensitivity reaction;  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  edema peripheral, fatigue, irritability, asthenia, malaise;  Neoplasms Benign, Malignant, and Unspecified (Including Cysts and Polyps):  breast cancer, breast mass, breast neoplasm, cervix carcinoma;  Immune System Disorders:  anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reaction  ; Hepatobiliary Disorders:  hepatitis, cholelithiasis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS: CARDIOVASCULAR RISK ASSOCIATED WITH SMOKING

    WARNINGS: CARDIOVASCULAR RISK ASSOCIATED WITH SMOKING  

  Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive use. This risk increases with age, particularly in women over 35 years of age, and with the number of cigarettes smoked. For this reason, combination oral contraceptives, including ORTHO-NOVUM  (r)   and MODICON  (r)  , should not be used by women who are over 35  years of age and smoke.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
