<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ortho1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions with the use of COCs are discussed elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Serious cardiovascular events and stroke [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Vascular events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Liver disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
    Adverse reactions commonly reported by COC users are:
 

 *  Irregular uterine bleeding 
 *  Nausea 
 *  Breast tenderness 
 *  Headache 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions reported during clinical trials (&gt;=2%) were:
 

 ORTHO-CYCLEN: headache/migraine, abdominal/gastrointestinal pain, vaginal infection, genital discharge, breast issues (including breast pain, discharge, and enlargement), mood disorders (including depression and mood altered), flatulence, nervousness, rash. (  6.1  )



 ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN: headache/migraine, breast issues (including breast pain, enlargement, and discharge), vaginal infection, abdominal/gastrointestinal pain, mood disorders (including mood alteration and depression), genital discharge, changes in weight (including weight increased or decreased). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Pharmaceutical, Inc. at 1-800-JANSSEN (1-800-526-7736) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     ORTHO-CYCLEN  



 The safety of ORTHO-CYCLEN was evaluated in 1,647 healthy women of child-bearing potential who participated in 3 clinical trials and received at least 1 dose of ORTHO-CYCLEN for contraception. Two trials were randomized active-controlled trials and 1 was an uncontrolled open-label trial. In all 3 trials, subjects were followed for up to 24 cycles.



     Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 2% of subjects)  : The most common adverse reactions reported by at least 2% of the 1,647 women were the following in order of decreasing incidence: headache/migraine (32.9%), abdominal/gastrointestinal pain (7.8%), vaginal infection (8.4%), genital discharge (6.8%), breast issues (including breast pain, discharge, and enlargement) (6.3%), mood disorders (including depression and mood altered) (5.0%), flatulence (3.2%), nervousness (2.9%), and rash (2.6%).



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Study Discontinuation  : Over the three trials, between 11 to 21% of subjects discontinued the trial due to an adverse reaction. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=1%) leading to discontinuation were: metrorrhagia (6.9%), nausea/vomiting (5.0%), headache (4.1%), mood disorders (including depression and mood altered) (2.4%), premenstrual syndrome (1.7%), hypertension (1.4%), breast pain (1.4%), nervousness (1.3%), amenorrhea (1.1%), dysmenorrhea (1.1%), weight increased (1.1%), and flatulence (1.1%).



     Serious Adverse Reactions  : breast cancer (1 subject), mood disorders including depression, irritability, and mood swings (1 subject), myocardial infarction (1 subject), and venous thromboembolic events including pulmonary embolism (1 subject) and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) (1 subject).



     ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN  



 The safety of ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN was evaluated in 4,826 healthy women of child-bearing potential who participated in 6 clinical trials and received at least 1 dose of ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN for contraception. Two trials were randomized active-controlled trials and 4 were uncontrolled open-label trials. In 3 trials, subjects were followed for up to 24 cycles; in 2 trials, subjects were followed for up to 12 cycles; and in 1 trial, subjects were followed for up to 6 cycles.



     Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 2% of subjects)  : The most common adverse reactions reported by at least 2% of the 4,826 women were the following in order of decreasing incidence: headache/migraine (33.6%), breast issues (including breast pain, enlargement, and discharge) (8.0%), vaginal infection (7.1%), abdominal/gastrointestinal pain (5.6%), mood disorders (including mood alteration and depression) (3.8%), genital discharge (3.2%), and changes in weight (including weight fluctuation, increased or decreased) (2.5%).



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Study Discontinuation  : Over the trials, between 9 to 27% of subjects discontinued the trial due to an adverse reaction. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=1%) leading to discontinuation were: metrorrhagia (4.3%), nausea/vomiting (2.8%), headache/migraine (2.4%), mood disorders (including depression and mood altered) (1.1%), and weight increased (1.1%).



     Serious Adverse Reactions  : breast cancer (1 subject), carcinoma of the cervix  in situ  (1 subject), hypertension (1 subject), and migraine (2 subjects).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse drug reactions have been reported from worldwide postmarketing experience with norgestimate/ethinyl estradiol. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Infections and Infestations  : Urinary tract infection;



   Neoplasms Benign, Malignant and Unspecified (Incl. Cysts and Polyps)  : Breast cancer, benign breast neoplasm, hepatic adenoma, focal nodular hyperplasia, breast cyst;



   Immune System Disorders  : Hypersensitivity;



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  : Dyslipidemia;



   Psychiatric Disorders  : Anxiety, insomnia;



   Nervous System Disorders  : Syncope, convulsion, paresthesia, dizziness;



   Eye Disorders  : Visual impairment, dry eye, contact lens intolerance;



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders  : Vertigo;



   Cardiac Disorders  : Tachycardia, palpitations;



   Vascular Events  : Deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, retinal vascular thrombosis, hot flush;



   Arterial Events:  Arterial thromboembolism, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular accident;



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  : Dyspnea;



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : Pancreatitis, abdominal distension, diarrhea, constipation;



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Hepatitis;



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  : Angioedema, erythema nodosum, hirsutism, night sweats, hyperhidrosis, photosensitivity reaction, urticaria, pruritus, acne;



   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue, and Bone Disorders  : Muscle spasms, pain in extremity, myalgia, back pain;



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders  : Ovarian cyst, suppressed lactation, vulvovaginal dryness;



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  : Chest pain, asthenic conditions.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS

    WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS  

    Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive (COC) use. This risk increases with age, particularly in women over 35 years of age, and with the number of cigarettes smoked. For this reason, COCs are contraindicated in women who are over 35 years of age and smoke   [see   Contraindications (4)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN is contraindicated in women over 35 years old who smoke. (4) 
 *  Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptives (COC) use. (4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Thromboembolic Disorders and Other Vascular Problems: Stop ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if a thrombotic event occurs. Stop at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery. Start no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Liver disease: Discontinue ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if jaundice occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *   High blood pressure: If used in women with well-controlled hypertension, monitor blood pressure and stop ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if blood pressure rises significantly. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Carbohydrate and lipid metabolic effects: Monitor prediabetic and diabetic women taking ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN. Consider an alternate contraceptive method for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemia. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Headache: Evaluate significant change in headaches and discontinue ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if indicated. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Bleeding Irregularities and Amenorrhea: Evaluate irregular bleeding or amenorrhea. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thromboembolic Disorders and Other Vascular Problems



    *  Stop ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if an arterial thrombotic event or venous thromboembolic (VTE) event occurs. 
 *  Stop ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if there is unexplained loss of vision, proptosis, diplopia, papilledema, or retinal vascular lesions. Evaluate for retinal vein thrombosis immediately [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ] . 
 *  If feasible, stop ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery or other surgeries known to have an elevated risk of VTE as well as during and following prolonged immobilization. 
 *  Start ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. The risk of postpartum VTE decreases after the third postpartum week, whereas the risk of ovulation increases after the third postpartum week. 
 *  The use of COCs increases the risk of VTE. However, pregnancy increases the risk of VTE as much or more than the use of COCs. The risk of VTE in women using COCs is 3 to 9 cases per 10,000 woman-years. The risk of VTE is highest during the first year of use of COCs and when restarting hormonal contraception after a break of 4 weeks or longer. The risk of thromboembolic disease due to COCs gradually disappears after use is discontinued. 
 *  Use of COCs also increases the risk of arterial thromboses such as strokes and myocardial infarctions, especially in women with other risk factors for these events. COCs have been shown to increase both the relative and attributable risks of cerebrovascular events (thrombotic and hemorrhagic strokes). This risk increases with age, particularly in women over 35 years of age who smoke. 
 *  Use COCs with caution in women with cardiovascular disease risk factors. 
       5.2 Liver Disease
 

   Impaired Liver Function  



 Do not use ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN in women with liver disease, such as acute viral hepatitis or severe (decompensated) cirrhosis of liver [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . Acute or chronic disturbances of liver function may necessitate the discontinuation of COC use until markers of liver function return to normal and COC causation has been excluded. Discontinue ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if jaundice develops.



    Liver Tumors  



 ORTHO-CYCLEN and ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN are contraindicated in women with benign and malignant liver tumors [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . Hepatic adenomas are associated with COC use. An estimate of the attributable risk is 3.3 cases/100,000 COC users. Rupture of hepatic adenomas may cause death through intra-abdominal hemorrhage.



 Studies have shown an increased risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in long-term (&gt;8 years) COC users. However, the risk of liver cancers in COC users is less than one case per million users.



    5.3 High Blood Pressure



  ORTHO-CYCLEN and ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN are contraindicated in women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . For women with well-controlled hypertension, monitor blood pressure and stop ORTHO-CYCLEN and ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if blood pressure rises significantly.



 An increase in blood pressure has been reported in women taking COCs, and this increase is more likely in older women with extended duration of use. The incidence of hypertension increases with increasing concentrations of progestin.



    5.4 Gallbladder Disease



  Studies suggest a small increased relative risk of developing gallbladder disease among COC users. Use of COCs may worsen existing gallbladder disease. A past history of COC-related cholestasis predicts an increased risk with subsequent COC use. Women with a history of pregnancy-related cholestasis may be at an increased risk for COC related cholestasis.



    5.5 Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects



  Carefully monitor prediabetic and diabetic women who take ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN. COCs may decrease glucose tolerance.



 Consider alternative contraception for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemia. A small proportion of women will have adverse lipid changes while on COCs.



 Women with hypertriglyceridemia, or a family history thereof, may be at an increased risk of pancreatitis when using COCs.



    5.6 Headache



  If a woman taking ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN develops new headaches that are recurrent, persistent, or severe, evaluate the cause and discontinue ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if indicated.



 Consider discontinuation of ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN in the case of increased frequency or severity of migraine during COC use (which may be prodromal of a cerebrovascular event).



    5.7 Bleeding Irregularities and Amenorrhea



   Unscheduled Bleeding and Spotting  



 Unscheduled (breakthrough or intracyclic) bleeding and spotting sometimes occur in patients on COCs, especially during the first three months of use. If bleeding persists or occurs after previously regular cycles, check for causes such as pregnancy or malignancy. If pathology and pregnancy are excluded, bleeding irregularities may resolve over time or with a change to a different contraceptive product.



 In clinical trials of ORTHO-CYCLEN and ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN, the frequency and duration of breakthrough bleeding and/or spotting was assessed in 1,647 patients (21,275 evaluable cycles) and 4,826 patients (35,546 evaluable cycles), respectively. A total of 100 (7.5%) women discontinued ORTHO-CYCLEN and 231 (4.8%) women discontinued ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN, at least in part, due to bleeding or spotting. Based on data from the clinical trials, 14-34% of women using ORTHO-CYCLEN experienced unscheduled bleeding per cycle in the first year; for ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN, the respective numbers were 13-38%. The percent of women who experienced breakthrough/unscheduled bleeding tended to decrease over time.



    Amenorrhea and Oligomenorrhea  



 Women who use ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN may experience amenorrhea. Some women may experience amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea after discontinuation of COCs, especially when such a condition was pre-existent.



 If scheduled (withdrawal) bleeding does not occur, consider the possibility of pregnancy. If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed dosing schedule (missed one or more active tablets or started taking them on a day later than she should have), consider the possibility of pregnancy at the time of the first missed period and take appropriate diagnostic measures. If the patient has adhered to the prescribed regimen and misses two consecutive periods, rule out pregnancy.



    5.8 COC Use Before or During Early Pregnancy



  Extensive epidemiological studies have revealed no increased risk of birth defects in women who have used oral contraceptives prior to pregnancy. Studies also do not suggest a teratogenic effect, particularly in so far as cardiac anomalies and limb reduction defects are concerned, when oral contraceptives are taken inadvertently during early pregnancy. Discontinue ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN use if pregnancy is confirmed.



 Administration of COCs to induce withdrawal bleeding should not be used as a test for pregnancy [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



    5.9 Depression



  Carefully observe women with a history of depression and discontinue ORTHO-CYCLEN or ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN if depression recurs to a serious degree.



    5.10 Carcinoma of Breast and Cervix



    *  ORTHO-CYCLEN and ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN are contraindicated in women who currently have or have had breast cancer because breast cancer may be hormonally sensitive [see  Contraindications (4)  ] . There is substantial evidence that COCs do not increase the incidence of breast cancer. Although some past studies have suggested that COCs might increase the incidence of breast cancer, more recent studies have not confirmed such findings.



 
 *  Some studies suggest that COC use has been associated with an increase in the risk of cervical cancer or intraepithelial neoplasia. However, there continues to be controversy about the extent to which such findings may be due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors. 
       5.11 Effect on Binding Globulins
 

  The estrogen component of COCs may raise the serum concentrations of thyroxine-binding globulin, sex hormone-binding globulin, and cortisol-binding globulin. The dose of replacement thyroid hormone or cortisol therapy may need to be increased.



    5.12 Monitoring



  A woman who is taking COCs should have a yearly visit with her healthcare provider for a blood pressure check and for other indicated healthcare.



    5.13 Hereditary Angioedema



  In women with hereditary angioedema, exogenous estrogens may induce or exacerbate symptoms of angioedema.



    5.14 Chloasma



  Chloasma may occasionally occur, especially in women with a history of chloasma gravidarum. Women with a tendency to chloasma should avoid exposure to the sun or ultraviolet radiation while taking ORTHO TRI-CYCLEN or ORTHO-CYCLEN.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
