<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="otrexup" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling.



 *      Organ System Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *      Embryo-Fetal Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *      Effects on Reproduction [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *      Malignant Lymphomas [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
    The most frequently reported adverse reactions include ulcerative stomatitis, leukopenia, nausea, and abdominal distress. Other frequently reported adverse reactions are malaise, undue fatigue, chills and fever, dizziness and decreased resistance to infection.
 

   EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions are: nausea, abdominal pain, dyspepsia, stomatitis/mouth sores, rash, nasopharyngitis, diarrhea, liver function test abnormalities, vomiting, headache, bronchitis, thrombocytopenia, alopecia, leucopenia, pancytopenia, dizziness, photosensitivity, and "burning of skin lesions" (  6  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    Antares at 1-855-Otrexup (1-855-687-3987)    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  This section provides a summary of adverse reactions reported in subjects in clinical studies conducted with Otrexup as well as with methotrexate injection and oral methotrexate.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Rheumatoid Arthritis  



 The approximate incidences of methotrexate-attributed (i.e. placebo rate subtracted) adverse reactions in 12 to 18 week double-blind studies of patients (n=128) with rheumatoid arthritis treated with low-dose oral (7.5 to 15 mg/week) pulse methotrexate, are listed below. Virtually all of these patients were on concomitant nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and some were also taking low dosages of corticosteroids. Hepatic histology was not examined in these short-term studies.



 Incidence greater than 10%: Elevated liver function tests 15%, nausea/vomiting 10%.



 Incidence 3% to 10%: Stomatitis, thrombocytopenia (platelet count less than 100,000/mm  3  ).



 Incidence 1% to 3%: Rash/pruritis/dermatitis, diarrhea, alopecia, leukopenia (WBC less than 3000/mm  3  ), pancytopenia, dizziness.



 Two other controlled trials of patients (n=680) with Rheumatoid Arthritis on 7.5 mg to 15 mg/wk oral doses showed an incidence of interstitial pneumonitis of 1%.



 Other less common reactions included decreased hematocrit, headache, upper respiratory infection, anorexia, arthralgias, chest pain, coughing, dysuria, eye discomfort, epistaxis, fever, infection, sweating, tinnitus, and vaginal discharge.



   Polyarticular    Juvenile Idiopathic Arthritis  



 The approximate incidences of adverse reactions reported in pediatric patients with pJIA treated with oral, weekly doses of methotrexate (5 to 20 mg/m  2  /wk or 0.1 to 0.65 mg/kg/wk) were as follows (virtually all patients were receiving concomitant nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and some also were taking low doses of corticosteroids): elevated liver function tests, 14%; gastrointestinal reactions (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea), 11%; stomatitis, 2%; leukopenia, 2%; headache, 1.2%; alopecia, 0.5%; dizziness, 0.2%; and rash, 0.2%. Although there is experience with dosing up to 30 mg/m  2  /wk in pJIA, the published data for doses above 20 mg/m  2  /wk are too limited to provide reliable estimates of adverse reaction rates.



   Psoriasis  



 There are two literature reports (Roenigk, 1969, and Nyfors, 1978) describing large series (n=204, 248) of psoriasis patients treated with methotrexate. Dosages ranged up to 25 mg per week and treatment was administered for up to four years. With the exception of alopecia, photosensitivity, and "burning of skin lesions" (each 3% to 10%), the adverse reaction rates in these reports were very similar to those in the rheumatoid arthritis studies. Rarely, painful plaque erosions may appear (Pearce, HP and Wilson, BB: Am Acad Dermatol 35: 835-838, 1996).



   6.2 Other Adverse Reactions

  Other adverse reactions that have been reported with methotrexate in oncology, RA, pJIA, and psoriasis patients are listed below by organ system.



     Alimentary System:    gingivitis, pharyngitis, stomatitis, anorexia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, hematemesis, melena, gastrointestinal ulceration and bleeding, enteritis, pancreatitis.



     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:    suppressed hematopoiesis, anemia, aplastic anemia, pancytopenia, leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, agranulocytosis, eosinophilia, lymphadenopathy and lymphoproliferative disorders (including reversible). Hypogammaglobulinemia has been reported rarely.



     Cardiovascular:    pericarditis, pericardial effusion, hypotension, and thromboembolic events (including arterial thrombosis, cerebral thrombosis, deep vein thrombosis, retinal vein thrombosis, thrombophlebitis, and pulmonary embolus).



     Central Nervous System:    headaches, drowsiness, blurred vision, transient blindness, speech impairment including dysarthria and aphasia, hemiparesis, paresis and convulsions have also occurred following administration of methotrexate. Following low doses, there have been occasional reports of transient subtle cognitive dysfunction, mood alteration or unusual cranial sensations, leukoencephalopathy, or encephalopathy.



     Hepatobiliary        Disorders:    hepatotoxicity, acute hepatitis, chronic fibrosis and cirrhosis, hepatic failure, decrease in serum albumin, liver enzyme elevations.



     Infection:    There have been case reports of sometimes fatal opportunistic infections in patients receiving methotrexate therapy for neoplastic and non-neoplastic diseases.  Pneumocystis    jiroveci      pneumonia was the most common opportunistic infection. There have also been reports of infections, pneumonia, Cytomegalovirus infection, including cytomegaloviral pneumonia, sepsis, fatal sepsis, nocardiosis; histoplasmosis, cryptococcosis,  Herpes zoster  ,  Herpes simplex  hepatitis, and disseminated  Herpes simplex  .



     Musculoskeletal System:    stress fracture.



     Ophthalmic:    conjunctivitis, serious visual changes of unknown etiology.



     Pulmonary System:    respiratory fibrosis, respiratory failure, alveolitis, interstitial pneumonitis deaths have been reported, and chronic interstitial obstructive pulmonary disease has occasionally occurred.



     Skin:    erythematous rashes, pruritus, urticaria, photosensitivity, pigmentary changes, alopecia, ecchymosis, telangiectasia, acne, furunculosis, erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, skin necrosis, skin ulceration and exfoliative dermatitis.



     Urogenital System:    severe nephropathy or renal failure, azotemia, cystitis, hematuria, proteinuria; defective oogenesis or spermatogenesis, transient oligospermia, menstrual dysfunction, vaginal discharge, and gynecomastia; infertility, abortion, fetal death, fetal defects.



 Other rarer reactions related to or attributed to the use of methotrexate such as nodulosis, vasculitis, arthralgia/myalgia, loss of libido/ impotence, diabetes, osteoporosis, sudden death, lymphoma, including reversible lymphomas, tumor lysis syndrome, soft tissue necrosis and osteonecrosis. Anaphylactoid reactions have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SEVERE TOXIC REACTIONS, INCLUDING EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY AND DEATH

  WARNING: SEVERE TOXIC REACTIONS, INCLUDING EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY AND DEATH

    Otrexup     should be used only by physicians whose knowledge and experience include the use of antimetabolite therapy. Because of the possibility of serious toxic reactions (which can be fatal),     Otrexup     should be used only in patients with psoriasis or rheumatoid arthritis with severe, recalcitrant, disabling disease which is not adequately responsive to other forms of therapy. Deaths have been reported with the use of methotrexate in the treatment of malignancy, psoriasis, and rheumatoid arthritis. Patients should be closely monitored for bone marrow, liver, lung, skin, and kidney toxicities. Patients should be informed by their physician of the risks involved and be under a physician's care throughout therapy   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   1. Methotrexate has been reported to cause fetal death and/or congenital anomalies.  



   Therefore, Otrexup is not recommended for females of childbearing potential unless there is clear medical evidence that the benefits can be expected to outweigh the considered risks   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .     Otrexup is contraindicated in pregnant women   [see Contraindications (  4  )].    



   2. Methotrexate elimination is reduced in patients with impaired renal functions, ascites, or pleural effusions. Such patients require especially careful monitoring for toxicity, and require dose reduction or, in some cases, discontinuation of     Otrexup     administration   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  .  



   3. Unexpectedly severe (sometimes fatal) bone marrow suppression, aplastic anemia, and gastrointestinal toxicity have been reported with concomitant administration of methotrexate (usually in high dosage) along with some     nonsteroidal     anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) and Drug Interactions (  7.1  )].    



   4. Methotrexate causes hepatotoxicity, fibrosis and cirrhosis, but generally only after prolonged use. Acutely, liver enzyme elevations are frequently seen. These are usually transient and asymptomatic, and also do not appear predictive of subsequent hepatic disease. Liver biopsy after sustained use often shows histologic changes, and fibrosis and cirrhosis have been reported; these latter lesions may not be preceded by symptoms or abnormal liver function tests in the psoriasis population. For this reason, periodic liver biopsies are usually recommended for psoriatic patients who are under     long-term     treatment. Persistent abnormalities in liver function tests may precede appearance of fibrosis or cirrhosis in the rheumatoid arthritis population   [see Warnings and Precautions     (  5.1  )].    



   5. Methotrexate-induced lung disease, including acute or chronic interstitial pneumonitis, is a potentially dangerous lesion, which may occur acutely at any time during therapy and has been reported at low doses. It is not always fully reversible and fatalities have been reported. Pulmonary symptoms (especially a dry, nonproductive cough) may require interruption of treatment and careful investigation   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   6. Diarrhea and ulcerative stomatitis require interruption of therapy: otherwise, hemorrhagic enteritis and death from intestinal perforation may occur   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   7. Malignant lymphomas, which may regress following withdrawal of methotrexate, may occur in patients receiving low-dose methotrexate and, thus, may not require cytotoxic treatment. Discontinue     Otrexup     first and, if the lymphoma does not regress, appropriate treatment should be instituted   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  .  



   8. Like other cytotoxic drugs, methotrexate may induce "tumor     lysis     syndrome" in patients with rapidly growing tumors   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  .  



   9. Severe, occasionally fatal, skin reactions have been reported following single or multiple doses of methotrexate. Reactions have occurred within days of oral, intramuscular, intravenous, or     intrathecal     methotrexate administration. Recovery has been reported with discontinuation of therapy   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  



   10. Potentially fatal opportunistic infections, especially   Pneumocystis         jiroveci           pneumonia, may occur with methotrexate therapy   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  



   11. Methotrexate given concomitantly with radiotherapy may increase the risk of soft tissue necrosis and osteonecrosis   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SEVERE TOXIC REACTIONS, INCLUDING EMBRYO-FETAL TOXICITY AND DEATH



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



    Serious toxic reactions and death have been reported with the use of methotrexate. Patients should be closely monitored for bone marrow, liver, lung, skin, and kidney toxicities (  5.1  ).  



    Methotrexate has been reported to cause fetal death and/or congenital anomalies and is contraindicated in pregnancy (  4  ,   5.2  ).  



    Unexpectedly severe (sometimes fatal) bone marrow suppression, aplastic anemia, and gastrointestinal toxicity have been reported with concomitant administration of methotrexate (usually in high dosage) along with some     nonsteroidal     anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) (  5.1  ).  



    Hepatotoxicity, fibrosis, and cirrhosis may occur after prolonged use (  5.1  ).  



    Methotrexate may cause interstitial pneumonitis at any time during therapy and has been reported at low doses. Pulmonary symptoms (especially a dry, nonproductive cough) may require interruption of treatment and careful investigation (  5.1  ).  



    Diarrhea, ulcerative stomatitis, hemorrhagic enteritis, and death from intestinal perforation may occur (  5.1  ).  



    Severe, occasionally fatal, skin reactions have been reported (  5.1  ).  



    Potentially fatal opportunistic infections may occur (  5.1  ).  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *      Organ system toxicity: Potential for serious toxicity. Only for use by physicians experienced in antimetabolite therapy (  5.1  ). 
 *      Embryo-fetal toxicity: Exclude pregnancy before treatment. Avoid pregnancy if either partner is receiving Otrexup. Advise males to avoid pregnancy for a minimum of three months after therapy and females to avoid pregnancy for at least one ovulatory cycle after therapy (  5.2  ). 
 *      Effects on reproduction: May cause impairment of fertility, oligospermia and menstrual dysfunction (  5.3  ) 
 *      Laboratory tests: Monitor complete blood counts, renal function and liver function tests (  5.4  ). 
 *      Risks from improper dosing: Mistaken daily use has led to fatal toxicity (  5.5  ) 
 *      Patients with impaired renal function, ascites, or pleural effusions: 
 *     Elimination is reduced (  5.6  ). 
 *      Dizziness and fatigue: May impair ability to drive or operate machinery (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Organ System Toxicity



  Otrexup should be used only by physicians whose knowledge and experience include the use of antimetabolite therapy. Because of the possibility of serious toxic reactions (which can be fatal), Otrexup should be used only in patients with psoriasis or rheumatoid arthritis with severe, recalcitrant, disabling disease which is not adequately responsive to other forms of therapy.



 Deaths have been reported with the use of methotrexate in the treatment of malignancy, psoriasis, and rheumatoid arthritis. Patients should be closely monitored for bone marrow, liver, lung and kidney toxicities.



 Otrexup has the potential for serious toxicity. Toxic effects may be related in frequency and severity to dose or frequency of administration but have been seen at all doses. Because they can occur at any time during therapy, it is necessary to follow patients on Otrexup closely. Most adverse reactions are reversible if detected early. When such reactions do occur, the drug should be reduced in dosage or discontinued and appropriate corrective measures should be taken. If necessary, this could include the use of leucovorin calcium and/or acute, intermittent hemodialysis with a high-flux dialyzer [see Overdosage (  10  )]  . If Otrexup therapy is reinstituted, it should be carried out with caution, with adequate consideration of further need for the drug and increased alertness as to possible recurrence of toxicity.



 The clinical pharmacology of methotrexate has not been well studied in older individuals. Due to diminished hepatic and renal function as well as decreased folate stores in this population, relatively low doses should be considered, and these patients should be closely monitored for early signs of toxicity [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )].  



  Gastrointestinal:  



 Diarrhea and ulcerative stomatitis require interruption of therapy: otherwise, hemorrhagic enteritis and death from intestinal perforation may occur.



 If vomiting, diarrhea, or stomatitis occur, which may result in dehydration, Otrexup should be discontinued until recovery occurs. Otrexup should be used with extreme caution in the presence of peptic ulcer disease or ulcerative colitis.



 Unexpectedly severe (sometimes fatal) gastrointestinal toxicity has been reported with concomitant administration of methotrexate (usually in high dosage) along with some nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )].  



  Hematologic:  



 Otrexup can suppress hematopoiesis and cause anemia, aplastic anemia, pancytopenia, leukopenia, neutropenia, and/or thrombocytopenia. In patients with preexisting hematopoietic impairment, Otrexup should be used with caution, if at all. In controlled clinical trials conducted with another formulation of methotrexate in rheumatoid arthritis (n=128), leukopenia (WBC &lt;3000/mm  3  ) was seen in 2 patients, thrombocytopenia (platelets &lt;100,000/mm  3  ) in 6 patients, and pancytopenia in 2 patients.



 Otrexup should be stopped immediately if there is a significant drop in blood counts. Patients with profound granulocytopenia and fever should be evaluated immediately and usually require parenteral broad-spectrum antibiotic therapy.



 Unexpectedly severe (sometimes fatal) bone marrow suppression and aplastic anemia have been reported with concomitant administration of methotrexate (usually in high dosage) along with some nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs ) [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )].  



  Hepatic:  



 Otrexup has the potential for acute (elevated transaminases) and chronic (fibrosis and cirrhosis) hepatotoxicity. Chronic toxicity is potentially fatal; it generally has occurred after prolonged use (generally two years or more) and after a total dose of at least 1.5 grams. In studies in psoriatic patients, hepatotoxicity appeared to be a function of total cumulative dose and appeared to be enhanced by alcoholism, obesity, diabetes and advanced age. An accurate incidence rate has not been determined; the rate of progression and reversibility of lesions is not known. Special caution is indicated in the presence of preexisting liver damage or impaired hepatic function.



 In psoriasis, liver function tests, including serum albumin, should be performed periodically prior to dosing but are often normal in the face of developing fibrosis or cirrhosis. These lesions may be detectable only by biopsy. The usual recommendation is to obtain a liver biopsy at 1) pretherapy or shortly after initiation of therapy (2 to 4 months), 2) a total cumulative dose of 1.5 grams, and 3) after each additional 1.0 to 1.5 grams. Moderate fibrosis or any cirrhosis normally leads to discontinuation of the drug; mild fibrosis normally suggests a repeat biopsy in 6 months.



 Milder histologic findings such as fatty change and low grade portal inflammation, are relatively common pretherapy. Although these mild changes are usually not a reason to avoid or discontinue Otrexup therapy, the drug should be used with caution.



 In rheumatoid arthritis, age at first use of methotrexate and duration of therapy have been reported as risk factors for hepatotoxicity; other risk factors, similar to those observed in psoriasis, may be present in rheumatoid arthritis but have not been confirmed to date. Persistent abnormalities in liver function tests may precede appearance of fibrosis or cirrhosis in this population. There is a combined reported experience in 217 rheumatoid arthritis patients with liver biopsies both before and during treatment (after a cumulative dose of at least 1.5 g) and in 714 patients with a biopsy only during treatment. There are 64 (7%) cases of fibrosis and 1 (0.1%) case of cirrhosis. Of the 64 cases of fibrosis, 60 were deemed mild. The reticulin stain is more sensitive for early fibrosis and its use may increase these figures. It is unknown whether even longer use will increase these risks.



 Liver function tests should be performed at baseline at 4 to 8 week intervals in patients receiving Otrexup for rheumatoid arthritis. Pretreatment liver biopsy should be performed for patients with a history of excessive alcohol consumption, persistently abnormal baseline liver function test values or chronic hepatitis B or C infection. During therapy, liver biopsy should be performed if there are persistent liver function test abnormalities or there is a decrease in serum albumin below the normal range (in the setting of well controlled rheumatoid arthritis).



 If the results of a liver biopsy show mild changes (Roenigk, grades I, II, IIIa), Otrexup may be continued and the patient monitored as per recommendations listed above. Otrexup should be discontinued in any patient who displays persistently abnormal liver function tests and refuses liver biopsy or in any patient whose liver biopsy shows moderate to severe changes (Roenigk grade IIIb or IV).



  Infection or Immunologic States:  



 Otrexup should be used with extreme caution in the presence of active infection, and is contraindicated in patients with overt or laboratory evidence of immunodeficiency syndromes.



 Immunization may be ineffective when given during Otrexup therapy. Immunization with live virus vaccines is generally not recommended. There have been reports of disseminated vaccinia infections after smallpox immunizations in patients receiving methotrexate therapy. Hypogammaglobulinemia has been reported rarely.



 Potentially fatal opportunistic infections, especially Pneumocystis   jiroveci     pneumonia, may occur with Otrexup therapy. When a patient presents with pulmonary symptoms, the possibility of Pneumocystis   jiroveci     pneumonia should be considered.



  Neurologic:  



 There have been reports of leukoencephalopathy following intravenous administration of methotrexate to patients who have had craniospinal irradiation. Serious neurotoxicity, frequently manifested as generalized or focal seizures, has been reported with unexpectedly increased frequency among pediatric patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia who were treated with intermediate-dose intravenous methotrexate (1 gm/m  2  ). Symptomatic patients were commonly noted to have leukoencephalopathy and/or microangiopathic calcifications on diagnostic imaging studies. Chronic leukoencephalopathy has also been reported in patients who received repeated doses of high-dose methotrexate with leucovorin rescue even without cranial irradiation.



 Discontinuation of methotrexate does not always result in complete recovery. A transient acute neurologic syndrome has been observed in patients treated with high dose regimens. Manifestations of this stroke-like encephalopathy may include confusion, hemiparesis, transient blindness, seizures and coma. The exact cause is unknown. After the intrathecal use of methotrexate, the central nervous system toxicity which may occur can be classified as follows: acute chemical arachnoiditis manifested by such symptoms as headache, back pain, nuchal rigidity, and fever; sub-acute myelopathy characterized by paraparesis/paraplegia associated with involvement with one or more spinal nerve roots; chronic leukoencephalopathy manifested by confusion, irritability, somnolence, ataxia, dementia, seizures and coma. This condition can be progressive and even fatal.



  Pulmonary:  



 Methotrexate-induced lung disease, including acute or chronic interstitial pneumonitis, is a potentially dangerous lesion, which may occur acutely at any time during therapy and has been reported at low doses. It is not always fully reversible and fatalities have been reported.



 Pulmonary symptoms (especially a dry nonproductive cough) or a non-specific pneumonitis occurring during Otrexup therapy may be indicative of a potentially dangerous lesion and require interruption of treatment and careful investigation. Although clinically variable, the typical patient with methotrexate induced lung disease presents with fever, cough, dyspnea, hypoxemia, and an infiltrate on chest X-ray; infection (including pneumonia) needs to be excluded. This lesion can occur at all dosages.



  Renal:  



 Otrexup may cause renal damage that may lead to acute renal failure. High doses of methotrexate used in the treatment of osteosarcoma may cause renal damage leading to acute renal failure. Nephrotoxicity is due primarily to the precipitation of methotrexate and 7- hydroxymethotrexate in the renal tubules. Close attention to renal function including adequate hydration, urine alkalinization and measurement of serum methotrexate and creatinine levels are essential for safe administration.



  Skin:  



 Severe, occasionally fatal, dermatologic reactions, including toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis, skin necrosis, and erythema multiforme, have been reported in children and adults, within days of oral, intramuscular, intravenous, or intrathecal methotrexate administration. Reactions were noted after single or multiple low, intermediate, or high doses of methotrexate in patients with neoplastic and non-neoplastic diseases.



 Lesions of psoriasis may be aggravated by concomitant exposure to ultraviolet radiation.



 Radiation dermatitis and sunburn may be "recalled" by the use of methotrexate.



  Other precautions:  



 Otrexup should be used with extreme caution in the presence of debility.



 Methotrexate exits slowly from third space compartments (e.g., pleural effusions or ascites). This results in a prolonged terminal plasma half-life and unexpected toxicity. In patients with significant third space accumulations, it is advisable to evacuate the fluid before treatment and to monitor plasma methotrexate levels.



    5.2 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  Methotrexate has been reported to cause fetal death and/or congenital anomalies. Therefore, Otrexup is not recommended for females of childbearing potential unless there is clear medical evidence that the benefits can be expected to outweigh the considered risks. Otrexup is contraindicated in pregnant women with psoriasis or rheumatoid arthritis.



 Females of childbearing potential should not be started on Otrexup until pregnancy is excluded and should be fully counseled on the serious risk to the fetus should they become pregnant while undergoing treatment. Appropriate steps should be taken to avoid conception during Otrexup therapy. Pregnancy should be avoided if either partner is receiving Otrexup; during and for a minimum of three months after therapy for male patients, and during and for at least one ovulatory cycle after therapy for female patients.



    5.3 Effects on Reproduction



  Methotrexate has been reported to cause impairment of fertility, oligospermia and menstrual dysfunction in humans, during and for a short period after cessation of therapy.



 The risk of effects of reproduction should be discussed with both male and female patients taking Otrexup.



    5.4 Laboratory Tests



  Patients undergoing Otrexup therapy should be closely monitored so that toxic effects are detected promptly. Baseline assessment should include a complete blood count with differential and platelet counts, hepatic enzymes, renal function tests and a chest X-ray.



 During therapy, monitoring of these parameters is recommended: hematology at least monthly, renal function and liver function every 1 to 2 months [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



  During initial or changing doses  , or during periods of increased risk of elevated methotrexate blood levels (e.g., dehydration), more frequent monitoring may also be indicated.



  Liver Function Tests  



 Transient liver function test abnormalities are observed frequently after methotrexate administration and are usually not cause for modification of methotrexate therapy. Persistent liver function test abnormalities, and/or depression of serum albumin may be indicators of serious liver toxicity and require evaluation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



 A relationship between abnormal liver function tests and fibrosis or cirrhosis of the liver has not been established for patients with psoriasis. Persistent abnormalities in liver function tests may precede appearance of fibrosis or cirrhosis in the rheumatoid arthritis population.



  Pulmonary Function Tests  



 Pulmonary function tests may be useful if methotrexate-induced lung disease is suspected, especially if baseline measurements are available [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



    5.5 Risks from Improper Dosing



  Both the physician and pharmacist should emphasize to the patient that Otrexup is administered weekly and that mistaken daily use has led to fatal toxicity [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )].  



    5.6 Patients with Impaired Renal Function, Ascites, or Pleural Effusions



  Methotrexate elimination is reduced in patients with impaired renal function, ascites, or pleural effusions. Such patients require especially careful monitoring for toxicity and require dose reduction or, in some cases, discontinuation of Otrexup administration.



    5.7 Dizziness and Fatigue



  Adverse reactions, such as dizziness and fatigue, may affect the ability to drive or operate machinery.



    5.8 Malignant Lymphomas



  Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma and other tumors have been reported in patients receiving low-dose oral methotrexate. However, there have been instances of malignant lymphoma arising during treatment with low-dose oral methotrexate, which have regressed completely following withdrawal of methotrexate, without requiring active anti-lymphoma treatment. Discontinue Otrexup first and, if the lymphoma does not regress, appropriate treatment should be instituted.



    5.9 Tumor Lysis Syndrome



  Like other cytotoxic drugs, methotrexate may induce "tumor lysis syndrome" in patients with rapidly growing tumors.



    5.10 Concomitant Radiation Therapy



  Methotrexate given concomitantly with radiotherapy may increase the risk of soft tissue necrosis and osteonecrosis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
