<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="oxcarbazepine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   The most commonly observed (&gt;=5%) adverse experiences were: dizziness, somnolence, diplopia, fatigue, nausea, vomiting, ataxia, abnormal vision, abdominal pain, tremor, dyspepsia, abnormal gait, and in pediatric patients &lt;4 years old, also infections and infestations. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sandoz Inc. at 1-800-525-8747 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1     Clinical Studies Experience

  Most Common Adverse Reactions in All Clinical Studies



     Adjunctive Therapy/Monotherapy in Adults Previously Treated with other AEDs:    The most commonly observed (&gt;=5%) adverse reactions seen in association with oxcarbazepine and substantially more frequent than in placebo-treated patients were: dizziness, somnolence, diplopia, fatigue, nausea, vomiting, ataxia, abnormal vision, abdominal pain, tremor, dyspepsia, abnormal gait.



 Approximately 23% of these 1,537 adult patients discontinued treatment because of an adverse experience. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were: dizziness (6.4%), diplopia (5.9%), ataxia (5.2%), vomiting (5.1%), nausea (4.9%), somnolence (3.8%), headache (2.9%), fatigue (2.1%), abnormal vision (2.1%), tremor (1.8%), abnormal gait (1.7%), rash (1.4%), hyponatremia (1.0%).



     Monotherapy in Adults Not Previously Treated with other AEDs:    The most commonly observed (&gt;=5%) adverse reactions seen in association with oxcarbazepine in these patients were similar to those in previously treated patients.



 Approximately 9% of these 295 adult patients discontinued treatment because of an adverse experience. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were: dizziness (1.7%), nausea (1.7%), rash (1.7%), headache (1.4%).



     Adjunctive Therapy/Monotherapy in Pediatric Patients 4 Years Old and Above Previously Treated with other AEDs:    The most commonly observed (&gt;=5%) adverse reactions seen in association with oxcarbazepine in these patients were similar to those seen in adults.



 Approximately 11% of these 456 pediatric patients discontinued treatment because of an adverse experience. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were: somnolence (2.4%), vomiting (2.0%), ataxia (1.8%), diplopia (1.3%), dizziness (1.3%), fatigue (1.1%), nystagmus (1.1%).



     Monotherapy in Pediatric Patients 4 Years Old and Above Not Previously Treated with other AEDs:    The most commonly observed (&gt;=5%) adverse reactions seen in association with oxcarbazepine in these patients were similar to those in adults.



 Approximately 9.2% of 152 pediatric patients discontinued treatment because of an adverse experience. The adverse reactions most commonly associated (&gt;=1%) with discontinuation were rash (5.3%) and maculopapular rash (1.3%).



     Adjunctive Therapy/Monotherapy in Pediatric Patients 1 Month to &lt;4 Years Old Previously Treated or Not Previously Treated with other AEDs:    The most commonly observed (&gt;=5%) adverse reactions seen in association with oxcarbazepine in these patients were similar to those seen in older children and adults except for infections and infestations which were more frequently seen in these younger children.



 Approximately 11% of these 241 pediatric patients discontinued treatment because of an adverse experience. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation were: convulsions (3.7%), status epilepticus (1.2%), and ataxia (1.2%).



     Incidence in Controlled Clinical Studies:    The prescriber should be aware that the figures in Tables 3, 4, 5 and 6 cannot be used to predict the frequency of adverse reactions in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those prevailing during clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be directly compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, or investigators. An inspection of these frequencies, however, does provide the prescriber with one basis to estimate the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the adverse event incidences in the population studied.



     Controlled Clinical Studies of Adjunctive Therapy/Monotherapy in Adults Previously Treated with other AEDs:    Table 3 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that occurred in at least 2% of adult patients with epilepsy treated with oxcarbazepine or placebo as adjunctive treatment and were numerically more common in the patients treated with any dose of oxcarbazepine. Table 4 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms in patients converted from other AEDs to either high dose oxcarbazepine or low dose (300 mg) oxcarbazepine. Note that in some of these monotherapy studies patients who dropped out during a preliminary tolerability phase are not included in the tables.



 *      Table  3 Treatment  -Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in a Controlled Clinical Study of Adjunctive Therapy in Adults (Events in at Least 2% of Patients Treated with 2400 mg/day of Oxcarbazepine and Numerically More Frequent than in the Placebo Group)  
  
                                                       Oxcarbazepine Dosage (mg/day)    
  Body System/  Adverse Event                          OXC 600  N=163  %    OXC 1200  N=171  %    OXC 2400  N=126  %    Placebo  N=166  %    
  Body as a Whole                                                                                                           
                                                      Fatigue                                             
                                                                                                            15               12                15                7               
  Asthenia                                             6                3                 6                 5               
  Edema Legs                                           2                1                 2                 1               
  Weight Increase                                      1                2                 2                 1               
  Feeling Abnormal                                     0                1                 2                 0               
  Cardiovascular System                                                                                                     
  Hypotension                                          0                1                 2                 0               
  Digestive System                                                                                                          
  Nausea                                               15               25                29                10              
  Vomiting                                             13               25                36                5               
  Pain Abdominal                                       10               13                11                5               
  Diarrhea                                             5                6                 7                 6               
  Dyspepsia                                            5                5                 6                 2               
  Constipation                                         2                2                 6                 4               
  Gastritis                                            2                1                 2                 1               
  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                                       
  Hyponatremia                                         3                1                 2                 1               
  Musculoskeletal System                                                                                                    
  Muscle Weakness                                      1                2                 2                 0               
  Sprains and Strains                                  0                2                 2                 1               
  Nervous System                                                                                                            
  Headache                                             32               28                26                23              
  Dizziness                                            26               32                49                13              
  Somnolence                                           20               28                36                12              
  Ataxia                                               9                17                31                5               
  Nystagmus                                            7                20                26                5               
  Gait Abnormal                                        5                10                17                1               
  Insomnia                                             4                2                 3                 1               
  Tremor                                               3                8                 16                5               
  Nervousness                                          2                4                 2                 1               
  Agitation                                            1                1                 2                 1               
  Coordination Abnormal                                1                3                 2                 1               
  EEG Abnormal                                         0                0                 2                 0               
  Speech Disorder                                      1                1                 3                 0               
  Confusion                                            1                1                 2                 1               
  Cranial Injury NOS                                   1                0                 2                 1               
  Dysmetria                                            1                2                 3                 0               
  Thinking Abnormal                                    0                2                 4                 0               
  Respiratory System                                                                                                        
  Rhinitis                                             2                4                 5                 4               
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                                       
  Acne                                                 1                2                 2                 0               
  Special Senses                                                                                                            
  Diplopia                                             14               30                40                5               
  Vertigo                                              6                12                15                2               
  Vision Abnormal                                      6                14                13                4               
  Accommodation Abnormal                               0                0                 2                 0               
             Table    4 Treatment    -Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in Controlled Clinical Studies of Monotherapy in Adults Previously Treated with Other AEDs (Events in at Least 2% of Patients Treated with 2400 mg/day of Oxcarbazepine and Numerically More Frequent than in the Low Dose Control Group  )
 


                                                                 Oxcarbazepine Dosage (mg/day)    
  Body System/  Adverse Event                                    2400  N=86  %            300  N=86  %                    
  Body as a Whole                                                                                                         
  Fatigue                                                        21                       5                               
  Fever                                                          3                        0                               
  Allergy                                                        2                        0                               
  Edema Generalized                                              2                        1                               
  Pain Chest                                                     2                        0                               
  Digestive System                                                                                                        
  Nausea                                                         22                       7                               
  Vomiting                                                       15                       5                               
  Diarrhea                                                       7                        5                               
  Dyspepsia                                                      6                        1                               
  Anorexia                                                       5                        3                               
  Pain Abdominal                                                 5                        3                               
  Mouth Dry                                                      3                        0                               
  Hemorrhage Rectum                                              2                        0                               
  Toothache                                                      2                        1                               
  Hemic and Lymphatic System                                                                                              
  Lymphadenopathy                                                2                        0                               
  Infections and Infestations                                                                                             
  Infection Viral                                                7                        5                               
  Infection                                                      2                        0                               
  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                                     
  Hyponatremia                                                   5                        0                               
  Thirst                                                         2                        0                               
  Nervous System                                                                                                          
  Headache                                                       31                       15                              
  Dizziness                                                      28                       8                               
  Somnolence                                                     19                       5                               
  Anxiety                                                        7                        5                               
  Ataxia                                                         7                        1                               
  Confusion                                                      7                        0                               
  Nervousness                                                    7                        0                               
  Insomnia                                                       6                        3                               
  Tremor                                                         6                        3                               
  Amnesia                                                        5                        1                               
  Convulsions Aggravated                                         5                        2                               
  Emotional Lability                                             3                        2                               
  Hypoesthesia                                                   3                        1                               
  Coordination Abnormal                                          2                        1                               
  Nystagmus                                                      2                        0                               
  Speech Disorder                                                2                        0                               
  Respiratory System                                                                                                      
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                              10                       5                               
  Coughing                                                       5                        0                               
  Bronchitis                                                     3                        0                               
  Pharyngitis                                                    3                        0                               
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                                     
  Hot Flushes                                                    2                        1                               
  Purpura                                                        2                        0                               
  Special Senses                                                                                                          
  Vision Abnormal                                                14                       2                               
  Diplopia                                                       12                       1                               
  Taste Perversion                                               5                        0                               
  Vertigo                                                        3                        0                               
  Earache                                                        2                        1                               
  Ear Infection NOS                                              2                        0                               
  Urogenital and Reproductive System                                                                                      
  Urinary Tract Infection                                        5                        1                               
  Micturition Frequency                                          2                        1                               
  Vaginitis                                                      2                        0                               
             Controlled Clinical Study of Monotherapy in Adults Not Previously Treated with other AEDs:    Table 5 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms in a controlled clinical study of monotherapy in adults not previously treated with other AEDs that occurred in at least 2% of adult patients with epilepsy treated with oxcarbazepine or placebo and were numerically more common in the patients treated with oxcarbazepine.
 

 *      Table  5 Treatment  -Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in a Controlled Clinical Study of Monotherapy in Adults Not Previously Treated with Other AEDs (Events in at Least 2% of Patients Treated with Oxcarbazepine and Numerically More Frequent than in the Placebo Group)  
  
  Body System/  Adverse Event                                 Oxcarbazepine  N=55  %            Placebo  N=49  %          
  Body as a Whole                                                                                                         
  Falling Down NOS                                            4                                 0                         
  Digestive System                                                                                                        
  Nausea                                                      16                                12                        
  Diarrhea                                                    7                                 2                         
  Vomiting                                                    7                                 6                         
  Constipation                                                5                                 0                         
  Dyspepsia                                                   5                                 4                         
  Musculoskeletal System                                                                                                  
  Pain Back                                                   4                                 2                         
  Nervous System                                                                                                          
  Dizziness                                                   22                                6                         
  Headache                                                    13                                10                        
  Ataxia                                                      5                                 0                         
  Nervousness                                                 5                                 2                         
  Amnesia                                                     4                                 2                         
  Coordination Abnormal                                       4                                 2                         
  Tremor                                                      4                                 0                         
  Respiratory System                                                                                                      
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                           7                                 0                         
  Epistaxis                                                   4                                 0                         
  Infection Chest                                             4                                 0                         
  Sinusitis                                                   4                                 2                         
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                                     
  Rash                                                        4                                 2                         
  Special Senses                                                                                                          
  Vision Abnormal                                             4                                 0                         
             Controlled Clinical Studies of Adjunctive Therapy/Monotherapy in Pediatric Patients Previously Treated with other AEDs:    Table 6 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that occurred in at least 2% of pediatric patients with epilepsy treated with oxcarbazepine or placebo as adjunctive treatment and were numerically more common in the patients treated with oxcarbazepine.
 

 *      Table   6 Treatment  -Emergent Adverse Event Incidence in Controlled Clinical Studies of Adjunctive Therapy/Monotherapy in Pediatric Patients Previously Treated with Other AEDs (Events in at Least 2% of Patients Treated with Oxcarbazepine and Numerically More Frequent than in the Placebo Group)  
  
  Body System/  Adverse Event                                 Oxcarbazepine  N=171  %            Placebo  N=139  %         
  Body as a Whole                                                                                                          
  Fatigue                                                     13                                 9                         
  Allergy                                                     2                                  0                         
  Asthenia                                                    2                                  1                         
  Digestive System                                                                                                         
  Vomiting                                                    33                                 14                        
  Nausea                                                      19                                 5                         
  Constipation                                                4                                  1                         
  Dyspepsia                                                   2                                  0                         
  Nervous System                                                                                                           
  Headache                                                    31                                 19                        
  Somnolence                                                  31                                 13                        
  Dizziness                                                   28                                 8                         
  Ataxia                                                      13                                 4                         
  Nystagmus                                                   9                                  1                         
  Emotional Lability                                          8                                  4                         
  Gait Abnormal                                               8                                  3                         
  Tremor                                                      6                                  4                         
  Speech Disorder                                             3                                  1                         
  Concentration Impaired                                      2                                  1                         
  Convulsions                                                 2                                  1                         
                                                             Muscle Contractions Involuntary                            
                                                                                                                          2                                  1                         
  Respiratory System                                                                                                       
  Rhinitis                                                    10                                 9                         
  Pneumonia                                                   2                                  1                         
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                                      
  Bruising                                                    4                                  2                         
  Sweating Increased                                          3                                  0                         
  Special Senses                                                                                                           
  Diplopia                                                    17                                 1                         
  Vision Abnormal                                             13                                 1                         
  Vertigo                                                     2                                  0                         
           Other Events Observed in Association with the Administration of Oxcarbazepine  
 

 In the paragraphs that follow, the adverse events, other than those in the preceding tables or text, that occurred in a total of 565 children and 1,574 adults exposed to oxcarbazepine and that are reasonably likely to be related to drug use are presented. Events common in the population, events reflecting chronic illness and events likely to reflect concomitant illness are omitted particularly if minor. They are listed in order of decreasing frequency. Because the reports cite events observed in open label and uncontrolled trials, the role of oxcarbazepine in their causation cannot be reliably determined.



     Body as a Whole:    fever, malaise, pain chest precordial, rigors, weight decrease.



     Cardiovascular System:     bradycardia, cardiac failure, cerebral hemorrhage, hypertension, hypotension postural, palpitation, syncope, tachycardia.



     Digestive System:    appetite increased, blood in stool, cholelithiasis, colitis, duodenal ulcer, dysphagia, enteritis, eructation, esophagitis, flatulence, gastric ulcer, gingival bleeding, gum hyperplasia, hematemesis, hemorrhage rectum, hemorrhoids, hiccup, mouth dry, pain biliary, pain right hypochondrium, retching, sialoadenitis, stomatitis, stomatitis ulcerative.



     Hematologic and Lymphatic System:     thrombocytopenia.



     Laboratory Abnormality:    gamma-GT increased, hyperglycemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, liver enzymes elevated, serum transaminase increased.



     Musculoskeletal System:     hypertonia muscle.



     Nervous System:     aggressive reaction, amnesia, anguish, anxiety, apathy, aphasia, aura, convulsions aggravated, delirium, delusion, depressed level of consciousness, dysphonia, dystonia, emotional lability, euphoria, extrapyramidal disorder, feeling drunk, hemiplegia, hyperkinesia, hyperreflexia, hypoesthesia, hypokinesia, hyporeflexia, hypotonia, hysteria, libido decreased, libido increased, manic reaction, migraine, muscle contractions involuntary, nervousness, neuralgia, oculogyric crisis, panic disorder, paralysis, paroniria, personality disorder, psychosis, ptosis, stupor, tetany.



     Respiratory System:     asthma, dyspnea, epistaxis, laryngismus, pleurisy.



     Skin and Appendages:    acne, alopecia, angioedema, bruising, dermatitis contact, eczema, facial rash, flushing, folliculitis, heat rash, hot flushes, photosensitivity reaction, pruritus genital, psoriasis, purpura, rash erythematous, rash maculopapular, vitiligo, urticaria.



     Special Senses:     accommodation abnormal, cataract, conjunctival hemorrhage, edema eye, hemianopia, mydriasis, otitis externa, photophobia, scotoma, taste perversion, tinnitus, xerophthalmia.



     Surgical and Medical Procedures:     procedure dental oral, procedure female reproductive, procedure musculoskeletal, procedure skin.



     Urogenital and Reproductive System:     dysuria, hematuria, intermenstrual bleeding, leukorrhea, menorrhagia, micturition frequency, pain renal, pain urinary tract, polyuria, priapism, renal calculus.



     Other:    Systemic lupus erythematosus.



   6.2     Post-Marketing and Other Experience

  The following adverse events have been observed in named patient programs or post-marketing experience. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Anaphylaxis:    [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]



     Digestive System:    pancreatitis and/or lipase and/or amylase increase



     Hematologic and Lymphatic Systems:    aplastic anemia [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]



     Metabolism:    hypothyroidism



     Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:     erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ], Acute Generalized Exanthematous Pustulosis (AGEP)



     Musculoskeletal, connective tissue and bone disorders:    There have been reports of decreased bone mineral density, osteoporosis and fractures in patients on long-term therapy with oxcarbazepine.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hyponatremia (  5.1  ) 
 *    Anaphylactic Reactions and Angioedema (  5.2  ) 
 *    Patients with a Past History of Hypersensitivity Reaction to Carbamazepine (  5.3  ) 
 *    Serious Dermatological Reactions (  5.4  ) 
 *    Suicidal Behavior and Ideation (  5.5  ) 
 *    Withdrawal of AEDs (  5.6  ) 
 *    Cognitive/Neuropsychiatric Adverse Events (  5.7  ) 
 *    Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS)/Multi-Organ Hypersensitivity (  5.8  ) 
 *    Hematologic Events (  5.9  ) 
 *    Seizure Control During Pregnancy (  5.10  ) 
 *    Laboratory Tests (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Hyponatremia



  Clinically significant hyponatremia (sodium &lt;125 mmol/L) can develop during oxcarbazepine use. In the 14 controlled epilepsy studies 2.5% of oxcarbazepine-treated patients (38/1,524) had a sodium of less than 125 mmol/L at some point during treatment, compared to no such patients assigned placebo or active control (carbamazepine and phenobarbital for adjunctive and monotherapy substitution studies, and phenytoin and valproate for the monotherapy initiation studies). Clinically significant hyponatremia generally occurred during the first three months of treatment with oxcarbazepine, although there were patients who first developed a serum sodium &lt;125 mmol/L more than one year after initiation of therapy. Most patients who developed hyponatremia were asymptomatic but patients in the clinical trials were frequently monitored and some had their oxcarbazepine dose reduced, discontinued, or had their fluid intake restricted for hyponatremia. Whether or not these maneuvers prevented the occurrence of more severe events is unknown. Cases of symptomatic hyponatremia have been reported during post-marketing use. In clinical trials, patients whose treatment with oxcarbazepine was discontinued due to hyponatremia generally experienced normalization of serum sodium within a few days without additional treatment.



 Measurement of serum sodium levels should be considered for patients during maintenance treatment with oxcarbazepine, particularly if the patient is receiving other medications known to decrease serum sodium levels (for example, drugs associated with inappropriate ADH secretion) or if symptoms possibly indicating hyponatremia develop (e.g., nausea, malaise, headache, lethargy, confusion, obtundation, or increase in seizure frequency or severity).



    5.2     Anaphylactic Reactions and Angioedema



  Rare cases of anaphylaxis and angioedema involving the larynx, glottis, lips and eyelids have been reported in patients after taking the first or subsequent doses of oxcarbazepine. Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema can be fatal. If a patient develops any of these reactions after treatment with oxcarbazepine, the drug should be discontinued and an alternative treatment started. These patients should not be rechallenged with the drug [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].



    5.3     Patients with a Past History of Hypersensitivity Reaction to Carbamazepine



  Patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to carbamazepine should be informed that approximately 25%-30% of them will experience hypersensitivity reactions with oxcarbazepine. For this reason patients should be specifically questioned about any prior experience with carbamazepine, and patients with a history of hypersensitivity reactions to carbamazepine should ordinarily be treated with oxcarbazepine only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk. If signs or symptoms of hypersensitivity develop, oxcarbazepine should be discontinued immediately [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.2, 5.8)  ].



    5.4     Serious Dermatological Reactions



   Serious dermatological reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have been reported in both children and adults in association with oxcarbazepine use. Such serious skin reactions may be life threatening, and some patients have required hospitalization, with very rare reports of fatal outcome. The median time of onset for reported cases was 19 days after treatment initiation. Recurrence of the serious skin reactions following rechallenge with oxcarbazepine has also been reported.  



  The reporting rate of TEN and SJS associated with oxcarbazepine use, which is generally accepted to be an underestimate due to underreporting, exceeds the background incidence rate estimates by a factor of 3- to 10-fold. Estimates of the background incidence rate for these serious skin reactions in the general population range between 0.5 to 6 cases per million-person years. Therefore, if a patient develops a skin reaction while taking oxcarbazepine, consideration should be given to discontinuing oxcarbazepine use and prescribing another antiepileptic medication.  



   Association with HLA-B*1502    



  Patients carrying the HLA-B*1502 allele may be at increased risk for SJS/TEN with oxcarbazepine treatment.  



  Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA) allele B*1502 increases the risk for developing SJS/TEN in patients treated with carbamazepine. The chemical structure of oxcarbazepine is similar to that of carbamazepine. Available clinical evidence, and data from nonclinical studies showing a direct interaction between oxcarbazepine and HLA-B*1502 protein, suggest that the HLA-B*1502 allele may also increase the risk for SJS/TEN with oxcarbazepine.  



  The frequency of HLA-B*1502 allele ranges from 2 to 12% in Han Chinese populations, is about 8% in Thai populations, and above 15% in the Philippines and in some Malaysian populations. Allele frequencies up to about 2% and 6% have been reported in Korea and India, respectively. The frequency of the HLA-B*1502 allele is negligible in people from European descent, several African populations, indigenous peoples of the Americas, Hispanic populations, and in Japanese (&lt;1%).  



  Testing for the presence of the HLA-B*1502 allele should be considered in patients with ancestry in genetically at-risk populations, prior to initiating treatment with oxcarbazepine. The use of oxcarbazepine should be avoided in patients positive for HLA-B*1502 unless the benefits clearly outweigh the risks. Consideration should also be given to avoid the use of other drugs associated with SJS/TEN in HLA-B*1502 positive patients, when alternative therapies are otherwise equally acceptable. Screening is not generally recommended in patients from populations in which the prevalence of HLA-B*1502 is low, or in current oxcarbazepine users, as the risk of SJS/TEN is largely confined to the first few months of therapy, regardless of HLA-B*1502 status.  



  The use of HLA-B*1502 genotyping has important limitations and must never substitute for appropriate clinical vigilance and patient management. The role of other possible factors in the development of, and morbidity from, SJS/TEN, such as antiepileptic drug (AED) dose, compliance, concomitant medications, comorbidities, and the level of dermatologic monitoring have not been well characterized.  



    5.5     Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including oxcarbazepine, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed. Table 2 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 2  Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis 
  Indication               Placebo Patients with Events Per 1,000 Patients    Drug Patients with Events Per 1,000 Patients    Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients    Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events Per 1,000 Patients    
  Epilepsy                 1.0                    3.4                    3.5                          2.4                      
  Psychiatric              5.7                    8.5                    1.5                          2.9                      
  Other                    1.0                    1.8                    1.9                          0.9                      
  Total                    2.4                    4.3                    1.8                          1.9                      
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing oxcarbazepine or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.6     Withdrawal of AEDs



  As with all antiepileptic drugs, oxcarbazepine should be withdrawn gradually to minimize the potential of increased seizure frequency.



    5.7     Cognitive/Neuropsychiatric Adverse Events



  Use of oxcarbazepine has been associated with central nervous system-related adverse events. The most significant of these can be classified into three general categories: 1) cognitive symptoms including psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration, and speech or language problems, 2) somnolence or fatigue, and 3) coordination abnormalities, including ataxia and gait disturbances.



  Adult Patients  



 In one large, fixed-dose study, oxcarbazepine was added to existing AED therapy (up to three concomitant AEDs). By protocol, the dosage of the concomitant AEDs could not be reduced as oxcarbazepine was added, reduction in oxcarbazepine dosage was not allowed if intolerance developed, and patients were discontinued if unable to tolerate their highest target maintenance doses. In this trial, 65% of patients were discontinued because they could not tolerate the 2400 mg/day dose of oxcarbazepine on top of existing AEDs. The adverse events seen in this study were primarily CNS related and the risk for discontinuation was dose related.



 In this trial, 7.1% of oxcarbazepine-treated patients and 4% of placebo-treated patients experienced a cognitive adverse event. The risk of discontinuation for these events was about 6.5 times greater on oxcarbazepine than on placebo. In addition, 26% of oxcarbazepine-treated patients and 12% of placebo-treated patients experienced somnolence. The risk of discontinuation for somnolence was about 10 times greater on oxcarbazepine than on placebo. Finally, 28.7% of oxcarbazepine-treated patients and 6.4% of placebo-treated patients experienced ataxia or gait disturbances. The risk for discontinuation for these events was about seven times greater on oxcarbazepine than on placebo.



 In a single placebo-controlled monotherapy trial evaluating 2400 mg/day of oxcarbazepine, no patients in either treatment group discontinued double-blind treatment because of cognitive adverse events, somnolence, ataxia, or gait disturbance.



 In the two dose-controlled conversion to monotherapy trials comparing 2400 mg/day and 300 mg/day oxcarbazepine, 1.1% of patients in the 2400 mg/day group discontinued double-blind treatment because of somnolence or cognitive adverse events compared to 0% in the 300 mg/day group. In these trials, no patients discontinued because of ataxia or gait disturbances in either treatment group.



  Pediatric Patients  



 A study was conducted in pediatric patients (3 to 17 years old) with inadequately controlled partial seizures in which oxcarbazepine was added to existing AED therapy (up to two concomitant AEDs). By protocol, the dosage of concomitant AEDs could not be reduced as oxcarbazepine was added. Oxcarbazepine was titrated to reach a target dose ranging from 30 mg/kg to 46 mg/kg (based on a patient's body weight with fixed doses for predefined weight ranges).



 Cognitive adverse events occurred in 5.8% of oxcarbazepine-treated patients (the single most common event being concentration impairment, 4 of 138 patients) and in 3.1% of patients treated with placebo. In addition, 34.8% of oxcarbazepine-treated patients and 14.0% of placebo-treated patients experienced somnolence. (No patient discontinued due to a cognitive adverse event or somnolence.). Finally, 23.2% of oxcarbazepine-treated patients and 7.0% of placebo-treated patients experienced ataxia or gait disturbances. Two (1.4%) oxcarbazepine-treated patients and 1 (0.8%) placebo-treated patient discontinued due to ataxia or gait disturbances.



    5.8     Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS)/Multi-Organ Hypersensitivity



   Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms (DRESS), also known as multi-organ hypersensitivity, has occurred with oxcarbazepine. Some of these events have been fatal or life-threatening. DRESS typically, although not exclusively, presents with fever, rash, and/or lymphadenopathy, in association with other organ system involvement, such as hepatitis, nephritis, hematologic abnormalities, myocarditis, or myositis, sometimes resembling an acute viral infection. Eosinophilia is often present. This disorder is variable in its expression, and other organ systems not noted here may be involved. It is important to note that early manifestations of hypersensitivity (e.g., fever, lymphadenopathy) may be present even though rash is not evident. If such signs or symptoms are present, the patient should be evaluated immediately. Oxcarbazepine should be discontinued if an alternative etiology for the signs or symptoms cannot be established. Although there are no case reports to indicate cross sensitivity with other drugs that produce this syndrome, the experience amongst drugs associated with DRESS/multi-organ hypersensitivity would indicate this to be a possibility [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)].  



    5.9     Hematologic Events



  Rare reports of pancytopenia, agranulocytosis, and leukopenia have been seen in patients treated with oxcarbazepine during postmarketing experience. Discontinuation of the drug should be considered if any evidence of these hematologic events develop.



    5.10     Seizure Control During Pregnancy



  Due to physiological changes during pregnancy, plasma levels of the active metabolite of oxcarbazepine, the 10-monohydroxy derivative (MHD), may gradually decrease throughout pregnancy. It is recommended that patients be monitored carefully during pregnancy. Close monitoring should continue through the postpartum period because MHD levels may return after delivery. 



    5.11     Laboratory Tests



  Serum sodium levels below 125 mmol/L have been observed in patients treated with oxcarbazepine [ see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]. Experience from clinical trials indicates that serum sodium levels return toward normal when the oxcarbazepine dosage is reduced or discontinued, or when the patient was treated conservatively (e.g., fluid restriction).



 Laboratory data from clinical trials suggest that oxcarbazepine use was associated with decreases in T4, without changes in T3 or TSH.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
