<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="oxtellar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Hyponatremia [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Anaphylactic Reactions and Angioedema [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions in Patients with Hypersensitivity to Carbamazepine [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Serious Dermatological Reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Withdrawal of AEDs [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Multi-Organ Hypersensitivity [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Hematologic Reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Risk of Seizures in the Pregnant Patient [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Laboratory Tests [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most commonly observed (&gt;=5%) and more frequent than placebo adverse reactions were: dizziness, somnolence, headache, balance disorder, tremor, vomiting, diplopia, asthenia, and fatigue (    6.1    ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Supernus, Inc. at (1-866-398-0833) or contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety data presented below are from 384 patients with partial epilepsy who received Oxtellar XRTM (366 adults and 18 children) with concomitant AEDs.



 In addition, safety data presented below are from a total of 2,288 patients with seizure disorders treated with immediate-release oxcarbazepine; 1,832 were adults and 456 were children.



     Most Common Adverse Reactions Reported by Adult Patients Receiving Concomitant AEDs in Oxtellar XRTM Clinical Studies    



 Table 3 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of adult patients with epilepsy treated with Oxtellar XRTM or placebo and concomitant AEDs and that were numerically more common in the patients treated with any dose of Oxtellar XRTM than in patients receiving placebo.



 The overall incidence of adverse reactions appeared to be dose related, particularly during the Titration Period. The most commonly observed (&gt;= 5%) adverse reactions seen in association with Oxtellar XRTM and more frequent than in placebo-treated patients were: dizziness, somnolence, headache, balance disorder, tremor, vomiting, diplopia, and asthenia.



 Table 3: Adverse Reaction Incidence in a Controlled Clinical Study of Oxtellar XRTM with Concomitant AEDs in Adults* 
                              Oxtellar XR2400 mg/dayN=123%      Oxtellar XR1200 mg/dayN=122%      PlaceboN=121%             
 Any System / Any Term      69                         57                         55                          
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                      
     Dizziness              41                         20                         15                          
     Somnolence             14                         12                         9                           
     Headache               15                         8                          7                           
     Balance Disorder       7                          5                          5                           
     Tremor                 1                          5                          2                           
     Nystagmus              3                          3                          1                           
     Ataxia                 1                          3                          1                           
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                      
     Vomiting               15                         6                          9                           
     Abdominal Pain Upper   0                          3                          1                           
     Dyspepsia              0                          3                          1                           
     Gastritis              0                          3                          2                           
   Eye Disorders                                                                                              
     Diplopia               13                         10                         4                           
     Vision Blurred         1                          4                          3                           
     Visual Impairment      1                          3                          0                           
   General Disorders And AdministrationSite Conditions                                                                                      
     Asthenia               7                          3                          1                           
     Fatigue                3                          6                          1                           
     Gait Disturbance       0                          3                          1                           
     Drug Intolerance       2                          0                          0                           
   Infections And Infestations                                                                                      
     Nasopharyngitis        0                          3                          0                           
     Sinusitis              0                          3                          2                           
 * Reported by &gt;= 2% of Patients Treated with Oxtellar XRTM and Numerically More Frequent than in the Placebo Group   
        Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Oxtellar XRTM Treatment:  Approximately 23.3% of the 366 adult patients receiving Oxtellar XRTM in clinical studies discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions most commonly associated with discontinuation of Oxtellar XRTM (reported by &gt;=2%) were: dizziness (9.8%), vomiting (5.3%), nausea (3.7%), diplopia (3.2%), and somnolence (2.4%).
 

     Adjunctive Therapy with Oxtellar XRTM in Pediatric Patients 4 to 16 Years Old Previously Treated with other AEDs    



 In a pharmacokinetic study in 18 children (age 4-16 years) with partial seizures treated with different doses of Oxtellar XRTM, the observed adverse reactions seen in association with Oxtellar XRTM were similar to those seen in adults.



     Most Common Adverse Reactions in Immediate-Release Oxcarbazepine Controlled Clinical Studies    



   Controlled Clinical Studies of Adjunctive Therapy with Immediate-Release Oxcarbazepine in Adults Previously Treated with other AEDs:  Table 4 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of adult patients with epilepsy treated with immediate-release oxcarbazepine or placebo with concomitant AEDs and that were numerically more common in the patients treated with any dose of immediate-release oxcarbazepine than in placebo. As immediate-release oxcarbazepine and Oxtellar XRTM were not examined in the same trial, adverse event frequencies cannot be directly compared between the two formulations.



 Table 4: Adverse Reaction Incidence in a Controlled Clinical Study of Immediate Release Oxcarbazepine with Concomitant AEDs in Adults* 
                                                        
   Immediate-Release Oxcarbazepine Dosage (mg/day)      PlaceboN = 166%           
   OXC 600N = 163%            OXC 1200N = 171%           OXC 2400N = 126%          
   Body as a Whole           
     Fatigue                15                         12                         15                         7                           
     Asthenia               6                          3                          6                          5                           
     Edema Legs             2                          1                          2                          1                           
     Weight Increase        1                          2                          2                          1                           
     Feeling Abnormal       0                          1                          2                          0                           
   Cardiovascular System     
     Hypotension            0                          1                          2                          0                           
   Digestive System          
     Nausea                 15                         25                         29                         10                          
     Vomiting               13                         25                         36                         5                           
     Pain Abdominal         10                         13                         11                         5                           
     Diarrhea               5                          6                          7                          6                           
     Dyspepsia              5                          5                          6                          2                           
     Constipation           2                          2                          6                          4                           
     Gastritis              2                          1                          2                          1                           
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders     
     Hyponatremia           3                          1                          2                          1                           
   Musculoskeletal System     
     Muscle Weakness        1                          2                          2                          0                           
     Sprains and Strains    0                          2                          2                          1                           
   Nervous System            
     Headache               32                         28                         26                         23                          
     Dizziness              36                         32                         49                         13                          
     Somnolence             20                         28                         36                         12                          
     Ataxia                 9                          17                         31                         5                           
     Nystagmus              7                          20                         26                         5                           
     Gait Abnormal          5                          10                         17                         1                           
     Insomnia               4                          2                          3                          1                           
     Tremor                 3                          8                          16                         5                           
     Nervousness            2                          4                          2                          1                           
     Agitation              1                          1                          2                          1                           
     Coordination Abnormal  1                          3                          2                          1                           
     EEG Abnormal           0                          0                          2                          0                           
     Speech Disorder        1                          1                          3                          0                           
     Confusion              1                          1                          2                          1                           
     Cranial Injury NOS     1                          0                          2                          1                           
     Dysmetria              1                          2                          3                          0                           
     Thinking Abnormal      0                          2                          4                          0                           
   Respiratory System        
     Rhinitis               2                          4                          5                          4                           
   Skin and Appendages       
     Acne                   1                          2                          2                          0                           
   Special Senses            
     Diplopia               14                         30                         40                         5                           
     Vertigo                6                          12                         15                         2                           
     Vision Abnormal        6                          14                         13                         4                           
     Accommodation Abnormal  0                          0                          2                          0                           
 * Events in at Least 2% of Patients Treated with 2400mg/day of Immediate-Release Oxcarbazepine and Numerically More Frequent than in the Placebo Group   
        Other Reactions Observed in Association with the Administration of Immediate-Release Oxcarbazepine  
 

 In the paragraphs that follow, the adverse reactions, other than those in the preceding tables or text, that occurred in a total of 565 children and 1,574 adults exposed to immediate-release oxcarbazepine and that are reasonably likely to be related to drug use are presented. Events common in the population, events reflecting chronic illness and events likely to reflect concomitant illness are omitted particularly if minor. They are listed in order of decreasing frequency. Because the reports cite reactions observed in open label and uncontrolled trials, the role of immediate-release oxcarbazepine in their causation cannot be reliably determined.



     Body as a Whole:    fever, malaise, pain chest precordial, rigors, weight decrease.



     Cardiovascular System:    bradycardia, cardiac failure, cerebral hemorrhage, hypertension, hypotension postural, palpitation, syncope, tachycardia.



     Digestive System:    appetite increased, blood in stool, cholelithiasis, colitis, duodenal ulcer, dysphagia, enteritis, eructation, esophagitis, flatulence, gastric ulcer, gingival bleeding, gum hyperplasia, hematemesis, hemorrhage rectum, hemorrhoids, hiccup, mouth dry, pain biliary, pain right hypochondrium, retching, sialoadenitis, stomatitis, stomatitis ulcerative.



     Hematologic and Lymphatic System:    thrombocytopenia.



     Laboratory Abnormality:    gamma-GT increased, hyperglycemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, liver enzymes elevated, serum transaminase increased.



     Musculoskeletal System:    hypertonia muscle.



     Nervous System:    aggressive reaction, amnesia, anguish, anxiety, apathy, aphasia, aura, convulsions aggravated, delirium, delusion, depressed level of consciousness, dysphonia, dystonia, emotional lability, euphoria, extrapyramidal disorder, feeling drunk, hemiplegia, hyperkinesia, hyperreflexia, hypoesthesia, hypokinesia, hyporeflexia, hypotonia, hysteria, libido decreased, libido increased, manic reaction, migraine, muscle contractions involuntary, nervousness, neuralgia, oculogyric crisis, panic disorder, paralysis, paroniria, personality disorder, psychosis, ptosis, stupor, tetany.



     Respiratory System:    asthma, bronchitis, coughing, dyspnea, epistaxis, laryngismus, pleurisy.



     Skin and Appendages:    acne, alopecia, angioedema, bruising, dermatitis contact, eczema, facial rash, flushing, folliculitis, heat rash, hot flushes, photosensitivity reaction, pruritus genital, psoriasis, purpura, rash erythematous, rash maculopapular, vitiligo, urticaria.



     Special Senses:    accommodation abnormal, cataract, conjunctival hemorrhage, edema eye, hemianopia, mydriasis, otitis externa, photophobia, scotoma, taste perversion, tinnitus, xerophthalmia.



     Urogenital and Reproductive System:    dysuria, hematuria, intermenstrual bleeding, leukorrhea, menorrhagia, micturition frequency, pain renal, pain urinary tract, polyuria, priapism, renal calculus, urinary tract infection.



     Other:    Systemic lupus erythematosus.



   6.2 Postmarketing and Other Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of immediate-release oxcarbazepine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Body as a Whole:    multi-organ hypersensitivity disorders characterized by features such as rash, fever, lymphadenopathy, abnormal liver function tests, eosinophilia and arthralgia [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )  ]



     Anaphylaxis:    [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ]



     Digestive System:    pancreatitis and/or lipase and/or amylase increase



     Hematologic and Lymphatic Systems:    aplastic anemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )  ]



     Skin and Appendages:    erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )  ]
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hyponatremia: Monitor sodium as recommended. (   5.1   ) 
 *   Anaphylactic Reactions and Angioedema. Discontinue if occurs (   5.2   ) 
 *   Patients with a Past History of Hypersensitivity Reaction to Carbamazepine: Only use based upon risk benefit (   5.3   ) 
 *   Serious Dermatological Reactions: Discontinue if observed (   5.4   ) 
 *   Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for symptoms (   5.5   ) 
 *   Withdrawal of Oxtellar XRTM: Withdrawal gradually (   5.6   ) 
 *   Multi-Organ Hypersensitivity: Discontinue if suspected (   5.7   ) 
 *   Hematologic Reactions: Discontinue if suspected (   5.8   ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hyponatremia



  Clinically significant hyponatremia (sodium &lt;125 mmol/L) may develop during Oxtellar XRTM use. Serum sodium levels less than 125 mmol/L have occurred in immediate-release oxcarbazepine-treated patients generally in the first three months of treatment. However, clinically significant hyponatremia may develop more than a year after initiating therapy.



 Most immediate-release oxcarbazepine-treated patients who developed hyponatremia were asymptomatic in clinical trials. However, some of these patients had their dose reduced, discontinued, or had their fluid intake restricted for hyponatremia. Serum sodium levels returned toward normal when the dosage was reduced or discontinued, or when the patient was treated conservatively (e.g., fluid restriction). Post-marketing cases of symptomatic hyponatremia have been reported during post-marketing use of immediate-release oxcarbazepine.



 Among treated patients in a controlled trial of adjunctive therapy with Oxtellar XRTM in 366 adults with complex partial seizures, 1 patient receiving 2400 mg experienced a severe reduction in serum sodium (117 mEq/L) requiring discontinuation from treatment, while 2 other patients receiving 1200 mg experienced serum sodium concentrations low enough (125 and 126 mEq/L) to require discontinuation from treatment. The overall incidence of clinically significant hyponatremia in patients treated with Oxtellar XRTM was 1.2%, although slight shifts in serum sodium concentrations from Normal to Low (&lt;135 mEq/L) were observed for the 2400 mg (6.5%) and 1200 mg (9.8%) groups compared to placebo (1.7%). Measure serum sodium concentrations if patients develop symptoms of hyponatremia (e.g., nausea, malaise, headache, lethargy, confusion, obtunded consciousness, or increase in seizure frequency or severity). Consider measurement of serum sodium concentrations during treatment with Oxtellar XRTM, particularly if the patient receives concomitant medications known to decrease serum sodium levels (for example, drugs associated with inappropriate ADH secretion).



    5.2 Anaphylactic Reactions and Angioedema



  Rare cases of anaphylaxis and angioedema involving the larynx, glottis, lips and eyelids have been reported in patients after taking the first or subsequent doses of immediate-release oxcarbazepine. Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema can be fatal. If a patient develops any of these reactions after treatment with Oxtellar XRTM, discontinue the drug and initiate an alternative treatment. Do not rechallenge these patients with Oxtellar XRTM.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions in Patients with Hypersensitivity to Carbamazepine



  Inform patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to carbamazepine that approximately 25%-30% of them will experience hypersensitivity reactions with Oxtellar XRTM. Question patients about any prior adverse reactions with carbamazepine. Patients with a history of hypersensitivity reactions to carbamazepine should ordinarily be treated with Oxtellar XRTM only if the potential benefit justifies the potential risk. Discontinue Oxtellar XRTM immediately if signs or symptoms of hypersensitivity develop [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8    )].



    5.4 Serious Dermatological Reactions



  Serious dermatological reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have occurred in both children and adults in treated with immediate-release oxcarbazepine use. The median time of onset for reported cases was 19 days. Such serious skin reactions may be life threatening, and some patients have required hospitalization with very rare reports of fatal outcome. Recurrence of the serious skin reactions following rechallenge with immediate-release oxcarbazepine has also been reported.



 The reporting rate of TEN and SJS associated with immediate-release oxcarbazepine use, which is generally accepted to be an underestimate due to underreporting, exceeds the background incidence rate estimates by a factor of 3- to 10-fold. Estimates of the background incidence rate for these serious skin reactions in the general population range between 0.5 to 6 cases per million-person years. Therefore, if a patient develops a skin reaction while taking Oxtellar XRTM, consider discontinuing Oxtellar XRTM use and prescribing another AED.



    5.5 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including Oxtellar XRTM, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Monitor patients treated with any AED for any indication for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed. Table 2 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 2:           Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis 
 Indication                 PlaceboPatients withEvents per1,000 Patients  Drug Patientswith Events per1,000 Patients  Relative Risk:Incidence ofEvents in DrugPatients/Incidencein PlaceboPatients  RiskDifference:AdditionalDrug Patientswith Events per1,000 Patients   
 Epilepsy                   1.0                        3.4                        3.5                        2.4                         
 Psychiatric                5.7                        8.5                        1.5                        2.9                         
 Other                      1.0                        1.8                        1.9                        0.9                         
 Total                      2.4                        4.3                        1.8                        1.9                         
      The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing Oxtellar XRTM or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during Oxtellar XRTM treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.6 Withdrawal of AEDs



  As with all AEDs, Oxtellar XRTM should be withdrawn gradually to minimize the potential of increased seizure frequency.



    5.7 Multi-Organ Hypersensitivity



  Multi-organ hypersensitivity reactions have occurred in close temporal association (median time to detection 13 days: range 4-60) to the initiation of immediate-release oxcarbazepine therapy in adult and pediatric patients. Although there have been a limited number of reports, many of these cases resulted in hospitalization and some were life-threatening. Signs and symptoms of this disorder were diverse; however, patients typically, although not exclusively, presented with fever and rash associated with other organ system involvement. These included the following: hematologic and lymphatic (e.g., eosinophilia, thrombocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, leukopenia, neutropenia, splenomegaly), hepatobiliary (e.g., hepatitis, liver function test abnormalities), renal (e.g., proteinuria, nephritis, oliguria, renal failure), muscles and joints (e.g., joint swelling, myalgia, arthralgia, asthenia), nervous system (e.g., hepatic encephalopathy), respiratory (e.g., dyspnea, pulmonary edema, asthma, bronchospasm, interstitial lung disease), hepatorenal syndrome, pruritus, and angioedema. Because the disorder is variable in its expression, other organ system symptoms and signs, not noted here, may occur. If this reaction is suspected, discontinue Oxtellar XRTM and initiate an alternative treatment.



    5.8 Hematologic Reactions



  Rare reports of pancytopenia, agranulocytosis, and leukopenia have been seen in patients treated with immediate-release oxcarbazepine during post-marketing experience. Discontinuation of Oxtellar XRTM should be considered if any evidence of these hematologic reactions develops.



    5.9 Risk of Seizures in the Pregnant Patient



  Due to physiological changes during pregnancy, plasma concentrations of the active metabolite of oxcarbazepine, the 10-monohydroxy derivative (MHD), may gradually decrease throughout pregnancy. Monitor patients carefully during pregnancy and through the postpartum period because MHD concentrations may increase after delivery.



    5.10 Laboratory Tests



  Laboratory data from clinical trials suggest that immediate-release oxcarbazepine may be associated with decreases in T4, without changes in T3 or TSH.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
