<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="oxycodone0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described, or described in greater detail, in other sections:



 *  Respiratory depression [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Seizures [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.12)   ] 
 *  Hypotension [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and increases in the serum amylase level [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
    Serious adverse reactions that may be associated with oxycodone therapy in clinical use are those observed with other opioid analgesics and include: respiratory depression, respiratory arrest, circulatory depression, cardiac arrest, hypotension, and/or shock [see    Overdose (10.1)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1  ,  5.3)    ].
 

 The less severe adverse events seen on initiation of therapy with oxycodone are also typical opioid side effects. These events are dose dependent, and their frequency depends on the clinical setting, the patient's level of opioid tolerance, and host factors specific to the individual. They should be expected and managed as a part of opioid analgesia. The most frequent of these include nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, and pruritus.



 In many cases the frequency of adverse events during initiation of opioid therapy may be minimized by careful individualization of starting dosage, slow titration and the avoidance of large rapid swings in plasma concentration of the opioid. Many of these adverse events will abate as therapy is continued and some degree of tolerance is developed, but others may be expected to remain throughout therapy.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In all patients for whom dosing information was available (n=191) from the open-label and double-blind studies involving immediate-release oxycodone, the following adverse events were recorded in oxycodone treated patients with an incidence &gt;= 3%. In descending order of frequency they were: nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, pruritus, insomnia, dizziness, asthenia, and somnolence.



 The following adverse experiences occurred in less than 3% of patients involved in clinical trials with oxycodone:



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain, accidental injury, allergic reaction, back pain, chills and fever, fever, flu syndrome, infection, neck pain, pain, photosensitivity reaction, and sepsis.



   Cardiovascular:  deep thrombophlebitis, heart failure, hemorrhage, hypotension, migraine, palpitation, and tachycardia.



   Digestive:  anorexia, diarrhea, dyspepsia, dysphagia, gingivitis, glossitis, and nausea and vomiting.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  anemia and leukopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  edema, gout, hyperglycemia, iron deficiency anemia and peripheral edema.



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, arthritis, bone pain, myalgia and pathological fracture.



   Nervous:  agitation, anxiety, confusion, dry mouth, hypertonia, hypesthesia, nervousness, neuralgia, personality disorder, tremor, and vasodilation.



   Respiratory:  bronchitis, cough increased, dyspnea, epistaxis, laryngismus, lung disorder, pharyngitis, rhinitis, and sinusitis.



   Skin and Appendages:  herpes simplex, rash, sweating, and urticaria.



   Special Senses:  amblyopia.



   Urogenital:  urinary tract infection



    EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions are nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, pruritus, insomnia, dizziness, asthenia, and somnolence. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS CONTACT FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF MEDICATION ERRORS

    WARNING: RISK OF MEDICATION ERRORS  

  Take care when prescribing and administering Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution 5 mg per 5 mL to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between mg and mL, and other oxycodone solutions with different concentrations, which could result in accidental overdose and death. Take care to ensure the proper dose is communicated and dispensed.



 Keep Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution out of the reach of children. In case of accidental ingestion, seek emergency medical help immediately.



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: RISK OF MEDICATION ERRORS  



  



 Take care when prescribing and administering Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution 5 mg per 5 mL to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between mg and mL, and other oxycodone solutions with different concentrations, which could result in accidental overdose and death. Take care to ensure the proper dose is communicated and dispensed.



 Keep Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution out of the reach of children. In case of accidental ingestion, seek emergency medical help immediately.



 









    BOXED WARNING: 

    MEDICATION GUIDEOxycodone Hydrochloride(ox-ee-CO-dohn) (CII)Oral Solution  



 Rx Only



     IMPORTANT: Keep Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution in a safe place away from children. Accidental use by a child is a medical emergency and can cause death. If a child accidentally takes Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution, get emergency help right away.  



   Read the Medication Guide that comes with Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution before you start taking it and each time you get a new prescription. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or your treatment.



   What Is The Most Important Information I Should Know About Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution?  



   Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution can cause serious side effects, including death.  



 *  Take Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution exactly as prescribed by your healthcare provider. If you take the wrong dose or strength of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution, you could overdose and die. 
 *  It is especially important when you take Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution that you know exactly what dose and strength to take, and the right way to measure your medicine. Your healthcare provider or pharmacist should show you the right way to measure your medicine. Always use the dosing cup provided with Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to help make sure you measure the right amount. 
 *  Do not drink alcohol. Using alcohol with Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may increase your risk of dangerous side effects, including death. 
      What is Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution?  
 

 Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution is in a group of drugs called narcotic pain medicine. Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution is only for adults who have moderate to severe pain.



 *  A prescription medicine that is used to manage moderate to severe pain that is expected to last a short period of time (acute), and pain that continues around-the-clock and is expected to last for a long period of time (chronic). 
 *  Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution is a federally controlled substance (CII) because it is a strong opioid pain medicine that can be abused by people who abuse prescription medicines or street drugs. 
 *  Prevent theft, misuse or abuse. Keep Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution in a safe place to keep it from being stolen. Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution can be a target for people who misuse or abuse prescription medicines or street drugs. 
 *  Never give Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to anyone else, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them or even cause death. 
 *  Selling or giving away this medicine is against the law. 
 *  It is not known if Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution is safe and effective in children under age 18 years of age. 
      Who Should Not Take Oxycodone Oral Solution?  
 

   Do not take Oxycodone if you:  



 *  are having breathing problems and there is no emergency medical equipment nearby 
 *  have a bowel blockage called paralytic ileus 
 *  are having an asthma attack or have severe asthma, trouble breathing, or lung problems 
 *  are allergic to oxycodone or any of the ingredients in Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution?  
 

   Before taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution, tell your healthcare provider if you:  



 *  have trouble breathing or lung problems 
 *  have had a head injury 
 *  have liver or kidney problems 
 *  have adrenal gland problems, such as Addison's disease 
 *  have severe scoliosis that affects your breathing 
 *  have thyroid problems 
 *  have problems urinating or enlargement of your prostate 
 *  have or had convulsions or seizures 
 *  have a past or present drinking problem or alcoholism 
 *  have hallucinations (seeing or hearing things that are not really there) or other severe mental problems 
 *  have constipation or other bowel problems 
 *  have problems with your pancreas or gallbladder 
 *  have past or present substance abuse or drug addiction 
 *  have any other medical conditions 
 *  are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. It is not known if Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution will harm your unborn baby. Talk to your healthcare provider if you are pregnant or plan to become pregnant.If you take Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution regularly before your baby is born, your newborn baby may have signs of withdrawal because their body has become used to the medicine. Signs of withdrawal in a newborn baby can include:irritabilitybeing very activeproblems sleepinghigh pitched cryvomitingdiarrhea or more stools than normalweight lossshaking (tremors)If you are taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution right before your baby is born, your baby could have breathing problems. 
 *  are breast-feeding or plan to breastfeed. Some Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution passes into your breast milk. A nursing baby could become very sleepy or have difficulty breathing or feeding well. If you stop breastfeeding, your baby may have withdrawal symptoms. See the list of withdrawal symptoms above. You and your healthcare provider should decide if you will take Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution or breastfeed. 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take  , including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Sometimes the doses of medicines that you take with Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may need to be changed if used together. Be especially careful about taking other medicines that make you sleepy such as:
 

 *  sleeping pills 
 *  other pain medicines 
 *  anti-nausea medicines 
 *  tranquilizers 
 *  muscle relaxants 
 *  anti-anxiety medicines 
 *  antihistamines 
 *  anti-depressants 
 *  monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs): Do not take Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution if you already take an MAOI or within 14 days after you stop taking an MAOI medicine 
    Ask your healthcare provider if you are not sure if your medicine is one listed above.
 

 Do not take other medicines while using Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution until you have talked with your healthcare provider or pharmacist. They will tell you if it is safe to take other medicines with Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution.



   Know the medicines you take. Keep a list of them and show it to your healthcare provider and pharmacist when you get a new medicine.  



   How Should I Take Oxycodone?  



 *  See "What is the most important information I should know about Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution?" 
 *  Take Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution exactly as prescribed. Do not change your dose unless your healthcare provider tells you to. Your healthcare provider may change your dose after seeing how the medicine affects you. Call your healthcare provider if your pain is not well controlled with your prescribed dose of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. 
 *  Make sure you understand exactly how to measure your dose. Always use the dosing cup provided with our Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to help make sure you measure the right amount. See the Patient Instructions for Use at the end of this Medication Guide for information about how to measure your dose the right way. Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure what dose of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution you should take or if you are not sure how to use the dosing cup. 
 *  Do not stop taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution suddenly. If you have been taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution for more than a few weeks, stopping it suddenly can make you sick with withdrawal symptoms (for example, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anxiety, and shivering). If your healthcare provider decides you no longer need Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution, ask how to slowly reduce this medicine. Do not stop taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution without talking to your healthcare provider. 
 *  If you miss a dose, take it as soon as possible. If it is almost time for your next dose, skip the missed dose and go back to your regular dosing schedule. Do not take 2 doses at one time unless your healthcare provider tells you to. 
 *  If you take too much Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution call your healthcare provider or your local Poison Control Center right away or go to the nearest hospital emergency room right away. 
 *  Talk with your healthcare provider regularly about your pain to see if you still need to take Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. 
      What Should I Avoid While Taking Oxycodone?  
 

 *  You should not drink alcohol while using Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. Drinking alcohol with Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may increase your risk of having dangerous side effects or death. 
 *  Do not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities, especially when you start taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution and when your dose is changed, until you know how Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution affects you. Oxycodone can make you sleepy. Ask your healthcare provider to tell you when it is okay to do these activities. 
      What are the Possible Side Effects of Oxycodone?  
 

   Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution can cause serious side effects, including:  



 *  See "What is the most important information I should know about Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution?" 
 *  Oxycodone can cause serious breathing problems that can become life-threatening, especially if Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution is used the wrong way. Call your healthcare provider or get help right away if:your breathing slows downyou have shallow breathing (little chest movement with breathing)you feel faint, dizzy, confused, oryou have any other unusual symptomsThese can be symptoms that you have taken too much Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution (overdose) or the dose is too high for you. These symptoms may lead to serious problems or death if not treated right away. 
 *  Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution can cause your blood pressure to drop. This can make you feel dizzy if you get up too fast from sitting or lying down. Low blood pressure is also more likely to happen if you take other medicines that can also lower your blood pressure. Severe low blood pressure can happen if you lose blood or take certain other medicines. 
 *  Oxycodone can cause physical dependence. Do not stop taking Oxycodone or any other opioid without talking to your healthcare provider about how to slowly stop your medicine. You could become sick with uncomfortable withdrawal symptoms because your body has become used to these medicines. Physical dependence is not the same as drug addiction. Tell your healthcare provider if you have any of these symptoms of withdrawal while slowly stopping Oxycodone:feel restlesstearing eyessweatingchills or hair on your arms "stand up"muscle aches, backachedilated pupils of your eyesfeel irritable or anxioustrouble sleepingrunny noseyawningnausea, loss of appetite, vomitingdiarrhea, stomach area (abdominal) crampsincrease in your blood pressurebreathing faster, or your heart beats faster 
 *  There is a chance of abuse or addiction with Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. The chance is higher if you are or have been addicted to or abused other medicines, street drugs, or alcohol, or if you have a history of mental problems. 
 *  Seizures: Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may cause seizures or make seizures that you already have worse. 
      Call your healthcare provider if you have any of the symptoms listed above.  
 

   Common side effects of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution include:  




 nauseaconstipationvomitingheadacheitchingtrouble sleeping  dizzinessweaknessdrowsinesssweatinglightheadedness   
        Constipation (not often enough or hard bowel movements) is a very common side effect of pain medicines (opioids) including Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. Talk to your healthcare provider about dietary changes, and the use of laxatives (medicines to treat constipation) and stool softeners to prevent or treat constipation while taking Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution.
 

 Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away.



 These are not all the possible side effects of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.



 Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.



   How should I store Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution?  



 *  Store Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution at controlled room temperature between 68 degrees F - 77 degrees F (20 degrees C - 25 degrees C). 
 *  Protect Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution from moisture and light. 
 *  When Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution is no longer needed, the unused solution should be destroyed by flushing down the toilet. 
      Keep Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution out of the reach of children. Accidental overdose by a child is a medical emergency and can lead to death.  
 

   General information about Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution for a condition for which it was not prescribed.



   Do not give your Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have. Selling or giving away Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may harm others, may cause death, and is against the law.  



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You can ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for information about Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution that is written for healthcare professionals.



 For more information about Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution, contact VistaPharm, Inc. at (727) 530-1633.



   What are the ingredients in Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution?  



   Active ingredient: oxycodone hydrochloride  



   Inactive ingredients:   anhydrous citric acid, FD&amp;C red #40, glycerin, poloxamer 188, purified water, raspberry flavor, sodium benzoate and sorbitol solution.



 This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.



   Manufactured by:    VistaPharm  (r)    Largo, FL 33771



 VP210001/12  Rx Only  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Use caution when prescribing, dispensing, and administering Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between different concentrations and between mg and mL, which could result in accidental overdose and death. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Increased risk or respiratory depression in elderly, debilitated patients, those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnea, or upper airway obstruction. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Oxycodone hydrochloride is a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to other opioids. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Assess patients for their clinical risks for opioid abuse or addiction prior to being prescribed opioids. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Additive CNS depressive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Increased risk of respiratory depression and of elevation of cerebrospinal fluid pressure in patients with head injury, intracranial lesions or pre-existing increase in intracranial pressure. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Risk of severe hypotension in patients with compromised ability to maintain blood pressure. (  5.6  ) 
 *  May obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal conditions. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Use with caution in patients with biliary tract disease and acute pancreatitis. (  5.8  ) 
 *  The mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery may be impaired. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors may increase opioid effects. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Medication Errors



  Use caution when prescribing, dispensing, and administering Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to avoid dosing errors due to confusion between mg and mL, and other oxycodone solutions with different concentrations, which could result in accidental overdose and death. Use caution to ensure the dose is communicated clearly and dispensed accurately. Always use the enclosed calibrated measuring cup when administering Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to ensure the dose is measured and administered accurately.



    5.2 Respiratory Depression



  Respiratory depression is the primary risk of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution. Respiratory depression occurs most frequently in elderly or debilitated patients, and in those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or upper airway obstruction, in whom even moderate therapeutic doses may significantly decrease pulmonary ventilation, or following large initial doses in non-tolerant patients, or when opioids are given in conjunction with other agents that depress respiration.



 Use Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution with extreme caution in patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and in patients having substantially decreased respiratory reserve (e.g., severe kyphoscoliosis), hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression. In such patients, even usual therapeutic doses of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may increase airway resistance and decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea. Consider alternative non-opioid analgesics, and use Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution only under careful medical supervision at the lowest effective dose in such patients.



    5.3 Misuse and Abuse of Opioids



  Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution is a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to other opioids.



 Such drugs are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders. Diversion of Schedule II products is an act subject to criminal penalty.



 Patients should be assessed for their clinical risks for opioid abuse or addiction prior to being prescribed opioids.



 Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse or abuse.



 Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may be abused by injecting the product. These practices pose a significant risk to the abuser that could result in overdose and death [see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2)  and  Overdosage (10)  ].  



 Concerns about abuse, addiction, and diversion should not prevent the proper management of pain. Healthcare professionals should contact their State Professional Licensing Board or State Controlled Substances Authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.4 Interactions with Alcohol and Drugs of Abuse



  Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may be expected to have additive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs that cause central nervous system depression because respiratory depression, hypotension, profound sedation, coma or death may result [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ].  



    5.5 Use in Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  In the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a preexisting increase in intracranial pressure, the possible respiratory depressant effects of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution and its potential to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2retention) may be markedly exaggerated. Furthermore, Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution can produce effects on pupillary response and consciousness, which may obscure neurologic signs of further increases in intracranial pressure in patients with head injuries.



    5.6 Hypotensive Effect



  Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may cause severe hypotension in an individual whose ability to maintain blood pressure has been compromised by a depleted blood volume, or after concurrent administration with drugs such as phenothiazines or general anesthetics or other agents which compromise vasomotor tone. Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may produce orthostatic hypotension in ambulatory patients. Administer Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution with caution in hypovolemic patients, such as those suffering acute myocardial infarction, because oxycodone may cause or further aggravate their hypotension. Administer Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution with caution to patients in circulatory shock, since vasodilatation produced by the drug may further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure.



    5.7 Gastrointestinal Effects



  Do not administer Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, especially paralytic ileus because oxycodone hydrochloride diminishes propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and may prolong the obstruction.



 The administration of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal condition.



    5.8 Use in Pancreatic/Biliary Tract Disease



  Use Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution with caution in patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, as oxycodone hydrochloride may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and diminish biliary and pancreatic secretions.



    5.9 Special Risk Groups



  Use Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution with caution and in reduced dosages in patients with severe renal or hepatic impairment, Addison's disease, hypothyroidism, prostatic hypertrophy, or urethral stricture, and in elderly or debilitated patients [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  ] .  



 Exercise caution in the administration of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution to patients with CNS depression, toxic psychosis, acute alcoholism and delirium tremens. All opioids may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and all opioids may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings.



 Keep Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution out of the reach of children. In case of accidental ingestion, seek emergency medical help immediately.



    5.10 Driving and Operating Machinery



  Caution patients that oxycodone hydrochloride could impair the mental and/or physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery.



 Caution patients about the potential combined effects of Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution with other CNS depressants, including other opioids, phenothiazines, sedative/hypnotics and alcohol [see  Drug Interactions (7.)  ].  



    5.11 Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  Since the CYP3A4 isoenzyme plays a major role in the metabolism of oxycodone, drugs that alter CYP3A4 activity may cause changes in clearance of oxycodone which could lead to changes in oxycodone plasma concentrations. The expected clinical results with CYP3A4 inhibitors would be an increase in oxycodone plasma concentrations and possibly increased or prolonged opioid effects. The expected clinical results with CYP3A4 inducers would be a decrease in oxycodone plasma concentrations, lack of efficacy or, possibly, development of an abstinence syndrome in a patient who had developed physical dependence to oxycodone.



 If co-administration is necessary, caution is advised when initiating Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution treatment in patients currently taking, or discontinuing, CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers. Evaluate these patients at frequent intervals and consider dose adjustments until stable drug effects are achieved [see  Drug Interactions (7.4)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.12 Seizures



  Oxycodone Hydrochloride Oral Solution may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and all opioids may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
