<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="oxycodone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Interactions with Other CNS Depressants [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Hypotensive Effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  ,  5.10  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) were constipation, nausea, somnolence, dizziness, vomiting, pruritus, headache, dry mouth, asthenia, and sweating. (  6.1  )
 

   To report suspected adverse reactions, contact Impax Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-934-6729 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Adult Clinical Trial Experience 



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The safety of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS was evaluated in double-blind clinical trials involving 713 patients with moderate to severe pain of various etiologies.  In open-label studies of cancer pain, 187 patients received OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS in total daily doses ranging from 20 mg to 640 mg per day.  The average total daily dose was approximately 105 mg per day.



 OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may increase the risk of serious adverse reactions such as those observed with other opioid analgesics, including respiratory depression, apnea, respiratory arrest, circulatory depression, hypotension, or shock  [see    Overdosage (  10  )]  .



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) reported by patients in clinical trials comparing OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS with placebo are shown in Table 2 below:



 TABLE 2: Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;5%) 
 Adverse Reaction  Oxycodone HCl Extended-release Tablets(n=227)  Placebo(n=45)     
                  (%)              (%)               
  
  Constipation     (23)             (7)              
  Nausea           (23)             (11)             
  Somnolence       (23)             (4)              
  Dizziness        (13)             (9)              
  Pruritus         (13)             (2)              
  Vomiting         (12)             (7)              
  Headache         (7)              (7)              
  Dry Mouth        (6)              (2)              
  Asthenia         (6)              -                
  Sweating         (5)              (2)              
      In clinical trials, the following adverse reactions were reported in patients treated with OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS with an incidence between 1% and 5%:  
 

   Gastrointestinal disorders:   abdominal pain, diarrhea, dyspepsia, gastritis



   General disorders and administration site conditions:   chills, fever



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:   anorexia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:   twitching



   Psychiatric disorders:   abnormal dreams, anxiety, confusion, dysphoria, euphoria, insomnia, nervousness, thought abnormalities



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:   dyspnea, hiccups



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:   rash



   Vascular disorders:   postural hypotension



 The following adverse reactions occurred  in less than 1% of patients  involved in clinical trials:



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:   lymphadenopathy



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:   tinnitus



   Eye disorders:   abnormal vision



   Gastrointestinal disorders:   dysphagia, eructation, flatulence, gastrointestinal disorder, increased appetite, stomatitis



   General disorders and administration site conditions:   withdrawal syndrome (with and without seizures), edema, peripheral edema, thirst, malaise, chest pain, facial edema



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications:   accidental injury



   Investigations:   ST depression



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:   dehydration



   Nervous system disorders:   syncope, migraine, abnormal gait, amnesia, hyperkinesia, hypoesthesia, hypotonia, paresthesia, speech disorder, stupor, tremor, vertigo, taste perversion



   Psychiatric disorders:   depression, agitation, depersonalization, emotional lability, hallucination



   Renal and urinary disorders:   dysuria, hematuria, polyuria, urinary retention



   Reproductive system and breast disorders:   impotence



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:   cough increased, voice alteration



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:   dry skin, exfoliative dermatitis



 Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Patients 11 Years and Older



 The safety of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS has been evaluated in one clinical trial with 140 patients 11 to 16 years of age.  The median duration of treatment was approximately three weeks. The most frequently reported adverse events were vomiting, nausea, headache, pyrexia, and constipation.



 Table 3 includes a summary of the incidence of treatment emergent adverse events reported in &gt;=5% of patients.



 Table 3: Incidence of Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 5.0% Patients 11 to 16 Years 
   System Organ Class  Preferred Term      11 to 16 Years    (N=140)n (%)     
  Any Adverse Event &gt;= 5%   71 (51)          
                   
  GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS   56 (40)          
  Vomiting         30 (21)          
  Nausea           21 (15)          
  Constipation     13 (9)           
   Diarrhea        8 (6)            
                   
  GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS   32 (23)          
  Pyrexia          15 (11)          
                   
  METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS   9 (6)            
  Decreased appetite   7 (5)            
                   
  NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS   23 (16)          
  Pruritus         8 (6)            
                   
      The following adverse reactions occurred in a clinical trial of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS in patients 11 to 16 years of age with an incidence between &gt;=1.0% and &lt; 5.0%. Events are listed within each System/Organ Class.
 

   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  febrile neutropenia, neutropenia



   Cardiac disorders:  tachycardia



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal pain, gastroesophageal reflux disease



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  fatigue, pain, chills, asthenia



   Injury, poisoning, and procedural complications:  procedural pain, seroma



   Investigations:   oxygen saturation decreased, alanine aminotransferase increased, hemoglobin decreased, platelet count decreased, neutrophil count decreased, red blood cell count decreased, weight decreased



   Metabolic and nutrition disorders:  hypochloremia, hyponatraemia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  pain in extremity, musculoskeletal pain



   Nervous system disorders:  somnolence, hypoesthesia, lethargy, paresthesia



   Psychiatric disorders:   insomnia, anxiety, depression, agitation



   Renal and urinary disorders:  dysuria, urinary retention



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:   oropharyngeal pain



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  hyperhidrosis, rash



 



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of controlled-release oxycodone:  abuse, addiction, aggression, amenorrhea, cholestasis, completed suicide, death, dental caries, increased hepatic enzymes, hyperalgesia, hypogonadism, hyponatremia, ileus, intentional overdose, mood altered, muscular hypertonia, overdose, palpitations (in the context of withdrawal), seizures, suicidal attempt, suicidal ideation, syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion, and urticaria.



 Anaphylaxis has been reported with ingredients contained in OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS.  Advise patients how to recognize such a reaction and when to seek medical attention.



 In addition to the events listed above, the following have also been reported, potentially due to the swelling and hydrogelling property of the tablet: choking, gagging, regurgitation, tablets stuck in the throat and difficulty swallowing the tablet.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE and MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION

  WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE and MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION

      Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse    



   OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS expose patients and other users to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death.  Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS and monitor all patients regularly for the development of these behaviors or conditions   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



     Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression    



   Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of     OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS. Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of     OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS or following a dose increase  .    Instruct patients to     swallow OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS whole; crushing, chewing, or dissolving OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS can cause rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of oxycodone   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]      .   



     Accidental Ingestion    



   Accidental ingestion of even one dose of     OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, especially by children, can result in a fatal overdose of oxycodone   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



     Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome    



   Prolonged use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .  



     Cytochrome P450 3A4 Interaction    



   The concomitant use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS with all cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in oxycodone plasma concentrations, which could increase or prolong adverse drug effects and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression. In addition, discontinuation of a concomitantly used cytochrome P450 3A4 inducer may result in an increase in oxycodone plasma concentration. Monitor patients receiving OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS and any CYP3A4 inhibitor or inducer   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.14  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE and MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING     RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS expose users to risks of addictions, abuse and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors and conditions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients to swallow OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS whole to avoid exposure to a potentially fatal dose of oxycodone. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental ingestion of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, especially in children, can result in a fatal overdose of oxycodone. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
 *  Initiation of CYP3A4 inhibitors (or discontinuation of CYP3A4 inducers) can result in a fatal overdose of oxycodone from OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS. (5.14, 12.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Risk of life-threatening respiratory depression in elderly, cachectic, and debilitated patients, and in patients with chronic pulmonary disease : Monitor closely. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *   Severe hypotension : Monitor during dosage initiation and titration. Avoid use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS in patients with circulatory shock. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Risk of use in patients with increased intracranial pressure, brain tumors, head injury, or impaired consciousness :Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression.Avoid use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS in patients with impaired consciousness or coma. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Risk of obstruction in patients who have difficulty swallowing or have underlying GI disorders that may predispose them to obstruction :Consider use of an alternative analgesic. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS contain oxycodone, a Schedule II controlled substance. As an opioid, OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS expose users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )].  As modified-release products such as OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS deliver the opioid over an extended period of time, there is a greater risk for overdose and death due to the larger amount of oxycodone present [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  .



 Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS. Addiction can occur at recommended doses and if the drug is misused or abused.



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse or misuse prior to prescribing OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, and monitor all patients receiving OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS for the development of these behaviors or conditions.  Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed modified-release opioid formulations such as OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks and proper use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, and misuse.



 Abuse, or misuse of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS by crushing, chewing, snorting, or injecting the dissolved product will result in the uncontrolled delivery of oxycodone and can result in overdose and death [see Overdosage (  10  )    ].  



 Opioid agonists are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion.  Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper disposal of unused drug [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .  Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.2 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of modified-release opioids, even when used as recommended.  Respiratory depression, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see Overdosage (  10  )]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids. 



 While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dose increase. Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression when initiating therapy with OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS and following dose increases. 



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS are essential [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  .  Overestimating the OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS dose when converting patients from another opioid product can result in a fatal overdose with the first dose.  



 Accidental ingestion of even one dose of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, especially by children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of oxycodone.  



    5.3 Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Prolonged use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS during pregnancy can result in withdrawal signs in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available.



 Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome presents as irritability, hyperactivity and abnormal sleep pattern, high pitched cry, tremor, vomiting, diarrhea and failure to gain weight. The onset, duration, and severity of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome vary based on the specific opioid used, duration of use, timing and amount of last maternal use, and rate of elimination of the drug by the newborn.



    5.4 Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



  Hypotension and profound sedation, coma, or respiratory depression may result if OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS are used concomitantly with other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids).



 When considering the use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration of use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression.  Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that can cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS therapy is made, start with 1/3 to 1/2 the usual dose of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, monitor patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression and consider using a lower dose of the concomitant CNS depressant [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  ) and Dosage and Administration (  2.6  )]  .



    5.5 Use in Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



  Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS and when OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS are given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .



    5.6 Use in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Monitor patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression for respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy and titrating with OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, as in these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    Consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients if possible. 



    5.7 Hypotensive Effects



  OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may cause severe hypotension, including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is an increased risk in patients whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a reduced blood volume or concurrent administration of certain CNS depressant drugs (e.g., phenothiazines or general anesthetics) [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )   ]  .  Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dose of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS. In patients with circulatory shock, OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. Avoid the use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS in patients with circulatory shock.



    5.8 Use in Patients with Head Injury or Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Monitor patients taking OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors) for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS.  OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2retention can further increase intracranial pressure. Opioids may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury.



 Avoid the use of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS in patients with impaired consciousness or coma. 



    5.9 Difficulty in Swallowing and Risk for Obstruction in Patients at Risk for a Small Gastrointestinal Lumen



  There have been post-marketing reports of difficulty in swallowing OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS. These reports included choking, gagging, regurgitation and tablets stuck in the throat. Instruct patients not to pre-soak, lick or otherwise wet OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS prior to placing in the mouth, and to take one tablet at a time with enough water to ensure complete swallowing immediately after placing in the mouth.



 There have been rare post-marketing reports of cases of intestinal obstruction, and exacerbation of diverticulitis, some of which have required medical intervention to remove the tablet. Patients with underlying GI disorders such as esophageal cancer or colon cancer with a small gastrointestinal lumen are at greater risk of developing these complications. Consider use of an alternative analgesic in patients who have difficulty swallowing and patients at risk for underlying GI disorders resulting in a small gastrointestinal lumen.



    5.10 Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS are contraindicated in patients with GI obstruction, including paralytic ileus.  The oxycodone in OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi.  Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, for worsening symptoms.  Opioids may cause increases in the serum amylase.



    5.11 Use in Patients with Convulsive or Seizure Disorders



  The oxycodone in OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings.  Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS therapy.



    5.12 Avoidance of Withdrawal



  Avoid the use of mixed agonist/antagonist (i.e., pentazocine, nalbuphine, and butorphanol) or partial agonist (buprenorphine) analgesics in patients who have received or are receiving a course of therapy with a full opioid agonist analgesic, including OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS.  In these patients, mixed agonist/antagonist and partial agonist analgesics may reduce the analgesic effect and/or may precipitate withdrawal symptoms.



 When discontinuing OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, gradually taper the dose [see Dosage and Administration (  2.9  )]  . Do not abruptly discontinue OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS. 



    5.13 Driving and Operating Machinery



  OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS may impair the mental or physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery.  Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to the effects of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS and know how they will react to the medication.



    5.14 Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  Since the CYP3A4 isoenzyme plays a major role in the metabolism of OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS, drugs that alter CYP3A4 activity may cause changes in clearance of oxycodone which could lead to changes in oxycodone plasma concentrations.



 Inhibition of CYP3A4 activity by its inhibitors, such as macrolide antibiotics (e.g., erythromycin), azole-antifungal agents (e.g., ketoconazole), and protease inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir), may increase plasma concentrations of oxycodone and prolong opioid effects.



 CYP450 inducers, such as rifampin, carbamazepine, and phenytoin, may induce the metabolism of oxycodone and, therefore, may cause increased clearance of the drug which could lead to a decrease in oxycodone plasma concentrations, lack of efficacy or, possibly, development of an abstinence syndrome in a patient who had developed physical dependence to oxycodone.



 If co-administration is necessary, caution is advised when initiating OXYCODONE HCl EXTENDED-RELEASE TABLETS treatment in patients currently taking, or discontinuing, CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers.  Evaluate these patients at frequent intervals and consider dose adjustments until stable drug effects are achieved [see Drug Interactions(  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )].  



    5.15 Laboratory Monitoring



  Not every urine drug test for "opioids" or "opiates" detects oxycodone reliably, especially those designed for in-office use. Further, many laboratories will report urine drug concentrations below a specified "cut-off" value as "negative".  Therefore, if urine testing for oxycodone is considered in the clinical management of an individual patient, ensure that the sensitivity and specificity of the assay is appropriate, and consider the limitations of the testing used when interpreting results.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
