<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="oxycodone1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions that may be associated with oxycodone therapy in clinical use are those observed with other opioid analgesics and include: respiratory depression, respiratory arrest, circulatory depression, cardiac arrest, hypotension, and/or shock.



 The common adverse events seen on initiation of therapy with oxycodone are also typical opioid side effects. These events are dose dependent, and their frequency depends on the clinical setting, the patient's level of opioid tolerance, and host factors specific to the individual. They should be expected and managed as a part of opioid therapy. The most frequent of adverse events include nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, and pruritus.



 The frequency of adverse events during initiation of opioid therapy may be minimized by careful individualization of starting dosage, slow titration and the avoidance of large rapid swings in plasma concentration of the opioid. Many of these common adverse events may abate as therapy is continued and some degree of tolerance is developed, but others may be expected to remain throughout therapy.



 In all patients for whom dosing information was available (n=191) from the open-label and double-blind studies involving immediate-release oxycodone, the following adverse events were recorded in oxycodone treated patients with an incidence greater than or equal to 3%. In descending order of frequency they were: nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, pruritus, insomnia, dizziness, asthenia, and somnolence.



 The following adverse experiences occurred in less than 3% of patients involved in clinical trials with oxycodone:



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain, accidental injury, allergic reaction, back pain, chills and fever, fever, flu syndrome, infection, neck pain, pain, photosensitivity reaction, and sepsis.



   Cardiovascular:  deep thrombophlebitis, heart failure, hemorrhage, hypotension, migraine, palpitation, and tachycardia.



   Digestive:  anorexia, diarrhea, dyspepsia, dysphagia, gingivitis, glossitis, and nausea and vomiting.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  anemia and leukopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  edema, gout, hyperglycemia, iron deficiency anemia and peripheral edema.



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, arthritis, bone pain, myalgia and pathological fracture.



   Nervous:  agitation, anxiety, confusion, dry mouth, hypertonia, hypesthesia, nervousness, neuralgia, personality disorder, tremor, and vasodilation.



   Respiratory:  bronchitis, cough increased, dyspnea, epistaxis, laryngismus, lung disorder, pharyngitis, rhinitis, and sinusitis.



   Skin and Appendages:  herpes simplex, rash, sweating, and urticaria.



   Special Senses:  amblyopia.



   Urogenital:  urinary tract infection



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, pruritus, insomnia, dizziness, asthenia, and somnolence.  (6)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pharm-Olam at 1-866-511-6754 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Respiratory depression: Increased risk in elderly, debilitated patients, those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or upper airway obstruction.  (5.1)   
 *  Misuse, Abuse and Diversion: Oxycodone hydrochloride is a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to other opioids.  (5.2)   
 *  CNS effects: Additive CNS depressive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs.  (5.3)   
 *  Elevation of intracranial pressure: May be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, other intracranial lesions.  (5.4)   
 *  Hypotensive effect: Increased risk with compromised ability to maintain blood pressure.  (5.5)   
 *  Prolonged gastric obstruction: In patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, especially paralytic ileus.  (5.6)   
 *  Sphincter of Oddi spasm and diminished biliary/pancreatic secretions. Increased risk with biliary tract disease.  (5.7)   
 *  Special Risk Groups: Use with caution and in reduced dosages in patients with severe renal or hepatic impairment, Addison's disease, hypothyroidism, prostatic hypertrophy, or urethral stricture, elderly, CNS depression, toxic psychosis, acute alcoholism and delirium tremens, may aggravate or induce seizures.  (5.8)   
 *  Impaired mental/physical abilities: Caution must be used with potentially hazardous activities.  (5.9)   
 *  Concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors may increase opioid effects.  (5.10)   
    
 

   5.1 Respiratory Depression



 Respiratory depression is the primary risk of oxycodone hydrochloride. Respiratory depression occurs more frequently in elderly or debilitated patients and in those suffering from conditions accompanied by hypoxia, hypercapnia, or upper airway obstruction, in whom even moderate therapeutic doses may significantly decrease pulmonary ventilation. Use oxycodone hydrochloride with extreme caution in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale and in patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve (e.g., severe kyphoscoliosis), hypoxia, hypercapnia, or preexisting respiratory depression. In such patients, even usual therapeutic doses of oxycodone hydrochloride may increase airway resistance and decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea. Consider alternative non-opioid analgesics, and use oxycodone hydrochloride only under careful medical supervision at the lowest effective dose in such patients.



    5.2 Misuse, Abuse and Diversion of Opioids



 Oxycodone hydrochloride is an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance. Such drugs are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders. Diversion of Schedule II products is an act subject to criminal penalty. Oxycodone hydrochloride can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit. This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing oxycodone hydrochloride in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse, or diversion.



 Oxycodone hydrochloride may be abused by crushing, chewing, snorting or injecting the product. These practices pose a significant risk to the abuser that could result in overdose and death. [See DRUG ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE  (9)  ]



 Concerns about abuse, addiction, and diversion should not prevent the proper management of pain. Healthcare professionals should contact their State Professional Licensing Board or State Controlled Substances Authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.3 Interactions with Alcohol and Drugs of Abuse



 Oxycodone hydrochloride may be expected to have additive effects when used in conjunction with alcohol, other opioids, or illicit drugs that cause central nervous system depression because respiratory depression, hypotension, profound sedation, coma or death may result.    5.4 Use In Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure



 In the presence of head injury, intracranial lesions or a preexisting increase in intracranial pressure, the possible respiratory depressant effects of oxycodone hydrochloride and its potential to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure (resulting from vasodilation following CO2retention) may be markedly exaggerated. Furthermore, oxycodone hydrochloride can produce effects on pupillary response and consciousness, which may obscure neurologic signs of further increases in intracranial pressure in patients with head injuries.    5.5 Hypotensive Effect



 Oxycodone hydrochloride may cause severe hypotension in an individual whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a depleted blood volume or concurrent administration of drugs such as phenothiazines or general anesthetics. Oxycodone hydrochloride may produce orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. Administer oxycodone hydrochloride with caution to patients in circulatory shock, as vasodilation produced by the drug may further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure.



    5.6 Gastrointestinal Effects



 Do not administer oxycodone hydrochloride to patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, especially paralytic ileus because oxycodone hydrochloride diminishes propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and may prolong the obstruction. The administration of oxycodone hydrochloride may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal condition.



    5.7 Use In Pancreatic/Biliary Tract Disease



 Use oxycodone hydrochloride with caution in patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, as oxycodone hydrochloride may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi and diminish biliary and pancreatic secretions.    5.8 Special Risk Groups



 Use oxycodone hydrochloride with caution and in reduced dosages in patients with severe renal or hepatic impairment, Addison's disease, hypothyroidism, prostatic hypertrophy, or urethral stricture, and in elderly or debilitated patients. [See USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS  (8.5)  ] Exercise caution in the administration of oxycodone hydrochloride to patients with CNS depression, toxic psychosis, acute alcoholism and delirium tremens. All opioids may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and all opioids may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings.



 Keep Oxycodone Hydrochloride capsules out of the reach of children. In case of accidental ingestion, seek emergency medical help immediately.



    5.9 Driving and Operating Machinery



 Caution patients that oxycodone hydrochloride could impair the mental and/or physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. Caution patients about the potential combined effects of oxycodone hydrochloride with other CNS depressants, including other opioids, phenothiazines, sedative/hypnotics and alcohol. [See DRUG INTERACTIONS  (7)  ]    5.10 Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



 Since the CYP3A4 isoenzyme plays a major role in the metabolism of oxycodone, drugs that alter CYP3A4 activity may cause changes in clearance of oxycodone which could lead to changes in oxycodone plasma concentrations. The expected clinical results with CYP3A4 inhibitors would be an increase in oxycodone plasma concentrations and possibly increased or prolonged opioid effects. The expected clinical results with CYP3A4 inducers would be a decrease in oxycodone plasma concentrations, lack of efficacy or, possibly, development of an abstinence syndrome in a patient who had developed physical dependence to oxycodone. If co-administration is necessary, caution is advised when initiating oxycodone treatment in patients currently taking, or discontinuing, CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers. Evaluate these patients at frequent intervals and consider dose adjustments until stable drug effects are achieved. [ see Drug Interactions  (7.4)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)    ]
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
