<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="oxytocin1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions have been reported in the mother:



 Anaphylactic reaction                                Nausea



 Postpartum hemorrhage                            Vomiting



 Cardiac arrhythmia                                    Premature ventricular contractions



 Fatal afibrinogenemia                                Pelvic hematoma



 Excessive dosage or hypersensitivity to the drug may result in uterine hypertonicity, spasm, tetanic contraction, or rupture of the uterus.



 The possibility of increased blood loss and afibrinogenemia should be kept in mind when administering the drug.



 Severe water intoxication with convulsions and coma has occurred, associated with a slow oxytocin infusion over a 24-hour period. Maternal death due to oxytocin-induced water intoxication has been reported.



 The following adverse reactions have been reported in the fetus or infant:



 (Due to induced uterine motility)



     Bradycardia



     Premature ventricular contractions and other arrhythmias



     Permanent CNS or brain damage



     Fetal death



 (Due to use of oxytocin in the mother)



     Low Apgar scores at five minutes



     Neonatal jaundice



     Neonatal retinal hemorrhage
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: INDICATIONS AND USAGE

  INDICATIONS AND USAGE

  

    IMPORTANT NOTICE  Oxytocin is indicated for the medical rather than the

                                    elective induction of labor. Available data and information are

                                    inadequate to define the benefits-to-risks considerations in the

                                    use of the drug product for elective induction. Elective

                                    induction of labor is defined as the initiation of labor for

                                    convenience in an individual with a term pregnancy who is free

                                    of medical indications. 



   Antepartum

  Oxytocin is indicated for the initiation or improvement

                                    of uterine contractions, where this is desirable and considered

                                    suitable for reasons of fetal or maternal concern, in order to

                                    achieve early vaginal delivery. It is indicated for (1)

                                    induction of labor in patients with a medical indication for the

                                    initiation of labor, such as Rh problems, maternal diabetes,

                                    preeclampsia at or near term, when delivery is in the best

                                    interests of mother and fetus or when membranes are prematurely

                                    ruptured and delivery is indicated; (2) stimulation or

                                    reinforcement of labor, as in selected cases of uterine inertia;

                                    (3) as adjunctive therapy in the management of incomplete or

                                    inevitable abortion. In the first trimester, curettage is

                                    generally considered primary therapy. In second trimester

                                    abortion, oxytocin infusion will often be successful in emptying

                                    the uterus. Other means of therapy, however, may be required in

                                    such cases.



   Postpartum

  Oxytocin is indicated to produce uterine contractions

                                    during the third stage of labor and to control postpartum

                                    bleeding or hemorrhage.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
