<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ozurdex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   In controlled studies, the most common adverse reactions reported by 20-70% of patients were cataract, increased intraocular pressure and conjunctival hemorrhage. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Allergan at 1-800-433-8871 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reactions associated with ophthalmic steroids including  OZURDEX    (r)  include elevated intraocular pressure, which may be associated with optic nerve damage, visual acuity and field defects, posterior subcapsular cataract formation, secondary ocular infection from pathogens including herpes simplex, and perforation of the globe where there is thinning of the cornea or sclera.



     Retinal Vein Occlusion and Posterior Segment Uveitis  



 The following information is based on the combined clinical trial results from 3 initial, randomized, 6-month, sham-controlled studies (2 for retinal vein occlusion and 1 for posterior segment uveitis):



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported by Greater than 2% of Patients 
   MedDRA Term                                         OZURDEX      (r)    N=497 (%)    Sham  N=498 (%)         
 Intraocular pressure increased                      125 (25%)                   10 (2%)                   
 Conjunctival hemorrhage                             108 (22%)                   79 (16%)                  
 Eye pain                                            40 (8%)                     26 (5%)                   
 Conjunctival hyperemia                              33 (7%)                     27 (5%)                   
 Ocular hypertension                                 23 (5%)                     3 (1%)                    
 Cataract                                            24 (5%)                     10 (2%)                   
 Vitreous detachment                                 12 (2%)                     8 (2%)                    
 Headache                                            19 (4%)                     12 (2%)                   
         Increased IOP with  OZURDEX      (r)    peaked at approximately week 8. During the initial treatment period, 1% (3/421) of the patients who received  OZURDEX      (r)    required surgical procedures for management of elevated IOP.
 

 Following a second injection of  OZURDEX      (r)    in cases where a second injection was indicated, the overall incidence of cataracts was higher after 1 year.



     Diabetic Macular Edema  



 The following information is based on the combined clinical trial results from 2 randomized, 3-year, sham-controlled studies in patients with diabetic macular edema. Discontinuation rates due to the adverse reactions listed in  Table 2  were 3% in the  OZURDEX      (r)    group and 1% in the Sham group. The most common ocular (study eye) and non-ocular adverse reactions are shown in  Tables 2  and  3  :



 Table 2: Ocular Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;= 1% of Patients and Non-ocular Adverse Reactions Reported by &gt;= 5% of Patients 
  1 Includes cataract, cataract nuclear, cataract subcapsular, lenticular opacities in patients who were phakic at baseline. Among these patients, 61% of OZURDEX(r) subjects vs. 8% of sham-controlled subjects underwent cataract surgery.    
  2 243 of the 324 OZURDEX(r) subjects were phakic at baseline; 230 of 328 sham-controlled subjects were phakic at baseline.    
  
   MedDRA Term                                       OZURDEX      (r)    N=324 (%)    Sham  N=328 (%)           
   Ocular                                                                                                 
 Cataract  1                                       166/243  2  (68%)          49/230 (21%)                
 Conjunctival hemorrhage                           73 (23%)                   44 (13%)                    
 Visual acuity reduced                             28 (9%)                    13 (4%)                     
 Conjunctivitis                                    19 (6%)                    8 (2%)                      
 Vitreous floaters                                 16 (5%)                    6 (2%)                      
 Conjunctival edema                                15 (5%)                    4 (1%)                      
 Dry eye                                           15 (5%)                    7 (2%)                      
 Vitreous detachment                               14 (4%)                    8 (2%)                      
 Vitreous opacities                                11 (3%)                    3 (1%)                      
 Retinal aneurysm                                  10 (3%)                    5 (2%)                      
 Foreign body sensation                            7 (2%)                     4 (1%)                      
 Corneal erosion                                   7 (2%)                     3 (1%)                      
 Keratitis                                         6 (2%)                     3 (1%)                      
 Anterior Chamber Inflammation                     6 (2%)                     0 (0%)                      
 Retinal tear                                      5 (2%)                     2 (1%)                      
 Eyelid ptosis                                     5 (2%)                     2 (1%)                      
   Non-ocular                                                                                             
 Hypertension                                      41 (13%)                   21 (6%)                     
 Bronchitis                                        15 (5%)                    8 (2%)                      
             Increased Intraocular Pressure  
 

 Table 3: Summary of Elevated Intraocular Pressure (IOP) Related Adverse Reactions 
  * OZURDEX(r): 1 surgical trabeculectomy for steroid-induced IOP increase, 1 surgical trabeculectomy for iris neovascularization, 1 laser iridotomy, 1 surgical iridectomySham: 1 laser iridotomy    
  
   IOP                                                      Treatment: N (%)       
   OZURDEX      (r)      N=324                              Sham    N=328          
 IOP elevation &gt;=10 mm Hg from Baseline at any visit      91 (28%)                13 (4%)                  
 &gt;=30 mm Hg IOP at any visit                              50 (15%)                5 (2%)                   
 Any IOP lowering medication                              136 (42%)               32 (10%)                 
 Any surgical intervention for elevated IOP *             4 (1.2%)                1 (0.3%)                 
         The increase in mean IOP was seen with each treatment cycle, and the mean IOP generally returned to baseline between treatment cycles (at the end of the 6 month period) shown below:
 

   Figure 1: Mean IOP during the study  



  Figure 1     Cataracts and Cataract Surgery  



 At baseline, 243 of the 324  OZURDEX      (r)    subjects were phakic; 230 of 328 sham-controlled subjects were phakic. The incidence of cataract development in patients who had a phakic study eye was higher in the  OZURDEX      (r)    group (68%) compared with Sham (21%). The median time of cataract being reported as an adverse event was approximately 15 months in the  OZURDEX      (r)    group and 12 months in the Sham group. Among these patients, 61% of  OZURDEX      (r)    subjects vs. 8% of sham-controlled subjects underwent cataract surgery, generally between Month 18 and Month 39 (Median Month 21 for  OZURDEX      (r)    group and 20 for Sham) of the studies.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following reactions have been identified during post-marketing use of  OZURDEX    (r)  in clinical practice. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. The reactions, which have been chosen for inclusion due to either their seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to  OZURDEX    (r)  , or a combination of these factors, include: complication of device insertion (implant misplacement), device dislocation with or without corneal edema, endophthalmitis, hypotony of the eye (associated with vitreous leakage due to injection), and retinal detachment.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Intravitreal injections have been associated with endophthalmitis, eye inflammation, increased intraocular pressure, and retinal detachments. Patients should be monitored following the injection. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Use of corticosteroids may produce posterior subcapsular cataracts, increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and may enhance the establishment of secondary ocular infections due to bacteria, fungi, or viruses. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Intravitreal Injection-related Effects



  Intravitreal injections, including those with OZURDEX    (r)  , have been associated with endophthalmitis, eye inflammation, increased intraocular pressure, and retinal detachments. Patients should be monitored regularly following the injection [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



    5.2 Steroid-related Effects



  Use of corticosteroids including OZURDEX    (r)  may produce posterior subcapsular cataracts, increased intraocular pressure, and glaucoma. Use of corticosteroids may enhance the establishment of secondary ocular infections due to bacteria, fungi, or viruses [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  .



    Corticosteroids are not recommended to be used in patients with a history of ocular herpes simplex because of the potential for reactivation of the viral infection.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
