<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pamelor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Note -  Included in the following list are a few adverse reactions that have not been reported with this specific drug. However, the pharmacologic similarities among the tricyclic antidepressant drugs require that each of the reactions be considered when nortriptyline is administered.



   

      Cardiovascular -    Hypotension, hypertension, tachycardia, palpitation, myocardial infarction, arrhythmias, heart block, stroke.



   

      Psychiatric -    Confusional states (especially in the elderly) with hallucinations, disorientation, delusions; anxiety, restlessness, agitation; insomnia, panic, nightmares; hypomania; exacerbation of psychosis.



   

      Neurologic -    Numbness, tingling, paresthesias of extremities; incoordination, ataxia, tremors; peripheral neuropathy; extrapyramidal symptoms; seizures, alteration in EEG patterns; tinnitus.



   

      Anticholinergic -    Dry mouth and, rarely, associated sublingual adenitis; blurred vision, disturbance of accommodation, mydriasis; constipation, paralytic ileus; urinary retention, delayed micturition, dilation of the urinary tract.



   

      Allergic -    Skin rash, petechiae, urticaria, itching, photosensitization (avoid excessive exposure to sunlight); edema (general or of face and tongue), drug fever, cross-sensitivity with other tricyclic drugs.



   

      Hematologic -    Bone marrow depression, including agranulocytosis; eosinophilia; purpura; thrombocytopenia.



   

      Gastrointestinal -    Nausea and vomiting, anorexia, epigastric distress, diarrhea, peculiar taste, stomatitis, abdominal cramps, blacktongue.



   

      Endocrine -    Gynecomastia in the male, breast enlargement and galactorrhea in the female; increased or decreased libido, impotence; testicular swelling; elevation or depression of blood sugar levels; syndrome of inappropriate ADH (antidiuretic hormone) secretion.



   

      Other -    Jaundice (simulating obstructive), altered liver function; weight gain or loss; perspiration; flushing; urinary frequency, nocturia; drowsiness, dizziness, weakness, fatigue; headache; parotid swelling; alopecia.



   

      Withdrawal Symptoms -    Though these are not indicative of addiction, abrupt cessation of treatment after prolonged therapy may produce nausea, headache, and malaise.



     Postmarketing Experience  

  The following adverse drug reaction has been reported during post-approval use of Pamelor. Because this reaction is reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate frequency.



   

      Eye Disorders  -  angle-closure glaucoma 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs  



   Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of     nortriptyline hydrochloride or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber.     Nortriptyline hydrochloride is not approved for use in pediatric patients (      see         WARNINGS, Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk  ;   PRECAUTIONS, Information for Patients  ;       and         PRECAUTIONS, Pediatric Use  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
