<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="paxilcr" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The information included under the "Adverse Findings Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials With PAXIL CR" subsection of ADVERSE REACTIONS is based on data from 11 placebo-controlled clinical trials. Three of these studies were conducted in patients with major depressive disorder, 3 studies were done in patients with panic disorder, 1 study was conducted in patients with social anxiety disorder, and 4 studies were done in female patients with PMDD. Two of the studies in major depressive disorder, which enrolled patients in the age range 18 to 65 years, are pooled. Information from a third study of major depressive disorder, which focused on elderly patients (60 to 88 years), is presented separately as is the information from the panic disorder studies and the information from the PMDD studies. Information on additional adverse events associated with PAXIL CR and the immediate-release formulation of paroxetine hydrochloride is included in a separate subsection (see Other Events Observed During the Clinical Development of Paroxetine).



   Adverse Findings Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials With PAXIL CR:

  Adverse Events Associated With Discontinuation of Treatment

      Major Depressive Disorder    

  Ten percent (21/212) of patients treated with PAXIL CR discontinued treatment due to an adverse event in a pool of 2 studies of patients with major depressive disorder. The most common events (&gt;=1%) associated with discontinuation and considered to be drug related (i.e., those events associated with dropout at a rate approximately twice or greater for PAXIL CR compared to placebo) included the following:




                                        PAXIL CR   (n = 212)                Placebo   (n = 211)            
 Nausea                                3.7%                                0.5%                            
 Asthenia                              1.9%                                0.5%                            
 Dizziness                             1.4%                                0.0%                            
 Somnolence                            1.4%                                0.0%                            
         In a placebo-controlled study of elderly patients with major depressive disorder, 13% (13/104) of patients treated with PAXIL CR discontinued due to an adverse event. Events meeting the above criteria included the following:
 


                                        PAXIL CR   (n = 104)                Placebo   (n = 109)            
 Nausea                                2.9%                                0.0%                            
 Headache                              1.9%                                0.9%                            
 Depression                            1.9%                                0.0%                            
 LFT's abnormal                        1.9%                                0.0%                            
               Panic Disorder    
   Eleven percent (50/444) of patients treated with PAXIL CR in panic disorder studies discontinued treatment due to an adverse event. Events meeting the above criteria included the following:




                                        PAXIL CR   (n = 444)                Placebo   (n = 445)            
 Nausea                                2.9%                                0.4%                            
 Insomnia                              1.8%                                0.0%                            
 Headache                              1.4%                                0.2%                            
 Asthenia                              1.1%                                0.0%                            
               Social Anxiety Disorder    
   Three percent (5/186) of patients treated with PAXIL CR in the social anxiety disorder study discontinued treatment due to an adverse event. Events meeting the above criteria included the following:




                                        PAXIL CR   (n = 186)                Placebo   (n = 184)            
 Nausea                                2.2%                                0.5%                            
 Headache                              1.6%                                0.5%                            
 Diarrhea                              1.1%                                0.5%                            
               Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder    
   Spontaneously reported adverse events were monitored in studies of both continuous and intermittent dosing of PAXIL CR in the treatment of PMDD. Generally, there were few differences in the adverse event profiles of the 2 dosing regimens. Thirteen percent (88/681) of patients treated with PAXIL CR in PMDD studies of continuous dosing discontinued treatment due to an adverse event.



 The most common events (&gt;=1%) associated with discontinuation in either group treated with PAXIL CR with an incidence rate that is at least twice that of placebo in PMDD trials that employed a continuous dosing regimen are shown in the following table. This table also shows those events that were dose dependent (indicated with an asterisk) as defined as events having an incidence rate with 25 mg of PAXIL CR that was at least twice that with 12.5 mg of PAXIL CR (as well as the placebo group).




                                     PAXIL CR  25 mg   (n = 348)     PAXIL CR  12.5 mg   (n = 333)     Placebo   (n = 349)     
   TOTAL                            15%                      9.9%                    6.3%                   
 Nausea  a                          6.0%                     2.4%                    0.9%                   
 Asthenia                           4.9%                     3.0%                    1.4%                   
 Somnolence  a                      4.3%                     1.8%                    0.3%                   
 Insomnia                           2.3%                     1.5%                    0.0%                   
 Concentration Impaired  a          2.0%                     0.6%                    0.3%                   
 Dry mouth  a                       2.0%                     0.6%                    0.3%                   
 Dizziness  a                       1.7%                     0.6%                    0.6%                   
 Decreased Appetite  a              1.4%                     0.6%                    0.0%                   
 Sweating  a                        1.4%                     0.0%                    0.3%                   
 Tremor  a                          1.4%                     0.3%                    0.0%                   
 Yawn  a                            1.1%                     0.0%                    0.0%                   
 Diarrhea                           0.9%                     1.2%                    0.0%                   
          a.  Events considered to be dose dependent are defined as events having an incidence rate with 25 mg of PAXIL CR that was at least twice that with 12.5 mg of PAXIL CR (as well as the placebo group).
 

   Commonly Observed Adverse Events

      Major Depressive Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of PAXIL CR in a pool of 2 trials (incidence of 5.0% or greater and incidence for PAXIL CR at least twice that for placebo, derived from Table 2) were: Abnormal ejaculation, abnormal vision, constipation, decreased libido, diarrhea, dizziness, female genital disorders, nausea, somnolence, sweating, trauma, tremor, and yawning.



 Using the same criteria, the adverse events associated with the use of PAXIL CR in a study of elderly patients with major depressive disorder were: Abnormal ejaculation, constipation, decreased appetite, dry mouth, impotence, infection, libido decreased, sweating, and tremor.



       Panic Disorder    

  In the pool of panic disorder studies, the adverse events meeting these criteria were: Abnormal ejaculation, somnolence, impotence, libido decreased, tremor, sweating, and female genital disorders (generally anorgasmia or difficulty achieving orgasm).



       Social Anxiety Disorder    

  In the social anxiety disorder study, the adverse events meeting these criteria were: Nausea, asthenia, abnormal ejaculation, sweating, somnolence, impotence, insomnia, and libido decreased.



       Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of PAXIL CR either during continuous dosing or luteal phase dosing (incidence of 5% or greater and incidence for PAXIL CR at least twice that for placebo, derived from Table 6) were: Nausea, asthenia, libido decreased, somnolence, insomnia, female genital disorders, sweating, dizziness, diarrhea, and constipation.



 In the luteal phase dosing PMDD trial, which employed dosing of 12.5 mg/day or 25 mg/day of PAXIL CR limited to the 2 weeks prior to the onset of menses over 3 consecutive menstrual cycles, adverse events were evaluated during the first 14 days of each off-drug phase. When the 3 off-drug phases were combined, the following adverse events were reported at an incidence of 2% or greater for PAXIL CR and were at least twice the rate of that reported for placebo: Infection (5.3% versus 2.5%), depression (2.8% versus 0.8%), insomnia (2.4% versus 0.8%), sinusitis (2.4% versus 0%), and asthenia (2.0% versus 0.8%).



   Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials

  Table 2 enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 1% or more among patients treated with PAXIL CR, aged 18 to 65, who participated in 2 short-term (12-week) placebo-controlled trials in major depressive disorder in which patients were dosed in a range of 25 mg to 62.5 mg/day. Table 3 enumerates adverse events reported at an incidence of 5% or greater among elderly patients (ages 60 to 88) treated with PAXIL CR who participated in a short-term (12-week) placebo-controlled trial in major depressive disorder in which patients were dosed in a range of 12.5 mg to 50 mg/day. Table 4 enumerates adverse events reported at an incidence of 1% or greater among patients (19 to 72 years) treated with PAXIL CR who participated in short-term (10-week) placebo-controlled trials in panic disorder in which patients were dosed in a range of 12.5 mg to 75 mg/day. Table 5 enumerates adverse events reported at an incidence of 1% or greater among adult patients treated with PAXIL CR who participated in a short-term (12-week), double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in social anxiety disorder in which patients were dosed in a range of 12.5 to 37.5 mg/day. Table 6 enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 1% or more among patients treated with PAXIL CR who participated in three, 12-week, placebo-controlled trials in PMDD in which patients were dosed at 12.5 mg/day or 25 mg/day and in one 12-week placebo-controlled trial in which patients were dosed for 2 weeks prior to the onset of menses (luteal phase dosing) at 12.5 mg/day or 25 mg/day. Reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based Dictionary terminology.



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the side effect incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 2. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;=1% of Patients Treated With PAXIL CR in a Pool of 2 Studies in Major Depressive Disordera,b 
   Body System/Adverse Event                   % Reporting Event            
  PAXIL CR   (n     =     212)                Placebo   (n     = 211)       
   Body as a Whole                                                                                         
 Headache                                    27%                           20%                             
 Asthenia                                    14%                           9%                              
 Infection  c                                8%                            5%                              
 Abdominal Pain                              7%                            4%                              
 Back Pain                                   5%                            3%                              
 Trauma  d                                   5%                            1%                              
 Pain  e                                     3%                            1%                              
 Allergic Reaction  f                        2%                            1%                              
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                   
 Tachycardia                                 1%                            0%                              
 Vasodilatation  g                           2%                            0%                              
   Digestive System                                                                                        
 Nausea                                      22%                           10%                             
 Diarrhea                                    18%                           7%                              
 Dry Mouth                                   15%                           8%                              
 Constipation                                10%                           4%                              
 Flatulence                                  6%                            4%                              
 Decreased Appetite                          4%                            2%                              
 Vomiting                                    2%                            1%                              
   Nervous System                                                                                          
 Somnolence                                  22%                           8%                              
 Insomnia                                    17%                           9%                              
 Dizziness                                   14%                           4%                              
 Libido Decreased                            7%                            3%                              
 Tremor                                      7%                            1%                              
 Hypertonia                                  3%                            1%                              
 Paresthesia                                 3%                            1%                              
 Agitation                                   2%                            1%                              
 Confusion                                   1%                            0%                              
   Respiratory System                                                                                      
 Yawn                                        5%                            0%                              
 Rhinitis                                    4%                            1%                              
 Cough Increased                             2%                            1%                              
 Bronchitis                                  1%                            0%                              
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                     
 Sweating                                    6%                            2%                              
 Photosensitivity                            2%                            0%                              
   Special Senses                                                                                          
 Abnormal Vision  h                          5%                            1%                              
 Taste Perversion                            2%                            0%                              
   Urogenital System                                                                                       
 Abnormal Ejaculation  i,j                   26%                           1%                              
 Female Genital Disorder  i,k                10%                           &lt;1%                             
 Impotence  i                                5%                            3%                              
 Urinary Tract Infection                     3%                            1%                              
 Menstrual Disorder  i                       2%                            &lt;1%                             
 Vaginitis  i                                2%                            0%                              
         a. Adverse events for which the PAXIL CR reporting incidence was less than or equal to the placebo incidence are not included. These events are: Abnormal dreams, anxiety, arthralgia, depersonalization, dysmenorrhea, dyspepsia, hyperkinesia, increased appetite, myalgia, nervousness, pharyngitis, purpura, rash, respiratory disorder, sinusitis, urinary frequency, and weight gain.
 

 b.  &lt;1% means greater than zero and less than 1%.



 c. Mostly flu.



 d.  A wide variety of injuries with no obvious pattern.



 e.  Pain in a variety of locations with no obvious pattern.



 f.  Most frequently seasonal allergic symptoms.



 g.  Usually flushing.



 h.  Mostly blurred vision.



 i.  Based on the number of males or females.



 j.  Mostly anorgasmia or delayed ejaculation.



 k.  Mostly anorgasmia or delayed orgasm.



 Table 3. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;=5% of Patients Treated With PAXIL CR in a Study of Elderly Patients With Major Depressive Disordera,b 
   Body System/Adverse Event                % Reporting Event             
  PAXIL CR   (n = 104)                     Placebo   (n = 109)            
   Body as a Whole                                                                                        
 Headache                                 17%                            13%                              
 Asthenia                                 15%                            14%                              
 Trauma                                   8%                             5%                               
 Infection                                6%                             2%                               
   Digestive System                                                                                       
 Dry Mouth                                18%                            7%                               
 Diarrhea                                 15%                            9%                               
 Constipation                             13%                            5%                               
 Dyspepsia                                13%                            10%                              
 Decreased Appetite                       12%                            5%                               
 Flatulence                               8%                             7%                               
   Nervous System                                                                                         
 Somnolence                               21%                            12%                              
 Insomnia                                 10%                            8%                               
 Dizziness                                9%                             5%                               
 Libido Decreased                         8%                             &lt;1%                              
 Tremor                                   7%                             0%                               
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                    
 Sweating                                 10%                            &lt;1%                              
   Urogenital System                                                                                      
 Abnormal Ejaculation  c,d                17%                            3%                               
 Impotence  c                             9%                             3%                               
         a.  Adverse events for which the PAXIL CR reporting incidence was less than or equal to the placebo incidence are not included. These events are nausea and respiratory disorder.
 

 b.  &lt;1% means greater than zero and less than 1%.



 c.  Based on the number of males.



 d.  Mostly anorgasmia or delayed ejaculation.



 Table 4. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;=1% of Patients Treated With PAXIL CR in a Pool of 3 Panic Disorder Studiesa,b 
   Body System/Adverse Event                % Reporting Event          
  PAXIL CR   (n = 444)                     Placebo   (n = 445)         
   Body as a Whole                                                                                         
 Asthenia                                 15%                         10%                                  
 Abdominal Pain                           6%                          4%                                   
 Trauma  c                                5%                          4%                                   
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                   
 Vasodilation  d                          3%                          2%                                   
   Digestive System                                                                                        
 Nausea                                   23%                         17%                                  
 Dry Mouth                                13%                         9%                                   
 Diarrhea                                 12%                         9%                                   
 Constipation                             9%                          6%                                   
 Decreased Appetite                       8%                          6%                                   
   Metabolic/Nutritional Disorders                                                                         
 Weight Loss                              1%                          0%                                   
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                                  
 Myalgia                                  5%                          3%                                   
   Nervous System                                                                                          
 Insomnia                                 20%                         11%                                  
 Somnolence                               20%                         9%                                   
 Libido Decreased                         9%                          4%                                   
 Nervousness                              8%                          7%                                   
 Tremor                                   8%                          2%                                   
 Anxiety                                  5%                          4%                                   
 Agitation                                3%                          2%                                   
 Hypertonia  e                            2%                          &lt;1%                                  
 Myoclonus                                2%                          &lt;1%                                  
   Respiratory System                                                                                      
 Sinusitis                                8%                          5%                                   
 Yawn                                     3%                          0%                                   
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                     
 Sweating                                 7%                          2%                                   
   Special Senses                                                                                          
 Abnormal Vision  f                       3%                          &lt;1%                                  
   Urogenital System                                                                                       
 Abnormal Ejaculation  g,h                27%                         3%                                   
 Impotence  g                             10%                         1%                                   
 Female Genital Disorders  i,j            7%                          1%                                   
 Urinary Frequency                        2%                          &lt;1%                                  
 Urination Impaired                       2%                          &lt;1%                                  
 Vaginitis  i                             1%                          &lt;1%                                  
         a.  Adverse events for which the reporting rate for PAXIL CR was less than or equal to the placebo rate are not included. These events are: Abnormal dreams, allergic reaction, back pain, bronchitis, chest pain, concentration impaired, confusion, cough increased, depression, dizziness, dysmenorrhea, dyspepsia, fever, flatulence, headache, increased appetite, infection, menstrual disorder, migraine, pain, paresthesia, pharyngitis, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, tachycardia, taste perversion, thinking abnormal, urinary tract infection, and vomiting.
 

 b. &lt; 1% means greater than zero and less than 1%.



 c.  Various physical injuries.



 d.  Mostly flushing.



 e.  Mostly muscle tightness or stiffness.



 f.  Mostly blurred vision.



 g.  Based on the number of male patients.



 h.  Mostly anorgasmia or delayed ejaculation.



 i.  Based on the number of female patients.



 j.  Mostly anorgasmia or difficulty achieving orgasm.



 Table 5. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Effects Occurring in &gt;=1% of Patients Treated With PAXIL CR in a Social Anxiety Disorder Studya,b 
   Body System/Adverse Event                % Reporting Event              
  PAXIL CR   (n = 186)                     Placebo   (n = 184)             
   Body as a Whole                                                                                         
 Headache                                 23%                             17%                              
 Asthenia                                 18%                             7%                               
 Abdominal Pain                           5%                              4%                               
 Back Pain                                4%                              1%                               
 Trauma  c                                3%                              &lt;1%                              
 Allergic Reaction  d                     2%                              &lt;1%                              
 Chest Pain                               1%                              &lt;1%                              
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                   
 Hypertension                             2%                              0%                               
 Migraine                                 2%                              1%                               
 Tachycardia                              2%                              1%                               
   Digestive System                                                                                        
 Nausea                                   22%                             6%                               
 Diarrhea                                 9%                              8%                               
 Constipation                             5%                              2%                               
 Dry Mouth                                3%                              2%                               
 Dyspepsia                                2%                              &lt;1%                              
 Decreased Appetite                       1%                              &lt;1%                              
 Tooth Disorder                           1%                              0%                               
   Metabolic/Nutritional Disorders                                                                         
 Weight Gain                              3%                              1%                               
 Weight Loss                              1%                              0%                               
   Nervous System                                                                                          
 Insomnia                                 9%                              4%                               
 Somnolence                               9%                              4%                               
 Libido Decreased                         8%                              1%                               
 Dizziness                                7%                              4%                               
 Tremor                                   4%                              2%                               
 Anxiety                                  2%                              1%                               
 Concentration Impaired                   2%                              0%                               
 Depression                               2%                              1%                               
 Myoclonus                                1%                              &lt;1%                              
 Paresthesia                              1%                              &lt;1%                              
   Respiratory System                                                                                      
 Yawn                                     2%                              0%                               
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                     
 Sweating                                 14%                             3%                               
 Eczema                                   1%                              0%                               
   Special Senses                                                                                          
 Abnormal Vision  e                       2%                              0%                               
 Abnormality of Accommodation             2%                              0%                               
   Urogenital System                                                                                       
 Abnormal Ejaculation  f,g                15%                             1%                               
 Impotence  f                             9%                              0%                               
 Female Genital Disorders  h,i            3%                              0%                               
         a.  Adverse events for which the reporting rate for PAXIL CR was less than or equal to the placebo rate are not included. These events are: Dysmenorrhea, flatulence, gastroenteritis, hypertonia, infection, pain, pharyngitis, rash, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, and vomiting.
 

 b.  &lt;1% means greater than zero and less than 1%.



 c.  Various physical injuries.



 d.  Most frequently seasonal allergic symptoms.



 e.  Mostly blurred vision.



 f.  Based on the number of male patients.



 g.  Mostly anorgasmia or delayed ejaculation.



 h.  Based on the number of female patients.



 i.  Mostly anorgasmia or difficulty achieving orgasm.



 Table 6. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;=1% of Patients Treated With PAXIL CR in a Pool of 3 Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder Studies With Continuous Dosing or in 1 Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder Study With Luteal Phase Dosinga,b,c 
   Body System/Adverse Event      % Reporting Event     
   Continuous Dosing             Luteal Phase Dosing     
  PAXIL CR   (n = 681)          Placebo   (n = 349)     PAXIL CR   (n = 246)     Placebo   (n = 120)     
   Body as a Whole                                                                                            
 Asthenia                      17%                 6%                  15%                4%                  
 Headache                      15%                 12%                 -                  -                   
 Infection                     6%                  4%                  -                  -                   
 Abdominal pain                -                   -                   3%                 0%                  
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                      
 Migraine                      1%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
   Digestive System                                                                                           
 Nausea                        17%                 7%                  18%                2%                  
 Diarrhea                      6%                  2%                  6%                 0%                  
 Constipation                  5%                  1%                  2%                 &lt;1%                 
 Dry Mouth                     4%                  2%                  2%                 &lt;1%                 
 Increased Appetite            3%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
 Decreased Appetite            2%                  &lt;1%                 2%                 0%                  
 Dyspepsia                     2%                  1%                  2%                 2%                  
 Gingivitis                    -                   -                   1%                 0%                  
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                                   
 Generalized Edema             -                   -                   1%                 &lt;1%                 
 Weight Gain                   -                   -                   1%                 &lt;1%                 
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                                     
 Arthralgia                    2%                  1%                  -                  -                   
   Nervous System                                                                                             
 Libido Decreased              12%                 5%                  9%                 6%                  
 Somnolence                    9%                  2%                  3%                 &lt;1%                 
 Insomnia                      8%                  2%                  7%                 3%                  
 Dizziness                     7%                  3%                  6%                 3%                  
 Tremor                        4%                  &lt;1%                 5%                 0%                  
 Concentration Impaired        3%                  &lt;1%                 1%                 0%                  
 Nervousness                   2%                  &lt;1%                 3%                 2%                  
 Anxiety                       2%                  1%                  -                  -                   
 Lack of Emotion               2%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
 Depression                    -                   -                   2%                 &lt;1%                 
 Vertigo                       -                   -                   2%                 &lt;1%                 
 Abnormal Dreams               1%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
 Amnesia                       -                   -                   1%                 0%                  
   Respiratory System                                                                                         
 Sinusitis                     -                   -                   4%                 2%                  
 Yawn                          2%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
 Bronchitis                    -                   -                   2%                 0%                  
 Cough Increased               1%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                        
 Sweating                      7%                  &lt;1%                 6%                 &lt;1%                 
   Special Senses                                                                                             
 Abnormal Vision               -                   -                   1%                 0%                  
   Urogenital System                                                                                          
 Female Genital Disorders  d    8%                  1%                  2%                 0%                  
 Menorrhagia                   1%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
 Vaginal Moniliasis            1%                  &lt;1%                 -                  -                   
 Menstrual Disorder            -                   -                   1%                 0%                  
           a.  Adverse events for which the reporting rate of PAXIL CR was less than or equal to the placebo rate are not included. These events for continuous dosing are: Abdominal pain, back pain, pain, trauma, weight gain, myalgia, pharyngitis, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, sinusitis, pruritis, dysmenorrhea, menstrual disorder, urinary tract infection, and vomiting. The events for luteal phase dosing are: Allergic reaction, back pain, headache, infection, pain, trauma, myalgia, anxiety, pharyngitis, respiratory disorder, cystitis, and dysmenorrhea.
 

 b.  &lt;1% means greater than zero and less than 1%.



 c.  The luteal phase and continuous dosing PMDD trials were not designed for making direct comparisons between the 2 dosing regimens. Therefore, a comparison between the 2 dosing regimens of the PMDD trials of incidence rates shown in Table 6 should be avoided.



 d.  Mostly anorgasmia or difficulty achieving orgasm.



       Dose Dependency of Adverse Events    

  Table 7 shows results in PMDD trials of common adverse events, defined as events with an incidence of &gt;=1% with 25 mg of PAXIL CR that was at least twice that with 12.5 mg of PAXIL CR and with placebo.



 Table 7. Incidence of Common Adverse Events in Placebo, 12.5 mg, and 25 mg of PAXIL CR in a Pool of 3 Fixed-Dose PMDD Trials 
                                   PAXIL CR  25 mg   (n = 348)     PAXIL CR  12.5 mg   (n = 333)     Placebo   (n = 349)     
   Common Adverse Event                                                                                     
 Sweating                         8.9%                     4.2%                     0.9%                    
 Tremor                           6.0%                     1.5%                     0.3%                    
 Concentration Impaired           4.3%                     1.5%                     0.6%                    
 Yawn                             3.2%                     0.9%                     0.3%                    
 Paresthesia                      1.4%                     0.3%                     0.3%                    
 Hyperkinesia                     1.1%                     0.3%                     0.0%                    
 Vaginitis                        1.1%                     0.3%                     0.3%                    
          A comparison of adverse event rates in a fixed-dose study comparing immediate-release paroxetine with placebo in the treatment of major depressive disorder revealed a clear dose dependency for some of the more common adverse events associated with the use of immediate-release paroxetine.
 

       Male and Female Sexual Dysfunction With SSRIs    

  Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that SSRIs can cause such untoward sexual experiences.



 Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain; however, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling, are likely to underestimate their actual incidence.



 The percentage of patients reporting symptoms of sexual dysfunction in the pool of 2 placebo-controlled trials in nonelderly patients with major depressive disorder, in the pool of 3 placebo-controlled trials in patients with panic disorder, in the placebo-controlled trial in patients with social anxiety disorder, and in the intermittent dosing and the pool of 3 placebo-controlled continuous dosing trials in female patients with PMDD are as follows:




                Major Depressive Disorder      Panic Disorder      Social Anxiety Disorder     PMDD   Continuous Dosing     PMDD   Luteal Phase Dosing     
                PAXIL CR      Placebo      PAXIL CR      Placebo      PAXIL CR      Placebo      PAXIL CR      Placebo      PAXIL CR      Placebo     
   n (males)      78         78        162       194       88        97        n/a        n/a       n/a       n/a      
 Decreased Libido  10%        5%        9%        6%        13%       1%        n/a        n/a       n/a       n/a        
 Ejaculatory Disturbance  26%        1%        27%       3%        15%       1%        n/a        n/a       n/a       n/a        
 Impotence    5%         3%        10%       1%        9%        0%        n/a        n/a       n/a       n/a        
   n (females)      134        133       282       251       98        87        681        349       246       120      
 Decreased Libido  4%         2%        8%        2%        4%        1%        12%        5%        9%        6%         
 Orgasmic Disturbance  10%        &lt;1%       7%        1%        3%        0%        8%         1%        2%        0%         
                 There are no adequate, controlled studies examining sexual dysfunction with paroxetine treatment.
 

 Paroxetine treatment has been associated with several cases of priapism. In those cases with a known outcome, patients recovered without sequelae.



 While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



       Weight and Vital Sign Changes    

  Significant weight loss may be an undesirable result of treatment with paroxetine for some patients but, on average, patients in controlled trials with PAXIL CR or the immediate-release formulation, had minimal weight loss (about 1 pound). No significant changes in vital signs (systolic and diastolic blood pressure, pulse, and temperature) were observed in patients treated with PAXIL CR, or immediate-release paroxetine hydrochloride, in controlled clinical trials.



       ECG Changes    

  In an analysis of ECGs obtained in 682 patients treated with immediate-release paroxetine and 415 patients treated with placebo in controlled clinical trials, no clinically significant changes were seen in the ECGs of either group.



       Liver Function Tests    

  In a pool of 2 placebo-controlled clinical trials, patients treated with PAXIL CR or placebo exhibited abnormal values on liver function tests at comparable rates. In particular, the controlled-release paroxetine-versus-placebo comparisons for alkaline phosphatase, SGOT, SGPT, and bilirubin revealed no differences in the percentage of patients with marked abnormalities.



 In a study of elderly patients with major depressive disorder, 3 of 104 patients treated with PAXIL CR and none of 109 placebo patients experienced liver transaminase elevations of potential clinical concern.



 Two of the patients treated with PAXIL CR dropped out of the study due to abnormal liver function tests; the third patient experienced normalization of transaminase levels with continued treatment. Also, in the pool of 3 studies of patients with panic disorder, 4 of 444 patients treated with PAXIL CR and none of 445 placebo patients experienced liver transaminase elevations of potential clinical concern. Elevations in all 4 patients decreased substantially after discontinuation of PAXIL CR. The clinical significance of these findings is unknown.



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials with the immediate-release formulation of paroxetine, patients exhibited abnormal values on liver function tests at no greater rate than that seen in placebo-treated patients.



       Hallucinations    

  In pooled clinical trials of immediate-release paroxetine hydrochloride, hallucinations were observed in 22 of 9,089 patients receiving drug and in 4 of 3,187 patients receiving placebo.



   Other Events Observed During the Clinical Development of Paroxetine

  The following adverse events were reported during the clinical development of PAXIL CR and/or the clinical development of the immediate-release formulation of paroxetine.



 Adverse events for which frequencies are provided below occurred in clinical trials with the controlled-release formulation of paroxetine. During its premarketing assessment in major depressive disorder, panic disorder, social anxiety disorder, and PMDD, multiple doses of PAXIL CR were administered to 1,627 patients in phase 3 double-blind, controlled, outpatient studies. Untoward events associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized event categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, reported adverse events were classified using a COSTART-based dictionary. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the 1,627 patients exposed to PAXIL CR who experienced an event of the type cited on at least 1 occasion while receiving PAXIL CR. All reported events are included except those already listed in Tables 2 through 7 and those events where a drug cause was remote. If the COSTART term for an event was so general as to be uninformative, it was deleted or, when possible, replaced with a more informative term. It is important to emphasize that although the events reported occurred during treatment with paroxetine, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: Frequent adverse events are those occurring on 1 or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients (only those not already listed in the tabulated results from placebo-controlled trials appear in this listing); infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients; rare events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1,000 patients.



 Adverse events for which frequencies are not provided occurred during the premarketing assessment of immediate-release paroxetine in phase 2 and 3 studies of major depressive disorder, obsessive compulsive disorder, panic disorder, social anxiety disorder, generalized anxiety disorder, and posttraumatic stress disorder. The conditions and duration of exposure to immediate-release paroxetine varied greatly and included (in overlapping categories) open and double-blind studies, uncontrolled and controlled studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, and fixed-dose and titration studies. Only those events not previously listed for controlled-release paroxetine are included. The extent to which these events may be associated with PAXIL CR is unknown.



 Events are listed alphabetically within the respective body system. Events of major clinical importance are also described in the PRECAUTIONS section.



       Body as a Whole    

  Infrequent were chills, face edema, fever, flu syndrome, malaise; rare were abscess, anaphylactoid reaction, anticholinergic syndrome, hypothermia; also observed were adrenergic syndrome, neck rigidity, sepsis.



       Cardiovascular System    

  Infrequent were angina pectoris, bradycardia, hematoma, hypertension, hypotension, palpitation, postural hypotension, supraventricular tachycardia, syncope; rare were bundle branch block; also observed were arrhythmia nodal, atrial fibrillation, cerebrovascular accident, congestive heart failure, low cardiac output, myocardial infarct, myocardial ischemia, pallor, phlebitis, pulmonary embolus, supraventricular extrasystoles, thrombophlebitis, thrombosis, vascular headache, ventricular extrasystoles.



       Digestive System    

  Infrequent were bruxism, dysphagia, eructation, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastroesophageal reflux, gingivitis, hemorrhoids, liver function test abnormal, melena, pancreatitis, rectal hemorrhage, toothache, ulcerative stomatitis; rare were colitis, glossitis, gum hyperplasia, hepatosplenomegaly, increased salivation, intestinal obstruction, peptic ulcer, stomach ulcer, throat tightness; also observed were aphthous stomatitis, bloody diarrhea, bulimia, cardiospasm, cholelithiasis, duodenitis, enteritis, esophagitis, fecal impactions, fecal incontinence, gum hemorrhage, hematemesis, hepatitis, ileitis, ileus, jaundice, mouth ulceration, salivary gland enlargement, sialadenitis, stomatitis, tongue discoloration, tongue edema.



       Endocrine System    

  Infrequent were ovarian cyst, testes pain; rare were diabetes mellitus, hyperthyroidism; also observed were goiter, hypothyroidism, thyroiditis.



       Hemic and Lymphatic System    

  Infrequent were anemia, eosinophilia, hypochromic anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, purpura; rare were thrombocytopenia; also observed were anisocytosis, basophilia, bleeding time increased, lymphedema, lymphocytosis, lymphopenia, microcytic anemia, monocytosis, normocytic anemia, thrombocythemia.



       Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders    

  Infrequent were generalized edema, hyperglycemia, hypokalemia, peripheral edema, SGOT increased, SGPT increased, thirst; rare were bilirubinemia, dehydration, hyperkalemia, obesity; also observed were alkaline phosphatase increased, BUN increased, creatinine phosphokinase increased, gamma globulins increased, gout, hypercalcemia, hypercholesteremia, hyperphosphatemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, ketosis, lactic dehydrogenase increased, non-protein nitrogen (NPN) increased.



       Musculoskeletal System    

  Infrequent were arthritis, bursitis, tendonitis; rare were myasthenia, myopathy, myositis; also observed were generalized spasm, osteoporosis, tenosynovitis, tetany.



       Nervous System    

  Frequent were depression; infrequent were amnesia, convulsion, depersonalization, dystonia, emotional lability, hallucinations, hyperkinesia, hypesthesia, hypokinesia, incoordination, libido increased, neuralgia, neuropathy, nystagmus, paralysis, vertigo; rare were ataxia, coma, diplopia, dyskinesia, hostility, paranoid reaction, torticollis, withdrawal syndrome; also observed were abnormal gait, akathisia, akinesia, aphasia, choreoathetosis, circumoral paresthesia, delirium, delusions, dysarthria, euphoria, extrapyramidal syndrome, fasciculations, grand mal convulsion, hyperalgesia, irritability, manic reaction, manic-depressive reaction, meningitis, myelitis, peripheral neuritis, psychosis, psychotic depression, reflexes decreased, reflexes increased, stupor, trismus.



       Respiratory System    

  Frequent were pharyngitis; infrequent were asthma, dyspnea, epistaxis, laryngitis, pneumonia; rare were stridor; also observed were dysphonia, emphysema, hemoptysis, hiccups, hyperventilation, lung fibrosis, pulmonary edema, respiratory flu, sputum increased.



       Skin and Appendages    

  Frequent were rash; infrequent were acne, alopecia, dry skin, eczema, pruritus, urticaria; rare were exfoliative dermatitis, furunculosis, pustular rash, seborrhea; also observed were angioedema, ecchymosis, erythema multiforme, erythema nodosum, hirsutism, maculopapular rash, skin discoloration, skin hypertrophy, skin ulcer, sweating decreased, vesiculobullous rash.



       Special Senses    

  Infrequent were conjunctivitis, earache, keratoconjunctivitis, mydriasis, photophobia, retinal hemorrhage, tinnitus; rare were blepharitis, visual field defect; also observed were amblyopia, anisocoria, blurred vision, cataract, conjunctival edema, corneal ulcer, deafness, exophthalmos, glaucoma, hyperacusis, night blindness, parosmia, ptosis, taste loss.



       Urogenital System    

  Frequent were dysmenorrhea  *  ; infrequent were albuminuria, amenorrhea  *  , breast pain  *  , cystitis, dysuria, prostatitis  *  , urinary retention; rare were breast enlargement  *  , breast neoplasm  *  , female lactation, hematuria, kidney calculus, metrorrhagia  *  , nephritis, nocturia, pregnancy and puerperal disorders  *  , salpingitis, urinary incontinence, uterine fibroids enlarged  *  ; also observed were breast atrophy, ejaculatory disturbance, endometrial disorder, epididymitis, fibrocystic breast, leukorrhea, mastitis, oliguria, polyuria, pyuria, urethritis, urinary casts, urinary urgency, urolith, uterine spasm, vaginal hemorrhage.



   *  Based on the number of men and women as appropriate.



   Postmarketing Reports

  Voluntary reports of adverse events in patients taking immediate-release paroxetine hydrochloride that have been received since market introduction and not listed above that may have no causal relationship with the drug include acute pancreatitis, elevated liver function tests (the most severe cases were deaths due to liver necrosis, and grossly elevated transaminases associated with severe liver dysfunction), Guillain-Barre syndrome, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, priapism, syndrome of inappropriate ADH secretion, symptoms suggestive of prolactinemia and galactorrhea; extrapyramidal symptoms which have included akathisia, bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, dystonia, hypertonia, oculogyric crisis which has been associated with concomitant use of pimozide; tremor and trismus; status epilepticus, acute renal failure, pulmonary hypertension, allergic alveolitis, anaphylaxis, eclampsia, laryngismus, optic neuritis, porphyria, restless legs syndrome (RLS), ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia (including torsade de pointes), thrombocytopenia, hemolytic anemia, events related to impaired hematopoiesis (including aplastic anemia, pancytopenia, bone marrow aplasia, and agranulocytosis), and vasculitic syndromes (such as Henoch-Schonlein purpura). There has been a case report of an elevated phenytoin level after 4 weeks of immediate-release paroxetine and phenytoin coadministration. There has been a case report of severe hypotension when immediate-release paroxetine was added to chronic metoprolol treatment.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

  Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of PAXIL CR or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. PAXIL CR is not approved for use in pediatric patients. (See WARNINGS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk, PRECAUTIONS: Information for Patients, and PRECAUTIONS: Pediatric Use.)  



 





    BOXED WARNING: Medication Guide

    Medication Guide  

    PAXIL CR  (r)   (PAX-il) (paroxetine hydrochloride) Controlled-Release Tablets  



 Read the Medication Guide that comes with PAXIL CR before you start taking it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or treatment. Talk with your healthcare provider if there is something you do not understand or want to learn more about.



   What is the most important information I should know about PAXIL CR?  



 PAXIL CR and other antidepressant medicines may cause serious side effects, including:



   1. Suicidal thoughts or actions:  



 *  PAXIL CR and other antidepressant medicines may increase suicidal thoughts or actions in some children, teenagers, and young adults within the first few months of treatment or when the dose is changed. 
 *  Depression or other serious mental illnesses are the most important causes of suicidal thoughts or actions. 
 *  Watch for these changes and call your healthcare provider right away if you notice: New or sudden changes in mood, behavior, actions, thoughts, or feelings, especially if severe. Pay particular attention to such changes when PAXIL CR is started or when the dose is changed. 
    Keep all follow-up visits with your healthcare provider and call between visits if you are worried about symptoms.
 

   Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency, especially if they are new, worse, or worry you:  



 *  attempts to commit suicide 
 *  acting on dangerous impulses 
 *  acting aggressive or violent 
 *  thoughts about suicide or dying 
 *  new or worse depression 
 *  new or worse anxiety or panic attacks 
 *  feeling agitated, restless, angry, or irritable 
 *  trouble sleeping 
 *  an increase in activity and talking more than what is normal for you 
 *  other unusual changes in behavior or mood 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency. PAXIL CR may be associated with these serious side effects:  
 

   2. Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome-like reactions. This condition can be life-threatening and may include:  



 *  agitation, hallucinations, coma, or other changes in mental status 
 *  coordination problems or muscle twitching (overactive reflexes) 
 *  racing heartbeat, high or low blood pressure 
 *  sweating or fever 
 *  nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea 
 *  muscle rigidity 
      3. Severe allergic reactions:  
 

 *  trouble breathing 
 *  swelling of the face, tongue, eyes, or mouth 
 *  rash, itchy welts (hives), or blisters, alone or with fever or joint pain 
      4. Abnormal bleeding:   PAXIL CR and other antidepressant medicines may increase your risk of bleeding or bruising, especially if you take the blood thinner warfarin (Coumadin  (r)  , Jantoven  (r)  ), a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAIDs, like ibuprofen or naproxen), or aspirin.
 

   5. Seizures or convulsions  



   6. Manic episodes:  



 *  greatly increased energy 
 *  severe trouble sleeping 
 *  racing thoughts 
 *  reckless behavior 
 *  unusually grand ideas 
 *  excessive happiness or irritability 
 *  talking more or faster than usual 
      7. Changes in appetite or weight.   Children and adolescents should have height and weight monitored during treatment.
 

   8. Low salt (sodium) levels in the blood.   Elderly people may be at greater risk for this. Symptoms may include:



 *  headache 
 *  weakness or feeling unsteady 
 *  confusion, problems concentrating or thinking, or memory problems 
      Do not stop PAXIL CR without first talking to your healthcare provider.   Stopping PAXIL CR too quickly may cause serious symptoms including:
 

 *  anxiety, irritability, high or low mood, feeling restless, or changes in sleep habits 
 *  headache, sweating, nausea, dizziness 
 *  electric shock-like sensations, shaking, confusion 
      What is PAXIL CR?  
 

 PAXIL CR is a prescription medicine used to treat depression. It is important to talk with your healthcare provider about the risks of treating depression and also the risks of not treating it. You should discuss all treatment choices with your healthcare provider. PAXIL CR is   also   used to treat:



 *  Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) 
 *  Panic Disorder 
 *  Social Anxiety Disorder 
 *  Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder (PMDD) 
    Talk to your healthcare provider if you do not think that your condition is getting better with treatment using PAXIL CR.
 

   Who should not take PAXIL CR?  



 Do not take PAXIL CR if you:



 *  are allergic to paroxetine or any of the ingredients in PAXIL CR. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in PAXIL CR. 
 *  take a monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI). Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure if you take an MAOI, including the antibiotic linezolid. 
 *  Do not take an MAOI within 2 weeks of stopping PAXIL CR unless directed to do so by your physician.. 
 *  Do not start PAXIL CR if you stopped taking an MAOI in the last 2 weeks unless directed to do so by your physician. 
 *  People who take PAXIL CR close in time to an MAOI may have serious or even life-threatening side effects. Get medical help right away if you have any of these symptoms:high feveruncontrolled muscle spasmsstiff musclesrapid changes in heart rate or blood pressureconfusionloss of consciousness (pass out) 
   *  take MELLARIL(r) (thioridazine). Do not take MELLARIL(r) together with PAXIL CR because this can cause serious heart rhythm problems or sudden death. 
 *  take the antipsychotic medicine pimozide (ORAP(r)) because this can cause serious heart problems. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking PAXIL CR? Ask if you are not sure.  
 

 Before starting PAXIL CR, tell your healthcare provider if you:



 *  are pregnant, may be pregnant, or plan to become pregnant. There is a possibility that PAXIL CR may harm your unborn baby, including an increased risk of birth defects, particularly heart defects. Other risks may include a serious condition in which there is not enough oxygen in the baby's blood. Your baby may also have certain other symptoms shortly after birth. Premature births have also been reported in some women who used PAXIL CR during pregnancy 
 *  are breastfeeding. PAXIL CR passes into your milk. Talk to your healthcare provider about the best way to feed your baby while taking PAXIL CR. 
 *  are taking certain drugs such as: triptans used to treat migraine headacheother antidepressants (SSRIs, SNRIs, tricyclics, or lithium) or antipsychoticsdrugs that affect serotonin, such as lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, St. John's wortcertain drugs used to treat irregular heart beatscertain drugs used to treat schizophreniacertain drugs used to treat HIV infection certain drugs that affect the blood, such as warfarin, aspirin, and ibuprofencertain drugs used to treat epilepsyatomoxetinecimetidinefentanylmetoprololpimozideprocyclidinetamoxifen 
 *  have liver problems 
 *  have kidney problems 
 *  have heart problems 
 *  have or had seizures or convulsions 
 *  have bipolar disorder or mania 
 *  have low sodium levels in your blood 
 *  have a history of a stroke 
 *  have high blood pressure 
 *  have or had bleeding problems 
 *  have glaucoma (high pressure in the eye) 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take  , including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. PAXIL CR and some medicines may interact with each other, may not work as well, or may cause serious side effects.
 

 Your healthcare provider or pharmacist can tell you if it is safe to take PAXIL CR with your other medicines. Do not start or stop any medicine while taking PAXIL CR without talking to your healthcare provider first.



   If you take PAXIL CR, you should not take any other medicines that contain paroxetine, including PAXIL and PEXEVA  (r)   (paroxetine mesylate). 



     How should I take PAXIL CR?  



 *  Take PAXIL CR exactly as prescribed. Your healthcare provider may need to change the dose of PAXIL CR until it is the right dose for you. 
 *  PAXIL CR may be taken with or without food. 
 *  PAXIL CR controlled-release tablets should not be chewed or crushed and should be swallowed whole. 
 *  If you miss a dose of PAXIL CR, take the missed dose as soon as you remember. If it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and take your next dose at the regular time. Do not take two doses of PAXIL CR at the same time. 
 *  If you take too much PAXIL CR, call your healthcare provider or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
 *  Do not stop taking PAXIL CR suddenly without talking to your doctor (unless you have symptoms of a severe allergic reaction). If you need to stop taking PAXIL CR, your healthcare provider can tell you how to safely stop taking it. 
      What should I avoid while taking PAXIL CR?  
 

 PAXIL CR can cause sleepiness or may affect your ability to make decisions, think clearly, or react quickly. You should not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how PAXIL CR affects you. Do not drink alcohol while using PAXIL CR.



   What are possible side effects of PAXIL CR?  



 PAXIL CR may cause serious side effects, including all of those described in the section entitled "What is the most important information I should know about PAXIL CR?" 



 Common possible side effects in people who take PAXIL CR include:



 *  nausea 
 *  sleepiness 
 *  feeling anxious or trouble sleeping 
 *  sexual problems 
 *  sweating 
 *  shaking 
 *  constipation 
 *  yawning 
 *  blurred vision 
 *  diarrhea 
 *  dry mouth 
 *  decreased appetite 
 *  weakness 
    Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away. These are not all the possible side effects of PAXIL CR. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.
 

   CALL YOUR DOCTOR FOR MEDICAL ADVICE ABOUT SIDE EFFECTS. YOU MAY REPORT SIDE EFFECTS TO THE FDA AT 1-800-FDA-1088 or 1-800-332-1088.  



   How should I store PAXIL CR?  



 *  Store PAXIL CR at or below room temperature (77oF or 25oC). 
 *  Keep PAXIL CR away from light. 
 *  Keep bottle of PAXIL CR closed tightly. 
      Keep PAXIL CR and all medicines out of the reach of children.  
 

   General information about PAXIL CR  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use PAXIL CR for a condition for which it was not prescribed. Do not give PAXIL CR to other people, even if they have the same condition. It may harm them.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about PAXIL CR. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You may ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for information about PAXIL CR that is written for healthcare professionals.



 For more information about PAXIL CR call 1-888-825-5249 or go to www.us.gsk.com.



   What are the ingredients in PAXIL CR?  



   Active ingredient:   paroxetine hydrochloride



   Inactive ingredients in tablets:  hypromellose, polyvinylpyrrolidone, lactose monohydrate, magnesium stearate, silicon dioxide, glyceryl behenate, methacrylic acid copolymer type C, sodium lauryl sulfate, polysorbate 80, talc, triethyl citrate, titanium dioxide, polyethylene glycols, and 1 or more of the following colorants: Yellow ferric oxide, red ferric oxide, D&amp;C Red No. 30 aluminum lake, FD&amp;C Yellow No. 6 aluminum lake, D&amp;C Yellow No. 10 aluminum lake, FD&amp;C Blue No. 2 aluminum lake.



 PAXIL and PAXIL CR are registered trademarks of GlaxoSmithKline. The other brands listed are trademarks of their respective owners and are not trademarks of GlaxoSmithKline. The makers of these brands are not affiliated with and do not endorse GlaxoSmithKline or its products.



 This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.



 GlaxoSmithKline



 Research Triangle Park, NC 27709



 (c)2011, GlaxoSmithKline. All rights reserved.



 July 2011 PCR:5MG
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
