<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="paxil0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Associated With Discontinuation of Treatment

  Twenty percent (1,199/6,145) of patients treated with PAXIL in worldwide clinical trials in major depressive disorder and 16.1% (84/522), 11.8% (64/542), 9.4% (44/469), 10.7% (79/735), and 11.7% (79/676) of patients treated with PAXIL in worldwide trials in social anxiety disorder, OCD, panic disorder, GAD, and PTSD, respectively, discontinued treatment due to an adverse event. The most common events (&gt;=1%) associated with discontinuation and considered to be drug related (i.e., those events associated with dropout at a rate approximately twice or greater for PAXIL compared to placebo) included the following:




                Major Depressive Disorder      OCD      Panic Disorder      Social Anxiety Disorder      Generalized Anxiety Disorder      PTSD     
                PAXIL      Placebo      PAXIL      Placebo      PAXIL      Placebo      PAXIL      Placebo      PAXIL      Placebo      PAXIL      Placebo     
   CNS                                                                                                                     
 Somnolence   2.3%     0.7%     -                 1.9%     0.3%     3.4%     0.3%     2.0%     0.2%     2.8%     0.6%      
 Insomnia     -        -        1.7%     0%       1.3%     0.3%     3.1%     0%                         -        -         
 Agitation    1.1%     0.5%     -                                                                       -        -         
 Tremor       1.1%     0.3%     -                                   1.7%     0%                         1.0%     0.2%      
 Anxiety      -        -        -                                   1.1%     0%                         -        -         
 Dizziness    -        -        1.5%     0%                         1.9%     0%       1.0%     0.2%     -        -         
   Gastroin-testinal                                                                                                                 
 Constipation  -                 1.1%     0%                                                             -        -         
 Nausea       3.2%     1.1%     1.9%     0%       3.2%     1.2%     4.0%     0.3%     2.0%     0.2%     2.2%     0.6%      
 Diarrhea     1.0%     0.3%     -                                                                                          
 Dry mouth    1.0%     0.3%     -                                                                       -        -         
 Vomiting     1.0%     0.3%     -                                   1.0%     0%                         -        -         
 Flatulence                                                         1.0%     0.3%                       -        -         
   Other                                                                                                                   
 Asthenia     1.6%     0.4%     1.9%     0.4%                       2.5%     0.6%     1.8%     0.2%     1.6%     0.2%      
  Abnormal Ejaculation  a    1.6%     0%       2.1%     0%                         4.9%     0.6%     2.5%     0.5%     -        -         
 Sweating     1.0%     0.3%     -                                   1.1%     0%       1.1%     0.2%     -        -         
 Impotence  a    -                 1.5%     0%                                                             -        -         
  Libido Decreased                                                        1.0%     0%                         -        -         
                   Where numbers are not provided the incidence of the adverse events in patients treated with PAXIL was not &gt;1% or was not greater than or equal to 2 times the incidence of placebo.
 

   a  Incidence corrected for gender.



   Commonly Observed Adverse Events

      Major Depressive Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of paroxetine (incidence of 5% or greater and incidence for PAXIL at least twice that for placebo, derived from Table 2) were: Asthenia, sweating, nausea, decreased appetite, somnolence, dizziness, insomnia, tremor, nervousness, ejaculatory disturbance, and other male genital disorders.



       Obsessive Compulsive Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of paroxetine (incidence of 5% or greater and incidence for PAXIL at least twice that of placebo, derived from Table 3) were: Nausea, dry mouth, decreased appetite, constipation, dizziness, somnolence, tremor, sweating, impotence, and abnormal ejaculation.



       Panic Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of paroxetine (incidence of 5% or greater and incidence for PAXIL at least twice that for placebo, derived from Table 3) were: Asthenia, sweating, decreased appetite, libido decreased, tremor, abnormal ejaculation, female genital disorders, and impotence.



       Social Anxiety Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of paroxetine (incidence of 5% or greater and incidence for PAXIL at least twice that for placebo, derived from Table 3) were: Sweating, nausea, dry mouth, constipation, decreased appetite, somnolence, tremor, libido decreased, yawn, abnormal ejaculation, female genital disorders, and impotence.



       Generalized Anxiety Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of paroxetine (incidence of 5% or greater and incidence for PAXIL at least twice that for placebo, derived from Table 4) were: Asthenia, infection, constipation, decreased appetite, dry mouth, nausea, libido decreased, somnolence, tremor, sweating, and abnormal ejaculation.



       Posttraumatic Stress Disorder    

  The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of paroxetine (incidence of 5% or greater and incidence for PAXIL at least twice that for placebo, derived from Table 4) were: Asthenia, sweating, nausea, dry mouth, diarrhea, decreased appetite, somnolence, libido decreased, abnormal ejaculation, female genital disorders, and impotence.



   Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials

  The prescriber should be aware that the figures in the tables following cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the side effect incidence rate in the populations studied.



       Major Depressive Disorder    

  Table 2 enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 1% or more among paroxetine-treated patients who participated in short-term (6-week) placebo-controlled trials in which patients were dosed in a range of 20 mg to 50 mg/day. Reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based Dictionary terminology.



 Table 2. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials for Major Depressive Disordera 
   Body System                  Preferred Term                      PAXIL   (n     =     421)     Placebo   (n     =     421)     
 Body as a Whole              Headache                             18%                 17%                  
                              Asthenia                             15%                 6%                   
 Cardiovascular               Palpitation                          3%                  1%                   
                              Vasodilation                         3%                  1%                   
 Dermatologic                 Sweating                             11%                 2%                   
                              Rash                                 2%                  1%                   
 Gastrointestinal             Nausea                               26%                 9%                   
                              Dry Mouth                            18%                 12%                  
                              Constipation                         14%                 9%                   
                              Diarrhea                             12%                 8%                   
                              Decreased Appetite                   6%                  2%                   
                              Flatulence                           4%                  2%                   
                              Oropharynx Disorder  b               2%                  0%                   
                              Dyspepsia                            2%                  1%                   
 Musculoskeletal              Myopathy                             2%                  1%                   
                              Myalgia                              2%                  1%                   
                              Myasthenia                           1%                  0%                   
 Nervous System               Somnolence                           23%                 9%                   
                              Dizziness                            13%                 6%                   
                              Insomnia                             13%                 6%                   
                              Tremor                               8%                  2%                   
                              Nervousness                          5%                  3%                   
                              Anxiety                              5%                  3%                   
                              Paresthesia                          4%                  2%                   
                              Libido Decreased                     3%                  0%                   
                              Drugged Feeling                      2%                  1%                   
                              Confusion                            1%                  0%                   
 Respiration                  Yawn                                 4%                  0%                   
 Special Senses               Blurred Vision                       4%                  1%                   
                              Taste Perversion                     2%                  0%                   
 Urogenital System            Ejaculatory Disturbance  c,d         13%                 0%                   
                              Other Male Genital Disorders  c,e    10%                 0%                   
                              Urinary Frequency                    3%                  1%                   
                              Urination Disorder  f                3%                  0%                   
                              Female Genital Disorders  c,g        2%                  0%                   
            a  Events reported by at least 1% of patients treated with PAXIL are included, except  the following events which had an incidence on placebo &gt;= PAXIL: Abdominal pain, agitation, back pain, chest pain, CNS stimulation, fever, increased appetite, myoclonus, pharyngitis, postural hypotension, respiratory disorder (includes mostly "cold symptoms" or "URI"), trauma, and vomiting.
 

   b  Includes mostly "lump in throat" and "tightness in throat."



   c  Percentage corrected for gender.



   d  Mostly "ejaculatory delay."



   e  Includes "anorgasmia," "erectile difficulties," "delayed ejaculation/orgasm," and "sexual dysfunction," and "impotence."



   f  Includes mostly "difficulty with micturition" and "urinary hesitancy."



   g  Includes mostly "anorgasmia" and "difficulty reaching climax/orgasm."



       Obsessive Compulsive Disorder, Panic Disorder, and Social Anxiety Disorder    

  Table 3 enumerates adverse events that occurred at a frequency of 2% or more among OCD patients on PAXIL who participated in placebo-controlled trials of 12-weeks duration in which patients were dosed in a range of 20 mg to 60 mg/day or among patients with panic disorder on PAXIL who participated in placebo-controlled trials of 10- to 12-weeks duration in which patients were dosed in a range of 10 mg to 60 mg/day or among patients with social anxiety disorder on PAXIL who participated in placebo-controlled trials of 12-weeks duration in which patients were dosed in a range of 20 mg to 50 mg/day.



 Table 3. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials for Obsessive Compulsive Disorder, Panic Disorder, and Social Anxiety Disordera 
   Body System         Preferred Term     Obsessive  Compulsive   Disorder     Panic   Disorder     Social Anxiety   Disorder     
  PAXIL   (n     =     542)     Placebo   (n     =     265)     PAXIL   (n     =     469)     Placebo   (n     =     324)     PAXIL   (n     =     425)     Placebo   (n     =     339)     
 Body as a Whole     Asthenia           22%         14%         14%         5%          22%         14%          
                     Abdominal Pain     -           -           4%          3%          -           -            
                     Chest Pain         3%          2%          -           -           -           -            
                     Back Pain          -           -           3%          2%          -           -            
                     Chills             2%          1%          2%          1%          -           -            
                     Trauma             -           -           -           -           3%          1%           
 Cardiovascular      Vasodilation       4%          1%          -           -           -           -            
                     Palpitation        2%          0%          -           -           -           -            
 Dermatologic        Sweating           9%          3%          14%         6%          9%          2%           
                     Rash               3%          2%          -           -           -           -            
 Gastrointestinal    Nausea             23%         10%         23%         17%         25%         7%           
                     Dry Mouth          18%         9%          18%         11%         9%          3%           
                     Constipation       16%         6%          8%          5%          5%          2%           
                     Diarrhea           10%         10%         12%         7%          9%          6%           
                      Decreased Appetite  9%          3%          7%          3%          8%          2%           
                     Dyspepsia          -           -           -           -           4%          2%           
                     Flatulence         -           -           -           -           4%          2%           
                      Increased Appetite  4%          3%          2%          1%          -           -            
                     Vomiting           -           -           -           -           2%          1%           
 Musculoskeletal     Myalgia            -           -           -           -           4%          3%           
 Nervous System      Insomnia           24%         13%         18%         10%         21%         16%          
                     Somnolence         24%         7%          19%         11%         22%         5%           
                     Dizziness          12%         6%          14%         10%         11%         7%           
                     Tremor             11%         1%          9%          1%          9%          1%           
                     Nervousness        9%          8%          -           -           8%          7%           
                     Libido Decreased   7%          4%          9%          1%          12%         1%           
                     Agitation          -           -           5%          4%          3%          1%           
                     Anxiety            -           -           5%          4%          5%          4%           
                      Abnormal Dreams   4%          1%          -           -           -           -            
                      Concentration Impaired  3%          2%          -           -           4%          1%           
                     Depersonalization  3%          0%          -           -           -           -            
                     Myoclonus          3%          0%          3%          2%          2%          1%           
                     Amnesia            2%          1%          -           -           -           -            
 Respiratory System  Rhinitis           -           -           3%          0%          -           -            
                     Pharyngitis        -           -           -           -           4%          2%           
                     Yawn               -           -           -           -           5%          1%           
 Special Senses      Abnormal Vision    4%          2%          -           -           4%          1%           
                     Taste Perversion   2%          0%          -           -           -           -            
 Urogenital System    Abnormal Ejaculation  b    23%         1%          21%         1%          28%         1%           
                     Dysmenorrhea       -           -           -           -           5%          4%           
                      Female Genital Disorder  b    3%          0%          9%          1%          9%          1%           
                     Impotence  b       8%          1%          5%          0%          5%          1%           
                      Urinary Frequency  3%          1%          2%          0%          -           -            
                      Urination Impaired  3%          0%          -           -           -           -            
                      Urinary Tract Infection  2%          1%          2%          1%          -           -            
                a  Events reported by at least 2% of OCD, panic disorder, and social anxiety disorder in patients treated with PAXIL are included, except the following events which had an incidence on placebo &gt;=PAXIL: [OCD]: Abdominal pain, agitation, anxiety, back pain, cough increased, depression, headache, hyperkinesia, infection, paresthesia, pharyngitis, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, and sinusitis. [panic disorder]: Abnormal dreams, abnormal vision, chest pain, cough increased, depersonalization, depression, dysmenorrhea, dyspepsia, flu syndrome, headache, infection, myalgia, nervousness, palpitation, paresthesia, pharyngitis, rash, respiratory disorder, sinusitis, taste perversion, trauma, urination impaired, and vasodilation. [social anxiety disorder]: Abdominal pain, depression, headache, infection, respiratory disorder, and sinusitis.
 

   b  Percentage corrected for gender.



       Generalized Anxiety Disorder and Posttraumatic Stress Disorder    

  Table 4 enumerates adverse events that occurred at a frequency of 2% or more among GAD patients on PAXIL who participated in placebo-controlled trials of 8-weeks duration in which patients were dosed in a range of 10 mg/day to 50 mg/day or among PTSD patients on PAXIL who participated in placebo-controlled trials of 12-weeks duration in which patients were dosed in a range of 20 mg/day to 50 mg/day.



 Table 4. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials for Generalized Anxiety Disorder and Posttraumatic Stress Disordera 
   Body System         Preferred Term          Generalized Anxiety Disorder      Posttraumatic Stress Disorder     
  PAXIL   (n     =     735)     Placebo   (n     =     529)     PAXIL   (n     =     676)     Placebo   (n     =     504)     
 Body as a Whole     Asthenia                14%             6%              12%            4%                   
 Headache            17%                     14%             -               -               
 Infection           6%                      3%              5%              4%              
 Abdominal Pain                                              4%              3%              
 Trauma                                                      6%              5%              
 Cardiovascular      Vasodilation            3%              1%              2%             1%                   
 Dermatologic        Sweating                6%              2%              5%             1%                   
 Gastrointestinal    Nausea                  20%             5%              19%            8%                   
 Dry Mouth           11%                     5%              10%             5%              
 Constipation        10%                     2%              5%              3%              
 Diarrhea            9%                      7%              11%             5%              
 Decreased Appetite  5%                      1%              6%              3%              
 Vomiting            3%                      2%              3%              2%              
 Dyspepsia           -                       -               5%              3%              
  Nervous System     Insomnia                11%             8%              12%            11%                  
 Somnolence          15%                     5%              16%             5%              
 Dizziness           6%                      5%              6%              5%              
 Tremor              5%                      1%              4%              1%              
 Nervousness         4%                      3%              -               -               
 Libido Decreased    9%                      2%              5%              2%              
 Abnormal Dreams                                             3%              2%              
 Respiratory System  Respiratory Disorder    7%              5%              -              -                    
 Sinusitis           4%                      3%              -               -               
 Yawn                4%                      -               2%              &lt;1%             
 Special Senses      Abnormal Vision         2%              1%              3%             1%                   
 Urogenital System   Abnormal Ejaculation  b    25%             2%              13%            2%                   
 Female Genital Disorder  b    4%                      1%              5%              1%              
 Impotence  b        4%                      3%              9%              1%              
            a. Events reported by at least 2% of GAD and PTSD in patients treated with PAXIL are included, except the following events which had an incidence on placebo &gt;=PAXIL [GAD]: Abdominal pain, back pain, trauma, dyspepsia, myalgia, and pharyngitis. [PTSD]: Back pain, headache, anxiety, depression, nervousness, respiratory disorder, pharyngitis, and sinusitis.
 

   b.  Percentage corrected for gender.



       Dose Dependency of Adverse Events    

  A comparison of adverse event rates in a fixed-dose study comparing 10, 20, 30, and 40 mg/day of PAXIL with placebo in the treatment of major depressive disorder revealed a clear dose dependency for some of the more common adverse events associated with use of PAXIL, as shown in Table 5:



 Table 5. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Experience Incidence in a Dose-Comparison Trial in the Treatment of Major Depressive Disordera 
   Body System/Preferred Term                 Placebo       PAXIL       
   n     =     51                            10 mg   n     =     102     20 mg   n     =     104     30 mg   n     =     101     40 mg   n     =     102     
   Body as a Whole                                                                                             
 Asthenia                                   0.0%          2.9%         10.6%        13.9%        12.7%         
   Dermatology                                                                                                 
 Sweating                                   2.0%          1.0%         6.7%         8.9%         11.8%         
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                            
 Constipation                               5.9%          4.9%         7.7%         9.9%         12.7%         
 Decreased Appetite                         2.0%          2.0%         5.8%         4.0%         4.9%          
 Diarrhea                                   7.8%          9.8%         19.2%        7.9%         14.7%         
 Dry Mouth                                  2.0%          10.8%        18.3%        15.8%        20.6%         
 Nausea                                     13.7%         14.7%        26.9%        34.7%        36.3%         
   Nervous System                                                                                              
 Anxiety                                    0.0%          2.0%         5.8%         5.9%         5.9%          
 Dizziness                                  3.9%          6.9%         6.7%         8.9%         12.7%         
 Nervousness                                0.0%          5.9%         5.8%         4.0%         2.9%          
 Paresthesia                                0.0%          2.9%         1.0%         5.0%         5.9%          
 Somnolence                                 7.8%          12.7%        18.3%        20.8%        21.6%         
 Tremor                                     0.0%          0.0%         7.7%         7.9%         14.7%         
   Special Senses                                                                                              
 Blurred Vision                             2.0%          2.9%         2.9%         2.0%         7.8%          
   Urogenital System                                                                                           
 Abnormal Ejaculation                       0.0%          5.8%         6.5%         10.6%        13.0%         
 Impotence                                  0.0%          1.9%         4.3%         6.4%         1.9%          
 Male Genital Disorders                     0.0%          3.8%         8.7%         6.4%         3.7%          
              a  Rule for including adverse events in table: Incidence at least 5% for 1 of paroxetine groups and &gt;= twice the placebo incidence for at least 1 paroxetine group.
 

 In a fixed-dose study comparing placebo and 20, 40, and 60 mg of PAXIL in the treatment of OCD, there was no clear relationship between adverse events and the dose of PAXIL to which patients were assigned. No new adverse events were observed in the group treated with 60 mg of PAXIL compared to any of the other treatment groups.



 In a fixed-dose study comparing placebo and 10, 20, and 40 mg of PAXIL in the treatment of panic disorder, there was no clear relationship between adverse events and the dose of PAXIL to which patients were assigned, except for asthenia, dry mouth, anxiety, libido decreased, tremor, and abnormal ejaculation. In flexible-dose studies, no new adverse events were observed in patients receiving 60 mg of PAXIL compared to any of the other treatment groups.



 In a fixed-dose study comparing placebo and 20, 40, and 60 mg of PAXIL in the treatment of social anxiety disorder, for most of the adverse events, there was no clear relationship between adverse events and the dose of PAXIL to which patients were assigned.



 In a fixed-dose study comparing placebo and 20 and 40 mg of PAXIL in the treatment of generalized anxiety disorder, for most of the adverse events, there was no clear relationship between adverse events and the dose of PAXIL to which patients were assigned, except for the following adverse events: Asthenia, constipation, and abnormal ejaculation.



 In a fixed-dose study comparing placebo and 20 and 40 mg of PAXIL in the treatment of posttraumatic stress disorder, for most of the adverse events, there was no clear relationship between adverse events and the dose of PAXIL to which patients were assigned, except for impotence and abnormal ejaculation.



       Adaptation to Certain Adverse Events    

  Over a 4- to 6-week period, there was evidence of adaptation to some adverse events with continued therapy (e.g., nausea and dizziness), but less to other effects (e.g., dry mouth, somnolence, and asthenia).



       Male and Female Sexual Dysfunction With SSRIs    

  Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) can cause such untoward sexual experiences.



 Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, however, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling, are likely to underestimate their actual incidence.



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials involving more than 3,200 patients, the ranges for the reported incidence of sexual side effects in males and females with major depressive disorder, OCD, panic disorder, social anxiety disorder, GAD, and PTSD are displayed in Table 6.



 Table 6. Incidence of Sexual Adverse Events in Controlled Clinical Trials 
                                     PAXIL                              Placebo                           
   n (males)                         1446                               1042                              
 Decreased Libido                  6-15%                              0-5%                                
 Ejaculatory Disturbance           13-28%                             0-2%                                
 Impotence                         2-9%                               0-3%                                
   n (females)                       1822                               1340                              
 Decreased Libido                  0-9%                               0-2%                                
 Orgasmic Disturbance              2-9%                               0-1%                                
         There are no adequate and well-controlled studies examining sexual dysfunction with paroxetine treatment.
 

 Paroxetine treatment has been associated with several cases of priapism. In those cases with a known outcome, patients recovered without sequelae.



 While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



       Weight and Vital Sign Changes    

  Significant weight loss may be an undesirable result of treatment with PAXIL for some patients but, on average, patients in controlled trials had minimal (about 1 pound) weight loss versus smaller changes on placebo and active control. No significant changes in vital signs (systolic and diastolic blood pressure, pulse and temperature) were observed in patients treated with PAXIL in controlled clinical trials.



       ECG Changes    

  In an analysis of ECGs obtained in 682 patients treated with PAXIL and 415 patients treated with placebo in controlled clinical trials, no clinically significant changes were seen in the ECGs of either group.



       Liver Function Tests    

  In placebo-controlled clinical trials, patients treated with PAXIL exhibited abnormal values on liver function tests at no greater rate than that seen in placebo-treated patients. In particular, the PAXIL-versus-placebo comparisons for alkaline phosphatase, SGOT, SGPT, and bilirubin revealed no differences in the percentage of patients with marked abnormalities.



       Hallucinations    

  In pooled clinical trials of immediate-release paroxetine hydrochloride, hallucinations were observed in 22 of 9089 patients receiving drug and 4 of 3187 patients receiving placebo.



   Other Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of PAXIL

  During its premarketing assessment in major depressive disorder, multiple doses of PAXIL were administered to 6,145 patients in phase 2 and 3 studies. The conditions and duration of exposure to PAXIL varied greatly and included (in overlapping categories) open and double-blind studies, uncontrolled and controlled studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, and fixed-dose, and titration studies. During premarketing clinical trials in OCD, panic disorder, social anxiety disorder, generalized anxiety disorder, and posttraumatic stress disorder, 542, 469, 522, 735, and 676 patients, respectively, received multiple doses of PAXIL. Untoward events associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized event categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based Dictionary terminology. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the 9,089 patients exposed to multiple doses of PAXIL who experienced an event of the type cited on at least 1 occasion while receiving PAXIL. All reported events are included except those already listed in Tables 2 to 5, those reported in terms so general as to be uninformative and those events where a drug cause was remote. It is important to emphasize that although the events reported occurred during treatment with paroxetine, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: Frequent adverse events are those occurring on 1 or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients (only those not already listed in the tabulated results from placebo-controlled trials appear in this listing); infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients; rare events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1,000 patients. Events of major clinical importance are also described in the PRECAUTIONS section.



       Body as a Whole    

    Infrequent:  Allergic reaction, chills, face edema, malaise, neck pain;  rare:  Adrenergic syndrome, cellulitis, moniliasis, neck rigidity, pelvic pain, peritonitis, sepsis, ulcer.



       Cardiovascular System    

    Frequent:  Hypertension, tachycardia;  infrequent:  Bradycardia, hematoma, hypotension, migraine, postural hypotension, syncope;  rare:  Angina pectoris, arrhythmia nodal, atrial fibrillation, bundle branch block, cerebral ischemia, cerebrovascular accident, congestive heart failure, heart block, low cardiac output, myocardial infarct, myocardial ischemia, pallor, phlebitis, pulmonary embolus, supraventricular extrasystoles, thrombophlebitis, thrombosis, varicose vein, vascular headache, ventricular extrasystoles.



       Digestive System    

    Infrequent:  Bruxism, colitis, dysphagia, eructation, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gingivitis, glossitis, increased salivation, liver function tests abnormal, rectal hemorrhage, ulcerative stomatitis;  rare:  Aphthous stomatitis, bloody diarrhea, bulimia, cardiospasm, cholelithiasis, duodenitis, enteritis, esophagitis, fecal impactions, fecal incontinence, gum hemorrhage, hematemesis, hepatitis, ileitis, ileus, intestinal obstruction, jaundice, melena, mouth ulceration, peptic ulcer, salivary gland enlargement, sialadenitis, stomach ulcer, stomatitis, tongue discoloration, tongue edema, tooth caries.



       Endocrine System    

    Rare:  Diabetes mellitus, goiter, hyperthyroidism, hypothyroidism, thyroiditis.



       Hemic and Lymphatic Systems    

    Infrequent:  Anemia, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, purpura;  rare:  Abnormal erythrocytes, basophilia, bleeding time increased, eosinophilia, hypochromic anemia, iron deficiency anemia, leukocytosis, lymphedema, abnormal lymphocytes, lymphocytosis, microcytic anemia, monocytosis, normocytic anemia, thrombocythemia, thrombocytopenia.



       Metabolic and Nutritional    

    Frequent:  Weight gain;  infrequent:  Edema, peripheral edema, SGOT increased, SGPT increased, thirst, weight loss;  rare:  Alkaline phosphatase increased, bilirubinemia, BUN increased, creatinine phosphokinase increased, dehydration, gamma globulins increased, gout, hypercalcemia, hypercholesteremia, hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia, hyperphosphatemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, ketosis, lactic dehydrogenase increased, non-protein nitrogen (NPN) increased.



       Musculoskeletal System    

    Frequent:  Arthralgia;  infrequent:  Arthritis, arthrosis;  rare:  Bursitis, myositis, osteoporosis, generalized spasm, tenosynovitis, tetany.



       Nervous System    

    Frequent:  Emotional lability, vertigo;  infrequent:  Abnormal thinking, alcohol abuse, ataxia, dystonia, dyskinesia, euphoria, hallucinations, hostility, hypertonia, hypesthesia, hypokinesia, incoordination, lack of emotion, libido increased, manic reaction, neurosis, paralysis, paranoid reaction;  rare:  Abnormal gait, akinesia, antisocial reaction, aphasia, choreoathetosis, circumoral paresthesias, convulsion, delirium, delusions, diplopia, drug dependence, dysarthria, extrapyramidal syndrome, fasciculations, grand mal convulsion, hyperalgesia, hysteria, manic-depressive reaction, meningitis, myelitis, neuralgia, neuropathy, nystagmus, peripheral neuritis, psychotic depression, psychosis, reflexes decreased, reflexes increased, stupor, torticollis, trismus, withdrawal syndrome.



       Respiratory System    

    Infrequent:  Asthma, bronchitis, dyspnea, epistaxis, hyperventilation, pneumonia, respiratory flu;  rare:  Emphysema, hemoptysis, hiccups, lung fibrosis, pulmonary edema, sputum increased, stridor, voice alteration.



       Skin and Appendages    

    Frequent:  Pruritus;  infrequent:  Acne, alopecia, contact dermatitis, dry skin, ecchymosis, eczema, herpes simplex, photosensitivity, urticaria;  rare:  Angioedema, erythema nodosum, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, fungal dermatitis, furunculosis; herpes zoster, hirsutism, maculopapular rash, seborrhea, skin discoloration, skin hypertrophy, skin ulcer, sweating decreased, vesiculobullous rash.



       Special Senses    

    Frequent  : Tinnitus;  infrequent:  Abnormality of accommodation, conjunctivitis, ear pain, eye pain, keratoconjunctivitis, mydriasis, otitis media;  rare:  Amblyopia, anisocoria, blepharitis, cataract, conjunctival edema, corneal ulcer, deafness, exophthalmos, eye hemorrhage, glaucoma, hyperacusis, night blindness, otitis externa, parosmia, photophobia, ptosis, retinal hemorrhage, taste loss, visual field defect.



       Urogenital System    

    Infrequent:  Amenorrhea, breast pain, cystitis, dysuria, hematuria, menorrhagia, nocturia, polyuria, pyuria, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urinary urgency, vaginitis;  rare:  Abortion, breast atrophy, breast enlargement, endometrial disorder, epididymitis, female lactation, fibrocystic breast, kidney calculus, kidney pain, leukorrhea, mastitis, metrorrhagia, nephritis, oliguria, salpingitis, urethritis, urinary casts, uterine spasm, urolith, vaginal hemorrhage, vaginal moniliasis.



   Postmarketing Reports

  Voluntary reports of adverse events in patients taking PAXIL that have been received since market introduction and not listed above that may have no causal relationship with the drug include acute pancreatitis, elevated liver function tests (the most severe cases were deaths due to liver necrosis, and grossly elevated transaminases associated with severe liver dysfunction), Guillain-Barre syndrome, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, priapism, syndrome of inappropriate ADH secretion, symptoms suggestive of prolactinemia and galactorrhea; extrapyramidal symptoms which have included akathisia, bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, dystonia, hypertonia, oculogyric crisis which has been associated with concomitant use of pimozide; tremor and trismus; status epilepticus, acute renal failure, pulmonary hypertension, allergic alveolitis, anaphylaxis, eclampsia, laryngismus, optic neuritis, porphyria,restless legs syndrome (RLS), ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia (including torsade de pointes), thrombocytopenia, hemolytic anemia, events related to impaired hematopoiesis (including aplastic anemia, pancytopenia, bone marrow aplasia, and agranulocytosis), and vasculitic syndromes (such as Henoch-Schonlein purpura). There has been a case report of an elevated phenytoin level after 4 weeks of PAXIL and phenytoin coadministration. There has been a case report of severe hypotension when PAXIL was added to chronic metoprolol treatment.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

  Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of PAXIL or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. PAXIL is not approved for use in pediatric patients. (See WARNINGS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk, PRECAUTIONS: Information for Patients, and PRECAUTIONS: Pediatric Use.)  



 





    BOXED WARNING: Medication Guide

  Medication Guide

    PAXIL  (r)   (PAX-il)  



   (paroxetine hydrochloride)  



   Tablets and Oral Suspension  



 Read the Medication Guide that comes with PAXIL before you start taking it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or treatment. Talk with your healthcare provider if there is something you do not understand or want to learn more about.



   What is the most important information I should know about PAXIL?  



 PAXIL and other antidepressant medicines may cause serious side effects, including:



   1. Suicidal thoughts or actions:  



 *  PAXIL and other antidepressant medicines may increase suicidal thoughts or actions in some children, teenagers, or young adults within the first few months of treatment or when the dose is changed. 
 *  Depression or other serious mental illnesses are the most important causes of suicidal thoughts or actions. 
 *  Watch for these changes and call your healthcare provider right away if you notice: New or sudden changes in mood, behavior, actions, thoughts, or feelings, especially if severe. Pay particular attention to such changes when PAXIL is started or when the dose is changed. 
    Keep all follow-up visits with your healthcare provider and call between visits if you are worried about symptoms.
 

   Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency, especially if they are new, worse, or worry you:  



 *  attempts to commit suicide 
 *  acting on dangerous impulses 
 *  acting aggressive or violent 
 *  thoughts about suicide or dying 
 *  new or worse depression 
 *  new or worse anxiety or panic attacks 
 *  feeling agitated, restless, angry, or irritable 
 *  trouble sleeping 
 *  an increase in activity or talking more than what is normal for you 
 *  other unusual changes in behavior or mood 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency. PAXIL may be associated with these serious side effects:  
 

   2. Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome-like reactions. This condition can be life-threatening and may include:  



 *  agitation, hallucinations, coma, or other changes in mental status 
 *  coordination problems or muscle twitching (overactive reflexes) 
 *  racing heartbeat, high or low blood pressure 
 *  sweating or fever 
 *  nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea 
 *  muscle rigidity 
      3. Severe allergic reactions:  
 

 *  trouble breathing 
 *  swelling of the face, tongue, eyes, or mouth 
 *  rash, itchy welts (hives), or blisters, alone or with fever or joint pain 
      4. Abnormal bleeding:   PAXIL and other antidepressant medicines may increase your risk of bleeding or bruising, especially if you take the blood thinner warfarin (Coumadin  (r)  , Jantoven  (r)  ), a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAIDs, like ibuprofen or naproxen), or aspirin.
 

   5. Seizures or convulsions  



   6. Manic episodes:  



 *  greatly increased energy 
 *  severe trouble sleeping 
 *  racing thoughts 
 *  reckless behavior 
 *  unusually grand ideas 
 *  excessive happiness or irritability 
 *  talking more or faster than usual 
      7. Changes in appetite or weight.   Children and adolescents should have height and weight monitored during treatment.
 

   8. Low salt (sodium) levels in the blood.   Elderly people may be at greater risk for this. Symptoms may include:



 *  headache 
 *  weakness or feeling unsteady 
 *  confusion, problems concentrating or thinking, or memory problems 
      Do not stop PAXIL without first talking to your healthcare provider.   Stopping PAXIL too quickly may cause serious symptoms including:
 

 *  anxiety, irritability, high or low mood, feeling restless, or changes in sleep habits 
 *  headache, sweating, nausea, dizziness 
 *  electric shock-like sensations, shaking, confusion 
      What is PAXIL?  
 

 PAXIL is a prescription medicine used to treat depression. It is important to talk with your healthcare provider about the risks of treating depression and also the risks of not treating it. You should discuss all treatment choices with your healthcare provider. PAXIL is   also   used to treat:



 *  Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) 
 *  Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD) 
 *  Panic Disorder 
 *  Social Anxiety Disorder 
 *  Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) 
 *  Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) 
    Talk to your healthcare provider if you do not think that your condition is getting better with treatment using PAXIL.
 

   Who should not take PAXIL?  



 Do not take PAXIL if you:



 *  are allergic to paroxetine or any of the ingredients in PAXIL. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in PAXIL. 
 *  take a monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI). Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure if you take an MAOI, including the antibiotic linezolid. 
 *  Do not take an MAOI within 2 weeks of stopping PAXIL unless directed to do so by your physician. 
 *  Do not start PAXIL if you stopped taking an MAOI in the last 2 weeks unless directed to do so by your physician. 
 *  People who take PAXIL close in time to an MAOI may have serious or even life-threatening side effects. Get medical help right away if you have any of these symptoms:high feveruncontrolled muscle spasmsstiff musclesrapid changes in heart rate or blood pressureconfusionloss of consciousness (pass out) 
   *  take MELLARIL(r) (thioridazine). Do not take MELLARIL(r) together with PAXIL because this can cause serious heart rhythm problems or sudden death. 
 *  take the antipsychotic medicine pimozide (ORAP(r)) because this can cause serious heart problems. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking PAXIL? Ask if you are not sure.  
 

 Before starting PAXIL, tell your healthcare provider if you:



 *  are pregnant, may be pregnant, or plan to become pregnant. There is a possibility that PAXIL may harm your unborn baby, including an increased risk of birth defects, particularly heart defects. Other risks may include a serious condition in which there is not enough oxygen in the baby's blood. Your baby may also have certain other symptoms shortly after birth. Premature births have also been reported in some women who used PAXIL during pregnancy 
 *  are breastfeeding. PAXIL passes into your milk. Talk to your healthcare provider about the best way to feed your baby while taking PAXIL. 
 *  are taking certain drugs such as: triptans used to treat migraine headacheother antidepressants (SSRIs, SNRIs, tricyclics, or lithium) or antipsychoticsdrugs that affect serotonin, such as lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, St. John's wortcertain drugs used to treat irregular heart beatscertain drugs used to treat schizophreniacertain drugs used to treat HIV infection certain drugs that affect the blood, such as warfarin, aspirin, and ibuprofencertain drugs used to treat epilepsyatomoxetinecimetidinefentanylmetoprololpimozideprocyclidinetamoxifen 
 *  have liver problems 
 *  have kidney problems 
 *  have heart problems 
 *  have or had seizures or convulsions 
 *  have bipolar disorder or mania 
 *  have low sodium levels in your blood 
 *  have a history of a stroke 
 *  have high blood pressure 
 *  have or had bleeding problems 
 *  have glaucoma (high pressure in the eye) 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take  , including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. PAXIL and some medicines may interact with each other, may not work as well, or may cause serious side effects.
 

 Your healthcare provider or pharmacist can tell you if it is safe to take PAXIL with your other medicines. Do not start or stop any medicine while taking PAXIL without talking to your healthcare provider first.



   If you take PAXIL, you should not take any other medicines that contain paroxetine, including PAXIL CR and PEXEVA  (r)   (paroxetine mesylate). 



     How should I take PAXIL?  



 *  Take PAXIL exactly as prescribed. Your healthcare provider may need to change the dose of PAXIL until it is the right dose for you. 
 *  PAXIL may be taken with or without food. 
 *  If you are taking PAXIL Oral Suspension, shake the suspension well before use. 
 *  If you miss a dose of PAXIL, take the missed dose as soon as you remember. If it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and take your next dose at the regular time. Do not take two doses of PAXIL at the same time. 
 *  If you take too much PAXIL, call your healthcare provider or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
 *  Do not stop taking PAXIL suddenly without talking to your doctor (unless you have symptoms of a severe allergic reaction). If you need to stop taking PAXIL, your healthcare provider can tell you how to safely stop taking it. 
      What should I avoid while taking PAXIL?  
 

 PAXIL can cause sleepiness or may affect your ability to make decisions, think clearly, or react quickly. You should not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how PAXIL affects you. Do not drink alcohol while using PAXIL.



   What are possible side effects of PAXIL?  



 PAXIL may cause serious side effects, including all of those described in the section entitled "What is the most important information I should know about PAXIL?" 



 Common possible side effects in people who take PAXIL include:



 *  nausea 
 *  sleepiness 
 *  weakness 
 *  dizziness 
 *  feeling anxious or trouble sleeping 
 *  sexual problems 
 *  sweating 
 *  shaking 
 *  not feeling hungry 
 *  dry mouth 
 *  constipation 
 *  infection 
 *  yawning 
    Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away. These are not all the possible side effects of PAXIL. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.
 

   CALL YOUR DOCTOR FOR MEDICAL ADVICE ABOUT SIDE EFFECTS. YOU MAY REPORT SIDE EFFECTS TO THE FDA AT 1-800-FDA-1088 or 1-800-332-1088.  



   How should I store PAXIL?  



 *  Store PAXIL Tablets at room temperature between 59o and 86oF (15o and 30oC). 
 *  Store PAXIL Oral Suspension at or below 77oF (25oC). 
 *  Keep PAXIL away from light. 
 *  Keep bottle of PAXIL closed tightly. 
      Keep PAXIL and all medicines out of the reach of children.  
 

   General information about PAXIL  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use PAXIL for a condition for which it was not prescribed. Do not give PAXIL to other people, even if they have the same condition. It may harm them.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about PAXIL. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You may ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for information about PAXIL that is written for healthcare professionals.



 For more information about PAXIL call 1-888-825-5249 or go to www.us.gsk.com.



   What are the ingredients in PAXIL?  



   Active ingredient:   paroxetine hydrochloride



   Inactive ingredients in tablets:   dibasic calcium phosphate dihydrate, hypromellose, magnesium stearate, polyethylene glycols, polysorbate 80, sodium starch glycolate, titanium dioxide, and 1 or more of the following: D&amp;C Red No. 30 aluminum lake, D&amp;C Yellow No. 10 aluminum lake, FD&amp;C Blue No. 2 aluminum lake, FD&amp;C Yellow No. 6 aluminum lake.



   Inactive ingredients in suspension for oral administration:   polacrilin potassium, microcrystalline cellulose, propylene glycol, glycerin, sorbitol, methylparaben, propylparaben, sodium citrate dihydrate, citric acid anhydrous, sodium saccharin, flavorings, FD&amp;C Yellow No. 6 aluminum lake, and simethicone emulsion, USP.



 PAXIL and PAXIL CR are registered trademarks of GlaxoSmithKline. The other brands listed are trademarks of their respective owners and are not trademarks of GlaxoSmithKline. The makers of these brands are not affiliated with and do not endorse GlaxoSmithKline or its products.



 This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.



 GlaxoSmithKline



 Research Triangle Park, NC 27709



 (c)2011, GlaxoSmithKline. All rights reserved.



 July 2011 PXL:6MG
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
