<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="peg33500" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Nausea, abdominal fullness and bloating are the most common adverse reactions (occurred in up to 50% of patients) to administration of PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution. Abdominal cramps, vomiting and anal irritation occur less frequently. These adverse reactions are transient and usually subside rapidly. Isolated cases of urticaria, rhinorrhea, dermatitis and (rarely) anaphylactic reaction have been reported which may represent allergic reactions.



 Published literature contains isolated reports of serious adverse reactions following the administration of PEG-electrolyte solution products in patients over 60 years of age. These adverse events include upper GI bleeding from Mallory-Weiss Tear, esophageal perforation, asystole, sudden dyspnea with pulmonary edema, and "butterfly-like" infiltrates on chest X-ray after vomiting and aspirating PEG.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3%) are: nausea, abdominal fullness and bloating. Abdominal cramps, vomiting and anal irritation occur less frequently



 (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Affordable Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-800-514-5617 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Risk of fluid and electrolyte abnormalities, arrhythmias, seizures and renal impairment- assess concurrent medications and consider testing in some patients (  5.1  ,  5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
 *  Patients with renal insufficiency- use caution, ensure adequate hydration and consider testing (  5.4  ) 
 *  Suspected GI obstruction or perforation - rule out the diagnosis before administration (  4  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Patients at risk for aspiration - observe during administration (  5.7  ) 
 *  Not for direct ingestion - dilute and take with additional water (  5.8  ) 
    
 

      5.1 Serious Fluid and Serum Chemistry Abnormalities



     Advise patients to hydrate adequately before, during, and after the use of PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution. Use caution in patients with congestive heart failure when replacing fluids. If a patient develops significant vomiting or signs of dehydration including signs of orthostatic hypotension after taking PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution, consider performing post-colonoscopy lab tests (electrolytes, creatinine, and BUN) and treat accordingly. Fluid and electrolyte disturbances can lead to serious adverse events including cardiac arrhythmias, seizures and renal impairment. Fluid and electrolyte abnormalities should be corrected before treatment with PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution.



    In addition, use caution when prescribing PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution for patients who have conditions, or who are using medications, that increase the risk for fluid and electrolyte disturbances or may increase the risk of adverse events of seizure, arrhythmias, and renal impairment [ see Drug Interactions  (  7.1  )]



       5.2 Cardiac Arrhythmias



     There have been rare reports of serious arrhythmias associated with the use of ionic osmotic laxative products for bowel preparation. Use caution when prescribing PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution for patients at increased risk of arrhythmias (e.g., patients with a history of prolonged QT, uncontrolled arrhythmias, recent myocardial infarction, unstable angina, congestive heart failure, or cardiomyopathy). Pre-dose and post-colonoscopy ECGs should be considered in patients at increased risk of serious cardiac arrhythmias.



       5.3 Seizures



     There have been reports of generalized tonic-clonic seizures and/or loss of consciousness associated with use of bowel preparation products in patients with no prior history of seizures. The seizure cases were associated with electrolyte abnormalities (e.g., hyponatremia, hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, and hypomagnesemia) and low serum osmolality. The neurologic abnormalities resolved with correction of fluid and electrolyte abnormalities.



    Use caution when prescribing PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution for patients with a history of seizures and in patients at increased risk of seizure, such as patients taking medications that lower the seizure threshold (e.g., tricyclic antidepressants), patients withdrawing from alcohol or benzodiazepines, or patients with known or suspected hyponatremia.



       5.4 Renal Impairment



     Use caution when prescribing PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution for patients with impaired renal function or patients taking concomitant medications that may affect renal function (such as diuretics, angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers, or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs). Advise these patients of the importance of adequate hydration, and consider performing baseline and post-colonoscopy laboratory tests (electrolytes, creatinine, and BUN) in these patients.



       5.5 Colonic Mucosal Ulcerations and Ischemic Colitis



     Administration of osmotic laxative products may produce colonic mucosal aphthous ulcerations, and there have been reports of more serious cases of ischemic colitis requiring hospitalization. Concurrent use of stimulant laxatives and PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution may increase this risk. The potential for mucosal ulcerations resulting from the bowel preparation should be considered when interpreting colonoscopy findings in patients with known or suspect inflammatory bowel disease (IBD).



       5.6 Use in Patients with Significant Gastrointestinal Disease



     If gastrointestinal obstruction or perforation is suspected, perform appropriate diagnostic studies to rule out these conditions before administering PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution. If a patient experiences severe bloating, distention or abdominal pain, administration should be slowed or temporarily discontinued until the symptoms abate. If gastrointestinal obstruction or perforation is suspected, appropriate studies should be performed to rule out these conditions before administration of PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution.



    Use with caution in patients with severe active ulcerative colitis.



       5.7 Aspiration



     Use with caution in patients with impaired gag reflex, unconscious, or semiconscious patients, and patients prone to regurgitation or aspiration. Such patients should be observed during administration of PEG-3350, sodium chloride, sodium bicarbonate and potassium chloride for oral solution, especially if it is administered via nasogastric tube.



       5.8 Not for Direct Ingestion



     The contents of each jug must be diluted with water to a final volume of 4 liters (4 L) and ingestion of additional water is important to patient tolerance. Direct ingestion of the undissolved powder may increase the risk of nausea, vomiting, dehydration, and electrolyte disturbances.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
