<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pennsaid" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse events with PENNSAID are application site reactions. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Horizon Pharma USA Inc. at 1-866-479-6742 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     PENNSAID  



 The data described below reflect exposure to PENNSAID of 130 patients treated for 4 weeks (mean duration of 28 days) in one Phase 2 controlled trial. This population's mean age was approximately 60 years, 85% of patients were Caucasian, 65% were females, and all patients had primary osteoarthritis. The most common adverse events with PENNSAID were application site skin reactions. These events were the most common reason for withdrawing from the study.



     Application Site Reactions:  



 In this controlled trial, application site reactions were characterized by one or more of the following: dryness (22%), exfoliation (7%), erythema (4%), pruritus (2%), pain (2%), induration (2%), rash (2%), and scabbing (&lt;1%).



     Other Common Adverse Reactions:  



 Table 1 lists all adverse reactions occurring in &gt;1% of patients receiving PENNSAID, where the rate in the PENNSAID group exceeded vehicle, from a controlled study conducted in patients with osteoarthritis.



 Table 1: Incidence of Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;1% of Subjects with Osteoarthritis Using PENNSAID and More Often than in Subjects with OA Using Vehicle Control (Pooled) 
 Adverse Reaction                                PENNSAIDN=130n (%)          Vehicle ControlN=129n (%)      
  
   Urinary tract infection                             4 (3%)                         1 (&lt;1%)               
   Application site induration                         2 (2%)                         1 (&lt;1%)               
   Contusion                                           2 (2%)                         1 (&lt;1%)               
   Sinus congestion                                    2 (2%)                         1 (&lt;1%)               
   Nausea                                              2 (2%)                            0                  
             PENNSAID 1.5%  
 

 The safety of PENNSAID 2% is based in part, on prior experience with PENNSAID 1.5%. The data described below reflect exposure to PENNSAID 1.5% of 911 patients treated between 4 and 12 weeks (mean duration of 49 days) in seven Phase 3 controlled trials, as well as exposure of 793 patients treated in an open-label study, including 463 patients treated for at least 6 months, and 144 patients treated for at least 12 months. The population mean age was approximately 60 years, 89% of patients were Caucasian, 64% were females, and all patients had primary osteoarthritis. The most common adverse events with PENNSAID 1.5% were application site skin reactions. These events were the most common reason for withdrawing from the studies.



     Application Site Reactions:  



 In controlled trials, application site reactions were characterized by one or more of the following: dryness, erythema, induration, vesicles, paresthesia, pruritus, vasodilation, acne, and urticaria. The most frequent of these reactions were dry skin (32%), contact dermatitis characterized by skin erythema and induration (9%), contact dermatitis with vesicles (2%) and pruritus (4%). In one controlled trial, a higher rate of contact dermatitis with vesicles (4%) was observed after treatment of 152 subjects with the combination of PENNSAID 1.5% and oral diclofenac. In the open-label uncontrolled long-term safety study, contact dermatitis occurred in 13% and contact dermatitis with vesicles in 10% of patients, generally within the first 6 months of exposure, leading to a withdrawal rate for an application site event of 14%.



     Other Common Adverse Reactions:  



 In controlled trials, subjects treated with PENNSAID 1.5% experienced some adverse events associated with the NSAID class more frequently than subjects using placebo (constipation, diarrhea, dyspepsia, nausea, flatulence, abdominal pain, edema; see  Table 2  ). The combination of PENNSAID 1.5% and oral diclofenac, compared to oral diclofenac alone, resulted in a higher rate of rectal hemorrhage (3% vs. less than 1%), and more frequent abnormal creatinine (12% vs. 7%), urea (20% vs. 12%), and hemoglobin (13% vs. 9%), but no difference in elevation of liver transaminases.



 Table 2 lists all adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=1% of patients receiving PENNSAID 1.5%, where the rate in the PENNSAID 1.5% group exceeded placebo, from seven controlled studies conducted in patients with osteoarthritis. Since these trials were of different durations, these percentages do not capture cumulative rates of occurrence.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=1% of Patients Treated with PENNSAID 1.5% Topical Solution in Placebo and Oral Diclofenac-Controlled Trials 
 Treatment Group:                                PENNSAID 1.5%N=911             Topical PlaceboN=332        
 Adverse Reaction                                      N (%)                           N (%)                
  
 Dry Skin (Application Site)                          292 (32)                         17 (5)               
 Contact Dermatitis (Application Site)                 83 (9)                          6 (2)                
 Dyspepsia                                             72 (8)                          13 (4)               
 Abdominal Pain                                        54 (6)                          10 (3)               
 Flatulence                                            35 (4)                          1 (&lt;1)               
 Pruritus (Application Site)                           34 (4)                          7 (2)                
 Diarrhea                                              33 (4)                          7 (2)                
 Nausea                                                33 (4)                          3 (1)                
 Pharyngitis                                           40 (4)                          13 (4)               
 Constipation                                          29 (3)                          1 (&lt;1)               
 Edema                                                 26 (3)                            0                  
 Rash (Non-Application Site)                           25 (3)                          5 (2)                
 Infection                                             25 (3)                          8 (2)                
 Ecchymosis                                            19 (2)                          1 (&lt;1)               
 Dry Skin (Non-Application Site)                       19 (2)                          1 (&lt;1)               
 Contact Dermatitis, vesicles (Application Site)              18 (2)                            0                  
 Paresthesia (Non-Application Site)                    14 (2)                          3 (&lt;1)               
 Accidental Injury                                     22 (2)                          7 (2)                
 Pruritus (Non-Application Site)                       15 (2)                          2 (&lt;1)               
 Sinusitis                                             10 (1)                          2 (&lt;1)               
 Halitosis                                             11 (1)                          1 (&lt;1)               
 Application Site Reaction (not otherwise specified)              11 (1)                          3 (&lt;1)               
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   In postmarketing surveillance, the following adverse reactions have been reported during post- approval use of PENNSAID 1.5%. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain, accidental injury, allergic reactions, asthenia, back pain, body odor, chest pain, edema, face edema, halitosis, headache, neck rigidity, pain



   Cardiovascular:  palpitation, cardiovascular disorder



   Gastrointestinal:  diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, gastroenteritis, decreased appetite, lip swelling, mouth ulceration, nausea, rectal hemorrhage, ulcerative stomatitis, swollen tongue



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  creatinine increased



   Musculoskeletal:  leg cramps, myalgia



   Nervous:  depression, dizziness, drowsiness, lethargy, paresthesia at application site



   Respiratory:  asthma, dyspnea, laryngismus, laryngitis, pharyngitis, throat swelling



   Skin and Appendages: At the Application Site:  rash, skin burning sensation;  Other Skin and Appendages Adverse Reactions:  eczema, skin discoloration, urticaria



   Special Senses:  abnormal vision, blurred vision, cataract, ear pain, eye disorder, eye pain, taste perversion



   Vascular:  blood pressure increased, hypertension
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISK

    WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISK  

    Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  PENNSAID is contraindicated in the perioperative setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery [see Contraindications (4)]. 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISK
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. (5.1) 
 *  PENNSAID is contraindicated for the treatment of perioperative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4) 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs, including PENNSAID, cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious and potentially fatal cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke can occur with NSAID treatment. Use the lowest effective dose of PENNSAID in patients with known cardiovascular (CV) disease or risk factors for CV disease. (  5.1  ) 
 *  NSAIDs can cause serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation. Closely monitor patients with a prior history of ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Elevation of one or more liver tests may occur during therapy with NSAIDs. Discontinue PENNSAID immediately if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hypertension can occur with NSAID treatment. Monitor blood pressure closely with PENNSAID treatment. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Monitor fluid status and cardiac function in patients with fluid retention or heart failure. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Long-term administration of NSAIDs can result in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Monitor renal function closely in patients at greatest risk of this reaction, including the elderly, those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, and those taking diuretics and ACE-inhibitors. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Anaphylactoid reactions may occur in patients with the aspirin triad or in patients without prior exposure to PENNSAID. (  5.7  ) 
 *  NSAIDs can cause serious skin adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Not for use during pregnancy. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Do not administer to patients with aspirin sensitive asthma and use with caution in patients with preexisting asthma. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Avoid exposure of treated knee(s) to natural or artificial sunlight. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Avoid contact of PENNSAID with eyes and mucosa. (  5.12  ) 
 *  Avoid concurrent use with oral NSAIDs. (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several oral COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction (MI), and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, including PENNSAID and COX-2 selective and nonselective orally administered NSAIDs, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Inform patients about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 Two large, controlled, clinical trials of an orally administered COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10 to 14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and NSAIDs, such as diclofenac, does increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



    5.2 Gastrointestinal Effects - Risk of GI Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including diclofenac, can cause serious GI adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs occur in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3 to 6 months, and in about 2 to 4% of patients treated for one year. These trends continue with longer duration of use, increasing the likelihood of developing a serious GI event at some time during the course of therapy. However, even short-term therapy is not without risk.



 When prescribing PENNSAID, for patients with a prior history of ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding, monitor closely for signs and symptoms of gastrointestinal ulcers and gastrointestinal bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or gastrointestinal bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing a GI bleed compared to patients with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk of GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants, longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most spontaneous reports of fatal GI events are in elderly or debilitated patients and therefore, use special care when treating this population.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI event, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest possible duration. Remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulceration and bleeding during diclofenac therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI adverse event is suspected. For high-risk patients, consider alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs.



    5.3 Hepatic Effects



  Borderline elevations (less than 3 times the upper limit of the normal [ULN] range) or greater elevations of transaminases occurred in about 15% of oral diclofenac-treated patients in clinical trials of indications other than acute pain. Of the markers of hepatic function, ALT (SGPT) is recommended for the monitoring of liver injury.



 In clinical trials of an oral diclofenac-misoprostol combination product, meaningful elevations (i.e., more than 3 times the ULN) of AST (SGOT) occurred in about 2% of approximately 5,700 patients at some time during diclofenac treatment (ALT was not measured in all studies).



 In an open-label, controlled trial of 3,700 patients treated for 2 to 6 months, patients with oral diclofenac were monitored first at 8 weeks and 1,200 patients were monitored again at 24 weeks. Meaningful elevations of ALT and/or AST occurred in about 4% of the 3,700 patients and included marked elevations (&gt;8 times the ULN) in about 1% of the 3,700 patients. In this open-label study, a higher incidence of borderline (less than 3 times the ULN), moderate (3 to 8 times the ULN), and marked (&gt;8 times the ULN) elevations of ALT or AST was observed in patients receiving diclofenac when compared to other NSAIDs. Elevations in transaminases were seen more frequently in patients with osteoarthritis than in those with rheumatoid arthritis. Almost all meaningful elevations in transaminases were detected before patients became symptomatic.



 Abnormal tests occurred during the first 2 months of therapy with oral diclofenac in 42 of the 51 patients in all trials who developed marked transaminase elevations. In postmarketing reports, cases of drug-induced hepatotoxicity have been reported in the first month, and in some cases, the first 2 months of NSAID therapy.



 Postmarketing surveillance has reported cases of severe hepatic reactions, including liver necrosis, jaundice, fulminant hepatitis with and without jaundice, and liver failure. Some of these reported cases resulted in fatalities or liver transplantation.



 In a European retrospective population-based, case-controlled study, 10 cases of oral diclofenac associated drug-induced liver injury with current use compared with non-use of diclofenac were associated with a statistically significant 4-fold adjusted odds ratio of liver injury. In this particular study, based on an overall number of 10 cases of liver injury associated with diclofenac, the adjusted odds ratio increased further with female gender, doses of 150 mg or more, and duration of use for more than 90 days.



 Measure transaminases (ALT and AST) periodically in patients receiving long-term therapy with diclofenac, because severe hepatotoxicity may develop without a prodrome of distinguishing symptoms. The optimum times for making the first and subsequent transaminase measurements are not known. Based on clinical trial data and postmarketing experiences, monitor transaminases within 4 to 8 weeks after initiating treatment with diclofenac. However, severe hepatic reactions can occur at any time during treatment with diclofenac. If abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, if clinical signs and/or symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, abdominal pain, diarrhea, dark urine, etc.), discontinue PENNSAID immediately.



 To minimize the possibility that hepatic injury will become severe between transaminase measurements, inform patients of the warning signs and symptoms of hepatotoxicity (e.g., nausea, fatigue, lethargy, diarrhea, pruritus, jaundice, right upper quadrant tenderness, and "flu-like" symptoms), and the appropriate action to take if these signs and symptoms appear.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse liver-related event in patients treated with PENNSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. When prescribing PENNSAID with concomitant drugs that are known to be potentially hepatotoxic (e.g., acetaminophen, certain antibiotics, antiepileptics), monitor patients for signs of hepatic injury. Instruct patients to avoid taking unprescribed acetaminophen while using PENNSAID.



    5.4 Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including diclofenac, can lead to new onset or worsening of preexisting hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. When prescribing PENNSAID for patients with hypertension, monitor blood pressure (BP) closely, especially during the initiation of NSAID treatment as well as throughout the course of therapy.



 Patients taking ACE-inhibitors, thiazides or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs.



    5.5 Congestive Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention and edema have been observed in some patients treated with NSAIDs, including PENNSAID. When prescribing PENNSAID for patients with fluid retention or heart failure, monitor their fluid status and cardiac function closely.



    5.6 Renal Effects



  Patients with considerable dehydration are at greater risk for renal injury when exposed to NSAIDs. Monitor renal function closely and consider correcting fluid status prior to initiating treatment with PENNSAID.



 Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of an NSAID may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics and ACE-inhibitors, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



 No information is available from controlled clinical studies regarding the use of PENNSAID in patients with advanced renal disease. Therefore, treatment with PENNSAID is not recommended in patients with advanced renal disease. If PENNSAID therapy is initiated, closely monitor the patient's renal function.



    5.7 Anaphylactoid Reactions



  As with other NSAIDs, anaphylactoid reactions may occur in patients without prior exposure to PENNSAID. Do not prescribe PENNSAID to patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  . Seek emergency help in cases where an anaphylactoid reaction occurs.



    5.8 Skin Reactions



  Do not apply PENNSAID to open skin wounds, infections, inflammations, or exfoliative dermatitis, as it may affect absorption and tolerability of the drug.



 NSAIDs, including PENNSAID, can cause serious skin adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations, and discontinue use of the drug at the first appearance of skin rash or any other signs of hypersensitivity.



    5.9 Pregnancy



  PENNSAID should not be used by pregnant or nursing women or those intending to become pregnant.



    5.10 Preexisting Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin- sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm, which can be fatal. Since cross- reactivity, including bronchospasm, between aspirin and other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, do not administer PENNSAID to patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and with use in patients with preexisting asthma, monitor closely for signs of worsening symptoms.



    5.11 Sun Exposure



  Instruct patients to avoid exposure to natural or artificial sunlight on treated knee(s) because studies in animals indicated topical diclofenac treatment resulted in an earlier onset of ultraviolet light-induced skin tumors. The potential effects of PENNSAID on skin response to ultraviolet damage in humans are not known.



    5.12 Eye Exposure



  Avoid contact of PENNSAID with eyes and mucosa. Advise patients that if eye contact occurs, immediately wash out the eye with water or saline and consult a physician if irritation persists for more than an hour.



    5.13 Oral Nonsteroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs



  Concomitant use of oral NSAIDs with PENNSAID 1.5% resulted in a higher rate of rectal hemorrhage, more frequent abnormal creatinine, urea and hemoglobin. Therefore, do not use combination therapy with PENNSAID and an oral NSAID unless the benefit outweighs the risk and conduct periodic laboratory evaluations.



    5.14 Corticosteroid Treatment



  PENNSAID cannot be expected to substitute for corticosteroids or to treat corticosteroid insufficiency. Abrupt discontinuation of corticosteroids may lead to exacerbation of corticosteroid-response illness. For patients on prolonged corticosteroid therapy, taper slowly if a decision is made to discontinue corticosteroids.



    5.15 Inflammation



  The pharmacological activity of PENNSAID in reducing inflammation, and possibly fever, may diminish the utility of these diagnostic signs in detecting complications of presumed noninfectious, painful conditions.



    5.16 Hematological Effects



  Anemia is sometimes seen in patients receiving NSAIDs. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. Check hemoglobin or hematocrit of patients on PENNSAID if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia or blood loss.



 NSAIDs inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effect on platelet function is quantitatively less, of shorter duration and reversible. Carefully monitor patients receiving PENNSAID who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants.



 The effects of PENNSAID 1.5% on platelet function were studied in 10 healthy subjects administered 80 drops four times a day for 7 days. There was no significant change in platelet aggregation following one week of treatment.



    5.17 Monitoring



  Because serious GI tract ulcerations and bleeding can occur without warning symptoms in patients taking NSAIDs, monitor patients for signs or symptoms of GI bleeding. Check CBC and a chemistry profile periodically in patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs. Discontinue PENNSAID if abnormal liver tests or renal tests persist or worsen.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
