<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pentacel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Rates of adverse reactions varied by dose number. Systemic reactions that occurred in &gt;50% of participants following any dose included fussiness/irritability and inconsolable crying. Fever &gt;=38.0 degrees C occurred in 6-16% of participants, depending on dose number. Injection site reactions that occurred in &gt;30% of participants following any dose included tenderness and increase in arm circumference. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sanofi Pasteur Inc., at 1-800-822-2463 (1-800-VACCINE) or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 and  http://vaers.hhs.gov.
 

 

  6.1 Data from Clinical Studies

  Rates of adverse reactions varied by dose number. The most frequent (&gt;50% of participants) systemic reactions following any dose were fussiness/irritability and inconsolable crying. The most frequent (&gt;30% of participants) injection site reactions following any dose were tenderness and increased circumference of the injected arm.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to vaccine use and for approximating rates of those events.



 The safety of Pentacel vaccine was evaluated in four clinical studies in which a total of 5,980 participants received at least one dose of Pentacel vaccine. In three of the studies, conducted in the US, a total of 4,198 participants were enrolled to receive four consecutive doses of Pentacel vaccine. In the fourth study, conducted in Canada, 1,782 participants previously vaccinated with three doses of Pentacel vaccine received a fourth dose. The vaccination schedules of Pentacel vaccine, Control vaccines, and concomitantly administered vaccines used in these studies are provided in  Table 1  .



 Across the four studies, 50.8% of participants were female. Among participants in the three US studies, 64.5% were Caucasian, 9.2% were Black, 12.9% were Hispanic, 3.9% were Asian, and 9.5% were of other racial/ethnic groups. In the two controlled studies, the racial/ethnic distribution of participants who received Pentacel and Control vaccines was similar. In the Canadian fourth dose study, 86.0% of participants were Caucasian, 1.9% were Black, 0.8% were Hispanic, 4.3% were Asian, 2.0% were East Indian, 0.5% were Native Indian, and 4.5% were of other racial/ethnic groups.



 Table 1: Clinical Safety Studies of Pentacel Vaccine: Vaccination Schedules 
 Study                 Pentacel                   Control Vaccines           Concomitantly Administered Vaccines   
  
 HCPDT: non-US licensed DTaP vaccine that is identical to the DTaP component of Pentacel vaccine.POLIOVAX: US licensed Poliovirus Vaccine Inactivated, Sanofi Pasteur Limited.IPOL: US licensed Poliovirus Vaccine Inactivated, Sanofi Pasteur SA.   
  
   494-01              2, 4, 6 and 15 months      HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB at 2, 4, 6, and 15 months  7-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine(PCV7) at 2, 4, and 6 months in a subset of participants Hepatitis B vaccine at 2 and 6 months   
   P3T06               2, 4, 6, and 15-16 months  DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB at 2, 4, and 6 months; and DAPTACEL + ActHIB at 15-16 months  PCV7at 2, 4, and 6 months Hepatitis B vaccine at 2 and 6 months   
   494-03              2, 4, 6, and 15-16 months  None                       PCV7at 2, 4, and 6 months in all participants; and at 15 months in a random subset of participants Hepatitis B vaccine at 2 and 6 months (if a dose was previously administered)or at 2, 4, and 6 months (if no previous dose) Measles, mumps, rubella vaccine(MMR) and varicellavaccine at 12 or 15 months in random subsets of participants   
   5A9908              15-18 months               None                       None                             
              Solicited Adverse Reactions  
 

 The incidence and severity of selected solicited injection site and systemic adverse reactions that occurred within 3 days following each dose of Pentacel or Control vaccines in Study P3T06 is shown in  Table 2  . Information on these reactions was recorded daily by parents or guardians on diary cards. In  Table 2  , injection site reactions are reported for the Pentacel vaccine and DAPTACEL vaccine injection sites.



 Table 2: Number (Percentage) of Children with Selected Solicited Adverse Reactions by Severity Occurring within 0-3 days of Pentacel Vaccine or Control Vaccines in Study P3T06 
   Injection Site Reactions      Pentacel Vaccine      DAPTACEL Vaccine     
   Dose 1N  = 465-467  %      Dose 2N  = 451  %      Dose 3N  = 438-440  %      Dose 4N  = 387-396  %      Dose 1N  = 1,400-1,404  %      Dose 2N  = 1,358-1,359  %      Dose 3N  = 1,311-1,312  %      Dose 4N  = 376-380  %     
   Redness                                                                                                              
   &gt;5 mm                  7.1         8.4         8.7         17.3        6.2         7.1         9.6         16.4      
   &gt;25 mm                 2.8         1.8         1.8         9.2         1.0         0.6         1.9         7.9       
   &gt;50 mm                 0.6         0.2         0.0         2.3         0.4         0.1         0.0         2.4       
   Swelling                                                                                                             
   &gt;5 mm                  7.5         7.3         5.0         9.7         4.0         4.0         6.5         10.3      
   &gt;25 mm                 3.0         2.0         1.6         3.8         1.6         0.7         1.1         4.0       
   &gt;50 mm                 0.9         0.0         0.0         0.8         0.4         0.1         0.1         1.3       
   Tenderness                                                                                                           
   Any                    47.5        39.2        42.7        56.1        48.8        38.2        40.9        51.1      
   Moderate or Severe     19.6        10.6        11.6        16.7        20.7        12.2        12.3        15.8      
   Severe                 5.4         1.6         1.4         3.3         4.1         2.3         1.7         2.4       
   Increase in Arm Circumference                                                                                                     
   &gt;5 mm                                                      33.6                                            30.6      
   &gt;20 mm                  -           -           -          4.7          -           -           -          6.9       
   &gt;40 mm                                                     0.5                                             0.8       
   Systemic Reactions      Pentacel Vaccine      DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB Vaccines      DAPTACEL + ActHIB Vaccines     
   Dose 1N  = 466-467  %      Dose 2N  = 451-452  %      Dose 3N  = 435-440  %      Dose 4N  = 389-398  %      Dose 1N  = 1,390-1,406  %      Dose 2N  = 1,346-1,360  %      Dose 3N  = 1,301-1,312  %      Dose 4N  = 379-381  %     
   Fever                                                                                                                
   &gt;=38.0 degrees C       5.8         10.9        16.3        13.4        9.3         16.1        15.8        8.7       
   &gt;38.5 degrees C        1.3         2.4         4.4         5.1         1.6         4.3         5.1         3.2       
   &gt;39.5 degrees C        0.4         0.0         0.7         0.3         0.1         0.4         0.3         0.8       
   Decreased Activity/Lethargy                                                                                                     
   Any                    45.8        32.7        32.5        24.1        51.1        37.4        33.2        24.1      
   Moderate or Severe     22.9        12.4        12.7        9.8         24.3        15.8        12.7        9.2       
   Severe                 2.1         0.7         0.2         2.5         1.2         1.4         0.6         0.3       
   Inconsolable Crying                                                                                                     
   Any                    59.3        49.8        47.3        35.9        58.5        51.4        47.9        36.2      
   &gt;=1 hour               19.7        10.6        13.6        11.8        16.4        16.0        12.2        10.5      
   &gt;3 hours               1.9         0.9         1.1         2.3         2.2         3.4         1.4         1.8       
   Fussiness/Irritability                                                                                                     
   Any                    76.9        71.2        68.0        53.5        75.8        70.7        67.1        53.8      
   &gt;=1 hour               34.5        27.0        26.4        23.6        33.3        30.5        26.2        19.4      
   &gt;3 hours               4.3         4.0         5.0         5.3         5.6         5.5         4.3         4.5       
                   Hypotonic Hyporesponsive Episodes  
 

 In Study P3T06, the diary cards included questions pertaining to HHEs. In Studies 494-01, 494-03, and 5A9908, a question about the occurrence of fainting or change in mental status was asked during post-vaccination phone calls. Across these 4 studies, no HHEs, as defined in a report of a US Public Health Service workshop (  4  ) were reported among participants who received Pentacel vaccine (N = 5,979), separately administered HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB vaccines (N = 1,032) or separately administered DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB vaccines (N = 1,455). Hypotonia not fulfilling HHE criteria within 7 days following vaccination was reported in 4 participants after the administration of Pentacel vaccine (1 on the same day as the 1  st  dose; 3 on the same day as the 3  rd  dose) and in 1 participant after the administration of DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB vaccines (4 days following the 1  st  dose).



     Seizures  



 Across Studies 494-01, 494-03, 5A9908 and P3T06, a total of 8 participants experienced a seizure within 7 days following either Pentacel vaccine (4 participants; N = 4,197 for at least one of Doses 1-3; N = 5,033 for Dose 4), separately administered HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB vaccines (3 participants; N = 1,032 for at least one of Doses 1-3, N = 739 for Dose 4), separately administered DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB vaccines (1 participant; N = 1,455 for at least one of Doses 1-3), or separately administered DAPTACEL + ActHIB vaccines (0 participants; N = 418 for Dose 4). Among the four participants who experienced a seizure within 7 days following Pentacel vaccine, one participant in Study 494-01 had an afebrile seizure 6 days after the first dose, one participant in Study 494-01 had a possible seizure the same day as the third dose, and two participants in Study 5A9908 had a febrile seizure 2 and 4 days, respectively, after the fourth dose. Among the four participants who experienced a seizure within 7 days following Control vaccines, one participant had an afebrile seizure the same day as the first dose of DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB vaccines, one participant had an afebrile seizure the same day as the second dose of HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB vaccines, and two participants had a febrile seizure 6 and 7 days, respectively, after the fourth dose of HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB vaccines.



     Serious Adverse Events  



 In Study P3T06, within 30 days following any of Doses 1-3 of Pentacel or Control vaccines, 19 of 484 (3.9%) participants who received Pentacel vaccine and 50 of 1,455 (3.4%) participants who received DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB vaccines experienced a serious adverse event. Within 30 days following Dose 4 of Pentacel or Control vaccines, 5 of 431 (1.2%) participants who received Pentacel vaccine and 4 of 418 (1.0%) participants who received DAPTACEL + ActHIB vaccines experienced a serious adverse event. In Study 494-01, within 30 days following any of Doses 1-3 of Pentacel or Control vaccines, 23 of 2,506 (0.9%) participants who received Pentacel vaccine and 11 of 1,032 (1.1%) participants who received HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB vaccines experienced a serious adverse event. Within 30 days following Dose 4 of Pentacel or Control vaccines, 6 of 1,862 (0.3%) participants who received Pentacel vaccine and 2 of 739 (0.3%) participants who received HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB vaccines experienced a serious adverse event.



 Across Studies 494-01, 494-03 and P3T06, within 30 days following any of Doses 1-3 of Pentacel or Control vaccines, overall, the most frequently reported serious adverse events were bronchiolitis, dehydration, pneumonia and gastroenteritis. Across Studies 494-01, 494-03, 5A9908 and P3T06, within 30 days following Dose 4 of Pentacel or Control vaccines, overall, the most frequently reported serious adverse events were dehydration, gastroenteritis, asthma, and pneumonia.



 Across Studies 494-01, 494-03, 5A9908 and P3T06, two cases of encephalopathy were reported, both in participants who had received Pentacel vaccine (N = 5,979). One case occurred 30 days post-vaccination and was secondary to cardiac arrest following cardiac surgery. One infant who had onset of neurologic symptoms 8 days post-vaccination was subsequently found to have structural cerebral abnormalities and was diagnosed with congenital encephalopathy.



 A total of 5 deaths occurred during Studies 494-01, 494-03, 5A9908 and P3T06: 4 in children who had received Pentacel vaccine (N = 5,979) and one in a participant who had received DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB vaccines (N = 1,455). There were no deaths reported in children who received HCPDT + POLIOVAX + ActHIB vaccines (N = 1,032). Causes of death among children who received Pentacel vaccine were asphyxia due to suffocation, head trauma, Sudden Infant Death syndrome, and neuroblastoma (8, 23, 52 and 256 days post-vaccination, respectively). One participant with ependymoma died secondary to aspiration 222 days following DAPTACEL + IPOL + ActHIB vaccines.



   6.2 Data from Post-Marketing Experience

  The following additional adverse events have been spontaneously reported during the post-marketing use of Pentacel vaccine worldwide, since 1997. Between 1997 and 2007, Pentacel vaccine was primarily used in Canada. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it may not be possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure.



 The following adverse events were included based on one or more of the following factors: severity, frequency of reporting, or strength of evidence for a causal relationship to Pentacel vaccine.



 *    Cardiac disorders  Cyanosis 
 *    Gastrointestinal disorders  Vomiting, diarrhea 
 *    General disorders and administration site conditions  Injection site reactions (including inflammation, mass, abscess and sterile abscess), extensive swelling of the injected limb (including swelling that involved adjacent joints), vaccination failure/therapeutic response decreased (invasive H influenzae type b disease) 
 *    Immune system disorders  Anaphylaxis/anaphylactic reaction, hypersensitivity (such as rash and urticaria) 
 *    Infections and infestations  Meningitis, rhinitis, viral infection 
 *    Metabolism and nutrition disorders  Decreased appetite 
 *    Nervous system disorders  Somnolence, HHE, depressed level of consciousness 
 *    Psychiatric disorders  Screaming 
 *    Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  Apnea, cough 
 *    Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  Erythema, skin discoloration 
 *    Vascular disorders  Pallor 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  *  -  fever &gt;=40.5 degrees C (&gt;=105 degrees F), hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode (HHE) or persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours within 48 hours after a previous pertussis-containing vaccine. (  5.2  ) 
 *  -  seizures within 3 days after a previous pertussis-containing vaccine. (  5.2  ) 
 *  -  If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk for Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following Pentacel. (  5.3  ) 
   Carefully consider benefits and risks before administering Pentacel to persons with a history of: 
 *  For infants and children with a history of previous seizures, an antipyretic may be administered (in the dosage recommended in its prescribing information) at the time of vaccination with Pentacel and for the next 24 hours. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including Pentacel, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination.The potential risk of apnea and the need for respiratory monitoring for 48 - 72 hours should be considered when administering the primary immunization series to very premature infants (born &lt;= 28 weeks of gestation) and particularly for those with a previous history of respiratory immaturity. As the benefit of vaccination is high in this group of infants, vaccination should not be withheld or delayed. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Acute Allergic Reactions



  Epinephrine hydrochloride solution (1:1,000) and other appropriate agents and equipment must be available for immediate use in case an anaphylactic or acute hypersensitivity reaction occurs.



    5.2 Adverse Reactions Following Prior Pertussis Vaccination



  If any of the following events occur within the specified period after administration of a pertussis vaccine, the decision to administer Pentacel vaccine should be based on careful consideration of potential benefits and possible risks.



 *  Temperature of &gt;=40.5 degrees C (&gt;=105 degrees F) within 48 hours, not attributable to another identifiable cause. 
 *  Collapse or shock-like state (hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode (HHE)) within 48 hours. 
 *  Persistent, inconsolable crying lasting &gt;=3 hours within 48 hours. 
 *  Seizures with or without fever within 3 days. 
       5.3 Guillain-Barre Syndrome and Brachial Neuritis
 

  A review by the Institute of Medicine (IOM) found evidence for a causal relation between tetanus toxoid and both brachial neuritis and Guillain-Barre syndrome. (  3  ) If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of a prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the risk for Guillain-Barre syndrome may be increased following Pentacel vaccine.



    5.4 Infants and Children with a History of Previous Seizures



  For infants or children with a history of previous seizures, an appropriate antipyretic may be administered (in the dosage recommended in its prescribing information) at the time of vaccination with a vaccine containing acellular pertussis antigens (including Pentacel vaccine) and for the following 24 hours, to reduce the possibility of post-vaccination fever.



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with Pentacel vaccine may not protect all individuals.



    5.6 Altered Immunocompetence



  If Pentacel vaccine is administered to immunocompromised persons, including persons receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained. [See   Drug Interactions (7.2)  .  ]



    5.7 Apnea in Premature Infants



  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. The decision about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including Pentacel, to an infant born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
