<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pepcid0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The adverse reactions listed below have been reported during domestic and international clinical trials in approximately 2500 patients. In those controlled clinical trials in which PEPCID Tablets were compared to placebo, the incidence of adverse experiences in the group which received PEPCID Tablets, 40 mg at bedtime, was similar to that in the placebo group.



 The following adverse reactions have been reported to occur in more than 1% of patients on therapy with PEPCID in controlled clinical trials, and may be causally related to the drug: headache (4.7%), dizziness (1.3%), constipation (1.2%) and diarrhea (1.7%).



 The following other adverse reactions have been reported infrequently in clinical trials or since the drug was marketed. The relationship to therapy with PEPCID has been unclear in many cases. Within each category the adverse reactions are listed in order of decreasing severity:



   Body as a Whole:  fever, asthenia, fatigue



   Cardiovascular:  arrhythmia, AV block, palpitation



   Gastrointestinal:  cholestatic jaundice, liver enzyme abnormalities, vomiting, nausea, abdominal discomfort, anorexia, dry mouth



   Hematologic:  rare cases of agranulocytosis, pancytopenia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia



   Hypersensitivity:  anaphylaxis, angioedema, orbital or facial edema, urticaria, rash, conjunctival injection



   Musculoskeletal:  musculoskeletal pain including muscle cramps, arthralgia



   Nervous System/Psychiatric:  grand mal seizure; psychic disturbances, which were reversible in cases for which follow-up was obtained, including hallucinations, confusion, agitation, depression, anxiety, decreased libido; paresthesia; insomnia; somnolence. Convulsions, in patients with impaired renal function, have been reported very rarely.



   Respiratory:  bronchospasm, interstitial pneumonia



   Skin:  toxic epidermal necrolysis/Stevens Johnson syndrome (very rare), alopecia, acne, pruritus, dry skin, flushing



   Special Senses:  tinnitus, taste disorder



   Other:  rare cases of impotence and rare cases of gynecomastia have been reported; however, in controlled clinical trials, the incidences were not greater than those seen with placebo.



 The adverse reactions reported for PEPCID Tablets may also occur with PEPCID for Oral Suspension.



   Pediatric Patients  



 In a clinical study in 35 pediatric patients &lt;1 year of age with GERD symptoms [e.g., vomiting (spitting up), irritability (fussing)], agitation was observed in 5 patients on famotidine that resolved when the medication was discontinued.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
