<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="plan0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 10%) in the clinical trial included menstrual changes (26%), nausea (23%), abdominal pain (18%), fatigue (17%), headache (17%), dizziness (11%) and breast tenderness (11%). (  6.1  )



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact  Barr Laboratories at 1-800-330-1271  or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 A double-blind, controlled clinical trial in 1,955 evaluable women compared the efficacy and safety of Plan B (one 0.75 mg tablet of levonorgestrel taken within 72 hours of unprotected intercourse, and one tablet taken 12 hours later) to the Yuzpe regimen (two tablets each containing 0.25 mg levonorgestrel and 0.05 mg ethinyl estradiol, taken within 72 hours of intercourse, and two tablets taken 12 hours later).



 The most common adverse events (&gt;10%) in the clinical trial for women receiving Plan B included menstrual changes (26%), nausea (23%), abdominal pain (18%), fatigue (17%), headache (17%), dizziness (11%), and breast tenderness (11%). Table 1 lists those adverse events that were reported in &gt;= 5% of Plan B users.



 Table 1: Adverse Events in &gt;= 5%of Women, by % Frequency 
                                                          Plan B  Levonorgestrel   N=977 (%)             
 Nausea                                                  23.1                                            
 Abdominal Pain                                          17.6                                            
 Fatigue                                                 16.9                                            
 Headache                                                16.8                                            
 Heavier Menstrual Bleeding                              13.8                                            
 Lighter Menstrual Bleeding                              12.5                                            
 Dizziness                                               11.2                                            
 Breast Tenderness                                       10.7                                            
 Vomiting                                                5.6                                             
 Diarrhea                                                5.0                                             
          6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Plan B. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  Abdominal Pain, Nausea, Vomiting



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  Fatigue



   Nervous System Disorders  Dizziness, Headache



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders  Dysmenorrhea, Irregular Menstruation, Oligomenorrhea, Pelvic Pain
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Ectopic Pregnancy: Women who become pregnant or complain of lower abdominal pain after taking Plan B  should be evaluated for ectopic pregnancy. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Plan B is not effective in terminating an existing pregnancy. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Effect on menses: Plan B may alter the next expected menses. If menses is delayed beyond 1 week, pregnancy should be considered. (  5.3  ) 
 *  STI/HIV: Plan B does not protect against STI/HIV. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Ectopic Pregnancy



  Ectopic pregnancies account for approximately 2% of all reported pregnancies. Up to 10% of pregnancies reported in clinical studies of routine use of progestin-only contraceptives are ectopic.



 A history of ectopic pregnancy is not a contraindication to use of this emergency contraceptive method. Healthcare providers, however, should consider the possibility of an ectopic pregnancy in women who become pregnant or complain of lower abdominal pain after taking Plan B. A follow-up physical or pelvic examination is recommended if there is any doubt concerning the general health or pregnancy status of any woman after taking Plan B.



    5.2 Existing Pregnancy



  Plan B is not effective in terminating an existing pregnancy.



    5.3 Effects on Menses



  Some women may experience spotting a few days after taking Plan B. Menstrual bleeding patterns are often irregular among women using progestin-only oral contraceptives and women using levonorgestrel for postcoital and emergency contraception.



 If there is a delay in the onset of expected menses beyond 1 week, consider the possibility of pregnancy.



    5.4 STI/HIV



  Plan B does not protect against HIV infection (AIDS) or other sexually transmitted infections (STIs).



    5.5 Physical Examination and Follow-up



  A physical examination is not required prior to prescribing Plan B. A follow-up physical or pelvic examination is recommended if there is any doubt concerning the general health or pregnancy status of any woman after taking Plan B.



    5.6 Fertility Following Discontinuation



  A rapid return of fertility is likely following treatment with Plan B for emergency contraception; therefore, routine contraception should be continued or initiated as soon as possible following use of Plan B to ensure ongoing prevention of pregnancy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
