<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pletal" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in    other sections of the labeling:



 *  o  Patients with Heart Failure [see Boxed Warning ] 
 *  o  Tachycardia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  o  Hematologic Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  o  Hemostatic Disorders or Active Pathologic Bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions greater than or equal to 2% and at least twice that for placebo in patients on 100 mg twice daily are headache, diarrhea, abnormal stools, and palpitation (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact    Otsuka America Pharmaceutical, Inc. at 1-877-438-9927    or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reactions were assessed in eight placebo-controlled clinical trials involving patients exposed to either 50 or 100 mg twice daily PLETAL (n=1301) or placebo (n=973), with a median treatment duration of 127 days for patients on PLETAL and 134 days for patients on placebo.



 The most frequent adverse reaction resulting in discontinuation of therapy in more than 3% of patients treated with PLETAL was headache [50 mg twice daily (1.3%), 100 mg twice daily (3.5%) and placebo (0.3%)]. Other frequent causes of discontinuation included palpitation and diarrhea, both 1.1% for PLETAL (all doses) versus 0.1% for placebo.



 The most common adverse reactions, occurring in at least 2% of patients treated with PLETAL 50 or 100 mg twice daily, are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Most Common Adverse Reactions in Patients on PLETAL (PLT) 50 or 100 mg Twice Daily (Incidence at least 2% and Occurring More Frequently (&gt;= 2%) in the 100 mg Twice Daily Group than on Placebo) 
  Adverse Reactions            Placebo (N=973)            PLT 50 mg twice daily (N=303)    PLT 100 mg twice daily (N=998)    
  Headache                     14%                        27%                       34%                        
  Diarrhea                     7%                         12%                       19%                        
  Abnormal stools              4%                         12%                       15%                        
  Palpitation                  1%                         5%                        10%                        
  Dizziness                    6%                         9%                        10%                        
  Pharyngitis                  7%                         7%                        10%                        
  Infection                    8%                         14%                       10%                        
  Peripheral edema             4%                         9%                        7%                         
  Rhinitis                     5%                         12%                       7%                         
  Dyspepsia                    4%                         6%                        6%                         
  Abdominal pain               3%                         4%                        5%                         
  Tachycardia                  1%                         4%                        4%                         
          Less frequent clinical significant adverse reactions (less than 2%) that were experienced by patients treated with PLETAL 50 mg twice daily or 100 mg twice daily in the eight controlled clinical trials and that occurred at a frequency in the 100 mg twice daily group greater than in the placebo group are listed below.
 

   Body as a whole:  fever, generalized edema, malaise



   Cardiovascular:  atrial fibrillation, heart failure, myocardial infarction, nodal arrhythmia, supraventricular tachycardia, ventricular extrasystoles, ventricular tachycardia



   Digestive:  anorexia, melena



   Hematologic and Lymphatic  : anemia



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  increased creatinine, hyperuricemia



   Nervous:  insomnia



   Respiratory:  epistaxis



   Skin and Appendages:  urticaria



   Special Senses:  conjunctivitis, retinal hemorrhage, tinnitus



   Urogenital:  urinary frequency



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of PLETAL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of an unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  



 Aplastic anemia, granulocytopenia, pancytopenia, bleeding tendency



   Cardiac disorders:  



 Torsade de pointes and QTc prolongation in patients with cardiac disorders (e.g. complete atrioventricular block, heart failure; and bradyarrythmia), angina pectoris.



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  



 Gastrointestinal hemorrhage, vomiting, flatulence, nausea



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  



 Pain, chest pain, hot flushes



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  



 Hepatic dysfunction/abnormal liver function tests, jaundice



   Immune system disorders:  



 Anaphylaxis, angioedema, and hypersensitivity



   Investigations:  



 Blood glucose increased, blood uric acid increased, increase in BUN (blood urea increased), blood pressure increase



   Nervous system disorders:  



 Intracranial hemorrhage, cerebral hemorrhage, cerebrovascular accident, extradural hematoma and subdural hematoma



   Renal and urinary disorders:  



 Hematuria



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  



 Pulmonary hemorrhage, interstitial pneumonia



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  



 Hemorrhage subcutaneous, pruritus, skin eruptions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, skin drug eruption (dermatitis medicamentosa), rash



   Vascular disorders:  



 Subacute stent thrombosis, hypertension.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CONTRAINDICATED IN HEART FAILURE PATIENTS 

  WARNING: CONTRAINDICATED IN HEART FAILURE PATIENTS 

    PLETAL is contraindicated in patients with heart failure of any severity. Cilostazol and several of its metabolites are inhibitors of phosphodiesterase III. Several drugs with this pharmacologic effect have caused decreased survival compared to placebo in patients with class III-IV heart failure. (  4  )  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: CONTRAINDICATED IN HEART FAILURE PATIENTS 



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  PLETAL is contraindicated in patients with heart failure of any severity. Cilostazol and several of its metabolites are inhibitors of phosphodiesterase III. Several drugs with the pharmacologic effect have caused decreased survival compared to placebo patients with class III-IV heart failure. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Risks of tachycardia, palpitation, tachyarrhythmia or hypotension. Risks of exacerbations of angina pectoris or myocardial infarction in patients with a history of ischemic heart disease (  5.1  ) 
 *    Risks of thrombocytopenia or leukopenia progressing to agranulocytosis-monitor platelets and white blood cell counts (  5.2  ) 
 *    Avoid use in patients with hemostatic disorders or active pathologic bleeding (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Tachycardia



  Cilostazol may induce tachycardia, palpitation, tachyarrhythmia or hypotension. The increase in heart rate associated with cilostazol is approximately 5 to 7 bpm. Patients with a history of ischemic heart disease may be at risk for exacerbations of angina pectoris or myocardial infarction.



    5.2 Hematologic Adverse Reactions



  Cases of thrombocytopenia or leukopenia progressing to agranulocytosis when PLETAL was not immediately discontinued have been reported. Agranulocytosis is reversible on discontinuation of PLETAL. Monitor platelets and white blood cell counts periodically.



    5.3 Hemostatic Disorders or Active Pathologic Bleeding  



  PLETAL inhibits platelet aggregation in a reversible manner. PLETAL has not been studied in patients with hemostatic disorders or active pathologic bleeding. Avoid use of PLETAL in these patients.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
