<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pneumovax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions, reported in &gt;10% of subjects vaccinated with PNEUMOVAX 23 in clinical trials were: injection-site pain/soreness/tenderness (60.0%), injection-site swelling/induration (20.3%), headache (17.6%), injection-site erythema (16.4%), asthenia/fatigue (13.2%), and myalgia (11.9%).  [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  .]  



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions, reported in &gt;10% of subjects vaccinated with PNEUMOVAX 23 in clinical trials, were: injection-site pain/soreness/tenderness (60.0%), injection-site swelling/induration (20.3%), headache (17.6%), injection-site erythema (16.4%), asthenia and fatigue (13.2%), and myalgia (11.9%). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover clinical trial, subjects were enrolled in four different cohorts defined by age (50-64 years of age and &gt;=65 years of age) and vaccination status (no pneumococcal vaccination or receipt of a pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine 3-5 years prior to the study). Subjects in each cohort were randomized to receive intramuscular injections of PNEUMOVAX 23 followed by placebo (saline containing 0.25% phenol), or placebo followed by PNEUMOVAX 23, at 30-day (+/-7 days) intervals. The safety of an initial vaccination (first dose) was compared to revaccination (second dose) with PNEUMOVAX 23 for 14 days following each vaccination.



 All 1008 subjects (average age, 67 years; 49% male and 51% female; 91% Caucasian, 4.7% African-American, 3.5% Hispanic, and 0.8% Other) received placebo injections.



 Initial vaccination was evaluated in a total of 444 subjects (average age 65 years; 32% male and 68% female; 93% Caucasian, 3.2% African-American, 3.4% Hispanic, and 1.1% Other).



 Revaccination was evaluated in 564 subjects (average age 69 years; 53% male and 47% female; 90% Caucasian, 3.5% Hispanic, 6.0% African-American, and 0.5% Other).



   

    Serious Adverse Experiences  



 In this study, 10 subjects had serious adverse experiences within 14 days of vaccination: 6 who received PNEUMOVAX 23 and 4 who received placebo. Serious adverse experiences within 14 days after PNEUMOVAX 23 included angina pectoris, heart failure, chest pain, ulcerative colitis, depression, and headache/tremor/stiffness/sweating. Serious adverse experiences within 14 days after placebo included myocardial infarction complicated with heart failure, alcohol intoxication, angina pectoris, and edema/urinary retention/heart failure/diabetes.



 Five subjects reported serious adverse experiences that occurred outside the 14-day follow-up window: 3 who received PNEUMOVAX 23 and 2 who received placebo. Serious adverse experiences after PNEUMOVAX 23 included cerebrovascular accident, lumbar radiculopathy, and pancreatitis/myocardial infarction resulting in death. Serious adverse experiences after placebo included heart failure and motor vehicle accident resulting in death.



   

    Solicited and Unsolicited Reactions  



   Table 1  presents the adverse event rates for all solicited and unsolicited reactions reported in &gt;=1% in any group in this study, without regard to causality.



 The most common local adverse reactions reported at the injection site after initial vaccination with PNEUMOVAX 23 were pain/tenderness/soreness (60.0%), swelling/induration (20.3%), and erythema (16.4%). The most common systemic adverse experiences were headache (17.6%), asthenia/fatigue (13.2%), and myalgia (11.9%).



 The most common local adverse reactions reported at the injection site after revaccination with PNEUMOVAX 23 were pain/soreness/tenderness (77.2%), swelling (39.8%), and erythema (34.5%). The most common systemic adverse reactions with revaccination were headache (18.1%), asthenia/fatigue (17.9%), and myalgia (17.3%). All of these adverse reactions were reported at a rate lower than 10% after receiving a placebo injection.



 Table 1: Incidence of Injection-Site and Systemic Complaints in Adults &gt;=50 Years of Age Receiving Their First (Initial) or Second (Revaccination) Dose of PNEUMOVAX 23 (Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, 23 Valent) or Placebo Occurring at &gt;=1% in Any Group 
                                 PNEUMOVAX 23Initial Vaccination  PNEUMOVAX 23Revaccination     Placebo Injection      
                                          N=444                     N=564                   N=1008            
  
   Number Followed for Safety              438                       548                      984             
                                         AE Rate                   AE Rate                  AE Rate           
   Injection-Site Complaints                                                                                  
   Solicited Events                                                                                           
   Pain/Soreness/Tenderness               60.0%                     77.2%                    7.7%             
   Swelling/Induration                    20.3%                     39.8%                    2.8%             
   Erythema                               16.4%                     34.5%                    3.3%             
   Unsolicited Events                                                                                         
   Ecchymosis                               0%                      1.1%                     0.3%             
   Pruritus                                0.2%                     1.6%                     0.0%             
   Systemic Complaints                                                                                        
   Solicited Events                                                                                           
   Asthenia/Fatigue                       13.2%                     17.9%                    6.7%             
   Chills                                  2.7%                     7.8%                     1.8%             
   Myalgia                                11.9%                     17.3%                    3.3%             
   Headache                               17.6%                     18.1%                    8.9%             
   Unsolicited Events                                                                                         
   Fever                                   1.4%                     2.0%                     0.7%             
   Diarrhea                                1.1%                     0.7%                     0.5%             
   Dyspepsia                               1.1%                     1.1%                     0.9%             
   Nausea                                  1.8%                     1.8%                     0.9%             
   Back Pain                               0.9%                     0.9%                     1.0%             
   Neck Pain                               0.7%                     1.5%                     0.2%             
   Upper Respiratory  Infection            1.8%                     2.6%                     1.8%             
   Pharyngitis                             1.1%                     0.4%                     1.3%             
          In this clinical study an increased rate of local reactions was observed with revaccination at 3-5 years following initial vaccination.
 

 For subjects aged 65 years or older, injection-site adverse reaction rate was higher following revaccination (79.3%) than following initial vaccination (52.9%). The proportion of subjects reporting injection site discomfort that interfered with or prevented usual activity or injection site induration &gt;=4 inches was higher following revaccination (30.6%) than following initial vaccination (10.4%). Injection site reactions typically resolved by 5 days following vaccination.



 For subjects aged 50-64 years, the injection-site adverse reaction rate for revaccinees and initial vaccinees was similar (79.6% and 72.8% respectively).



 The rate of systemic adverse reactions was similar among both initial vaccinees and revaccinees within each age group. The rate of vaccine-related systemic adverse reactions was higher following revaccination (33.1%) than following initial vaccination (21.7%) in subjects 65 years of age or older, and was similar following revaccination (37.5%) and initial vaccination (35.5%) in subjects 50-64 years of age. The most common systemic adverse reactions reported after PNEUMOVAX 23 were as follows: asthenia/fatigue, myalgia and headache.



 Regardless of age, the observed increase in post vaccination use of analgesics (&lt;=13% in the revaccinees and &lt;=4% in the initial vaccinees) returned to baseline by day 5.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following list of adverse reactions includes those identified during post approval use of PNEUMOVAX 23. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or their causal relationship to product exposure.



   General disorders and administration site conditions    Cellulitis  Malaise  Fever (&gt;102 degrees F)  Warmth at the injection site  Decreased limb mobility  Peripheral edema in the injected extremity



   Digestive System    Nausea  Vomiting



   Hematologic/Lymphatic    Lymphadenitis  Lymphadenopathy  Thrombocytopenia in patients with stabilized idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura{3}  Hemolytic anemia in patients who have had other hematologic disorders  Leukocytosis



   Hypersensitivity reactions including    Anaphylactoid reactions  Serum Sickness  Angioneurotic edema



   Musculoskeletal System    Arthralgia  Arthritis



   Nervous System    Paresthesia  Radiculoneuropathy  Guillain-Barre syndrome  Febrile convulsion



   Skin    Rash  Urticaria  Cellulitis-like reactions  Erythema multiforme



   Investigations    Increased serum C-reactive protein
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Use caution and appropriate care for individuals with severely compromised cardiovascular and/or pulmonary function in whom a systemic reaction would pose a significant risk. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Persons with Moderate or Severe Acute Illness



  Defer vaccination with PNEUMOVAX 23 in persons with moderate or severe acute illness.



    5.2 Persons with Severely Compromised Cardiovascular or Pulmonary Function



  Caution and appropriate care should be exercised in administering PNEUMOVAX 23 to individuals with severely compromised cardiovascular and/or pulmonary function in whom a systemic reaction would pose a significant risk.



    5.3 Use of Antibiotic Prophylaxis



  This vaccine does not replace the need for penicillin (or other antibiotic) prophylaxis against pneumococcal infection. In patients who require penicillin (or other antibiotic) prophylaxis against pneumococcal infection, such prophylaxis should not be discontinued after vaccination with PNEUMOVAX 23.



    5.4 Persons with Altered Immunocompetence



  Persons who are immunocompromised, including persons receiving immunosuppressive therapy, may have a diminished immune response to PNEUMOVAX 23. [See  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  .]  



    5.5 Persons with Chronic Cerebrospinal Fluid Leakage



  PNEUMOVAX 23 may not be effective in preventing pneumococcal meningitis in patients who have chronic cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) leakage resulting from congenital lesions, skull fractures, or neurosurgical procedures.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
