<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pollens" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

 Physicians administering allergenic extract testing or treatment materials should be experienced in the treatment of severe systemic reactions. See  WARNINGS  box at the beginning of this package insert.  1. Local Reactions  Some erythema, swelling, or pruritus at the site of injection are common, the extent varying with the patient. Such reactions should not be considered significant unless they persist for at least 24 hours.Local reactions (erythema or swelling) which exceed 4-5 cm in diameter are not only uncomfortable, but also indicate the possibility of a systemic reaction if dosage is increased. In such cases the dosage should be reduced to the last level not causing the reaction and maintained at this level for two or three treatments before cautiously increasing again.Large, persistent local reactions may be treated by local cold, wet dressings and/or the use of oral antihistamines. They should be considered a warning of possible severe systemic reactions and the need for temporarily reduced dosages.A mild burning immediately after the injection is to be expected; this usually subsides in 10 to 20 seconds.  2. Systemic Reactions  With careful attention to dosage and administration, systemic reactions occur infrequently, but it cannot be overemphasized that in sensitive individuals any injection could result in anaphylactic shock. Therefore, it is imperative that physicians administering allergenic extracts understand and be prepared for the treatment of severe reactions.Most severe systemic reactions will begin within a 30 minute time period, but systemic reactions may occur at any time after skin tests or immunotherapy. Symptoms may range from mild to life-threatening (due to anaphylaxis) as described below.Other possible systemic reaction symptoms which may occur in varying degrees of severity are laryngeal edema, fainting, pallor, bradycardia, hypotension, angioedema, cough, wheezing, conjunctivitis, rhinitis, and urticaria. Adverse reaction frequency data for allergenic extract administration for testing and treatment show that risk is low.  1, 41    If a systemic or anaphylactic reaction does occur, apply a tourniquet above the site of injection and inject 1:1000 epinephrine-hydrochloride intramuscularly into the opposite arm. Loosen the tourniquet at least every 10 minutes. Do not obstruct arterial blood flow with the tourniquet.    EPINEPHRINE DOSAGE    ADULT:  0.3 to 0.5 mL should be injected. Repeat in 5 to 10 minutes if necessary.  PEDIATRIC  : The usual initial dose is 0.01 mg (mL) per kg body weight or 0.3 mg (mL) per square meter of body surface area. Suggested dosage for infants to 2 years of age is 0.05 mL to 0.1 mL; for children 2 to 6 years, 0.15 mL; and children 6 to 12 years, 0.2 mL. Single pediatric doses should not exceed 0.3 mg (mL). Doses may be repeated as frequently as every 20 minutes, depending on the severity of the condition and the response of the patient.After administration of epinephrine, profound shock or vasomotor collapse should be treated with intravenous fluids, and possibly vasoactive drugs. Airway patiency should be insured. Oxygen should be given by mask. Intravenous antihistamine, inhaled bronchodilators, theophylline, and/or adrenal corticosteroids may be used if necessary after adequate epinephrine and circulatory support have been given.Emergency resuscitation measures and personnel trained in their use must be available immediately in the event of a serious systemic or anaphylactic reaction not responsive to the above measures [  Ref. J. Allergy and Clinical Immunology  77(2): p. 271-273, 1986].Rarely are all of the above measures necessary; the tourniquet and epinephrine usually produce prompt responses. However, the physician should be prepared in advance for all contingencies. Promptness in beginning emergency treatment measures is of utmost importance.Severe systemic reactions mandate a decrease of at least 50% in the next dose, followed by cautious increases. Repeated systemic reactions, even of a mild nature, are sufficient reason for the cessation of further attempts to increase the reaction-causing dose.  3. Adverse Event Reporting  Report all adverse events to Jubilant HollisterStier LLC, Customer Technical Services Department at 1(800) 992-1120. A voluntary adverse event reporting system for health professionals is available through the FDA MEDWATCH program. Preprinted forms (FDA Form 3500) are available from the FDA by calling 1(800) FDA-1088. Completed forms should be mailed to MEDWATCH, 5600 Fisher Lane, Rockville, MD 20852-9787 or Fax to: 1(800) FDA-0178. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNINGS

  WARNINGS

  This product is intended for use only by licensed medical personnel experienced in administering allergenic extracts and trained to provide immediate emergency treatment in the event of a life-threatening reaction.



 Allergenic extracts may potentially elicit a severe life-threatening systemic reaction, rarely resulting in death.  1    Therefore, emergency measures and personnel trained in their use must be available immediately in the event of such a reaction.  Patients should be instructed to recognize adverse reaction symptoms, be observed in the office for at least 30 minutes after skin testing or treatment, and be cautioned to contact the physician's office if symptoms occur. See   ADVERSE REACTION   section of this package insert regarding adverse event reporting.  This product should never be injected intravenously.



 Patients with cardiovascular diseases and/or pulmonary diseases such as symptomatic unstable, steroid-dependent asthma, and/or those who are receiving cardiovascular drugs such as beta blockers, may be at higher risk for severe adverse reactions. These patients may also be more refractory to the normal allergy treatment regimen. Patients should be treated only if the benefit of treatment outweighs the risks.  1  



 Patients on beta blockers may be more reactive to allergens given for testing or treatment and may be unresponsive to the actual doses of epinephrine used to treat allergic reactions.   2  



 Refer to the   WARNINGS  ,   PRECAUTIONS  ,   ADVERSE REACTIONS   and   OVERDOSE   Sections for further discussion.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
