<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="positive" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Large doses of histamine may precipitate systemic reactions. These reactions may include flushing, dizziness, headache, bronchial constriction, urticaria, asthma, marked hypotension or hypertension, abdominal cramps, vomiting, metallic taste, local or generalized allergic manifestations.



 An antihistamine preparation may be given orally, I.M. or I.V. to prevent or ameliorate systemic reactions to the drug.



   If a systemic or anaphylactic reaction does occur, apply a tourniquet above the site of injection and inject 1:1000 epinephrine-hydrochloride intramuscularly or subcutaneously into the opposite arm. Loosen the tourniquet at least every 10 minutes. Do not obstruct arterial blood flow with the tourniquet.  



 Epinephrine Dosage:ADULT: 0.3 to 0.5 mL should be injected. Repeat in 5 to 10 minutes if necessary.PEDIATRIC: The usual initial dose is 0.01 mg (mL) per kg body weight or 0.3 mg(mL) per square meter of body surface area. Suggested dosage for infants to 2 years of age is 0.05 mL to 0.1 mL; for children 2 to 6 years, 0.15 mL; and children 6 to 12 years, 0.2 mL. Single pediatric doses should not exceed 0.3 mg (mL). Doses may be repeated as frequently as every 20 minutes, depending on the severity of the condition and the response of the patient.



 After administration of epinephrine, profound shock or vasomotor collapse should be treated with intravenous fluids, and possibly vasoactive drugs. Oxygen should be given by mask. Aminophylline or adrenal corticosteroids may be used if necessary after adequate epinephrine and circulatory support has been given.



 Emergency resuscitation measures and personnel trained in their use should be available immediately in the event of a serious systemic or anaphylactic reaction not responsive to the above measures (Ref. J. ALLERGY AND CLINICAL IMMUNOLOGY 77s (2): p. 271-273, 1986).  16      



 Rarely are all of the above measures necessary, the tourniquet and epinephrine usually producing prompt responses. However, the physician should be prepared in advance for all contingencies. Promptness in beginning emergency treatment measures is of utmost importance.



   Adverse Event Reporting  Report all adverse events to Jubilant HollisterStier LLC Customer Technical Services Department at 1 (800) 992-1120. A voluntary adverse event reporting system for health professionals is available through the FDA MEDWATCH program. Preprinted forms (FDA Form 3500) are available from the FDA by calling 1 (800) FDA-1088. Completed forms should be mailed to MEDWATCH, 5600 Fisher Lane, Rockville, MD 20852-9787 or Fax to: 1 (800) FDA-0178.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: POSITIVE SKIN TEST CONTROL - HISTAMINE

  POSITIVE SKIN TEST CONTROL - HISTAMINE

  For Percutaneous (Scratch, Prick or Puncture) Administration Histamine Base: 6mg/mL(Histamine Dihydrochloride: 10mg/mL)  This product is to be used by a physician or under the supervision of a physician.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
