<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prandimet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Hypoglycemia and headache were the most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) reported among patients treated with repaglinide in combination with metformin HCl, occurring more frequently than among patients treated with repaglinide alone or metformin HCl alone. (  6.2  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal reactions (e.g., diarrhea, nausea and vomiting) are the most common adverse reactions with metformin HCl treatment and are more frequent at higher metformin HCl doses. (  6.1  ,  6.2  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novo Nordisk at 1-800-727-6500 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch. 



 
   Table 1: Repaglinide added to metformin HCl in patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on metformin HCl alone. Adverse reaction reported (regardless of Investigator Assessment of Causality) in &gt;=10% of patients receiving combination therapyIntent to treat population 
                                          Coadministered repaglinide  and metformin HCl    Metformin HCl  monotherapy    Repaglinide  monotherapy    
                                          N (%)                    N (%)                   N (%)              
  No. of Patients Exposed                 27                       27                      28                 
  Gastrointestinal System Disorder        9 (33)                   13 (48)                 10 (36)            
  Diarrhea                                5 (19)                   8 (30)                  2 (7)              
  Nausea                                  4 (15)                   2 (7)                   1 (4)              
  Symptomatic HypoglycemiaThere were no cases of severe hypoglycemia (hypoglycemia requiring the assistance of another person)    9 (33)                   0 (0)                   3 (11)             
  Headache                                6 (22)                   4 (15)                  3 (11)             
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection       3 (11)                   3 (11)                  3 (11)             
          

  6.1 Most Frequently Observed Adverse Reactions

    Repaglinide  



 In clinical trials of repaglinide, hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction (&gt; 5%) leading to withdrawal of patients treated with repaglinide.



   Metformin    HCl  



 Gastrointestinal reactions (e.g., diarrhea, nausea, vomiting) are the most common adverse reactions (&gt; 5%) with metformin HCl treatment and are more frequent at higher metformin HCl doses.



   6.2 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Patients with Inadequate Glycemic Control on Metformin    HCl        Monotherapy  



 Table 1 summarizes the most common adverse reactions occurring in a 6-month randomized study of repaglinide added to metformin HCl in patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on metformin HCl alone.



   Cardiovascular Events in    repaglinide        monotherapy    trials  



 In one-year trials comparing repaglinide to sulfonylurea drugs, the incidence of angina was 1.8% for both treatments, with an incidence of chest pain of 1.8% for repaglinide and 1.0% for sulfonylureas. The incidence of other selected cardiovascular events (hypertension, abnormal electrocardiogram, myocardial infarction, arrhythmias, and palpitations) was &lt;= 1% and not different between repaglinide and the comparator drugs.



 The incidence of total serious cardiovascular adverse events, including ischemia, was higher for repaglinide (51/1228 or 4%) than for sulfonylurea drugs (13/498 or 3%) in controlled clinical trials. In 1-year controlled trials, repaglinide treatment was not associated with excess mortality when compared to the rates observed with other oral hypoglycemic agent therapies such as glyburide and glipizide.



 Seven controlled clinical trials included repaglinide combination therapy with NPH-insulin (n=431), insulin formulations alone (n=388) or other combinations (sulfonylurea plus NPH-insulin or repaglinide plus metformin HCl) (n=120). There were six serious adverse events of myocardial ischemia in patients treated with repaglinide plus NPH-insulin (1.4%) from two studies, and one event in patients using insulin formulations alone from another study (0.3%)  [    see          Warnings and Precautions (5.6)      ].  



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

    Repaglinide  



 The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of repaglinide. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Postmarketing experience with repaglinide includes infrequent reports of the following adverse events; alopecia, hemolytic anemia, pancreatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, and severe hepatic dysfunction including jaundice and hepatitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

  WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    Lactic acidosis is a rare but serious complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure.  



   The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise,     myalgias    , respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress.  



   Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap and elevated blood lactate.  



   If acidosis is suspected,     PrandiMet     should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].   



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap and elevated blood lactate. (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue PrandiMet and hospitalize the patient immediately. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Metformin HCl is contraindicated in renal impairment. Assess renal function before initiating PrandiMet and at least annually thereafter, and verify as normal. (  4  ,  5.2  ) 
 *  Temporarily discontinue PrandiMet in patients receiving iodinated contrast for radiological studies. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hepatic impairment is associated with lactic acidosis. Recommend not using in patients with hepatic impairment. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Alcohol potentiates the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Warn patients against excess alcohol intake. (  5.5  ) 
 *  PrandiMet should not be used in combination with NPH insulin. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Gemfibrozil substantially increases repaglinide exposure. Coadministration of gemfibrozil and PrandiMet is not recommended. (  4  ,  5.7  ,  7.2  ,  12.3  ) 
 *  The repaglinide component can cause hypoglycemia. Initiate PrandiMet at the lowest available dose in patients naive to meglitinide therapy. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Metformin can cause vitamin B12deficiency. Measure hematological parameters annually. (  5.9  ) 
 *  May need to discontinue PrandiMet and temporarily use insulin if glycemic control deteriorates during periods of stress or if there is decreased intake of fluids and food (e.g., infection, surgery). (  5.10  ) 
 *  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with PrandiMet or any other oral anti-diabetic drug. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



   Metformin hydrochloride  



 Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with PrandiMet; when it occurs, it is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate levels (&gt;5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels &gt;5 ug/mL are generally found.



 The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin HCl is very low (approximately 0.03 cases/1,000 patient-years of exposure, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1,000 patient-years of exposure). In more than 20,000 patient-years exposure to metformin HCl in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal impairment, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, in particular those with unstable or acute congestive heart failure who are at risk of hypoperfusion and hypoxemia, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal impairment and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking PrandiMet and by use of the minimum effective dose of PrandiMet. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. Treatment with PrandiMet should not be initiated in patients &gt;=80 years of age unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced, as these patients are more susceptible to developing lactic acidosis. In addition, PrandiMet should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, PrandiMet should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake, either acute or chronic, when taking PrandiMet, since alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin HCl on lactate metabolism. In addition, PrandiMet should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  , (  5.5  ), and (  5.10  )  ].



 The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis. The patient and the patient's physician must be aware of the possible importance of such symptoms and the patient should be instructed to notify the physician immediately if they occur (see also Warnings and Precautions). PrandiMet should be withdrawn until the situation is clarified. Serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose and, if indicated, blood pH, lactate levels, and even blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of PrandiMet, gastrointestinal symptoms, which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to be drug related. Later occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease.



 Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking PrandiMet do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explainable by other mechanisms, such as poorly controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity or technical problems in sample handling [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  , (  5.14  )  ].



 Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia).



 Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking PrandiMet, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin HCl is dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.2 Impaired Renal Function



  Patients with renal impairment should not receive PrandiMet [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ,  Contraindications (4)    ].



 As metformin is substantially excreted by the kidney, before initiation of therapy with PrandiMet and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal impairment is anticipated, renal function should be assessed more frequently and PrandiMet discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present [ see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



    5.3 Radiologic Studies with Intravascular Iodinated Contrast Materials



  Intravascular contrast studies with iodinated materials can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin HCl [ see  Contraindications (4)    ]. Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, PrandiMet should be temporarily discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been re-evaluated and found to be normal.



    5.4 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Hepatic impairment has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis. Therefore, PrandiMet should generally be avoided in patients with hepatic impairment [ see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



    5.5 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol potentiates the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients should be warned against excessive alcohol intake while receiving PrandiMet.



    5.6 Combination with NPH-insulin



   Repaglinide  



 Repaglinide is not indicated for use in combination with NPH-insulin.



 Across seven controlled clinical trials, there were six serious adverse events (1.4%) of myocardial ischemia with repaglinide in combination with NPH-insulin compared to one event (0.3%) in patients using insulin alone [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



    5.7 Drug Interactions



   Repaglinide   is partly metabolized by CYP2C8 and CYP3A4 and appears to be a substrate for active hepatic uptake transporter (organic anion transporting protein OATP1B1). Drugs that inhibit CYP2C8, CYP3A4, or OATP1B1 (e.g., cyclosporine) may increase plasma concentrations of   repaglinide   . Dose reduction of   repaglinide   may be needed [see       Drug Interactions (7.2)   and    Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)   ].    



 Gemfibrozil significantly increased repaglinide exposure. Therefore, patients should not take PrandiMet with gemfibrozil [ see  Contraindications (4)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



    5.8 Hypoglycemia



  Most blood glucose-lowering drugs, including repaglinide, can cause hypoglycemia. Patients who have not previously been treated with a meglitinide should be started on the lowest available repaglinide component of PrandiMet to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia. Elderly, debilitated or malnourished patients and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemia. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.9 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled clinical trials of metformin HCl of 29 weeks' duration, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. This finding, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin HCl or vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on PrandiMet and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed.



 Certain individuals (those with inadequate vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum vitamin B12measurements at 2- to 3-year intervals may be useful.



    5.10 Surgical Procedures



  Use of PrandiMet should be temporarily suspended for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.11 Loss of Control of Blood Glucose



  When a patient stabilized on any diabetic regimen is exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a temporary loss of glycemic control may occur. At such times, it may be necessary to withhold PrandiMet and temporarily administer insulin. PrandiMet may be reinstituted after the acute episode is resolved.



    5.12 Use of Concomitant Medications Affecting Renal Function or Metformin Disposition



  Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or may interfere with the disposition of metformin, such as cationic drugs that are eliminated by renal tubular secretion [ see  Drug Interactions (7.1)    ] should be used with caution.



    5.13 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause, acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction, and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients receiving PrandiMet, the drug should be promptly discontinued.



    5.14 Change in Clinical Status of Patients with Previously Controlled Type 2 Diabetes



  A patient with type 2 diabetes previously well-controlled on PrandiMet who develops laboratory abnormalities or clinical illness (especially vague and poorly defined illness) should be evaluated promptly for evidence of ketoacidosis or lactic acidosis. Evaluation should include serum electrolytes and ketones, blood glucose and, if indicated, blood pH, lactate, pyruvate, and metformin levels. If acidosis of either form occurs, PrandiMet must be stopped immediately and other appropriate corrective measures initiated.



    5.15 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with PrandiMet or any other oral anti-diabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
