<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pravachol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Pravastatin is generally well tolerated; adverse reactions have usually been mild and transient. In 4-month-long placebo-controlled trials, 1.7% of pravastatin-treated patients and 1.2% of placebo-treated patients were discontinued from treatment because of adverse experiences attributed to study drug therapy; this difference was not statistically significant.



   EXCERPT:   In short-term clinical trials, the most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=2% and &gt; placebo) regardless of causality were: musculoskeletal pain, nausea/vomiting, upper respiratory infection, diarrhea, and headache.  (6.1)     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Adverse Clinical Events

  Short-Term Controlled Trials

  In the PRAVACHOL placebo-controlled clinical trials database of 1313 patients (age range 20-76 years, 32.4% women, 93.5% Caucasians, 5% Blacks, 0.9% Hispanics, 0.4% Asians, 0.2% Others) with a median treatment duration of 14 weeks, 3.3% of patients on PRAVACHOL and 1.2% patients on placebo discontinued due to adverse events regardless of causality. The most common adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation and occurred at an incidence greater than placebo were: liver function test increased, nausea, anxiety/depression, and dizziness.



 All adverse clinical events (regardless of causality) reported in &gt;=2% of pravastatin-treated patients in placebo-controlled trials of up to 8 months duration are identified in Table 1:



 Table 1: Adverse Events in &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with Pravastatin 5 to 40 mg and at an Incidence Greater Than Placebo in Short-Term Placebo-Controlled Trials (% of patients) 
   Body System/Event          5 mgN=100      10 mgN=153      20 mgN=478      40 mgN=171      Any DoseN=902      PlaceboN=411     
  
 Cardiovascular    Angina Pectoris  5.0           4.6           4.8           3.5           4.5           3.4            
 Dermatologic    Rash       3.0           2.6           6.7           1.2           4.5           1.4            
 Gastrointestinal    Nausea/Vomiting    Diarrhea    Flatulence    Dyspepsia/Heartburn    Abdominal Distension  4.08.02.00.02.0  5.98.53.33.33.3  10.56.54.63.62.1  2.34.70.00.60.6  7.46.73.22.52.0  7.15.64.42.72.4   
 General    Fatigue    Chest Pain    Influenza  4.04.04.0     1.31.32.6     5.23.31.9     0.01.20.6     3.42.72.0     3.91.90.7      
 Musculoskeletal    Musculoskeletal Pain    Myalgia  13.01.0       3.92.6        13.22.9       5.31.2        10.12.3       10.21.2        
 Nervous System        Headache    Dizziness  5.04.0        6.51.3        7.55.2        3.50.6        6.33.5        4.63.4         
 Respiratory    Pharyngitis    Upper Respiratory Infection    Rhinitis    Cough  2.06.07.04.0  4.69.85.21.3  1.55.23.83.1  1.24.11.21.2  2.05.93.92.5  2.75.84.91.7   
 Investigation    ALT Increased    g-GT Increased    CPK Increased  2.03.05.0     2.02.61.3     4.02.15.2     1.20.62.9     2.92.04.1     1.21.23.6      
      The safety and tolerability of PRAVACHOL at a dose of 80 mg in 2 controlled trials with a mean exposure of 8.6 months was similar to that of PRAVACHOL at lower doses except that 4 out of 464 patients taking 80 mg of pravastatin had a single elevation of CK &gt;10 times ULN compared to 0 out of 115 patients taking 40 mg of pravastatin.
 

   Long-Term Controlled Morbidity and Mortality Trials

  In the PRAVACHOL placebo-controlled clinical trials database of 21,483 patients (age range 24-75 years, 10.3% women, 52.3% Caucasians, 0.8% Blacks, 0.5% Hispanics, 0.1% Asians, 0.1% Others, 46.1% Not Recorded) with a median treatment duration of 261 weeks, 8.1% of patients on PRAVACHOL and 9.3% patients on placebo discontinued due to adverse events regardless of causality.



 Adverse event data were pooled from 7 double-blind, placebo-controlled trials (West of Scotland Coronary Prevention Study [WOS]; Cholesterol and Recurrent Events study [CARE]; Long-term Intervention with Pravastatin in Ischemic Disease study [LIPID]; Pravastatin Limitation of Atherosclerosis in the Coronary Arteries study [PLAC I]; Pravastatin, Lipids and Atherosclerosis in the Carotids study [PLAC II]; Regression Growth Evaluation Statin Study [REGRESS]; and Kuopio Atherosclerosis Prevention Study [KAPS]) involving a total of 10,764 patients treated with pravastatin 40 mg and 10,719 patients treated with placebo. The safety and tolerability profile in the pravastatin group was comparable to that of the placebo group. Patients were exposed to pravastatin for a mean of 4.0 to 5.1 years in WOS, CARE, and LIPID and 1.9 to 2.9 years in PLAC I, PLAC II, KAPS, and REGRESS. In these long-term trials, the most common reasons for discontinuation were mild, non-specific gastrointestinal complaints. Collectively, these 7 trials represent 47,613 patient-years of exposure to pravastatin. All clinical adverse events (regardless of causality) occurring in &gt;=2% of patients treated with pravastatin in these studies are identified in Table 2.



 Table 2: Adverse Events in &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with Pravastatin 40 mg and at an Incidence Greater Than Placebo in Long-Term Placebo-Controlled Trials 
   Body System/Event                                             Pravastatin(N=10,764)% of patients      Placebo(N=10,719)% of patients     
  
 Dermatologic    Rash (including dermatitis)                   7.2                   7.1                    
 General    Edema    Fatigue    Chest Pain    Fever    Weight Gain    Weight Loss  3.08.410.02.13.83.3   2.77.89.81.93.32.8     
 Musculoskeletal    Musculoskeletal Pain    Muscle Cramp    Musculoskeletal Traumatism  24.95.110.2           24.44.69.6             
 Nervous System    Dizziness    Sleep Disturbance    Anxiety/Nervousness    Paresthesia  7.33.04.83.2          6.62.44.73.0           
 Renal/Genitourinary    Urinary Tract Infection                2.7                   2.6                    
 Respiratory    Upper Respiratory Tract Infection    Cough    Influenza    Pulmonary Infection    Sinus Abnormality    Tracheobronchitis  21.28.29.23.87.03.4   20.27.49.03.56.73.1    
 Special Senses    Vision Disturbance (includes blurred vision, diplopia)  3.4                   3.3                    
 Infections    Viral Infection                                 3.2                   2.9                    
      In addition to the events listed above in the long-term trials table, events of probable, possible, or uncertain relationship to study drug that occurred in &lt;2.0% of pravastatin-treated patients in the long-term trials included the following:
 

   Dermatologic:  scalp hair abnormality (including alopecia), urticaria.



   Endocrine/Metabolic:  sexual dysfunction, libido change.



   General:  flushing.



   Immunologic:  allergy, edema head/neck.



   Musculoskeletal:  muscle weakness.



   Nervous System:  vertigo, insomnia, memory impairment, neuropathy (including peripheral neuropathy).



   Special Senses:  taste disturbance.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to the events reported above, as with other drugs in this class, the following events have been reported rarely during postmarketing experience with PRAVACHOL, regardless of causality assessment:



   Musculoskeletal:  myopathy, rhabdomyolysis.



 There have been rare reports of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy associated with statin use [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].



   Nervous System:  dysfunction of certain cranial nerves (including alteration of taste, impairment of extraocular movement, facial paresis), peripheral nerve palsy.



 There have been rare postmarketing reports of cognitive impairment (e.g., memory loss, forgetfulness, amnesia, memory impairment, confusion) associated with statin use. These cognitive issues have been reported for all statins. The reports are generally nonserious, and reversible upon statin discontinuation, with variable times to symptom onset (1 day to years) and symptom resolution (median of 3 weeks).



   Hypersensitivity:  anaphylaxis, angioedema, lupus erythematosus-like syndrome, polymyalgia rheumatica, dermatomyositis, vasculitis, purpura, hemolytic anemia, positive ANA, ESR increase, arthritis, arthralgia, asthenia, photosensitivity, chills, malaise, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme (including Stevens-Johnson syndrome).



   Gastrointestinal:  abdominal pain, constipation, pancreatitis, hepatitis (including chronic active hepatitis), cholestatic jaundice, fatty change in liver, cirrhosis, fulminant hepatic necrosis, hepatoma, fatal and non-fatal hepatic failure.



   Dermatologic:  a variety of skin changes (e.g., nodules, discoloration, dryness of mucous membranes, changes to hair/nails).



   Renal:  urinary abnormality (including dysuria, frequency, nocturia).



   Respiratory:  dyspnea.



   Reproductive:  gynecomastia.



   Laboratory Abnormalities:  liver function test abnormalities, thyroid function abnormalities.



   6.3 Laboratory Test Abnormalities

  Increases in ALT, AST values and CPK have been observed [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1,    5.2)    ].



 Transient, asymptomatic eosinophilia has been reported. Eosinophil counts usually returned to normal despite continued therapy. Anemia, thrombocytopenia, and leukopenia have been reported with statins.



   6.4 Pediatric Patients

  In a 2-year, double-blind, placebo-controlled study involving 100 boys and 114 girls with HeFH (n=214; age range 8-18.5 years, 53% female, 95% Caucasians, &lt;1% Blacks, 3% Asians, 1% Other), the safety and tolerability profile of pravastatin was generally similar to that of placebo. [See    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ,    Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    , and    Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    .]
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  Skeletal muscle effects (e.g., myopathy and rhabdomyolysis): predisposing factors include advanced age (&gt;=65), uncontrolled hypothyroidism, and renal impairment. Patients should be advised to promptly report to their physician any unexplained and/or persistent muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness. Pravastatin therapy should be discontinued if myopathy is diagnosed or suspected.  (5.1  ,  8.5)   
 *  Liver enzyme abnormalities: persistent elevations in hepatic transaminases can occur. Check liver enzyme tests before initiating therapy and as clinically indicated thereafter.  (5.2)   
    
 

   5.1 Skeletal Muscle



   Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis with acute renal failure secondary to myoglobinuria have been reported with pravastatin and other drugs in this class.  A history of renal impairment may be a risk factor for the development of rhabdomyolysis. Such patients merit closer monitoring for skeletal muscle effects.



 Uncomplicated myalgia has also been reported in pravastatin-treated patients [see   Adverse Reactions (6)    ]. Myopathy, defined as muscle aching or muscle weakness in conjunction with increases in creatine phosphokinase (CPK) values to greater than 10 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), was rare (&lt;0.1%) in pravastatin clinical trials. Myopathy should be considered in any patient with diffuse myalgias, muscle tenderness or weakness, and/or marked elevation of CPK. Predisposing factors include advanced age (&gt;=65), uncontrolled hypothyroidism, and renal impairment.



 There have been rare reports of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy (IMNM), an autoimmune myopathy, associated with statin use. IMNM is characterized by: proximal muscle weakness and elevated serum CPK, which persist despite discontinuation of statin treatment; muscle biopsy showing necrotizing myopathy without significant inflammation and improvement with immunosuppressive agents.



 All patients should be advised to promptly report to their physician unexplained muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness, particularly if accompanied by malaise or fever or if muscle signs and symptoms persist after discontinuing PRAVACHOL.



  Pravastatin therapy should be discontinued if markedly elevated CPK levels occur or myopathy is diagnosed or suspected. Pravastatin therapy should also be temporarily withheld in any patient experiencing an acute or serious condition predisposing to the development of renal failure secondary to rhabdomyolysis, e.g., sepsis; hypotension; major surgery; trauma; severe metabolic, endocrine, or electrolyte disorders; or uncontrolled epilepsy.  



 The risk of myopathy during treatment with statins is increased with concurrent therapy with either erythromycin, cyclosporine, niacin, or fibrates. However, neither myopathy nor significant increases in CPK levels have been observed in 3 reports involving a total of 100 post-transplant patients (24 renal and 76 cardiac) treated for up to 2 years concurrently with pravastatin 10 to 40 mg and cyclosporine. Some of these patients also received other concomitant immunosuppressive therapies. Further, in clinical trials involving small numbers of patients who were treated concurrently with pravastatin and niacin, there were no reports of myopathy. Also, myopathy was not reported in a trial of combination pravastatin (40 mg/day) and gemfibrozil (1200 mg/day), although 4 of 75 patients on the combination showed marked CPK elevations versus 1 of 73 patients receiving placebo. There was a trend toward more frequent CPK elevations and patient withdrawals due to musculoskeletal symptoms in the group receiving combined treatment as compared with the groups receiving placebo, gemfibrozil, or pravastatin monotherapy. The use of fibrates alone may occasionally be associated with myopathy. The benefit of further alterations in lipid levels by the combined use of PRAVACHOL with fibrates should be carefully weighed against the potential risks of this combination.  



 Cases of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, have been reported with pravastatin coadministered with colchicine, and caution should be exercised when prescribing pravastatin with colchicine [see   Drug Interactions (7.3)    ].



    5.2 Liver



  Statins, like some other lipid-lowering therapies, have been associated with biochemical abnormalities of liver function. In 3 long-term (4.8-5.9 years), placebo-controlled clinical trials (WOS, LIPID, CARE), 19,592 subjects (19,768 randomized) were exposed to pravastatin or placebo [see   Clinical Studies (14)    ]. In an analysis of serum transaminase values (ALT, AST), incidences of marked abnormalities were compared between the pravastatin and placebo treatment groups; a marked abnormality was defined as a post-treatment test value greater than 3 times the upper limit of normal for subjects with pretreatment values less than or equal to the upper limit of normal, or 4 times the pretreatment value for subjects with pretreatment values greater than the upper limit of normal but less than 1.5 times the upper limit of normal. Marked abnormalities of ALT or AST occurred with similar low frequency (&lt;=1.2%) in both treatment groups. Overall, clinical trial experience showed that liver function test abnormalities observed during pravastatin therapy were usually asymptomatic, not associated with cholestasis, and did not appear to be related to treatment duration. In a 320-patient placebo-controlled clinical trial, subjects with chronic (&gt;6 months) stable liver disease, due primarily to hepatitis C or non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, were treated with 80 mg pravastatin or placebo for up to 9 months. The primary safety endpoint was the proportion of subjects with at least one ALT &gt;=2 times the upper limit of normal for those with normal ALT (&lt;= the upper limit of normal) at baseline or a doubling of the baseline ALT for those with elevated ALT (&gt; the upper limit of normal) at baseline. By Week 36, 12 out of 160 (7.5%) subjects treated with pravastatin met the prespecified safety ALT endpoint compared to 20 out of 160 (12.5%) subjects receiving placebo. Conclusions regarding liver safety are limited since the study was not large enough to establish similarity between groups (with 95% confidence) in the rates of ALT elevation.



  It is recommended that liver function tests be performed prior to the initiation of therapy and when clinically indicated.  



 Active liver disease or unexplained persistent transaminase elevations are contraindications to the use of pravastatin [see   Contraindications (4.2)    ]. Caution should be exercised when pravastatin is administered to patients who have a recent (&lt;6 months) history of liver disease, have signs that may suggest liver disease (e.g., unexplained aminotransferase elevations, jaundice), or are heavy users of alcohol.



 There have been rare postmarketing reports of fatal and non-fatal hepatic failure in patients taking statins, including pravastatin. If serious liver injury with clinical symptoms and/or hyperbilirubinemia or jaundice occurs during treatment with PRAVACHOL, promptly interrupt therapy. If an alternate etiology is not found do not restart PRAVACHOL.



    5.3 Endocrine Function



  Statins interfere with cholesterol synthesis and lower circulating cholesterol levels and, as such, might theoretically blunt adrenal or gonadal steroid hormone production. Results of clinical trials with pravastatin in males and post-menopausal females were inconsistent with regard to possible effects of the drug on basal steroid hormone levels. In a study of 21 males, the mean testosterone response to human chorionic gonadotropin was significantly reduced (p&lt;0.004) after 16 weeks of treatment with 40 mg of pravastatin. However, the percentage of patients showing a &gt;=50% rise in plasma testosterone after human chorionic gonadotropin stimulation did not change significantly after therapy in these patients. The effects of statins on spermatogenesis and fertility have not been studied in adequate numbers of patients. The effects, if any, of pravastatin on the pituitary-gonadal axis in pre-menopausal females are unknown. Patients treated with pravastatin who display clinical evidence of endocrine dysfunction should be evaluated appropriately. Caution should also be exercised if a statin or other agent used to lower cholesterol levels is administered to patients also receiving other drugs (e.g., ketoconazole, spironolactone, cimetidine) that may diminish the levels or activity of steroid hormones.



 In a placebo-controlled study of 214 pediatric patients with HeFH, of which 106 were treated with pravastatin (20 mg in the children aged 8-13 years and 40 mg in the adolescents aged 14-18 years) for 2 years, there were no detectable differences seen in any of the endocrine parameters (ACTH, cortisol, DHEAS, FSH, LH, TSH, estradiol [girls] or testosterone [boys]) relative to placebo. There were no detectable differences seen in height and weight changes, testicular volume changes, or Tanner score relative to placebo.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
