<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prednisolone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    (listed alphabetically under each subsection):  



   Cardiovascular:  Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy in premature infants.



   Dermatologic:  Facial erythema; increased sweating; impaired wound healing; may suppress reactions to skin tests; petechiae and ecchymoses; thin fragile skin; urticaria; edema.



   Endocrine:  Decreased carbohydrate tolerance; development of cushingoid state; hirsutism; increased requirements for insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents in diabetic patients; manifestations of latent diabetes mellitus; menstrual irregularities; secondary adrenocortical and pituitary unresponsiveness, particularly in times of stress, as in trauma, surgery or illness; suppression of growth in children.



   Fluid and Electrolyte Disturbances:  Congestive heart failure in susceptible patients; fluid retention; hypertension; hypokalemic alkalosis; potassium loss; sodium retention.



   Gastrointestinal:  Abdominal distention; elevation in serum liver enzyme levels (usually reversible upon discontinuation); pancreatitis; peptic ulcer with possible perforation and hemorrhage; ulcerative esophagitis.



   Metabolic:  Negative nitrogen balance due to protein catabolism.



   Musculoskeletal:  Aseptic necrosis of femoral and humeral heads; loss of muscle mass; muscle weakness; osteoporosis; pathologic fracture of long bones; steroid myopathy; tendon rupture; vertebral compression fractures.



   Neurological:  Convulsions; headache; increased intracranial pressure with papilledema (pseudotumor cerebri) usually following discontinuation of treatment; psychic disorders; vertigo.



   Ophthalmic:  Exophthalmos; glaucoma; increased intraocular pressure; posterior subcapsular cataracts.



   Other:  Increased appetite; malaise; nausea; weight gain.



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Seton Pharmaceuticals at 1-800-510-3401 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
