<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="premarin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  See    BOXED WARNINGS,        WARNINGS,    and    PRECAUTIONS    .



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During the first year of a 2-year clinical trial with 2,333 postmenopausal women between 40 and 65 years of age (88% Caucasian), 1,012 women were treated with conjugated estrogens and 332 were treated with placebo.  Table 6  summarizes adverse events that occurred at a rate of &gt;= 5%.



 TABLE 6. NUMBER (%) OF PATIENTS REPORTING &gt;= 5% TREATMENT EMERGENT ADVERSE EVENTS 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                       --Conjugated Estrogens Treatment Group--                                                                                                                                                                         
 Body System                                                                                                                                                                                                           0.625 mg                                                                                                      0.45 mg                                                                                           0.3 mg                                                                                                        Placebo                                                                                    
    Adverse event                                                                                                                                                                                                      (n = 348)                                                                                                     (n = 338)                                                                                         (n = 326)                                                                                                     (n = 332)                                                                                  
 Any adverse event                                                                                                                                                                                                     323 (93%)                                                                                                     305 (90%)                                                                                         292 (90%)                                                                                                     281 (85%)                                                                                  
 Body as a Whole                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                
    Abdominal pain   Accidental injury   Asthenia   Back pain   Flu syndrome   Headache   Infection   Pain                                                                                                             56 (16%)21 (6%)25 (7%)49 (14%)37 (11%)90 (26%)61 (18%)58 (17%)                                                50 (15%)41 (12%)23 (7%)43 (13%)38 (11%)109 (32%)75 (22%)61 (18%)                                  54 (17%)20 (6%)25 (8%)43 (13%)33 (10%)96 (29%)74 (23%)66 (20%)                                                37 (11%)29 (9%)16 (5%)39 (12%)35 (11%)93 (28%)74 (22%)61 (18%)                             
 Digestive System                                                                                                                                                                                                       
    Diarrhea   Dyspepsia   Flatulence   Nausea                                                                                                                                                                         21 (6%)33 (9%)24 (7%)32 (9%)                                                                                  25 (7%)32 (9%)23 (7%)21 (6%)                                                                      19 (6%)36 (11%)18 (6%)21 (6%)                                                                                 21 (6%)46 (14%)9 (3%)30 (9%)                                                               
 Musculoskeletal System                                                                                                                                                                                                 
    Arthralgia   Leg cramps   Myalgia                                                                                                                                                                                  47 (14%)19 (5%)18 (5%)                                                                                        42 (12%)23 (7%)18 (5%)                                                                            22 (7%)11 (3%)29 (9%)                                                                                         39 (12%)7 (2%)25 (8%)                                                                      
 Nervous System                                                                                                                                                                                                         
    Depression   Dizziness   Insomnia   Nervousness                                                                                                                                                                    25 (7%)19 (5%)21 (6%)12 (3%)                                                                                  27 (8%)20 (6%)25 (7%)17 (5%)                                                                      17 (5%)12 (4%)24 (7%)6 (2%)                                                                                   22 (7%)17 (5%)33 (10%)7 (2%)                                                               
 Respiratory System                                                                                                                                                                                                     
    Cough increased   Pharyngitis   Rhinitis   Sinusitis   Upper respiratory infection                                                                                                                                 13 (4%)35 (10%)21 (6%)22 (6%)42 (12%)                                                                         22 (7%)35 (10%)30 (9%)36 (11%)34 (10%)                                                            14 (4%)40 (12%)31 (10%)24 (7%)28 (9%)                                                                         14 (4%)38 (11%)42 (13%)24 (7%)35 (11%)                                                     
 Skin and Appendages                                                                                                                                                                                                    
    Pruritus                                                                                                                                                                                                           14 (4%)                                                                                                       17 (5%)                                                                                           16 (5%)                                                                                                       7 (2%)                                                                                     
 Urogenital System                                                                                                                                                                                                      
    Breast pain   Leukorrhea   Vaginal hemorrhage   Vaginal moniliasis   Vaginitis                                                                                                                                     38 (11%)18 (5%)47 (14%)20 (6%)24 (7%)                                                                         41 (12%)22 (7%)14 (4%)18 (5%)20 (6%)                                                              24 (7%)13 (4%)7 (2%)17 (5%)16 (5%)                                                                            29 (9%)9 (3%)06 (2%)4 (1%)                                                                 
      The following additional adverse reactions have been reported with estrogen and/or progestin therapy:
 

   1. Genitourinary system

  Abnormal uterine bleeding/spotting



 Dysmenorrhea/pelvic pain



 Increase in size of uterine leiomyomata



 Vaginitis, including vaginal candidiasis



 Change in amount of cervical secretion



 Change in cervical ectropion



 Ovarian cancer



 Endometrial hyperplasia



 Endometrial cancer



   2. Breasts

  Tenderness, enlargement, pain, discharge, galactorrhea



 Fibrocystic breast changes



 Breast cancer



   3. Cardiovascular

  Deep and superficial venous thrombosis



 Pulmonary embolism



 Thrombophlebitis



 Myocardial infarction



 Stroke



 Increase in blood pressure



   4. Gastrointestinal

  Nausea, vomiting



 Abdominal cramps, bloating



 Cholestatic jaundice



 Increased incidence of gallbladder disease



 Pancreatitis



 Enlargement of hepatic hemangiomas



 Ischemic colitis



   5. Skin

  Chloasma or melasma that may persist when drug is discontinued



 Erythema multiforme



 Erythema nodosum



 Hemorrhagic eruption



 Loss of scalp hair



 Hirsutism



 Pruritus, rash



   6. Eyes

  Retinal vascular thrombosis



 Intolerance to contact lenses



   7. Central Nervous System

  Headache



 Migraine



 Dizziness



 Mental depression



 Exacerbation of chorea



 Nervousness



 Mood disturbances



 Irritability



 Exacerbation of epilepsy



 Dementia



 Possible growth potentiation of benign meningioma



   8. Miscellaneous

  Increase or decrease in weight



 Glucose intolerance



 Aggravation of porphyria



 Edema



 Arthralgias



 Leg cramps



 Changes in libido



 Urticaria, angioedema, anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions



 Hypocalcemia (preexisting condition)



 Exacerbation of asthma



 Increased triglycerides
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    Rx only  



   WARNINGS

    ENDOMETRIAL CANCER  



 Adequate diagnostic measures, including endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in all cases of undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal vaginal bleeding. (See     WARNINGS, Malignant neoplasms, Endometrial cancer    .)



   CARDIOVASCULAR AND OTHER RISKS  



 Estrogens with or without progestins should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Dementia    .)



 The estrogen alone substudy of the Women's Health Initiative (WHI) reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 6.8 years and 7.1 years, respectively, of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE 0.625 mg), relative to placebo. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders    .)



 The estrogen plus progestin substudy of WHI reported increased risks of myocardial infarction, stroke, invasive breast cancer, pulmonary emboli, and DVT in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily CE 0.625 mg combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA 2.5 mg), relative to placebo. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Malignant neoplasms, Breast cancer    .)



 The Women's Health Initiative Memory Study (WHIMS), a substudy of WHI, reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE 0.625 mg alone and during 4 years of treatment with daily CE 0.625 mg combined with MPA 2.5 mg, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Dementia     and     PRECAUTIONS, Geriatric Use    .)



 In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins. Because of these risks, estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.



 





    BOXED WARNING: PATIENT INFORMATION

  PATIENT INFORMATION

    PREMARIN    (r)  



   (conjugated estrogens tablets, USP)  



 Read this PATIENT INFORMATION before you start taking PREMARIN and read what you get each time you refill your PREMARIN prescription. There may be new information. This information does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or your treatment.



     What is the most important information I should know about PREMARIN (an estrogen mixture)?  

    *  Estrogens increase the chance of getting cancer of the uterus.Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are taking PREMARIN. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  Do not use estrogens with or without progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes, or dementia.Using estrogens, with or without progestins, may increase your chance of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, and blood clots. Using estrogens, with or without progestins, may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women age 65 years or older. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN. 
      What is PREMARIN?
   PREMARIN is a medicine that contains a mixture of estrogen hormones.



   PREMARIN is used after menopause to:

    *  Reduce moderate to severe hot flashes. Estrogens are hormones made by a woman's ovaries. The ovaries normally stop making estrogens when a woman is between 45 and 55 years old. This drop in body estrogen levels causes the "change of life" or menopause (the end of monthly menstrual periods). Sometimes both ovaries are removed during an operation before natural menopause takes place. The sudden drop in estrogen levels causes "surgical menopause."When the estrogen levels begin dropping, some women get very uncomfortable symptoms, such as feelings of warmth in the face, neck, and chest, or sudden strong feelings of heat and sweating ("hot flashes" or "hot flushes"). In some women the symptoms are mild, and they will not need to take estrogens. In other women, symptoms can be more severe. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN. 
 *  Treat moderate to severe dryness, itching, and burning, in and around the vagina. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN to control these problems. If you use PREMARIN only to treat your dryness, itching, and burning in and around your vagina, talk with your healthcare provider about whether a topical vaginal product would be better for you. 
 *  Help reduce your chances of getting osteoporosis (thin weak bones). Osteoporosis from menopause is a thinning of the bones that makes them weaker and easier to break. If you use PREMARIN only to prevent osteoporosis due to menopause, talk with your healthcare provider about whether a different treatment or medicine without estrogens might be better for you. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you should continue with PREMARIN.Weight-bearing exercise, like walking or running, and taking calcium and vitamin D supplements may also lower your chances for getting postmenopausal osteoporosis. It is important to talk about exercise and supplements with your healthcare provider before starting them. 
      PREMARIN is also used to:
     *  Treat certain conditions in women before menopause if their ovaries do not make enough estrogen naturally. 
 *  Ease symptoms of certain cancers that have spread through the body, in men and women. 
      Who should not take PREMARIN?
   Do not start taking PREMARIN if you:



 *  Have unusual vaginal bleeding. 
 *  Currently have or have had certain cancers. Estrogens may increase the chance of getting certain types of cancers, including cancer of the breast or uterus. If you have or have had cancer, talk with your healthcare provider about whether you should take PREMARIN. 
 *  Had a stroke or heart attack in the past year. 
 *  Currently have or have had blood clots. 
 *  Currently have or have had liver problems. 
 *  Are allergic to PREMARIN tablets or any of its ingredients. See the list of ingredients in PREMARIN at the end of this leaflet. 
 *  Think you may be pregnant. 
      Tell your healthcare provider:
     *  If you are breast feeding. The hormones in PREMARIN can pass into your milk. 
 *  About all of your medical problems. Your healthcare provider may need to check you more carefully if you have certain conditions, such as asthma (wheezing), epilepsy (seizures), migraine, endometriosis, lupus, problems with your heart, liver, thyroid, kidneys, or have high calcium levels in your blood. 
 *  About all the medicines you take, including prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Some medicines may affect how PREMARIN works. PREMARIN may also affect how your other medicines work. 
 *  If you are going to have surgery or will be on bedrest. You may need to stop taking estrogens. 
      How should I take PREMARIN?
     *  Take one PREMARIN tablet at the same time each day. 
 *  If you miss a dose, take it as soon as possible. If it is almost time for your next dose, skip the missed dose and go back to your normal schedule. Do not take 2 doses at the same time. 
 *  Estrogens should be used at the lowest dose possible for your treatment only as long as needed. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly (for example, every 3 to 6 months) about the dose you are taking and whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN. 
      What are the possible side effects of PREMARIN?
     Side effects are grouped by how serious they are and how often they happen when you are treated.  

    Serious but less common side effects include:  

    *  Breast cancer 
 *  Cancer of the uterus 
 *  Stroke 
 *  Heart attack 
 *  Blood clots 
 *  Dementia 
 *  Gallbladder disease 
 *  Ovarian cancer 
 *  High blood pressure 
 *  Liver problems 
 *  High blood sugar 
 *  Enlargement of benign tumors of the uterus ("fibroids") 
        Some of the warning signs of these serious side effects include:  
     *  Breast lumps 
 *  Unusual vaginal bleeding 
 *  Dizziness and faintness 
 *  Changes in speech 
 *  Severe headaches 
 *  Chest pain 
 *  Shortness of breath 
 *  Pains in your legs 
 *  Changes in vision 
 *  Vomiting 
 *  Yellowing of the skin, eyes or nail beds 
    Call your healthcare provider right away if you get any of these warning signs, or any other unusual symptoms that concern you.
 

     Less serious but common side effects include:  

    *  Headache 
 *  Breast pain 
 *  Irregular vaginal bleeding or spotting 
 *  Stomach/abdominal cramps, bloating 
 *  Nausea and vomiting 
 *  Hair loss 
 *  Fluid retention 
 *  Vaginal yeast infection 
    These are not all the possible side effects of PREMARIN. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.
 

   What can I do to lower my chances of getting a serious side effect with PREMARIN?

    *  Talk with your healthcare provider regularly about whether you should continue taking PREMARIN. 
 *  If you have a uterus, talk to your healthcare provider about whether the addition of a progestin is right for you. The addition of a progestin is generally recommended for women with a uterus to reduce the chance of getting cancer of the uterus. 
 *  See your healthcare provider right away if you get vaginal bleeding while taking PREMARIN. 
 *  Have a breast exam and mammogram (breast X-ray) every year unless your healthcare provider tells you something else. If members of your family have had breast cancer or if you have ever had breast lumps or an abnormal mammogram, you may need to have breast exams more often. 
 *  If you have high blood pressure, high cholesterol (fat in the blood), diabetes, are overweight, or if you use tobacco, you may have higher chances for getting heart disease. Ask your healthcare provider for ways to lower your chances for getting heart disease. 
      General information about the safe and effective use of PREMARIN
   Medicines are sometimes prescribed for conditions that are not mentioned in patient information leaflets. Do not take PREMARIN for conditions for which it was not prescribed. Do not give PREMARIN to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them.



   Keep PREMARIN out of the reach of children.    



 This leaflet provides a summary of the most important information about PREMARIN. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider or pharmacist. You can ask for information about PREMARIN that is written for health professionals. You can get more information by calling the toll free number 800-934-5556.



   What are the ingredients in PREMARIN?

  PREMARIN contains a mixture of conjugated estrogens, which are a mixture of sodium estrone sulfate and sodium equilin sulfate and other components including sodium sulfate conjugates, 17 alpha-dihydroequilin, 17 alpha-estradiol, and 17 beta-dihydroequilin. 



 PREMARIN 0.3 mg, 0.45 mg, 0.625 mg, 0.9 mg, and 1.25 mg tablets also contain the following inactive ingredients: calcium phosphate tribasic, carnauba wax, hydroxypropyl cellulose, hypromellose, lactose monohydrate, magnesium stearate, microcrystalline cellulose, polyethylene glycol, powdered cellulose, sucrose and titanium dioxide. 



 The tablets come in different strengths and each strength tablet is a different color. The color ingredients are:



  - 0.3 mg tablet (green color): D&amp;C Yellow No. 10 and FD&amp;C Blue No. 2. 



  - 0.45 mg tablet (blue color): FD&amp;C Blue No. 2.



  - 0.625 mg tablet (maroon color): FD&amp;C Blue No. 2 and FD&amp;C Red No. 40.



  - 0.9 mg tablet (white color): D&amp;C Red No. 30 and D&amp;C Red No. 7.



  - 1.25 mg tablet (yellow color): black iron oxide, D&amp;C Yellow No. 10, and FD&amp;C Yellow No. 6.



 The appearance of these tablets is a trademark of Wyeth Pharmaceuticals.



 Store at Controlled Room Temperature 20 degrees  - 25 degrees C (68 degrees  - 77 degrees F).



   

  This product was manufactured by:



 Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc. Philadelphia, PA 19101



 This Product was Repackaged By:



   State of Florida DOH Central Pharmacy  

104-2 Hamilton Park Drive

Tallahassee, FL 32304

United States
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
