<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="premarin2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  See    BOXED WARNINGS    ,    WARNINGS    , and    PRECAUTIONS    .



 Premarin Intravenous for injection is indicated for short-term use. However, the warnings, precautions and adverse reactions associated with oral Premarin treatment should be taken into account.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of oral or intravenous Premarin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Genitourinary system  



 *     Abnormal uterine bleeding/spotting. 
 *     Dysmenorrhea or pelvic pain. 
 *     Increase in size of uterine leiomyomata. 
 *     Vaginitis, including vaginal candidiasis. 
 *     Change in amount of cervical secretion. 
 *     Change in cervical ectropion. 
 *     Ovarian cancer. 
 *     Endometrial hyperplasia. 
 *     Endometrial cancer. 
      Breasts  
 

 *     Tenderness, enlargement, pain, discharge, galactorrhea. 
 *     Fibrocystic breast changes. 
 *     Breast cancer. 
      Cardiovascular  
 

 *     Deep and superficial venous thrombosis. 
 *     Pulmonary embolism. 
 *     Thrombophlebitis. 
 *     Myocardial infarction. 
 *     Stroke. 
 *     Increase in blood pressure. 
      Gastrointestinal  
 

 *     Nausea, vomiting. 
 *     Abdominal cramps, bloating. 
 *     Cholestatic jaundice. 
 *     Increased incidence of gallbladder disease. 
 *     Pancreatitis. 
 *     Enlargement of hepatic hemangiomas. 
 *     Ischemic colitis. 
      Skin  
 

 *     Chloasma or melasma that may persist when drug is discontinued. 
 *     Erythema multiforme. 
 *     Erythema nodosum. 
 *     Hemorrhagic eruption. 
 *     Loss of scalp hair. 
 *     Hirsutism. 
 *     Pruritis. 
 *     Rash. 
      Eyes  
 

 *     Retinal vascular thrombosis. 
 *     Intolerance to contact lenses. 
      Central Nervous System  
 

 *     Headache. 
 *     Migraine. 
 *     Dizziness. 
 *     Mental depression. 
 *     Exacerbation of chorea. 
 *     Nervousness. 
 *     Exacerbation of epilepsy. 
 *     Dementia. 
 *     Possible growth potentiation of benign meningioma. 
      Miscellaneous  
 

 *     Increase or decrease in weight. 
 *     Glucose intolerance. 
 *     Aggravation of porphyria. 
 *     Edema. 
 *     Arthralgia. 
 *     Leg cramps. 
 *     Changes in libido. 
 *     Urticaria. 
 *     Hypocalcemia (preexisting condition). 
 *     Injection site pain. 
 *     Injection site edema. 
 *     Phlebitis (injection site). 
 *     Exacerbation of asthma. 
 *     Increased triglycerides. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA

    WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA  

  Estrogen-Alone Therapy

  Endometrial Cancer

  There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in  postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding. (See     WARNINGS, Malignant Neoplasms, Endometrial cancer    .)



   Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia

  Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular Disorders     and     Probable Dementia    .)



 The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg]-alone, relative to placebo. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders    .)



 The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study  of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Probable Dementia     and     PRECAUTIONS, Geriatric Use    .)



 In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE  and other dosage forms of estrogens.



 Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.



   Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy

  Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia

  Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Probable Dementia    .)



 The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders    .)



 The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Probable Dementia     and     PRECAUTIONS, Geriatric Use    .)



   Breast Cancer

  The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Malignant Neoplasms, Breast cancer    .)



 In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.



 Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.



 





    BOXED WARNING: 

    What is the most important information I should know about Premarin Intravenous (an estrogen mixture)?  



 *  Using estrogen-alone increases your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb)Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes, or dementia (decline in brain function) 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting stroke or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older 
 *  Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older 
 *  You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with estrogens 
    
 



    BOXED WARNING: 

    What is the most important information I should know about Premarin Intravenous (an estrogen mixture)?  



 *  Using estrogen-alone increases your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb)Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes, or dementia (decline in brain function) 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting stroke or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older 
 *  Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older 
 *  You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with estrogens. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
