<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="premarin1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular Disorders [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Malignant Neoplasms [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   In a prospective, randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind study, the most common adverse reactions &gt;= 2 percent are headache, pelvic pain, vasodilation, breast pain, leucorrhea, metrorrhagia, vaginitis, vulvovaginal disorder (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trial of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a 12-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of PREMARIN Vaginal Cream (PVC), a total of 423 postmenopausal women received at least 1 dose of study medication and were included in all safety analyses: 143 women in the PVC-21/7 treatment group (0.5 g PVC daily for 21 days, then 7 days off), 72 women in the matching placebo treatment group; 140 women in the PVC-2*/wk treatment group (0.5 g PVC twice weekly), 68 women in the matching placebo treatment group. A 40-week, open-label extension followed, in which a total of 394 women received treatment with PVC, including those subjects randomized at baseline to placebo. In this study, the most common adverse reactions &gt;= 1 percent in the double blind phase are shown below (Table 1)  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  .



 Table 1: Number (%) of Patients Reporting Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions &gt;= 1 Percent Only 
                                 Treatment           
 Body System/Adverse Reaction    PVC 21/7N=143      Placebo 21/7N=72     PVC 2*/weekN=140     Placebo 2*/weekN=68   
                                 Number (%) of Patients with Adverse Reaction   
  
   Body As A Whole                
 Abdominal Pain                  1 (0.7)            1 (1.4)              0                    1 (1.5)           
 Headache                        5 (3.5)            1 (1.4)              3 (2.1)              1 (1.5)           
 Moniliasis                      2 (1.4)            1 (1.4)              1 (0.7)              0                 
 Pain                            2 (1.4)            0                    1 (0.7)              0                 
 Pelvic Pain                     4 (2.8)            2 (2.8)              4 (2.9)              0                 
   Cardiovascular System          
 Migraine                        0                  0                    0                    1 (1.5)           
 Vasodilation                    3 (2.1)            2 (2.8)              2 (1.4)              0                 
   Musculoskeletal System         
 Muscle Cramp                    2 (1.4)            0                    0                    0                 
   Nervous System                 
 Dizziness                       1 (0.7)            0                    0                    1 (1.5)           
   Skin and Appendages            
 Acne                            0                  0                    2 (1.4)              0                 
 Erythema                        0                  1 (1.4)              0                    0                 
 Pruritus                        2 (1.4)            1 (1.4)              1 (0.7)              0                 
   Urogenital System              
 Breast Enlargement              1 (0.7)            1 (1.4)              0                    0                 
 Breast Pain                     7 (4.9)            0                    3 (2.1)              0                 
 Dysuria                         2 (1.4)            0                    0                    0                 
 Leukorrhea                      3 (2.1)            1 (1.4)              4 (2.9)              5 (7.4)           
 Metrorrhagia                    0                  0                    0                    2 (2.9)           
 Urinary Frequency               0                  1 (1.4)              0                    0                 
 Urinary Tract Infection         0                  1 (1.4)              0                    0                 
 Urinary Urgency                 1 (0.7)            1 (1.4)              0                    0                 
 Vaginal Hemorrhage              2 (1.4)            0                    1 (0.7)              1 (1.5)           
 Vaginal Moniliasis              2 (1.4)            0                    0                    0                 
 Vaginitis                       2 (1.4)            1 (1.4)              3 (2.1)              3 (4.4)           
 Vulvovaginal Disorder           4 (2.8)            0                    3 (2.1)              2 (2.9)           
             6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Genitourinary System  



 Abnormal uterine bleeding or spotting, dysmenorrhea or pelvic pain, increase in size of uterine leiomyomata, vaginitis (including vaginal candidiasis), change in cervical secretion, cystitis-like syndrome, application site reactions of vulvovaginal discomfort, (including burning, irritation, and genital pruritus), endometrial hyperplasia, endometrial cancer, precocious puberty, leukorrhea.



   Breasts  



 Tenderness, enlargement, pain, discharge, fibrocystic breast changes, breast cancer, gynecomastia in males.



   Cardiovascular  



 Deep venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, myocardial infarction, stroke, increase in blood pressure.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Nausea, vomiting, abdominal cramps, bloating, increased incidence of gallbladder disease.



   Skin  



 Chloasma that may persist when drug is discontinued, loss of scalp hair, hirsutism, rash.



   Eyes  



 Retinal vascular thrombosis, intolerance to contact lenses.



   Central Nervous System  



 Headache, migraine, dizziness, mental depression, nervousness, mood disturbances, irritability, dementia.



   Miscellaneous  



 Increase or decrease in weight, glucose intolerance, edema, arthralgias, leg cramps, changes in libido, urticaria, exacerbation of asthma, increased triglycerides, hypersensitivity.



 Additional postmarketing adverse reactions have been reported in patients receiving other forms of hormone therapy.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA

    WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA  

      Estrogen-Alone Therapy    



   Endometrial Cancer  



   There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding       [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]    . 



   Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia       [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2  ,   5.4)  , and   Clinical Studies (14.2  ,   14.3)  ]    . 



   The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg]-alone, relative to placebo       [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  , and   Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].    



   The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) -alone, relative to placebo.  It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ,   Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  , and   Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .  



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and other dosage forms of estrogens.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.  



     Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy    



   Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia       [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2  ,   5.4)  , and   Clinical Studies (14.2  ,   14.3)  ]    . 



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo       [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  , and   Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]    . 



   The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women       [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ,   Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  , and Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]    . 



   Breast Cancer  



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3  ), and   Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]    .



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



     Estrogen-Alone Therap  y  



 *  There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens (5.3) 
 *  Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.2, 5.4) 
 *  The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) (5.2) 
 *  The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.4) 
        Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy    
 

 *  Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.2, 5.4) 
 *  The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of stroke, DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), and myocardial infarction (MI) (5.2) 
 *  The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of invasive breast cancer (5.3) 
 *  The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.4) 
    
 







    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    FDA-Approved Patient Labeling  



   PREMARIN  (r)   (conjugated estrogens) Vaginal Cream  



 Read this PATIENT INFORMATION before you start using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream and read what you get each time you refill your PREMARIN Vaginal Cream prescription. There may be new information. This information does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your menopausal symptoms or your treatment.



     What is the most important information I should know about PREMARIN Vaginal Cream (an estrogen mixture)?  



 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb) Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia (decline in brain function) 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting strokes or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women 65 years of age or older 
 *  Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women age 65 years of age or older 
 *  You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN Vaginal Cream 
        What is PREMARIN Vaginal Cream?  
 

 PREMARIN Vaginal Cream is a medicine that contains a mixture of estrogen hormones.



   What is PREMARIN Vaginal Cream used for?  



   PREMARIN Vaginal Cream is used after menopause to:  



 *  Treat menopausal changes in and around the vaginaYou and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN Vaginal Cream to control these problems. 
 *  Treat painful intercourse caused by menopausal changes of the vagina 
      Who should not use PREMARIN Vaginal Cream?  
 

 Do not start using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream if you:



 *  Have unusual vaginal bleeding 
 *  Currently have or have had certain cancersEstrogens may increase the chance of getting certain types of cancers, including cancer of the breast or uterus. If you have or have had cancer, talk with your healthcare provider about whether you should use PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. 
 *  Had a stroke or heart attack 
 *  Currently have or have had blood clots 
 *  Currently have or have had liver problems 
 *  Have been diagnosed with a bleeding disorder 
 *  Are allergic to PREMARIN Vaginal Cream or any of its ingredientsSee the list of ingredients in PREMARIN Vaginal Cream at the end of this leaflet. 
 *  Think you may be pregnant 
      Tell your healthcare provider:  
 

 *  If you have unusual vaginal bleedingVaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  About all of your medical problemsYour healthcare provider may need to check you more carefully if you have certain conditions, such as asthma (wheezing), epilepsy (seizures), diabetes, migraine, endometriosis, lupus, or problems with your heart, liver, thyroid, kidneys, or have high calcium levels in your blood. 
 *  About all the medicines you takeThis includes prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Some medicines may affect how PREMARIN Vaginal Cream works. PREMARIN Vaginal Cream may also affect how your other medicines work. 
 *  If you are going to have surgery or will be on bedrestYou may need to stop using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. 
 *  If you are breast feedingThe estrogen hormones in PREMARIN Vaginal Cream can pass into your breast milk. 
      How should I use PREMARIN Vaginal Cream?  
 

 PREMARIN Vaginal Cream is a cream that you place in your vagina with the applicator provided with the cream. 



 *  Take the dose recommended by your healthcare provider and talk to him or her about how well that dose is working for you 
 *  Estrogens should be used at the lowest dose possible for your treatment only as long as needed. You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly (for example, every 3 to 6 months) about the dose you are taking and whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN Vaginal Cream 
   *    Step 1. Remove cap from tube. 
 *    Step 2. Screw nozzle end of applicator onto tube (Figure A). Figure A 
 *    Step 3. Gently squeeze tube from the bottom to force sufficient cream into the barrel to provide the prescribed dose. Use the marked stopping points on the applicator to measure the correct dose, as prescribed by your healthcare provider (Figure B). Figure B 
 *    Step 4. Unscrew applicator from tube. 
 *    Step 5. Lie on back with knees drawn up. To deliver medication, gently insert applicator deeply into vagina and press plunger downward to its original position (Figure C). Figure C 
 *    Step 6. TO CLEANSE: Pull plunger to remove it from barrel. Wash with mild soap and warm water (Figure D). DO NOT BOIL OR USE HOT WATER. 
  
                                                                                                        
                                               Figure D                                                 
         What are the possible side effects of PREMARIN Vaginal Cream?  
 

 PREMARIN Vaginal Cream is only used in and around the vagina; however, the risks associated with oral estrogens should be taken into account.



   Side effects are grouped by how serious they are and how often they happen when you are treated.  



   Serious, but less common side effects include:  



 *  Heart attack 
 *  Stroke 
 *  Blood clots 
 *  Dementia 
 *  Breast cancer 
 *  Cancer of the lining of the uterus (womb) 
 *  Cancer of the ovary 
 *  High blood pressure 
 *  High blood sugar 
 *  Gallbladder disease 
 *  Liver problems 
 *  Enlargement of benign tumors of the uterus ("fibroids") 
 *  Severe allergic reaction 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you get any of the following warning signs or any other unusual symptoms that concern you:  
 

 *  New breast lumps 
 *  Unusual vaginal bleeding 
 *  Changes in vision or speech 
 *  Sudden new severe headaches 
 *  Severe pains in your chest or legs with or without shortness of breath, weakness and fatigue 
 *  Swollen lips, tongue or face 
      Less serious, but common side effects include:  
 

 *  Headache 
 *  Breast pain 
 *  Irregular vaginal bleeding or spotting 
 *  Stomach or abdominal cramps, bloating 
 *  Nausea and vomiting 
 *  Hair loss 
 *  Fluid retention 
 *  Vaginal yeast infection 
 *  Reactions from inserting PREMARIN Vaginal Cream, such as vaginal burning, irritation, and itching 
    These are not all the possible side effects of PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for advice about side effects. You may report side effects to Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.
 

   What can I do to lower my chances of getting a serious side effect with PREMARIN Vaginal Cream?  



 *  Talk with your healthcare provider regularly about whether you should continue using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream 
 *  If you have a uterus, talk with your healthcare provider about whether the addition of a progestin is right for youThe addition of a progestin is generally recommended for a woman with a uterus to reduce the chance of getting cancer of the uterus. See your healthcare provider right away if you get vaginal bleeding while using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. 
 *  Have a pelvic exam, breast exam and mammogram (breast X-ray) every year unless your healthcare provider tells you something else If members of your family have had breast cancer or if you have ever had breast lumps or an abnormal mammogram, you may need to have breast exams more often. 
 *  If you have high blood pressure, high cholesterol (fat in the blood), diabetes, are overweight, or if you use tobacco, you may have higher chances for getting heart disease Ask your healthcare provider for ways to lower your chances for getting heart disease. 
      General information about the safe and effective use of PREMARIN Vaginal Cream  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for conditions that are not mentioned in patient information leaflets. Do not use PREMARIN Vaginal Cream for conditions for which it was not prescribed. Do not give PREMARIN Vaginal Cream to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them.



   Keep PREMARIN Vaginal Cream out of the reach of children.  



 Latex or rubber condoms, diaphragms and cervical caps may be weakened and fail when they come into contact with PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. 



 This leaflet provides a summary of the most important information about PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider or pharmacist. You can ask for information about PREMARIN Vaginal Cream that is written for health professionals.



   What are the ingredients in PREMARIN Vaginal Cream?  



 PREMARIN Vaginal Cream contains a mixture of conjugated estrogens, which are a mixture of sodium estrone sulfate and sodium equilin sulfate and other components, including sodium sulfate conjugates: 17 alpha-dihydroequilin, 17 alpha-estradiol, and 17 beta-dihydroequilin. PREMARIN Vaginal Cream also contains cetyl esters wax, cetyl alcohol, white wax, glyceryl monostearate, propylene glycol monostearate, methyl stearate, benzyl alcohol, sodium lauryl sulfate, glycerin, and mineral oil.



 PREMARIN (conjugated estrogens) Vaginal Cream-Each gram contains 0.625 mg conjugated estrogens, USP.



   Combination package:   Each contains a net wt. of 1.06 oz (30 g) tube with plastic applicator(s) calibrated in 0.5 g increments to a maximum of 2 g (NDC 0046-0872-21), or a net wt. 1.5 oz (42.5 g) tube with one plastic applicator calibrated in 0.5 g increments to a maximum of 2 g (NDC 0046-0872-93).



   Store at 20 degrees  to 25 degrees C (68 degrees  to 77 degrees F); excursions permitted to 15 degrees  to 30 degrees C (59 degrees  to 86 degrees F) [see USP Controlled Room Temperature].  



  Logo 





    BOXED WARNING: 

    FDA-Approved Patient Labeling  



   PREMARIN  (r)   (conjugated estrogens) Vaginal Cream  



 Read this PATIENT INFORMATION before you start using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream and read what you get each time you refill your PREMARIN Vaginal Cream prescription. There may be new information. This information does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your menopausal symptoms or your treatment.



     What is the most important information I should know about PREMARIN Vaginal Cream (an estrogen mixture)?  



 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting cancer of the uterus (womb) Report any unusual vaginal bleeding right away while you are using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. Vaginal bleeding after menopause may be a warning sign of cancer of the uterus (womb). Your healthcare provider should check any unusual vaginal bleeding to find out the cause. 
 *  Do not use estrogen-alone to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia (decline in brain function) 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chances of getting strokes or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogen-alone may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women age 65 years of age or older 
 *  Do not use estrogens with progestins to prevent heart disease, heart attacks, strokes or dementia 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chances of getting heart attacks, strokes, breast cancer, or blood clots 
 *  Using estrogens with progestins may increase your chance of getting dementia, based on a study of women age 65 years of age or older 
 *  You and your healthcare provider should talk regularly about whether you still need treatment with PREMARIN Vaginal Cream 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Estrogens increase the risk of gallbladder disease (  5.5  ) 
 *  Discontinue estrogen if severe hypercalcemia, loss of vision, severe hypertriglyceridemia or cholestatic jaundice occurs (  5.6  ,  5.7  ,  5.10  ,  5.11  ) 
 *  Monitor thyroid function in women on thyroid replacement therapy (  5.12  ,  5.21  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risks from Systemic Absorption



  Systemic absorption occurs with the use of PREMARIN Vaginal Cream. The warnings, precautions, and adverse reactions associated with oral PREMARIN treatment should be taken into account.



    5.2 Cardiovascular Disorders



  An increased risk of stroke and DVT has been reported with estrogen-alone therapy. An increased risk of PE, DVT, stroke and MI has been reported with estrogen plus progestin therapy. Should any of these occur or be suspected, estrogen with or without progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 Risk factors for arterial vascular disease (for example, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, tobacco use, hypercholesterolemia, and obesity) and/or venous thromboembolism (VTE) (for example, personal history or family history of VTE, obesity, and systemic lupus erythematosus) should be managed appropriately.



    Stroke  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) -alone compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (45 versus 33 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in risk was demonstrated in year 1 and persisted [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest no increased risk of stroke for those women receiving CE (0.625 mg) -alone versus those receiving placebo (18 versus 21 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (33 versus 25 per 10,000 women-years) [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  . The increase in risk was demonstrated after the first year and persisted.  1  Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



    Coronary Heart Disease  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, no overall effect on coronary heart disease (CHD) events (defined as nonfatal MI, silent MI, or CHD death) was reported in women receiving estrogen-alone compared to placebo  2   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest a statistically non-significant reduction in CHD events (CE [0.625 mg]-alone compared to placebo) in women with less than 10 years since menopause (8 versus 16 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, there was a statistically non-significant increased risk of CHD events reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (41 versus 34 per 10,000 women-years).  1  An increase in relative risk was demonstrated in year 1, and a trend toward decreasing relative risk was reported in years 2 through 5 [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  



 In postmenopausal women with documented heart disease (n = 2,763), average 66.7 years of age, in a controlled clinical trial of secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease (Heart and Estrogen/Progestin Replacement Study [HERS]), treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) demonstrated no cardiovascular benefit. During an average follow-up of 4.1 years, treatment with CE plus MPA did not reduce the overall rate of CHD events in postmenopausal women with established coronary heart disease. There were more CHD events in the CE plus MPA-treated group than in the placebo group in year 1, but not during subsequent years. Two thousand, three hundred and twenty-one (2,321) women from the original HERS trial agreed to participate in an open label extension of HERS, HERS II. Average follow-up in HERS II was an additional 2.7 years, for a total of 6.8 years overall. Rates of CHD events were comparable among women in the CE plus MPA group and the placebo group in HERS, HERS II, and overall.



    Venous Thromboembolism  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, the risk of VTE (DVT and PE) was increased for women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) -alone compared to placebo (30 versus 22 per 10,000 women-years), although only the increased risk of DVT reached statistical significance (23 versus 15 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first 2 years  3   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  . Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant 2-fold greater rate of VTE was reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (35 versus 17 per 10,000 women-years). Statistically significant increases in risk for both DVT (26 versus 13 per 10,000 women-years) and PE (18 versus 8 per 10,000 women-years) were also demonstrated. The increase in VTE risk was observed during the first year and persisted  4   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  . Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 If feasible, estrogens should be discontinued at least 4 to 6 weeks before surgery of the type associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, or during periods of prolonged immobilization.



    5.3 Malignant Neoplasms



   Endometrial Cancer  



 An increased risk of endometrial cancer has been reported with the use of unopposed estrogen therapy in a woman with a uterus. The reported endometrial cancer risk among unopposed estrogen users is about 2 to 12 times greater than in non-users, and appears dependent on duration of treatment and on estrogen dose. Most studies show no significant increased risk associated with use of estrogens for less than 1 year. The greatest risk appears to be associated with prolonged use, with increased risks of 15- to 24-fold for 5 to 10 years or more, and this risk has been shown to persist for at least 8 to 15 years after estrogen therapy is discontinued.



 Clinical surveillance of all women using estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy is important. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding.



 There is no evidence that the use of natural estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens of equivalent estrogen dose. Adding a progestin to postmenopausal estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



 In a 52-week clinical trial using PREMARIN Vaginal Cream alone (0.5 g inserted twice weekly or daily for 21 days, then off for 7 days), there was no evidence of endometrial hyperplasia or endometrial carcinoma.



    Breast Cancer  



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen-alone users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg) -alone. In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, after an average follow-up of 7.1 years, daily CE-alone was not associated with an increased risk of invasive breast cancer [relative risk (RR) 0.80]    5   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen plus progestin users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg). After a mean follow-up of 5.6 years, the estrogen plus progestin substudy reported an increased risk of invasive breast cancer in women who took daily CE plus MPA. In this substudy, prior use of estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy was reported by 26 percent of the women. The relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.24, and the absolute risk was 41 versus 33 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.86, and the absolute risk was 46 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported no prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.09, and the absolute risk was 40 versus 36 cases per 10,000 women-years for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. In the same substudy, invasive breast cancers were larger, were more likely to be node positive, and were diagnosed at a more advanced stage in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group compared with the placebo group. Metastatic disease was rare, with no apparent difference between the two groups. Other prognostic factors, such as histologic subtype, grade and hormone receptor status did not differ between the groups  6   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 Consistent with the WHI clinical trial, observational studies have also reported an increased risk of breast cancer for estrogen plus progestin therapy, and a smaller increased risk for estrogen-alone therapy, after several years of use. The risk increased with duration of use, and appeared to return to baseline over about 5 years after stopping treatment (only the observational studies have substantial data on risk after stopping). Observational studies also suggest that the risk of breast cancer was greater, and became apparent earlier, with estrogen plus progestin therapy as compared to estrogen-alone therapy. However, these studies have not generally found significant variation in the risk of breast cancer among different estrogen plus progestin combinations, doses, or routes of administration.



 The use of estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin therapy has been reported to result in an increase in abnormal mammograms, requiring further evaluation.



 All women should receive yearly breast examinations by a healthcare provider and perform monthly breast self-examinations. In addition, mammography examinations should be scheduled based on patient age, risk factors, and prior mammogram results.



    Ovarian Cancer  



 The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported a statistically non-significant increased risk of ovarian cancer. After an average follow-up of 5.6 years, the relative risk for ovarian cancer for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 1.58 (95 percent CI, 0.77-3.24). The absolute risk for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 4 versus 3 cases per 10,000 women-years.  7  In some epidemiologic studies, the use of estrogen plus progestin and estrogen-only products, in particular for 5 or more years, has been associated with an increased risk of ovarian cancer . However, the duration of exposure associated with increased risk is not consistent across all epidemiologic studies, and some report no association.



    5.4 Probable Dementia



  In the WHIMS estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI, a population of 2,947 hysterectomized women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg) -alone or placebo.



 After an average follow-up of 5.2 years, 28 women in the estrogen-alone group and 19 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 1.49 (95 percent CI, 0.83-2.66). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 37 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years  8   [see  Use in Specific Populations (8. 5)  , and  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .



 In the WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI, a population of 4,532 postmenopausal women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) or placebo.



 After an average follow-up of 4 years, 40 women in the CE plus MPA group and 21 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 2.05 (95 percent CI, 1.21-3.48). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 45 versus 22 cases per 10,000 women-years  8   [see  Use in Specific Populations (8. 5)  , and  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .



 When data from the two populations in the WHIMS estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin ancillary studies were pooled as planned in the WHIMS protocol, the reported overall relative risk for probable dementia was 1.76 (95 percent CI, 1.19-2.60). Since both ancillary studies were conducted in women 65 to 79 years of age, it is unknown whether these findings apply to younger postmenopausal women  8   [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  , and  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .



    5.5 Gallbladder Disease



  A 2- to 4-fold increase in the risk of gallbladder disease requiring surgery in postmenopausal women receiving estrogens has been reported.



    5.6 Hypercalcemia



  Estrogen administration may lead to severe hypercalcemia in women with breast cancer and bone metastases. If hypercalcemia occurs, use of the drug should be stopped and appropriate measures taken to reduce the serum calcium level.



    5.7 Visual Abnormalities



  Retinal vascular thrombosis has been reported in patients receiving estrogens. Discontinue medication pending examination if there is sudden partial or complete loss of vision, or a sudden onset of proptosis, diplopia, or migraine. If examination reveals papilledema or retinal vascular lesions, estrogens should be permanently discontinued.



    5.8 Addition of a Progestin When a Woman Has Not Had a Hysterectomy



  Studies of the addition of a progestin for 10 or more days of a cycle of estrogen administration, or daily with estrogen in a continuous regimen, have reported a lowered incidence of endometrial hyperplasia than would be induced by estrogen treatment alone. Endometrial hyperplasia may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



 There are, however, possible risks that may be associated with the use of progestins with estrogens compared to estrogen-alone regimens. These include an increased risk of breast cancer.



    5.9 Elevated Blood Pressure



  In a small number of case reports, substantial increases in blood pressure have been attributed to idiosyncratic reactions to estrogens. In a large, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial, a generalized effect of estrogen therapy on blood pressure was not seen.



    5.10 Hypertriglyceridemia



  In women with pre-existing hypertriglyceridemia, estrogen therapy may be associated with elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis. Consider discontinuation of treatment if pancreatitis occurs.



    5.11 Hepatic Impairment and/or Past History of Cholestatic Jaundice



  Estrogens may be poorly metabolized in women with impaired liver function. For women with a history of cholestatic jaundice associated with past estrogen use or with pregnancy, caution should be exercised, and in the case of recurrence, medication should be discontinued.



    5.12 Hypothyroidism



  Estrogen administration leads to increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels. Women with normal thyroid function can compensate for the increased TBG by making more thyroid hormone, thus maintaining free T4and T3serum concentrations in the normal range. Women dependent on thyroid hormone replacement therapy who are also receiving estrogens may require increased doses of their thyroid replacement therapy. These women should have their thyroid function monitored in order to maintain their free thyroid hormone levels in an acceptable range.



    5.13 Fluid Retention



  Estrogens may cause some degree of fluid retention. Women with conditions that might be influenced by this factor, such as cardiac or renal dysfunction, warrant careful observation when estrogen-alone is prescribed.



    5.14 Hypocalcemia



  Estrogen therapy should be used with caution in women with hypoparathyroidism as estrogen-induced hypocalcemia may occur.



    5.15 Exacerbation of Endometriosis



  A few cases of malignant transformation of residual endometrial implants have been reported in women treated post-hysterectomy with estrogen-alone therapy. For women known to have residual endometriosis post-hysterectomy, the addition of progestin should be considered.



    5.16 Anaphylactic Reaction and Angioedema



   Cases of anaphylaxis, which develop within minutes to hours after taking orally-administered PREMARIN and require emergency management, have been reported in the postmarketing setting. Skin (hives, pruritus, swollen lips-tongue-face) and either respiratory tract (respiratory compromise) or gastrointestinal tract (abdominal pain, vomiting) involvement has been noted.  



  Angioedema involving the tongue, larynx, face, and feet requiring medical intervention has occurred postmarketing in patients taking orally-administered PREMARIN. If angioedema involves the tongue, glottis, or larynx, airway obstruction may occur. Patients who develop an anaphylactic reaction with or without angioedema after treatment with oral PREMARIN should not receive oral PREMARIN again.  



    5.17 Hereditary Angioedema



   Exogenous estrogens may exacerbate symptoms of angioedema in women with hereditary angioedema.  



    5.18 Exacerbation of Other Conditions



  Estrogen therapy may cause an exacerbation of asthma, diabetes mellitus, epilepsy, migraine, porphyria, systemic lupus erythematosus, and hepatic hemangiomas and should be used with caution in women with these conditions.



    5.19 Effects on Barrier Contraception



  PREMARIN Vaginal Cream exposure has been reported to weaken latex condoms. The potential for PREMARIN Vaginal Cream to weaken and contribute to the failure of condoms, diaphragms, or cervical caps made of latex or rubber should be considered.



    5.20 Laboratory Tests



  Serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels have not been shown to be useful in the management of moderate to severe symptoms of vulvar and vaginal atrophy.



    5.21 Drug-Laboratory Test Interactions



  Accelerated prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet aggregation time; increased platelet count; increased factors II, VII antigen, VIII antigen, VIII coagulant activity, IX, X, XII, VII-X complex, II-VII-X complex, and beta-thromboglobulin; decreased levels of antifactor Xa and antithrombin III, decreased antithrombin III activity; increased levels of fibrinogen and fibrinogen activity; increased plasminogen antigen and activity.



 Increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone, as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T4levels (by column or by radioimmunoassay) or T3levels by radioimmunoassay. T3resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG. Free T4and free T3concentrations are unaltered. Women on thyroid replacement therapy may require higher doses of thyroid hormone.



 Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum, for example, corticosteroid binding globulin (CBG), sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), leading to increased total circulating corticosteroids and sex steroids, respectively. Free hormone concentrations, such as testosterone and estradiol, may be decreased. Other plasma proteins may be increased (angiotensinogen/renin substrate, alpha-1-antitrypsin, ceruloplasmin).



 Increased plasma high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and HDL2cholesterol subfraction concentrations, reduced low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol concentrations, increased triglyceride levels.



 Impaired glucose tolerance.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
