<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prevnar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse-reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. As with any vaccine, there is the possibility that broad use of Prevnar 13 could reveal adverse reactions not observed in clinical trials.



    EXCERPT:    *  In infants and toddlers vaccinated at 2, 4, 6, and 12-15 months of age in US clinical trials, the most commonly reported solicited adverse reactions were irritability (&gt;70%), injection site tenderness (&gt;50%), decreased appetite (&gt;40%), decreased sleep (&gt;40%), increased sleep (&gt;40%), fever (&gt;20%), injection site redness (&gt;20%), and injection site swelling (&gt;20%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In children aged 5 through 17 years, the most commonly reported solicited adverse reactions were injection site tenderness (&gt;80%), injection site redness (&gt;30%), injection site swelling (&gt;30%), irritability (&gt;20%), decreased appetite (&gt;20%), increased sleep (&gt;20%), fever (&gt;5%), and decreased sleep (&gt;5%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  In adults aged 50 years and older the commonly reported solicited adverse reactions were pain at the injection site (&gt;50%), fatigue (&gt;30%), headache (&gt;20%), muscle pain (&gt;20%), joint pain (&gt;10%), decreased appetite (&gt;10%), injection site redness (&gt;10%), injection site swelling (&gt;10%), limitation of arm movement (&gt;10%), chills (&gt;5%) or rash (&gt;5%). (  6.2  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or http://vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience With Prevnar 13 in Children 6 Weeks Through 17 Years of Age

  The safety of Prevnar 13 was evaluated in 13 clinical trials in which 4,729 infants (6 weeks through 11 months of age) and toddlers (12 months through 15 months of age) received at least one dose of Prevnar 13 and 2,760 infants and toddlers received at least one dose of Prevnar active control. Safety data for the first three doses are available for all 13 infant studies; dose 4 data are available for 10 studies; and data for the 6-month follow-up are available for 7 studies. The vaccination schedule and concomitant vaccinations used in these infant trials were consistent with country-specific recommendations and local clinical practice. There were no substantive differences in demographic characteristics between the vaccine groups. By race, 84.0% of subjects were White, 6.0% were Black or African-American, 5.8% were Asian and 3.8% were of 'Other' race (most of these being biracial). Overall, 52.3% of subjects were male infants.



 Three studies in the US (Studies 1, 2 and 3) evaluated the safety of Prevnar 13 when administered concomitantly with routine US pediatric vaccinations at 2, 4, 6, and 12-15 months of age. Solicited local and systemic adverse reactions were recorded daily by parents/guardians using an electronic diary for 7 consecutive days following each vaccination. For unsolicited adverse events, study subjects were monitored from administration of the first dose until one month after the infant series, and for one month after the administration of the toddler dose. Information regarding unsolicited and serious adverse events, newly diagnosed chronic medical conditions, and hospitalizations since the last visit were collected during the clinic visit for the fourth-study dose and during a scripted telephone interview 6 months after the fourth-study dose. Serious adverse events were also collected throughout the study period. Overall, the safety data show a similar proportion of Prevnar 13 and Prevnar subjects reporting serious adverse events. Among US study subjects, a similar proportion of Prevnar 13 and Prevnar recipients reported solicited local and systemic adverse reactions as well as unsolicited adverse events.



     Serious Adverse Events in All Infant and Toddler Clinical Studies  



 Serious adverse events were collected throughout the study period for all 13 clinical trials. This reporting period is longer than the 30-day post-vaccination period used in some vaccine trials. The longer reporting period may have resulted in serious adverse events being reported in a higher percentage of subjects than for other vaccines. Serious adverse events reported following vaccination in infants and toddlers occurred in 8.2% among Prevnar 13 recipients and 7.2% among Prevnar recipients. Serious adverse events observed during different study periods for Prevnar 13 and Prevnar respectively were: 1) 3.7% and 3.5% from dose 1 to the bleed approximately 1 month after the infant series; 2) 3.6% and 2.7% from the bleed after the infant series to the toddler dose; 3) 0.9% and 0.8% from the toddler dose to the bleed approximately 1 month after the toddler dose and 4) 2.5% and 2.8% during the 6 month follow-up period after the last dose.



 The most commonly reported serious adverse events were in the 'Infections and infestations' system organ class including bronchiolitis (0.9%, 1.1%), gastroenteritis, (0.9%, 0.9%), and pneumonia (0.9%, 0.5%) for Prevnar 13 and Prevnar respectively.



 There were 3 (0.063%) deaths among Prevnar 13 recipients, and 1 (0.036%) death in Prevnar recipients, all as a result of sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS). These SIDS rates are consistent with published age specific background rates of SIDS from the year 2000.



 Among 6,839 subjects who received at least 1 dose of Prevnar 13 in clinical trials conducted globally, there was 1 hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode adverse reaction reported (0.015%). Among 4,204 subjects who received at least 1 dose of Prevnar in clinical trials conducted globally, there were 3 hypotonic-hyporesponsive episode adverse reactions reported (0.071%). All 4 events occurred in a single clinical trial in Brazil in which subjects received whole cell pertussis vaccine at the same time as Prevnar 13 or Prevnar.



     Solicited Adverse Reactions in the Three US Infant and Toddler Studies  



 A total of 1,907 subjects received at least 1 dose of Prevnar 13 and 701 subjects received at least 1 dose of Prevnar in the three US studies (Studies 1, 2 and 3). Most subjects were White (77.3%), 14.2% were Black or African-American, and 1.7% were Asian; 79.1% of subjects were non-Hispanic and non-Latino and 14.6% were Hispanic or Latino. Overall, 53.6% of subjects were male infants.



 The incidence and severity of solicited adverse reactions that occurred within 7 days following each dose of Prevnar 13 or Prevnar administered to US infants and toddlers are shown in Tables 3 and 4.



 Table 3: Percentage of US Infant and Toddler Subjects Reporting Solicited Local Reactions at the Prevnar 13 or Prevnar Injection Sites Within 7 Days After Each Vaccination at 2, 4, 6, and 12-15 Months of AgeData are from three primary US safety studies (the US Phase 2 infant study [National Clinical Trial (NCT) number NCT00205803] Study 1, the US noninferiority study [NCT00373958] Study 2, and the US lot consistency study [NCT00444457] Study 3). All infants received concomitant routine infant immunizations. Concomitant vaccines and pneumococcal conjugate vaccines were administered in different limbs. 
                 Dose 1       Dose 2       Dose 3       Dose 4      
 Graded Local Reaction  Prevnar 13(N=1375-1612)%  Prevnar(N=516-606)%  Prevnar 13(N=1069-1331)%  Prevnar(N=405-510)%  Prevnar 13(N=998-1206)%  Prevnar (N=348-446)%  Prevnar 13(N=874-1060)%  Prevnar (N=283-379)%   
  
 Redness                                                                                                                
   Any            24.3         26.0         33.3         29.7         37.1         36.6         42.3         45.5       
   Mild           23.1         25.2         31.9         28.7         35.3         35.3         39.5         42.7       
   Moderate        2.2          1.5          2.7          2.2          4.6          5.1          9.6         13.4       
   Severe           0            0            0            0            0            0            0            0        
 Swelling                                                                                                               
   Any            20.1         20.7         25.2         22.5         26.8         28.4         31.6         36.0       
   Mild           17.2         18.7         23.8         20.5         25.2         27.5         29.4         33.8       
   Moderate        4.9          3.9          3.7          4.9          3.8          5.8          8.3         11.2       
   Severe           0            0           0.1           0            0            0            0            0        
 Tenderness                                                                                                             
   Any            62.5         64.5         64.7         62.9         59.2         60.8         57.8         62.5       
   Interferes with limb movement     10.4          9.6          9.0         10.5          8.4          9.0          6.9          5.7       
              Table 4: Percentage of US Infant and Toddler Subjects Reporting Solicited Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 7 Days After Each Vaccination at 2, 4, 6, and 12-15 Months of AgeNumber of subjects reporting Yes for at least 1 day or No for all days.,Data are from three primary US safety studies (the US Phase 2 infant study [NCT00205803] Study 1, the US noninferiority study [NCT00373958] Study 2, and the US lot consistency study [NCT00444457] Study 3). All infants received concomitant routine infant immunizations. Concomitant vaccines and pneumococcal conjugate vaccines were administered in different limbs. 
                 Dose 1       Dose 2       Dose 3       Dose 4      
 Graded Systemic Events  Prevnar 13(N=1360 - 1707)%  Prevnar(N=497-640)%  Prevnar 13(N=1084-1469)%  Prevnar(N=409-555)%  Prevnar 13(N=997-1361)%  Prevnar(N=354-521)%  Prevnar 13(N=850-1227)%  Prevnar(N=278-436)%   
  
 Fever                                                                                                                  
   Any            24.3         22.1         36.5         32.8         30.3         31.6         31.9         30.6       
   Mild           23.6         21.7         34.9         31.6         29.1         30.2         30.3         30.0       
   Moderate        1.1          0.6          3.4          2.8          4.2          3.3          4.4          4.6       
   Severe          0.1          0.2          0.1          0.3          0.1          0.7          1.0           0        
 Decreased appetite     48.3         43.6         47.8         43.6         47.6         47.6         51.0         49.4       
 Irritability     85.6         83.6         84.8         80.4         79.8         80.8         80.4         77.8       
 Increased sleep     71.5         71.5         66.6         63.4         57.7         55.2         48.7         55.1       
 Decreased sleep     42.5         40.6         45.6         43.7         46.5         47.7         45.3         40.3       
               The incidence rates of any fever (&gt;=38.0 degrees C) were similar on days 1 and 2 following each dose of Prevnar 13 compared to after each dose of Prevnar administered to US infants and toddlers (day 1 = day of vaccination). After dose 1, fever was reported in 11.0-12.7% on day 1 and 6.4-6.8% on day 2. After dose 2, fever was reported in 12.3-13.1% on day 1 and 12.5-12.8% on day 2. After dose 3, fever was reported in 8.0-9.6% on day 1 and 9.1-10.5% on day 2. And after dose 4, fever was reported in 6.3-6.4% on day 1 and 7.3-9.7% on day 2.
 

     Unsolicited Adverse Reactions in the Three US Infant and Toddler Safety Studies  



 The following were determined to be adverse drug reactions based on experience with Prevnar 13 in clinical trials.



 Reactions occurring in greater than 1% of infants and toddlers: diarrhea, vomiting, and rash.



 Reactions occurring in less than 1% of infants and toddlers: crying, hypersensitivity reaction (including face edema, dyspnea, and bronchospasm), seizures (including febrile seizures), and urticaria or urticaria-like rash.



     Safety Assessments in the Catch-Up Studies in Infants and Children Through 5 Years of Age  



 In a catch-up study conducted in Poland (Study 4), 354 children (7 months through 5 years of age) receiving at least one dose of Prevnar 13 were also monitored for safety. All subjects in this study were White and non-Hispanic. Overall, 49.6% of subjects were male infants. The incidence and severity of solicited adverse reactions that occurred within 4 days following each dose of Prevnar 13 administered to pneumococcal-vaccine naive children 7 months through 5 years of age are shown in Tables 5 and 6.



 Table 5: Percentage of Subjects 7 Months Through 5 Years of Age Reporting Solicited Local Reactions Within 4 Days After Each Catch-Up Prevnar 13 VaccinationStudy conducted in Poland (NCT00452452) Study 4. 
                   7 through 11 months  12 through 23 months  24 months through 5 years   
 Graded Local Reaction    Dose 1N=86    Dose 2N=86-87   Dose 3N=78-82   Dose 1N=108-110  Dose 2N=98-106  Dose 1N=147-149   
                         %               %               %               %               %               %          
  
 Redness            
   Any                  48.8            46.0            37.8            70.0            54.7            50.0        
   Mild                 41.9            40.2            31.3            55.5            44.7            37.4        
   Moderate             16.3            9.3             12.5            38.2            25.5            25.7        
   Severe               0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0         
 Swelling           
   Any                  36.0            32.2            25.0            44.5            41.0            36.9        
   Mild                 32.6            28.7            20.5            36.7            36.2            28.2        
   Moderate             11.6            14.0            11.3            24.8            12.1            20.3        
   Severe               0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0         
 Tenderness         
   Any                  15.1            15.1            15.2            33.3            43.7            42.3        
   Interferes with limb movement       1.2             3.5             6.4             0.0             4.1             4.1         
            Table 6: Percentage of Subjects 7 Months Through 5 Years of Age Reporting Solicited Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 4 Days After Each Catch-Up Prevnar 13 VaccinationStudy conducted in Poland (NCT00452452) Study 4. 
                   7 through 11 months  12 through 23 months  24 months through 5 years   
 Systemic Reaction  Dose 1N=86-87   Dose 2N=86-87   Dose 3N=78-81    Dose 1N=108    Dose 2N=98-100  Dose 1N=147-148   
                         %               %               %               %               %               %          
  
 Fever              
   Mild                 3.4             8.1             5.1             3.7             5.1             0.7         
   Moderate             1.2             2.3             1.3             0.9             0.0             0.7         
   Severe               0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0             0.0         
 Decreased appetite       19.5            17.2            17.5            22.2            25.5            16.3        
 Irritability           24.1            34.5            24.7            30.6            34.0            14.3        
 Increased sleep        9.2             9.3             2.6             13.0            10.1            11.6        
 Decreased sleep        24.1            18.4            15.0            19.4            20.4            6.8         
             A US study (Study 5) evaluated the use of Prevnar 13 in children previously immunized with Prevnar. In this open label trial, 596 healthy children 15 through 59 months of age previously vaccinated with at least 3 doses of Prevnar, received 1 or 2 doses of Prevnar 13. Children 15 months through 23 months of age (group 1) received 2 doses, and children 24 months through 59 months of age (group 2) received one dose. Most subjects were White (74.3%), 14.9% were Black or African-American, and 1.2% were Asian; 89.3% of subjects were non-Hispanic and non-Latino and 10.7% were Hispanic or Latino. Overall, 52.2% of subjects were male.
 

 The incidence and severity of solicited adverse reactions that occurred within 7 days following one dose of Prevnar 13 administered to children 15 months through 59 months of age are shown in Tables 7 and 8.



 Table 7: Percentage of Subjects 15 Months Through 59 Months of Age, Previously Vaccinated With 3 or 4 Prior Infant Doses of Prevnar, Reporting Solicited Local Reactions Within 7 Days After One Supplemental Prevnar 13 VaccinationStudy conducted in US NCT00761631 (Study 5). 
                            15 months through 23 months  24 months through 59 months   
 Graded Local Reaction      1 dose Prevnar 133 prior Prevnar dosesN=67-72%  1 dose Prevnar 134 prior Prevnar dosesN=154-184%  1 dose Prevnar 133 or 4 prior Prevnar dosesN=209-238%   
  
 Redness                     
   Any                                26.4                       28.2                       35.4              
   Mild                               18.8                       24.3                       31.1              
   Moderate                           11.4                        7.5                       12.1              
   Severe                              1.5                        0.0                        0.0              
 Swelling                    
   Any                                23.9                       19.6                       20.7              
   Mild                               18.6                       16.4                       17.2              
   Moderate                            8.8                        8.1                        7.5              
   Severe                              0.0                        0.0                        0.0              
 Tenderness                  
   Any                                48.6                       47.3                       62.6              
   Interferes with limb movement             5.9                        6.4                       10.7              
         Table 8: Percentage of Subjects 15 Months Through 59 Months of Age, Previously Vaccinated With 3 or 4 Prior Infant Prevnar Doses, Reporting Solicited Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 7 Days After One Supplemental Prevnar 13 VaccinationStudy conducted in US NCT00761631 (Study 5). 
                              15 through 23 months     24 months through 59 months   
 Systemic Reaction          1 dose Prevnar 133 prior Prevnar dosesN=66-75%  1 dose Prevnar 134 prior Prevnar dosesN=154-189%  1 dose Prevnar 133 or 4 prior Prevnar dosesN=209-236%   
  
 Fever                                                  
   Any                                19.1                       19.9                        8.1              
   Mild                               16.2                       17.4                        7.6              
   Moderate                            6.1                        3.9                        1.9              
   Severe                              0.0                        0.0                        0.5              
 Decreased appetite                   44.4                       39.3                       28.1              
 Irritability                         73.3                       65.1                       45.8              
 Increased sleep                      35.2                       35.3                       18.8              
 Decreased sleep                      25.0                       29.7                       14.8              
              Clinical Trials Experience With Prevnar 13 in Children 5 Through 17 Years of Age  
 

 In a US study (Study 5), the safety of Prevnar 13 was evaluated in children 5 through 9 years of age previously immunized with at least one dose of Prevnar, and in children 10 through 17 years of age with no prior pneumococcal vaccination. In this open label trial, 592 children, including those with asthma, received a single dose of Prevnar 13. The percentage of children 5 through 9 years of age who received 3 and 4 prior doses of Prevnar was 29.1% and 54.5% respectively.



 Most subjects were White (72.8%), 21.8% were Black or African-American, and 1.5% were Asian; 91.4% of subjects were non-Hispanic and non-Latino and 8.6% were Hispanic or Latino. Overall, 51.2% of subjects were male.



 The incidence and severity of solicited adverse reactions that occurred within 7 days following one dose of Prevnar 13 administered to children 5 through 17 years of age are shown in Tables 9 and 10.



 Table 9: Percentage of Subjects 5 Through 17 Years of Age, Reporting Solicited Local Reactions Within 7 Days After Prevnar 13 Vaccination Study conducted in US NCT00761631 (Study 5). 
                         Vaccine Group (as Administered)   
                         Prevnar 13(5 Through 9 Years)  Prevnar 13(10 Through 17 Years)   
 Local Reaction                N              n              %              N              n              %         
  
 Redness                                                                                                            
   Any                        233            100           42.9            232            70            30.2        
   Mild                       226            63            27.9            226            48            21.2        
   Moderate                   218            48            22.0            221            31            14.0        
   Severe                     212             7             3.3            213             4             1.9        
 Swelling                                                                                                           
   Any                        226            85            37.6            233            86            36.9        
   Mild                       220            48            21.8            221            50            22.6        
   Moderate                   219            48            21.9            226            48            21.2        
   Severe                     211             7             3.3            214             4             1.9        
 Tenderness                                                                                                         
   Any                        265            230           86.8            283            252           89.0        
   Significant                221            43            19.5            242            106           43.8        
            Table 10: Percentage of Subjects 5 Through 17 Years of Age, Reporting Solicited Systemic Adverse Reactions Within 7 Days After Prevnar 13 VaccinationStudy conducted in US NCT00761631 (Study 5). 
                         Vaccine Group (as Administered)   
                         Prevnar 13(5 Through 9 Years)  Prevnar 13(10 Through 17 Years)   
 Systemic Event                N              n              %              N              n              %         
  
 Any fever &gt;=38 degrees C       214            13             6.1            214            12             5.6        
 Mild                         212             9             4.2            214            11             5.1        
 Moderate                     212             5             2.4            212             1             0.5        
 Severe                       210             1             0.5            212             1             0.5        
 Decreased appetite           227            52            22.9            223            51            22.9        
 Irritability                 234            73            31.2            234            59            25.2        
 Increased sleep              226            48            21.2            229            61            26.6        
 Decreased sleep              212            12             5.7            224            42            18.8        
 Hives (urticaria)            213             4             1.9            214             3             1.4        
               6.2 Clinical Trials Experience With Prevnar 13 in Adults &gt;=50 Years of Age
   The safety of Prevnar 13 was assessed in 7 clinical studies (Studies 6-12) conducted in the US and Europe which included 90,694 adults (47,907 received Prevnar 13) ranging in age from 50 through 101 years.



 The 47,907 Prevnar 13 recipients included 2,616 adults who were aged 50 through 64 years and 45,291 adults aged 65 years and older. Of the 47,907 Prevnar 13 recipients, 45,991 adults had not previously received PPSV23 ("PPSV23 unvaccinated") and 1,916 adults were previously vaccinated ("PPSV23 previously vaccinated") with PPSV23 at least 3 years prior to enrollment.



     Safety and Immunogenicity Studies  



 Two of the 6 clinical studies supporting safety were randomized comparing the safety and immunogenicity of Prevnar 13 with PPSV23 as a single dose in PPSV23 unvaccinated adults aged 50 through 64 years (Study 6) and in adults &gt;=70 years PPSV23 previously vaccinated (&gt;=5 years prior to enrollment) (Study 7). One study was randomized comparing the safety and immunogenicity of a single dose of Prevnar 13 compared to a single dose of PPSV23 in PPSV23 unvaccinated adults aged 60 through 64 years (Study 8). One clinical safety study (Study 9) of Prevnar 13, conducted in PPSV23 previously vaccinated (&gt;=3 years prior to enrollment) adults aged &gt;=68 years was a single arm study. Two studies, one in the US (Study 10) in adults aged 50 through 59 years and the other in Europe (Study 11) in adults aged &gt;=65 years, evaluated the concomitant administration of Prevnar 13 with trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine (Fluarix    (r)    , A/H1N1, A/H3N2, and B, Fall 2007/Spring 2008: TIV) in these two age groups in PPSV23 unvaccinated adults.



 The total safety population in the 6 safety and immunogenicity studies was 6,198. In 5 of the 6 safety and immunogenicity studies, more females than males were enrolled (50.2% - 61.8%). Across the 6 studies the racial distribution included: &gt;91% White; 0.2%-7.5% Black or African American; 0%-1.7% Asian; &lt;1% Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander; &lt;=1%, American Indian or Alaskan Native. Ethnicity data were not collected in Study 6; in the 5 other studies 0.6%-4.8% were Hispanic or Latino.



 In five studies, subjects with pre-existing underlying diseases were enrolled if the medical condition was stable (did not require a change in therapy or hospitalization for worsening disease for 12 weeks before receipt of study vaccine) except in Study 9 where subjects were enrolled if the medical condition was stable for 6 or more weeks before receipt of study vaccine.



 In the 6 safety and immunogenicity studies, subjects were excluded from study participation due to prior receipt of diphtheria toxoid-containing vaccines within 6 months of study vaccine. However, the time of prior receipt of a diphtheria toxoid-containing vaccine was not recorded.



 Solicited adverse reactions for Prevnar 13 in the safety and immunogenicity studies were monitored by subjects recording local adverse reactions and systemic reactions daily using an electronic diary for 14 consecutive days following vaccination. Unsolicited serious and non-serious adverse events were collected for one month after each vaccination. In addition, serious adverse events were collected for an additional 5 months after each vaccination (at the 6-month follow-up phone contact) in all studies except Study 11.



     Efficacy Study  



 Study 12 was a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled study conducted in the Netherlands in community-dwelling adults aged 65 years and older with no prior pneumococcal vaccination history. A total of 84,496 subjects received either a single dose of Prevnar 13 (42,240) or placebo (42,256) in a 1:1 randomization. Among the 84,496 subjects, 58,072 (68.7%) were &gt;=65 to &lt;75 years of age, 23,481 (27.8%) were &gt;=75 and &lt;85 years of age, and 2,943 (3.5%) were &gt;=85 years of age. In the total safety population, more males (55.9%) were enrolled than females. The racial distribution was 98.5% White, 0.3% Black, 0.7% Asian, 0.5% Other, with &lt;0.1% having missing data.



 Adults with immunocompromising conditions or receiving immunosuppressive therapy and adults residing in a long-term care facility or requiring semiskilled nursing care were excluded. Adults with pre-existing medical conditions, as well as subjects with a history of smoking were eligible for enrollment. In the safety population, 42.3% of subjects had pre-existing medical conditions including heart disease (25.4%), lung disease or asthma (15.1%) and type 1 and type 2 diabetes mellitus (12.5%). Smoking was reported at baseline by 12.3% of the subjects.



 For a subset of 2,011 subjects (1,006 Prevnar 13 recipients and 1,005 placebo recipients), solicited adverse reactions were monitored by recording local and systemic events using electronic diaries for 7 days after vaccination; unsolicited adverse events were collected for 28 days after vaccination, and serious adverse events were collected for 6 months after vaccination. For the remaining 41,231 Prevnar 13 and 41,250 placebo vaccinated subjects, serious adverse events were collected for 28 days after vaccination.



     Serious Adverse Events in Adult Clinical Studies  



     Safety and Immunogenicity Studies  



 Across the 6 safety and immunogenicity studies, serious adverse events within 1 month of vaccination were reported after an initial study dose in 0.2%-1.4% of 5,055 subjects vaccinated with Prevnar 13, and in 0.4%-1.7% of 1,124 subjects vaccinated after an initial study dose of PPSV23. From 1 month to 6 months after an initial study dose, serious adverse events were reported in 1.2%-5.8% of subjects vaccinated during the studies with Prevnar 13 and in 2.4%-5.5% of subjects vaccinated with PPSV23. One case of erythema multiforme occurred 34 days after receipt of a second dose of Prevnar 13.



 Twelve of 5,667 (0.21%) Prevnar 13 recipients and 4 of 1,391 (0.29 %) PPSV23 recipients died. Deaths occurred between Day 3 and Day 309 after study vaccination with Prevnar 13 or PPSV23. Two of 12 deaths occurred within 30 days of vaccination and both deaths were in subjects &gt;65 years of age. One death due to cardiac failure occurred 3 days after receiving placebo. This subject had received Prevnar 13 and TIV one month earlier. The other death was due to peritonitis 20 days after receiving Prevnar 13. The reported causes of the 10 remaining deaths occurring greater than 30 days after receiving Prevnar 13 were cardiac disorders (4), neoplasms (4),  Mycobacterium avium  complex pulmonary infection (1) and septic shock (1).



     Efficacy Study  



 In Study 12 (subjects 65 years and older), serious adverse events within 1 month of vaccination were reported in 327 of 42,237 (0.8%) Prevnar 13 recipients (352 events) and in 314 of 42,225 (0.7%) placebo recipients (337 events). In the subset of subjects where serious adverse events were monitored for 6 months, 70 of 1,006 (7%) Prevnar 13 vaccinated subjects (90 events) and 60 of 1,005 (6%) placebo vaccinated subjects (69 events) reported serious adverse events.



 During the follow-up period (average of 4 years) for case accumulation there were 3,006 deaths (7.1%) in the Prevnar 13 group and 3,005 deaths (7.1%) in the placebo group. There were 10 deaths (&lt;0.1%) in the Prevnar 13 group and 10 deaths (&lt;0.1%) in the placebo group within 28 days of vaccination. There were 161 deaths (0.4%) in the Prevnar 13 group and 144 deaths (0.3%) in the placebo group within 29 days - 6 months following vaccination. These data do not provide evidence for a causal relationship between deaths and vaccination with Prevnar 13.



     Solicited Adverse Reactions in Adult Clinical Studies  



 The incidence and severity of solicited adverse reactions that occurred within 7 or 14 days following each dose of Prevnar 13, PPSV23, or placebo administered to adults in 5 studies are shown in Tables 11, 12, 13, and 14.



 The commonly reported local adverse reactions after Prevnar 13 vaccination in PPSV23 unvaccinated and PPSV23 previously vaccinated adults were redness, swelling and pain at the injection site, or limitation of arm movement (Tables 11 and 12). The commonly reported systemic adverse reactions in PPSV23 unvaccinated and PPSV23 previously vaccinated adults were fatigue, headache, chills, rash, decreased appetite, or muscle pain and joint pain (Tables 13 and 14).



 Table 11 - Percentage of Subjects With Solicited Local Adverse Reactions in PPSV23 Unvaccinated AdultsStudies conducted in US NCT00427895 (Study 6) and NCT00574548 (Study 8) reported local reactions within 14 days. Study conducted in the Netherlands NCT00744263 (Study 12) reported local reactions within 7 days. 
                     Study 6       Study 8       Study 12     
 Age in Years         50-59         60-64         60-64          &gt;=65       
 Local Reaction    Prevnar 13N=152-322%  Prevnar 13N=193-331%  PPSV23N=190-301%  Prevnar 13N=270-370%  PPSV23N=134-175%  Prevnar 13N=886-914%  PlaceboN=859-865%   
  
 Redness                                                                                                              
   Any                 15.8          20.2          14.2          12.2          11.2          4.9           1.2        
   Mild                15.2          15.9          11.2          8.3           9.7           3.7           0.8        
   Moderate            5.0           8.6           4.9           6.4           3.9           1.7           0.3        
   Severe              0.7           1.7           0.0           1.2           0.8           0.5           0.1        
 Swelling                                                                                                             
   Any                 21.7          19.3          13.1          10.0          10.4          6.8           1.2        
   Mild                20.6          15.6          10.1          8.2           6.1           5.5           0.7        
   Moderate            4.3           8.2           4.4           3.8           7.6           2.6           0.6        
   Severe              0.0           0.6           1.1           0.0           0.0           0.1           0.1        
 Pain                                                                                                                 
   Any                 88.8          80.1          73.4          69.2          58.3          36.1          6.1        
   Mild                85.9          78.6          68.6          66.1          52.9          32.9          5.6        
   Moderate            39.5          23.3          30.0          20.1          21.7          7.7           0.6        
   Severe              3.6           1.7           8.6           2.3           0.8           0.3           0.1        
 Limitation of arm movement                                                                                                     
   Any                 40.7          28.5          30.8          23.5          28.2          14.1          3.2        
   Mild                38.6          26.9          29.3          22.7          26.1          12.4          2.5        
   Moderate            2.9           2.2           3.8           1.2           3.1           1.7           0.5        
   Severe              2.9           1.7           4.3           1.1           2.3           1.2           0.7        
             Table 12 - Percentage of Subjects With Solicited Local Adverse Reactions in PPSV23 Previously Vaccinated AdultsStudy conducted in US and Sweden NCT00546572 (Study 7) reported local reactions within 14 days. Study conducted in US, Sweden and Germany NCT00500266 (Study 9) reported local reactions within 14 days. 
                                     Study 7                    Study 9            
 Age in Years                         &gt;=70                       &gt;=68              
 Local Reaction               Prevnar 13N=306-362%         PPSV23N=324-383%         Prevnar 13N=664-777%      
  
 Redness                                                                                                      
   Any                                10.8                       22.2                       14.3              
   Mild                                9.5                       13.5                       12.6              
   Moderate                            4.7                       11.5                        6.5              
   Severe                              1.7                        4.8                        1.1              
 Swelling                                                                                                     
   Any                                10.4                       23.1                       12.8              
   Mild                                8.9                       14.0                       10.9              
   Moderate                            4.0                       13.6                        5.5              
   Severe                              0.0                        4.8                        0.6              
 Pain                                                                                                         
   Any                                51.7                       58.5                       51.0              
   Mild                               50.1                       54.1                       49.4              
   Moderate                            7.5                       23.6                        9.0              
   Severe                              1.3                        2.3                        0.2              
 Limitation of arm movement                                                                                    
   Any                                10.5                       27.6                       16.2              
   Mild                               10.3                       25.2                       14.8              
   Moderate                            0.3                        2.6                        1.6              
   Severe                              0.7                        3.0                        1.6              
         Table 13 - Percentage of Subjects With Solicited Systemic Events in PPSV23 Unvaccinated AdultsStudies conducted in US NCT00427895 (Study 6) and NCT00574548 (Study 8) reported systemic events within 14 days. Study conducted in the Netherlands NCT00744263 (Study 12) reported systemic events within 7 days. 
                     Study 6       Study 8       Study 12     
 Age in Years         50-59         60-64         60-64          &gt;=65       
                   Prevnar 13N=137-248%  Prevnar 13N=174-277%  PPSV23N=176-273%  Prevnar 13N=261-328%  PPSV23N=127-173%  Prevnar 13N=881-896%  PlaceboN=859-878%   
  
 Systemic Event                                                                                                       
 Fever                                                                                                                
   &gt;=38.0 degrees C      1.5           4.0           1.1           4.2           1.6           2.9           1.3        
   38.0 degrees C to 38.4 degrees C      1.5           4.0           1.1           3.8           0.8           1.1           0.6        
   38.5 degrees C to 38.9 degrees C      0.0           0.6           0.0           0.8           0.0           0.6           0.2        
   39.0 degrees C to 40.0 degrees C      0.0           0.0           0.0           0.4           0.8           0.7           0.2        
   &gt;40.0 degrees C      0.0           0.0           0.0           0.0           0.0           0.8           0.3        
 Fatigue               63.3          63.2          61.5          50.5          49.1          18.8          14.8       
 Headache              65.9          54.0          54.4          49.7          46.1          15.9          14.8       
 Chills                19.6          23.5          24.1          19.9          26.9          9.4           8.4        
 Rash                  14.2          16.5          13.0          8.6           13.4          3.3           0.8        
 Vomiting              6.9           3.9           5.4           3.1           3.1           0.3           0.9        
 Decreased appetite      25.3          21.3          21.7          14.7          23.0          5.3           3.7        
 Generalized new muscle pain      61.8          56.2          57.8          46.9          51.5          18.4          8.4        
 Generalized aggravated muscle pain      39.9          32.6          37.3          22.0          32.5          9.1           4.4        
 Generalized new joint pain      31.5          24.4          30.1          15.5          23.8          7.4           5.4        
 Generalized aggravated joint pain      25.6          24.9          21.4          14.0          21.1          5.2           4.2        
             Table 14 - Percentage of Subjects With Systemic Events in PPSV23 Previously Vaccinated AdultsStudy conducted in US and Sweden NCT00546572 (Study 7) reported systemic events within 14 days. Study conducted in US, Sweden and Germany NCT00500266 (Study 9) reported systemic events within 14 days. 
                                     Study 7                    Study 9            
 Age in Years                         &gt;=70                       &gt;=68              
                              Prevnar 13N=299-350%         PPSV23N=303-367%         Prevnar 13N=635-733%      
  
 Systemic Event                                                                                               
 Fever                                                                                                        
   &gt;=38.0 degrees C                    1.0                        2.3                        1.1              
   38.0 degrees C to 38.4 degrees C             1.0                        2.0                        0.8              
   38.5 degrees C to 38.9 degrees C             0.0                        0.0                        0.0              
   39.0 degrees C to 40.0 degrees C             0.0                        0.3                        0.3              
   &gt;40.0 degrees C                     0.0                        0.0                        0.0              
 Fatigue                              34.0                       43.3                       34.4              
 Headache                             23.7                       26.0                       26.1              
 Chills                                7.9                       11.2                        7.5              
 Rash                                  7.3                       16.4                        8.4              
 Vomiting                              1.7                        1.3                        0.9              
 Decreased appetite                   10.4                       11.5                       11.2              
 Generalized new muscle pain            36.8                       44.7                       25.3              
 Generalized aggravated muscle pain            20.6                       27.5                       12.3              
 Generalized new joint pain            12.6                       14.9                       12.8              
 Generalized aggravated joint pain            11.6                       16.5                        9.7              
              Solicited Adverse Reactions in Adult Clinical Studies of Concomitant Administration of Prevnar 13 and TIV (Fluarix)  
 

 The safety of concomitant administration of Prevnar 13 with TIV was assessed in 2 studies in PPSV23 unvaccinated adults aged 50 through 59 years (Study 10) and aged &gt;=65 years (Study 11).



 Frequencies of local reactions within 14 days post-vaccination in adults aged 50 through 59 years and in adults aged &gt;=65 years were similar after Prevnar 13 was administered with TIV compared to Prevnar 13 administered alone, with the exception of mild redness at the injection site, which was increased when Prevnar 13 was administered concomitantly with TIV and mild limitation of arm movement, which was increased when Prevnar 13 was administered alone.



 An increase in some solicited systemic reactions within 14 days post-vaccination was noted when Prevnar 13 was administered concomitantly with TIV compared with TIV given alone (headache, chills, rash, decreased appetite, muscle and joint pain) or with Prevnar 13 given alone (fatigue, headache, chills, decreased appetite, and joint pain).



   6.3 Clinical Trials Experience With Prevnar in Infants and Toddlers

  The safety experience with Prevnar is relevant to Prevnar 13 because the two vaccines share common components.



 Generally, the adverse reactions reported in clinical trials with Prevnar 13 were also reported in clinical trials with Prevnar.



 Overall, the safety of Prevnar was evaluated in a total of five clinical studies in the U.S. in which 18,168 infants and children received a total of 58,699 doses of vaccine at 2, 4, 6, and 12-15 months of age.



 Adverse events reported in clinical trials with Prevnar that occurred within 3 days of vaccination in infants and toddlers and resulted in emergency room visits or hospitalizations, but were not presented in Section 6.1 as adverse reactions for Prevnar 13 are listed below:



 Bronchiolitis, UTI, acute gastroenteritis, asthma, aspiration, breath holding, influenza, inguinal hernia repair, viral syndrome, URI, croup, thrush, wheezing, choking, conjunctivitis, pharyngitis, colic, colitis, congestive heart failure, roseola, sepsis.



   6.4 Post-marketing Experience With Prevnar 13 in Infants and Toddlers

  The following adverse events have been reported through passive surveillance since market introduction of Prevnar 13. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the vaccine. The following adverse events were included based on one or more of the following factors: severity, frequency of reporting, or strength of evidence for a causal relationship to Prevnar 13 vaccine.



   Administration site conditions  : Vaccination-site dermatitis, vaccination-site pruritus, vaccination-site urticaria



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders  : Lymphadenopathy localized to the region of the injection site



   Cardiac Disorders  : Cyanosis



   Immune system disorders  : Anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reaction including shock



   Nervous System Disorders  : Hypotonia



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Angioneurotic edema, erythema multiforme



   Respiratory  : Apnea



   Vascular Disorders  : Pallor



   6.5 Post-marketing Experience With Prevnar in Infants and Toddlers

  There are no adverse reactions reported for Prevnar through passive post-marketing surveillance that were not already reported for Prevnar 13.



 The safety of Prevnar given concomitantly with other vaccines as part of routine care was assessed in a three-year observational study performed at Northern California Kaiser Permanente (NCKP) in which 65,927 children received three doses of Prevnar in the first year of life. Primary safety outcomes analyses included an evaluation of pre-defined adverse events occurring in temporal relationship to immunization. Rates of adverse events occurring within various time periods post-vaccination (e.g., 0-2, 0-7, 0-14, and 0-30 days) were compared to the rates of those events occurring within a control time window (i.e., 31-60 days). Secondary safety outcomes analyses included comparisons to a historical control population of infants (1995-1996, N=40,223) prior to the introduction of Prevnar. In addition, the study included extended follow-up of subjects originally enrolled in the NCKP efficacy trial (N=37,866).



 The primary safety outcomes analyses did not demonstrate a consistently elevated risk of healthcare utilization for croup, gastroenteritis, allergic reactions, seizures, wheezing diagnoses, or breath-holding across doses, healthcare settings, or multiple time windows. As in prelicensure trials, fever was associated with Prevnar administration. In analyses of secondary safety outcomes, the adjusted relative risk of hospitalization for reactive airways disease was 1.23 (95% CI: 1.11, 1.35). Potential confounders, such as differences in concomitantly administered vaccines, yearly variation in respiratory infections, or secular trends in reactive airways disease incidence, could not be controlled. Extended follow-up of subjects originally enrolled in the NCKP efficacy trial revealed no increased risk of reactive airways disease among Prevnar recipients. In general, the study results support the previously described safety profile of Prevnar.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. Decisions about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including Prevnar 13, to infants born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status, and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination. (  5.3  )



 



   5.1 Management of Allergic Reactions



  Epinephrine and other appropriate agents used to manage immediate allergic reactions must be immediately available should an acute anaphylactic reaction occur following administration of Prevnar 13.



    5.2 Altered Immunocompetence



  Individuals with altered immunocompetence, including those at higher risk for invasive pneumococcal disease (e.g., individuals with congenital or acquired splenic dysfunction, HIV infection, malignancy, hematopoietic stem cell transplant, nephrotic syndrome), may have reduced antibody responses to immunization with Prevnar 13 [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ]  .



    5.3 Apnea in Premature Infants



  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. Decisions about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including Prevnar 13, to infants born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
