<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prialt" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:    The most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;= 25%) in clinical trials were dizziness, nausea, confusional state, nystagmus (  6  )



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Jazz Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 890-3098 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates in clinical practice.



 A total of 1254 adult patients received PRIALT as a continuous infusion in acute and severe chronic pain trials with an exposure of 662 patient-years. The mean duration of treatment was 193 days with 173 patients (14%) treated for at least 1 year. The average final dose was 17.6 mcg/day (0.73 mcg/hr).



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;= 25%) in clinical trials were dizziness, nausea, confusional state and nystagmus. Slower titration of PRIALT may result in fewer serious adverse reactions and discontinuation of PRIALT for adverse reactions [  see Clinical Studies (  14  )  and  Dosage and Administration (  2  )  ].



 Adverse reactions during the slow titration placebo-controlled trial that occurred in 5% or greater of patients and more commonly with PRIALT than with placebo are summarized in Table  1  .



 Table 1. Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Slow Titration Placebo-Controlled Trial by Percent (Events That Occurred in &gt;= 5% of Patients and More Commonly with PRIALT than with Placebo) 
  MedDRA System Organ ClassMedDRA Preferred term                     PRIALT     N=112         Placebo     N=108                
  Percentage of Patients                                        
  Any AE                                                        93                   82                                    
  Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                                                                                              
    Vertigo                                                     7                    0                                     
  Eye Disorders                                                                                                            
    Vision Blurred                                              12                   3                                     
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                               
    Diarrhea                                                    18                   15                                    
    Nausea                                                      40                   29                                    
    Vomiting                                                    16                   14                                    
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                     
    Asthenia                                                    18                   6                                     
    Gait Abnormal                                               14                   2                                     
    Pyrexia                                                     5                    3                                     
    Rigors                                                      7                    5                                     
  Infections and Infestations                                                                                              
    Sinusitis                                                   5                    2                                     
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                                       
    Anorexia                                                    6                    2                                     
  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                          
    Muscle Spasms                                               6                    4                                     
    Pain in Limb                                                5                    2                                     
  Nervous System Disorders                                                                                                 
    Amnesia                                                     8                    0                                     
    Ataxia                                                      14                   1                                     
    Dizziness                                                   46                   13                                    
    Dysarthria                                                  7                    0                                     
    Dysgeusia                                                   5                    5                                     
    Headache                                                    13                   11                                    
    Memory Impairment                                           7                    1                                     
    Nystagmus                                                   8                    0                                     
    Somnolence                                                  17                   10                                    
    Tremor                                                      7                    3                                     
  Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                                    
    Anxiety                                                     8                    3                                     
    Confusional State                                           15                   5                                     
    Insomnia                                                    6                    9                                     
  Renal and Urinary Disorders                                                                                              
    Urinary Retention                                           9                    0                                     
  Skin and Subcutaneous Disorders                                                                                          
    Pruritis                                                    7                    7                                     
    Sweating Increased                                          5                    6                                     
           Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Clinical Studies of PRIALT  
 

 The following adverse reactions assessed as related to PRIALT have been reported in 2% or greater of patients participating in the clinical studies:



 EYE DISORDERS: diplopia, visual disturbance



 GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS: abdominal pain, constipation, dry mouth, nausea aggravated



 GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS: fall, fatigue, lethargy, edema peripheral



 INVESTIGATIONS: blood creatine phosphokinase increased



 METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS: appetite decreased



 MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS: muscle cramp, muscle weakness, myalgia, pain in limb



 NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS: aphasia, areflexia, balance impaired, burning sensation, coordination abnormal, disturbance in attention, dizziness postural, dysarthria, dysgeusia, hypoaesthesia, mental impairment, paraesthesia, sedation, speech disorder



 PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS: agitation, anxiety, cognitive disorder, confusional state, depression, depression aggravated, disorientation, hallucination, hallucination auditory, hallucination visual, insomnia, irritability, mood disorder, nervousness, paranoia



 RENAL AND URINARY DISORDERS: dysuria, urinary hesitation



 VASCULAR DISORDERS: hypotension, orthostatic hypotension.



 The following medically important adverse reactions occurred in less than 2% of patients were assessed by the clinical investigators as related to PRIALT: acute renal failure  ,  atrial fibrillation, cerebrovascular accident, sepsis, meningitis, psychotic disorder, suicidal ideation, respiratory distress  ,  rhabdomyolysis, electrocardiogram abnormal, stupor, loss of consciousness, clonic convulsion and grand mal convulsion. Fatal aspiration pneumonia and suicide attempt were reported in less than 1% of patients.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been reported during post-approval use of PRIALT. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: Hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema, serious skin reactions including bullous dermatitis, skin ulcers, skin exfoliation, and burning skin sensation.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: NEUROPSYCHIATRIC ADVERSE REACTIONS

  WARNING: NEUROPSYCHIATRIC ADVERSE REACTIONS

    PRIALT is contraindicated in patients with a preexisting history of psychosis. Severe psychiatric symptoms and neurological impairment may occur during treatment with PRIALT. Monitor all patients frequently for evidence of cognitive impairment, hallucinations, or changes in mood or consciousness. Discontinue PRIALT therapy in the event of serious neurological or psychiatric signs or symptoms.  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: NEUROPSYCHIATRIC ADVERSE REACTIONS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   Severe psychiatric symptoms and neurological impairment may occur during treatment with PRIALT. Do not treat patients with a pre-existing history of psychosis with PRIALT  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Cognitive and neuropsychiatric adverse reactions - Cognitive impairment and severe neuropsychiatric symptoms may occur with PRIALT use (  5.1  ) 
 *    Meningitis and other infections - Patients, caregivers, and healthcare providers must be aware of the signs and symptoms of meningitis, including but not limited to fever, headache, stiff neck, altered mental status (e.g., lethargy, confusion, disorientation), nausea or vomiting, and occasionally seizures. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Reduced level of consciousness - Patients may become unresponsive or stuporous while receiving PRIALT (  5.3  ) 
 *    Elevation of serum creatine kinase - Patients taking PRIALT may experience elevations in creatine kinase. Monitor serum CK in patients undergoing treatment with PRIALT periodically (  5.4  ) 
 *    Withdrawal from opiates: Patients must not be abruptly withdrawn from opiates and must be gradually tapered over a few weeks and replaced with a pharmacologically equivalent dose of oral opiates (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cognitive and Neuropsychiatric Adverse Reactions



  Severe psychiatric symptoms and neurological impairment may occur during treatment with PRIALT. PRIALT is contraindicated in patients with a pre-existing history of psychosis. Monitor all patients frequently for evidence of cognitive impairment, hallucinations, or changes in mood or consciousness. PRIALT therapy can be interrupted or discontinued abruptly without evidence of withdrawal effects in the event of serious neurological or psychiatric signs or symptoms.



 Events of acute psychiatric disturbances such as hallucinations (12%), paranoid reactions (3%), hostility (2%), delirium (2%), psychosis (1%), and manic reactions (0.4%) have been reported in patients treated with PRIALT. Patients with pretreatment psychiatric disorders may be at an increased risk. PRIALT may cause or worsen depression with the risk of suicide in susceptible patients. In placebo-controlled trials, there was a higher incidence of suicide, suicide attempts, and suicide ideations in PRIALT-treated patients than in the placebo group (0.27/patient year for PRIALT patients and 0.10/patient year for placebo patients).



 Management of psychiatric complications may need to include discontinuation of PRIALT, treatment with psychotherapeutic agents and/or short-term hospitalization. Before drug is reinitiated, careful evaluation must be performed on an individual basis.



 Use of PRIALT has been associated with cognitive impairment and decreased alertness/unresponsiveness. The following cognitive adverse reaction rates were reported: confusion (33%), memory impairment (22%), speech disorder (14%), aphasia (12%), thinking abnormal (8%), and amnesia (1%). Cognitive impairment may appear gradually after several weeks of treatment. Reduce the dose of PRIALT or discontinue the use of PRIALT if signs or symptoms of cognitive impairment develop, but other contributing causes must also be considered. The cognitive effects of PRIALT are generally reversible within 2 weeks after drug discontinuation. The median time to reversal of the individual cognitive effects ranged from 3 to 15 days. The elderly (&gt;= 65 years of age) are at higher risk for confusion. [ see   Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )  ]



 There may be additive effects on cognitive impairment and decreased alertness when PRIALT is used in conjunction with other CNS-depressant drugs that may necessitate dosage adjustments.



    5.2 Meningitis and Other Infections



  Meningitis can occur due to inadvertent contamination of the microinfusion device and other means such as CSF seeding due to hematogenous or direct spread from an infected pump pocket or catheter tract. While meningitis is rare with an internal microinfusion device and surgically-implanted catheter, the incidence increases substantially with external devices. In PRIALT clinical trials, meningitis occurred in 3% (40) of patients in the PRIALT group using either internal or external microinfusion devices and 1% (1 case) of patients in the placebo group.



 The risk of meningitis was particularly high in patients with external microinfusion devices and catheters, occurring in 38 out of 41 patients (93%), 37 of whom received PRIALT and one who received placebo.



 Patients, caregivers, and healthcare providers must be particularly vigilant for the signs and symptoms of meningitis, including but not limited to fever, headache, stiff neck, altered mental status (e.g., lethargy, confusion, disorientation), nausea or vomiting, and occasionally seizures. Serious infection or meningitis can occur within 24 hours of a breach in sterility such as a disconnected catheter, the most common cause of meningitis with external microinfusion devices. The patient and health care provider must be familiar with the handling of the external microinfusion device and care of the catheter skin exit site.



 Strict aseptic procedures must be used during the preparation of the PRIALT solution and refilling of the microinfusion device to decrease the risk of introducing contaminants or other environmental pathogens into the reservoir. In suspected cases (especially in immuno-compromised patients) or in confirmed cases of meningitis, CSF cultures must be obtained and appropriate antibiotic therapy must be promptly instituted. Treatment of meningitis usually requires removal of the microinfusion system, catheter, and any other foreign body materials within the intrathecal space and, therefore, discontinuation of PRIALT therapy.



    5.3 Reduced Level of Consciousness



  Patients have become unresponsive or stuporous while receiving PRIALT. The incidence of unresponsiveness or stupor in clinical trials was 2% in PRIALT-treated patients. During these episodes, patients sometimes appear to be conscious and breathing is not depressed. If reduced levels of consciousness occur, discontinue PRIALT until the event resolves, and other etiologies (e.g., meningitis) must be considered. There is no known pharmacologic antagonist for this effect. Patients taking concomitant antiepileptics, neuroleptics, sedatives, or diuretics may be at higher risk of depressed levels of consciousness. If altered consciousness occurs, discontinue other CNS-depressant drugs as clinically appropriate.



    5.4 Elevation of Serum Creatine Kinase



  In clinical studies, 40% of PRIALT-treated patients had serum creatine kinase (CK) levels above the upper limit of normal (ULN), and 11% had CK levels that were greater than three times the ULN. In cases where CK was fractionated, only the muscle isoenzyme (MM) was elevated. The time to occurrence was sporadic, but the greatest incidence of CK elevation was during the first two months of treatment. One case of symptomatic myopathy with EMG findings, and two cases of acute renal failure associated with rhabdomyolysis and extreme CK elevations (17,000-27,000 IU/L) have been reported in PRIALT-treated patients.



 Therefore, monitor serum CK in patients undergoing treatment with PRIALT periodically (e.g., every other week for the first month and monthly as appropriate thereafter). Evaluate patients clinically and obtain CK measurements in the setting of new neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., myalgias, myasthenia, muscle cramps, asthenia) or a reduction in physical activity. If these symptoms continue and CK levels remain elevated or continue to rise, reduce the dose or discontinue the use of PRIALT.



    5.5 Withdrawal From Opiates



  PRIALT is not an opiate and cannot prevent or relieve the symptoms associated with the withdrawal of opiates.



 To avoid withdrawal syndrome when opiate withdrawal is necessary, do not abruptly reduce or withdraw opioid medications.



 For patients being withdrawn from intrathecal opiates or intrathecal opiate infusion, gradually taper over a few weeks and replace with a pharmacologically equivalent dose of oral opiates.



    5.6 Driving and Operating Machinery



  Use of PRIALT has been associated with cognitive impairment and decreased alertness/unresponsiveness. Therefore, caution patients against engaging in hazardous activities that require complete mental alertness or motor coordination such as operating machinery or driving a motor vehicle.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
