<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="priftin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse drug reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of labeling:



 *  Hepatotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity [see  Contraindications (4.1)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Discoloration of Body Fluids [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *   Clostridium difficile -Associated Diarrhea [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Porphyria [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions with regimen for active pulmonary tuberculosis (1% and greater) are anemia, lymphopenia, neutropenia, increased ALT, arthralgia, conjunctivitis, headache, vomiting, nausea, diarrhea, rash, pruritus, anorexia and lymphadenopathy. The most common adverse reaction (1% and greater) with the regimen for latent tuberculosis infection is hypersensitivity reaction. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi-aventis U.S. LLC at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Active Pulmonary Tuberculosis  



 PRIFTIN was studied in a randomized, open label, active-controlled trial of HIV-negative patients with active pulmonary tuberculosis. The population consisted of primarily of male subjects with a mean age of 37 +/- 11 years. In the initial 2 month phase of treatment, 361 patients received PRIFTIN 600 mg twice a week in combination with daily isoniazid, pyrazinamide, and ethambutol and 361 subjects received rifampin in combination with isoniazid, pyrazinamide and ethambutol all administered daily. Ethambutol was discontinued when drug susceptibly testing was known. During the 4 month continuation phase, 317 patients in the PRIFTIN group continued to receive PRIFTIN 600 mg dosed once-weekly with isoniazid and 304 patients in the rifampin group received twice weekly rifampin and isoniazid. Both treatment groups received pyridoxine (Vitamin B6) over the 6 month treatment period.



 Because PRIFTIN was administered as part of a combination regimen, the adverse reaction profile reflects the entire regimen.



 Twenty-two deaths occurred in the study, eleven in the rifampin combination therapy group and eleven in the PRIFTIN combination therapy group. 18/361 (5%) rifampin combination therapy patients discontinued the study due to an adverse reaction compared to 11/361 (3%) PRIFTIN combination therapy patients. Three patients (two rifampin combination therapy patients and one PRIFTIN combination therapy patient) were discontinued in the initial phase due to hepatotoxicity. Concomitant medications for all three patients included isoniazid, pyrazinamide, ethambutol, and pyridoxine. All three recovered without sequelae.



 Five patients had adverse reactions associated with PRIFTIN overdose. These reactions included hematuria, neutropenia, hyperglycemia, ALT increased, hyperuricemia, pruritus, and arthritis.



 Table 2 presents selected treatment-emergent adverse reactions associated with the treatment regimens which occurred in at least 1% of patients during treatment and post-treatment through the first three months of follow-up.



 Table 2: Selected Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions During Treatment of Active Pulmonary Tuberculosis and Through Three Months Follow-up 
                                  Initial Phase        Continuation Phase     
   System Organ ClassPreferred Term      PRIFTIN Combination(N=361)N (%)      Rifampin Combination(N=361)N (%)      PRIFTIN Combination(N=317)N (%)      Rifampin Combination(N=304)N (%)     
  
   BLOOD AND LYMPHATICS                                                                                         
 Anemia                             41 (11.4)           41 (11.4)             5 (1.6)            10 (3.3)       
 Lymphopenia                        38 (10.5)           37 (10.2)            10 (3.2)             9 (3.)        
 Neutropenia                        22 (6.1)             21 (5.8)            27 (8.5)            24 (7.9)       
 Leukocytosis                        6 (1.7)             13 (3.6)             5 (1.6)             2 (0.7)       
 Thrombocytosis                     20 (5.5)             13 (3.6)             1 (0.3)             0 (0.0)       
 Thrombocytopenia                    6 (1.7)             6 (1.7)              4 (1.3)              6 (2)        
 Lymphadenopathy                     4 (1.1)             2 (0.6)              0 (0.0)             2 (0.7)       
 Nonprotein Nitrogen Increased         4 (1.1)             3 (0.8)             10 (3.2)            15 (4.9)       
   EYE                                                                                                          
 Conjunctivitis                      8 (2.2)             2 (0.6)              1 (0.3)             1 (0.3)       
   GASTROINTESTINAL                                                                                             
 Dyspepsia                           6 (1.7)              11 (3)              4 (1.3)              6 (2)        
 Vomiting                            6 (1.7)             14 (3.9)             3 (0.9)              3 (1)        
 Nausea                              7 (1.9)             3 (0.8)              2 (0.6)             1 (0.3)       
 Diarrhea                            5 (1.4)             2 (0.6)              2 (0.6)             0 (0.0)       
   GENERAL                                                                                                      
 Back Pain                          15 (4.2)              11 (3)             11 (3.5)             4 (1.3)       
 Abdominal Pain                      3 (0.8)             3 (0.8)              4 (1.3)             4 (1.3)       
 Fever                               5 (1.4)             7 (1.9)              1 (0.3)             1 (0.3)       
 Anorexia                           14 (3.9)              18 (5)              8 (2.5)              6 (2)        
   HEPATIC &amp; BILIARY                                                                                            
 ALT Increased                       18 (5)              23 (6.4)             7 (2.2)            10 (3.3)       
 AST Increased                      15 (4.2)              18 (5)              7 (2.2)             8 (2.6)       
   MUSCULOSKELETAL                                                                                              
 Arthralgia                         13 (3.6)             13 (3.6)             3 (0.9)             5 (1.6)       
   NEUROLOGIC                                                                                                   
 Headache                            11 (3)              13 (3.6)             3 (0.9)             7 (2.3)       
 Dizziness                           5 (1.4)             5 (1.4)              1 (0.3)             1 (0.3)       
   RESPIRATORY                                                                                                  
 Hemoptysis                         27 (7.5)             20 (5.5)             6 (1.9)              6 (2)        
 Coughing                           21 (5.8)             8 (2.2)              9 (2.8)            11 (3.6)       
   SKIN                                                                                                         
 Rash                               15 (4.2)             26 (7.2)             8 (2.5)             8 (2.6)       
 Sweating Increased                 19 (5.3)              18 (5)              5 (1.6)             4 (1.3)       
 Pruritus                           10 (2.8)             16 (4.4)             3 (0.9)             0 (0.0)       
 Rash Maculopapular                  6 (1.7)             3 (0.8)              0 (0.0)             1 (0.3)       
           The following selected treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported in less than 1% of the PRIFTIN combination therapy patients during treatment and post-treatment through the first three months of follow-up.
 

   Blood and Lymphatics:  lymphocytosis, hematoma, purpura, thrombosis.



   Cardiovascular:  syncope, tachycardia, palpitation, orthostatic hypotension, pericarditis.



   Metabolic &amp; Nutritional:  BUN increased, alkaline phosphatase increased.



   Gastrointestinal:  gastritis, esophagitis, pancreatitis, salivary gland enlargement.



   General:  asthenia, facial edema.



   Hepatobiliary:  bilirubinemia, hepatomegaly, jaundice.



   Infectious Disease:  infection fungal.



   Musculoskeletal:  myalgia, myositis.



   Neurologic:  somnolence, dysphonia.



   Pregnancy, Puerperium and Perinatal conditions:  abortion



   Psychiatric:  anxiety, confusion



   Reproductive Disorders:  vaginitis, vaginal hemorrhage, leukorrhea.



   Respiratory:  dyspnea, pneumonitis, pulmonary fibrosis, asthma, bronchospasm, laryngeal edema, laryngitis.



   Skin:  urticaria, skin discoloration,



 In another randomized, open-label trial, 1075 HIV non-infected and infected patients with active pulmonary tuberculosis who had completed an initial 2 month phase of treatment with 4 drugs were randomly assigned to receive either PRIFTIN 600 mg and isoniazid once weekly or rifampin and isoniazid twice weekly for the 4 month continuation phase. 502 HIV non-infected and 36 HIV-infected patients were randomized to receive the PRIFTIN regimen and 502 HIV-noninfected and 35 HIV-infected patients were randomized to receive the rifampin regimen.



 The death rate was 6.5% for the PRIFTIN combination regimen compared to 6.7% for the rifampin combination regimen.



     Latent Tuberculosis Infection  



     Main Study  



 PRIFTIN in combination with isoniazid given once-weekly for 3 months (3RPT/INH) was compared to isoniazid given once daily for 9 months (9INH) in an open-label, randomized trial in patients with a positive tuberculin skin test, and at high risk for progression from latent tuberculosis infection to active tuberculosis disease. PRIFTIN was dosed by weight, and isoniazid mg/kg dose was determined according to age [  see  Dosing and Administration (2.2)    ] to a maximum of 900 mg each.



 A total of 4040 patients received at least one dose of the 3RPT/INH regimen, including 348 children 2-17 years of age and 105 HIV-infected individuals. A total of 3759 received at least one dose of the 9INH regimen, including 342 children 2 years-17 years of age and 95 HIV-infected individuals.



 Patients were followed for 33 months from the time of enrollment. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions were defined as those occurring during treatment and 60 days after the last dose of treatment. 161 (4%) 3RPT/INH subjects had a rifamycin hypersensitivity reaction, defined as either: a) one of the following: hypotension, urticaria, angioedema, acute bronchospasm, or conjunctivitis occurring in relation to study drug or b) at least four of the following symptoms occurring in relation to the study drug, with at least one symptom being CTCAE Grade 2 or higher: weakness, fatigue, nausea, vomiting, headache, fever, aches, sweats, dizziness, shortness of breath, flushing or chills. No specific definition was used for isoniazid hypersensitivity; 18 (0.5%) 9INH subjects were classified as having a hypersensitivity reaction. Hepatotoxicity was defined as AST&gt;=3* upper limit of normal in the presence of specific signs and symptoms of hepatitis, or AST&gt;5* upper limit of normal regardless of signs or symptoms. 113 (3%) 9INH subjects and 24 (0.6%) 3RPT/INH subjects developed hepatotoxicity.



 196 subjects (4.9%) in the 3RPT/INH arm discontinued treatment due to a treatment related adverse reaction patients and 142 (3.8%) in the 9INH arm discontinued treatment due to a treatment related adverse reaction. In the 3RPT/INH group, the most frequent treatment related adverse reaction resulting in treatment discontinuation was hypersensitivity reaction, occurring in 120 (3%) patients. In the 9INH group, the most frequent treatment related adverse reaction resulting in treatment discontinuation was hepatotoxicity, occurring in 76 (2%) patients.



 Seventy one deaths occurred, 31/4040, 0.77% in the 3RPT/INH group and 40/3759 (1.06%) in the 9INH group) during the 33 month study period. During the treatment emergent period, 11 deaths occurred, 4 in the 3RPT/INH group and 7 in the 9INH group. None of the reported deaths were considered related to treatment with study drugs or were attributed to tuberculosis disease.



 Table 3 presents select adverse reactions that occurred during the treatment emergent period in the main study in LTBI patients treated with 3RPT/INH or 9INH at a frequency greater than 0.5%.



 Table 3 Select Adverse Reactions occurring in 0.5% or greater of patientsIncludes events reported through 60 days after last dose of study drug in the Latent Tuberculosis Infection Main Study 
   System Organ ClassPreferred Term            3RPT/INH(N=4040)N (%)             9INH(N=3759)N (%)          
  
   Immune system disorders                                                                                  
   Hypersensitivity                                   161 (4)                         18 (0.5)              
   Hepatobiliary disorders                                                                                  
   Hepatitis                                          24 (0.6)                        113 (3)               
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                 
   Headache                                           26 (0.6)                        17 (0.5)              
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                     
   Skin reaction                                      31 (0.8)                        21 (0.6)              
             Pediatric Substudy  
 

 Six-hundred and ninety children 2 years-17 years of age received at least one dose of study drugs in the main study. An additional 342 children 2 years-17 years of age received at least one dose in the pediatric extension study (total 1032 children; 539 received 3RPT/INH and 493 received 9INH).



 No children in either treatment arm developed hepatotoxicity. Using the same definition for rifamycin hypersensitivity reaction as in the main study, 7 (1.3%) of children in the 3RPT/INH group experienced a rifamycin hypersensitivity reaction. Adverse reactions in children 2 years-11 years of age and 12 years-17 years of age were similar.



     HIV Substudy  



 Two-hundred HIV-infected patients with latent tuberculosis infection received at least one dose of study drugs in the main study and an additional 193 patients received at least one dose in the extension study (total of 393; 207 received 3RPT/INH and 186 received 9INH). Compared to the HIV-negative patients enrolled in the main study, a higher proportion of HIV-infected patients in each treatment arm experienced a treatment emergent adverse reaction, including a higher incidence of hepatotoxicity. Hepatotoxicity occurred in 3/207 (1.5%) patients in the 3RPT/INH arm and in 14/186 (7.5%) in the 9INH arm. Rifamycin hypersensitivity occurred in only one HIV-infected patient.



 Eleven deaths occurred during the 33 month follow up period (6/207 in the 3RPT/INH group and 5/186 in the 9INH group) including one death in the 9INH arm during the treatment emergent period. None of the reported deaths were considered related to treatment with study drugs or tuberculosis disease.



 Selected treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported during treatment and 60 days post-treatment in less 0.5% of the 3RPT/INH combination-therapy group in the main study are presented below by body system.



   Eye Disorders:  conjunctivitis.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  leukopenia, anemia, lymphadenopathy, neutropenia.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, abdominal pain constipation, dry mouth, dyspepsia, esophageal irritation, gastritis, pancreatitis.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  fatigue, pyrexia, asthenia, chest pain, chills, feeling jittery.



   Infections and Infestations:  pharyngitis, viral infection, vulvovaginal candidiasis.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  hyperglycemia, gout, hyperkalemia, decreased appetite, hyperlipidemia.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  arthralgia, myalgia, back pain, rhabdomyolysis.



   Nervous system Disorders:  dizziness, convulsion, paresthesia, headache, neuropathy peripheral, syncope.



   Psychiatric Disorders:  depression, anxiety, disorientation, suicidal ideation.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  azotemia.



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  vulvovaginal pruritus.



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  cough, dyspnea, oropharyngeal pain, asthma, bronchial hyperactivity, epistaxis.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  rash, hyperhidrosis, pruritus, urticaria.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hepatotoxicity: Monitor for symptoms of liver injury and discontinue PRIFTIN if signs or symptoms or liver injury occur (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypersensitivity: Discontinue PRIFTIN if signs or symptoms of hypersensitivity reaction occur. (  5.2  ). 
 *  Relapse in the treatment of active pulmonary tuberculosis: Do not use as a once-weekly continuation phase regimen with isoniazid in HIV-infected patients. Monitor for signs or symptoms of relapse in patients with cavitary lesions or bilateral disease. (  5.3  ,  14.1  ) 
 *  Drug Interactions: May interact with drugs metabolized by CYP450. (  5.4  ,  7.1  ,  7.4  ) 
 *  Discoloration of body fluids: May permanently stain contact lenses or dentures red-orange. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile -associated colitis: Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Porphyria: Avoid use in patients with porphyria. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatotoxicity



   Elevations of liver transaminases may occur in patients receiving PRIFTIN [ see  Adverse Reactions 6.1    ]. Patients on PRIFTIN should be monitored for symptoms of liver injury.  



  Patients with abnormal liver tests and/or liver disease or patients initiating treatment for active pulmonary tuberculosis should only be given PRIFTIN in cases of necessity and under strict medical supervision. In such patients, obtain serum transaminase levels prior to therapy and every 2-4 weeks while on therapy. Discontinue PRIFTIN if evidence of liver injury occurs.  



    5.2 Hypersensitivity and Related Reactions



   Hypersensitivity reactions may occur in patients receiving PRIFTIN. Signs and symptoms of these reactions may include hypotension, urticaria, angioedema, acute bronchospasm, conjunctivitis, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia or flu-like syndrome (weakness, fatigue, muscle pain, nausea, vomiting, headache, fever, chills, aches, rash, itching, sweats, dizziness, shortness of breath, chest pain, cough, syncope, palpitations). There have been reports of anaphylaxis [ see  Patient Counseling Information (17)    ].  



  Monitor patients receiving PRIFTIN therapy for signs and/or symptoms of hypersensitivity reactions. If these symptoms occur, administer supportive measures and discontinue PRIFTIN.  



    5.3 Relapse in the Treatment of Active Pulmonary Tuberculosis



  PRIFTIN has not been evaluated as part of the initial phase treatment regimen in HIV-infected patients with active pulmonary TB.



 Do not use PRIFTIN as a once-weekly continuation phase regimen in HIV-infected patients with active pulmonary tuberculosis because of a higher rate of failure and/or relapse with rifampin-resistant organisms [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ].  



 Higher relapse rates may occur in patients with cavitary pulmonary lesions and/or positive sputum cultures after the initial phase of active tuberculosis treatment and in patients with evidence of bilateral pulmonary disease. Monitor for signs and symptoms of TB relapse in these patients [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ].  



 Poor adherence to therapy is associated with high relapse rate. Emphasize the importance of compliance with therapy [ see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  



    5.4 Drug Interactions



   Rifapentine is an inducer of CYP450 enzymes. Concomitant use of rifapentine with other drugs metabolized by these enzymes, such as protease inhibitors, certain reverse transcriptase inhibitors, and hormonal contraception may cause a significant decrease in plasma concentrations and loss of therapeutic effect [see  Drug Interactions (7.1  ,  7.2  ,  7.3  and  7.4)    and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].    



    5.5 Discoloration of Body Fluids



  PRIFTIN may produce a red-orange discoloration of body tissues and/or fluids (e.g., skin, teeth, tongue, urine, feces, saliva, sputum, tears, sweat, and cerebrospinal fluid). Contact lenses or dentures may become permanently stained.



    5.6 Clostridium difficile-Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with the use of nearly all systemic antibacterial agents, including PRIFTIN, with severity ranging from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents can alter the normal flora of the colon and may permit overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial use. Careful medical history is necessary because CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, discontinue antibacterial use not directed against C. difficile  if possible. Institute appropriate measures such as fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial treatment of C. difficile,  and surgical evaluation as clinically indicated .  



    5.7 Porphyria



  Porphyria has been reported in patients receiving rifampin, attributed to induction of delta amino levulinic acid synthetase. Because PRIFTIN may have similar enzyme induction properties, avoid the use of PRIFTIN in patients with porphyria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
