<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prilosec" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Adults: Most common adverse reactions in adults (incidence &gt;= 2%) are



 *    Headache, abdominal pain, nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, and flatulence  (6)   
    Pediatric patients (1 to 16 years of age):
 

 *    Safety profile similar to that in adults, except that respiratory system events and fever were the most frequently reported reactions in pediatric studies.  (8.4)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience with PRILOSEC

    Monotherapy  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety data described below reflects exposure to PRILOSEC Delayed-Release Capsules in 3096 patients from worldwide clinical trials (465 patients from US studies and 2,631 patients from international studies). Indications clinically studied in US trials included duodenal ulcer, resistant ulcer, and Zollinger-Ellison syndrome. The international clinical trials were double blind and open-label in design. The most common adverse reactions reported (i.e., with an incidence rate &gt;= 2%) from PRILOSEC-treated patients enrolled in these studies included headache (6.9%), abdominal pain (5.2%), nausea (4.0%), diarrhea (3.7%), vomiting (3.2%), and flatulence (2.7%).



 Additional adverse reactions that were reported with an incidence &gt;=1% included acid regurgitation (1.9%), upper respiratory infection (1.9%), constipation (1.5%), dizziness (1.5%), rash (1.5%), asthenia (1.3%), back pain (1.1%), and cough (1.1%).



 The clinical trial safety profile in patients greater than 65 years of age was similar to that in patients 65 years of age or less.



 The clinical trial safety profile in pediatric patients who received PRILOSEC Delayed-Release Capsules was similar to that in adult patients. Unique to the pediatric population, however, adverse reactions of the respiratory system were most frequently reported in both the 1 to &lt;2 and 2 to 16 year age groups (75.0% and 18.5%, respectively). Similarly, fever was frequently reported in the 1 to 2 year age group (33.0%), and accidental injuries were reported frequently in the 2 to 16 year age group (3.8%) [  see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ].



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience with PRILOSEC in Combination Therapy for  H. pylori  Eradication

  In clinical trials using either dual therapy with PRILOSEC and clarithromycin, or triple therapy with PRILOSEC, clarithromycin, and amoxicillin, no adverse reactions unique to these drug combinations were observed. Adverse reactions observed were limited to those previously reported with omeprazole, clarithromycin, or amoxicillin alone.



   Dual Therapy (PRILOSEC/clarithromycin)  



 Adverse reactions observed in controlled clinical trials using combination therapy with PRILOSEC and clarithromycin (n = 346) that differed from those previously described for PRILOSEC alone were taste perversion (15%), tongue discoloration (2%), rhinitis (2%), pharyngitis (1%) and flu-syndrome (1%). (For more information on clarithromycin, refer to the clarithromycin prescribing information, Adverse Reactions section.)



   Triple Therapy (PRILOSEC/clarithromycin/amoxicillin)  



 The most frequent adverse reactions observed in clinical trials using combination therapy with PRILOSEC, clarithromycin, and amoxicillin (n = 274) were diarrhea (14%), taste perversion (10%), and headache (7%). None of these occurred at a higher frequency than that reported by patients taking antimicrobial agents alone. (For more information on clarithromycin or amoxicillin, refer to the respective prescribing information, Adverse Reactions sections.)



   6.3 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of PRILOSEC Delayed-Release Capsules. Because these reactions are voluntarily reported from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their actual frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body As a Whole:  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, anaphylactic shock, angioedema, bronchospasm, interstitial nephritis, urticaria, (see also  Skin  below); fever; pain; fatigue; malaise



   Cardiovascular:  Chest pain or angina, tachycardia, bradycardia, palpitations, elevated blood pressure, peripheral edema



   Endocrine:  Gynecomastia



   Gastrointestinal:  Pancreatitis (some fatal), anorexia, irritable colon, fecal discoloration, esophageal candidiasis, mucosal atrophy of the tongue, stomatitis, abdominal swelling, dry mouth, microscopic colitis. During treatment with omeprazole, gastric fundic gland polyps have been noted rarely. These polyps are benign and appear to be reversible when treatment is discontinued.



 Gastroduodenal carcinoids have been reported in patients with ZE syndrome on long-term treatment with PRILOSEC. This finding is believed to be a manifestation of the underlying condition, which is known to be associated with such tumors.



   Hepatic:  Liver disease including hepatic failure (some fatal), liver necrosis (some fatal), hepatic encephalopathy hepatocellular disease, cholestatic disease, mixed hepatitis, jaundice, and elevations of liver function tests [ALT, AST, GGT, alkaline phosphatase, and bilirubin]



     Infections and Infestations:  Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



   Metabolism and Nutritional disorders:  Hypoglycemia, hypomagnesemia, with or without hypocalcemia and/or hypokalemia, hyponatremia, weight gain



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle weakness, myalgia, muscle cramps, joint pain, leg pain, bone fracture



   Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Psychiatric and sleep disturbances including depression, agitation, aggression, hallucinations, confusion, insomnia, nervousness, apathy, somnolence, anxiety, and dream abnormalities; tremors, paresthesia; vertigo



   Respiratory:  Epistaxis, pharyngeal pain



   Skin:  Severe generalized skin reactions including toxic epidermal necrolysis (some fatal), Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and erythema multiforme; photosensitivity; urticaria; rash; skin inflammation; pruritus; petechiae; purpura; alopecia; dry skin; hyperhidrosis



   Special Senses:  Tinnitus, taste perversion



   Ocular:  Optic atrophy, anterior ischemic optic neuropathy, optic neuritis, dry eye syndrome, ocular irritation, blurred vision, double vision



   Urogenital:  Interstitial nephritis, hematuria, proteinuria, elevated serum creatinine, microscopic pyuria, urinary tract infection, glycosuria, urinary frequency, testicular pain



   Hematologic:  Agranulocytosis (some fatal), hemolytic anemia, pancytopenia, neutropenia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, leucocytosis
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Symptomatic response does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.  (5.1)   
 *    Atrophic gastritis: has been noted with long-term therapy.  (5.2)   
 *    Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs.  (5.3)   
 *    Cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) Deficiency: Daily long-term use (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption or a deficiency of cyanocobalamin.  (5.4)   
 *    PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea.  (5.5)   
 *    Avoid concomitant use of PRILOSEC with clopidogrel.  (5.6)   
 *    Bone Fracture: Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine.  (5.7)   
 *    Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs.  (5.8)   
 *    Avoid concomitant use of PRILOSEC with St. John's Wort or rifampin due to the potential reduction in omeprazole concentrations. (  5.9  ,  7.3  ) 
 *    Interactions with diagnostic investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors: Increases in intragastric pH may result in hypergastrinemia and enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia and increased Choromogranin A levels which may interfere with diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. (  5.10  ,  12.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Concomitant Gastric Malignancy



  Symptomatic response to therapy with omeprazole does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



    5.2 Atrophic Gastritis



  Atrophic gastritis has been noted occasionally in gastric corpus biopsies from patients treated long-term with omeprazole.



    5.3 Acute Interstitial Nephritis



   Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including PRILOSEC. Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue PRILOSEC if acute interstitial nephritis develops [ see       Contraindications (4)     ].  



    5.4 Cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) Deficiency



   Daily treatment with any acid-suppressing medications over a long period of time (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption of cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) caused by hypo- or achlorhydria. Rare reports of cyanocobalamin deficiency occurring with acidsuppressing therapy have been reported in the literature. This diagnosis should be considered if clinical symptoms consistent with cyanocobalamin deficiency are observed.  



    5.5 Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



  Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like PRILOSEC may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



 Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.



  Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents. For more information specific to antibacterial agents (clarithromycin and amoxicillin) indicated for use in combination with PRILOSEC, refer to WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS sections of those package inserts.



    5.6 Interaction with Clopidogrel



  Avoid concomitant use of PRILOSEC with clopidogrel. Clopidogrel is a prodrug. Inhibition of platelet aggregation by clopidogrel is entirely due to an active metabolite. The metabolism of clopidogrel to its active metabolite can be impaired by use with concomitant medications, such as omeprazole, that inhibit CYP2C19 activity. Concomitant use of clopidogrel with 80 mg omeprazole reduces the pharmacological activity of clopidogrel, even when administered 12 hours apart. When using PRILOSEC, consider alternative anti-platelet therapy [ see  Drug Interactions (7.3)     and     Pharmacokinetics (12.3)    ].



    5.7 Bone Fracture



  Several published observational studies suggest that proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines [ see  Dosage and Administration (2)     and     Adverse Reactions (6.3)    ].



    5.8 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), health care professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)    ].



    5.9 Concomitant use of PRILOSEC with St. John's Wort or rifampin



  Drugs which induce CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 (such as St. John's Wort or rifampin) can substantially decrease omeprazole concentrations [ see  Drug Interactions (7.3)    ]. Avoid concomitant use of PRILOSEC with St. John's Wort or rifampin.



    5.10 Interactions with Diagnostic Investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors



  Serum chromogranin A (CgA) levels increase secondary to drug-induced decreases in gastric acidity. The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. Healthcare providers should temporarily stop omeprazole treatment at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high.  If serial tests are performed (e.g., for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary.



    5.11 Concomitant use of PRILOSEC with Methotrexate



  Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients [ see  Drug Interactions (7.7)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
