<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="primaxin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adults

  PRIMAXIN I.V. is generally well tolerated. Many of the 1,723 patients treated in clinical trials were severely ill and had multiple background diseases and physiological impairments, making it difficult to determine causal relationship of adverse experiences to therapy with PRIMAXIN I.V.



   Local Adverse Reactions

  Adverse local clinical reactions that were reported as possibly, probably, or definitely related to therapy with PRIMAXIN I.V. were:



 Phlebitis/thrombophlebitis - 3.1%



 Pain at the injection site - 0.7%



 Erythema at the injection site - 0.4%



 Vein induration - 0.2%



 Infused vein infection - 0.1%



   Systemic Adverse Reactions

  The most frequently reported systemic adverse clinical reactions that were reported as possibly, probably, or definitely related to PRIMAXIN I.V. were nausea (2.0%), diarrhea (1.8%), vomiting (1.5%), rash (0.9%), fever (0.5%), hypotension (0.4%), seizures (0.4%) (see  PRECAUTIONS  ), dizziness (0.3%), pruritus (0.3%), urticaria (0.2%), somnolence (0.2%).



 Additional adverse systemic clinical reactions reported as possibly, probably, or definitely drug related occurring in less than 0.2% of the patients or reported since the drug was marketed are listed within each body system in order of decreasing severity:  Gastrointestinal  - pseudomembranous colitis (the onset of pseudomembranous colitis symptoms may occur during or after antibacterial treatment, see  WARNINGS  ), hemorrhagic colitis, hepatitis (including fulminant hepatitis), hepatic failure, jaundice, gastroenteritis, abdominal pain, glossitis, tongue papillar hypertrophy, staining of the teeth and/or tongue, heartburn, pharyngeal pain, increased salivation;  Hematologic  - pancytopenia, bone marrow depression, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia;  CNS  - encephalopathy, tremor, confusion, myoclonus, paresthesia, vertigo, headache, psychic disturbances including hallucinations;  Special Senses  - hearing loss, tinnitus, taste perversion;  Respiratory  - chest discomfort, dyspnea, hyperventilation, thoracic spine pain;  Cardiovascular  - palpitations, tachycardia;  Skin  - Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, angioneurotic edema, flushing, cyanosis, hyperhidrosis, skin texture changes, candidiasis, pruritus vulvae;  Body as a whole  - polyarthralgia, asthenia/weakness, drug fever;  Renal  - acute renal failure, oliguria/anuria, polyuria, urine discoloration. The role of PRIMAXIN I.V. in changes in renal function is difficult to assess, since factors predisposing to pre-renal azotemia or to impaired renal function usually have been present.



   Adverse Laboratory Changes

  Adverse laboratory changes without regard to drug relationship that were reported during clinical trials or reported since the drug was marketed were:



   Hepatic:  Increased ALT (SGPT), AST (SGOT), alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin, and LDH



   Hemic:  Increased eosinophils, positive Coombs test, increased WBC, increased platelets, decreased hemoglobin and hematocrit, agranulocytosis, increased monocytes, abnormal prothrombin time, increased lymphocytes, increased basophils



   Electrolytes:  Decreased serum sodium, increased potassium, increased chloride



   Renal:  Increased BUN, creatinine



   Urinalysis:  Presence of urine protein, urine red blood cells, urine white blood cells, urine casts, urine bilirubin, and urine urobilinogen.



   Pediatric Patients

  In studies of 178 pediatric patients &gt;=3 months of age, the following adverse events were noted:



 The Most Common Clinical Adverse Experiences Without Regard to Drug Relationship (Patient Incidence &gt;1%) 
 Adverse Experience                                                 No. of Patients (%)                   
  
   Digestive System                                                                                       
      Diarrhea                                                             7(3.9)                         
      Gastroenteritis                                                     2 (1.1)                         
      Vomiting                                                             2(1.1)                         
   Skin                                                                                                   
      Rash                                                                4 (2.2)                         
      Irritation, I.V. site                                               2 (1.1)                         
   Urogenital System                                                                                      
      Urine discoloration                                                 2 (1.1)                         
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                  
      Phlebitis                                                           4 (2.2)                         
        In studies of 135 patients (newborn to 3 months of age), the following adverse events were noted:
 

 The Most Common Clinical Adverse Experiences Without Regard to Drug Relationship (Patient Incidence &gt;1%) 
 Adverse Experience                                                     No. of Patients (%)               
  
   Digestive System                                                                                       
      Diarrhea                                                                4 (3.0%)                    
      Oral Candidiasis                                                        2 (1.5%)                    
   Skin                                                                                                   
      Rash                                                                    2 (1.5%)                    
   Urogenital System                                                                                      
      Oliguria/anuria                                                         3 (2.2%)                    
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                  
      Tachycardia                                                             2 (1.5%)                    
   Nervous System                                                                                         
      Convulsions                                                             8 (5.9%)                    
       Patients (&gt;=3 Months of Age) With Normal Pretherapy but Abnormal During Therapy Laboratory Values 
 Laboratory Parameter           Abnormality  No. of Patients With Abnormalities/No. of Patients With Lab Done(%)   
  
 Hemoglobin                       Age     &lt;5 mos.:              &lt;10 gm %&lt;11.5 gm %       19/129       (14.7)      
                                          6 mos. - 12 yrs.:                                                       
 Hematocrit                       Age     &lt;5 mos.:              &lt;30 vol %&lt;34.5 vol %     23/129       (17.8)      
                                          6 mos. - 12 yrs.:                                                       
 Neutrophils                                        &lt;=1000/mm  3  (absolute)  4/123                 (3.3)                  
 Eosinophils                                        &gt;=7%  15/117                (12.8)                 
 Platelet Count                                     &gt;=500 ths/mm  3    16/119                (13.4)                 
 Urine Protein                                      &gt;=1  8/97                  (8.2)                  
 Serum Creatinine                                   &gt;1.2 mg/dL  0/105                 (0)                    
 BUN                                                &gt;22 mg/dL  0/108                 (0)                    
 AST (SGOT)                                         &gt;36 IU/L  14/78                 (17.9)                 
 ALT (SGPT)                                         &gt;30 IU/L  10/93                 (10.8)                 
           Patients (&lt;3 Months of Age) With Normal Pretherapy but Abnormal During Therapy Laboratory Values 
 Laboratory Parameter                                      No. of Patients With Abnormalities(%)          
  
 Eosinophil Count?                                                       11 (9.0%)                        
 Hematocrit?                                                              3 (2.0%)                        
 Hematocrit?                                                              1 (1.0%)                        
 Platelet Count?                                                          5 (4.0%)                        
 Platelet Count?                                                          2 (2.0%)                        
 Serum Creatinine?                                                        5 (5.0%)                        
 Bilirubin?                                                               3 (3.0%)                        
 Bilirubin?                                                               1 (1.0%)                        
 AST (SGOT)?                                                              5 (6.0%)                        
 ALT (SGPT)?                                                              3 (3.0%)                        
 Serum Alkaline Phosphate?                                                2 (3.0%)                        
        Examination of published literature and spontaneous adverse event reports suggested a similar spectrum of adverse events in adult and pediatric patients.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
