<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="primsol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    To         report         SUSPECTED         ADVERSE         REACTION    S,         contact    Aytu BioScience    ,         Inc.         at         1 855 AYTU BIO (298-8246)    ,         or         FDA         at    1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



   Adverse         Events         Reported         During         Pediatric         Clinical         T    rials         With         PRIMSOL  :



 The following table lists those drug-related adverse events reported most frequently during the clinical trials in pediatric patients aged 6 months to 12 years. Most of these events were determined to be mild. The incidence of drug-related adverse events was significantly lower for PRIMSOL, which was most apparent for those events related to skin/appendages as a body system.




 Drug-relatedAdverse Event  Percent of Pediatric Patients   
                  PRIMSOL (N=310)  SMX + TMP*(N=197)   
 Body as a wholeabdominal painDigestive systemdiarrheavomitingSkin/Appendagesrash  &lt;14.21.61.3      2.54.61.56.1      
         *sulfamethoxazole + trimethoprim oral suspension
 

 An increase in lymphocytes and eosinophils was noted in some pediatric patients following treatment with PRIMSOL or sulfamethoxazole + trimethoprim oral suspension.



   Adverse         Reactions         Reported         For         T    rimethoprim:  



 In addition to the adverse events listed above which have been observed in pediatric patients receiving PRIMSOL, the following adverse reactions and altered laboratory tests have been previously reported for trimethoprim and therefore, may occur with PRIMSOL therapy:



   Dermatologic reactions:  pruritus and exfoliative dermatitis. At the recommended adult dosage regimens of 100 mg b.i.d., or 200 mg q.d., each for 10 days, the incidence of rash is 2.9% to 6.7%.



 In clinical studies which employed high doses of trimethoprim in adults, an elevated incidence of rash was noted. These rashes were maculopapular, morbilliform, pruritic and generally mild to moderate, appearing 7 to 14 days after the initiation of therapy  .  



   Gastrointestinal         reactions:       Epigastric distress, nausea, and glossitis.  Hematologic         reactions:       Thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, neutropenia, megaloblastic anemia and methemoglobinemia.  Metabolic         reactions:       Hyperkalemia, hyponatremia.  Miscellaneous         reactions:       Fever, elevation of serum transaminase and bilirubin, and increases in BUN and serum creatinine levels.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
