<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="privigen" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions (ARs), as presented below and in  Clinical Trials Experience (6.1),  are defined as adverse events at least possibly related or events occurring during or within 72 hours of a Privigen infusion  or treatment cycle (for ITP).  



    EXCERPT:    *   PI - The most common adverse reactions, observed in &gt;5% of study subjects, were headache, fatigue, nausea, chills, vomiting, back pain, pain, elevated body temperature, abdominal pain, diarrhea, cough, stomach discomfort, chest pain, joint swelling/effusion, influenza-like illness, pharyngolaryngeal pain, urticaria, and dizziness. Serious adverse reactions were hypersensitivity, chills, fatigue, dizziness, and increased body temperature (  6  ). 
 *   Chronic ITP - The most common adverse reactions, observed in &gt;5% of study subjects, were headache, elevated body temperature, positive direct antiglobulin test (DAT), anemia, nausea, epistaxis, vomiting, blood bilirubin unconjugated increased, blood bilirubin conjugated increased, blood total bilirubin increased, hematocrit decreased, and blood lactate dehydrogenase increased. A serious adverse reaction was aseptic meningitis (  6  ). 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

    Primary Humoral Immunodeficiency  



 The most serious adverse reaction observed in clinical study subjects receiving Privigen for PI was hypersensitivity in one subject  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . The most common adverse reactions observed in &gt;5% of clinical study subjects with PI were headache, fatigue, nausea, chills, vomiting, back pain, pain, elevated body temperature, abdominal pain, diarrhea, cough, stomach discomfort, chest pain, joint swelling/effusion, influenza-like illness, pharyngolaryngeal pain, urticaria, and dizziness.



     Chronic Immune Thrombocytopenic Purpura  



 The most serious adverse reactions observed in clinical study subjects receiving Privigen for chronic ITP were aseptic meningitis syndrome in one subject and hemolysis in two subjects  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5    ,    5.6)  ]  . A total of 8 subjects (14%) in the ITP study experienced hemolysis as documented from clinical laboratory data. The most common adverse reactions observed in &gt;5% of clinical study subjects with chronic ITP were headache, elevated body temperature, positive DAT, anemia, nausea, epistaxis, vomiting, blood bilirubin unconjugated increased, blood bilirubin conjugated increased, blood total bilirubin increased, hematocrit decreased, and blood lactate dehydrogenase increased.



   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because different clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.  



     Treatment of Primary Humoral Immunodeficiency  



 In a prospective, open-label, single-arm, multicenter clinical study (pivotal study), 80 subjects with PI (with a diagnosis of XLA or CVID) received Privigen every 3 or 4 weeks for up to 12 months  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  . All subjects had been on regular IGIV replacement therapy for at least 6 months prior to participating in the study. Subjects ranged in age from 3 to 69; 46 (57.5%) were male and 34 (42.5%) were female.



 The safety analysis included all 80 subjects, 16 (20%) on the 3-week schedule and 64 (80%) on the 4-week schedule. The median dose of Privigen administered was 428.3 mg/kg (3-week schedule) or 440.6 mg/kg (4-week schedule) and ranged from 200 to 888 mg/kg. A total of 1038 infusions of Privigen were administered, 272 in the 3-week schedule and 766 in the 4-week schedule.



 Routine premedication was not allowed. However, subjects who experienced two consecutive infusion-related ARs that were likely to be prevented by premedication were permitted to receive antipyretics, antihistamines, NSAIDs, or antiemetic agents. During the study, 8 (10%) subjects received premedication prior to 51 (4.9%) of the 1038 infusions administered.



 Table 2 summarizes the most frequent ARs (defined as adverse events at least possibly related or events occurring during or within 72 hours of a Privigen infusion) that occurred in &gt;5% of subjects.



 Table 2: PI Pivotal Study - ARsExcluding infections. Occurring in &gt;5% of Subjects 
 AR                                         Number (%) of Subjects[n=80]   Number (Rate) of Infusions with AR[n=1038]   
  
 Headache                                            36 (45.0)                      100 (0.096)             
 Fatigue                                             13 (16.3)                       29 (0.028)             
 Nausea                                              11 (13.8)                       23 (0.022)             
 Chills                                               9 (11.3)                       15 (0.014)             
 Vomiting                                             9 (11.3)                       15 (0.014)             
 Back pain                                            8 (10.0)                       15 (0.014)             
 Pain                                                 7 (8.8)                        14 (0.013)             
 Elevated body temperature                            7 (8.8)                        12 (0.012)             
 Diarrhea                                             6 (7.5)                        6 (0.006)              
 Cough                                                5 (6.3)                        5 (0.005)              
 Stomach discomfort                                   5 (6.3)                        5 (0.005)              
         Of the 192 ARs reported (including 5 serious, severe ARs described below) 91 were mild (awareness of sign, symptom or event, but easily tolerated), 81 were moderate (discomfort enough to cause interference with usual activity and may have warranted intervention), 19 were severe (incapacitating with inability to do usual activities or significantly affected clinical status, and warranted intervention), and 1 was of unknown severity.
 

 The five serious ARs (hypersensitivity, chills, fatigue, dizziness, and increased body temperature, all severe) were related to Privigen, occurred in one subject, and resulted in the subject's withdrawal from the study. Two other subjects withdrew from the study due to ARs (chills and headache in one subject; vomiting in the other).



 Seventy-seven of the 80 subjects enrolled in this study had a negative DAT at baseline. Of these 77 subjects, 36 (46.8%) developed a positive DAT at some time during the study. However, no subjects showed evidence of hemolytic anemia.



 During this study, no subjects tested positive for infection due to human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), or B19 virus (B19V).



 An extension of the pivotal study was conducted in 55 adult and pediatric subjects with PI to collect additional efficacy, safety, and tolerability data. This study included 45 subjects from the pivotal study who were receiving Privigen and 10 new subjects who were receiving another IGIV product prior to enrolling in the extension study. Subjects ranged in age from 4 to 81 years; 26 (47.3%) were male and 29 (52.7%) were female.



 Subjects were treated with Privigen at median doses ranging from 286 to 832 mg/kg per infusion over a treatment period ranging from 1 to 27 months. Twelve (21.8%) subjects were on a 3-week treatment schedule with the number of infusions per subject ranging from 4 to 38 (median: 8 infusions); 43 (78.2%) subjects were on a 4-week schedule with the number of infusions ranging from 1 to 31 (median: 15 infusions). A total of 771 infusions were administered in this study.



 In this study, subjects who continued from the pivotal study were permitted to receive infusions of Privigen at a rate up to 12 mg/kg/min (as opposed to the maximum of 8 mg/kg/min allowed in the pivotal study) at the discretion of the investigator based on individual tolerability. Twenty-three (51%) of the 45 subjects from the pivotal study (41.8% of the 55 subjects in the extension study) received 265 (38.4%) infusions at a maximum rate greater than the recommended rate of 8 mg/kg/min  [see  Administration (2.4)  ]  . The median of the maximum infusion rate in this subset was 12 mg/kg/min. However, because the study was not designed to compare infusion rates, no definitive conclusions regarding tolerability could be drawn for infusion rates higher than the recommended rate of 8 mg/kg/min.



 Table 3 summarizes the ARs that occurred in &gt;5% of subjects.



 Table 3: PI Extension Study - ARsExcluding infections. Occurring in &gt;5% of Subjects 
 AR                                      Number (%) of Subjects[n=55]  Number (Rate) of Infusions with AR[n=771]   
  
 Note: The AR rates in this study cannot be compared directly to the rates in other IGIV studies, including the original pivotal study described earlier in this section, because (1) the extension study used an enriched population and (2) the selective use of higher infusion rates at the investigators' discretion in a subset of subjects may have introduced bias.   
  
 Headache                                        18 (32.7)                       76 (0.099)                 
 Nausea                                          6 (10.9)                        10 (0.013)                 
 Elevated body temperature                        4 (7.3)                        12 (0.016)                 
 Abdominal painChest pain                     4 (7.3)3 (5.5)                 7 (0.009)4 (0.005)             
 Chills                                           3 (5.5)                         7 (0.009)                 
 Joint swelling/effusion                          3 (5.5)                         7 (0.009)                 
 Pain                                             3 (5.5)                         6 (0.008)                 
 Fatigue                                          3 (5.5)                         5 (0.006)                 
 Influenza-like illness                           3 (5.5)                         5 (0.006)                 
 Pharyngolaryngeal pain                           3 (5.5)                         4 (0.005)                 
 Urticaria                                        3 (5.5)                         4 (0.005)                 
 Dizziness                                        3 (5.5)                         3 (0.004)                 
         Of the 125 reported ARs, 76 were mild (does not interfere with routine activities), 40 were moderate (interferes somewhat with routine activities), and 9 were severe (impossible to perform routine activities).
 

 Three subjects experienced ARs that were considered to be at least possibly related to Privigen: dyspnea and pancytopenia in one subject, a transient ischemic attack 16 days after the infusion in one subject, and mild urticaria in one subject, resulting in the subject's withdrawal from the study.



     Treatment of Chronic Immune Thrombocytopenic Purpura  



 In a prospective, open-label, single-arm, multicenter clinical study, 57 subjects with chronic ITP and a platelet count of 20 * 10  9  /L or less received a total of 2 g/kg dose of Privigen administered as 1 g/kg infusions daily for 2 consecutive days  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  . Subjects ranged in age from 15 to 69; 23 (40.4%) were male and 34 (59.6%) were female.



 Concomitant medications affecting platelets or other treatments for chronic ITP were not allowed. Thirty-two (56.1%) subjects received premedication with acetaminophen and/or an antihistamine.



 Table 4 summarizes the most frequent ARs (adverse events at least possibly related or events occurring during or within 72 hours after the end of a treatment cycle [two consecutive infusions]) that occurred in &gt;5% of subjects with chronic ITP.



 Table 4: Chronic ITP Study - ARs Occurring in &gt;5% of Subjects 
 AR                                         Number (%) of Subjects[n=57]   Number (Rate) of Infusions with AR[n=114]   
  
 Headache                                            37 (64.9)                       52 (0.456)             
 Elevated body temperature                           21 (36.8)                       23 (0.202)             
 Positive DAT                                         7 (12.3)                       8 (0.070)              
 Anemia                                               6 (10.5)                       6 (0.053)              
 Nausea                                               6 (10.5)                       8 (0.070)              
 Epistaxis                                            6 (10.5)                       8 (0.070)              
 Vomiting                                             6 (10.5)                       7 (0.061)              
 Blood bilirubin unconjugated increased               6 (10.5)                       6 (0.053)              
 Blood bilirubin conjugated increased                  5 (8.8)                        5 (0.044)             
 Blood total bilirubin increased                      3 (5.3)                        3 (0.026)              
 Hematocrit decreased                                 3 (5.3)                        3 (0.026)              
 Blood lactate dehydrogenase increased                3 (5.3)                        3 (0.026)              
         Of the 149 non-serious ARs, 103 were mild (awareness of sign, symptom or event, but easily tolerated), 37 were moderate (discomfort enough to cause interference with usual activity and may have warranted intervention), and 9 were severe (incapacitating with inability to do usual activities or significantly affected clinical status, and warranted intervention).
 

 One subject experienced a serious AR (aseptic meningitis).



 Eight subjects, all of whom had a positive DAT, experienced transient drug-related hemolytic reactions, which were associated with elevated bilirubin, elevated lactate dehydrogenase, and a decrease in hemoglobin level within two days after the infusion of Privigen. Two of the eight subjects were clinically anemic but did not require clinical intervention; these cases resolved uneventfully.



 Four other subjects with active bleeding were reported to have developed anemia without evidence of hemolysis.



 In this study, there was a decrease in hemoglobin after the first Privigen infusion (median decrease of 1.2 g/dL by Day 8) followed by a return to near baseline by Day 29.



 Fifty-six of the 57 subjects in this study had a negative DAT at baseline. Of these 56 subjects, 12 (21.4%) developed a positive DAT during the 29-day study period.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Because adverse reactions are reported voluntarily post-approval from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



     Privigen  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of Privigen. This list does not include reactions already reported in clinical studies with Privigen [see    Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



 *   Infusion reactions: Changes in blood pressure, dyspnea, tachycardia, flushing 
 *   Hematologic: hemoglobinuria/hematuria/chromaturia, renal failure 
 *   Neurological: photophobia 
 *   Integumentary: pruritus, rash 
        General  
 

 In addition, the following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during the post-approval use of immune globulin products.  14  



 *   Infusion Reactions  : Tachycardia, malaise, flushing, rigors 
 *   Renal : Acute renal dysfunction/failure, osmotic nephropathy 
 *   Respiratory : Apnea, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS), TRALI, cyanosis, hypoxemia, pulmonary edema, bronchospasm 
 *   Cardiovascular: Cardiac arrest, thromboembolism, vascular collapse, hypotension 
 *   Neurological: Coma, loss of consciousness, seizures, tremor 
 *   Integumentary: Stevens-Johnson syndrome, epidermolysis, erythema multiforme, bullous dermatitis 
 *   Hematologic: Pancytopenia, leukopenia 
 *   Gastrointestinal: Hepatic dysfunction 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION AND ACUTE RENAL FAILURE

    WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION AND ACUTE RENAL FAILURE  

    *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products1-3, including Privigen. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3), Patient Counseling Information (17)]. 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products in predisposed patients. Patients predisposed to renal dysfunction include those with any degree of pre-existing renal insufficiency, diabetes mellitus, age greater than 65, volume depletion, sepsis, paraproteinemia, or patients receiving known nephrotoxic drugs. 
 *  Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose.4 Privigen does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, renal dysfunction or failure, administer Privigen at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity [see Dosage and Administration (2.3), Warnings and Precautions (5.2, 5.3)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: THROMBOSIS, RENAL DYSFUNCTION AND ACUTE RENAL FAILURE
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including Privigen. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. 
 *  Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products in predisposed patients. Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose. Privigen does not contain sucrose. 
 *  For patients at risk of thrombosis, renal dysfunction or failure, administer Privigen at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  IgA-deficient patients with antibodies to IgA are at greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions (  5.1  ). 
 *  Monitor renal function, including blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine, and urine output in patients at risk of developing acute renal failure (  5.2  ). 
 *  Thrombosis may occur with immune globulin products, including Privigen (  5.3  ). 
 *  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia may occur (  5.4  ). 
 *  Aseptic meningitis syndrome (AMS) may occur, especially with high doses or rapid infusion (  5.5  ). 
 *  Hemolysis that is either intravascular or due to enhanced red blood cell sequestration can develop subsequent to Privigen treatments. Risk factors for hemolysis include high doses and non-O blood group. Closely monitor patients for hemolysis and hemolytic anemia (  5.6  ). 
 *  Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions (transfusion-related acute lung injury [TRALI]) (  5.7  ). 
 *  Carefully consider the relative risks and benefits before prescribing the high dose regimen (for chronic ITP) in patients at increased risk of thrombosis, hemolysis, acute kidney injury, or volume overload (  5.8  ). 
 *  Privigen is made from human blood and may contain infectious agents, e.g., viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent (  5.9  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity



  Severe hypersensitivity reactions may occur [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . In case of hypersensitivity, discontinue the Privigen infusion immediately and institute appropriate treatment. Medications such as epinephrine should be available for immediate treatment of acute hypersensitivity reactions.



 Privigen contains trace amounts of IgA (&lt;=25 mcg/mL) [see  Description (11)  ].  Individuals with IgA deficiency can develop anti-IgA antibodies and anaphylactic reactions (including anaphylaxis and shock) after administration of blood components containing IgA. Patients with known antibodies to IgA may have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions with administration of Privigen. Privigen is contraindicated in patients with antibodies against IgA and a history of hypersensitivity.



    5.2 Renal Dysfunction and Acute Renal Failure



   Renal dysfunction, acute renal failure, osmotic nephrosis, and death may occur with immune globulin intravenous (IGIV) products in predisposed patients. Renal dysfunction and acute renal failure occur more commonly in patients receiving IGIV products containing sucrose.  4  Privigen does not contain sucrose. Ensure that patients are not volume depleted and assess renal function, including measurement of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and serum creatinine, before the initial infusion of Privigen and at appropriate intervals thereafter.  



 Periodic monitoring of renal function and urine output is particularly important in patients judged to be at increased risk of developing acute renal failure.  4  If renal function deteriorates, consider discontinuing Privigen. For patients judged to be at risk of developing renal dysfunction because of pre-existing renal insufficiency, or predisposition to acute renal failure (such as those with diabetes mellitus or hypovolemia, those who are obese, those who use concomitant nephrotoxic medicinal products, or those who are over 65 years of age), administer Privigen at the minimum rate of infusion practicable [see  Boxed Warning    ,   Administration (2.4)  ]  .



    5.3 Thrombosis



   Thrombosis may occur following treatment with immune globulin products  1-3  , including Privigen. Risk factors may include: advanced age, prolonged immobilization, hypercoagulable conditions, history of venous or arterial thrombosis, use of estrogens, indwelling central vascular catheters, hyperviscosity, and cardiovascular risk factors. Thrombosis may occur in the absence of known risk factors.  



  Consider baseline assessment of blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity, including those with cryoglobulins, fasting chylomicronemia/markedly high triacylglycerols (triglycerides), or monoclonal gammopathies. For patients at risk of thrombosis, administer Privigen at the minimum dose and infusion rate practicable. Ensure adequate hydration in patients before administration. Monitor for signs and symptoms of thrombosis and assess blood viscosity in patients at risk for hyperviscosity [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ,  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ].    



    5.4 Hyperproteinemia, Increased Serum Viscosity, and Hyponatremia



  Hyperproteinemia, increased serum viscosity, and hyponatremia may occur following treatment with IGIV products, including Privigen. The hyponatremia is likely to be a pseudohyponatremia, as demonstrated by a decreased calculated serum osmolality or elevated osmolar gap. It is critical to distinguish true hyponatremia from pseudohyponatremia, as treatment aimed at decreasing serum free water in patients with pseudohyponatremia may lead to volume depletion, a further increase in serum viscosity, and a possible predisposition to thromboembolic events.  5  



    5.5 Aseptic Meningitis Syndrome (AMS)



  AMS may occur infrequently following treatment with Privigen [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  and other human immune globulin products. Discontinuation of treatment has resulted in remission of AMS within several days without sequelae.  6  AMS usually begins within several hours to 2 days following IGIV treatment.



 AMS is characterized by the following signs and symptoms: severe headache, nuchal rigidity, drowsiness, fever, photophobia, painful eye movements, nausea, and vomiting. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies are frequently positive with pleocytosis up to several thousand cells per cubic millimeter, predominantly from the granulocytic series, and with elevated protein levels up to several hundred mg/dL, but negative culture results. Conduct a thorough neurological examination on patients exhibiting such signs and symptoms, including CSF studies, to rule out other causes of meningitis.



 AMS may occur more frequently in association with high doses (2 g/kg) and/or rapid infusion of IGIV.



    5.6 Hemolysis



  Privigen may contain blood group antibodies that can act as hemolysins and induce in vivo  coating of red blood cells (RBCs) with immunoglobulin, causing a positive direct antiglobulin test (DAT) (Coombs' test) result and hemolysis.  7-9  Delayed hemolytic anemia can develop subsequent to Privigen therapy due to enhanced RBC sequestration, and acute hemolysis, consistent with intravascular hemolysis, has been reported.  10  Cases of severe hemolysis-related renal dysfunction/failure or disseminated intravascular coagulation have occurred following infusion of Privigen.



 The following risk factors may be associated with the development of hemolysis: high doses (e.g., &gt;=2 g/kg), given either as a single administration or divided over several days, and non-O blood group.  11  Other individual patient factors, such as an underlying inflammatory state (as may be reflected by, for example, elevated C-reactive protein or erythrocyte sedimentation rate), have been hypothesized to increase the risk of hemolysis following administration of IGIV,  12  but their role is uncertain. Hemolysis has been reported following administration of IGIV for a variety of indications, including ITP and PI.  9  



 Closely monitor patients for clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis, particularly patients with risk factors noted above. Consider appropriate laboratory testing in higher risk patients, including measurement of hemoglobin or hematocrit prior to infusion and within approximately 36 to 96 hours post infusion. If clinical signs and symptoms of hemolysis or a significant drop in hemoglobin or hematocrit have been observed, perform additional confirmatory laboratory testing. If transfusion is indicated for patients who develop hemolysis with clinically compromising anemia after receiving IGIV, perform adequate cross-matching to avoid exacerbating on-going hemolysis.



    5.7 Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI)



  Noncardiogenic pulmonary edema may occur following treatment with IGIV products, including Privigen.  13  TRALI is characterized by severe respiratory distress, pulmonary edema, hypoxemia, normal left ventricular function, and fever. Symptoms typically appear within 1 to 6 hours following treatment.



 Monitor patients for pulmonary adverse reactions. If TRALI is suspected, perform appropriate tests for the presence of anti-neutrophil antibodies and anti-human leukocyte antigen (HLA) antibodies in both the product and the patient's serum.



 TRALI may be managed using oxygen therapy with adequate ventilatory support.



    5.8 Volume Overload



  Carefully consider the relative risks and benefits before prescribing the high dose regimen (for chronic ITP) in patients at increased risk of thrombosis, hemolysis, acute kidney injury, or volume overload.



    5.9 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because Privigen is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents (e.g., viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease [CJD] agent). The risk of infectious agent transmission has been reduced by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, testing for the presence of certain current virus infections, and including virus inactivation/removal steps in the manufacturing process for Privigen.



 Report any infection thought to be possibly transmitted by Privigen to CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958 .  



    5.10 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  Various passively transferred antibodies in immunoglobulin preparations may lead to misinterpretation of the results of serological testing.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
