<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="probuphine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

    The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:  



 *  Serious Complications from Insertion and Removal of PROBUPHINE [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Respiratory and CNS Depression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Adrenal Insufficiency [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Opioid Withdrawal [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8.    5.11)  ]  
 *  Hepatitis, Hepatic Events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ]  
 *  Elevation of Cerebrospinal Fluid Pressure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.16)  ]  
 *  Elevation of Intracholedochal Pressure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.17)  ]  
 *  Infection [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.19)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse events commonly associated with PROBUPHINE administration (&gt;10% of subjects) were implant-site pain, pruritis, and erythema, as well as non-implant-site related events (2:5%) of headache, depression, constipation, nausea, vomiting, back pain, toothache, and oropharyngeal pain (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Braeburn at 1-844- 859-6341 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1. Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of PROBUPHINE is supported by clinical trials using PROBUPHINE, and other trials using buprenorphine tablets and buprenorphine sublingual solutions. The safety of PROBUPHINE was evaluated in 349 opioid-dependent subjects across three double-blind trials (n = 309) and two open-label extension studies (n = 40). In these studies, there were a total of 258 subjects exposed to PROBUPHINE for at least 24 weeks and 82 subjects exposed for 48 weeks.



 The safety of the PROBUPHINE insertion and removal procedures has been evaluated in 568 unique subjects across the entire development program who received PROBUPHINE implants or placebo implants, with 507 subjects across the three double-blind trials, 40 subjects from two open- label extension trials, and 21 subjects from two phase 2 pharmacokinetic studies.



 In total, safety data from clinical studies are available from over 3000 opioid-dependent subjects exposed to buprenorphine at doses in the range used in the treatment of opioid dependence.



 Table 1 shows the non-implant-site related adverse events for PROBUPHINE and comparator groups in the three 6-month, double-blind, PROBUPHINE Phase 3 studies. Patients in the PROBUPHINE arm were treated with 4-5 implants and may have received supplemental sublingual buprenorphine. Patients in the Placebo/SL BPN comparator group had either regularly-dosed or as- needed sublingual buprenorphine; some had placebo implants. Adverse events were categorized using the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA, Version 17).



 In Table 1, MedDRA High Level Group Terms (HLGT) reported in at least 5% of patients in the PROBUPHINE group and more commonly than in the comparator group, are listed at the Higher Level Group Term (HLGT) level along with subordinate Preferred Terms (PT) reported in 2: 1% of PROBUPHINE patients (and at least 0.5% more frequent than comparator). Events involving the implant site, or insertion or removal procedures or complications are not included in the table below, but are shown in Table 2.



 Table 1: Adverse events (&gt;= 5% in the PROBUPHINE arm and more than in Placebo/SL BPN) by HLGT and treatment group for phase 3 controlled trials 
 System Organ Class  High Level Group Term    MedDRA Preferred Term       PROBUPHINE(N=309)n (%)         Placebo/ SL BPN(N=317)n (%)      
  
   GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                                                                               
   GASTROINTESTINAL SIGNS AND SYMPTOMS              42 (14)                           39 (12)                
     Nausea                                         20 (6)                            15 (5)                
     Vomiting                                       17 (6)                            11 (3)                
     Abdominal pain upper                           10 (3)                            7 (2)                 
     Flatulence                                     2 (1)                            1 (0.3)                
   GASTROINTESTINAL MOTILITY AND DEFAECATION CONDITIONS               27 (9)                            23 (7)                
     Constipation                                   20 (6)                            9 (3)                 
   DENTAL AND GINGIVAL CONDITIONS                   16 (5)                            12 (4)                
     Toothache                                      14 (5)                            10 (3)                
   GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS                                                                         
   GENERAL SYSTEM DISORDERS NEC                    38 (12)                            26 (8)                
     Pain                                           12 (4)                            9 (3)                 
     Fatigue                                        9 (3)                             4 (1)                 
     Asthenia                                       5 (2)                            1 (0.3)                
     Chest pain                                     2 (1)                               0                   
     Local swelling                                 2 (1)                               0                   
   BODY TEMPERATURE CONDITIONS                      14 (5)                            6 (2)                 
     Pyrexia                                        8 (3)                             4 (1)                 
     Chills                                         5 (2)                             2 (1)                 
     Feeling cold                                   2 (1)                               0                   
   INJURY, POISONING AND PROCEDURAL COMPLICATIONS                                                                         
   INJURIES NEC                                     25 (8)                            23 (7)                
     Laceration                                     8 (3)                             4 (1)                 
     Excoriation                                    6 (2)                             2 (1)                 
     Scratch                                        2 (1)                               0                   
   MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS                                                                         
   MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS NEC               26 (8)                            23 (7)                
     Back pain                                      18 (6)                            15 (5)                
     Pain in extremity                              8 (3)                             3 (1)                 
   NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                                 
   HEADACHES                                       42 (14)                           35 (11)                
     Headache                                      39 (13)                           32 (10)                
     Migraine                                       5 (2)                             3 (1)                 
   NEUROLOGICAL DISORDERS NEC                       25 (8)                            16 (5)                
     Dizziness                                      11 (4)                            7 (2)                 
     Somnolence                                     9 (3)                            1 (0.3)                
     Sedation                                       3 (1)                               0                   
     Paraesthesia                                   2 (1)                               0                   
   PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                                                                                    
   DEPRESSED MOOD DISORDERS AND DISTURBANCES               20 (6)                            13 (4)                
     Depression                                     20 (6)                            10 (3)                
   RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS                                                                         
   RESPIRATORY DISORDERS NEC                       31 (10)                            19 (6)                
     Oropharyngeal pain                             14 (5)                            10 (3)                
     Cough                                          10 (3)                            4 (1)                 
     Dyspnoea                                       3 (1)                            1 (0.3)                
   SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS                                                                         
   EPIDERMAL AND DERMAL CONDITIONS                  16 (5)                            6 (2)                 
     Rash                                           5 (2)                             2 (1)                 
     Skin lesion                                    2 (1)                               0                   
         The following implant site-related adverse events were reported to occur by at least 2% of patients who received either PROBUPHINE or placebo implants in the pooled double-blind, PROBUPHINE Phase 3 studies:
 

 Table 2: Implant site adverse events reported by &gt;= 2% of subjects in the Phase 3 Controlled Trials 
 MedDRA Preferred Term                     PROBUPHINEN=309n (%)  Placebo implantN=198n (%)    TotalN=507n (%)      
  
 Any Implant Site TEAE                           115 (37)              54 (27)               169 (33)         
 Individual Implant Site AE                 
   Implant site pain                             39 (13)                18 (9)               57 (11)          
   Implant site pruritus                         38 (12)                15 (8)               53 (11)          
   Implant site erythema                         32 (10)                13 (7)                45 (9)          
   Implant site hematoma                          20 (7)                15 (8)                35 (7)          
   Implant site hemorrhage                        23 (7)                10 (5)                33 (7)          
   Implant site edema                             16 (5)                5 (3)                 21 (4)          
          The adverse event profile of buprenorphine in a transmucosal form (i.e., sublingual) was also characterized in the dose-controlled study of buprenorphine solution, over a range of doses in four months of treatment. The table below shows adverse events reported by at least 5% of subjects in any dose group in the dose-controlled study.
 

 Table 3: Adverse events reported by at least 5% of subjects in any dose group in the dose- controlled study 
 Body System/Adverse Event (COSTART Terminology)  Buprenorphine Dose   
 Very Low(N=184)          Low(N=180)     Moderate(N=186)     High(N=181)       Total(N=731)     
 N (%)                      N (%)             N (%)             N (%)             N (%)         
  
   Body as a Whole      
 Abscess                    9 (5%)            2 (1%)            3 (2%)            2 (1%)           16 (2%)        
 Asthenia                  26 (14%)          28 (16%)          26 (14%)          24 (13%)         104 (14%)       
 Chills                    11 (6%)           12 (7%)            9 (5%)           10 (6%)           42 (6%)        
 Fever                      7 (4%)            2 (1%)            2 (1%)           10 (6%)           21 (3%)        
 Flu Syndrome               4 (2%)           13 (7%)           19 (10%)           8 (4%)           44 (6%)        
 Headache                  51 (28%)          62 (34%)          54 (29%)          53 (29%)         220 (30%)       
 Infection                 32 (17%)          39 (22%)          38 (20%)          40 (22%)         149 (20%)       
 Injury Accidental          5 (3%)           10 (6%)            5 (3%)            5 (3%)           25 (3%)        
 Pain                      47 (26%)          37 (21%)          49 (26%)          44 (24%)         177 (24%)       
 Pain Back                 18 (10%)          29 (16%)          28 (15%)          27 (15%)         102 (14%)       
 Withdrawal Syndrome       45 (24%)          40 (22%)          41 (22%)          36 (20%)         162 (22%)       
   Digestive System     
 Constipation              10 (5%)           23 (13%)          23 (12%)          26 (14%)          82 (11%)       
 Diarrhea                  19 (10%)           8 (4%)            9 (5%)            4 (2%)           40 (5%)        
 Dyspepsia                  6 (3%)           10 (6%)            4 (2%)            4 (2%)           24 (3%)        
 Nausea                    12 (7%)           22 (12%)          23 (12%)          18 (10%)          75 (10%)       
 Vomiting                   8 (4%)            6 (3%)           10 (5%)           14 (8%)           38 (5%)        
   Nervous System       
 Anxiety                   22 (12%)          24 (13%)          20 (11%)          25 (14%)          91 (12%)       
 Depression                24 (13%)          16 (9%)           25 (13%)          18 (10%)          83 (11%)       
 Dizziness                  4 (2%)            9 (5%)            7 (4%)           11 (6%)           31 (4%)        
 Insomnia                  42 (23%)          50 (28%)          43 (23%)          51 (28%)         186 (25%)       
 Nervousness               12 (7%)           11 (6%)           10 (5%)           13 (7%)           46 (6%)        
 Somnolence                 5 (3%)           13 (7%)            9 (5%)           11 (6%)           38 (5%)        
   Respiratory System     
 Cough Increase             5 (3%)           11 (6%)            6 (3%)            4 (2%)           26 (4%)        
 Pharyngitis                6 (3%)            7 (4%)            6 (3%)            9 (5%)           28 (4%)        
 Rhinitis                  27 (15%)          16 (9%)           15 (8%)           21 (12%)          79 (11%)       
   Skin And Appendages     
 Sweat                     23 (13%)          21 (12%)          20 (11%)          23 (13%)          87 (12%)       
   Special Senses       
 Runny Eyes                13 (7%)            9 (5%)            6 (3%)            6 (3%)           34 (5%)        
              6.2. Postmarketing Experience
   No post-marketing data exist at this time for PROBUPHINE. The most frequently reported post- marketing adverse event observed with buprenorphine sublingual tablets was drug misuse or abuse. The most frequently reported post-marketing adverse event with buprenorphine/naloxone sublingual tablets was peripheral edema.



   Serotonin syndrome  : Cases of serotonin syndrome, a potentially life-threatening condition, have been reported during concomitant use of opioids with serotonergic drugs.



   Adrenal insufficiency  : Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than one month of use.



   Anaphylaxis  : Anaphylaxis has been reported with ingredients contained in PROBUPHINE.



   Androgen deficiency  : Cases of androgen deficiency have occurred with chronic use of opioids  [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: IMPLANT MIGRATION, PROTRUSION, EXPULSION, and NERVE DAMAGE ASSOCIATED WITH INSERTION and REMOVAL

    WARNING: IMPLANT MIGRATION, PROTRUSION, EXPULSION, and NERVE DAMAGE ASSOCIATED WITH INSERTION and REMOVAL  

  EXCERPT:     WARNING: IMPLANT MIGRATION, PROTRUSION, EXPULSION, and NERVE DAMAGE ASSOCIATED WITH INSERTION and REMOVAL  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Insertion and removal of PROBUPHINE are associated with the risk of implant migration, protrusion, expulsion, and nerve damage resulting from the procedure. (5.1) 
 *  PROBUPHINE is available only through a restricted program called the PROBUPHINE REMS Program. (5.2) 
    
 

    Risk Associated with Insertion and Removal  



   Insertion and removal of PROBUPHINE are associated with the risk of implant migration, protrusion, and expulsion resulting from the procedure. Rare but serious complications including nerve damage and migration resulting in embolism and death may result from improper insertion of drug implants inserted in the upper arm.  Additional complications may include local migration, protrusion and expulsion.  



   Incomplete insertions or infections may lead to protrusion or expulsion.     [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]    .  



   Because of the risks associated with insertion and removal, PROBUPHINE is available only through a restricted program called the PROBUPHINE REMS Program. All Healthcare Providers must successfully complete a live training program on the insertion and removal procedures and become certified, prior to performing insertions or prescribing PROBUPHINE implants. Patients must be monitored to ensure that PROBUPHINE is removed by a healthcare provider certified to perform insertions.     [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]    .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Serious Complications from Insertion and Removal : Rare but serious complications including nerve damage and migration resulting in embolism and death may result from improper insertion of drug implants inserted in the upper arm. Additional complications may include local migration, protrusion, and expulsion. Incomplete insertions or infections may lead to protrusion or expulsion. All Healthcare Providers must successfully complete a live training program on the insertion and removal procedures and become certified in the PROBUPHINE REMS program, prior to performing insertions or prescribing PROBUPHINE implants. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse : Buprenorphine can be abused in a manner similar to other opioids. Monitor patients for conditions indicative of diversion or progression of opioid dependence and addictive behaviors. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Respiratory Depression : Significant respiratory depression and death have occurred in association with buprenorphine particularly when taken by the intravenous (IV) route in combination with benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants (including alcohol). Consider dose reduction of CNS depressants when used concomitantly (  5.4  ). 
 *   Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome : Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome (NOWS) is an expected and treatable outcome of prolonged use of opioids during pregnancy. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Adrenal Insufficiency : If diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement of corticosteroids, and wean patient off of the opioid. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Unintentional Pediatric Exposure : In the event an implant protrudes or comes out, keep the implant away from children. Buprenorphine can cause severe, possibly fatal, respiratory depression in children. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Risk of Opioid Withdrawal with Abrupt Discontinuation : If treatment is temporarily interrupted or discontinued, monitor patients for withdrawal and treat appropriately (  5.8  ) 
 *   Risk of Hepatitis, Hepatic Events : Monitor liver function tests prior to initiation and during treatment. (  5.9  ) 
 *   Risk of Withdrawal in Patients Dependent on Full Agonist Opioids: Verify that patient is clinically stable on transmucosal buprenorphineand not dependent on full agonists before inserting PROBUPHINE. (  5.11  ) 
 *   Treatment of Emergent Acute Pain : Treat pain with a non-opioid analgesic whenever possible. If opioid therapy is required, monitor patients closely because higher doses may be required for analgesic effect. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1. Serious Complications from Insertion and Removal of PROBUPHINE



  Rare but serious complications including nerve damage and migration resulting in embolism and death may result from improper insertion of drug implants inserted in the upper arm. Additional complications may include local migration, protrusion, and expulsion.



 Insert PROBUPHINE in accordance with the instructions. [see  Indications and Usage (1)  ,  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ]  . It is essential to insert PROBUPHINE subdermally so that each implant is palpable after insertion. It is also essential to confirm proper placement by palpation immediately after insertion. If PROBUPHINE is inserted too deeply (intramuscular or in the fascia), neural or vascular injury may occur.



 Incomplete insertions or infections may lead to protrusion or expulsion. [see  Dosage and Administration (2.8)  ].  Accidental exposures to PROBUPHINE can result from protrusion or expulsion of the implants. [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ].  



 Improper insertion may lead to complicated removal if the implant is inserted too deeply, is not palpable, or has migrated. Deep insertions may lead to difficulty localizing the implant; additional surgical procedures may be required in order to remove the implant [see  Dosage and Administration (2.6  ,  2.7)  ]  . Injury to deeper neural or vascular structures in the arm may occur when removing deeply inserted implants.



 All Healthcare Providers must successfully complete a live training program on the insertion and removal procedures and become certified in the PROBUPHINE REMS program, prior to performing insertions or prescribing PROBUPHINE implants. There are additional requirements and prerequisites that must be met to become certified to insert PROBUPHINE implants. Only Healthcare Providers who have performed a surgical procedure in the last 3 months and demonstrate competency in the PROBUPHINE procedures at the live training can become certified to perform insertions. Patients must be monitored to ensure that PROBUPHINE is removed by a healthcare provider certified to insert PROBUPHINE implants. [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



    5.2. PROBUPHINE REMS Program



  PROBUPHINE is available only through a restricted program under a REMS, called the PROBUPHINE REMS Program, because of the risk of complications of migration, protrusion and expulsion, and nerve damage associated with the insertion and removal of PROBUPHINE [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



 Notable requirements of the PROBUPHINE REMS Program include the following:



 *  Healthcare Providers who Prescribe PROBUPHINE must be certified with the program by enrolling and completing live training 
 *  *  meet the prerequisite requirements [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  be certified with the program by enrolling and completing live training, including demonstrating competency in PROBUPHINE procedures 
   Healthcare Providers who Insert PROBUPHINE must 
 *  Patients must be monitored to ensure that PROBUPHINE is removed by a healthcare provider certified to insert PROBUPHINE implants 
 *  PROBUPHINE will only be distributed to certified prescribers through a restricted distribution program 
    Further information is available at www.PROBUPHINEREMS.com or 1-844-859-6341  .
 

    5.3. Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  PROBUPHINE contains buprenorphine, a Schedule III controlled substance that can be abused in a manner similar to other opioids. Buprenorphine is sought by people with opioid use disorders and is subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks and the patient's stability in treatment for opioid dependence when determining whether PROBUPHINE is appropriate for the patient. Monitor all patients receiving PROBUPHINE for conditions indicative of diversion or progression of opioid dependence and addictive behaviors.



    5.4. Risk of Respiratory and Central Nervous System (CNS) Depression



  Buprenorphine, particularly when taken by the IV route, in combination with benzodiazepines or other CNS depressants (including alcohol), has been associated with significant respiratory depression and death. Many, but not all, post-marketing reports regarding coma and death associated with the concomitant use of buprenorphine and benzodiazepines involved misuse by self- injection. Deaths have also been reported in association with concomitant administration of buprenorphine with other depressants such as alcohol or other CNS depressant drugs.



 PROBUPHINE should be prescribed with caution to patients taking benzodiazepines or other drugs that act on the CNS, at onset of treatment, regardless of whether these drugs are taken on the advice of a healthcare provider or are being abused/misused. If patients are anticipated to begin taking benzodiazepines or other drugs after beginning PROBUPHINE treatment, healthcare providers should assess the risks and benefits of initiating PROBUPHINE for those patients. Warn patients of the potential danger of self-administration of benzodiazepines or other depressants while under treatment with PROBUPHINE [see  Drug Interactions (7.3  ,  7.4)  ,  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  .



 Use PROBUPHINE with caution in patients with compromised respiratory function (e.g., chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, cor pulmonale, decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  .



 Patients receiving buprenorphine in the presence of opioid analgesics, general anesthetics, benzodiazepines, phenothiazines, other tranquilizers, sedative/hypnotics, or other CNS depressants (including alcohol) may exhibit increased CNS depression. Consider dose reduction of CNS depressants in situations of concomitant prescription [see  Drug Interactions (7.3  ,  7.4)  ]  .



    5.5. Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome (NOWS) is an expected and treatable outcome of prolonged use of opioids during pregnancy, whether that use is medically-authorized or illicit. Unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, NOWS may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated in the neonate. Healthcare professionals should observe newborns for signs of NOWS and manage accordingly [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



 Advise pregnant women receiving opioid addiction treatment with PROBUPHINE of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available [see  Use in Specific Populations 8.1  ]  . This risk must be balanced against the risk of untreated opioid addiction which often results in continued or relapsing illicit opioid use and is associated with poor pregnancy outcomes. Therefore, prescribers should discuss the importance and benefits of management of opioid addiction throughout pregnancy.



    5.6. Adrenal Insufficiency



  Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than one month of use. Presentation of adrenal insufficiency may include non-specific symptoms and signs including nausea, vomiting, anorexia, fatigue, weakness, dizziness, and low blood pressure. If adrenal insufficiency is suspected, confirm the diagnosis with diagnostic testing as soon as possible. If adrenal insufficiency is diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement doses of corticosteroids. Wean the patient off of the opioid to allow adrenal function to recover and continue corticosteroid treatment until adrenal function recovers. Other opioids may be tried as some cases reported use of a different opioid without recurrence of adrenal insufficiency. The information available does not identify any particular opioids as being more likely to be associated with adrenal insufficiency.



    5.7. Unintentional Pediatric Exposure



  Buprenorphine can cause severe, possibly fatal, respiratory depression in children who are accidentally exposed to it. Instruct patients to keep the expelled implant(s) away from others, especially children.



    5.8. Risk of Opioid Withdrawal with Abrupt Discontinuation of PROBUPHINE Treatment



  Buprenorphine is a partial agonist at the mu-opioid receptor and chronic administration produces physical dependence of the opioid type, characterized by withdrawal signs and symptoms upon abrupt discontinuation or rapid taper. The withdrawal syndrome is milder than that seen with full agonists, and may be delayed in onset [see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2  ,  9.3)  ]  . If PROBUPHINE implants are not to be immediately replaced upon removal, maintain patients on their previous dosage of sublingual buprenorphine until PROBUPHINE treatment is resumed [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ].  Patients who elect to discontinue PROBUPHINE treatment should be monitored for withdrawal with consideration given to use of a tapering dose of transmucosal buprenorphine.



    5.9. Risk of Hepatitis, Hepatic Events



  Cases of cytolytic hepatitis and hepatitis with jaundice have been observed in individuals receiving sublingual buprenorphine for the treatment of opioid dependence, both in clinical trials and through post-marketing adverse event reports.



 The spectrum of abnormalities ranges from transient asymptomatic elevations in hepatic transaminases to case reports of death, hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatorenal syndrome, and hepatic encephalopathy. In many cases, the presence of pre-existing liver enzyme abnormalities, infection with hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus, concomitant usage of other potentially hepatotoxic drugs, and ongoing injection drug abuse may have played a causative or contributory role. In other cases, insufficient data were available to determine the etiology of the abnormality. The possibility exists that buprenorphine had a causative or contributory role in the development of the hepatic abnormality in some cases. Liver function tests are recommended prior to initiation of treatment to establish a baseline. Periodic monitoring of liver function during treatment is also recommended.



 A biological and etiological evaluation is recommended when a hepatic event is suspected. Monitor patients with declining hepatic function for side effects resulting from increased exposure to buprenorphine. Patients may require removal of PROBUPHINE implants [see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  ]  .



    5.10. Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Allergic reactions to buprenorphine and/or EVA are possible. Cases of hypersensitivity to buprenorphine sublingual tablets have been reported both in clinical trials and in the post-marketing experience. Cases of bronchospasm, angioneurotic edema, and anaphylactic shock have been reported. The most common signs and symptoms include rashes, hives, and pruritus. A history of hypersensitivity to buprenorphine or EVA is a contraindication to PROBUPHINE use.



    5.11. Precipitation of Opioid Withdrawal in Patients Dependent on Full Agonist Opioids



  Because of the partial opioid agonist properties of buprenorphine, buprenorphine may precipitate opioid withdrawal signs and symptoms in persons who are currently physically dependent on full opioid agonists such as heroin, morphine, or methadone before the effects of the full opioid agonist have subsided. Verify that patients are clinically stable on transmucosal buprenorphine and not dependent on full agonists before inserting PROBUPHINE.



    5.12. Risks Associated with Treatment of Emergent Acute Pain



  While on PROBUPHINE, situations may arise where patients need acute pain management, or may require anesthesia. Treat patients receiving PROBUPHINE with a non-opioid analgesic whenever possible. Patients requiring opioid therapy for analgesia may be treated with a high-affinity full opioid analgesic under the supervision of a physician, with particular attention to respiratory function. Higher doses may be required for analgesic effect. Therefore, a higher potential for toxicity exists with opioid administration. If opioid therapy is required as part of anesthesia, patients should be continuously monitored in an anesthesia care setting by persons not involved in the conduct of the surgical or diagnostic procedure. The opioid therapy must be provided by individuals specifically trained in the use of anesthetic drugs and the management of the respiratory effects of potent opioids, specifically the establishment and maintenance of a patent airway and assisted ventilation.



    5.13. Use in Patients With Impaired Hepatic Function



  In a pharmacokinetic study with sublingual buprenorphine, buprenorphine plasma levels were found to be higher and the half-life was found to be longer in subjects with moderate and severe hepatic impairment, but not in subjects with mild hepatic impairment. The effect of hepatic impairment on the pharmacokinetics of implanted buprenorphine, such as PROBUPHINE, has not been studied.



 Because PROBUPHINE cannot be titrated, patients with pre-existing moderate to severe hepatic impairment are not candidates for treatment with PROBUPHINE. Patients who develop moderate to severe hepatic impairment while being treated with PROBUPHINE should be monitored for signs and symptoms of toxicity or overdose caused by increased levels of buprenorphine, and patients may require removal of PROBUPHINE implants [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12)  ].  



    5.14. Impairment of Ability to Drive and Operate Machinery



  PROBUPHINE may impair the mental or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery, especially for the first 24-48 hours following initial insertion. Caution patients about driving or operating hazardous machinery until they are reasonably certain that PROBUPHINE does not adversely affect their ability to engage in such activities.



    5.15. Orthostatic Hypotension



  PROBUPHINE may produce orthostatic hypotension in ambulatory patients.



    5.16. Elevation of Cerebrospinal Fluid Pressure



  Buprenorphine may elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure and should be used with caution in patients with head injury, intracranial lesions, and other circumstances where cerebrospinal pressure may be increased. Buprenorphine can produce miosis and changes in the level of consciousness that may interfere with patient evaluation.



    5.17. Elevation of Intracholedochal Pressure



  Buprenorphine has been shown to increase intracholedochal pressure, as do other opioids, and thus should be administered with caution to patients with dysfunction of the biliary tract.



    5.18. Effects in Acute Abdominal Conditions



  Buprenorphine may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course of patients with acute abdominal conditions.



    5.19. Infection at Implant Site



  Infection may occur at the site of the insertion or removal. Excessive palpation shortly after insertion of the implants may increase the chance of infection. Improper removal carries risk of implant-site infection.



    5.20. General Precautions



  PROBUPHINE should be administered with caution in debilitated patients and those with myxedema or hypothyroidism; adrenal cortical insufficiency (e.g., Addison's disease); CNS depression or coma; toxic psychoses; prostatic hypertrophy or urethral stricture; acute alcoholism; delirium tremens; or kyphoscoliosis. PROBUPHINE should also be administered with caution in patients with a history of keloid formation, connective tissue disease, e.g. scleroderma, or history of recurrent MRSA infections.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
