<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="procysbi" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are also discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Ehlers-Danlos-like Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Skin Rash [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal (GI) Ulcers and Bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Central Nervous System Symptoms [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Leukopenia and/or Elevated Phosphatase Levels [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Benign Intracranial Hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) are: vomiting, nausea, abdominal pain, breath odor, diarrhea, skin odor, fatigue, rash, and headache. (  6.1  )
 

  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Raptor Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-855-888-4004 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to cysteamine in 328 patients with nephropathic cystinosis (246 patients receiving immediate-release cysteamine as cysteamine hydrochloride or phosphocysteamine, and 63 patients receiving PROCYSBI) in open-label clinical trials.



   Clinical Trials Experience with PROCYSBI  



 Sixty-two patients with cystinosis (38 males and 24 females) received PROCYSBI in two clinical trials at doses ranging from 0.29 grams/m  2  per day to 2.19 grams/m  2  per day  [see Clinical Studies (  14.2  )]  . All patients were switched from immediate-release cysteamine to PROCYSBI. Forty-three patients, ages 7 to 24 years old, received PROCYSBI in an 8-week, open-label, randomized, cross-over trial comparing PROCYSBI to immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate. Forty of 43 patients continued PROCYSBI treatment in an open-label extension trial, and were treated with PROCYSBI for longer than 2 years. An additional 19 patients (6 transplanted patients and 13 patients aged 2 to 6 years) were enrolled directly into this trial and were treated with PROCYSBI for up to 18 months.



 In the open-label, randomized, cross-over trial, a higher incidence of adverse reactions was reported in patients during the PROCYSBI treatment period compared with the immediate-release cysteamine treatment period (see  Table 3  ). Other significant adverse reactions reported during clinical trials included hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis.



 Table 3: Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=5% of patients in the randomized, cross-over clinical trial 
                              Immediate-release cysteamine      PROCYSBI                  
   Adverse Reaction           (n = 41)%                  (n = 43)%                 
    Vomiting/emesis         12                         19                          
    Nausea                  7                          16                          
    Abdominal pain/discomfort  0                          14                          
    Headache                0                          9                           
    Dizziness               0                          5                           
    Anorexia/loss of appetite  5                          2                           
      For all patients treated with PROCYSBI in both trials (N=62), the most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;5%) were vomiting, nausea, abdominal pain, breath odor, diarrhea, skin odor, fatigue, rash, and headache.
 

   Clinical Trials Experience with Immediate-Release Cysteamine  



 The most frequent adverse reactions involved the gastrointestinal and central nervous systems and were especially prominent at the initiation of cysteamine therapy. Most patients were able to resume therapy at lower doses. The most common reactions (&gt;5%) were vomiting, anorexia, fever, diarrhea, lethargy, and rash. Other adverse reactions included nausea, bad breath, abdominal pain, headache, dizziness, and urticaria.



 Withdrawals due to intolerance, vomiting, anorexia, lethargy, and fever occurred more frequently in those patients receiving 1.95 grams/m  2  per day as compared with 1.3 grams/m  2  per day of immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *   Musculoskeletal: Joint hyperextension, leg pain, osteopenia, compression fracture, scoliosis, genu valgum [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )] . 
 *   Skin: Erythema multiforme bullosa, toxic epidermal necrolysis, Ehlers-Danlos-like syndrome, molluscoid pseudotumors, skin striae, skin fragility [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,  5.2  )].  
 *   Central Nervous System: seizures, lethargy, somnolence, depression.and encephalopathy [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )] , benign intracranial hypertension (or PTC) and/or papilledema [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )].  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Ehlers-Danlos-like Syndrome: Reduce dosage if skin and bone lesions occur. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Skin Rash: Discontinue if severe skin rash such as erythema multiforme bullosa or toxic epidermal necrolysis occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Gastrointestinal (GI) Ulcers and Bleeding: Monitor for GI symptoms and consider decreasing the dose if severe symptoms occur. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Central Nervous System (CNS) Symptoms: Monitor for CNS symptoms; interrupt or reduce the dose for severe symptoms or those that persist or progress (  5.4  ). 
 *   Leukopenia and/or Elevated Alkaline Phosphatase Levels: Monitor white blood cell count and alkaline phosphatase levels; decrease or discontinue the dose until values revert to normal. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Benign Intracranial Hypertension: Monitor for signs and symptoms; interrupt or reduce the dose for signs/symptoms that persist, or discontinue if diagnosis is confirmed. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Ehlers-Danlos-like Syndrome



  Skin and bone lesions that resemble clinical findings for Ehlers-Danlos-like syndrome have been reported in patients treated with high doses of immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate or other cysteamine salts. These include molluscoid pseudotumors (purplish hemorrhagic lesions), skin striae, bone lesions (including osteopenia, compression fractures, scoliosis and genu valgum), leg pain, and joint hyperextension. One patient on immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate with serious skin lesions subsequently died of acute cerebral ischemia with marked vasculopathy. Monitor patients for development of skin or bone lesions and interrupt PROCYSBI dosing if patients develop these lesions. PROCYSBI may be restarted at a lower dose under close supervision, then slowly increase to the appropriate therapeutic dose [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  .



    5.2 Skin Rash



  Severe skin rashes such as erythema multiforme bullosa or toxic epidermal necrolysis have been reported in patients receiving immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate. If severe skin rashes develop, permanently discontinue use of PROCYSBI [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



    5.3 Gastrointestinal Ulcers and Bleeding



  Gastrointestinal (GI) ulceration and bleeding have been reported in patients receiving immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate. GI tract symptoms including nausea, vomiting, anorexia and abdominal pain, sometimes severe, have been associated with cysteamine. If severe GI tract symptoms develop, consider decreasing the dose of PROCYSBI [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  .



    5.4 Central Nervous System Symptoms



  Central Nervous System (CNS) symptoms such as seizures, lethargy, somnolence, depression, and encephalopathy have been associated with immediate-release cysteamine. Neurological complications have also been described in some patients with cystinosis who have not been treated with cysteamine. Carefully evaluate and monitor patients who develop CNS symptoms. Interrupt medication or adjust the dose as necessary for patients with severe symptoms or with symptoms that persist or progress. Inform patients that PROCYSBI may impair their ability to perform tasks such as driving or operating machinery.



    5.5 Leukopenia and/or Elevated Alkaline Phosphatase Levels



  Cysteamine has been associated with reversible leukopenia and elevated alkaline phosphatase levels. Monitor white blood cell counts and alkaline phosphatase levels. If tests values remain elevated, consider decreasing the dose or discontinuing the drug until values revert to normal.



    5.6 Benign Intracranial Hypertension



  Benign intracranial hypertension (pseudotumor cerebri; PTC) and/or papilledema have been reported in patients receiving immediate-release cysteamine bitartrate treatment. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of PTC, including headache, tinnitus, dizziness, nausea, diplopia, blurry vision, loss of vision, pain behind the eye or pain with eye movement. If signs/symptoms persist, interrupt dosing or decrease the dose and refer the patient to an ophthalmologist. If the diagnosis is confirmed, permanently discontinue use of PROCYSBI.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
