<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prograf0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious and otherwise important adverse drug reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of labeling:



 *    Lymphoma and Other Malignancies [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.2  )]  
 *    Serious Infections [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.3  )]  
 *    Polyoma Virus Infections [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  )]  
 *    CMV Infections [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.5  )]  
 *    New Onset Diabetes After Transplant [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.6  )]  
 *    Nephrotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.7  )]  
 *    Neurotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.8  )]  
 *    Hyperkalemia [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.9  )]  
 *    Hypertension [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.10  )]  
 *    Anaphylaxis with Prograf Injection [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.11  )]  
 *    Myocardial Hypertrophy [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.15  )]  
 *    Pure Red Cell Aplasia [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.17  )]  
 *    Gastrointestinal Perforation [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.18  )]  
   *    Kidney Transplant: The most common adverse reactions ( &gt;= 30%) were infection, tremor, hypertension, abnormal renal function, constipation, diarrhea, headache, abdominal pain, insomnia, nausea, hypomagnesemia, urinary tract infection, hypophosphatemia, peripheral edema, asthenia, pain, hyperlipidemia, hyperkalemia, anemia (  6.1  ) 
 *    Liver Transplant: The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 40%) were tremor, headache, diarrhea, hypertension, nausea, abnormal renal function, abdominal pain, insomnia, paresthesia, anemia, pain, fever, asthenia, hyperkalemia, hypomagnesemia, and hyperglycemia (  6.1  ) 
 *    Heart Transplant: The most common adverse reactions ( &gt;= 15%) were abnormal renal function, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, CMV infection, tremor, hyperglycemia, leukopenia, infection, anemia, bronchitis, pericardial effusion, urinary tract infection and hyperlipemia (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Astellas Pharma US, Inc at 1-800-727-7003 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. In addition, the clinical trials were not designed to establish comparative differences across study arms with regards to the adverse reactions discussed below.



   Kidney Transplant  



 The incidence of adverse reactions was determined in three randomized kidney transplant trials. One of the trials used azathioprine (AZA) and corticosteroids and two of the trials used mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) and corticosteroids concomitantly for maintenance immunosuppression.



 Prograf-based immunosuppression in conjunction with azathioprine and corticosteroids following kidney transplantation was assessed in trial where 205 patients received Prograf based immunosuppression and 207 patients received cyclosporine based immunosuppression. The trial population had a mean age of 43 years (mean+/-sd was 43+/-13 years on Prograf and 44+/-12 years on cyclosporine arm), the distribution was 61% male, and the composition was White (58%), Black (25%), Hispanic (12%) and Other (5%). The 12 month post-transplant information from this trial is presented below.



 The most common adverse reactions ( &gt;= 30%) observed in Prograf-treated kidney transplant patients are: infection, tremor, hypertension, abnormal renal function, constipation, diarrhea, headache, abdominal pain, insomnia, nausea, hypomagnesemia, urinary tract infection, hypophosphatemia, peripheral edema, asthenia, pain, hyperlipidemia, hyperkalemia and anemia.



 Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 15% of kidney transplant patients treated with Prograf in conjunction with azathioprine are presented below:



 Table 4. Kidney Transplantation: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 15% of Patients Treated with Prograf in Conjunction with Azathioprine (AZA) 
                                                         Prograf/AZA  (N=205)    Cyclosporine/AZA(N=207)     
  Nervous System                                                                                            
  Tremor  Headache  Insomnia  Paresthesia  Dizziness     54%  44%  32%  23%  19%    34%  38%  30%  16%  16%     
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                          
  Diarrhea  Nausea  Constipation  Vomiting  Dyspepsia    44%  38%  35%  29%  28%    41%  36%  43%  23%  20%     
  Cardiovascular                                                                                            
  Hypertension  Chest Pain                               50%  19%               52%  13%                    
  Urogenital                                                                                                
  Creatinine Increased  Urinary Tract Infection          45%  34%               42%  35%                    
  Metabolic and Nutritional                                                                                 
  Hypophosphatemia  Hypomagnesemia  Hyperlipemia  Hyperkalemia  Diabetes Mellitus  Hypokalemia  Hyperglycemia  Edema    49%  34%  31%  31%  24%  22%  22%  18%    53%  17%  38%  32%  9%  25%  16%  19%    
  Hemic and Lymphatic                                                                                       
  Anemia  Leukopenia                                     30%  15%               24%  17%                    
  Miscellaneous                                                                                             
  Infection  Peripheral Edema  Asthenia  Abdominal Pain  Pain  Fever  Back Pain    45%  36%  34%  33%  32%  29%  24%    49%  48%  30%  31%  30%  29%  20%    
  Respiratory System                                                                                        
  Dyspnea  Cough Increased                               22%  18%               18%  15%                    
  Musculoskeletal                                                                                           
  Arthralgia                                             25%                    24%                         
  Skin                                                                                                      
  Rash  Pruritus                                         17%  15%               12%  7%                     
         Two trials were conducted for Prograf-based immunosuppression in conjunction with MMF and corticosteroids. In the non-US trial (Study 1), the incidence of adverse reactions was based on 1195 kidney transplant patients that received Prograf (Group C, n=403), or one of two cyclosporine (CsA) regimens (Group A, n=384 and Group B, n=408) in combination with MMF and corticosteroids; all patients, except those in one of the two cyclosporine groups, also received induction with daclizumab. The trial population had a mean age of 46 years (range 17 to 76), the distribution was 65% male, and the composition was 93% Caucasian. The 12 month post-transplant information from this trial is presented below.
 

 Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 10% of kidney transplant patients treated with Prograf in conjunction with MMF in Study 1 [Note: This trial was conducted entirely outside of the United States. Such trials often report a lower incidence of adverse reactions in comparison to U.S. trials] are presented below:



 Table 5. Kidney Transplantation: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 10% of Patients Treated with Prograf in Conjunction with MMF (Study 1) 
 Key: Group A = CsA/MMF/CS, B = CsA/MMF/CS/Daclizumab, C= Tac/MMF/CS/DaclizumabCsA= Cyclosporine, CS = Corticosteroids, Tac = Tacrolimus, MMF = mycophenolate mofetil   
  
                                                            Prograf(Group C)    Cyclosporine(Group A)    Cyclosporine(Group B)    
                                                            (N=403)       (N=384)            (N=408)          
  Diarrhea                                                  25%           16%                13%              
  Urinary Tract Infection                                   24%           28%                24%              
  Anemia                                                    17%           19%                17%              
  Hypertension                                              13%           14%                12%              
  Leukopenia                                                13%           10%                10%              
  Edema Peripheral                                          11%           12%                13%              
  Hyperlipidemia                                            10%           15%                13%              
          In the U.S. trial (Study 2) with Prograf-based immunosuppression in conjunction with MMF and corticosteroids, 424 kidney transplant patients received Prograf (n=212) or cyclosporine (n=212) in combination with MMF 1 gram twice daily, basiliximab induction, and corticosteroids. The trial population had a mean age of 48 years (range 17 to 77), the distribution was 63% male, and the composition was White (74%), Black (20%), Asian (3%) and other (3%). The 12 month post-transplant information from this trial is presented below.
 

 Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=15% of kidney transplant patients treated with Prograf in conjunction with MMF in Study 2 are presented below:



 Table 6. Kidney Transplantation: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 15% of Patients Treated with Prograf in Conjunction with MMF (Study 2) 
                                                                Prograf/MMF         Cyclosporine/MMF        
                                                                (N=212)             (N=212)                 
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                
  Diarrhea                                                      44%                 26%                     
  Nausea                                                        39%                 47%                     
  Constipation                                                  36%                 41%                     
  Vomiting                                                      26%                 25%                     
  Dyspepsia                                                     18%                 15%                     
                                                                                                            
  Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications                                                           
  Post-Procedural Pain                                          29%                 27%                     
  Incision Site Complication                                    28%                 23%                     
  Graft Dysfunction                                             24%                 18%                     
                                                                                                            
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                        
  Hypomagnesemia                                                28%                 22%                     
  Hypophosphatemia                                              28%                 21%                     
  Hyperkalemia                                                  26%                 19%                     
  Hyperglycemia                                                 21%                 15%                     
  Hyperlipidemia                                                18%                 25%                     
  Hypokalemia                                                   16%                 18%                     
                                                                                                            
  Nervous System Disorders                                                                                  
  Tremor                                                        34%                 20%                     
  Headache                                                      24%                 25%                     
                                                                                                            
  Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders                                                                      
  Anemia                                                        30%                 28%                     
  Leukopenia                                                    16%                 12%                     
                                                                                                            
  Miscellaneous                                                                                             
  Edema Peripheral                                              35%                 46%                     
  Hypertension                                                  32%                 35%                     
  Insomnia                                                      30%                 21%                     
  Urinary Tract Infection                                       26%                 22%                     
  Blood Creatinine Increased                                    23%                 23%                     
         Less frequently observed adverse reactions in both liver transplantation and kidney transplantation patients are described under the subsection  Less Frequently Reported Adverse Reactions  .  Liver Transplantation  
 

 There were two randomized comparative liver transplant trials. In the U.S. trial, 263 adult and pediatric patients received tacrolimus and steroids and 266 patients received cyclosporine-based immunosuppressive regimen (CsA/AZA). The trial population had a mean age of 44 years (range 0.4 to70), the distribution was 52% male, and the composition was White (78%), Black (5%), Asian (2%), Hispanic (13%) and Other (2%). In the European trial, 270 patients received tacrolimus and steroids and 275 patients received CsA/AZA. The trial population had a mean age of 46 years (range 15 to 68), the distribution was 59% male, and the composition was White (95.4%), Black (1%), Asian (2%) and Other (2%).



 The proportion of patients reporting more than one adverse event was &gt; 99% in both the tacrolimus group and the CsA/AZA group. Precautions must be taken when comparing the incidence of adverse reactions in the U.S. trial to that in the European trial. The 12-month post-transplant information from the U.S. trial and from the European trial is presented below. The two trials also included different patient populations and patients were treated with immunosuppressive regimens of differing intensities. Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=15% in tacrolimus patients (combined trial results) are presented below for the two controlled trials in liver transplantation.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 40%) observed in Prograf-treated liver transplant patients are: tremor, headache, diarrhea, hypertension, nausea, abnormal renal function, abdominal pain, insomnia, paresthesia, anemia, pain, fever, asthenia, hyperkalemia, hypomagnesemia, and hyperglycemia. These all occur with oral and IV administration of Prograf and some may respond to a reduction in dosing (e.g., tremor, headache, paresthesia, hypertension). Diarrhea was sometimes associated with other gastrointestinal complaints such as nausea and vomiting.



 Table 7. Liver Transplantation: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 15% of Patients Treated with Prograf 
                         U.S. TRIAL             EUROPEAN TRIAL        
  Prograf  (N=250)       Cyclosporine/AZA(N=250)    Prograf  (N=264)      Cyclosporine/AZA(N=265)    
  Nervous System                                                                                                
  Headache  Insomnia  Tremor  Paresthesia    64%  64%  56%  40%     60%  68%  46%  30%    37%  32%  48%  17%    26%  23%  32%  17%    
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                              
  Diarrhea  Nausea  LFT Abnormal  Anorexia  Vomiting  Constipation    72%  46%  36%  34%  27%  24%    47%  37%  30%  24%  15%  27%    37%  32%  6%  7%  14%  23%    27%  27%  5%  5%  11%  21%    
  Cardiovascular                                                                                                
  Hypertension           47%                    56%                   38%                  43%                  
  Urogenital                                                                                                    
  Kidney Function Abnormal    40%                    27%                   36%                  23%                  
  Creatinine Increased    39%                    25%                   24%                  19%                  
  BUN Increased          30%                    22%                   12%                  9%                   
  Oliguria               18%                    15%                   19%                  12%                  
  Urinary Tract Infection    16%                    18%                   21%                  19%                  
  Metabolic and Nutritional                                                                                           
  Hypomagnesemia  Hyperglycemia  Hyperkalemia  Hypokalemia    48%  47%  45%  29%     45%  38%  26%  34%    16%  33%  13%  13%    9%  22%  9%  16%     
  Hemic and Lymphatic                                                                                           
  Anemia  Leukocytosis  Thrombocytopenia    47%  32%  24%          38%  26%  20%         5%  8%  14%          1%  8%  19%          
  Miscellaneous                                                                                                 
  Pain  Abdominal Pain  Asthenia  Fever  Back Pain  Ascites  Peripheral Edema    63%  59%  52%  48%  30%  27%  26%    57%  54%  48%  56%  29%  22%  26%    24%  29%  11%  19%  17%  7%  12%    22%  22%  7%  22%  17%  8%  14%    
  Respiratory System                                                                                            
  Pleural Effusion  Dyspnea  Atelectasis    30%  29%  28%          32%  23%  30%         36%  5%  5%          35%  4%  4%          
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                           
  Pruritus  Rash         36%  24%               20%  19%              15%  10%             7%  4%               
           Less frequently observed adverse reactions in both liver transplantation and kidney transplantation patients are described under the subsection  Less Frequently Reported Adverse Reactions  .  Heart Transplantation  
 

 The incidence of adverse reactions was determined based on two trials in primary orthotopic heart transplantation. In a trial conducted in Europe, 314 patients received a regimen of antibody induction, corticosteroids and azathioprine (AZA) in combination with Prograf (n=157) or cyclosporine (n=157) for 18 months. The trial population had a mean age of 51 years (range 18 to 65), the distribution was 82% male, and the composition was White (96%), Black (3%) and other (1%).



 The most common adverse reactions ( &gt;= 15%) observed in Prograf-treated heart transplant patients are: abnormal renal function, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, CMV infection, tremor, hyperglycemia, leukopenia, infection, anemia, bronchitis, pericardial effusion, urinary tract infection and hyperlipemia.



 Adverse reactions in heart transplant patients in the European trial are presented below:



 Table 8. Heart Transplantation: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 15% of Patients Treated with Prograf in Conjunction with Azathioprine (AZA) 
                                                           Prograf/AZA  (n=157)     Cyclosporine/AZA   (n=157)    
  Cardiovascular System                                    
  Hypertension                                             62%                  69%                         
  Pericardial Effusion                                     15%                  14%                         
  Body as a Whole                                          
  CMV Infection                                            32%                  30%                         
  Infection                                                24%                  21%                         
  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                      
                                                                                                            
  Diabetes Mellitus                                        26%                  16%                         
  Hyperglycemia                                            23%                  17%                         
  Hyperlipemia                                             18%                  27%                         
  Hemic and Lymphatic System                               
  Anemia                                                   50%                  36%                         
  Leukopenia                                               48%                  39%                         
                                                                                                            
  Urogenital System                                        
  Kidney Function Abnormal                                 56%                  57%                         
  Urinary Tract Infection                                  16%                  12%                         
  Respiratory System                                       
  Bronchitis                                               17%                  18%                         
  Nervous System                                           
  Tremor                                                   15%                  6%                          
         In the European trial, the cyclosporine trough concentrations were above the pre-defined target range (i.e., 100 to 200 ng/mL) at Day 122 and beyond in 32 to 68% of the patients in the cyclosporine treatment arm, whereas the tacrolimus trough concentrations were within the pre-defined target range (i.e., 5 to 15 ng/mL) in 74 to 86% of the patients in the tacrolimus treatment arm.
 

 In a U.S. trial, the incidence of adverse reactions was based on 331 heart transplant patients that received corticosteroids and Prograf in combination with sirolimus (n=109), Prograf in combination with MMF (n=107) or cyclosporine modified in combination with MMF (n=115) for 1 year. The trial population had a mean age of 53 years (range 18 to 75), the distribution was 78% male, and the composition was White (83%), Black (13%) and other (4%).



 Only selected targeted treatment-emergent adverse reactions were collected in the U.S. heart transplantation trial. Those reactions that were reported at a rate of 15% or greater in patients treated with Prograf and MMF include the following: any target adverse reactions (99%), hypertension (89%), hyperglycemia requiring antihyperglycemic therapy (70%)  ,  hypertriglyceridemia (65%), anemia (hemoglobin &lt;10.0 g/dL) (65%), fasting blood glucose &gt;140 mg/dL (on two separate occasions) (61%), hypercholesterolemia (57%), hyperlipidemia (34%), WBCs &lt;3000 cells/mcL (34%), serious bacterial infections (30%), magnesium &lt;1.2 mEq/L (24%), platelet count &lt;75,000 cells/mcL (19%), and other opportunistic infections (15%).



 Other targeted treatment-emergent adverse reactions in Prograf-treated patients occurred at a rate of less than 15%, and include the following: Cushingoid features, impaired wound healing, hyperkalemia,  Candida  infection, and CMV infection/syndrome.



  



   New Onset Diabetes After Transplant  



   Kidney Transplant  



 New Onset Diabetes After Transplant (NODAT) is defined as a composite of fasting plasma glucose &gt;=126 mg/dL, HbA1C&gt;= 6%, insulin use &gt;= 30 days or oral hypoglycemic use. In a trial in kidney transplant patients (Study 2), NODAT was observed in 75% in the Prograf-treated and 61% in the Neoral-treated patients without pre-transplant history of diabetes mellitus (  Table 9  )  [see  Clinical Studies  (  14.1  )]  .



 Table 9. Incidence of New Onset Diabetes After Transplant at 1 year in Kidney Transplant Recipients in a Phase 3 Trial (Study 2) 
  Parameter                          Treatment Group                     
  Prograf/MMF  (n = 212)             Neoral/MMF  (n = 212)               
  NODAT                              112/150 (75%)                       93/152 (61%)                        
      Fasting Plasma Glucose &gt;= 126 mg/dL    96/150 (64%)                        80/152 (53%)                        
      HbA1C &gt;= 6%                    59/150 (39%)                        28/152 (18%)                        
      Insulin Use &gt;= 30 days         9/150 (6%)                          4/152 (3%)                          
      Oral Hypoglycemic Use          15/150 (10%)                        5/152 (3%)                          
         In early trials of Prograf, Post-Transplant Diabetes Mellitus (PTDM) was evaluated with a more limited criteria of "use of insulin for 30 or more consecutive days with &lt; 5 day gap" in patients without a prior history of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus or non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus. Data are presented in Tables 10 to 13. PTDM was reported in 20% of Prograf/Azathioprine (AZA)-treated kidney transplant patients without pre-transplant history of diabetes mellitus in a Phase 3 trial (  Table 10  ). The median time to onset of PTDM was 68 days. Insulin dependence was reversible in 15% of these PTDM patients at one year and in 50% at 2 years post-transplant. Black and Hispanic kidney transplant patients were at an increased risk of development of PTDM (  Table 11  ).
 

 Table 10. Incidence of Post-Transplant Diabetes Mellitus and Insulin Use at 2 Years in Kidney Transplant Recipients in a Phase 3 Trial using Azathioprine (AZA) 
  Status of PTDMUse of insulin for 30 or more consecutive days, with &lt; 5 day gap, without a prior history of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus or non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus.    Prograf/AZA            CsA/AZA               
  Patients without pre-transplant history of diabetes mellitus    151                    151                   
  New onset PTDM, 1st Year                                      30/151 (20%)           6/151 (4%)            
  Still insulin-dependent at one year in those without prior history of diabetes    25/151 (17%)           5/151 (3%)            
  New onset PTDM post 1 year                                    1                      0                     
  Patients with PTDM at 2 years                                 16/151 (11%)           5/151 (3%)            
        Table 11. Development of Post-Transplant Diabetes Mellitus by Race or Ethnicity and by Treatment Group During First Year Post Kidney Transplantation in a Phase 3 Trial 
  Patient Race                  Patients Who Developed PTDMUse of insulin for 30 or more consecutive days, with &lt; 5 day gap, without a prior history of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus or non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus.    
  Prograf                       Cyclosporine                          
  Black                         15/41 (37%)                           3 (8%)                                
  Hispanic                      5/17 (29%)                            1 (6%)                                
  Caucasian                     10/82 (12%)                           1 (1%)                                
  Other                         0/11 (0%)                             1 (10%)                               
  Total                         30/151 (20%)                          6 (4%)                                
           Liver Transplant  
 

 Insulin-dependent PTDM was reported in 18% and 11% of Prograf-treated liver transplant patients and was reversible in 45% and 31% of these patients at 1 year post-transplant, in the U.S. and European randomized trials, respectively, (  Table 12  ). Hyperglycemia was associated with the use of Prograf in 47% and 33% of liver transplant recipients in the U.S. and European randomized trials, respectively, and may require treatment  [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )]  .



 Table 12. Incidence of Post-Transplant Diabetes Mellitus and Insulin Use at 1 Year in Liver Transplant Recipients 
  Status of PTDMUse of insulin for 30 or more consecutive days, with &lt; 5 day gap, without a prior history of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus or non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus.    US Trial              European Trial        
  Prograf               Cyclosporine          Prograf               Cyclosporine          
  Patients at riskPatients without pre-transplant history of diabetes mellitus.    239                   236                   239                   249                   
  New Onset PTDM        42 (18%)              30 (13%)              26 (11%)              12 (5%)               
  Patients still on insulin at 1 year    23 (10%)              19 (8%)               18 (8%)               6 (2%)                
             Heart Transplant  
 

 Insulin-dependent PTDM was reported in 13% and 22% of Prograf-treated heart transplant patients receiving mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) or azathioprine (AZA) and was reversible in 30% and 17% of these patients at one year post-transplant, in the U.S. and European randomized trials, respectively (  Table 13  ).  Hyperglycemia defined as two fasting plasma glucose levels &gt;=126 mg/dL was reported with the use of Prograf plus MMF or AZA in 32% and 35% of heart transplant recipients in the U.S. and European randomized trials, respectively, and may require treatment  [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )]  .



 Table 13. Incidence of Post-Transplant Diabetes Mellitus and Insulin Use at 1 Year in Heart Transplant Recipients 
  Status of PTDMUse of insulin for 30 or more consecutive days without a prior history of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus or non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus.    US Trial            European Trial          
  Prograf/MMF     Cyclosporine/MMF    Prograf/AZA             Cyclosporine/AZA        
  Patients at riskPatients without pre-transplant history of diabetes mellitus.    75                  83                      132                     138                        
  New Onset PTDM     10 (13%)            6 (7%)                  29 (22%)                5 (4%)                     
  Patients still on insulin at 1 year 7-12 months for the U.S. trial.    7 (9%)              1 (1%)                  24 (18%)                4 (3%)                     
             Less Frequently Reported Adverse Reactions (&gt;3% and &lt;15%)  
 

 The following adverse reactions were reported in either liver, kidney, and/or heart transplant recipients who were treated with tacrolimus in clinical trials.  Nervous System    [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.8  )]  



 Abnormal dreams, agitation, amnesia, anxiety, confusion, convulsion, crying, depression, elevated mood, emotional lability, encephalopathy, haemorrhagic stroke, hallucinations, hypertonia, incoordination, monoparesis, myoclonus, nerve compression, nervousness, neuralgia, neuropathy, paralysis flaccid, psychomotor skills impaired, psychosis, quadriparesis, somnolence, thinking abnormal, vertigo, writing impaired  Special Senses  



 Abnormal vision, amblyopia, ear pain, otitis media, tinnitus  Gastrointestinal  



 Cholangitis, cholestatic jaundice, duodenitis, dysphagia, esophagitis, flatulence, gastritis, gastroesophagitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, GGT increase, GI disorder, GI perforation, hepatitis, hepatitis granulomatous, ileus, increased appetite, jaundice, liver damage, oesophagitis ulcerative, oral moniliasis, pancreatic pseudocyst, rectal disorder, stomatitis  Cardiovascular  



 Abnormal ECG, angina pectoris, arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, bradycardia, cardiac fibrillation, cardiopulmonary failure, cardiovascular disorder, congestive heart failure, deep thrombophlebitis, echocardiogram abnormal, electrocardiogram QRS complex abnormal, electrocardiogram ST segment abnormal, heart failure, heart rate decreased, hemorrhage, hypotension, peripheral vascular disorder, phlebitis, postural hypotension, syncope, tachycardia, thrombosis, vasodilatation  Urogenital  



 Acute kidney failure  [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.7  )]  , albuminuria, BK nephropathy, bladder spasm, cystitis, dysuria, hematuria, hydronephrosis, kidney failure, kidney tubular necrosis, nocturia, pyuria, toxic nephropathy, urge incontinence, urinary frequency, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, vaginitis  Metabolic/Nutritional  



 Acidosis, alkaline phosphatase increased, alkalosis, ALT (SGPT) increased, AST (SGOT) increased, bicarbonate decreased, bilirubinemia, dehydration, GGT increased, gout, healing abnormal, hypercalcemia, hypercholesterolemia, hyperphosphatemia, hyperuricemia, hypervolemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, hypoproteinemia, lactic dehydrogenase increase, weight gain  Endocrine  



 Cushing's syndrome  Hemic/Lymphatic  



 Coagulation disorder, ecchymosis, haematocrit increased, haemoglobin abnormal, hypochromic anemia, leukocytosis, polycythemia, prothrombin decreased, serum iron decreased  Miscellaneous  



 Abdomen enlarged, abscess, accidental injury, allergic reaction, cellulitis, chills, fall, feeling abnormal, flu syndrome, generalized edema, hernia, mobility decreased, peritonitis, photosensitivity reaction, sepsis, temperature intolerance, ulcer  Musculoskeletal  



 Arthralgia, cramps, generalized spasm, joint disorder, leg cramps, myalgia, myasthenia, osteoporosis  Respiratory  



 Asthma, emphysema, hiccups, lung disorder, lung function decreased, pharyngitis, pneumonia, pneumothorax, pulmonary edema, respiratory disorder, rhinitis, sinusitis, voice alteration  Skin  



 Acne, alopecia, exfoliative dermatitis, fungal dermatitis, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, hirsutism, neoplasm skin benign, skin discoloration, skin disorder, skin ulcer, sweating



   6.2 Postmarketing Adverse Reactions

  The following adverse reactions have been reported from worldwide marketing experience with Prograf. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors: (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of the reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to the drug.



 Other reactions include:  Cardiovascular  



 Atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, cardiac arrhythmia, cardiac arrest, electrocardiogram T wave abnormal, flushing, myocardial infarction, myocardial ischaemia, pericardial effusion, QT prolongation, Torsade de Pointes, venous thrombosis deep limb, ventricular extrasystoles, ventricular fibrillation, myocardial hypertrophy  [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.15  )]  .  Gastrointestinal  



 Bile duct stenosis, colitis, enterocolitis, gastroenteritis, gastrooesophageal reflux disease, hepatic cytolysis, hepatic necrosis, hepatotoxicity, impaired gastric emptying, liver fatty, mouth ulceration, pancreatitis haemorrhagic, pancreatitis necrotizing, stomach ulcer, venoocclusive liver disease  Hemic/Lymphatic  



 Agranulocytosis, disseminated intravascular coagulation, hemolytic anemia, neutropenia, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenic purpura, thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura, pure red cell aplasia  [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.17  )]    Infections  



 Cases of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), sometimes fatal; -polyoma virus-associated nephropathy, (PVAN) including graft loss  [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  )]    Metabolic/Nutritional  



 Glycosuria, increased amylase including pancreatitis, weight decreased  Miscellaneous  



 Feeling hot and cold, feeling jittery, hot flushes, multi-organ failure, primary graft dysfunction  Nervous System  



 Carpal tunnel syndrome, cerebral infarction, hemiparesis, leukoencephalopathy, mental disorder, mutism, posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES)  [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.8  )]  , progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML)  [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  )]  , quadriplegia, speech disorder, syncope  Respiratory  



 Acute respiratory distress syndrome, interstitial lung disease, lung infiltration, respiratory distress, respiratory failure  Skin  



 Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis  Special Senses  



 Blindness, blindness cortical, hearing loss including deafness, photophobia  Urogenital  



 Acute renal failure, cystitis haemorrhagic, hemolytic-uremic syndrome, micturition disorder
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: BOXED WARNING - MALIGNANCIES AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS

  BOXED WARNING - MALIGNANCIES AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS

    *  Increased risk of development of lymphoma and other malignancies, particularly of the skin, due to immunosuppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
 *  Increased susceptibility to bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3, 5.4, 5.5)]. 
 *  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe Prograf. Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physician responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: MALIGNANCIES AND SERIOUS INFECTIONS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Increased risk of development of lymphoma and other malignancies, particularly of the skin, due to immunosuppression (5.2) 
 *  Increased susceptibility to bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections (5.3, 5.4, 5.5) 
 *  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe Prograf (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Lymphoma and Other Malignancies: Risk of lymphomas, including post transplant lymphoproliferative disorder (PLTD); appears related to intensity and duration of use. Avoid prolonged exposure to UV light and sunlight (  5.2  ) 
 *    Serious infections: Increased risk of bacterial, viral, fungal and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections: combination immunosuppression should be used with caution (  5.3  ) 
 *    Polyoma Virus Infections: Serious, sometimes fatal outcomes, including polyoma virus-associated nephropathy (PVAN), mostly due to BK virus, and JC virus-associated progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML); consider reducing immunosuppression (  5.4  ) 
 *    Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infections: Increased risk of CMV viremia and disease; consider reducing immunosuppression (  5.5  ) 
 *    New Onset Diabetes After Transplant: Monitor blood glucose (  5.6  ) 
 *    Nephrotoxicity: Acute and/or chronic; reduce the dose; use caution with other nephrotoxic drugs (  5.7  ) 
 *    Neurotoxicity: Risk of Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome, monitor for neurologic abnormalities; reduce or discontinue Prograf and other immunosuppressants (  5.8  ) 
 *    Hyperkalemia: Monitor serum potassium levels. Careful consideration should be given prior to use of other agents also associated with hyperkalemia (  5.9  ) 
 *    Hypertension: May require antihypertensive therapy. Monitor relevant drug-drug interactions (  5.10  ) 
 *    Anaphylactic Reactions with IV formulation: Observe patients receiving Prograf injection for signs and symptoms of anaphylaxis (  5.11  ) 
 *    Use with Sirolimus: Not recommended in liver and heart transplant due to increased risk of serious adverse reactions (  5.12  ) 
 *    Myocardial Hypertrophy: Consider dosage reduction or discontinuation (  5.15  ) 
 *    Immunizations: Use of live vaccines should be avoided (  5.16  ) 
 *    Pure Red Cell Aplasia: Discontinuation should be considered (  5.17  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Immunosuppression



  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should use Prograf. Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physicians responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow up of the patient [see  Boxed Warning  ]  .



    5.2 Lymphoma and Other Malignancies



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Prograf, are at increased risk of developing lymphomas and other malignancies, particularly of the skin [see  Boxed Warning  ].  The risk appears to be related to the intensity and duration of immunosuppression rather than to the use of any specific agent.



 As usual for patients with increased risk for skin cancer, exposure to sunlight and UV light should be limited by wearing protective clothing and using a sunscreen with a high protection factor.



 Post transplant lymphoproliferative disorder (PTLD) has been reported in immunosuppressed organ transplant recipients. The majority of PTLD events appear related to Epstein Barr Virus (EBV) infection. The risk of PTLD appears greatest in those individuals who are EBV seronegative, a population which includes many young children.



    5.3 Serious Infections



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Prograf, are at increased risk of developing bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoal infections, including opportunistic infections [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.4  ,  5.5  )]  . These infections may lead to serious, including fatal, outcomes. Because of the danger of oversuppression of the immune system which can increase susceptibility to infection, combination immunosuppressant therapy should be used with caution.



    5.4 Polyoma Virus Infections



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Prograf, are at increased risk for opportunistic infections, including polyoma virus infections. Polyoma virus infections in transplant patients may have serious, and sometimes fatal, outcomes. These include polyoma virus-associated nephropathy (PVAN), mostly due to BK virus infection, and JC virus-associated progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML) which have been observed in patients receiving tacrolimus [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.2  )]  .



 PVAN is associated with serious outcomes, including deteriorating renal function and kidney graft loss [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.2  )]  . Patient monitoring may help detect patients at risk for PVAN.



 Cases of PML have been reported in patients treated with Prograf. PML, which is sometimes fatal, commonly presents with hemiparesis, apathy, confusion, cognitive deficiencies and ataxia. Risk factors for PML include treatment with immunosuppressant therapies and impairment of immune function. In immunosuppressed patients, physicians should consider PML in the differential diagnosis in patients reporting neurological symptoms and consultation with a neurologist should be considered as clinically indicated.



 Reductions in immunosuppression should be considered for patients who develop evidence of PVAN or PML. Physicians should also consider the risk that reduced immunosuppression represents to the functioning allograft.



    5.5 Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infections



  Patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Prograf, are at increased risk of developing CMV viremia and CMV disease. The risk of CMV disease is highest among transplant recipients seronegative for CMV at time of transplant who receive a graft from a CMV seropositive donor. Therapeutic approaches to limiting CMV disease exist and should be routinely provided. Patient monitoring may help detect patients at risk for CMV disease. Consideration should be given to reducing the amount of immunosuppression in patients who develop CMV viremia and/or CMV disease.



    5.6 New Onset Diabetes After Transplant



  Prograf was shown to cause new onset diabetes mellitus in clinical trials of kidney, liver, and heart transplantation. New onset diabetes after transplantation may be reversible in some patients. Black and Hispanic kidney transplant patients are at an increased risk. Blood glucose concentrations should be monitored closely in patients using Prograf [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )]  .



    5.7 Nephrotoxicity



  Prograf, like other calcineurin-inhibitors, can cause acute or chronic nephrotoxicity, particularly when used in high doses. Acute nephrotoxicity is most often related to vasoconstriction of the afferent renal arteriole, is characterized by increasing serum creatinine, hyperkalemia, and/or a decrease in urine output, and is typically reversible. Chronic calcineurin-inhibitor nephrotoxicity is associated with increased serum creatinine, decreased kidney graft life, and characteristic histologic changes observed on renal biopsy; the changes associated with chronic calcineurin-inhibitor nephrotoxicity are typically progressive. Patients with impaired renal function should be monitored closely as the dosage of Prograf may need to be reduced. In patients with persistent elevations of serum creatinine who are unresponsive to dosage adjustments, consideration should be given to changing to another immunosuppressive therapy.



 Based on reported adverse reactions terms related to decreased renal function, nephrotoxicity was reported in approximately 52% of kidney transplantation patients and in 40% and 36% of liver transplantation patients receiving Prograf in the U.S. and European randomized trials, respectively, and in 59% of heart transplantation patients in a European randomized trial [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )].  



 Due to the potential for additive or synergistic impairment of renal function, care should be taken when administering Prograf with drugs that may be associated with renal dysfunction. These include, but are not limited to, aminoglycosides, ganciclovir, amphotericin B, cisplatin, nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors (e.g., tenofovir) and protease inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, indinavir). Similarly, care should be exercised when administering with CYP3A4 inhibitors such as antifungal drugs (e.g., ketoconazole), calcium channel blockers (e.g., diltiazem, verapamil), and macrolide antibiotics (e.g., clarithromycin, erythromycin, troleandomycin) which will result in increased tacrolimus whole blood concentrations due to inhibition of tacrolimus metabolism [see  Drug Interactions  (  7.3  ,  7.4  ,  7.5  ,  7.6  )]  .



    5.8 Neurotoxicity



   Prograf may cause a spectrum of neurotoxicities, particularly when used in high doses. The most severe neurotoxicities include posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES), delirium, and coma. Patients treated with tacrolimus have been reported to develop PRES. Symptoms indicating PRES include headache, altered mental status, seizures, visual disturbances and hypertension. Diagnosis may be confirmed by radiological procedure. If PRES is suspected or diagnosed, blood pressure control should be maintained and immediate reduction of immunosuppression is advised. This syndrome is characterized by reversal of symptoms upon reduction or discontinuation of immunosuppression.  
 

 Coma and delirium, in the absence of PRES, have also been associated with high plasma concentrations of tacrolimus. Seizures have occurred in adult and pediatric patients receiving Prograf [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )]  .



 Less severe neurotoxicities, include tremors, paresthesias, headache, and other changes in motor function, mental status, and sensory function [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )].  Tremor and headache have been associated with high whole-blood concentrations of tacrolimus and may respond to dosage adjustment.



    5.9 Hyperkalemia



  Hyperkalemia has been reported with Prograf use. Serum potassium levels should be monitored. Careful consideration should be given prior to use of other agents also associated with hyperkalemia (e.g., potassium-sparing diuretics, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers) during Prograf therapy [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )]  .



    5.10 Hypertension



  Hypertension is a common adverse effect of Prograf therapy and may require antihypertensive therapy [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )].  The control of blood pressure can be accomplished with any of the common antihypertensive agents, though careful consideration should be given prior to use of antihypertensive agents associated with hyperkalemia (e.g., potassium-sparing diuretics, ACE inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers) [see  Warnings and Precautions  (  5.9  )]  . Calcium-channel blocking agents may increase tacrolimus blood concentrations and therefore require dosage reduction of Prograf [see  Drug Interactions  (  7.5  )].  



    5.11 Anaphylactic Reactions with Prograf Injection



  Anaphylactic reactions have occurred with injectables containing castor oil derivatives, including Prograf, in a small percentage of patients (0.6%). The exact cause of these reactions is not known. Prograf injection should be reserved for patients who are unable to take Prograf capsules [see  Indications and Usage  (  1.4  )]  .



 Patients receiving Prograf injection should be under continuous observation for at least the first 30 minutes following the start of the infusion and at frequent intervals thereafter. If signs or symptoms of anaphylaxis occur, the infusion should be stopped. An aqueous solution of epinephrine should be available at the bedside as well as a source of oxygen.



    5.12 Use with Sirolimus



  The safety and efficacy of Prograf with sirolimus has not been established in kidney transplant patients.



 Use of sirolimus with Prograf in studies of de novo  liver transplant patients was associated with an excess mortality, graft loss, and hepatic artery thrombosis (HAT) and is not recommended [see  Indications and Usage  (  1.4  )]  .



 Use of sirolimus (2 mg per day) with Prograf in heart transplant patients in a U.S. trial was associated with increased risk of renal function impairment, wound healing complications, and insulin-dependent post-transplant diabetes mellitus, and is not recommended [see  Clinical Studies  (  14.3  )]  .



    5.13 Use with CYP3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  When coadministering Prograf with strong CYP3A4-inhibitors (e.g., telaprevir, boceprevir, ritonavir, ketoconazole, itraconazole, voriconazole, clarithromycin) and strong inducers (e.g., rifampin, rifabutin) adjustments in the dosing regimen of Prograf and subsequent frequent monitoring of tacrolimus whole blood trough concentrations and tacrolimus-associated adverse reactions are recommended [see  Drug Interactions  (  7  )].  



    5.14 QT Prolongation



  Prograf may prolong the QT/QTc interval and may cause Torsade de Pointes. Avoid Prograf in patients with congenital long QT syndrome. In patients with congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, those taking certain antiarrhythmic medications or other medicinal products that lead to QT prolongation, and those with electrolyte disturbances such as hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, or hypomagnesemia, consider obtaining electrocardiograms and monitoring electrolytes (magnesium, potassium, calcium) periodically during treatment.



 When coadministering Prograf with other substrates and/or inhibitors of CYP3A4 that also have the potential to prolong the QT interval, a reduction in Prograf dose, frequent monitoring of tacrolimus whole blood concentrations, and monitoring for QT prolongation is recommended. Use of Prograf with amiodarone has been reported to result in increased tacrolimus whole blood concentrations with or without concurrent QT prolongation [see  Drug Interactions  (  7  )].  



    5.15 Myocardial Hypertrophy



  Myocardial hypertrophy has been reported in infants, children, and adults, particularly those with high tacrolimus trough concentrations, and is generally manifested by echocardiographically demonstrated concentric increases in left ventricular posterior wall and interventricular septum thickness. This condition appears reversible in most cases following dose reduction or discontinuance of therapy. In patients who develop renal failure or clinical manifestations of ventricular dysfunction while receiving Prograf therapy, echocardiographic evaluation should be considered. If myocardial hypertrophy is diagnosed, dosage reduction or discontinuation of Prograf should be considered [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.2  )]  .



    5.16 Immunizations



  The use of live vaccines should be avoided during treatment with tacrolimus; examples include (not limited to) the following: intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, BCG, yellow fever, varicella, and TY21a typhoid vaccines.



    5.17 Pure Red Cell Aplasia



  Cases of pure red cell aplasia (PRCA) have been reported in patients treated with tacrolimus. A mechanism for tacrolimus-induced PRCA has not been elucidated. All patients reported risk factors for PRCA such as parvovirus B19 infection, underlying disease, or concomitant medications associated with PRCA. If PRCA is diagnosed, discontinuation of Prograf should be considered [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.2  )]  .



    5.18 Gastrointestinal Perforation



  Gastrointestinal perforation has been reported in patients treated with Prograf; all reported cases were considered to be a complication of transplant surgery or accompanied by infection, diverticulum, or malignant neoplasm. As gastrointestinal perforation may be serious or life-threatening, appropriate medical/surgical management should be instituted promptly [see  Adverse Reactions  (  6.1  )].   
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
