<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="proglycem" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS:

    Frequent and Serious:  

  Sodium and fluid retention is most common in young infants and in adults and may precipitate congestive heart failure in patients with compromised cardiac reserve. It usually responds to diuretic therapy (See  DRUG INTERACTIONS  ).



     Infrequent but Serious:  

  Diabetic ketoacidosis and hyperosmolar nonketotic coma may develop very rapidly. Conventional therapy with insulin and restoration of fluid and electrolyte balance is usually effective if instituted promptly. Prolonged surveillance is essential in view of the long half-life of PROGLYCEM  (r)  (See  OVERDOSAGE  ).



     Other frequent adverse reactions:  

  Hirsutism of the lanugo type, mainly on the forehead, back and limbs, occurs most commonly in children and women and may be cosmetically unacceptable. It subsides on discontinuation of the drug.



 Hyperglycemia or glycosuria may require reduction in dosage in order to avoid progression to ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma.



 Gastrointestinal intolerance may include anorexia, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, ileus, diarrhea, transient loss of taste.



 Tachycardia, palpitations, increased levels of serum uric acid are common.



 Thrombocytopenia with or without purpura may require discontinuation of the drug. Neutropenia is transient, is not associated with increased susceptibility to infection, and ordinarily does not require discontinuation of the drug. Skin rash, headache, weakness, and malaise may also occur.



     Other adverse reactions which have been observed are:  

    Cardiovascular:  hypotension occurs occasionally, which may be augmented by thiazide diuretics given concurrently. A few cases of transient hypertension, for which no explanation is apparent, have been noted. Chest pain has been reported rarely.



   Hematologic:  eosinophilia; decreased hemoglobin / hematocrit; excessive bleeding, decreased IgG.



   Hepato-renal:  increased AST, alkaline phosphatase; azotemia, decreased creatinine clearance, reversible nephrotic syndrome, decreased urinary output, hematuria, albuminuria. Neurologic: anxiety, dizziness, insomnia, polyneuritis, paresthesia, pruritus, extrapyramidal signs.



   Ophthalmologic:  transient cataracts, subconjunctival hemorrhage, ring scotoma, blurred vision, diplopia, lacrimation.  Skeletal, integumentary;  monilial dermatitis, herpes, advance in bone age; loss of scalp hair.  Systemic:  fever, lymphadenopathy.  Other;  gout acute pancreatitis/pancreatic necrosis, galactorrhea, enlargement of lump in breast.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
