<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prohance1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The adverse events described in this section were observed in clinical trials involving 1251 patients (670 males and 581 females). Adult patients ranged in age from 18-91 yrs. Pediatric patients ranged from 2-17 years. The racial breakdown was 83% Caucasian, 8% Black, 3% Hispanic, 2% Asian, and 1% other. In 2% of the patients, race was not reported.



 The most commonly noted adverse experiences were nausea and taste perversion with an incidence of 1.4%. These events were mild to moderate in severity.



 The following additional adverse events occurred in fewer than 1% of the patients:




 Body as a Whole:                Facial Edema; Neck Rigidity; Pain; Pain at Injection Site; Injection Site Reaction; Chest Pain; Headache; Fever; Itching; Watery Eyes; Abdominal Cramps; Tingling Sensation in Throat; Laryngismus; Flushed Feeling; Vasovagal Reaction; Anaphylactoid Reactions (characterized by cardiovascular, respiratory and cutaneous symptoms)   
 Cardiovascular:                 Prolonged P-R Interval; Hypotension; Elevated Heart Rate; A-V Nodal Rhythm   
 Digestive:                      Edematous and/or itching tongue; Gingivitis; Dry Mouth; Loose Bowel; Vomiting   
 Nervous System:                 Anxiety; Dizziness; Paresthesia; Mental Status Decline; Loss of Coordination in Arm; Staring Episode; Seizure; Syncope   
 Respiratory System:             Dyspnea; Rhinitis; Cough                                                 
 Skin and Appendages:            Pruritus; Rash; Rash Macular Papular; Urticaria; Hives; Tingling Sensation of Extremity and Digits   
 Special Senses:                 Tinnitus                                                                 
      The following adverse drug reactions have also been reported:
 


 Body as a Whole:                Generalized Edema; Laryngeal Edema; Malaise; Anaphylactoid Reactions (characterized by cardiovascular, respiratory and cutaneous symptoms, and rarely resulting in Death)   
 Cardiovascular:                 Cardiac Arrest; Bradycardia; Hypertension; and Death in association with pre-existing cardiovascular disorders   
 Digestive:                      Increased Salivation; Dysphagia                                          
 Nervous System:                 Stupor; Tremor; Loss of Consciousness                                    
 Respiratory:                    Apnea; Wheezing                                                          
 Skin and Appendages:            Sweating; and Cyanosis                                                   
 Special Senses:                 Voice Alteration; Transitory Deafness                                    
 Urogenital:                     Urinary Incontinence                                                     
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: NEPHROGENIC SYSTEMIC FIBROSIS

  WARNING: NEPHROGENIC SYSTEMIC FIBROSIS

  Gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs) increase

the risk for NSF among patients with impaired elimination of the drugs.

Avoid use of GBCAs in these patients unless the diagnostic information

is essential and not available with non-contrasted MRI or other modalities.

NSF may result in fatal or debilitating systemic fibrosis affecting

the skin, muscle and internal organs.



 *  The risk for NSF appears highest among patients with: chronic, severe kidney disease (GFR &lt;30 mL/min/1.73m2), or acute kidney injury. 
 *  Screen patients for acute kidney injury and other conditions that may reduce renal function. For patients at risk for chronically reduced renal function (e.g. age &gt; 60 years, hypertension or diabetes), estimate the glomerular filtration rate (GFR) through laboratory testing. 
 *  For patients at highest risk for NSF, do not exceed the recommended ProHance dose and allow a sufficient period of time for elimination of the drug from the body prior to re-administration (see WARNINGS). 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
