<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prolensa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions in 3 to 8% of patients were anterior chamber inflammation, foreign body sensation, eye pain, photophobia, and vision blurred. (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bausch &amp; Lomb Incorporated at 1-800-323-0000, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions following use of PROLENSA following cataract surgery include: anterior chamber inflammation, foreign body sensation, eye pain, photophobia, and vision blurred. These reactions were reported in 3 to 8% of patients.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:    Sulfite Allergic Reactions (  5.1  )



  Slow or Delayed Healing (  5.2  )



  Potential for cross-sensitivity (  5.3  )



  Increase bleeding of ocular tissues (  5.4  )



  Corneal effects including keratitis (  5.5  )



  Contact Lens Wear (  5.6  )



 



   5.1 Sulfite Allergic Reactions



  Contains sodium sulfite, a sulfite that may cause allergic type reactions including anaphylactic symptoms and life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in certain susceptible people. The overall prevalence of sulfite sensitivity in the general population is unknown and probably low. Sulfite sensitivity is seen more frequently in asthmatic than in non-asthmatic people.



    5.2 Slow or Delayed Healing



  All topical nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), including bromfenac, may slow or delay healing. Topical corticosteroids are also known to slow or delay healing. Concomitant use of topical NSAIDs and topical steroids may increase the potential for healing problems.



    5.3 Potential for Cross-Sensitivity



  There is the potential for cross-sensitivity to acetylsalicylic acid, phenylacetic acid derivatives, and other NSAIDs, including bromfenac. Therefore, caution should be used when treating individuals who have previously exhibited sensitivities to these drugs.



    5.4 Increased Bleeding Time



  With some NSAIDs, including bromfenac, there exists the potential for increased bleeding time due to interference with platelet aggregation. There have been reports that ocularly applied NSAIDs may cause increased bleeding of ocular tissues (including hyphemas) in conjunction with ocular surgery.



 It is recommended that PROLENSA ophthalmic solution be used with caution in patients with known bleeding tendencies or who are receiving other medications which may prolong bleeding time.



    5.5 Keratitis and Corneal Reactions



  Use of topical NSAIDs may result in keratitis. In some susceptible patients, continued use of topical NSAIDs may result in epithelial breakdown, corneal thinning, corneal erosion, corneal ulceration or corneal perforation. These events may be sight threatening. Patients with evidence of corneal epithelial breakdown should immediately discontinue use of topical NSAIDs, including bromfenac, and should be closely monitored for corneal health.



 Post-marketing experience with topical NSAIDs suggests that patients with complicated ocular surgeries, corneal denervation, corneal epithelial defects, diabetes mellitus, ocular surface diseases (e.g., dry eye syndrome), rheumatoid arthritis, or repeat ocular surgeries within a short period of time may be at increased risk for corneal adverse events which may become sight threatening. Topical NSAIDs should be used with caution in these patients.



 Post-marketing experience with topical NSAIDs also suggests that use more than 24 hours prior to surgery or use beyond 14 days post-surgery may increase patient risk for the occurrence and severity of corneal adverse events.



    5.6 Contact Lens Wear



  PROLENSA should not be instilled while wearing contact lenses. Remove contact lenses prior to instillation of PROLENSA. The preservative in PROLENSA, benzalkonium chloride may be absorbed by soft contact lenses. Lenses may be reinserted after 10 minutes following administration of PROLENSA.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
