<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prolastinc" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most serious adverse reaction observed during clinical trials with PROLASTIN-C was an abdominal and extremity rash in one subject. The abdominal rash recurred upon rechallenge with PROLASTIN-C, which led to withdrawal of the subject from the trial. [  see  Warnings and Precautions       (5.1)  ]



 The most common adverse reaction observed at a rate of &gt; 5% in subjects receiving PROLASTIN-C was upper respiratory tract infection.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reaction during clinical trials in &gt; 5% of subjects was upper respiratory tract infection.   (6.1)  



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Grifols Therapeutics Inc. at 1-800-520-2807 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical trials and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  



 Two separate clinical trials were conducted with PROLASTIN-C: 1.) a 20 week, open-label, single arm safety study in 38 subjects (single-arm open-label trial), and 2.) a 16 week, randomized, double-blind, crossover pharmacokinetic comparability study vs. PROLASTIN in 24 subjects, followed by an 8 week open-label treatment with PROLASTIN-C (randomized double-blinded comparator trial). Thus, 62 subjects were exposed to PROLASTIN-C in clinical trials.



 The most serious adverse reaction observed during clinical trials with PROLASTIN-C was an abdominal and extremity rash in one subject. The rash resolved subsequent to outpatient treatment with antihistamines and steroids. Two instances of a less severe, pruritic abdominal rash were observed upon rechallenge despite continued antihistamine and steroid treatment, which led to withdrawal of the subject from the trial.



 The adverse reaction occurring in &gt; 5% of subjects treated with PROLASTIN-C was upper respiratory tract infection.



 Grifols assessed the randomized double-blinded comparator trial for adverse reactions (as defined in the footnote to  Table 1  ) occurring during each 8 week double-blind crossover treatment period, as shown in  Table 1  .



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Occurring during the First 8 Weeks of Each Double-Blinded Treatment 
                                             PROLASTIN  (r)  -C  No. of subjects: 62    PROLASTIN  (r)    No. of subjects: 24   
 Adverse Reaction  ,                       No. of Subjects with Adverse Reaction(percentage of all subjects)  No. of Subjects with Adverse Reaction(percentage of all subjects)   
 Upper respiratory tract infection         3 (12.5%)                       1 (4.2%)                         
 Headache                                  1 (4.2%)                        2 (8.3%)                         
 Pruritus                                  1 (4.2%)                        0                                
 Urticaria                                 1 (4.2%)                        0                                
 Nausea                                    1 (4.2%)                        0                                
 Peripheral edema                          1 (4.2%)                        0                                
 Pyrexia                                   1 (4.2%)                        0                                
        Table 2  below displays the adverse reaction rate as a percentage of infusions received during the 8 weeks of each double-blinded treatment.
 

 Table 2: Adverse Reaction Frequency as a Percent of All Infusions during the First 8 Weeks of Each Double-Blinded Infusion Treatment 
                                             PROLASTIN  (r)  -C  No. of infusions: 188    PROLASTIN  (r)    No. of infusions: 192   
 Adverse Reaction  ,                       No. of Adverse Reactions(percentage of all infusions)  No. of Adverse Reactions(percentage of all infusions)   
 Upper respiratory tract infection         3 (1.6%)                        1 (0.5%)                         
 Headache                                  1 (0.5%)                        3 (1.6%)                         
 Pruritus                                  1 (0.5%)                        0                                
 Urticaria                                 1 (0.5%)                        0                                
 Nausea                                    1 (0.5%)                        0                                
 Peripheral edema                          1 (0.5%)                        0                                
 Pyrexia                                   1 (0.5%)                        0                                
        Table 3  below displays the adverse reactions occurring in two or more subjects during the single-arm open-label trial.
 

 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Occurring in Two or More Subjects (&gt;5%) during the 20 Week Single-Arm Open-Label Trial 
                                                       PROLASTIN-C  No. subjects: 38                      
 Adverse Reaction  ,                                 No. of subjects with Adverse Reaction(percentage of all subjects)   
 Upper respiratory tract infection                   6 (15.8%)                                            
 Urinary tract infection                             5 (13.2%)                                            
 Nausea                                              4 (10.5%)                                            
 Chest pain                                          3 (7.9%)                                             
 Back pain                                           2 (5.3%)                                             
 Chills                                              2 (5.3%)                                             
 Cough                                               2 (5.3%)                                             
 Dizziness                                           2 (5.3%)                                             
 Dyspnea                                             2 (5.3%)                                             
 Headache                                            2 (5.3%)                                             
 Hot flush                                           2 (5.3%)                                             
 Oral candidiasis                                    2 (5.3%)                                             
      Ten exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease were reported by 8 subjects in the 24 week crossover pharmacokinetic study. During the 16 week double-blind crossover phase, 4 subjects (17%) had a total of 4 exacerbations during PROLASTIN-C treatment and 4 subjects (17%) had a total of 4 exacerbations during PROLASTIN treatment. Two additional exacerbations in 2 subjects (8%) occurred during the 8 week open-label treatment period with PROLASTIN-C. The overall rate of pulmonary exacerbations during treatment with either product was 0.9 exacerbations per subject-year.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

    Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



 The reactions which have been chosen for inclusion due to their seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to PROLASTIN  (r)  -C, or a combination of these factors, are:



 *   General :                                              Chest discomfort/chest pain, chills, malaise, influenza-like illness, fatigue 
 *   Nervous system :                                 Dizziness, headache 
 *   Skin and subcutaneous system :        Pruritus and rash including urticarial 
 *   Respiratory system :                           Dyspnea 
 *   Immune system :                                 Hypersensitivity including anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions 
 *   Cardiac :                                              Tachycardia 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  IgA deficient patients with antibodies against IgA are at greater risk of developing severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions.  (5.1)   
 *  This product is made from human plasma and may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease agent.  (5.2)   
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions may occur. Should evidence of an acute hypersensitivity reaction be observed, promptly stop the infusion and begin appropriate therapy. [ see  Patient Counseling Information       (17)  ]



 PROLASTIN-C may contain trace amounts of IgA. Patients with known antibodies to IgA, which can be present in patients with selective or severe IgA deficiency, have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. PROLASTIN-C is contraindicated in patients with antibodies against IgA.



    5.2 Transmissible Infectious Agents



   Because PROLASTIN-C is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses and, theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent.  



 Discuss the risks and benefits of this product with the patient, before prescribing or administering it to a patient. [ see  Patient Counseling Information       (17)  ] Report all infections thought by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product to Grifols Therapeutics Inc. [1-800-520-2807].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
