<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prometrium" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  See    BOXED WARNING    ,    WARNINGS    and    PRECAUTIONS    .



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial, the effects of PROMETRIUM Capsules on the endometrium was studied in a total of 875 postmenopausal women.  Table 6  lists adverse reactions greater than or equal to 2 percent of women who received cyclic PROMETRIUM Capsules 200 mg daily (12 days per calendar month cycle) with 0.625 mg conjugated estrogens or placebo.



 TABLE 6. Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 2%) Reported in an 875 Patient Placebo-Controlled Trial in Postmenopausal Women Over a 3-Year Period [Percentage (%) of Patients Reporting] 
                                              PROMETRIUM Capsules 200 mg with Conjugated Estrogens 0.625 mg      Placebo           
                                              (n=178)                                   (n=174)           
 Headache                                   31                                        27                  
 Breast Tenderness                          27                                        6                   
 Joint Pain                                 20                                        29                  
 Depression                                 19                                        12                  
 Dizziness                                  15                                        9                   
 Abdominal Bloating                         12                                        5                   
 Hot Flashes                                11                                        35                  
 Urinary Problems                           11                                        9                   
 Abdominal Pain                             10                                        10                  
 Vaginal Discharge                          10                                        3                   
 Nausea / Vomiting                          8                                         7                   
 Worry                                      8                                         4                   
 Chest Pain                                 7                                         5                   
 Diarrhea                                   7                                         4                   
 Night Sweats                               7                                         17                  
 Breast Pain                                6                                         2                   
 Swelling of Hands and Feet                 6                                         9                   
 Vaginal Dryness                            6                                         10                  
 Constipation                               3                                         2                   
 Breast Carcinoma                           2                                         &lt;1                  
 Breast Excisional Biopsy                   2                                         &lt;1                  
 Cholecystectomy                            2                                         &lt;1                  
           Effects on Secondary Amenorrhea
   In a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial, the effects of PROMETRIUM Capsules on secondary amenorrhea was studied in 49 estrogen-primed postmenopausal women.  Table 7  lists adverse reactions greater than or equal to 5 percent of women who received PROMETRIUM Capsules or placebo.



 TABLE 7. Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5%) Reported in Patients Using 400 mg/day in a Placebo-Controlled Trial in Estrogen-Primed Postmenopausal Women 
   Adverse Experience                            PROMETRIUM    Capsules 400 mg      Placebo                
                                                 n=25                              n=24                   
                                                 Percentage (%) of Patients       
    Fatigue                                    8                                 4                        
    Headache                                   16                                8                        
    Dizziness                                  24                                4                        
    Abdominal Distention (Bloating)            8                                 8                        
    Abdominal Pain (Cramping)                  20                                13                       
    Diarrhea                                   8                                 4                        
    Nausea                                     8                                 0                        
    Back Pain                                  8                                 8                        
    Musculoskeletal Pain                       12                                4                        
    Irritability                               8                                 4                        
    Breast Pain                                16                                8                        
    Infection Viral                            12                                0                        
    Coughing                                   8                                 0                        
         In a multicenter, parallel-group, open label postmarketing dosing study consisting of three consecutive 28-day treatment cycles, 220 premenopausal women with secondary amenorrhea were randomized to receive daily conjugated estrogens therapy (0.625 mg conjugated estrogens) and PROMETRIUM Capsules, 300 mg per day (n=113) or PROMETRIUM Capsules, 400 mg per /day (n=107) for 10 days of each treatment cycle. Overall, the most frequently reported treatment-emergent adverse reactions, reported in greater than or equal to 5 percent of subjects, were nausea, fatigue, vaginal mycosis, nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, headache, dizziness, breast tenderness, abdominal distension, acne, dysmenorrhea, mood swing, and urinary tract infection.
 

   Postmarketing Experience:

  The following additional adverse reactions have been reported with PROMETRIUM Capsules. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Genitourinary System:  endometrial carcinoma, hypospadia, intra-uterine death, menorrhagia, menstrual disorder, metrorrhagia, ovarian cyst, spontaneous abortion.



   Cardiovascular:  circulatory collapse, congenital heart disease (including ventricular septal defect and patent ductus arteriosus), hypertension, hypotension, tachycardia.



   Gastrointestinal:  acute pancreatitis, cholestasis, cholestatic hepatitis, dysphagia, hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatitis, increased liver function tests (including alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, gamma-glutamyl transferase increased), jaundice, swollen tongue.



   Skin:  alopecia, pruritus, urticaria.



   Eyes:  blurred vision, diplopia, visual disturbance.



   Central Nervous System:  aggression, convulsion, depersonalization, depressed consciousness, disorientation, dysarthria, loss of consciousness, paresthesia, sedation, stupor, syncope (with and without hypotension), transient ischemic attack, suicidal ideation.



 During initial therapy, a few women have experienced a constellation of many or all of the following symptoms: extreme dizziness and/or drowsiness, blurred vision, slurred speech, difficulty walking, loss of consciousness, vertigo, confusion, disorientation, feeling drunk, and shortness of breath.



   Miscellaneous:  abnormal gait, anaphylactic reaction, arthralgia, blood glucose increased, choking, cleft lip, cleft palate, difficulty walking, dyspnea, face edema, feeling abnormal, feeling drunk, hypersensitivity, asthma, muscle cramp, throat tightness, tinnitus, vertigo, weight decreased, weight increased.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA FOR ESTROGEN PLUS PROGESTIN THERAPY 

  WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA FOR ESTROGEN PLUS PROGESTIN THERAPY 

    Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



 Estrogens plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders     and     Probable dementia    .) 



 The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, stroke and myocardial infarction in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg] combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Cardiovascular disorders    .) 



 The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Probable dementia     and     PRECAUTIONS, Geriatric Use    .)



   Breast Cancer  



 The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer. (See     CLINICAL STUDIES     and     WARNINGS, Malignant neoplasms,           Breast Cancer      .) 



 In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.



 Progestins with estrogens should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
