<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="propecia" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions, reported in &gt;=1% of patients treated with PROPECIA and greater than in patients treated with placebo are: decreased libido, erectile dysfunction and ejaculation disorder (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Clinical Studies for PROPECIA (finasteride 1 mg) in the Treatment of Male Pattern Hair Loss  



 In three controlled clinical trials for PROPECIA of 12-month duration, 1.4% of patients taking PROPECIA (n=945) were discontinued due to adverse experiences that were considered to be possibly, probably or definitely drug-related (1.6% for placebo; n=934).



 Clinical adverse experiences that were reported as possibly, probably or definitely drug-related in &gt;=1% of patients treated with PROPECIA or placebo are presented in  Table 1  .



 TABLE 1: Drug-Related Adverse Experiences for PROPECIA (finasteride 1 mg) in Year 1 (%) MALE PATTERN HAIR LOSS 
                                                   PROPECIAN=945                    PlaceboN=934            
  
 Decreased Libido                                       1.8                             1.3                 
 Erectile Dysfunction                                   1.3                             0.7                 
 Ejaculation Disorder    (Decreased Volume of Ejaculate)             1.2  (0.8)                      0.7  (0.4)              
 Discontinuation due to drug-related sexual adverse experiences               1.2                             0.9                 
         Integrated analysis of clinical adverse experiences showed that during treatment with PROPECIA, 36 (3.8%) of 945 men had reported one or more of these adverse experiences as compared to 20 (2.1%) of 934 men treated with placebo (p=0.04). Resolution occurred in men who discontinued therapy with PROPECIA due to these side effects and in most of those who continued therapy. The incidence of each of the above adverse experiences decreased to &lt;=0.3% by the fifth year of treatment with PROPECIA.
 

 In a study of finasteride 1 mg daily in healthy men, a median decrease in ejaculate volume of 0.3 mL (-11%) compared with 0.2 mL (-8%) for placebo was observed after 48 weeks of treatment. Two other studies showed that finasteride at 5 times the dosage of PROPECIA (5 mg daily) produced significant median decreases of approximately 0.5 mL (-25%) compared to placebo in ejaculate volume, but this was reversible after discontinuation of treatment.



 In the clinical studies with PROPECIA, the incidences for breast tenderness and enlargement, hypersensitivity reactions, and testicular pain in finasteride-treated patients were not different from those in patients treated with placebo  .  



     Controlled Clinical Trials and Long-Term Open Extension Studies for PROSCAR  (r)  (finasteride 5 mg) and AVODART (dutasteride) in the Treatment of Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia  



 In the PROSCAR Long-Term Efficacy and Safety Study (PLESS), a 4-year controlled clinical study, 3040 patients between the ages of 45 and 78 with symptomatic BPH and an enlarged prostate were evaluated for safety over a period of 4 years (1524 on PROSCAR 5 mg/day and 1516 on placebo). 3.7% (57 patients) treated with PROSCAR 5 mg and 2.1% (32 patients) treated with placebo discontinued therapy as a result of adverse reactions related to sexual function, which are the most frequently reported adverse reactions.



   Table 2  presents the only clinical adverse reactions considered possibly, probably or definitely drug related by the investigator, for which the incidence on PROSCAR was &gt;=1% and greater than placebo over the 4 years of the study. In years 2-4 of the study, there was no significant difference between treatment groups in the incidences of impotence, decreased libido and ejaculation disorder.



 TABLE 2: Drug-Related Adverse Experiences for PROSCAR (finasteride 5 mg) BENIGN PROSTATIC HYPERPLASIA 
                                  Year 1(%)          Years 2, 3 and 4(%)   
                              Finasteride, 5 mg         Placebo         Finasteride, 5 mg         Placebo       
  
 N = 1524 and 1516, finasteride vs placebo, respectively   
  
 Impotence                           8.1                  3.7                  5.1                  5.1         
 Decreased Libido                    6.4                  3.4                  2.6                  2.6         
 Decreased Volume of Ejaculate            3.7                  0.8                  1.5                  0.5         
 Ejaculation Disorder                0.8                  0.1                  0.2                  0.1         
 Breast Enlargement                  0.5                  0.1                  1.8                  1.1         
 Breast Tenderness                   0.4                  0.1                  0.7                  0.3         
 Rash                                0.5                  0.2                  0.5                  0.1         
           The adverse experience profiles in the 1-year, placebo-controlled, Phase III BPH studies and the 5-year open extensions with PROSCAR 5 mg and PLESS were similar.
 

 There is no evidence of increased sexual adverse experiences with increased duration of treatment with PROSCAR 5 mg. New reports of drug-related sexual adverse experiences decreased with duration of therapy.



 During the 4- to 6-year placebo- and comparator-controlled Medical Therapy of Prostatic Symptoms (MTOPS) study that enrolled 3047 men, there were 4 cases of breast cancer in men treated with PROSCAR but no cases in men not treated with PROSCAR. During the 4-year placebo-controlled PLESS study that enrolled 3040 men, there were 2 cases of breast cancer in placebo-treated men, but no cases were reported in men treated with PROSCAR.



 During the 7-year placebo-controlled Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT) that enrolled 18,882 men, there was 1 case of breast cancer in men treated with PROSCAR, and 1 case of breast cancer in men treated with placebo. The relationship between long-term use of finasteride and male breast neoplasia is currently unknown.



 The PCPT trial was a 7-year randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial that enrolled 18,882 healthy men &gt;=55 years of age with a normal digital rectal examination and a PSA &lt;=3.0 ng/mL. Men received either PROSCAR (finasteride 5 mg) or placebo daily. Patients were evaluated annually with PSA and digital rectal exams. Biopsies were performed for elevated PSA, an abnormal digital rectal exam, or the end of study. The incidence of Gleason score 8-10 prostate cancer was higher in men treated with finasteride (1.8%) than in those treated with placebo (1.1%). In a 4-year placebo-controlled clinical trial with another 5alpha-reductase inhibitor [AVODART (dutasteride)], similar results for Gleason score 8-10 prostate cancer were observed (1% dutasteride vs 0.5% placebo). The clinical significance of these findings with respect to use of PROPECIA by men is unknown.



 No clinical benefit has been demonstrated in patients with prostate cancer treated with PROSCAR. PROSCAR is not approved to reduce the risk of developing prostate cancer.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of PROPECIA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure:



   Hypersensitivity Reaction    :  hypersensitivity reactions such as rash, pruritus, urticaria, and angioedema (including swelling of the lips, tongue, throat, and face);



   Reproductive System:  sexual dysfunction that continued after discontinuation of treatment, including erectile dysfunction, libido disorders, ejaculation disorders, and orgasm disorders; male infertility and/or poor seminal quality (normalization or improvement of seminal quality has been reported after discontinuation of finasteride); testicular pain.  [See      Adverse Reactions (6.1)  .]  



   Neoplasms  : male breast cancer;



   Breast disorders:  breast tenderness and enlargement;



   Nervous System/Psychiatric  : depression
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  PROPECIA is not indicated for use in women or pediatric patients (  5.1  ,  5.4  ). 
 *  Women should not handle crushed or broken PROPECIA tablets when they are pregnant or may potentially be pregnant due to potential risk to a male fetus (  5.1  ,  8.1  ,  16  ). 
 *  PROPECIA causes a decrease in serum PSA levels. Any confirmed increase in PSA while on PROPECIA may signal the presence of prostate cancer and should be evaluated, even if those values are still within the normal range for men not taking a 5alpha-reductase inhibitor (  5.2  ). 
 *  5alpha-reductase inhibitors may increase the risk of high-grade prostate cancer (  5.3  ,  6.1  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Exposure of Women - Risk to Male Fetus



  PROPECIA is not indicated for use in women. Women should not handle crushed or broken PROPECIA tablets when they are pregnant or may potentially be pregnant because of the possibility of absorption of finasteride and the subsequent potential risk to a male fetus. PROPECIA tablets are coated and will prevent contact with the active ingredient during normal handling, provided that the tablets have not been broken or crushed. [See  Indications and Usage (1)  ,  Contraindications (4)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ,  How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  .]  



    5.2 Effects on Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA)



  In clinical studies with PROPECIA (finasteride, 1 mg) in men 18-41 years of age, the mean value of serum prostate specific antigen (PSA) decreased from 0.7 ng/mL at baseline to 0.5 ng/mL at Month 12. Further, in clinical studies with PROSCAR (finasteride, 5 mg) when used in older men who have benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH), PSA levels are decreased by approximately 50%. Other studies with PROSCAR showed it may also cause decreases in serum PSA in the presence of prostate cancer. These findings should be taken into account for proper interpretation of serum PSA when evaluating men treated with finasteride. Any confirmed increase from the lowest PSA value while on PROPECIA may signal the presence of prostate cancer and should be evaluated, even if PSA levels are still within the normal range for men not taking a 5alpha-reductase inhibitor. Non-compliance to therapy with PROPECIA may also affect PSA test results.



    5.3 Increased Risk of High-Grade Prostate Cancer with 5alpha-Reductase Inhibitors



  Men aged 55 and over with a normal digital rectal examination and PSA &lt;=3.0 ng/mL at baseline taking finasteride 5 mg/day (5 times the dose of PROPECIA) in the 7-year Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT) had an increased risk of Gleason score 8-10 prostate cancer (finasteride 1.8% vs placebo 1.1%). [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    . ]  Similar results were observed in a 4-year placebo-controlled clinical trial with another 5alpha-reductase inhibitor (dutasteride, AVODART) (1% dutasteride vs 0.5% placebo). 5alpha-reductase inhibitors may increase the risk of development of high-grade prostate cancer. Whether the effect of 5alpha-reductase inhibitors to reduce prostate volume, or study-related factors, impacted the results of these studies has not been established.



    5.4 Pediatric Patients



  PROPECIA is not indicated for use in pediatric patients [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
