<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="propranolol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse events were observed and have been reported in patients using propranolol.



   Cardiovascular:  Bradycardia; congestive heart failure; intensification of AV block; hypotension; paresthesia of hands; thrombocytopenic purpura; arterial insufficiency, usually of the Raynaud type.



   Central Nervous System:  Light-headedness; mental depression manifested by insomnia, lassitude, weakness, fatigue; catatonia; visual disturbances; hallucinations; vivid dreams; an acute reversible syndrome characterized by disorientation for time and place, short-term memory loss, emotional lability, slightly clouded sensorium, and decreased performance on neuropsychometrics. For immediate release formulations, fatigue, lethargy, and vivid dreams appear dose related.



   Gastrointestinal:  Nausea, vomiting, epigastric distress, abdominal cramping, diarrhea, constipation, mesenteric arterial thrombosis, ischemic colitis.



   Allergic:  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions; pharyngitis and agranulocytosis; erythematous rash; fever combined with aching and sore throat; laryngospasm; respiratory distress.



   Respiratory:  Bronchospasm.



   Hematologic:  Agranulocytosis, nonthrombocytopenic purpura, and thrombocytopenic purpura.



   Autoimmune:  Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE).



   Skin and mucous membranes:  Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, dry eyes, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme, urticaria, alopecia, SLE-like reactions, and psoriasisiform rashes. Oculomucocutaneous syndrome involving the skin, serous membranes, and conjunctivae reported for a beta-blocker (practolol) have not been associated with propranolol.



   Genitourinary:  Male impotence; Peyronie's disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
