<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="proquad" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  *  injection-site reactions (pain/tenderness/soreness, erythema, and swelling) 
 *  fever 
 *  irritability. (  6.1  ) 
   The most frequent vaccine-related adverse events reported in &gt;=5% of subjects vaccinated with ProQuad were: 
 *  *  fever 
 *  measles-like rash. (  6.1  ) 
   Systemic vaccine-related adverse events that were reported at a significantly greater rate in recipients of ProQuad than in recipients of the component vaccines administered concomitantly were: 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS or exposure during pregnancy or within three months prior to conception, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. Vaccine-related adverse reactions reported during clinical trials were assessed by the study investigators to be possibly, probably, or definitely vaccine-related and are summarized below.



     Children 12 Through 23 Months of Age Who Received a Single Dose of ProQuad  



 ProQuad was administered to 4497 children 12 through 23 months of age involved in 4 randomized clinical trials without concomitant administration with other vaccines. The safety of ProQuad was compared with the safety of M-M-R II and VARIVAX given concomitantly (N=2038) at separate injection sites. The safety profile for ProQuad was similar to the component vaccines. Children in these studies were monitored for up to 42 days postvaccination using vaccination report card-aided surveillance. Safety follow-up was obtained for 98% of children in each group. Few subjects (&lt;0.1%) who received ProQuad discontinued the study due to an adverse reaction. The race distribution of the study subjects across these studies following a first dose of ProQuad was as follows: 65.2% White; 13.1% African-American; 11.1% Hispanic; 5.8% Asian/Pacific; 4.5% other; and 0.2% American Indian. The racial distribution of the control group was similar to that of the group who received ProQuad. The gender distribution across the studies following a first dose of ProQuad was 52.5% male and 47.5% female. The gender distribution of the control group was similar to that of the group who received ProQuad. Vaccine-related injection-site and systemic adverse reactions observed among recipients of ProQuad or M-M-R II and VARIVAX at a rate of at least 1% are shown in Table 1. Systemic vaccine-related adverse reactions that were reported at a significantly greater rate in individuals who received a first dose of ProQuad than in individuals who received first doses of M-M-R II and VARIVAX concomitantly at separate injection sites were fever (&gt;=102 degrees F [&gt;=38.9 degrees C] oral equivalent or abnormal) (21.5% versus 14.9%, respectively, risk difference 6.6%, 95% CI: 4.6, 8.5), and measles-like rash (3.0% versus 2.1%, respectively, risk difference 1.0%, 95% CI: 0.1, 1.8). Both fever and measles-like rash usually occurred within 5 to 12 days following the vaccination, were of short duration, and resolved with no long-term sequelae. Pain/tenderness/soreness at the injection site was reported at a statistically lower rate in individuals who received ProQuad than in individuals who received M-M-R II and VARIVAX concomitantly at separate injection sites (22.0% versus 26.8%, respectively, risk difference -4.8%, 95% CI: -7.1, -2.5). The only vaccine-related injection-site adverse reaction that was more frequent among recipients of ProQuad than recipients of M-M-R II and VARIVAX was rash at the injection site (2.4% versus 1.6%, respectively, risk difference 0.9%, 95% CI: 0.1, 1.5).



 Table 1: Vaccine-Related Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Who Received ProQuad Dose 1 or M-M-R II and VARIVAX at 12 to 23 Months of Age (0 to 42 Days Postvaccination) 
                                                ProQuad(N=4497)          M-M-R II and VARIVAX(N=2038)       
 Adverse Reactions                                 (n=4424)%                       (n=1997)%                
  
 N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Injection Site                                                                                           
   Pain/tenderness/soreness                          22.0                            26.7                   
   Erythema                                          14.4                            15.8                   
   Swelling                                           8.4                             9.8                   
   Ecchymosis                                         1.5                             2.3                   
   Rash                                               2.3                             1.5                   
   Systemic                                                                                                 
   Fever  ,                                          21.5                            14.9                   
   Irritability                                       6.7                             6.7                   
   Measles-like rash                                  3.0                             2.1                   
   Varicella-like rash                                2.1                             2.2                   
   Rash (not otherwise specified)                     1.6                             1.4                   
   Upper respiratory infection                        1.3                             1.1                   
   Viral exanthema                                    1.2                             1.1                   
   Diarrhea                                           1.2                             1.3                   
         Rubella-like rashes were observed in &lt;1% of subjects following a first dose of ProQuad.
 

 In these clinical trials, two cases of herpes zoster were reported among 2108 healthy subjects 12 through 23 months of age who were vaccinated with their first dose of ProQuad and followed for 1 year. Both cases were unremarkable and no sequelae were reported.



     Children 15 to 31 Months of Age Who Received a Second Dose of ProQuad  



 In 5 clinical trials, 2780 healthy children were vaccinated with ProQuad (dose 1) at 12 to 23 months of age and then administered a second dose approximately 3 to 9 months later. The race distribution of the study subjects across these studies following a second dose of ProQuad was as follows: 64.4% White; 14.1% African-American; 12.0% Hispanic; 5.9% other; 3.5% Asian/Pacific; and 0.1% American Indian. The gender distribution across the studies following a second dose of ProQuad was 51.5% male and 48.5% female. Children in these open-label studies were monitored for at least 28 days postvaccination using vaccination report card-aided surveillance. Safety follow-up was obtained for approximately 97% of children overall. Vaccine-related injection-site and systemic adverse reactions observed after Dose 1 and 2 of ProQuad at a rate of at least 1% are shown in Table 2. In these trials, the overall rates of systemic adverse reactions after ProQuad (dose 2) were comparable to, or lower than, those seen with the first dose. In the subset of children who received both ProQuad dose 1 and dose 2 in these trials (N=2408) with follow-up for fever, fever &gt;=102.2 degrees F (&gt;=38.9 degrees C) was observed significantly less frequently days 1 to 28 after the second dose (10.8%) than after the first dose (19.1%) (risk difference 8.3%, 95% CI: 6.4, 10.3). Fevers &gt;=102.2 degrees F (&gt;=38.9 degrees C) days 5 to 12 after vaccinations were also reported significantly less frequently after dose 2 (3.9%) than after dose 1 (13.6%) (risk difference 9.7%, 95% CI: 8.1, 11.3). In the subset of children who received both doses and for whom injection-site reactions were reported (N=2679), injection-site erythema was noted significantly more frequently after ProQuad (dose 2) as compared to ProQuad (dose 1) (12.6% and 10.8%, respectively, risk difference -1.8, 95% CI: -3.3, -0.3); however, pain and tenderness at the injection site was significantly lower after dose 2 (16.1%) as compared with after dose 1 (21.9%) (risk difference, 5.8%, 95% CI: 4.1, 7.6). Two children had febrile seizures after ProQuad (dose 2); both febrile seizures were thought to be related to a concurrent viral illness  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  and  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . These studies were not designed or statistically powered to detect a difference in rates of febrile seizure between recipients of ProQuad as compared to M-M-R II and VARIVAX. The risk of febrile seizure has not been evaluated in a clinical study comparing the incidence rate after ProQuad (dose 2) with the incidence rate after concomitant M-M-R II (dose 2) and VARIVAX (dose 2).  [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1), Children 4 to 6 Years of Age Who Received ProQuad After Primary Vaccination with M-M-R II and VARIVAX  .]  



 Table 2: Vaccine-Related Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Who Received ProQuad Dose 1 at 12 to 23 Months of Age and Dose 2 at 15 to 31 Months of Age (1 to 28 Days Postvaccination) 
                                                           ProQuadDose 1              ProQuadDose 2         
 Adverse Reactions                                       (N=3112)(n=3019)%          (N=2780)(n=2695)%       
  
 N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Injection-Site                                                                                           
   Pain/tenderness/soreness                                    21.4                       15.9              
   Erythema                                                    10.7                       12.4              
   Swelling                                                     8.0                        8.5              
   Injection-site bruising                                      1.1                        0.0              
   Systemic                                                                                                 
   Fever  ,                                                    20.4                        8.3              
   Irritability                                                 6.0                        2.4              
   Measles-like/Rubella-like rash                               4.3                        0.9              
   Varicella-like/Vesicular rash                                1.5                        0.1              
   Diarrhea                                                     1.3                        0.6              
   Upper respiratory infection                                  1.3                        1.4              
   Rash (not otherwise specified)                               1.2                        0.6              
   Rhinorrhea                                                   1.1                        1.0              
               Children 4 to 6 Years of Age Who Received ProQuad After Primary Vaccination with M-M-R II and VARIVAX    
 

 In a double-blind clinical trial, 799 healthy 4- to 6-year-old children who received M-M-R II and VARIVAX at least 1 month prior to study entry were randomized to receive ProQuad and placebo (N=399), M-M-R II and placebo concomitantly (N=205) at separate injection sites, or M-M-R II and VARIVAX (N=195) concomitantly at separate injection sites  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . Children in these studies were monitored for up to 42 days postvaccination using vaccination report card-aided surveillance. Safety follow-up was obtained for &gt;98% of children in each group. The race distribution of the study subjects following a dose of ProQuad was as follows: 78.4% White; 12.3% African-American; 3.8% Hispanic; 3.5% other; and 2.0% Asian/Pacific. The gender distribution following a dose of ProQuad was 52.1% male and 47.9% female. Injection-site and systemic adverse reactions observed after Dose 1 and 2 of ProQuad at a rate of at least 1% are shown in Table 3.  [See  Clinical Studies (14)  .]  



 Table 3: Vaccine-Related Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Previously Vaccinated with M-M-R II and VARIVAX Who Received ProQuad + Placebo, M-M-R II + Placebo, or M-M-R II + VARIVAX at 4 to 6 Years of Age (1 to 43 Days Postvaccination) 
 Adverse Reactions                         ProQuad + Placebo(N=399)(n=397)%  M-M-R II + Placebo(N=205)(n=205)%  M-M-R II + VARIVAX(N=195)(n=193)%   
  
 N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Systemic                                                                     
   Fever  ,                                   2.5         2.0         4.1       
   Cough                                      1.3         0.5         0.5       
   Irritability                               1.0         0.5         1.0       
   Headache                                   0.8         1.5         1.6       
   Rhinorrhea                                 0.5         1.0         0.5       
   Nasopharyngitis                            0.3         1.0         1.0       
   Vomiting                                   0.3         1.0         0.5       
   Upper respiratory infection                0.0         0.0         1.0       
                                            ProQuad%    Placebo%   M-M-R II%    Placebo%   M-M-R II%    VARIVAX%    
   Injection-Site                                                                                                   
   Pain                                       41.1        34.5        36.6        34.1        35.2        36.8      
   Erythema                                   24.4        13.4        15.6        14.1        14.5        15.5      
   Swelling                                   15.6        8.1         10.2        8.8         7.8         10.9      
   Bruising                                   3.5         3.8         2.4         3.4         1.6         2.1       
   Rash                                       1.5         1.3         0.0         0.0         0.5         0.0       
   Pruritus                                   1.0         0.3         0.0         0.0         0.0         1.0       
   Nodule                                     0.0         0.0         0.0         0.0         0.0         1.0       
                 Safety in Trials That Evaluated Concomitant Use with Other Vaccines  
 

       ProQuad Administered with Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed (DTaP) and Haemophilus influenzae type b Conjugate (Meningococcal Protein Conjugate) and Hepatitis B (Recombinant) Vaccine    



 In an open-label clinical trial, 1434 children were randomized to receive ProQuad given with diphtheria and tetanus toxoids and acellular pertussis vaccine adsorbed (DTaP) and  Haemophilus influenzae  type b conjugate (meningococcal protein conjugate) and hepatitis B (recombinant) vaccine concomitantly (N=949) or non-concomitantly with ProQuad given first and the other vaccines 6 weeks later (N=485). No clinically significant differences in adverse events were reported between treatment groups  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . The race distribution of the study subjects who received ProQuad was as follows: 70.7% White; 10.9% Asian/Pacific; 10.7% African-American; 4.5% Hispanic; 3.0% other; and 0.2% American Indian. The gender distribution of the study subjects who received ProQuad was 53.6% male and 46.4% female.



     ProQuad Administered with Pneumococcal 7-valent Conjugate Vaccine and/or Hepatitis A Vaccine, Inactivated  



 In an open-label clinical trial, 1027 healthy children 12 to 23 months of age were randomized to receive ProQuad (dose 1) and pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine (dose 4) concomitantly (N=510) or non-concomitantly at different clinic visits (N=517). The race distribution of the study subjects was as follows: 65.2% White; 15.1% African-American; 10.0% Hispanic; 6.6% other; and 3.0% Asian/Pacific. The gender distribution of the study subjects was 54.5% male and 45.5% female. Injection-site and systemic adverse reactions observed among recipients of ProQuad administered concomitantly or non-concomitantly with pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine at a rate of at least 1% are shown in Table 4. No clinically significant differences in adverse reactions were reported between the concomitant and non-concomitant treatment groups  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .



 Table 4: Vaccine-Related Injection-Site and Systemic Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Who Received ProQuad (dose 1) Concomitantly or Non-Concomitantly with PCV7PCV7 = Pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine, dose 4. (dose 4) at the First Visit (1 to 28 Days Postvaccination) 
 Adverse Reactions                         ProQuad + PCV7(N=510)(n=498)%  PCV7(N=258)(n=250)%   ProQuad(N=259)(n=255)%   
  
 N/A = Not applicable.N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Injection-Site - ProQuad                                                                                   
   Pain                                            24.9                  N/A                   24.7           
   Erythema                                        12.4                  N/A                   11.0           
   Swelling                                        10.8                  N/A                   7.5            
   Bruising                                        2.0                   N/A                   1.6            
   Injection-Site - PCV7                                                                                      
   Pain                                            30.5                  29.6                  N/A            
   Erythema                                        21.1                  24.4                  N/A            
   Swelling                                        17.9                  20.0                  N/A            
   Bruising                                        1.6                   1.2                   N/A            
   Systemic                                                                                                   
   Fever  ,                                        15.5                  10.0                  15.3           
   Measles-like rash                               4.4                   0.8                   5.1            
   Irritability                                    3.8                   3.6                   3.5            
   Upper respiratory infection                     1.6                   0.8                   1.2            
   Varicella-like/vesicular rash                   1.6                   0.0                   1.2            
   Diarrhea                                        0.8                   1.2                   1.2            
   Vomiting                                        0.6                   0.8                   1.2            
   Rash                                            0.4                   0.0                   1.2            
   Somnolence                                      0.0                   0.0                   1.2            
          In an open-label clinical trial, 699 healthy children 12 to 23 months of age were randomized to receive 2 doses of VAQTA(r) (hepatitis A vaccine, inactivated) (N=352) or 2 doses of VAQTA concomitantly with 2 doses of ProQuad (N=347) at least 6 months apart. An additional 1101 subjects received 2 doses of VAQTA alone at least 6 months apart (non-randomized), resulting in 1453 subjects receiving 2 doses of VAQTA alone (1101 non-randomized and 352 randomized) and 347 subjects receiving 2 doses of VAQTA concomitantly with ProQuad (all randomized). The race distribution of the study subjects following a dose of ProQuad was as follows: 47.3% White; 42.7% Hispanic; 5.5% other; 2.9% African-American; and 1.7% Asian/Pacific. The gender distribution of the study subjects following a dose of ProQuad was 49.3% male and 50.7% female. Vaccine-related injection-site adverse reactions (days 1 to 5 postvaccination) and systemic adverse events (days 1 to 14 post VAQTA and days 1 to 28 post ProQuad vaccination) observed among recipients of VAQTA and ProQuad administered concomitantly with VAQTA at a rate of at least 1% are shown in Tables 5 and 6, respectively. In addition, among the randomized cohort, in the 14 days after each vaccination, the rates of fever (including all vaccine- and non-vaccine-related reports) were significantly higher in subjects who received ProQuad with VAQTA concomitantly after dose 1 (22.0%) as compared to subjects given dose 1 of VAQTA without ProQuad (10.8%). However, rates of fever were not significantly higher in subjects who received ProQuad with VAQTA concomitantly after dose 2 (12.5%) as compared to subjects given dose 2 of VAQTA without ProQuad (9.4%). In post-hoc analyses, these rates were significantly different for dose 1 (relative risk (RR) 2.03 [95% CI: 1.42, 2.94]), but not dose 2 (RR 1.32 [95% CI: 0.82, 2.13]). Rates of injection-site adverse reactions and other systemic adverse events were lower following a second dose than following the first dose of both vaccines given concomitantly.
 

 Table 5: Vaccine-Related Injection-Site Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Who Received VAQTA or ProQuad Concomitantly with VAQTA 1 to 5 Days After Vaccination with VAQTA or VAQTA and ProQuad 
                                     Dose 1              Dose 2          
 Adverse Reactions               VAQTA(N=1453)(n=1412)%  ProQuad + VAQTA(N=347)(n=328)%  VAQTA(N=1301)(n=1254)%  ProQuad + VAQTA(N=292)(n=264)%   
  
 N/A = Not applicable.N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Injection-Site - VAQTA                                                                                       
   Pain/tenderness                    29.2                27.1               30.1                25.0           
   Erythema                           13.5                12.5               14.3                11.7           
   Swelling                            7.1                9.1                 9.0                8.0            
   Injection-site bruising             1.9                2.4                 1.0                0.8            
   Injection-Site - ProQuad                                                                                     
   Pain/tenderness                     N/A                30.5                N/A                26.2           
   Erythema                            N/A                13.4                N/A                12.9           
   Swelling                            N/A                6.7                 N/A                6.5            
   Injection-site bruising             N/A                1.5                 N/A                0.4            
          Table 6: Vaccine-Related Systemic Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Who Received VAQTASystemic adverse events for subjects given VAQTA alone were collected for 14 days postvaccination. or ProQuad Concomitantly with VAQTA 1 to 14 Days After VAQTA or Vaccination with ProQuad and VAQTA and 1 to 28 Days After Vaccination with ProQuad and VAQTA 
 Adverse Reactions             Dose 1        Dose 2       
 Days 1 to 14               Days 1 to 28  Days 1 to 14   Days 1 to 28    
 VAQTA(N=1453)(n=1412)%     ProQuad + VAQTA(N=347)(n=328)%  ProQuad + VAQTA(N=347)(n=328)%  VAQTA(N=1301)(n=1254)%  ProQuad + VAQTA(N=292)(n=264)%  ProQuad + VAQTA(N=291)(n=263)%   
  
 N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Fever  ,                     5.7           14.9           15.2           4.1            8.0           8.4        
   Irritability                 5.8            7.0            7.3           3.5            5.3           5.3        
   Measles-like rash            0.0            3.4            3.4           0.0            1.1           1.1        
   Rhinorrhea                   0.6            2.7            3.0           0.6            1.1           2.7        
   Diarrhea                     1.5            1.8            2.4           1.7            0.4           0.8        
   Cough                        0.6            2.1            2.1           0.2            0.8           1.5        
   Vomiting                     1.1            0.3            0.9           0.6            0.8           1.1        
             In an open-label clinical trial, 653 children 12 to 23 months of age were randomized to receive a first dose of ProQuad with VAQTA and pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine concomitantly (N=330) or a first dose of ProQuad and pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine concomitantly and then vaccinated with VAQTA 6 weeks later (N=323). Approximately 6 months later, subjects received either the second doses of ProQuad and VAQTA concomitantly or the second doses of ProQuad and VAQTA separately. The race distribution of the study subjects was as follows: 60.3% White; 21.6% African-American; 9.5% Hispanic; 7.2% other; 1.1% Asian/Pacific; and 0.3% American Indian. The gender distribution of the study subjects was 50.7% male and 49.3% female. Vaccine-related injection-site and systemic adverse reactions observed among recipients of concomitant ProQuad, VAQTA, and pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine and ProQuad and pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine at a rate of at least 1% are shown in Tables 7 and 8. In the 28 days after vaccination with the first dose of ProQuad, the rates of fever (including all vaccine- and non-vaccine-related reports) were comparable in subjects who received the 3 vaccines together (38.6%) as compared with subjects given ProQuad and pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine (42.7%). The rates of fever in the 28 days following the second dose of ProQuad were also comparable in subjects who received ProQuad and VAQTA together (17.4%) as compared with subjects given ProQuad separately from VAQTA (17.0%). In a post-hoc analysis, these differences were not statistically significant after ProQuad (dose 1) (RR 0.90 [95% CI: 0.75, 1.09]) nor after dose 2 (RR 1.02 [95% CI: 0.70, 1.51]). No clinically significant differences in adverse reactions were reported among treatment groups  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .
 

 Table 7: Vaccine-Related Injection-Site Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Who Received ProQuad + VAQTA + PCV7PCV7 = Pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine. Concomitantly or VAQTA Alone Followed by ProQuad + PCV7 Concomitantly (1 to 5 Days After a Dose of ProQuad) 
 Adverse Reactions                      Dose 1             Dose 2         
                                   VAQTA + ProQuad + PCV7(N=330)(n=311)%  VAQTA Alone Followed by ProQuad + PCV7(N=323)(n=302)%  VAQTA + ProQuad(N=273)(n=265)%  VAQTA Alone Followed by ProQuad(N=240)(n=230)%   
  
 N/A = Not applicable.N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Injection-Site - ProQuad                                                                                     
   Pain/tenderness                       21.2               24.2               18.1               17.0          
   Erythema                              13.5               11.9               10.6               13.0          
   Swelling                               7.4               10.9                8.3               11.7          
   Bruising                               1.9                1.3                0.8                0.4          
   Injection-Site - VAQTA                                                                                       
   Pain/tenderness                       20.6               15.3               17.5               20.3          
   Erythema                               9.6               11.7                9.1               12.7          
   Swelling                               6.8                9.5                6.1                7.6          
   Bruising                               1.3                1.1                1.1                1.6          
   Rash                                   1.0                0.0                0.4                0.4          
   Injection-Site - PCV7                                                                                        
   Pain/tenderness                       25.4               27.6                N/A                N/A          
   Erythema                              16.4               16.6                N/A                N/A          
   Swelling                              13.2               14.3                N/A                N/A          
   Bruising                               0.6                1.7                N/A                N/A          
          Table 8: Vaccine-Related Systemic Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=1% of Children Who Received ProQuad + VAQTA + PCV7PCV7 = Pneumococcal 7-valent conjugate vaccine. Concomitantly, or VAQTA Alone Followed by ProQuad + PCV7 Concomitantly (1 to 28 Days After a Dose of ProQuad) 
 Adverse Reactions                      Dose 1             Dose 2         
                                   VAQTA + ProQuad + PCV7(N=330)(n=311)%  VAQTA Alone Followed by ProQuad + PCV7(N=323)(n=302)%  VAQTA + ProQuad(N=273)(n=265)%  VAQTA Alone Followed by ProQuad(N=240)(n=230)%   
  
 N = number of subjects vaccinated.n = number of subjects with safety follow-up.   
  
   Fever  ,                              26.4               27.2                9.1                9.6          
   Irritability                           4.8                6.3                1.9                1.3          
   Measles-like rash                      2.3                4.0                0.0                0.0          
   Varicella-like rash                    1.0                1.7                0.0                0.0          
   Rash (not otherwise specified)         1.3                1.3                0.0                0.9          
   Diarrhea                               1.3                1.3                0.4                1.3          
   Upper respiratory infection            1.0                1.3                1.1                0.9          
   Viral infection                        1.0                0.7                0.0                0.0          
   Rhinorrhea                             0.0                0.7                1.1                0.0          
           Reye syndrome following wild-type varicella infection has occurred in children and adolescents, the majority of whom had received salicylates. In all clinical studies of ProQuad or VARIVAX, the recommendation was made to avoid the use of salicylates for 6 weeks after vaccination. There were no reports of Reye syndrome in recipients of ProQuad or VARIVAX during these studies  [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  .
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been identified during post-approval use of either the components of ProQuad or ProQuad. Because the reactions are in some cases described in the literature or reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship.



     Post-Marketing Reports  



 Adverse events reported with post-marketing use of ProQuad and/or in clinical studies and/or post-marketing use of M-M-R II, the component vaccines, and VARIVAX without regard to causality or frequency are summarized below.



   Infections and infestations  



 Atypical measles, candidiasis, cellulitis, herpes zoster, infection, influenza, measles, orchitis, parotitis, respiratory infection, skin infection, varicella (vaccine strain).



   Blood and the lymphatic system disorders  



 Aplastic anemia, lymphadenitis, regional lymphadenopathy, thrombocytopenia.



   Immune system disorders  



 Anaphylactoid reaction, anaphylaxis and related phenomena such as angioneurotic edema, facial edema, and peripheral edema, anaphylaxis in individuals with or without an allergic history.



   Psychiatric disorders  



 Agitation, apathy, nervousness.



   Nervous system disorders  



 Acute disseminated encephalomyelitis (ADEM), afebrile convulsions or seizures, aseptic meningitis (see below), ataxia, Bell's palsy, cerebrovascular accident, convulsion, dizziness, dream abnormality, encephalitis (see below), encephalopathy (see below), febrile seizure, Guillain-Barre syndrome, headache, hypersomnia, measles inclusion body encephalitis  [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ]  , ocular palsies, paraesthesia, polyneuritis, polyneuropathy, subacute sclerosing panencephalitis (see below), syncope, transverse myelitis, tremor.



   Eye disorders  



 Edema of the eyelid, irritation, necrotizing retinitis (in immunocompromised individuals), optic neuritis, retinitis, retrobulbar neuritis.



   Ear and labyrinth disorders  



 Ear pain, nerve deafness.



   Vascular disorders  



 Extravasation.



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  



 Bronchial spasm, bronchitis, epistaxis, pneumonitis  [see  Contraindications (4.3)  ]  , pneumonia, pulmonary congestion, rhinitis, sinusitis, sneezing, sore throat, wheezing.



   Gastrointestinal disorders  



 Abdominal pain, flatulence, hematochezia, mouth ulcer.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  



 Erythema multiforme, Henoch-Schonlein purpura, herpes simplex, impetigo, panniculitis, pruritus, purpura, skin induration, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, sunburn.



   Musculoskeletal, connective tissue and bone disorders  



 Arthritis and/or arthralgia (usually transient and rarely chronic, see below); musculoskeletal pain; myalgia; pain of the hip, leg, or neck; swelling.



   Reproductive system and breast disorders  



 Epididymitis.



   General disorders and administration site conditions  



 Injection-site complaints (burning and/or stinging of short duration, eczema, edema/swelling, hive-like rash, discoloration, hematoma, induration, lump, vesicles, wheal and flare), inflammation, lip abnormality, papillitis, roughness/dryness, stiffness, trauma, varicella-like rash, venipuncture site hemorrhage, warm sensation, warm to touch.



 Deaths have been reported following vaccination with measles, mumps, and rubella vaccines; however, a causal relationship has not been established in healthy individuals. Death as a direct consequence of disseminated measles vaccine virus infection has been reported in severely immunocompromised individuals in whom a measles-containing vaccine is contraindicated and who were inadvertently vaccinated. However, there were no deaths or permanent sequelae reported in a published post-marketing surveillance study in Finland involving 1.5 million children and adults who were vaccinated with M-M-R II during 1982 to 1993 {3}.



 Encephalitis and encephalopathy have been reported approximately once for every 3 million doses of the combination of measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine contained in M-M-R II. In no case has it been shown conclusively that reactions were actually caused by the vaccine; however, the data suggest the possibility that some of these cases may have been caused by measles vaccines. The risk of such serious neurological disorders following live measles virus vaccine administration remains far less than that for encephalitis and encephalopathy with wild-type measles (1 per 2000 reported cases).



 Recipients of rubella vaccine may develop chronic joint symptoms. Arthralgia and/or arthritis, and polyneuritis after wild-type rubella virus infection vary in frequency and severity with age and gender, being greatest in adult females and least in pre-pubertal children. Following vaccination in children, reactions in joints are uncommon (0 to 3%) and of brief duration. In women, incidence rates for arthritis and arthralgia are higher than those seen in children (12 to 26%), and the reactions tend to be more marked and of longer duration (  e.g.  , months or years). In adolescent girls, the reactions appear to be intermediate in incidence between those seen in children and adult women.



 Chronic arthritis has been associated with wild-type rubella infection and has been related to persistent virus and/or viral antigen isolated from body tissues. Chronic joint symptoms have been reported following administration of rubella-containing vaccine.



 There have been reports of subacute sclerosing panencephalitis (SSPE) in children who did not have a history of infection with wild-type measles but did receive measles vaccine. Some of these cases may have resulted from unrecognized measles in the first year of life or possibly from the measles vaccination. Based on estimated measles vaccine distribution in the United States (US), the association of SSPE cases to measles vaccination is about one case per million vaccine doses distributed. The association with wild-type measles virus infection is 6 to 22 cases of SSPE per million cases of measles. The results of a retrospective case-controlled study suggest that the overall effect of measles vaccine has been to protect against SSPE by preventing measles with its inherent higher risk of SSPE.



 Cases of aseptic meningitis have been reported to Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS) following measles, mumps, and rubella vaccination. Although a causal relationship between other strains of mumps vaccine and aseptic meningitis has been shown, there is no evidence to link Jeryl LynnTM mumps vaccine to aseptic meningitis.



 Cases of thrombocytopenia have been reported after use of measles vaccine; measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine; and after varicella vaccination. Post-marketing experience with live measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine indicates that individuals with current thrombocytopenia may develop more severe thrombocytopenia following vaccination. In addition, individuals who experienced thrombocytopenia following the first dose of a live measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine may develop thrombocytopenia with repeat doses. Serologic testing for antibody to measles, mumps, or rubella should be considered in order to determine if additional doses of vaccine are needed  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



 The reported rate of zoster in recipients of VARIVAX appears not to exceed that previously determined in a population-based study of healthy children who had experienced wild-type varicella {4}. In clinical trials, 8 cases of herpes zoster were reported in 9454 vaccinated individuals 12 months to 12 years of age during 42,556 person-years of follow-up. This resulted in a calculated incidence of at least 18.8 cases per 100,000 person-years. All 8 cases reported after VARIVAX were mild and no sequelae were reported. The long-term effect of VARIVAX on the incidence of herpes zoster is unknown at present.



   6.3 Post-Marketing Observational Safety Surveillance Study

  Safety was evaluated in an observational study that included 69,237 children vaccinated with ProQuad 12 months to 12 years old. A historical comparison group included 69,237 age-, gender-, and date-of-vaccination (day and month) matched subjects who were given M-M-R II and VARIVAX concomitantly. The primary objective was to assess the incidence of febrile seizures occurring within various time intervals after vaccination in 12- to 60-month-old children who had neither been vaccinated against measles, mumps, rubella, or varicella, nor had a history of the wild-type infections (N=31,298 vaccinated with ProQuad, including 31,043 who were 12 to 23 months old). The incidence of febrile seizures was also assessed in a historical control group of children who had received their first vaccination with M-M-R II and VARIVAX concomitantly (N=31,298, including 31,019 who were 12 to 23 months old). The secondary objective was to assess the general safety of ProQuad in the 30-day period after vaccination in children 12 months to 12 years old.



 In pre-licensure clinical studies, an increase in fever was observed 5 to 12 days after vaccination with ProQuad (dose 1) compared to M-M-R II and VARIVAX (dose 1) given concomitantly. In the post-marketing observational surveillance study, results from the primary safety analysis revealed an approximate two-fold increase in the risk of febrile seizures in the same 5 to 12 day timeframe after vaccination with ProQuad (dose 1). The incidence of febrile seizures 5 to 12 days after ProQuad (dose 1) (0.70 per 1000 children) was higher than that in children receiving M-M-R II and VARIVAX concomitantly (0.32 per 1000 children) [RR 2.20, 95% confidence interval (CI): 1.04, 4.65]. The incidence of febrile seizures 0 to 30 days after ProQuad (dose 1) (1.41 per 1000 children) was similar to that observed in children receiving M-M-R II and VARIVAX concomitantly [RR 1.10 (95% CI: 0.72, 1.69)]. See  Table 9  . General safety analyses revealed that the risks of fever (RR=1.89; 95% CI: 1.67, 2.15) and skin eruption (RR=1.68; 95% CI: 1.07, 2.64) were significantly higher after ProQuad (dose 1) compared with those who received concomitant first doses of M-M-R II and VARIVAX, respectively. All medical events that resulted in hospitalization or emergency room visits were compared between the group given ProQuad and the historical comparison group, and no other safety concerns were identified in this study.



 Table 9: Confirmed Febrile Seizures Days 5 to 12 and 0 to 30 After Vaccination with ProQuad (dose 1) Compared to Concomitant Vaccination with M-M-R II and VARIVAX (dose 1) in Children 12 to 60 Months of Age 
 Time Period           ProQuad cohort (N=31,298)  MMR+V cohort (N=31,298)  Relative risk (95% CI)   
 n                     Incidence per 1000         n         Incidence per 1000   
  
 5 to 12 Days              22           0.70            10           0.32              2.20 (1.04, 4.65)          
 0 to 30 Days              44           1.41            40           1.28              1.10 (0.72, 1.69)          
            In this observational post-marketing study, no case of febrile seizure was observed during the 5 to 12 day post-vaccination time period among 26,455 children who received ProQuad as a second dose of M-M-R II and VARIVAX. In addition, detailed general safety data were available from more than 25,000 children who received ProQuad as a second dose of M-M-R II and VARIVAX, most of them (95%) between 4 and 6 years of age, and an analysis of these data by an independent, external safety monitoring committee did not identify any specific safety concern.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Administration of ProQuad (dose 1) to children 12 to 23 months old who have not been previously vaccinated against measles, mumps, rubella, or varicella, nor had a history of the wild-type infections, is associated with higher rates of fever and febrile seizures at 5 to 12 days after vaccination when compared to children vaccinated with M-M-R(r) II and VARIVAX(r) administered separately. (  5.1  ,  6.1  ,  6.3  ) 
 *  Use caution when administering ProQuad to children with a history of cerebral injury or seizures or any other condition in which stress due to fever should be avoided. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Use caution when administering ProQuad to children with anaphylaxis or immediate hypersensitivity to eggs (  5.3  ) or contact hypersensitivity to neomycin. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Use caution when administering ProQuad to children with thrombocytopenia. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Avoid close contact with high-risk individuals susceptible to varicella since transmission of varicella vaccine virus may occur between vaccinees and susceptible contacts. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Defer vaccination for at least 3 months following blood or plasma transfusions, or administration of immune globulins (IG). (  5.9  ,  7.1  ) 
 *  Avoid using salicylates for 6 weeks after vaccination with ProQuad. (  6.1  ,  7.2  ,  17  ) 
 *  Avoid pregnancy for 3 months following vaccination with measles, mumps, rubella, and/or varicella vaccines. (  8.1  ,  17  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Fever and Febrile Seizures



  Administration of ProQuad (dose 1) to children 12 to 23 months old who have not been previously vaccinated against measles, mumps, rubella, or varicella, nor had a history of the wild-type infections, is associated with higher rates of fever and febrile seizures at 5 to 12 days after vaccination when compared to children vaccinated with dose 1 of both M-M-R II and VARIVAX administered separately [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .



    5.2 History of Cerebral Injury or Seizures



  Exercise caution when administering ProQuad to persons with a history of cerebral injury, individual or family history of convulsions, or any other condition in which stress due to fever should be avoided. Healthcare providers should be alert to the temperature elevations that may occur following vaccination.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity to Eggs



  Live measles vaccine and live mumps vaccine are produced in chick embryo cell culture. Persons with a history of anaphylactic or other immediate hypersensitivity reactions ( e.g.  , hives, swelling of the mouth and throat, difficulty breathing, hypotension, or shock) subsequent to egg ingestion may be at an enhanced risk of immediate-type hypersensitivity reactions after receiving vaccines containing traces of chick embryo antigen. Carefully evaluate the potential risk-to-benefit ratio before considering vaccination in such cases. Such individuals may be vaccinated with extreme caution; adequate treatment should be readily available should a reaction occur [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  {2}.



 Children with egg allergy are at low risk for anaphylactic reactions to measles-containing vaccines (including M-M-R II), and skin testing of children allergic to eggs is not predictive of reactions to M-M-R II vaccine. Persons with allergies to chickens or feathers are not at increased risk of reaction to the vaccine {2}.



    5.4 Contact Hypersensitivity to Neomycin



  Most often, neomycin allergy manifests as a contact dermatitis, which is not a contraindication to receiving measles-, mumps-, rubella-, or varicella-containing vaccine.



    5.5 Thrombocytopenia



  Carefully evaluate the potential risk-to-benefit ratio before considering vaccination with ProQuad in children with thrombocytopenia or in those who experienced thrombocytopenia after vaccination with a previous dose of measles, mumps, rubella, and/or varicella vaccine. No clinical data are available regarding the development or worsening of thrombocytopenia in individuals vaccinated with ProQuad. Cases of thrombocytopenia have been reported after primary vaccination with measles vaccine; measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine; after varicella vaccination; and following re-vaccination with measles vaccine or M-M-R II [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  .



    5.6 Use for Post-Exposure Prophylaxis



  The safety and efficacy of ProQuad for use after exposure to measles, mumps, rubella, or varicella have not been established.



    5.7 Use in HIV-Infected Children



  The safety and efficacy of ProQuad for use in children known to be infected with human immunodeficiency viruses have not been established.



    5.8 Risk of Vaccine Virus Transmission



  Post-licensing experience with VARIVAX suggests that transmission of varicella vaccine virus may occur between healthy vaccine recipients (who develop or do not develop a varicella-like rash) and contacts susceptible to varicella, as well as high-risk individuals susceptible to varicella.



 High-risk individuals susceptible to varicella include:



 *  Immunocompromised individuals; 
 *  Pregnant women without documented positive history of varicella (chickenpox) or laboratory evidence of prior infection; 
 *  Newborn infants of mothers without documented positive history of varicella or laboratory evidence of prior infection and all newborn infants born at &lt;28 weeks gestation regardless of maternal varicella immunity. 
    Vaccine recipients should attempt to avoid, to the extent possible, close association with high-risk individuals susceptible to varicella for up to 6 weeks following vaccination. In circumstances where contact with high-risk individuals susceptible to varicella is unavoidable, the potential risk of transmission of the varicella vaccine virus should be weighed against the risk of acquiring and transmitting wild-type varicella virus.
 

 Excretion of small amounts of the live, attenuated rubella virus from the nose or throat has occurred in the majority of susceptible individuals 7 to 28 days after vaccination. There is no confirmed evidence to indicate that such virus is transmitted to susceptible persons who are in contact with the vaccinated individuals. Consequently, transmission through close personal contact, while accepted as a theoretical possibility, is not regarded as a significant risk. However, transmission of the rubella vaccine virus to infants via breast milk has been documented [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.3)  ]  .



 There are no reports of transmission of the more attenuated Enders' Edmonston strain of measles virus or the Jeryl LynnTM strain of mumps virus from vaccine recipients to susceptible contacts.



    5.9 Immune Globulins and Transfusions



  Immune globulins (IG) administered concomitantly with ProQuad contain antibodies that may interfere with vaccine virus replication and decrease the expected immune response. Vaccination should be deferred for at least 3 months following blood or plasma transfusions, or administration of IG.



 The appropriate suggested interval between transfusion or IG administration and vaccination will vary with the type of transfusion or indication for, and dose of, IG ( e.g.  , 5 months for Varicella Zoster Immune Globulin [VZIG]) {2}. Following administration of ProQuad, any IG including VZIG should not be given for 1 month thereafter unless its use outweighs the benefits of vaccination {2}. [See  Drug Interactions (7.1)  .]  



    5.10 Risk of Transmission of Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease and Other Adventitious Agents



  This product contains albumin, a derivative of human blood. Based on effective donor screening and product manufacturing processes, it carries an extremely remote risk for transmission of viral diseases. Although there is a theoretical risk for transmission of Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD), no cases of transmission of CJD or viral disease have ever been identified that were associated with the use of albumin. The cells, virus pools, bovine serum, and human albumin used in manufacturing are all evaluated and tested to provide assurance that the final product is free of potential adventitious agents [see  Description (11)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
