<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="proscar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The drug-related adverse reactions, reported in &gt;=1% in patients treated with PROSCAR and greater than in patients treated with placebo over a 4-year study are: impotence, decreased libido, decreased volume of ejaculate, breast enlargement, breast tenderness and rash (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  PROSCAR is generally well tolerated; adverse reactions usually have been mild and transient.



   4-Year Placebo-Controlled Study (PLESS)  



 In PLESS, 1524 patients treated with PROSCAR and 1516 patients treated with placebo were evaluated for safety over a period of 4 years. The most frequently reported adverse reactions were related to sexual function. 3.7% (57 patients) treated with PROSCAR and 2.1% (32 patients) treated with placebo discontinued therapy as a result of adverse reactions related to sexual function, which are the most frequently reported adverse reactions.



 Table 1 presents the only clinical adverse reactions considered possibly, probably or definitely drug related by the investigator, for which the incidence on PROSCAR was &gt;=1% and greater than placebo over the 4 years of the study. In years 2-4 of the study, there was no significant difference between treatment groups in the incidences of impotence, decreased libido and ejaculation disorder.



 Table 1: Drug-Related Adverse Experiences 
                         Year 1(%)             Years 2, 3 and 4(%)   
                         Finasteride           Placebo            Finasteride            Placebo             
  
 N = 1524 and 1516, finasteride vs placebo, respectively   
  
     Impotence           8.1                   3.7                5.1                    5.1                 
     Decreased    Libido  6.4                   3.4                2.6                    2.6                 
     Decreased    Volume of    Ejaculate  3.7                   0.8                1.5                    0.5                 
     Ejaculation    Disorder  0.8                   0.1                0.2                    0.1                 
     Breast    Enlargement  0.5                   0.1                1.8                    1.1                 
     Breast    Tenderness  0.4                   0.1                0.7                    0.3                 
     Rash                0.5                   0.2                0.5                    0.1                 
             Phase III Studies and 5-Year Open Extensions  
 

 The adverse experience profile in the 1-year, placebo-controlled, Phase III studies, the 5-year open extensions, and PLESS were similar.



   Medical Therapy of Prostatic Symptoms (MTOPS) Study  



 In the MTOPS study, 3047 men with symptomatic BPH were randomized to receive PROSCAR 5 mg/day (n=768), doxazosin 4 or 8 mg/day (n=756), the combination of PROSCAR 5 mg/day and doxazosin 4 or 8 mg/day (n=786), or placebo (n=737) for 4 to 6 years.  [See  Clinical Studies (14.2)  .]  



 The incidence rates of drug-related adverse experiences reported by &gt;=2% of patients in any treatment group in the MTOPS Study are listed in Table 2.



 The individual adverse effects which occurred more frequently in the combination group compared to either drug alone were: asthenia, postural hypotension, peripheral edema, dizziness, decreased libido, rhinitis, abnormal ejaculation, impotence and abnormal sexual function (see Table 2). Of these, the incidence of abnormal ejaculation in patients receiving combination therapy was comparable to the sum of the incidences of this adverse experience reported for the two monotherapies.



 Combination therapy with finasteride and doxazosin was associated with no new clinical adverse experience.



 Four patients in MTOPS reported the adverse experience breast cancer. Three of these patients were on finasteride only and one was on combination therapy.  [See  Long-Term Data  .]  



 The MTOPS Study was not specifically designed to make statistical comparisons between groups for reported adverse experiences. In addition, direct comparisons of safety data between the MTOPS study and previous studies of the single agents may not be appropriate based upon differences in patient population, dosage or dose regimen, and other procedural and study design elements.



 Table 2: Incidence &gt;=2% in One or More Treatment Groups Drug-Related Clinical Adverse Experiences in MTOPS 
 Adverse Experience         Placebo(N=737)(%)  Doxazosin4 mg or 8 mg(N=756)(%)  Finasteride(N=768)(%)  Combination(N=786)(%)   
  
   Body as a whole           
         Asthenia           7.1              15.7             5.3              16.8              
         Headache           2.3              4.1              2.0              2.3               
   Cardiovascular            
         Hypotension        0.7              3.4              1.2              1.5               
         Postural Hypotension  8.0              16.7             9.1              17.8              
   Metabolic and Nutritional   
         Peripheral Edema   0.9              2.6              1.3              3.3               
   Nervous                   
         Dizziness          8.1              17.7             7.4              23.2              
         Libido Decreased   5.7              7.0              10.0             11.6              
         Somnolence         1.5              3.7              1.7              3.1               
   Respiratory               
         Dyspnea            0.7              2.1              0.7              1.9               
         Rhinitis           0.5              1.3              1.0              2.4               
   Urogenital                
         Abnormal Ejaculation  2.3              4.5              7.2              14.1              
         Gynecomastia       0.7              1.1              2.2              1.5               
         Impotence          12.2             14.4             18.5             22.6              
         Sexual Function Abnormal  0.9              2.0              2.5              3.1               
              Long-Term Data  
 

   High-Grade Prostate Cancer  



 The PCPT trial was a 7-year randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial that enrolled 18,882 men &gt;=55 years of age with a normal digital rectal examination and a PSA &lt;=3.0 ng/mL. Men received either PROSCAR (finasteride 5 mg) or placebo daily. Patients were evaluated annually with PSA and digital rectal exams. Biopsies were performed for elevated PSA, an abnormal digital rectal exam, or the end of study. The incidence of Gleason score 8-10 prostate cancer was higher in men treated with finasteride (1.8%) than in those treated with placebo (1.1%)  [see  Indications and Usage (1.3)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  . In a 4-year placebo-controlled clinical trial with another 5alpha-reductase inhibitor (dutasteride, AVODART), similar results for Gleason score 8-10 prostate cancer were observed (1% dutasteride vs 0.5% placebo).



 No clinical benefit has been demonstrated in patients with prostate cancer treated with PROSCAR.



   Breast Cancer  



 During the 4- to 6-year placebo- and comparator-controlled MTOPS study that enrolled 3047 men, there were 4 cases of breast cancer in men treated with finasteride but no cases in men not treated with finasteride. During the 4-year, placebo-controlled PLESS study that enrolled 3040 men, there were 2 cases of breast cancer in placebo-treated men but no cases in men treated with finasteride. During the 7-year placebo-controlled Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT) that enrolled 18,882 men, there was 1 case of breast cancer in men treated with finasteride, and 1 case of breast cancer in men treated with placebo. The relationship between long-term use of finasteride and male breast neoplasia is currently unknown.



   Sexual Function  



 There is no evidence of increased sexual adverse experiences with increased duration of treatment with PROSCAR. New reports of drug-related sexual adverse experiences decreased with duration of therapy.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse events have been reported in postmarketing experience with PROSCAR. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure:



 *  -  hypersensitivity reactions, such as pruritus, urticaria, and angioedema (including swelling of the lips, tongue, throat, and face) 
 *  -  testicular pain 
 *  -  sexual dysfunction that continued after discontinuation of treatment, including erectile dysfunction, decreased libido and ejaculation disorders (e.g. reduced ejaculate volume). These events were reported rarely in men taking PROSCAR for the treatment of BPH. Most men were older and were taking concomitant medications and/or had co-morbid conditions. The independent role of PROSCAR in these events is unknown. 
 *  -  male infertility and/or poor seminal quality were reported rarely in men taking PROSCAR for the treatment of BPH. Normalization or improvement of poor seminal quality has been reported after discontinuation of finasteride. The independent role of PROSCAR in these events is unknown. 
 *  -  depression 
 *  -  male breast cancer. 
    The following additional adverse event related to sexual dysfunction that continued after discontinuation of treatment has been reported in postmarketing experience with finasteride at lower doses used to treat male pattern baldness. Because the event is reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate its frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure:
 

 *  -  orgasm disorders 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  PROSCAR reduces serum prostate specific antigen (PSA) levels by approximately 50%. However, any confirmed increase in PSA while on PROSCAR may signal the presence of prostate cancer and should be evaluated, even if those values are still within the normal range for men not taking a 5alpha-reductase inhibitor (  5.1  ). 
 *  PROSCAR may increase the risk of high-grade prostate cancer (  5.2  ,  6.1  ). 
 *  Women should not handle crushed or broken PROSCAR tablets when they are pregnant or may potentially be pregnant due to potential risk to a male fetus (  5.3  ,  8.1  ,  16  ). 
 *  PROSCAR is not indicated for use in pediatric patients or women (  5.4  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ,  8.4  ,  12.3  ). 
 *  Prior to initiating treatment with PROSCAR for BPH, consideration should be given to other urological conditions that may cause similar symptoms (  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Effects on Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) and the Use of PSA in Prostate Cancer Detection



  In clinical studies, PROSCAR reduced serum PSA concentration by approximately 50% within six months of treatment. This decrease is predictable over the entire range of PSA values in patients with symptomatic BPH, although it may vary in individuals.



 For interpretation of serial PSAs in men taking PROSCAR, a new PSA baseline should be established at least six months after starting treatment and PSA monitored periodically thereafter. Any confirmed increase from the lowest PSA value while on PROSCAR may signal the presence of prostate cancer and should be evaluated, even if PSA levels are still within the normal range for men not taking a 5alpha-reductase inhibitor. Non-compliance with PROSCAR therapy may also affect PSA test results. To interpret an isolated PSA value in patients treated with PROSCAR for six months or more, PSA values should be doubled for comparison with normal ranges in untreated men. These adjustments preserve the utility of PSA to detect prostate cancer in men treated with PROSCAR.



 PROSCAR may also cause decreases in serum PSA in the presence of prostate cancer.



 The ratio of free to total PSA (percent free PSA) remains constant even under the influence of PROSCAR. If clinicians elect to use percent free PSA as an aid in the detection of prostate cancer in men undergoing finasteride therapy, no adjustment to its value appears necessary.



    5.2 Increased Risk of High-Grade Prostate Cancer



  Men aged 55 and over with a normal digital rectal examination and PSA &lt;=3.0 ng/mL at baseline taking finasteride 5 mg/day in the 7-year Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT) had an increased risk of Gleason score 8-10 prostate cancer (finasteride 1.8% vs placebo 1.1%). [See  Indications and Usage (1.3)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  .]  Similar results were observed in a 4-year placebo-controlled clinical trial with another 5alpha-reductase inhibitor (dutasteride, AVODART) (1% dutasteride vs 0.5% placebo). 5alpha-reductase inhibitors may increase the risk of development of high-grade prostate cancer. Whether the effect of 5alpha-reductase inhibitors to reduce prostate volume, or study-related factors, impacted the results of these studies has not been established.



    5.3 Exposure of Women - Risk to Male Fetus



  Women should not handle crushed or broken PROSCAR tablets when they are pregnant or may potentially be pregnant because of the possibility of absorption of finasteride and the subsequent potential risk to a male fetus. PROSCAR tablets are coated and will prevent contact with the active ingredient during normal handling, provided that the tablets have not been broken or crushed. [See  Contraindications (4)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ,  How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17.2)  .]  



    5.4 Pediatric Patients and Women



  PROSCAR is not indicated for use in pediatric patients [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  or women [see also  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ,  How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17.2)  ]  .



    5.5 Effect on Semen Characteristics



  Treatment with PROSCAR for 24 weeks to evaluate semen parameters in healthy male volunteers revealed no clinically meaningful effects on sperm concentration, mobility, morphology, or pH. A 0.6 mL (22.1%) median decrease in ejaculate volume with a concomitant reduction in total sperm per ejaculate was observed. These parameters remained within the normal range and were reversible upon discontinuation of therapy with an average time to return to baseline of 84 weeks.



    5.6 Consideration of Other Urological Conditions



  Prior to initiating treatment with PROSCAR, consideration should be given to other urological conditions that may cause similar symptoms. In addition, prostate cancer and BPH may coexist.



 Patients with large residual urinary volume and/or severely diminished urinary flow should be carefully monitored for obstructive uropathy. These patients may not be candidates for finasteride therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
