<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="protonix1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The adverse reaction profiles for PROTONIX (pantoprazole sodium) For Delayed-Release Oral Suspension and PROTONIX (pantoprazole sodium) Delayed-Release Tablets are similar.



   EXCERPT:   The most frequently occurring adverse reactions are as follows:



 *  For adult use (&gt;2%) are headache, diarrhea, nausea, abdominal pain, vomiting, flatulence, dizziness, and arthralgia. (  6  ) 
 *  For pediatric use (&gt;4%) are URI, headache, fever, diarrhea, vomiting, rash, and abdominal pain. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Adults  



 Safety in nine randomized comparative US clinical trials in patients with GERD included 1,473 patients on oral PROTONIX (20 mg or 40 mg), 299 patients on an H2-receptor antagonist, 46 patients on another proton pump inhibitor, and 82 patients on placebo. The most frequently occurring adverse reactions are listed in Table 3.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials of Adult Patients with GERD at a Frequency of &gt; 2% 
                                PROTONIX(n=1473)%         Comparators(n=345)%          Placebo(n=82)%         
  
 Headache                             12.2                       12.8                        8.5              
 Diarrhea                              8.8                        9.6                        4.9              
 Nausea                                7.0                        5.2                        9.8              
 Abdominal pain                        6.2                        4.1                        6.1              
 Vomiting                              4.3                        3.5                        2.4              
 Flatulence                            3.9                        2.9                        3.7              
 Dizziness                             3.0                        2.9                        1.2              
 Arthralgia                            2.8                        1.4                        1.2              
      Additional adverse reactions that were reported for PROTONIX in clinical trials with a frequency of &lt;= 2% are listed below by body system:
 

   Body as a Whole:  allergic reaction, pyrexia, photosensitivity reaction, facial edema



   Gastrointestinal:  constipation, dry mouth, hepatitis



   Hematologic:  leukopenia, thrombocytopenia



   Metabolic/Nutritional:  elevated CK (creatine kinase), generalized edema, elevated triglycerides, liver enzymes elevated



   Musculoskeletal:  myalgia



   Nervous:  depression, vertigo



   Skin and Appendages:  urticaria, rash, pruritus



   Special Senses:  blurred vision



     Pediatric Patients  



 Safety of PROTONIX in the treatment of Erosive Esophagitis (EE) associated with GERD was evaluated in pediatric patients ages 1 year through 16 years in three clinical trials. Safety trials involved pediatric patients with EE; however, as EE is uncommon in the pediatric population, 249 pediatric patients with endoscopically-proven or symptomatic GERD were also evaluated. All adult adverse reactions to PROTONIX are considered relevant to pediatric patients. In patients ages 1 year through 16 years, the most commonly reported (&gt; 4%) adverse reactions include: URI, headache, fever, diarrhea, vomiting, rash, and abdominal pain.



 For safety information in patients less than 1 year of age see    Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    .



 Additional adverse reactions that were reported for PROTONIX in pediatric patients in clinical trials with a frequency of &lt;= 4% are listed below by body system:



   Body as a Whole:  allergic reaction, facial edema



   Gastrointestinal:  constipation, flatulence, nausea



   Metabolic/Nutritional:  elevated triglycerides, elevated liver enzymes, elevated CK (creatine kinase)



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, myalgia



   Nervous:  dizziness, vertigo



   Skin and Appendages:  urticaria



 The following adverse reactions seen in adults in clinical trials were not reported in pediatric patients in clinical trials, but are considered relevant to pediatric patients: photosensitivity reaction, dry mouth, hepatitis, thrombocytopenia, generalized edema, depression, pruritus, leukopenia, and blurred vision.



     Zollinger-Ellison Syndrome  



 In clinical studies of Zollinger-Ellison Syndrome, adverse reactions reported in 35 patients taking PROTONIX 80 mg/day to 240 mg/day for up to 2 years were similar to those reported in adult patients with GERD.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of PROTONIX. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 These adverse reactions are listed below by body system:



   General Disorders and Administration Conditions:  asthenia, fatigue, malaise



   Hematologic:  pancytopenia, agranulocytosis



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  hepatocellular damage leading to jaundice and hepatic failure



   Immune System Disorders:  anaphylaxis (including anaphylactic shock)



   Infections and Infestations:     Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



   Investigations:  weight changes



   Metabolism and Nutritional Disorders  : hyponatremia, hypomagnesemia



   Musculoskeletal Disorders  : rhabdomyolysis, bone fracture



   Nervous:  ageusia, dysgeusia



   Psychiatric Disorders:  hallucination, confusion, insomnia, somnolence



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  interstitial nephritis



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  severe dermatologic reactions (some fatal), including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN, some fatal), and angioedema (Quincke's edema)
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Symptomatic response does not preclude presence of gastric malignancy (  5.1  ) 
 *  Atrophic gastritis has been noted with long-term therapy (  5.2  ) 
 *  Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) Deficiency: Daily long-term use (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption or a deficiency of cyanocobalamin. (  5.4  ) 
 *  PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Bone Fracture:Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Concurrent Gastric Malignancy



  Symptomatic response to therapy with PROTONIX does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



    5.2 Atrophic Gastritis



  Atrophic gastritis has been noted occasionally in gastric corpus biopsies from patients treated long-term with PROTONIX, particularly in patients who were H. pylori  positive.



    5.3 Acute Interstitial Nephritis



   Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including PROTONIX. Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue PROTONIX if acute interstitial nephritis develops [see  Contraindications (4)  ].    



    5.4 Cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B-12) Deficiency



  Generally, daily treatment with any acid-suppressing medications over a long period of time (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption of cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B-12) caused by hypo- or achlorhydria. Rare reports of cyanocobalamin deficiency occurring with acid-suppressing therapy have been reported in the literature. This diagnosis should be considered if clinical symptoms consistent with cyanocobalamin deficiency are observed.



    5.5 Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



  Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like PROTONIX may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  .



 Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.



    5.6 Bone Fracture



  Several published observational studies suggest that proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.7 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), health care professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically [see  Adverse Reactions 6.2)  ]  .



    5.8 Tumorigenicity



  Due to the chronic nature of GERD, there may be a potential for prolonged administration of PROTONIX. In long-term rodent studies, pantoprazole was carcinogenic and caused rare types of gastrointestinal tumors. The relevance of these findings to tumor development in humans is unknown [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  .



    5.9 Interference with Urine Screen for THC



  See   Drug Interactions (7.5)    .



    5.10 Concomitant use of PROTONIX with Methotrexate



  Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients [see  Drug Interactions (7.6)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
