<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="protonix0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Worldwide, approximately 80,500 patients have been treated with pantoprazole in clinical trials involving various dosages and duration of treatment.



   EXCERPT:   The most frequently occurring adverse reactions are as follows:



 *    For adult use (&gt;2%) are headache, diarrhea, nausea, abdominal pain, vomiting, flatulence, dizziness, and arthralgia. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD)  



 Safety in nine randomized comparative US clinical trials in patients with GERD included 1,473 patients on oral pantoprazole (20 mg or 40 mg), 299 patients on an H2-receptor antagonist, 46 patients on another proton pump inhibitor, and 82 patients on placebo. The most frequently occurring adverse reactions are listed in Table 1.



 The number of patients treated in comparative studies with I.V. pantoprazole is limited; however, the adverse reactions seen were similar to those seen in the oral studies. Thrombophlebitis was the only new adverse reaction identified with I.V. pantoprazole.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials of Adult Patients with GERD at a Frequency of &gt; 2% 
                            PROTONIX    (n=1473)    %      Comparators    (n=345)    %      Placebo    (n=82)    %     
  
  Headache                 12.2                     12.8                     8.5                      
  Diarrhea                 8.8                      9.6                      4.9                      
  Nausea                   7.0                      5.2                      9.8                      
  Abdominal pain           6.2                      4.1                      6.1                      
  Vomiting                 4.3                      3.5                      2.4                      
  Flatulence               3.9                      2.9                      3.7                      
  Dizziness                3.0                      2.9                      1.2                      
  Arthralgia               2.8                      1.4                      1.2                      
          Additional adverse reactions that were reported for PROTONIX in US clinical trials with a frequency of &lt;= 2% are listed below by body system:
 

   Body as a Whole:  allergic reaction, fever, photosensitivity reaction, facial edema, thrombophlebitis (I.V. only)



   Gastrointestinal:  constipation, dry mouth, hepatitis



   Hematologic:  leukopenia (reported in ex-US clinical trials only), thrombocytopenia



   Metabolic/Nutritional:  elevated CPK (creatine phosphokinase), generalized edema, elevated triglycerides, liver function tests abnormal



   Musculoskeletal:  myalgia



   Nervous:  depression, vertigo



   Skin and Appendages:  urticaria, rash, pruritus



   Special Senses:  blurred vision



     Zollinger-Ellison Syndrome  



 In clinical studies of Zollinger-Ellison Syndrome, adverse reactions reported in 35 patients taking PROTONIX 80 mg/day to 240 mg/day for up to 2 years were similar to those reported in adult patients with GERD.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of PROTONIX. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 These adverse reactions are listed below by body system:



   General Disorders and Administration Conditions:  asthenia, fatigue, malaise



   Immune System Disorders:  anaphylaxis (including anaphylactic shock)



   Investigations:  weight changes



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  severe dermatologic reactions (some fatal), including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), and angioedema (Quincke's edema)



   Musculoskeletal Disorders:  rhabdomyolysis, bone fracture



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  interstitial nephritis



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  hepatocellular damage leading to jaundice and hepatic failure



   Psychiatric Disorder:  hallucinations, confusion, insomnia, somnolence



   Metabolism and Nutritional Disorders:  hyponatremia, hypomagnesemia



   Infections and Infestations:     Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



   Hematologic:  pancytopenia, agranulocytosis



   Nervous:  ageusia, dysgeusia
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Symptomatic response to therapy with pantoprazole does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy (  5.1  ) 
 *    Anaphylaxis has been reported with use of intravenous pantoprazole (  5.2  ) 
 *    Thrombophlebitis is associated with the administration of intravenous pantoprazole (  5.3  ) 
 *    Zinc supplementation should be considered in patients treated with PROTONIX I.V. for Injection who are prone to zinc deficiency. Caution should be used when other EDTA containing products are also co-administered intravenously (  5.4  ) 
 *    Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs. (  5.5  ) 
 *    PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea (  5.6  ) 
 *    Bone Fracture:PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine after long term and multiple daily dose. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Implications of Symptomatic Response



  Symptomatic response to therapy with pantoprazole does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity and Severe Skin Reactions



  Anaphylaxis and other serious reactions such as erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) have been reported with use of intravenous pantoprazole. These may require emergency medical treatment [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  .



    5.3 Injection Site Reactions



  Thrombophlebitis was associated with the administration of intravenous pantoprazole.



    5.4 Potential for Exacerbation of Zinc Deficiency



  PROTONIX contains edetate disodium (the salt form of EDTA), a chelator of metal ions including zinc. Therefore, zinc supplementation should be considered in patients treated with PROTONIX I.V. for Injection who are prone to zinc deficiency. Caution should be used when other EDTA containing products are also co-administered intravenously.



    5.5 Acute Interstitial Nephritis



   Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including PROTONIX I.V. Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue PROTONIX I.V. if acute interstitial nephritis develops [ see       Contraindications (4)     ].  



    5.6 Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



  Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like PROTONIX may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



 Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated.



    5.7 Bone Fracture



  Several published observational studies suggest that proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to established treatment guidelines [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  .



    5.8 Hepatic Effects



  Mild, transient transaminase elevations have been observed in clinical studies. The clinical significance of this finding in a large population of subjects administered intravenous pantoprazole is unknown. [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ].  



    5.9 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, and in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), health care professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.10 Interference with Urine Screen for THC



  May produce false-positive urine screen for THC (tetrahydrocannabinol)



  [see  Drug Interactions (7.4)  ].  



    5.11 Concomitant use of PROTONIX with Methotrexate



  Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients [see  Drug Interactions (7.6)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
