<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="provayblue" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Serotonin Syndrome with Concomitant Use of Serotonergic Drugs [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Anaphylaxis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Lack of Effectiveness [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Hemolytic Anemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Interference with In-Vivo Monitoring Devices [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Effects on Ability to Drive and Operate Machinery [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Interference with Laboratory Tests [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) are pain in extremity, chromaturia, dysgeusia, feeling hot, dizziness, hyperhidrosis, nausea, skin, discoloration and headache. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact American Regent at 1-800-734-9236 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of PROVAYBLUETM was determined in 82 healthy adults of median age of 36 years (range, 19-55 years); 54% were male, and 68% were white. Each individual in the safety population received a single dose of PROVAYBLUETM 2 mg/kg intravenously. There was one serious adverse reaction reported (syncope due to sinus pauses of 3-14 seconds). The most common (&gt;=2%) moderate or severe adverse reactions were pain in the extremity (56%), headache (7%), feeling hot (6%), syncope (4%), back pain (2%), hyperhidrosis (2%) and nausea (2%). Table 1 lists the adverse reactions of any severity that occurred in at least 2% of individuals who received PROVAYBLUETM.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Following Infusion of PROVAYBLUETM 2 mg/kg 
   Adverse Reaction                                    Any Grade TEAE    (n=82)      Moderate-    Severe TEAE    (n=82)     
 Pain in extremity                                   69           84%            46           56%             
 Chromaturia                                         61           74%            0                            
 Dysgeusia                                           16           20%            1            1%              
 Feeling hot                                         14           17%            5            6%              
 Dizziness                                           13           16%            4            5%              
 Hyperhidrosis                                       11           13%            2            2%              
 Nausea                                              11           13%            2            2%              
 Skin discoloration                                  11           13%            0                            
 Headache                                            8            10%            6            7%              
 Musculoskeletal pain                                7            9%             0                            
 Paresthesia oral                                    7            9%             0                            
 Paresthesia                                         7            9%             0                            
 Infusion site pain                                  5            6%             1            1%              
 Feeling cold                                        5            6%             0                            
 Pallor                                              4            5%             0                            
 Dermatitis contact                                  4            5%             0                            
 Syncope                                             3            4%             3            4%              
 Influenza like illness                              3            4%             1            1%              
 Pruritus                                            3            4%             1            1%              
 Anxiety                                             3            4%             0                            
 Decreased appetite                                  3            4%             0                            
 Chest discomfort                                    3            4%             0                            
 Back pain                                           2            2%             2            2%              
 Cold sweat                                          2            2%             1            1%              
 Dizziness postural                                  2            2%             1            1%              
 Muscle spasms                                       2            2%             1            1%              
 Presyncope                                          2            2%             1            1%              
 Vomiting                                            2            2%             1            1%              
 Arthralgia                                          2            2%             1            1%              
 Chills                                              2            2%             0                            
 Diarrhea                                            2            2%             0                            
 Discomfort                                          2            2%             0                            
 Dyspnea                                             2            2%             0                            
 Erythema                                            2            2%             0                            
 Hypoesthesia oral                                   2            2%             0                            
 Infusion site discomfort                            2            2%             0                            
 Limb discomfort                                     2            2%             0                            
 Oral discomfort                                     2            2%             0                            
 Catheter site pain                                  2            2%             0                            
 Ecchymosis                                          2            2%             0                            
           Other adverse reactions reported to occur following administration of methylene blue class products include the following:
 

   Blood and lymphatic system disorders  : hemolytic anemia, hemolysis, hyperbilirubinemia, methemoglobinemia



   Cardiac disorders  : palpitations, tachycardia



   Eye disorders  : eye pruritus, ocular hyperemia, vision blurred



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : abdominal pain lower, dry mouth, flatulence, glossodynia, tongue eruption



   General disorders and administration site conditions  : death, infusion site extravasation, infusion site induration, infusion site pruritus, infusion site swelling, infusion site urticaria, peripheral swelling, thirst



   Investigations  : elevated liver enzymes



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  : myalgia



   Renal and urinary disorders  : dysuria



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  : nasal congestion, oropharyngeal pain, rhinorrhea, sneezing



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : necrotic ulcer, papule, phototoxicity



   Vascular disorders  : hypertension
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SEROTONIN SYNDROME WITH CONCOMITANT USE OF SEROTONERGIC DRUGS



  WARNING: SEROTONIN SYNDROME WITH CONCOMITANT USE OF SEROTONERGIC DRUGS



    PROVAYBLUETM may cause serious or fatal serotonergic syndrome when used in combination with serotonergic drugs. Avoid concomitant use of PROVAYBLUETM with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), and monoamine oxidase inhibitors

      (

        

   

      5.1  , 

        

   

      7.1  ). [see Warnings and Precautions (

        

   

      5.1  ) and Drug Interactions (

        

   

      7.1  )]
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity: If severe or life threatening allergic reaction occurs, discontinue PROVAYBLUETM, treat the allergic reaction, and monitor until signs and symptoms resolve (  5.2  ) 
 *  Lack of Effectiveness: Consider alternative treatments if there is no resolution of methemoglobinemia after 2 doses (  2.1  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  Hemolytic Anemia: Discontinue PROVAYBLUETM and transfuse (  5.4  ) 
 *  Interference with In-Vivo Monitoring Devices: Use methods other than pulse oximetry to assess oxygen satruation (  5.5  ) 
 *  Effects on Ability to Drive and Operate Machinery: Advise patients to refrain from these activities until neurologic and visual symptoms have resolved (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serotonin Syndrome with Concomitant Use of Serotonergic Drugs



  The development of serotonin syndrome has been reported with use of methylene blue class products. Most reports have been associated with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (e.g., selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), monoamine oxidase inhibitors). Some of the reported cases were fatal. Symptoms associated with serotonin syndrome may include the following combination of signs and symptoms: mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, and hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, and incoordination), seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Avoid concomitant use of PROVAYBLUETM with serotonergic drugs.



 Patients treated with PROVAYBLUETM should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome. If symptoms of serotonin syndrome occur, discontinue use of PROVAYBLUETM, and initiate supportive treatment. Inform patients of the increased risk of serotonin syndrome and advise them to not to take serotonergic drugs within 72 hours after the last dose of PROVAYBLUETM [see Drug Interactions (  7  ), Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



    5.2 Hypersensitivity



  Anaphylactic reactions to methylene blue class products have been reported. Patients treated with PROVAYBLUETM should be monitored for anaphylaxis. If anaphylaxis or other severe hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., angioedema, urticaria, bronchospasm) should occur, discontinue use of PROVAYBLUETM and initiate supportive treatment. PROVAYBLUETM is contraindicated in patients who have experienced anaphylaxis or other severe hypersensitivity reactions to a methylene blue class product in the past.



    5.3 Lack of Effectiveness



  Methemoglobinemia may not resolve or may rebound after response to treatment with PROVAYBLUETM in patients with methemoglobinemia due to aryl amines such as aniline or sulfa drugs such as dapsone. Monitor response to therapy with PROVAYBLUETM through resolution of methemoglobinemia. If methemoglobinemia does not respond to 2 doses of PROVAYBLUETM or if methemoglobinemia rebounds after a response, consider additional treatment options [see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )]  .



 Patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency may not reduce PROVAYBLUETM to its active form in vivo. PROVAYBLUETM may not be effective in patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency.



    5.4 Hemolytic Anemia



  Hemolysis can occur during treatment of methemoglobinemia with PROVAYBLUETM. Laboratory testing may show Heinz bodies, elevated indirect bilirubin and low haptoglobin, but the Coombs test is negative. The onset of anemia may be delayed 1 or more days after treatment with PROVAYBLUETM. The anemia may require red blood cell transfusions. [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )].  Use the lowest effective number of doses of PROVAYBLUETM to treat methemoglobinemia. Discontinue PROVAYBLUETM and consider alternative treatments of methemoglobinemia if severe hemolysis occurs.



 Treatment of patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency with PROVAYBLUETM may result in severe hemolysis and severe anemia. PROVAYBLUETM is contraindicated for use in patients with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency [see Contraindications (  4  )].  



    5.5 Interference with In Vivo Monitoring Devices



    *  Inaccurate Pulse Oximeter Readings 
    The presence of methylene blue in the blood may result in an underestimation of the oxygen saturation reading by pulse oximetry. If a measure of oxygen saturation is required during or shortly after infusion of PROVAYBLUETM, it is advisable to obtain an arterial blood sample for testing by an alternative method.
 

 *  Bispectral index monitor 
    A fall in the Bispectral Index (BIS) has been reported following administration of methylene blue class products. If PROVAYBLUETM is administered during surgery, alternative methods for assessing the depth of anesthesia should be employed.
 

    5.6 Effects on Ability to Drive and Operate Machinery



  Treatment with PROVAYBLUETM may cause confusion, dizziness and disturbances in vision [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  . Advise patients to refrain from driving or engaging in hazardous occupations or activities such as operating heavy or potentially dangerous machinery until such adverse reactions to PROVAYBLUETM have resolved.



    5.7 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  PROVAYBLUETM is a blue dye which passes freely into the urine and may interfere with the interpretation of any urine test which relies on a blue indicator, such as the dipstick test for leucocyte esterase.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
