<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="provenge" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions reported in clinical trials (&gt;= 15% of patients receiving PROVENGE) were chills, fatigue, fever, back pain, nausea, joint ache, and headache.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 15%) are chills, fatigue, fever, back pain, nausea, joint ache, and headache. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Dendreon Corporation at 1-877-336-3736 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety evaluation of PROVENGE is based on 601 prostate cancer patients in the PROVENGE group who underwent at least 1 leukapheresis procedure in four randomized, controlled clinical trials. The control group (n = 303) received non-activated autologous peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Patients received 3 infusions of PROVENGE or control every other week over a period of 4 weeks.



 Almost all (98.3%) patients in the PROVENGE group and 96% in the control group reported an adverse event. In 67.4% of patients in the PROVENGE group, these adverse events were mild or moderate in severity. Severe (Grade 3) and life-threatening (Grade 4) adverse events were reported in 23.6% and 4% of patients in the PROVENGE group compared with 25.1% and 3.3% of patients in the control group. Fatal (Grade 5) adverse events were reported in 3.3% of patients in the PROVENGE group compared with 3.6% of patients in the control group. The most common (&gt;= 2%) Grade 3-5 adverse events reported in the PROVENGE group were back pain and chills.



 Serious adverse events were reported in 24% of patients in the PROVENGE group and 25.1% of patients in the control group. Serious adverse events in the PROVENGE group included acute infusion reactions [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ], cerebrovascular events [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )  ], and single case reports of eosinophilia, rhabdomyolysis, myasthenia gravis, myositis, and tumor flare.



 PROVENGE was discontinued in 1.5% of patients in Study 1 due to adverse events. Some patients who required central venous catheters for treatment with PROVENGE developed infections, including sepsis. A small number of these patients discontinued treatment as a result. Monitoring for infectious sequelae in patients with central venous catheters is recommended.



 Each dose of PROVENGE requires a standard leukapheresis procedure approximately 3 days prior to the infusion. Adverse events that were reported &lt;= 1 day following a leukapheresis procedure in &gt;= 5% of patients in controlled clinical trials included citrate toxicity (14.2%), oral paresthesia (12.6%), paresthesia (11.4%), and fatigue (8.3%).



   Table 1  provides the frequency and severity of adverse events reported in &gt;= 5% of patients in the PROVENGE group of randomized, controlled trials of men with prostate cancer. The population included 485 patients with metastatic castrate-resistant prostate cancer and 116 patients with non-metastatic androgen-dependent prostate cancer who were scheduled to receive 3 infusions of PROVENGE at approximately 2-week intervals. The population was age 40 to 91 years (median 70 years), and 90.6% of patients were Caucasian.



 Table 1 Incidence of Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;= 5% of Patients Randomized to PROVENGE 
                         PROVENGE    (N = 601)      Control      *      (N = 303)     
                         All Grades    n (%)      Grade 3-5    n (%)      All Grades    n (%)      Grade 3-5    n (%)     
   Any Adverse Event      591 (98.3)      186 (30.9)      291 (96.0)      97 (32.0)     
  
  * Control group received non-activated autologous peripheral blood mononuclear cells.    
  
 Chills                319 (53.1)  13 (2.2)    33 (10.9)   0 (0.0)      
 Fatigue               247 (41.1)  6 (1.0)     105 (34.7)  4 (1.3)      
 Fever                 188 (31.3)  6 (1.0)     29 (9.6)    3 (1.0)      
 Back pain             178 (29.6)  18 (3.0)    87 (28.7)   9 (3.0)      
 Nausea                129 (21.5)  3 (0.5)     45 (14.9)   0 (0.0)      
 Joint ache            118 (19.6)  11 (1.8)    62 (20.5)   5 (1.7)      
 Headache              109 (18.1)  4 (0.7)     20 (6.6)    0 (0.0)      
 Citrate toxicity      89 (14.8)   0 (0.0)     43 (14.2)   0 (0.0)      
 Paresthesia           85 (14.1)   1 (0.2)     43 (14.2)   0 (0.0)      
 Vomiting              80 (13.3)   2 (0.3)     23 (7.6)    0 (0.0)      
 Anemia                75 (12.5)   11 (1.8)    34 (11.2)   7 (2.3)      
 Constipation          74 (12.3)   1 (0.2)     40 (13.2)   3 (1.0)      
 Pain                  74 (12.3)   7 (1.2)     20 (6.6)    3 (1.0)      
 Paresthesia oral      74 (12.3)   0 (0.0)     43 (14.2)   0 (0.0)      
 Pain in extremity     73 (12.1)   5 (0.8)     40 (13.2)   1 (0.3)      
 Dizziness             71 (11.8)   2 (0.3)     34 (11.2)   0 (0.0)      
 Muscle ache           71 (11.8)   3 (0.5)     17 (5.6)    0 (0.0)      
 Asthenia              65 (10.8)   6 (1.0)     20 (6.6)    2 (0.7)      
 Diarrhea              60 (10.0)   1 (0.2)     34 (11.2)   3 (1.0)      
 Influenza-like illness  58 (9.7)    0 (0.0)     11 (3.6)    0 (0.0)      
 Musculoskeletal pain  54 (9.0)    3 (0.5)     31 (10.2)   3 (1.0)      
 Dyspnea               52 (8.7)    11 (1.8)    14 (4.6)    3 (1.0)      
 Edema peripheral      50 (8.3)    1 (0.2)     31 (10.2)   1 (0.3)      
 Hot flush             49 (8.2)    2 (0.3)     29 (9.6)    1 (0.3)      
 Hematuria             46 (7.7)    6 (1.0)     18 (5.9)    3 (1.0)      
 Muscle spasms         46 (7.7)    2 (0.3)     17 (5.6)    0 (0.0)      
 Hypertension          45 (7.5)    3 (0.5)     14 (4.6)    0 (0.0)      
 Anorexia              39 (6.5)    1 (0.2)     33 (10.9)   3 (1.0)      
 Bone pain             38 (6.3)    4 (0.7)     22 (7.3)    3 (1.0)      
 Upper respiratory tract infection  38 (6.3)    0 (0.0)     18 (5.9)    0 (0.0)      
 Insomnia              37 (6.2)    0 (0.0)     22 (7.3)    1 (0.3)      
 Musculoskeletal chest pain  36 (6.0)    2 (0.3)     23 (7.6)    2 (0.7)      
 Cough                 35 (5.8)    0 (0.0)     17 (5.6)    0 (0.0)      
 Neck pain             34 (5.7)    3 (0.5)     14 (4.6)    2 (0.7)      
 Weight decreased      34 (5.7)    2 (0.3)     24 (7.9)    1 (0.3)      
 Urinary tract infection  33 (5.5)    1 (0.2)     18 (5.9)    2 (0.7)      
 Rash                  31 (5.2)    0 (0.0)     10 (3.3)    0 (0.0)      
 Sweating              30 (5.0)    1 (0.2)     3 (1.0)     0 (0.0)      
 Tremor                30 (5.0)    0 (0.0)     9 (3.0)     0 (0.0)      
                 6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of PROVENGE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *   Nervous system disorders  : syncope, transient ischemic attack, strokes [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,  5.3  )]  
 *   Vascular disorders  : hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *   Cardiovascular disorders  : myocardial infarction [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *   Thromboembolic disorders: deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute infusion reactions may occur. If reactions occur, decrease the rate or stop the infusion and administer appropriate medical treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Syncope and hypotension have also been observed. Closely monitor patients with cardiac or pulmonary conditions. (  5.1  ) 
 *  PROVENGE should be used with caution in patients with risk factors for thromboembolic events. (  5.2  ) 
 *  PROVENGE is not tested for transmissible infectious diseases and may transmit diseases to health care professionals handling the product. Universal precautions should be followed. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Concomitant use of chemotherapy and immunosuppressive medications with PROVENGE has not been studied. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Infusion Reactions



     Acute infusion reactions (reported within 1 day of infusion) may occur and include nausea, vomiting, fatigue, fever, rigor or chills, respiratory events (dyspnea, hypoxia, and bronchospasm), syncope, hypotension, hypertension, and tachycardia.



 In controlled clinical trials, 71.2% of patients in the PROVENGE group developed an acute infusion reaction. The most common events (&gt;= 20%) were chills, fever, and fatigue. In 95.1% of patients reporting acute infusion reactions, the reactions were mild or moderate. Fevers and chills generally resolved within 2 days (71.9% and 89%, respectively).



 In controlled clinical trials, severe (Grade 3) acute infusion reactions were reported in 3.5% of patients in the PROVENGE group. Reactions included chills, fever, fatigue, asthenia, dyspnea, hypoxia, bronchospasm, dizziness, headache, hypertension, muscle ache, nausea, and vomiting. The incidence of severe events was greater following the second infusion (2.1% vs. 0.8% following the first infusion), and decreased to 1.3% following the third infusion. Some (1.2%) patients in the PROVENGE group were hospitalized within 1 day of infusion for management of acute infusion reactions. No Grade 4 or 5 acute infusion reactions were reported in patients in the PROVENGE group.



 Closely monitor patients with cardiac or pulmonary conditions. In the event of an acute infusion reaction, decrease the infusion rate or stop the infusion, depending on the severity of the reaction. Administer appropriate medical treatment as needed. [ See Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ]



       5.2 Thromboembolic Events



     Thromboembolic events, including deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism, can occur following infusion of PROVENGE. The clinical significance and causal relationship are uncertain. Most patients had multiple risk factors for these events. PROVENGE should be used with caution in patients with risk factors for thromboembolic events.



       5.3 Vascular Disorders



      Cerebrovascular disease  : In controlled clinical trials, cerebrovascular events (hemorrhagic and ischemic strokes) were observed in 3.5% of patients in the PROVENGE group compared with 2.6% of patients in the control group.  In the postmarketing setting, cerebrovascular events, including transient ischemic attacks, have been observed following infusion of Provenge. The clinical significance and causal relationship are uncertain.  Most patients had multiple risk factors for these events.



       Cardiovascular disorders  :  In controlled clinical trials, myocardial infarctions were observed in 0.8% of patients in the PROVENGE group compared with 0.3% of patients in the control group.  In the postmarketing setting, myocardial infarctions have been observed following infusion of Provenge. The clinical significance and causal relationship are uncertain. Most patients had multiple risk factors for these events.



    5.4 Handling Precautions for Control of Infectious Disease



  PROVENGE is not  tested for transmissible infectious diseases. Therefore, patient leukapheresis material and PROVENGE may carry the risk of transmitting infectious diseases to health care professionals handling the product. Accordingly, health care professionals should employ universal precautions when handling leukapheresis material or PROVENGE.



    5.5 Concomitant Chemotherapy or Immunosuppressive Therapy



  Use of either chemotherapy or immunosuppressive agents (such as systemic corticosteroids) given concurrently with the leukapheresis procedure or PROVENGE has not been studied. PROVENGE is designed to stimulate the immune system, and concurrent use of immune-suppressive agents may alter the efficacy and/or safety of PROVENGE. Therefore, evaluate patients carefully to determine whether it is medically appropriate to reduce or discontinue immunosuppressive agents prior to treatment with PROVENGE.



    5.6 Product Safety Testing



  PROVENGE is released for infusion based on the microbial and sterility results from several tests: microbial contamination determination by Gram stain, endotoxin content, and in-process sterility with a 2-day incubation to determine absence of microbial growth. The final (7-day incubation) sterility test results are not available at the time of infusion. If the sterility results become positive for microbial contamination after PROVENGE has been approved for infusion, Dendreon will notify the treating physician. Dendreon will attempt to identify the microorganism, perform antibiotic sensitivity testing on recovered microorganisms, and communicate the results to the treating physician. Dendreon may request additional information from the physician in order to determine the source of contamination.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
