<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="prozac1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTION

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviors in Children, Adolescents, and Young Adults [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Serotonin Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Allergic Reactions and Rash [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder and Monitoring for Mania/Hypomania [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Seizures [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Altered Appetite and Weight [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Abnormal Bleeding [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Angle-Closure Glaucoma [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Hyponatremia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Anxiety and Insomnia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  QT Prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
 *  Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.13  )]  
 *  Discontinuation Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.15  )]  
      When using PROZAC and olanzapine in combination, also refer to the Adverse Reactions section of the package insert for Symbyax.  
 

   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and at least twice that for placebo) associated with:



 Major Depressive Disorder, Obsessive Compulsive Disorder, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder: abnormal dreams, abnormal ejaculation, anorexia, anxiety, asthenia, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, flu syndrome, impotence, insomnia, libido decreased, nausea, nervousness, pharyngitis, rash, sinusitis, somnolence, sweating, tremor, vasodilatation, and yawn (  6.1  )



 PROZAC and olanzapine in combination - Also refer to the Adverse Reactions section of the package insert for Symbyax (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect or predict the rates observed in practice.



 Multiple doses of PROZAC have been administered to 10,782 patients with various diagnoses in US clinical trials. In addition, there have been 425 patients administered PROZAC in panic clinical trials. The stated frequencies represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse reaction of the type listed. A reaction was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



     Incidence in Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder placebo-controlled clinical trials (excluding data from extensions of trials)   -  Table 3  enumerates the most common treatment-emergent adverse reactions associated with the use of PROZAC (incidence of at least 5% for PROZAC and at least twice that for placebo within at least 1 of the indications) for the treatment of Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, and bulimia in US controlled clinical trials and Panic Disorder in US plus non-US controlled trials.  Table 5  enumerates treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred in 2% or more patients treated with PROZAC and with incidence greater than placebo who participated in US Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, and bulimia controlled clinical trials and US plus non-US Panic Disorder controlled clinical trials.  Table 4  provides combined data for the pool of studies that are provided separately by indication in  Table 3  .



 Table 3: Most Common Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials1,2 
  1 Incidence less than 1%.    
  2 Includes US data for Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-US data for Panic Disorder clinical trials.    
  3 Denominator used was for males only (N=690 PROZAC Major Depressive Disorder; N=410 placebo Major Depressive Disorder; N=116 PROZAC OCD; N=43 placebo OCD; N=14 PROZAC bulimia; N=1 placebo bulimia; N=162 PROZAC panic; N=121 placebo panic).    
  
                    Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
                    Major Depressive Disorder      OCD         Bulimia      Panic Disorder     
   Body System/Adverse Reaction      PROZAC  (N=1728)    Placebo  (N=975)    PROZAC  (N=266)    Placebo  (N=89)    PROZAC  (N=450)    Placebo  (N=267)    PROZAC  (N=425)    Placebo  (N=342)   
   Body as a Whole                                                                                                       
     Asthenia     9           5           15          11        21          9             7           7              
     Flu syndrome  3           4           10          7         8           3             5           5              
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                                       
     Vasodilatation  3           2           5           --        2           1             1           --             
   Digestive System                                                                                                       
     Nausea       21          9           26          13        29          11            12          7              
     Diarrhea     12          8           18          13        8           6             9           4              
     Anorexia     11          2           17          10        8           4             4           1              
     Dry mouth    10          7           12          3         9           6             4           4              
     Dyspepsia    7           5           10          4         10          6             6           2              
   Nervous System                                                                                                       
     Insomnia     16          9           28          22        33          13            10          7              
     Anxiety      12          7           14          7         15          9             6           2              
     Nervousness  14          9           14          15        11          5             8           6              
     Somnolence   13          6           17          7         13          5             5           2              
     Tremor       10          3           9           1         13          1             3           1              
     Libido decreased  3           --          11          2         5           1             1           2              
     Abnormal dreams  1           1           5           2         5           3             1           1              
   Respiratory System                                                                                                       
     Pharyngitis  3           3           11          9         10          5             3           3              
     Sinusitis    1           4           5           2         6           4             2           3              
     Yawn         --          --          7           --        11          --            1           --             
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                                       
     Sweating     8           3           7           --        8           3             2           2              
     Rash         4           3           6           3         4           4             2           2              
   Urogenital System                                                                                                       
     Impotence  3    2           --          --          --        7           --            1           --             
     Abnormal ejaculation  3    --          --          7           --        7           --            2           1              
              Table 4: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials1,2 
  1 Incidence less than 1%.                     
  2 Includes US data for Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-US data for Panic Disorder clinical trials.    
  
                                                 Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
                                                 Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia,and Panic Disorder Combined     
   Body System/Adverse Reaction                  PROZAC  (N=2869)             Placebo  (N=1673)            
   Body as a Whole                                                                                         
     Headache                                  21                           19                             
     Asthenia                                  11                           6                              
     Flu syndrome                              5                            4                              
     Fever                                     2                            1                              
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                   
     Vasodilatation                            2                            1                              
   Digestive System                                                                                        
     Nausea                                    22                           9                              
     Diarrhea                                  11                           7                              
     Anorexia                                  10                           3                              
     Dry mouth                                 9                            6                              
     Dyspepsia                                 8                            4                              
     Constipation                              5                            4                              
     Flatulence                                3                            2                              
     Vomiting                                  3                            2                              
   Metabolic and NutritionalDisorders                                                                      
     Weight loss                               2                            1                              
   Nervous System                                                                                          
     Insomnia                                  19                           10                             
     Nervousness                               13                           8                              
     Anxiety                                   12                           6                              
     Somnolence                                12                           5                              
     Dizziness                                 9                            6                              
     Tremor                                    9                            2                              
     Libido decreased                          4                            1                              
     Thinking abnormal                         2                            1                              
   Respiratory System                                                                                      
     Yawn                                      3                            --                             
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                     
     Sweating                                  7                            3                              
     Rash                                      4                            3                              
     Pruritus                                  3                            2                              
   Special Senses                                                                                          
     Abnormal vision                           2                            1                              
             Associated with discontinuation in Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder placebo-controlled clinical trials (excluding data from extensions of trials)  -  Table 5  lists the adverse reactions associated with discontinuation of PROZAC treatment (incidence at least twice that for placebo and at least 1% for PROZAC in clinical trials collecting only a primary reaction associated with discontinuation) in Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-US Panic Disorder clinical trials.
 

 Table 5: Most Common Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation in Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials1 
  1 Includes US Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder clinical trials, plus non-US Panic Disorder clinical trials.    
  
   Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, Bulimia, and Panic Disorder Combined  (N=1533)    Major Depressive Disorder  (N=392)    OCD  (N=266)     Bulimia  (N=450)    Panic Disorder  (N=425)   
 Anxiety (1%)            --                    Anxiety (2%)     --                  Anxiety (2%)             
 --                      --                    --               Insomnia (2%)       --                       
 --                      Nervousness (1%)      --               --                  Nervousness (1%)         
 --                      --                    Rash (1%)        --                  --                       
               Other adverse reactions in pediatric patients (children and adolescents)  - Treatment-emergent adverse reactions were collected in 322 pediatric patients (180 fluoxetine-treated, 142 placebo-treated). The overall profile of adverse reactions was generally similar to that seen in adult studies, as shown in  Tables 4  and   5  . However, the following adverse reactions (excluding those which appear in the body or footnotes of  Tables 4  and   5  and those for which the COSTART terms were uninformative or misleading) were reported at an incidence of at least 2% for fluoxetine and greater than placebo: thirst, hyperkinesia, agitation, personality disorder, epistaxis, urinary frequency, and menorrhagia.
 

 The most common adverse reaction (incidence at least 1% for fluoxetine and greater than placebo) associated with discontinuation in 3 pediatric placebo-controlled trials (N=418 randomized; 228 fluoxetine-treated; 190 placebo-treated) was mania/hypomania (1.8% for fluoxetine-treated, 0% for placebo-treated). In these clinical trials, only a primary reaction associated with discontinuation was collected.



     Reactions observed in PROZAC Weekly clinical trials  - Treatment-emergent adverse reactions in clinical trials with PROZAC Weekly were similar to the adverse reactions reported by patients in clinical trials with PROZAC daily. In a placebo-controlled clinical trial, more patients taking PROZAC Weekly reported diarrhea than patients taking placebo (10% versus 3%, respectively) or taking PROZAC 20 mg daily (10% versus 5%, respectively).



     Male and female sexual dysfunction with SSRIs  - Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that SSRIs can cause such untoward sexual experiences. Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance, and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, however, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance, cited in product labeling, are likely to underestimate their actual incidence. In patients enrolled in US Major Depressive Disorder, OCD, and bulimia placebo-controlled clinical trials, decreased libido was the only sexual side effect reported by at least 2% of patients taking fluoxetine (4% fluoxetine, &lt;1% placebo). There have been spontaneous reports in women taking fluoxetine of orgasmic dysfunction, including anorgasmia.



 There are no adequate and well-controlled studies examining sexual dysfunction with fluoxetine treatment.



 Symptoms of sexual dysfunction occasionally persist after discontinuation of fluoxetine treatment.



 Priapism has been reported with all SSRIs.



 While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



   6.2 Other Reactions

  Following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported by patients treated with fluoxetine in clinical trials. This listing is not intended to include reactions (1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, (2) for which a drug cause was remote, (3) which were so general as to be uninformative, (4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or (5) which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo.



 Reactions are classified by body system using the following definitions: frequent adverse reactions are those occurring in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



   Body as a Whole  -  Frequent:   chills;  Infrequent:   suicide attempt;  Rare:   acute abdominal syndrome, photosensitivity reaction.



   Cardiovascular System  -  Frequent:  palpitation;  Infrequent:   arrhythmia, hypotension  1  .



   Digestive System  -  Infrequent:   dysphagia, gastritis, gastroenteritis, melena, stomach ulcer;  Rare:   bloody diarrhea, duodenal ulcer, esophageal ulcer, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hematemesis, hepatitis, peptic ulcer, stomach ulcer hemorrhage.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  -  Infrequent:   ecchymosis;  Rare:   petechia, purpura.



   Nervous System  -  Frequent:  emotional lability;  Infrequent:   akathisia, ataxia, balance disorder  1  , bruxism  1  , buccoglossal syndrome, depersonalization, euphoria, hypertonia, libido increased, myoclonus, paranoid reaction;  Rare:   delusions.



   Respiratory System  -  Rare:   larynx edema.



   Skin and Appendages  -  Infrequent:  alopecia;  Rare:   purpuric rash.



   Special Senses  -  Frequent:   taste perversion;  Infrequent:   mydriasis.



   Urogenital System  -  Frequent:  micturition disorder  ; Infrequent:  dysuria, gynecological bleeding  2  .



   1  MedDRA dictionary term from integrated database of placebo controlled trials of 15870 patients, of which 9673 patients received fluoxetine.



   2  Group term that includes individual MedDRA terms: cervix hemorrhage uterine, dysfunctional uterine bleeding, genital hemorrhage, menometrorrhagia, menorrhagia, metrorrhagia, polymenorrhea, postmenopausal hemorrhage, uterine hemorrhage, vaginal hemorrhage. Adjusted for gender.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of PROZAC. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is difficult to reliably estimate their frequency or evaluate a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Voluntary reports of adverse reactions temporally associated with PROZAC that have been received since market introduction and that may have no causal relationship with the drug include the following: aplastic anemia, atrial fibrillation  1  , cataract, cerebrovascular accident  1  , cholestatic jaundice, dyskinesia (including, for example, a case of buccal-lingual-masticatory syndrome with involuntary tongue protrusion reported to develop in a 77-year-old female after 5 weeks of fluoxetine therapy and which completely resolved over the next few months following drug discontinuation), eosinophilic pneumonia  1  , epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, erythema nodosum, exfoliative dermatitis, galactorrhea, gynecomastia, heart arrest  1  , hepatic failure/necrosis, hyperprolactinemia, hypoglycemia, immune-related hemolytic anemia, kidney failure, memory impairment, movement disorders developing in patients with risk factors including drugs associated with such reactions and worsening of pre-existing movement disorders, optic neuritis, pancreatitis  1  , pancytopenia, pulmonary embolism, pulmonary hypertension, QT prolongation, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, thrombocytopenia  1  , thrombocytopenic purpura, ventricular tachycardia (including Torsades de Pointes-type arrhythmias), vaginal bleeding, and violent behaviors  1  .



   1  These terms represent serious adverse events, but do not meet the definition for adverse drug reactions. They are included here because of their seriousness.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

                 WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS



  

                 WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS



    *  Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies. These studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressant use in patients over age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressant use in patients aged 65 and older [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  In patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy, monitor closely for worsening and for emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  PROZAC is not approved for use in children less than 7 years of age [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Use in Specific Populations (8.4)]. 
      When using PROZAC and olanzapine in combination, also refer to Boxed Warning section of the package insert for Symbyax.  
 

   EXCERPT:     WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants (5.1). 
 *  Monitor for worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors (5.1). 
      When using PROZAC and olanzapine in combination, also refer to Boxed Warning section of the package insert for Symbyax  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   When using PROZAC and olanzapine in combination, also refer to the Warnings and Precautions section of the package insert for Symbyax.  



    EXCERPT:    *   Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviors in Children, Adolescents, and Young Adults: Monitor for clinical worsening and suicidal thinking and behavior (  5.1  ) 
 *   Serotonin Syndrome: Serotonin syndrome has been reported with SSRIs and SNRIs, including PROZAC, both when taken alone, but especially when co-administered with other serotonergic agents (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone and St. John's Wort). If such symptoms occur, discontinue PROZAC and initiate supportive treatment. If concomitant use of PROZAC with other serotonergic drugs is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Allergic Reactions and Rash: Discontinue upon appearance of rash or allergic phenomena (  5.3  ) 
 *   Activation of Mania/Hypomania : Screen for Bipolar Disorder and monitor for mania/hypomania (  5.4  ) 
 *   Seizures: Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold (  5.5  ) 
 *   Altered Appetite and Weight: Significant weight loss has occurred (  5.6  ) 
 *   Abnormal Bleeding: May increase the risk of bleeding. Use with NSAIDs, aspirin, warfarin, or other drugs that affect coagulation may potentiate the risk of gastrointestinal or other bleeding (  5.7  ) 
 *   Angle-Closure Glaucoma: Angle-closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Hyponatremia: Has been reported with PROZAC in association with syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone (SIADH). Consider discontinuing if symptomatic hyponatremia occurs (  5.9  ) 
 *   Anxiety and Insomnia: May occur (  5.10  ) 
 *   QT Prolongation: QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia including Torsades de Pointes have been reported with PROZAC use. Use with caution in conditions that predispose to arrhythmias or increased fluoxetine exposure. Use cautiously in patients with risk factors for QT prolongation (  4.2  ,  5.11  ,  7.7  ,  7.8  ,  10.1  ) 
 *   Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment: Has potential to impair judgment, thinking, and motor skills. Use caution when operating machinery (  5.13  ) 
 *   Long Half-Life: Changes in dose will not be fully reflected in plasma for several weeks (  5.14  ) 
 *   PROZAC and Olanzapine in Combination: When using PROZAC and olanzapine in combination, also refer to the Warnings and Precautions section of the package insert for Symbyax (  5.16  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviors in Children, Adolescents, and Young Adults



  Patients with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug versus placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in  Table 2  .



 Table 2: Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated 
  Age Range                                         Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated     
                                                   Increases Compared to Placebo                         
 &lt;18                                               14 additional cases                                   
 18-24                                             5 additional cases                                    
                                                   Decreases Compared to Placebo                         
 25-64                                             1 fewer case                                          
 &gt;=65                                              6 fewer cases                                         
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for Major Depressive Disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



 If the decision has been made to discontinue treatment, medication should be tapered, as rapidly as is feasible, but with recognition that abrupt discontinuation can be associated with certain symptoms [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.15  )]  .



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for Major Depressive Disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers.  Prescriptions for PROZAC should be written for the smallest quantity of capsules consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



 It should be noted that PROZAC is approved in the pediatric population for Major Depressive Disorder and Obsessive Compulsive Disorder; and PROZAC in combination with olanzapine for the acute treatment of depressive episodes associated with Bipolar I Disorder.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs, including PROZAC, alone but particularly with concomitant use of other serotonergic drugs (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort) and with drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (in particular, MAOIs, both those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue).



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome.



 The concomitant use of PROZAC with MAOIs intended to treat psychiatric disorders is contraindicated. PROZAC should also not be started in a patient who is being treated with MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue. All reports with methylene blue that provided information on the route of administration involved intravenous administration in the dose range of 1 mg/kg to 8 mg/kg. No reports involved the administration of methylene blue by other routes (such as oral tablets or local tissue injection) or at lower doses. There may be circumstances when it is necessary to initiate treatment with an MAOI such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue in a patient taking PROZAC. PROZAC should be discontinued before initiating treatment with the MAOI [see Contraindications (  4.1  ) and Dosage and Administration (  2.9  ,  2.10  )]  .



 If concomitant use of PROZAC with other serotonergic drugs, i.e., triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, buspirone, tryptophan and St. John's Wort is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases.



 Treatment with PROZAC and any concomitant serotonergic agents, should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Allergic Reactions and Rash



  In US fluoxetine clinical trials, 7% of 10,782 patients developed various types of rashes and/or urticaria. Among the cases of rash and/or urticaria reported in premarketing clinical trials, almost a third were withdrawn from treatment because of the rash and/or systemic signs or symptoms associated with the rash. Clinical findings reported in association with rash include fever, leukocytosis, arthralgias, edema, carpal tunnel syndrome, respiratory distress, lymphadenopathy, proteinuria, and mild transaminase elevation. Most patients improved promptly with discontinuation of fluoxetine and/or adjunctive treatment with antihistamines or steroids, and all patients experiencing these reactions were reported to recover completely.



 In premarketing clinical trials, 2 patients are known to have developed a serious cutaneous systemic illness. In neither patient was there an unequivocal diagnosis, but one was considered to have a leukocytoclastic vasculitis, and the other, a severe desquamating syndrome that was considered variously to be a vasculitis or erythema multiforme. Other patients have had systemic syndromes suggestive of serum sickness.



 Since the introduction of PROZAC, systemic reactions, possibly related to vasculitis and including lupus-like syndrome, have developed in patients with rash. Although these reactions are rare, they may be serious, involving the lung, kidney, or liver. Death has been reported to occur in association with these systemic reactions.



 Anaphylactoid reactions, including bronchospasm, angioedema, laryngospasm, and urticaria alone and in combination, have been reported.



 Pulmonary reactions, including inflammatory processes of varying histopathology and/or fibrosis, have been reported rarely. These reactions have occurred with dyspnea as the only preceding symptom.



 Whether these systemic reactions and rash have a common underlying cause or are due to different etiologies or pathogenic processes is not known. Furthermore, a specific underlying immunologic basis for these reactions has not been identified. Upon the appearance of rash or of other possibly allergic phenomena for which an alternative etiology cannot be identified, PROZAC should be discontinued.



    5.4 Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder and Monitoring for Mania/Hypomania



  A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of Bipolar Disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for Bipolar Disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described for clinical worsening and suicide risk represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for Bipolar Disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, Bipolar Disorder, and depression. It should be noted that PROZAC and olanzapine in combination is approved for the acute treatment of depressive episodes associated with Bipolar I Disorder [see Warnings and Precautions section of the package insert for Symbyax]  . PROZAC monotherapy is not indicated for the treatment of depressive episodes associated with Bipolar I Disorder.



 In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for Major Depressive Disorder, mania/hypomania was reported in 0.1% of patients treated with PROZAC and 0.1% of patients treated with placebo. Activation of mania/hypomania has also been reported in a small proportion of patients with Major Affective Disorder treated with other marketed drugs effective in the treatment of Major Depressive Disorder [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )]  .



 In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for OCD, mania/hypomania was reported in 0.8% of patients treated with PROZAC and no patients treated with placebo. No patients reported mania/hypomania in US placebo-controlled clinical trials for bulimia. In US PROZAC clinical trials, 0.7% of 10,782 patients reported mania/hypomania [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )]  .



    5.5 Seizures



  In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for Major Depressive Disorder, convulsions (or reactions described as possibly having been seizures) were reported in 0.1% of patients treated with PROZAC and 0.2% of patients treated with placebo. No patients reported convulsions in US placebo-controlled clinical trials for either OCD or bulimia. In US PROZAC clinical trials, 0.2% of 10,782 patients reported convulsions. The percentage appears to be similar to that associated with other marketed drugs effective in the treatment of Major Depressive Disorder. PROZAC should be introduced with care in patients with a history of seizures.



    5.6 Altered Appetite and Weight



  Significant weight loss, especially in underweight depressed or bulimic patients, may be an undesirable result of treatment with PROZAC.



 In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for Major Depressive Disorder, 11% of patients treated with PROZAC and 2% of patients treated with placebo reported anorexia (decreased appetite). Weight loss was reported in 1.4% of patients treated with PROZAC and in 0.5% of patients treated with placebo. However, only rarely have patients discontinued treatment with PROZAC because of anorexia or weight loss [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )]  .



 In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for OCD, 17% of patients treated with PROZAC and 10% of patients treated with placebo reported anorexia (decreased appetite). One patient discontinued treatment with PROZAC because of anorexia [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )]  .



 In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for Bulimia Nervosa, 8% of patients treated with PROZAC 60 mg and 4% of patients treated with placebo reported anorexia (decreased appetite). Patients treated with PROZAC 60 mg on average lost 0.45 kg compared with a gain of 0.16 kg by patients treated with placebo in the 16-week double-blind trial. Weight change should be monitored during therapy.



    5.7 Abnormal Bleeding



  SNRIs and SSRIs, including fluoxetine, may increase the risk of bleeding reactions. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, warfarin, and other anti-coagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding reactions related to SNRIs and SSRIs use have ranged from ecchymoses, hematomas, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages. Patients should be cautioned about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of fluoxetine and NSAIDs, aspirin, warfarin, or other drugs that affect coagulation [see Drug Interactions (  7.4  )]  .



    5.8 Angle-Closure Glaucoma



      Angle-Closure Glaucoma  - The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including Prozac may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.



    5.9 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia has been reported during treatment with SNRIs and SSRIs, including PROZAC. In many cases, this hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported and appeared to be reversible when PROZAC was discontinued. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with SNRIs and SSRIs. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume depleted may be at greater risk [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )]  . Discontinuation of PROZAC should be considered in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia and appropriate medical intervention should be instituted.



 Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which may lead to falls. More severe and/or acute cases have been associated with hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.10 Anxiety and Insomnia



  In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for Major Depressive Disorder, 12% to 16% of patients treated with PROZAC and 7% to 9% of patients treated with placebo reported anxiety, nervousness, or insomnia.



 In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for OCD, insomnia was reported in 28% of patients treated with PROZAC and in 22% of patients treated with placebo. Anxiety was reported in 14% of patients treated with PROZAC and in 7% of patients treated with placebo.



 In US placebo-controlled clinical trials for Bulimia Nervosa, insomnia was reported in 33% of patients treated with PROZAC 60 mg, and 13% of patients treated with placebo. Anxiety and nervousness were reported, respectively, in 15% and 11% of patients treated with PROZAC 60 mg and in 9% and 5% of patients treated with placebo.



 Among the most common adverse reactions associated with discontinuation (incidence at least twice that for placebo and at least 1% for PROZAC in clinical trials collecting only a primary reaction associated with discontinuation) in US placebo-controlled fluoxetine clinical trials were anxiety (2% in OCD), insomnia (1% in combined indications and 2% in bulimia), and nervousness (1% in Major Depressive Disorder) [see  Table 5  ]  .



    5.11 QT Prolongation



  Post-marketing cases of QT interval prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia including Torsades de Pointes have been reported in patients treated with PROZAC. PROZAC should be used with caution in patients with congenital long QT syndrome; a previous history of QT prolongation; a family history of long QT syndrome or sudden cardiac death; and other conditions that predispose to QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia. Such conditions include concomitant use of drugs that prolong the QT interval; hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia; recent myocardial infarction, uncompensated heart failure, bradyarrhythmias, and other significant arrhythmias; and conditions that predispose to increased fluoxetine exposure (overdose, hepatic impairment, use of CYP2D6 inhibitors, CYP2D6 poor metabolizer status, or use of other highly protein-bound drugs). PROZAC is primarily metabolized by CYP2D6 [see Contraindications (  4.2  ), Drug Interactions (  7.7  ,  7.8  ), Overdose (  10.1  ), and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



 Pimozide and thioridazine are contraindicated for use with PROZAC. Avoid the concomitant use of drugs known to prolong the QT interval. These include specific antipsychotics (e.g., ziprasidone, iloperidone, chlorpromazine, mesoridazine, droperidol,); specific antibiotics (e.g., erythromycin, gatifloxacin, moxifloxacin, sparfloxacin); Class 1A antiarrhythmic medications (e.g., quinidine, procainamide); Class III antiarrhythmics (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol); and others (e.g., pentamidine, levomethadyl acetate, methadone, halofantrine, mefloquine, dolasetron mesylate, probucol or tacrolimus) [see Drug Interactions (  7.7  ,  7.8  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



 Consider ECG assessment and periodic ECG monitoring if initiating treatment with PROZAC in patients with risk factors for QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia. Consider discontinuing PROZAC and obtaining a cardiac evaluation if patients develop signs or symptoms consistent with ventricular arrhythmia.



    5.12 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with PROZAC in patients with concomitant systemic illness is limited. Caution is advisable in using PROZAC in patients with diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses.



    Cardiovascular  - Fluoxetine has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were systematically excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarket testing. However, the electrocardiograms of 312 patients who received PROZAC in double-blind trials were retrospectively evaluated; no conduction abnormalities that resulted in heart block were observed. The mean heart rate was reduced by approximately 3 beats/min.



    Glycemic Control  - In patients with diabetes, PROZAC may alter glycemic control. Hypoglycemia has occurred during therapy with PROZAC, and hyperglycemia has developed following discontinuation of the drug. As is true with many other types of medication when taken concurrently by patients with diabetes, insulin and/or oral hypoglycemic, dosage may need to be adjusted when therapy with PROZAC is instituted or discontinued.



    5.13 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  As with any CNS-active drug, PROZAC has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills. Patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that the drug treatment does not affect them adversely.



    5.14 Long Elimination Half-Life



  Because of the long elimination half-lives of the parent drug and its major active metabolite, changes in dose will not be fully reflected in plasma for several weeks, affecting both strategies for titration to final dose and withdrawal from treatment. This is of potential consequence when drug discontinuation is required or when drugs are prescribed that might interact with fluoxetine and norfluoxetine following the discontinuation of fluoxetine [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



    5.15 Discontinuation Adverse Reactions



  During marketing of PROZAC, SNRIs, and SSRIs, there have been spontaneous reports of adverse reactions occurring upon discontinuation of these drugs, particularly when abrupt, including the following: dysphoric mood, irritability, agitation, dizziness, sensory disturbances (e.g., paresthesias such as electric shock sensations), anxiety, confusion, headache, lethargy, emotional lability, insomnia, and hypomania. While these reactions are generally self-limiting, there have been reports of serious discontinuation symptoms. Patients should be monitored for these symptoms when discontinuing treatment with PROZAC. A gradual reduction in the dose rather than abrupt cessation is recommended whenever possible. If intolerable symptoms occur following a decrease in the dose or upon discontinuation of treatment, then resuming the previously prescribed dose may be considered. Subsequently, the physician may continue decreasing the dose but at a more gradual rate. Plasma fluoxetine and norfluoxetine concentration decrease gradually at the conclusion of therapy which may minimize the risk of discontinuation symptoms with this drug.



    5.16 PROZAC and Olanzapine in Combination



  When using PROZAC and olanzapine in combination, also refer to the Warnings and Precautions section of the package insert for Symbyax.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
