<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pulmicort1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic and inhaled corticosteroid use may result in the following:



 *    Candida albicans infection [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ]



 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ]



 
 *   Immunosuppression [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ]



 
 *   Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ]



 
 *   Reduction in bone mineral density [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ]



 
 *   Growth effects in pediatric patients [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  and  Use in Specific Populations, Pediatric Use (8.4)   ]



 
 *   Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure and cataracts [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ]



 
 *   Eosinophilic conditions and Churg-Strauss syndrome [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.11)   ]



 
   Table 1 - Adverse Reactions occurring at an incidence of &gt;=3% in at least one active treatment group where the incidence was higher with PULMICORT RESPULES than placebo 
  Adverse Events    Vehicle Placebo  (n=227)  %    PULMICORT RESPULES  Total Daily Dose    
  0.25 mg  (n=178)  %    0.5 mg  (n=223)  %    1 mg  (n=317)  %    
  Respiratory System Disorder    
  Respiratory Infection    36               34               35               38               
  Rhinitis         9                7                11               12               
  Coughing         5                5                9                8                
  Resistance Mechanism Disorders    
  Otitis Media     11               12               11               9                
  Viral Infection    3                4                5                3                
  Moniliasis       2                4                3                4                
  Gastrointestinal System Disorders    
  Gastroenteritis    4                5                5                5                
  Vomiting         3                2                4                4                
  Diarrhea         2                4                4                2                
  Abdominal Pain    2                3                2                3                
  Hearing and Vestibular Disorders    
  Ear Infection    4                2                4                5                
  Platelet, Bleeding and Clotting Disorders    
  Epistaxis        1                2                4                3                
  Vision Disorders    
  Conjunctivitis    2                &lt;1               4                2                
  Skin and Appendages Disorders    
  Rash             3                &lt;1               4                2                
        EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions at an incidence of  &gt;  3%:



 Respiratory infection, rhinitis, coughing, otitis media, viral infection, moniliasis, gastroenteritis, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain, ear infection, epistaxis, conjunctivitis, rash (6.1)



 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The incidence of common adverse reactions is based on three double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized U.S. clinical trials in which 945 patients, 12 months to 8 years of age, (98 patients &gt;=12 months and &lt;2 years of age; 225 patients &gt;=2 and &lt;4 years of age; and 622 patients &gt;=4 and &lt;=8 years of age) were treated with PULMICORT RESPULES (0.25 to 1 mg total daily dose for 12 weeks) or vehicle placebo. The incidence and nature of adverse events reported for PULMICORT RESPULES was comparable to that reported for placebo. The following table shows the incidence of adverse events in U.S. controlled clinical trials, regardless of relationship to treatment, in patients previously receiving bronchodilators and/or inhaled corticosteroids. This population included a total of 605 male and 340 female patients and 78.4% were Caucasian, 13.8% African American, 5.5% Hispanic and 2.3% Other.



 The information below includes all adverse reactions by system organ class with an incidence of 1 to &lt; 3%, in at least one PULMICORT RESPULES treatment group where the incidence was higher with PULMICORT RESPULES than with placebo, regardless of relationship to treatment.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  cervical lymphadenopathy



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  earache



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  fatigue, flu-like disorder



   Immune system disorders:  allergic reaction



   Infections and infestations:  eye infection, herpes simplex, external ear infection, infection



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complication:  fracture



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  anorexia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  myalgia



   Nervous system disorders:  hyperkinesia



   Psychiatric disorders:  emotional lability



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:  chest pain, dysphonia, stridor



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  contact dermatitis, eczema, pustular rash, pruritus, purpura



 The incidence of reported adverse events was similar between the 447 PULMICORT RESPULES-treated (mean total daily dose 0.5 to 1 mg) and 223 conventional therapy-treated pediatric asthma patients followed for one year in three open-label studies.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of PULMICORT RESPULES. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Some of these adverse reactions may also have been observed in clinical studies with PULMICORT RESPULES.



   Endocrine disorders:  symptoms of hypocorticism and hypercorticism [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ]



   Eye disorders:  cataracts, glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  fever, pain



   Immune system disorders:  immediate and delayed hypersensitivity reactions including, anaphylaxis, angioedema, bronchospasm, rash, contact dermatitis, and urticaria [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]



   Infection and Infestation:  sinusitis, pharyngitis, bronchitis



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  avascular necrosis of the femoral head, osteoporosis, growth suppression



   Nervous system disorders:  headache



   Psychiatric disorders:  psychiatric symptoms including psychosis, depression, aggressive reactions, irritability, nervousness, restlessness, and anxiety



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:  cough, dysphonia and throat irritation



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  skin bruising, facial skin irritation



 Cases of growth suppression have been reported for inhaled corticosteroids including post-marketing reports for PULMICORT RESPULES [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  and  Use In Specific Populations, Pediatric Use (8.4)    ].
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *   Localized infections: Candida albicans infection of the mouth and throat may occur. Monitor patients periodically for signs of adverse effects on the oral cavity. Advise patients to rinse the mouth following inhalation. (5.1)



 
 *   Deterioration of disease and acute asthma episodes: Do not use for the relief of acute bronchospasm. (5.2)



 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions: anaphylaxis, rash, contact dermatitis, urticaria, angioedema, and bronchospasm have been reported with use of PULMICORT RESPULES. Discontinue PULMICORT RESPULES if such reactions occur (5.3)



 
 *   Immunosuppression: Potential worsening of infections (e.g., existing tuberculosis, fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infection; or ocular herpes simplex). Use with caution in patients with these infections. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles can occur in susceptible patients. (5.4)



 
 *   Transferring patients from systemic corticosteroids: Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring from oral steroids. Taper patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to PULMICORT RESPULES. (5.5)



 
 *   Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: May occur with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals. If such changes occur, reduce PULMICORT RESPULES slowly. (5.6)



 
 *   Reduction in bone mineral density with long term administration. Monitor patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content. (5.7)



 
 *   Effects on growth: Monitor growth of pediatric patients. (5.8)



 
 *   Glaucoma and cataracts: Close monitoring is warranted. (5.9)



 
 *   Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue PULMICORT RESPULES and institute alternative therapy if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs. (5.10)



 
 *   Eosinophilic conditions and Churg-Strauss syndrome: Be alert to eosinophilic conditions. (5.11)



 
    



   5.1 Local Effects



  In clinical trials with PULMICORT RESPULES, localized infections with Candida albicans  occurred in the mouth and pharynx in some patients. The incidences of localized infections of Candida albicans  were similar between the placebo and PULMICORT RESPULES treatment groups. If these infections develop, they may require treatment with appropriate local or systemic antifungal therapy and/or discontinuance of treatment with PULMICORT RESPULES. Patients should rinse the mouth after inhalation of PULMICORT RESPULES.



    5.2 Deterioration of Disease and Acute Asthma Episodes



  PULMICORT RESPULES is not a bronchodilator and is not indicated for the rapid relief of acute bronchospasm or other acute episodes of asthma.



 Patients should be instructed to contact their physician immediately if episodes of asthma not responsive to their usual doses of bronchodilators occur during the course of treatment with PULMICORT RESPULES. During such episodes, patients may require therapy with oral corticosteroids.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions Including Anaphylaxis



  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, rash, contact dermatitis, urticaria, angioedema, and bronchospasm have been reported with use of PULMICORT RESPULES. Discontinue PULMICORT RESPULES if such reactions occur [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.4 Immunosuppression



  Patients who are on drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infection than healthy individuals. Chicken pox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible children or adults using corticosteroids. In children or adults who have not had these diseases, or been properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If exposed to chicken pox, therapy with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG), as appropriate, may be indicated. If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See the respective package inserts for complete VZIG and IG prescribing information.) If chicken pox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.



 The clinical course of chicken pox or measles infection in patients on inhaled corticosteroids has not been studied. However, a clinical study has examined the immune responsiveness of asthma patients 12 months to 8 years of age who were treated with PULMICORT RESPULES. An open-label non-randomized clinical study examined the immune responsiveness of varicella vaccine in 243 asthma patients 12 months to 8 years of age who were treated with PULMICORT RESPULES 0.25 mg to 1 mg daily (n=151) or noncorticosteroid asthma therapy (n=92) (i.e., beta2-agonists, leukotriene receptor antagonists, cromones). The percentage of patients developing a seroprotective antibody titer of &gt;=5.0 (gpELISA value) in response to the vaccination was similar in patients treated with PULMICORT RESPULES (85%) compared to patients treated with non-corticosteroid asthma therapy (90%). No patient treated with PULMICORT RESPULES developed chicken pox as a result of vaccination.



 Inhaled corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection of the respiratory tract, untreated systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infections; or ocular herpes simplex.



    5.5 Transferring Patients from Systemic Corticosteroid Therapy



  Particular care is needed for patients who are transferred from systemically active corticosteroids to inhaled corticosteroids because deaths due to adrenal insufficiency have occurred in asthmatic patients during and after transfer from systemic corticosteroids to less systemically available inhaled corticosteroids. After withdrawal from systemic corticosteroids, a number of months are required for recovery of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA)-axis function.



 Patients who have been previously maintained on 20 mg or more per day of prednisone (or its equivalent) may be most susceptible, particularly when their systemic corticosteroids have been almost completely withdrawn.



 During this period of HPA-axis suppression, patients may exhibit signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency when exposed to trauma, surgery, infection (particularly gastroenteritis) or other conditions associated with severe electrolyte loss. Although PULMICORT RESPULES may provide control of asthma symptoms during these episodes, in recommended doses it supplies less than normal physiological amounts of glucocorticosteroid systemically and does NOT provide the mineralocorticoid activity that is necessary for coping with these emergencies.



 During periods of stress or a severe asthma attack, patients who have been withdrawn from systemic corticosteroids should be instructed to resume oral corticosteroids (in large doses) immediately and to contact their physicians for further instructions. These patients should also be instructed to carry a medical identification card indicating that they may need supplementary systemic corticosteroids during periods of stress or a severe asthma attack.



 Patients requiring oral corticosteroids should be weaned slowly from systemic corticosteroid use after transferring to PULMICORT RESPULES. Initially, PULMICORT RESPULES should be used concurrently with the patient's usual maintenance dose of systemic corticosteroid. After approximately one week, gradual withdrawal of the systemic corticosteroid may be initiated by reducing the daily or alternate daily dose. Further incremental reductions may be made after an interval of one or two weeks, depending on the response of the patient. Generally, these decrements should not exceed 25% of the prednisone dose or its equivalent. A slow rate of withdrawal is strongly recommended.



 Lung function (FEV1or AM PEF), beta-agonist use, and asthma symptoms should be carefully monitored during withdrawal of oral corticosteroids. In addition to monitoring asthma signs and symptoms, patients should be observed for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency such as fatigue, lassitude, weakness, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension.



 Transfer of patients from systemic corticosteroid therapy to PULMICORT RESPULES may unmask allergic or other immunologic conditions previously suppressed by the systemic corticosteroid therapy, e.g., rhinitis, conjunctivitis, eosinophilic conditions, eczema, and arthritis [see   Dosage and Administration (2)    ].



 During withdrawal from oral corticosteroids, patients may experience symptoms of systemically active corticosteroid withdrawal (e.g., joint and/or muscular pain, lassitude, depression) despite maintenance or even improvement of respiratory function.



    5.6 Hypercorticism and Adrenal Suppression



  PULMICORT RESPULES, will often help control asthma symptoms with less suppression of HPA function than therapeutically equivalent oral doses of prednisone. Since individual sensitivity to effects on cortisol production exists, physicians should consider this information when prescribing PULMICORT RESPULES. Because of the possibility of systemic absorption of inhaled corticosteroids, patients treated with PULMICORT RESPULES should be observed carefully for any evidence of systemic corticosteroid effects. Particular care should be taken in observing patients post-operatively or during periods of stress for evidence of inadequate adrenal response. It is possible that systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism, and adrenal suppression (including adrenal crisis) may appear in a small number of patients, particularly when budesonide is administered at higher than recommended doses over prolonged periods of time. If such effects occur, the dosage of PULMICORT RESPULES should be reduced slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for tapering of systemic corticosteroids and for management of asthma.



    5.7 Reduction in Bone Mineral Density



  Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) have been observed with long-term administration of products containing inhaled corticosteroids. The clinical significance of small changes in BMD with regard to long-term outcomes is unknown. Patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content, such as prolonged immobilization, family history of osteoporosis, poor nutrition, or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass (e.g., anticonvulsants and corticosteroids), should be monitored and treated with established standards of care.



    5.8 Effects on Growth



  Orally inhaled corticosteroids, including budesonide, may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to pediatric patients. Monitor the growth of pediatric patients receiving PULMICORT RESPULES routinely (e.g., via stadiometry). To minimize the systemic effects of orally inhaled corticosteroids, including PULMICORT RESPULES, each patient should be titrated to his/her lowest effective dose [see   Use In Specific Populations, Pediatric Use (8.4)    ].



    5.9 Glaucoma and Cataracts



  Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure, and cataracts have been reported following the long-term administration of inhaled corticosteroids, including budesonide. Therefore, close monitoring is warranted in patients with a change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and/or cataracts.



    5.10 Paradoxical Bronchospasm and Upper Airway Symptoms



  As with other inhaled asthma medications, bronchospasm, with an immediate increase in wheezing, may occur after dosing. If acute bronchospasm occurs following dosing with PULMICORT RESPULES, it should be treated immediately with a fast-acting inhaled bronchodilator. Treatment with PULMICORT RESPULES should be discontinued and alternate therapy instituted.



    5.11 Eosinophilic Conditions and Churg-Strauss Syndrome



  In rare cases, patients on inhaled corticosteroids may present with systemic eosinophilic conditions. Some of these patients have clinical features of vasculitis consistent with Churg- Strauss syndrome, a condition that is often treated with systemic corticosteroids therapy. These events usually, but not always, have been associated with the reduction and/or withdrawal of oral corticosteroid therapy following the introduction of inhaled corticosteroids. Healthcare providers should be alert to eosinophilia, vasculitis rash, worsening pulmonary symptoms, cardiac complications, and/or neuropathy presenting in their patients. A causal relationship between budesonide and these underlying conditions has not been established.



    5.12 Drug Interactions with Strong Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors



  Caution should be exercised when considering the coadministration of PULMICORT RESPULES with ketoconazole, and other known strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin) because adverse effects related to increased systemic exposure to budesonide may occur [see   Drug Interactions (7.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology, Clinical Pharmacokinetics (12.3)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
