<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pulmicort0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic and inhaled corticosteroid use may result in the following:



 *      Candida albicans infection [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.1) ] 
 *     Hypersensitivity Including Anaphylaxis [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.3) ] 
 *     Immunosuppression [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.4) ] 
 *     Hypercorticism and Adrenal Suppression [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.6) ] 
 *     Reduction in Bone Mineral Density [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.8) ] 
 *     Growth Effects [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.9) and Use in Specific Populations (8.4) ] 
 *     Glaucoma and Cataracts [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.10) ] 
 *     Eosinophilic conditions and Churg-Strauss [see   Warnings and Precautions  (5.12) ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=1%):
 

 nasopharyngitis, nasal congestion, pharyngitis, rhinitis allergic, viral upper respiratory tract infection, nausea, viral gastroenteritis, otitis media, oral candidiasis. (6.1)



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   PULMICORT FLEXHALER  



   Patients 6 years and older  



 The incidence of common adverse reactions in Table 1 is based upon pooled data reported in patients treated with PULMICORT FLEXHALER 180 or 90 mcg in two double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trials in which 226 patients (106 females and 120 males) with mild to moderate asthma, previously receiving bronchodilators, inhaled corticosteroids, or both, were treated with PULMICORT FLEXHALER, administered as 360 mcg twice daily for 12 weeks. In these trials, the patients on PULMICORT FLEXHALER had a mean age of 28 years (range 6-80 years) and were predominantly Caucasian (59.7%) and Asian (31.4%). Table 1 includes all adverse reactions (regardless of investigator causality assessment) that occurred at a rate of &gt;=1% in the PULMICORT FLEXHALER group and more commonly than the placebo group.



 Table 1 - Adverse Reactions occurring at an incidence of &gt;=1% and more commonly than placebo in the PULMICORT FLEXHALER group: pooled data from two 12-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical asthma trials in patients 6 years and older 
  Adverse Event    PULMICORT FLEXHALER  360 mcg twice daily  N=226  %    Placebo  N=230  %    
  Nasopharyngitis    9.3              8.3              
  Nasal congestion    2.7              0.4              
  Pharyngitis      2.7              1.7              
  Rhinitis allergic    2.2              1.3              
  Viral upper respiratory tract infection    2.2              1.3              
  Nausea           1.8              0.9              
  Viral gastroenteritis    1.8              0.4              
  Otitis media     1.3              0.9              
  Oral candidiasis    1.3              0.4              
  Average exposure duration (days)    76.2             68.2             
           Long-Term Safety in Patients 6 years of age and older  
 

 Non-placebo controlled long-term studies in children (at doses up to 360 mcg daily), and adolescent and adult subjects (at doses up to 720 mcg daily), treated for up to one year with PULMICORT FLEXHALER, revealed a similar pattern and incidence of adverse events.



   PULMICORT TURBUHALER; a different PULMICORT DPI  



 The following adverse reactions occurred in placebo-controlled clinical trials with similar or lower doses with inhaled budesonide via a different PULMICORT dry powder inhaler with an incidence of &gt;=1% in the budesonide group and were more common than in the placebo group:



 &gt;=3%: respiratory infection, sinusitis, headache, pain, back pain, fever.



 &gt;=1-3%: neck pain, syncope, abdominal pain, dry mouth, vomiting, weight gain, fracture, myalgia, hypertonia, migraine, ecchymosis, insomnia, infection, taste perversion, voice alteration.



 Higher doses of inhaled budesonide (800 mcg twice daily) via a different PULMICORT dry powder inhaler resulted in an increased incidence of voice alteration, flu syndrome, dyspepsia, gastroenteritis, nausea, and back pain, compared with doses of 400 mcg twice daily.



 In a 20-week trial in adult asthmatics who previously required oral corticosteroids, the incidence of adverse reactions was evaluated with 400 mcg twice daily (N=53) and 800 mcg twice daily (N=53) of inhaled budesonide via a different PULMICORT dry powder inhaler and compared with placebo (N=53). In considering these data, the increased average duration of exposure for inhaled budesonide patients (78 days for inhaled budesonide vs. 41 days for placebo) should be taken into account. Adverse reactions, regardless of investigator causality assessment, reported in more than five patients in the budesonide group and which occurred more commonly than the placebo group in decreasing order of frequency include: respiratory infection, sinusitis, headache, oral candidiasis, pain, asthenia, dyspepsia, arthralgia, cough increased, nausea and rhinitis.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use of PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Immune system disorders:  immediate and delayed hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic reaction, angioedema, bronchospasm, rash, contact dermatitis, urticaria, and cough, wheezing or bronchospasm in patients with severe milk protein hypersensitivity [see    Warnings and Precautions  (5.3) and  Containdications  (4)  ]



   Endocrine disorders:  symptoms of hypocorticism and hypercorticism [see    Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)  ]



   Eye disorders:  cataracts, glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure [see    Warnings and Precautions  (5.10)  ]



   Psychiatric disorders:  psychiatric symptoms including psychosis, depression, aggressive reactions, irritability, nervousness, restlessness, and anxiety



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:  throat irritation



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  skin bruising
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    Patient Information  



   PULMICORT FLEXHALERTM 90 mcg   



 (budesonide inhalation powder, 90 mcg) 



     Important Note:   This medicine is to only be inhaled through the mouth (by oral inhalation only).



      



 Read the Patient Information that comes with PULMICORT FLEXHALER before you start using it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This leaflet does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or treatment.



   What is PULMICORT FLEXHALER?  



 PULMICORT FLEXHALER is an inhaled corticosteroid medicine. PULMICORT FLEXHALER is used for long-term (maintenance) treatment of asthma and to prevent asthma symptoms in adults and children 6 years of age and older.



 Inhaled corticosteroids help to decrease inflammation in the lungs. Inflammation in the lungs can lead to asthma symptoms.



  PULMICORT FLEXHALER helps reduce inflammation and helps keep the airways open to reduce asthma symptoms. 



   PULMICORT FLEXHALER does not treat the symptoms of a sudden asthma attack. Always have a short-acting beta2-agonist medicine (rescue inhaler) with you to treat sudden symptoms. If you do not have an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator, call your healthcare provider to have one prescribed for you.   



 It is not known if PULMICORT FLEXHALER is safe and effective in children younger than 6 years of age.



   Who should not use PULMICORT FLEXHALER?  



 Do not use PULMICORT FLEXHALER: 



 *   to treat sudden severe symptoms of asthma. 
 *   if you have a severe allergy to milk proteins. PULMICORT FLEXHALER contains a small amount of lactose (milk sugar). People with severe allergies to milk protein may have symptoms of an allergic reaction with PULMICORT FLEXHALER including: cough, wheezing, trouble breathing or feeling like your throat is closing. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before using PULMICORT FLEXHALER?  
 

 Before using PULMICORT FLEXHALER, tell your healthcare provider if you:



 *   have any allergies. See the section "Who should not use PULMICORT FLEXHALER". There is a complete list of ingredients in PULMICORT FLEXHALER at the end of this leaflet. 
 *   have or had chicken pox or measles, or have recently been near anyone with chicken pox or measles. 
 *   have or had tuberculosis of your respiratory tract. 
 *   have certain kinds of serious infections that have not been treated, including: 
 *   fungal infections 
 *   bacterial infections 
 *   viral infections 
 *   parasitic infections 
 *   herpes simplex infection of the eye (ocular herpes simplex) 
    PULMICORT FLEXHALER may not be right for people who have or had any of these types of infections.
 

 *   have liver problems 
 *   have decreased bone mineral density. 
 *   You are at risk for decreased bone mineral density if you: are inactive for a long period of time have a family history of osteoporosis are a woman going through menopause or are past menopause ("the change of life") smoke or use tobacco do not eat well (poor nutrition) are elderly take bone thinning medicines (such as anticonvulsant medicines or corticosteroids) for a long time. 
   *   have eye problems such as increased pressure in the eye, glaucoma, or cataracts 
 *   are planning to have surgery 
 *   are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. It is not known if PULMICORT FLEXHALER may harm your unborn baby 
 *   are breast-feeding or plan to breast-feed. PULMICORT FLEXHALER can pass into breast milk. You and your healthcare provider should decide if you will use PULMICORT FLEXHALER or breast-feed 
    Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take, including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Using PULMICORT FLEXHALER with certain other medicines may affect each other causing side effects. 
 

 Especially tell your healthcare provider if you take:



 *   a corticosteroid medicine 
 *   anti-seizure medicine (anticonvulsants) 
 *   medicines that suppress your immune system (immunosuppressant) 
 *   ketoconazale (Nizoral), other medicines that affect how your liver works. 
    Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure if your medicine is one listed above. 
 

 Know the medicines you take. Keep a list of them and show it to your healthcare provider and pharmacist when you get a new medicine. 



   How should I use PULMICORT FLEXHALER?  



 Use PULMICORT FLEXHALER exactly as prescribed by your healthcare provider. You must use PULMICORT FLEXHALER regularly for it to work.



 *   PULMICORT FLEXHALER comes in two strengths. Your healthcare provider has prescribed the strength that is best for you. 
 *   Be sure you know the difference between PULMICORT FLEXHALER and any other inhaled medicines that are prescribed for you, including what you use them for (prescribed use) and what they look like. 
    Do not stop using PULMICORT FLEXHALER, even if your symptoms get better. Your healthcare provider will change your medicines as needed.
 

 *   Do not change or stop any medicines used to control or treat your breathing problems, unless your healthcare provider tells you to. 
 *   Rinse your mouth with water and spit the water out after each dose of PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Do not swallow the water. This will lessen the chance of getting a fungal infection (thrush) in the mouth. 
 *   If you miss a dose, just take your next regularly scheduled dose when it is due. Do not use PULMICORT FLEXHALER more often or use more puffs than you have been prescribed. 
 *   Make sure you always have a short-acting beta2-agonist medicine with you. Use your short acting beta2-agonist medicine if you have breathing problems between doses of PULMICORT FLEXHALER or if a sudden asthma attack happens. Call your healthcare provider right away if: your short-acting rescue medicine does not work as well for relieving asthma symptoms. you need to use your short-acting rescue medicines more often than usual. your breathing problems worsen with PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
    If you use another inhaled medicine by mouth to treat your asthma, talk with your healthcare provider for instructions about when to use the other medicine and when to use your PULMICORT FLEXHALER.
 

 *   If you have used corticosteroid medicines for a long time and the dose is now being lowered or stopped, you should carry a medical alert card. The medical alert card should state that you may need increased corticosteroids during times of stress or during an asthma attack that does not get better with bronchodilator medicines. 
 *   Your healthcare provider may check your breathing, do blood tests and eye exams during treatment with PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
    Be sure to read, understand and follow the detailed Patient Instructions for Use at the end of this leaflet. These Instructions for Use tell you how to prime and use your PULMICORT FLEXHALER the right way.
 

   What are the possible side effects of PULMICORT FLEXHALER?  



 PULMICORT FLEXHALER can cause serious side effects, including:



 *   thrush (candida), a fungal infection in your mouth and throat. Tell your healthcare provider if you have any redness or white colored patches in your mouth or throat. 
 *   worsening of asthma or sudden asthma attacks. 
 *   allergic reactions. Tell your healthcare provider or get medical help right away if you have: skin rash, redness or swelling severe itching swelling of the face, mouth, and tongue trouble breathing or swallowing chest pain anxiety (feeling of doom) 
   *   Immune system effects and a higher chance of infections. You are more likely to get infections if you take medicines that weaken your immune system. Avoid contact with people who have contagious diseases such as chicken pox or measles while using PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Symptoms of infection may include: fever, pain, aches, chills, feeling tired, nausea and vomiting. Tell your healthcare provider about any signs of infection while you are using PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
 *   Adrenal insufficiency. Adrenal insufficiency is a condition in which the adrenal glands do not make enough steroid hormones. Symptoms of adrenal insufficiency include: tiredness, weakness, nausea and vomiting and low blood pressure. 
 *   Decrease in bone mineral density. Your healthcare provider should check you for this during treatment with PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
 *   Slowed or delayed growth problems in children. A child's growth should be checked regularly while using PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
 *   Eye problems, including glaucoma and cataracts. You should have regular eye exams while using PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
 *   Increased wheezing right after taking PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Always have a short-acting beta2-agonist medicine (rescue inhaler) with you to treat sudden wheezing. 
      Call your healthcare provider or get medical help right away if you have symptoms of any of the serious side effects listed above.  
 

 Common side effects reported by patients using PULMICORT FLEXHALER include:



 *   sore nose and throat 
 *   stuffy nose 
 *   runny nose 
 *   nausea 
 *   hay fever 
 *   viral infections of the upper respiratory tract 
 *   viral irritation and inflammation of the stomach and intestine (gastroenteritis). Symptoms may include stomach area pain, diarrhea, nausea and vomiting, loss of appetite, headaches, and weakness. 
 *   ear infections 
    Tell your healthcare provider about any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away. 
 

 These are not all of the side effects of PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for more information. 



 Call your healthcare provider for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.



   How should I store PULMICORT FLEXHALER?  



 Store PULMICORT FLEXHALER at 68 degrees  to 77 degrees F (20 degrees  to 25 degrees C).



 *   Keep PULMICORT FLEXHALER dry. 
 *   Keep your PULMICORT FLEXHALER with the cover tightly in place when not in use. 
      Keep your PULMICORT FLEXHALER and all medicines out of the reach of children.   
 

   General Information about PULMICORT FLEXHALER  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for conditions that are not mentioned in Patient Information Leaflets. Do not use PULMICORT FLEXHALER for a condition for which it was not prescribed. Do not give PULMICORT FLEXHALER to other people, even if they have the same symptoms that you have. It may harm them. 



 This Patient Information leaflet summarizes the most important information about PULMICORT FLEXHALER. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You can ask your pharmacist or healthcare provider for information about PULMICORT FLEXHALER that is written for health professionals. 



 For more information, go to pulmicortflexhaler.com or call 1- 800-236-9933.



   What are the ingredients in PULMICORT FLEXHALER?  



 Active ingredient: budesonide 



 Inactive ingredient: lactose 



   Patient Instructions for Use   



   How to use your PULMICORT FLEXHALER  



   Parts of your PULMICORT FLEXHALER  



 Figure 1



     Priming PULMICORT FLEXHALER:    



   Before you use a new PULMICORT FLEXHALER for the first time, you must prime it.  



 To prime your PULMICORT FLEXHALER, follow the steps below:



 *   Hold the inhaler by the brown grip so that the white cover points upward (upright position). With the other hand, turn the white cover and lift it off (see Figure 2). 
 *   Continue to hold your PULMICORT FLEXHALER upright as shown in Figure 1. Use your other hand to hold the inhaler in the middle. Do not hold the inhaler at the top of the mouthpiece. 
 *   Twist the brown grip as far as it will go in one direction and then fully back again in the other direction until it stops (it does not matter which way you turn it first). You will hear a "click" during one of the twisting movements (see Figures 3 and 4). 
 *   Repeat Step 3. Your PULMICORT FLEXHALER is now primed. You are ready to load your first dose. 
      You do not have to prime your PULMICORT FLEXHALER again after this even if you do not use it for a long period of time.  
 

 ?  Loading a dose  



 1. Hold your PULMICORT FLEXHALER upright as described above. With your other hand, twist the white cover and lift it off (see Figure 2).



 Figure 2



 2. Continue to hold your PULMICORT FLEXHALER upright to be sure that the right dose of medicine is loaded. 



 3. Use your other hand to hold the inhaler in the middle. Do not hold the mouthpiece when you load the inhaler. 



 4. Twist the brown grip fully in one direction as far as it will go. Twist it fully back again in the other direction as far as it will go (it does not matter which way you turn it first) [see Figure 3]. 



 Figure 3



  You will hear a "click" during one of the twisting movements (see Figure 4). 



 Figure 4



 *   PULMICORT FLEXHALER will only give one dose at a time, no matter how often you click the brown grip, but the dose indicator will continue to move (advance). This means that if you continue to move the brown grip, it is possible for the indicator to show fewer doses or zero doses even if more doses are left in the inhaler. 
 *   Do not shake the inhaler after loading it. 
    Figure 5 
 

 ?  Inhaling a dose  



 *   Turn your head away from the inhaler and breathe out (exhale). If you accidentally blow into your inhaler after loading a dose, follow the instructions for loading a new dose. 
 *   Place the mouthpiece in your mouth and close your lips around the mouthpiece. Breathe in (inhale) deeply and forcefully through the inhaler (see Figure 5). 
 *   You may not sense the presence of any medication entering your lungs when inhaling from PULMICORT FLEXHALER. This lack of sensation does not mean that you did not get the medication. You should not repeat your inhalations even if you did not feel the medication when inhaling. 
 *   Do not chew or bite on the mouthpiece. 
 *   Remove the inhaler from your mouth and exhale. Do not blow or exhale into the mouthpiece. 
 *   If more than one dose is prescribed repeat the steps above. 
 *   When you are finished taking your dose place the white cover back on the inhaler and twist shut. 
 *   Rinse your mouth with water after each dose to decrease your risk of getting thrush. Do not swallow the water. 
      Reading the Dose Indicator Window  
 

 *   The label on the box or cover will tell you how many doses are in your PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
 *   Your PULMICORT FLEXHALER has a dose indicator window just below the mouthpiece. The dose indicator tells you about how many doses are left in the inhaler. Look at the middle of the window to find out about how many doses are left in your inhaler (see Figure 6). 
    Figure 6
 

 *   The dose indicator is connected to the turning grip and moves (counts down) every time a dose is loaded. It is not likely that you will see the dose indicator move with each dose. You can usually see the indicator move each time you use about 5 doses. 
 *   The dose indicator starts with either the number 60 or 120 when full, depending upon the strength of the inhaler. The indicator is marked in intervals of 10 doses. Markings are either with numbers or dashes (alternating), counting down to "0". 
  
 60 Dose Inhaler  120 Dose Inhaler                    
 20-40-60         80-100-120       Dose indicator starts at 60 or 120 depending on strength (90 mcg or 180 mcg) of the inhaler and counts down to 0.   
        *   The dose indicator will tell you about how many doses are left in your PULMICORT FLEXHALER. 
 *   If you complete the instructions for loading the dose more than one time before you inhale the dose, you will only receive one dose. The dose indicator will move a small amount but it is not likely that you will see the dose indicator move with each dose. 
 *   Your inhaler is empty when the number 0 on the red background reaches the middle of the dose indicator window. Throw away this inhaler. The inhaler may not give you the right amount of medicine, even though it may not feel completely empty and may seem like it continues to work (see Figure 7). 
    Figure 7
 

 *   Do not put your PULMICORT FLEXHALER in water (do not immerse it) to find out if it is empty. Check the dose indicator window to see how many doses are left. 
 *   Refill your PULMICORT FLEXHALER prescription before your medicine runs out. You will get a new inhaler each time you refill your prescription. 
      Cleaning your PULMICORT FLEXHALER  
 

 *   Keep your PULMICORT FLEXHALER clean and dry at all times. Do not immerse it in water. 
 *   Wipe the outside of the mouthpiece one time each week with a dry tissue. 
 *   Do not use water or liquids when cleaning the mouthpiece. 
 *   Do not try to remove the mouthpiece or twist it. 
      Do not use your PULMICORT FLEXHALER if it has been damaged or if the mouthpiece has become detached. Talk to your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you have any problems with your PULMICORT FLEXHALER.  
 

 PULMICORT FLEXHALER is a trademark of the AstraZeneca group of companies. 



 (c)AstraZeneca 2007, 2008, 2010



 Manufactured for: AstraZeneca LP, Wilmington DE 19850 



 By: AstraZeneca AB, Sodertalje, Sweden 



 Product of Sweden



 Repackaged by:



 Rebel Distributors Corp



 Thousand Oaks, CA 91320



  Figure 1  Figure 2  Figure 3  Figure 4  Figure 5  Figure 6  Figure 7 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



    EXCERPT:    Localized infections: Candida albicans  infection of the mouth and throat may occur. Monitor patients periodically for signs of adverse effects on the oral cavity. Advise patients to rinse the mouth following inhalation. (5.1)



  Deterioration of asthma or acute episodes: PULMICORT FLEXHALER should not be used for relief of acute symptoms. Patients require immediate re-evaluation during rapidly deteriorating asthma. (5.2)



  Hypersensitivity reactions: Anaphylaxis, rash, contact dermatitis, urticaria, angioedema, and bronchospasm have been reported with use of PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Discontinue PULMICORT FLEXHALER if such reactions occur. (5.3)



  Immunosuppression: Potential worsening of infections (e.g., existing tuberculosis, fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infection; or ocular herpes simplex). Use with caution in patients with these infections. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles can occur in susceptible patients. (5.4)



  Transferring patients from systemic corticosteroids: Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring from oral steroids. Taper patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to PULMICORT FLEXHALER. (5.5)



  Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression: May occur with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals. If such changes occur, reduce PULMICORT FLEXHALER slowly. (5.6)



  Reduction in bone mineral density with long term administration. Monitor patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content. (5.8)



  Effects on growth: Monitor growth of pediatric patients. (5.9)



  Glaucoma and cataracts: Close monitoring is warranted. (5.10)



  Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue PULMICORT FLEXHALER and institute alternative therapy if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs. (5.11)



  Eosinophilic conditions and Churg-Strauss: Be alert to eosinophilic conditions. (5.12)



 



   5.1 Local Effects



  In clinical studies, the development of localized infections of the mouth and pharynx with Candida albicans  has occurred in patients treated with PULMICORT FLEXHALER. When such an infection develops, it should be treated with appropriate local or systemic (i.e. oral antifungal) therapy while treatment with PULMICORT FLEXHALER continues, but at times, therapy with PULMICORT FLEXHALER may need to be interrupted. Patients should rinse the mouth after inhalation of PULMICORT FLEXHALER.



    5.2 Deterioration of Asthma or Acute Episodes



  PULMICORT FLEXHALER is not a bronchodilator and is not indicated for the rapid relief of bronchospasm or other acute episodes of asthma. Patients should be instructed to contact their physician immediately if episodes of asthma not responsive to their usual doses of bronchodilators occur during the course of treatment with PULMICORT FLEXHALER. During such episodes, patients may require therapy with oral corticosteroids.



 An inhaled short acting beta2-agonist, not PULMICORT FLEXHALER, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath. When prescribing PULMICORT FLEXHALER, the physician must also provide the patient with an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist (e.g. albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms, despite regular twice-daily (morning and evening) use of PULMICORT FLEXHALER.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions Including Anaphylaxis



  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, rash, contact dermatitis, urticaria, angioedema, and bronchospasm have been reported with use of PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Discontinue PULMICORT FLEXHALER if such reactions occur [see   Contraindications (4)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)    ].



 PULMICORT FLEXHALER contains small amounts of lactose, which contains trace levels of milk proteins. It is possible that cough, wheezing, or bronchospasm may occur in patients who have a severe milk protein allergy [see   Contraindications (4)  and  Adverse Reactions, Post-marketing Experience (6.2)    ].



    5.4 Immunosuppression



  Patients who are on drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infection than healthy individuals. Chicken pox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible children or adults using corticosteroids. In children or adults who have not had these diseases or been properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affects the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If exposed to chicken pox, therapy with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG), as appropriate, may be indicated. If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See the respective package inserts for complete VZIG and IG prescribing information.) If chicken pox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered. The immune responsiveness to varicella vaccine was evaluated in pediatric patients with asthma ages 12 months to 8 years with budesonide inhalation suspension.



 An open-label, nonrandomized clinical study examined the immune responsiveness to varicella vaccine in 243 asthma patients 12 months to 8 years of age who were treated with budesonide inhalation suspension 0.25 mg to 1 mg daily (n=151) or non-corticosteroid asthma therapy (n=92) (i.e., beta2-agonists, leukotriene receptor antagonists, cromones). The percentage of patients developing a seroprotective antibody titer of &gt;=5.0 (gpELISA value) in response to the vaccination was similar in patients treated with budesonide inhalation suspension (85%), compared to patients treated with non-corticosteroid asthma therapy (90%). No patient treated with budesonide inhalation suspension developed chicken pox as a result of vaccination.



 Inhaled corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection of the respiratory tract, untreated systemic fungal, bacterial, viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex.



    5.5 Transferring Patients from Systemic Corticosteroid Therapy



  Particular care is needed for patients who are transferred from systemically active corticosteroids to PULMICORT FLEXHALER because deaths due to adrenal insufficiency have occurred in asthmatic patients during and after transfer from systemic corticosteroids to less systemically available inhaled corticosteroids. After withdrawal from systemic corticosteroids, a number of months are required for recovery of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) function.



 Patients who have been previously maintained on 20 mg or more per day of prednisone (or its equivalent) may be most susceptible, particularly when their systemic corticosteroids have been almost completely withdrawn.



 During this period of HPA suppression, patients may exhibit signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency when exposed to trauma, surgery, or infection (particularly gastroenteritis) or other conditions associated with severe electrolyte loss. Although PULMICORT FLEXHALER may provide control of asthma symptoms during these episodes, in recommended doses it supplies less than normal physiological amounts of glucocorticoid systemically and does NOT provide the mineralocorticoid activity that is necessary for coping with these emergencies.



 During periods of stress or a severe asthma attack, patients who have been withdrawn from systemic corticosteroids should be instructed to resume oral corticosteroids (in large doses) immediately and to contact their physicians for further instruction. These patients should also be instructed to carry a medical identification card indicating that they may need supplementary systemic corticosteroids during periods of stress or a severe asthma attack.



 Patients requiring oral corticosteroids should be weaned slowly from systemic corticosteroid use after transferring to PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Prednisone reduction can be accomplished by reducing the daily prednisone dose by 2.5 mg on a weekly basis during therapy with PULMICORT FLEXHALER. Lung function (mean forced expiratory volume in 1 second [FEV1] or morning peak expiratory flow [PEF]), beta-agonist use, and asthma symptoms should be carefully monitored during withdrawal of oral corticosteroids. In addition to monitoring asthma signs and symptoms, patients should be observed for signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency such as fatigue, lassitude, weakness, nausea and vomiting, and hypotension.



 Transfer of patients from systemic corticosteroid therapy to PULMICORT FLEXHALER may unmask allergic conditions previously suppressed by the systemic corticosteroid therapy, (e.g., rhinitis, conjunctivitis, eczema, arthritis, eosinophilic conditions). Some patients may experience symptoms of systemically active corticosteroid withdrawal (e.g., joint and/or muscular pain, lassitude, depression) despite maintenance or even improvement of respiratory function.



    5.6 Hypercorticism and Adrenal Suppression



  PULMICORT FLEXHALER will often help control asthma symptoms with less suppression of HPA function than therapeutically equivalent oral doses of prednisone. Since budesonide is absorbed into the circulation and can be systemically active at higher doses, the beneficial effects of PULMICORT FLEXHALER in minimizing HPA dysfunction may be expected only when recommended dosages are not exceeded and individual patients are titrated to the lowest effective dose. Since individual sensitivity to effects on cortisol production exists, physicians should consider this information when prescribing PULMICORT FLEXHALER.



 Because of the possibility of systemic absorption of inhaled corticosteroids, patients treated with PULMICORT FLEXHALER should be observed carefully for any evidence of systemic corticosteroid effects. Particular care should be taken in observing patients postoperatively or during periods of stress for evidence of inadequate adrenal response.



 It is possible that systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression (including adrenal crisis) may appear in a small number of patients, particularly when budesonide is administered at higher than recommended doses over prolonged periods of time. If such effects occur, the dosage of PULMICORT FLEXHALER should be reduced slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for reducing systemic corticosteroids and for management of asthma symptoms.



    5.7 Interactions with Strong Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors



  Caution should be exercised when considering the co-administration of PULMICORT FLEXHALER with ketoconazole, and other known strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (e.g. ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin) because adverse effects related to increased systemic exposure to budesonide may occur [ee   Drug Interactions (7.1),    Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



    5.8 Reduction in Bone Mineral Density



  Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) have been observed with long-term administration of products containing inhaled corticosteroids. The clinical significance of small changes in BMD with regard to long-term consequences such as fracture is unknown. Patients with major risk factors for decreased bone mineral content, such as prolonged immobilization, family history of osteoporosis, post menopausal status, tobacco use, advance age, poor nutrition, or chronic use of drugs that can reduce bone mass (e.g, anticonvulsants, oral corticosteroids) should be monitored and treated with established standards of care.



    5.9 Effect on Growth



  Orally inhaled corticosteroids, including budesonide, may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to pediatric patients. Monitor the growth of pediatric patients receiving PULMICORT FLEXHALER routinely (e.g., via stadiometry). To minimize the systemic effects of orally inhaled corticosteroids, including PULMICORT FLEXHALER, titrate each patient's dose to the lowest dosage that effectively controls his/her symptoms [see   Dosage and Administration (2.1),    Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ].



    5.10 Glaucoma and Cataracts



  Glaucoma, increased intraocular pressure, and cataracts have been reported following the long-term administration of inhaled corticosteroids, including budesonide. Therefore, close monitoring is warranted in patients with a change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and/or cataracts.



    5.11 Paradoxical Bronchospasm and Upper Airway Symptoms



  As with other inhaled asthma medications, PULMICORT FLEXHALER can produce paradoxical bronchospasm, which may be life threatening. If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs following dosing with PULMICORT FLEXHALER, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting beta2- bronchodilator. PULMICORT FLEXHALER should be discontinued immediately, and alternative therapy should be instituted.



    5.12 Eosinophilic Conditions and Churg-Strauss Syndrome



  In rare cases, patients on inhaled corticosteroids may present with systemic eosinophilic conditions. Some of these patients have clinical features of vasculitis consistent with Churg- Strauss syndrome, a condition that is often treated with systemic corticosteroid therapy. These events usually, but not always, have been associated with the reduction and/or withdrawal of oral corticosteroid therapy following the introduction of inhaled corticosteroids. Physicians should be alert to eosinophilia, vasculitic rash, worsening pulmonary symptoms, cardiac complications, and/or neuropathy presenting in their patients. A causal relationship between budesonide and these underlying conditions has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
