<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="pylera" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Most frequently reported adverse reactions (&gt;=5%); abnormal feces, diarrhea, nausea, and headache.  (6.1)  



     



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AXCAN Pharma US, Inc. at 1-800-472-2634 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of PYLERA plus omeprazole (OBMT) to eradicate  Helicobacter pylori  was assessed in an open-label, randomized, active-controlled clinical trial conducted in North America. The duration of treatment was 10 days with 147 patients exposed to PYLERA plus omeprazole (OBMT) and 152 exposed to control, consisting of omeprazole, amoxicillin, and clarithromycin (OAC). The age of the population in the study ranged from 18 to 75 years, with 59% male patients and 59% Caucasian patients.



 Adverse drug reactions were reported in 58% of patients in the OBMT group and 59% of patients in the OAC group. There were no adverse reactions leading to discontinuation of the study during the clinical trial.



 Adverse reactions with an incidence of &gt;= 5% in OBMT group include abnormal feces, diarrhea, nausea, and headache. Adverse drug reactions with an incidence of &gt;= 5% in OAC group include diarrhea, dysgeusia, dyspepsia, nausea and headache.



   Table 2  lists adverse reactions with an incidence of &gt;= 1%, in either groups (OBMT vs OAC) and in order of decreasing incidence for the OBMT group.



 Table 2: Adverse reactions with an incidence of &gt;= 1% from North American trial, [n (%)] 
   Preferred Term      OBMT(n = 147)      OAC(n = 152)     
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
 Abnormal feces     23 (15.6%)        7 (4.6%)       
 Nausea              12 (8.2%)        14 (9.2%)      
 Diarrhea            10 (6.8%)       20 (13.2%)      
 Abdominal Pain      7 (4.8%)         2 (1.3%)       
 Dyspepsia           4 (2.7%)         10 (6.6%)      
 Constipation        2 (1.4%)         5 (3.3%)       
 Dry Mouth           2 (1.4%)         1 (0.7%)       
 Flatulence              0            4 (2.6%)       
 Glossitis               0            2 (1.3%)       
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
 Asthenia            5 (3.4%)         2 (1.3%)       
   Infections and infestations     
 Vaginal infection     4 (2.7%)         3 (2.0%)       
   Nervous system disorders     
 Headache            8 (5.4%)         8 (5.3%)       
 Dysgeusia           6 (4.1%)        18 (11.8%)      
 Dizziness           4 (2.7%)         4 (2.6%)       
   Investigations     
 Laboratory test abnormal     3 (2.0%)         4 (2.6%)       
 Alanine aminotransferase increased     2 (1.4%)             0          
 Aspartate aminotransferase increased     2 (1.4%)             0          
   Renal and urinary disorders     
 Urine abnormality     2 (1.4%)             0          
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders     
 Rash Maculo-Papular     2 (1.4%)             0          
 Rash                1 (0.7%)         3 (2.0%)       
 Pruritus                0            4 (2.6%)       
      Adverse reactions with an incidence of &lt;1% for OBMT group are: back pain, vomiting, tongue darkening [See  Warnings and Precautions  (5.7)  ].  , anxiety, gastritis, gastroenteritis, myalgia, chest pain, increased appetite, blood creatine phosphokinase increased, malaise, somnolence, tachycardia, duodenal ulcer, visual disturbance, weight increased.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Additionally, the following adverse reactions, presented by system organ class in alphabetical order, have been identified during post approval use of PYLERA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *   Gastrointestinal disorders : abdominal distention, eructation, flatulence 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions : chest discomfort, fatigue. 
 *   Infections and infestations : candidiasis. 
      6.3 Other Important Adverse Reactions from Labeling for the Individual Components of PYLERA
     Metronidazole  



   Blood and Lymphatic system disorders:  reversible neutropenia, (leucopenia) in cases of prolonged treatment; rarely reversible thrombocytopenia however no persistent haematological abnormalities attributable to metronidazole have been observed [See  Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)  ]  .



   Cardiac disorders:  Flattening of the T-wave may be seen in electrocardiographic tracings.



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  Furry tongue, glositis, stomatitis; these may be associated with a sudden overgrowth of candida which may occur during therapy[See  Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  .



   Immune system disorders:  Urticaria, erythematous rash, Stevens - Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, flushing, nasal congestion, and fever [See  Contraindications  (4.5)  ]  .



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  Cases of pancreatitis have been reported, which abated on withdrawal of the drug, have been reported.



   Nervous system disorders:  The most serious adverse reactions reported in patients treated with metronidazole have been convulsive seizures, encephalopathy, aseptic meningitis, optic and peripheral neuropathy, the latter characterized mainly by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity. In addition, patients have reported syncope, vertigo, incoordination, ataxia, confusion, dysarthria, irritability, depression, weakness and insomnia [See  Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)  ]  .



   Tetracycline Hydrochloride  



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  Hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, thrombocytopenic purpura, neutropenia, and eosinophilia.



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  Rare instances of esophagitis and esophageal ulceration have been reported in patients taking the tetracycline-class antibiotics in capsule and tablet form. Most of the patients who experienced esophageal irritation took the medication immediately before going to bed. Permanent discoloration of teeth may be caused when tetracycline is used during tooth development. Enamel hypoplasia has also been reported [See  Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ].  



   Nervous system disorders:  Pseudotumor cerebri (benign intracranial hypertension) in adults and bulging fontanels in infants. Tinnitus and myasthenic syndrome have been reported rarely.



   Renal and urinary disorders:  Rise in BUN has been reported and is possibly dose related [See  Contraindications  (4.4)  ]  .



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Exfoliative dermatitis and photosensitivity have been rarely reported [See  Warnings and Precautions  (5.5)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  Fetal Toxicity: Advise pregnant women of the risk for permanent discoloration of teeth with tetracycline if used during the second or third trimester  (5.1,    8.1)   
 *  Maternal Toxicity: Risk of hepatotoxicity in pregnant women with high doses of intravenous tetracycline also resulting in stillborn or premature birth  (5.2,    8.1)   
 *  Central and Peripheral Nervous System Effects: encephalopathy and peripheral neuropathy with metronidazole, pseudotumor cerebri with tetracycline and neurotoxicity with bismuth-containing products; Monitor patients with CNS conditions closely and discontinue promptly if abnormal neurologic signs develop.  (5.4)   
 *  Development of Superinfection: If superinfection occurs, discontinue PYLERA and institute appropriate therapy.  (5.5)   
 *  Photosensitivity: avoid exposure to sun and sun lamps.  (5.6)   
    
 

   5.1 Fetal Toxicity



  There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of PYLERA in pregnant women. However, tetracycline can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant women. The use of drugs of the tetracycline class during the second and third trimester pregnancy can also cause permanent discoloration of the teeth (yellow-gray brown) and possibly inhibit bone development [See Warnings and Precautions  (5.3)  ]  . Administration of oral tetracycline to pregnant rats at various doses resulted in yellow fluorescence in teeth and bones in newborn animals. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [See Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  ]  



    5.2 Maternal Toxicity



  Tetracycline administered during pregnancy at high doses (&gt; 2 g IV) was associated with rare but serious cases of maternal hepatotoxicity. This syndrome may result in stillborn or premature birth due to maternal pathology [See Use in Specific Populations  (8.3)  ].  



    5.3 Tooth Enamel Discoloration and Hypoplasia



  The use of drugs of the tetracycline class during tooth development (last half of pregnancy, infancy, and childhood to the age of 8 years) may cause permanent discoloration of the teeth (yellow-gray brown). This adverse reaction is more commom during long-term use of the drug, but has been observed following repeated short-courses. Enamel hypoplasia has also been reported. PYLERA, therefore, should not be used in this age group unless other drugs are not likely to be effective or are contraindicated [See Use in Specific Populations  (8.4)  ]  .



    5.4 Central and Peripheral Nervous System Effects



  Metronidazole: Cases of encephalopathy and peripheral neuropathy (including optic neuropathy) have been reported with metronidazole: Encephalopathy has been reported in association with cerebellar toxicity characterized by ataxia, dizziness, and dysarthria. CNS lesions seen on MRI have been described in reports of encephalopathy. CNS symptoms are generally reversible within days to weeks upon discontinuation of metronidazole. CNS lesions seen on MRI have also been described as reversible; Peripheral neuropathy, mainly of sensory type has been reported and is characterized by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity.



 Convulsive seizures have been reported in patients treated with metronidazole.



 Aseptic meningitis: Cases of aseptic meningitis have been reported with metronidazole. Symptoms can occur within hours of dose adiminstration and generally resolve after metronidazole therapy is discontinued.



 Tetracycline: Cases of pseudotumor cerebri in adults have been associated with the use of tetracycline. The usual clinical manifestations are headache and blurred vision. While this condition and related symptoms usually resolve soon after discontinuation of the tetracycline, the possibility for permanent sequelae exists.



 Bismuth-containing products: Cases of neurotoxicity associated with excessive doses of various bismuth-containing products have been reported. Effects have been reversible with discontinuation of bismuth therapy.



 The appearance of abnormal neurologic signs and symptoms demands the prompt evaluation of the benefit/risk ratio of the continuation of PYLERA therapy [See Adverse Reactions  (6.3)  ]  



    5.5 Development of Superinfections



  Known or previously unrecognized candidiasis may present more prominent symptoms during therapy with metronidazole and requires treatment with an antifungal agent.



 As with other antibiotics, use of tetracycline hydrochloride may result in overgrowth of nonsusceptible organisms, including fungi. If superinfection occurs, discontinue PYLERA and institute appropriate therapy



    5.6 Photosensitivity



  Photosensitivity, manifested by an exaggerated sunburn reaction, has been observed in patients taking tetracycline [See Adverse Reactions  (6.3)  ]  . Patients apt to be exposed to direct sunlight or ultraviolet light should be advised that this reaction can occur with tetracycline drugs. Instruct patients taking PYLERA to avoid exposure to the sun or sun lamps. Discontinue treatment at the first evidence of skin erythema.



    5.7 Darkening of the Tongue and/or Black Stool



  Bismuth subcitrate potassium may cause temporary and harmless darkening of the tongue and/or black stool, generally reversible within several days after treatment is stopped [See Adverse Reactions  (6.1)  ]  . Stool darkening should not be confused with melena.



    5.8 Use in Patients with Blood Dyscrasias



  Metronidazole is a nitroimidazole, and should be used with care in patients with evidence or history of blood dyscrasia. A mild leukopenia has been observed during its administration; however, no persistent hematologic abnormalities attributable to metronidazole have been observed in clinical studies. Total and differential leukocyte counts are recommended before and after therapy [See Adverse Reactions  (6.3)  ]  .



    5.9 Laboratory Test Interactions



  Bismuth absorbs x-rays and may interfere with x-ray diagnostic procedures of the gastrointestinal tract.



 Bismuth subcitrate potassium may cause a temporary and harmless darkening of the stool. However, this change does not interfere with standard tests for occult blood.



 Metronizadole may interfere with certain types of determinations of serum chemistry values, such as aspartate aminotransferase (AST, SGOT), alanine aminotransferase (ALT, SGPT), lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), triglycerides, and hexokinase glucose. Values of zero may be observed. All of the assays in which interference has been reported involve enzymatic coupling of the assay to oxidation-reduction of nicotinamide (NAD+ &lt;=&gt; NADH). Interference is due to the similarity in absorbance peaks of NADH (340 nm) and metronidazole (322 nm) at pH 7



    5.10 Development of Drug Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing PYLERA in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
