<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="qnasl" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic and local corticosteroid use may result in the following:



 *    Epistaxis, nasal discomfort, nasal ulcerations, Candida albicans infection, and impaired wound healing [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *    Glaucoma and cataracts [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *    Hypercorticism, adrenal suppression, and growth reduction [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    (5.6)   ,   Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  
 *    Immunosuppression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 1% and greater than placebo) in patients 12 years of age and older include nasal discomfort, epistaxis, and headache. (    6.1    )
 

 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2% and greater than placebo) in children 4 to 11 years of age include headache, pyrexia, upper respiratory tract infection, and nasopharyngitis. (    6.1    )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Teva Respiratory, LLC at 1-888-482-9522 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adults and Adolescents 12 Years of Age and Older  :  



 The safety data described below for adults and adolescents 12 years of age and older with seasonal or perennial allergic rhinitis are based on 4 placebo-controlled clinical trials of 2 to 6 weeks duration evaluating doses of beclomethasone nasal aerosol from 80 to 320 mcg once daily. These short-term trials included a total of 1394 patients with either seasonal or perennial allergic rhinitis. Of these, 575 (378 female and 197 male) received at least one dose of QNASL Nasal Aerosol, 320 mcg once daily and 578 (360 female and 218 male) received placebo. Patient ages ranged from 12 to 82 years and the racial distribution of patients was 81% white, 16% black, and 4% other.



   Short-Term (2-6 Weeks) Trials  :Less than 2% of patients in the clinical trials discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions with the rate of withdrawal among patients who received QNASL Nasal Aerosol similar to or lower than the rate among patients who received placebo.  Table  displays the common adverse reactions (&gt;= 1% and greater than placebo-treated patients).




                                Table 1. Adverse Events With &gt;= 1% Incidence and Greater than Placebo in QNASL 
                                Nasal Aerosol-Treated Adult and Adolescent Patients with Seasonal or 
                                Perennial Allergic Rhinitis in Controlled Clinical Trials of 2 to 6 Weeks 
                                Duration (Safety Population)  
                                                                
                                 Adult and Adolescent Patients 12 Years of Age and Older    
                                 QNASL Nasal Aerosol320 mcg(N = 575)n (%)    Placebo(N = 578)n (%)    
  Nasal Discomfort               30 (5.2)                                  28 (4.8)             
  Epistaxis                      11 (1.9)                                  7 (1.2)              
  Headache                       13 (2.3)                                  9 (1.6)              
         Nasal ulcerations occurred in 2 patients treated with placebo and in 1 patient treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol. There were no differences in the incidence of adverse reactions based on gender or race. Clinical trials did not have sufficient numbers of patients aged 65 years and older to determine whether they respond differently than younger patients.
 

   Long-Term 52-Week Safety Trial  : In a 52-week placebo-controlled long-term safety trial in patients with PAR, 415 patients (128 males and 287 females, aged 12 to 74 years) were treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol at a dose of 320 mcg once daily and 111 patients (44 males and 67 females, aged 12 to 67 years) were treated with placebo. Of the 415 patients treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol, 219 patients were treated for 52 weeks and 196 patients were treated for 30 weeks. While most adverse events were similar in type and rate between the treatment groups, epistaxis occurred more frequently in patients who received QNASL Nasal Aerosol (45 out of 415, 11%) than in patients who received placebo (2 out of 111, 2%). Epistaxis also tended to be more severe in patients treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol. In 45 reports of epistaxis in patients who received QNASL Nasal Aerosol, 27, 13, and 5 cases were of mild, moderate, and severe intensity, respectively, while the reports of epistaxis in patients who received placebo were of mild (1) and moderate (1) intensity. Seventeen patients treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol experienced adverse reactions that led to withdrawal from the trial compared to 3 patients treated with placebo. There were 4 nasal erosions and 1 nasal septum ulceration which occurred in patients who received QNASL Nasal Aerosol, and no erosions or ulcerations noted in patients who received placebo. No patient experienced a nasal septum perforation during the trial.



     Pediatric Patients Aged 4 to 11 Years  :  



 The safety data described below for pediatric patients 4 to 11 years of age with seasonal or perennial allergic rhinitis are based on 3 placebo-controlled clinical trials. These trials were 2 to 12 weeks in duration, evaluated doses of beclomethasone nasal aerosol 80 mcg to 160 mcg once daily and included a total of 1360 patients with either seasonal or perennial allergic rhinitis. Of these, 668 (312 female and 356 male) received at least one dose of QNASL Nasal Aerosol, 80 mcg once daily, 241 (116 female and 125 male) received QNASL Nasal Aerosol 160 mcg once daily, and 451 (203 female and 248 male) received placebo. The racial distribution of patients was 73% white, 20% black, and 6% other. Based on the results from the dose ranging trial, 80 mcg once daily was chosen as the dose in pediatric patients.



 Less than 1.5% of patients in the clinical trials discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions with the rate of withdrawal among patients who received QNASL Nasal Aerosol 80 mcg once daily similar to or lower than the rate among patients who received placebo.  Table 2  displays the common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2% and greater than placebo-treated patients). Additionally, epistaxis was reported at a rate of 4% for both QNASL Nasal Aerosol 80 mcg once daily and placebo treated patients.




                                    Aerosol-Treated Pediatric Patients with Seasonal or Perennial Allergic Rhinitis in 
                                    Controlled Clinical Trials of 2 to 12 weeks Duration (Safety Population) 
                                     Table 2. Adverse Events With &gt;= 2% Incidence and Greater than Placebo in QNASL Nasal    
                                     Pediatric Patients 4 to 11 Years of Age    
                                     QNASL Nasal Aerosol 80 mcg (N=668)  n (%)    Placebo (N=451)  n (%)    
  Headache                           23 (3.4)                           15 (3.3)             
  Pyrexia                            19 (2.8)                           7 (1.6)              
  Upper respiratory tract infection    17 (2.5)                           8 (1.8)              
  Nasopharyngitis                    15 (2.2)                           6 (1.3)              
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials for QNASL Nasal Aerosol, the following adverse events have been reported during postmarketing use of QNASL Nasal Aerosol or other intranasal and inhaled formulations of beclomethasone dipropionate. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to either their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or causal connection to beclomethasone dipropionate or a combination of these factors.



   QNASL Nasal Aerosol:  sneezing, burning sensation



   Intranasal beclomethasone dipropionate  : Nasal septal perforation, glaucoma, cataracts, loss of taste and smell, and hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, rash, and urticaria have been reported following intranasal administration of beclomethasone dipropionate.



   Inhaled beclomethasone dipropionate  : Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, angioedema, rash, urticaria, and bronchospasm have been reported following the oral inhalation of beclomethasone dipropionate.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Nasal discomfort, epistaxis, nasal ulceration, Candida albicans infection, nasal septal perforation, impaired wound healing. Monitor patients periodically for signs of adverse effects on the nasal mucosa. Avoid use in patients with recent nasal ulcers, nasal surgery, or nasal trauma. (   5.1   ) 
 *    Development of glaucoma or posterior subcapsular cataracts. Monitor patients closely with a change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and/or cataracts. (   5.2   ) 
 *    Hypersensitivity, rash, and urticaria may occur after administration of QNASL Nasal Aerosol. (   5.3   ) 
 *    Potential worsening of existing tuberculosis; fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infections; or ocular herpes simplex. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles in susceptible patients. Use caution in patients with the above because of the potential for worsening of these infections. (   5.4   ) 
 *    Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression with very high dosages or at the regular dosage in susceptible individuals. If such changes occur, discontinue QNASL Nasal Aerosol slowly. (   5.5   ) 
 *    Potential reduction in growth velocity in pediatric patients. Monitor growth routinely in pediatric patients receiving QNASL Nasal Aerosol. (   5.6   ,   8.4   ) 
    
 

   5.1 Local Nasal Effects



   Nasal Discomfort, Epistaxis, and Nasal Ulceration  : In clinical trials of 2 to 52 weeks duration, epistaxis and nasal ulcerations were observed more frequently and some epistaxis events were more severe in patients treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol than those who received placebo. In the 52-week safety trial in patients with perennial allergic rhinitis, nasal erosions were identified in 4 of 415 patients and a nasal ulceration was identified in 1 of 415 patients treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol. No nasal erosions or ulcerations were reported for patients who received placebo. In clinical trials conducted in pediatric patients ages 4 to 11 years, the local nasal effect was similar to those reported in patients 12 years of age and older. Patients using QNASL Nasal Aerosol over several months or longer should be examined periodically for possible changes in the nasal mucosa. If an adverse reaction (e.g., erosion, ulceration) is noted, discontinue QNASL Nasal Aerosol. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



   Candida  Infection  : In previous clinical trials with an aqueous formulation of beclomethasone dipropionate administered intranasally, localized infections of the nose and pharynx with Candida albicans  had been reported. There were no instances of similar infections observed in clinical trials with QNASL Nasal Aerosol. If such an infection develops, it may require treatment with appropriate local therapy and discontinuation of QNASL Nasal Aerosol treatment. Thus, patients using QNASL Nasal Aerosol over several months or longer should be examined periodically for evidence of Candida  infection.



  Nasal Septal Perforation  : Instances of nasal septal perforation have been reported in patients following the intranasal application of beclomethasone dipropionate. There were no nasal septal perforations reported during clinical trials in the indicated dose of QNASL 80 mcg Nasal Aerosol administered as 320 mcg once daily in adults and adolescents. There was one report of nasal septal perforation observed in the dose-ranging pediatric clinical trial.



  Impaired Wound Healing  : Because of the inhibitory effect of corticosteroids on wound healing, patients who have experienced recent nasal septal ulcers, nasal surgery, or nasal trauma should not use QNASL Nasal Aerosol until healing has occurred.



    5.2 Glaucoma and Cataracts



  Use of intranasal and inhaled corticosteroids may result in the development of glaucoma and/or cataracts. Therefore, close monitoring is warranted in patients with a change in vision or with a history of increased intraocular pressure, glaucoma, and/or cataracts.



 Glaucoma and cataract formation was evaluated with ocular assessments that included intraocular pressure measurements and slit lamp examinations in 245 adolescent and adult patients (12 years of age and older) with perennial allergic rhinitis who were treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol 320 mcg daily (N=197) or placebo (N=48) for up to 52 weeks. In 94% of patients, intraocular pressure (IOP) remained within the normal range (&lt;21 mmHg) during the treatment portion of the trial. There were 10 patients (5%) treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol and 1 patient (2%) treated with placebo that had intraocular pressure that increased above normal levels (&gt;=21 mmHg) and greater than baseline during the treatment portion of the trial. Two of these occurrences in patients treated with QNASL Nasal Aerosol were reported as adverse reactions, one serious. No instances of cataract formation or other clinically significant ocular incidents were reported in this 52-week safety trial. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions Including Anaphylaxis



  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, urticaria, and rash have been reported following administration of beclomethasone dipropionate nasally administered and inhalationally administered products. Angioedema, urticaria, and rash have been reported following administration of QNASL Nasal Aerosol. Discontinue QNASL Nasal Aerosol if any such reactions occur [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.4 Immunosuppression



  Persons who are using drugs that suppress the immune system (e.g., corticosteroids) are more susceptible to infections than healthy individuals. Chickenpox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible children or adults using corticosteroids. In children or adults who have not had these diseases or been properly immunized, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure. How the dose, route, and duration of corticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior corticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If a patient is exposed to chickenpox, prophylaxis with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) may be indicated. If a patient is exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated (see the respective package inserts for complete VZIG and IG prescribing information). If chickenpox or measles develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.



 Corticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculous infections of the respiratory tract, untreated local or systemic fungal or bacterial infections, systemic viral or parasitic infections, or ocular herpes simplex because of the potential for worsening of these infections.



    5.5 Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Adrenal Axis Effect



  When intranasal steroids are used at higher-than-recommended dosages or in susceptible individuals at recommended dosages, systemic corticosteroid effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression may appear. If such changes occur, the dosage of QNASL Nasal Aerosol should be discontinued slowly, consistent with accepted procedures for discontinuing oral corticosteroid therapy.



 The replacement of a systemic corticosteroid with a topical corticosteroid can be accompanied by signs of adrenal insufficiency. In addition, some patients may experience symptoms of corticosteroid withdrawal (e.g., joint and/or muscular pain, lassitude, and depression). Patients previously treated for prolonged periods with systemic corticosteroids and transferred to topical corticosteroids should be carefully monitored for acute adrenal insufficiency in response to stress. In patients who have asthma or other clinical conditions requiring long-term systemic corticosteroid treatment, rapid decreases in systemic corticosteroid dosages may cause a severe exacerbation of their symptoms.



    5.6 Effect on Growth



  Corticosteroids may cause a reduction in growth velocity when administered to pediatric patients. Routinely monitor the growth of pediatric patients receiving QNASL Nasal Aerosol [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
