<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="qsymia" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following important adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Fetal Toxicity: [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ,  (8.6)  ]  
 *  Elevation in Heart Rate [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Acute Angle Closure Glaucoma [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Mood and Sleep Disorders [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Cognitive Impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Metabolic Acidosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 5% and at a rate at least 1.5 times placebo) are: paraesthesia, dizziness, dysgeusia, insomnia, constipation, and dry mouth (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact VIVUS, Inc., at 1-888-998-4887 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described herein reflects exposure to Qsymia in two, 1-year, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicenter clinical trials, and two Phase 2 supportive trials in 2318 adult patients (936 [40.4%] patients with hypertension, 309 [13.3%] patients with type 2 diabetes, 808 [34.9%] patients with BMI greater than 40 kg/m  2  ) exposed for a mean duration of 298 days.



     Common Adverse Reactions  : Adverse reactions occurring at a rate of greater than or equal to 5% and at a rate at least 1.5 times placebo include paraesthesia, dizziness, dysgeusia, insomnia, constipation, and dry mouth.



 Adverse reactions reported in greater than or equal to 2% of Qsymia-treated patients and more frequently than in the placebo group are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions Reported in Greater Than or Equal to 2% of Patients and More Frequently than Placebo during 1 Year of Treatment - Overall Study Population 
 System Organ Class  Preferred Term        Placebo(N = 1561)%  Qsymia3.75 mg/23 mg(N = 240)%  Qsymia7.5 mg/46 mg(N = 498)%  Qsymia15 mg/92 mg(N = 1580)%   
  
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                     
   Paraesthesia                                  1.9              4.2             13.7             19.9         
   Headache                                      9.3             10.4              7.0             10.6         
   Dizziness                                     3.4              2.9              7.2              8.6         
   Dysgeusia                                     1.1              1.3              7.4              9.4         
   Hypoesthesia                                  1.2              0.8              3.6              3.7         
   Disturbance in Attention                      0.6              0.4              2.0              3.5         
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                        
   Insomnia                                      4.7              5.0              5.8              9.4         
   Depression                                    2.2              3.3              2.8              4.3         
   Anxiety                                       1.9              2.9              1.8              4.1         
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                   
   Constipation                                  6.1              7.9             15.1             16.1         
   Dry Mouth                                     2.8              6.7             13.5             19.1         
   Nausea                                        4.4              5.8              3.6              7.2         
   Diarrhea                                      4.9              5.0              6.4              5.6         
   Dyspepsia                                     1.7              2.1              2.2              2.8         
   Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease               1.3              0.8              3.2              2.6         
   Paraesthesia Oral                             0.3              0.4              0.6              2.2         
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                         
   Fatigue                                       4.3              5.0              4.4              5.9         
   Irritability                                  0.7              1.7              2.6              3.7         
   Thirst                                        0.7              2.1              1.8              2.0         
   Chest Discomfort                              0.4              2.1              0.2              0.9         
   Eye Disorders                                                                                                
   Vision Blurred                                3.5              6.3              4.0              5.4         
   Eye Pain                                      1.4              2.1              2.2              2.2         
   Dry Eye                                       0.8              0.8              1.4              2.5         
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                                            
   Palpitations                                  0.8              0.8              2.4              1.7         
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                         
   Rash                                          2.2              1.7              2.0              2.6         
   Alopecia                                      0.7              2.1              2.6              3.7         
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                           
   Hypokalemia                                   0.4              0.4              1.4              2.5         
   Decreased Appetite                            0.6              2.1              1.8              1.5         
   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders                                                                         
   Dysmenorrhea                                  0.2              2.1              0.4              0.8         
   Infections and Infestations                                                                                  
   Upper Respiratory Tract Infection            12.8             15.8             12.2             13.5         
   Nasopharyngitis                               8.0             12.5             10.6              9.4         
   Sinusitis                                     6.3              7.5              6.8              7.8         
   Bronchitis                                    4.2              6.7              4.4              5.4         
   Influenza                                     4.4              7.5              4.6              4.4         
   Urinary Tract Infection                       3.6              3.3              5.2              5.2         
   Gastroenteritis                               2.2              0.8              2.2              2.5         
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                         
   Back Pain                                     5.1              5.4              5.6              6.6         
   Pain in Extremity                             2.8              2.1              3.0              3.0         
   Muscle Spasms                                 2.2              2.9              2.8              2.9         
   Musculoskeletal Pain                          1.2              0.8              3.0              1.6         
   Neck Pain                                     1.3              1.3              2.2              1.2         
   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders                                                                         
   Cough                                         3.5              3.3              3.8              4.8         
   Sinus Congestion                              2.0              2.5              2.6              2.0         
   Pharyngolaryngeal Pain                        2.0              2.5              1.2              2.3         
   Nasal Congestion                              1.4              1.7              1.2              2.0         
   Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications                                                                         
   Procedural Pain                               1.7              2.1              2.4              1.9         
               Paraesthesia/Dysgeusia  
 

 Reports of paraesthesia, characterized as tingling in hands, feet, or face, occurred in 4.2%, 13.7%, and 19.9% of patients treated with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 15 mg/92 mg, respectively, compared to 1.9% of patients treated with placebo. Dysgeusia was characterized as a metallic taste, and occurred in 1.3%, 7.4%, and 9.4% of patients treated with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 15 mg/92 mg, respectively, compared to 1.1% of patients treated with placebo. The majority of these events first occurred within the initial 12 weeks of drug therapy; however, in some patients, events were reported later in the course of treatment. Only Qsymia-treated patients discontinued treatment due to these events (1% for paraesthesia and 0.6% for dysgeusia).



     Mood and Sleep Disorders  



 The proportion of patients in 1-year controlled trials of Qsymia reporting one or more adverse reactions related to mood and sleep disorders was 15.8%, 14.5%, and 20.6% with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 15 mg/92 mg, respectively, compared to 10.3% with placebo. These events were further categorized into sleep disorders, anxiety, and depression. Reports of sleep disorders were typically characterized as insomnia, and occurred in 6.7%, 8.1%, and 11.1% of patients treated with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 15 mg/92 mg, respectively, compared to 5.8% of patients treated with placebo. Reports of anxiety occurred in 4.6%, 4.8%, and 7.9% of patients treated with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 15 mg/92 mg, respectively, compared to 2.6% of patients treated with placebo. Reports of depression/mood problems occurred in 5.0%, 3.8%, and 7.6% of patients treated with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 15 mg/92 mg, respectively, compared to 3.4% of patients treated with placebo. The majority of these events first occurred within the initial 12 weeks of drug therapy; however, in some patients, events were reported later in the course of treatments. In the Qsymia clinical trials, the overall prevalence of mood and sleep adverse reactions was approximately twice as great in patients with a history of depression compared to patients without a history of depression; however, the proportion of patients on active treatment versus placebo who reported mood and sleep adverse reactions was similar in these two subgroups. Occurrence of depression-related events was more frequent in patients with a past history of depression across all treatment groups. However, the placebo-adjusted difference in incidence of these events remained constant between groups regardless of previous depression history.



     Cognitive Disorders  



 In the 1-year controlled trials of Qsymia, the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 2.1% for Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 5.0% for Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 7.6% for Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, compared to 1.5% for placebo. These adverse reactions were comprised primarily of reports of problems with attention/concentration, memory, and language (word finding). These events typically began within the first 4 weeks of treatment, had a median duration of approximately 28 days or less, and were reversible upon discontinuation of treatment; however, individual patients did experience events later in treatment, and events of longer duration.



     Laboratory Abnormalities  



     Serum Bicarbonate  



 In the 1-year controlled trials of Qsymia, the incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate below the normal range (levels of less than 21 mEq/L at 2 consecutive visits or at the final visit) was 8.8% for Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 6.4% for Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 12.8% for Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, compared to 2.1% for placebo. The incidence of persistent, markedly low serum bicarbonate values (levels of less than 17 mEq/L on 2 consecutive visits or at the final visit) was 1.3% for Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 0.2% for Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg dose, and 0.7% for Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg dose, compared to 0.1% for placebo. Generally, decreases in serum bicarbonate levels were mild (average 1-3 mEq/L) and occurred early in treatment (4-week visit), however severe decreases and decreases later in treatment occurred.



     Serum Potassium  



 In the 1-year controlled trials of Qsymia, the incidence of persistent low serum potassium values (less than 3.5 mEq/L at two consecutive visits or at the final visit) during the trial was 0.4% for Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 3.6% for Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg dose, and 4.9% for Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, compared to 1.1% for placebo. Of the subjects who experienced persistent low serum potassium, 88% were receiving treatment with a non-potassium sparing diuretic.



 The incidence of markedly low serum potassium (less than 3 mEq/L, and a reduction from pre-treatment of greater than 0.5 mEq/L) at any time during the trial was 0.0% for Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 0.2% for Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg dose, and 0.7% for Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg dose, compared to 0.0% for placebo. Persistent markedly low serum potassium (less than 3 mEq/L, and a reduction from pre-treatment of greater than 0.5 mEq/L at two consecutive visits or at the final visit) occurred in 0.0% of subjects receiving Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 0.2% receiving Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg dose, and 0.1% receiving Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg dose, compared to 0.0% receiving placebo.



 Hypokalemia was reported by 0.4% of subjects treated with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 1.4% of subjects treated with Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 2.5% of subjects treated with Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg compared to 0.4% of subjects treated with placebo. "Blood potassium decreased" was reported by 0.4% of subjects treated with Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 0.4% of subjects treated with Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, 1.0% of subjects treated with Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, and 0.0% of subjects treated with placebo.



     Serum Creatinine  



 In the 1-year controlled trials of Qsymia, there was a dose-related increase from baseline, peaking between Week 4 to 8, which declined but remained elevated over baseline over 1 year of treatment. The incidence of increases in serum creatinine of greater than or equal to 0.3 mg/dL at any time during treatment was 2.1% for Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 7.2% for Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 8.4% for Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, compared to 2.0% for placebo. Increases in serum creatinine of greater than or equal to 50% over baseline occurred in 0.8% of subjects receiving Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 2.0% receiving Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 2.8% receiving Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, compared to 0.6% receiving placebo.



     Nephrolithiasis  



 In the 1-year controlled trials of Qsymia, the incidence of nephrolithiasis was 0.4% for Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 0.2% for Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, and 1.2% for Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, compared to 0.3% for placebo.



     Drug Discontinuation Due to Adverse Reactions  



 In the 1-year placebo-controlled clinical studies, 11.6% of Qsymia 3.75 mg/23 mg, 11.6% of Qsymia 7.5 mg/46 mg, 17.4% of Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg, and 8.4% of placebo-treated patients discontinued treatment due to reported adverse reactions. The most common adverse reactions that led to discontinuation of treatment are shown in Table 4.



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions Greater Than or Equal To 1% Leading to Treatment Discontinuation (1-Year Clinical Trials) 
 Adverse ReactionLeading to Treatment Discontinuation   Placebo(N=1561)%    Qsymia3.75 mg/23 mg(N=240)%  Qsymia7.5 mg/46 mg(N=498)%  Qsymia15 mg/92 mg(N=1580)%   
  
   Vision blurred                  0.5                  2.1                  0.8                  0.7           
   Headache                        0.6                  1.7                  0.2                  0.8           
   Irritability                    0.1                  0.8                  0.8                  1.1           
   Dizziness                       0.2                  0.4                  1.2                  0.8           
   Paraesthesia                    0.0                  0.4                  1.0                  1.1           
   Insomnia                        0.4                  0.0                  0.4                  1.6           
   Depression                      0.2                  0.0                  0.8                  1.3           
   Anxiety                         0.3                  0.0                  0.2                  1.1           
             6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been reported during post approval use of phentermine and topiramate, the components of Qsymia. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Qsymia  



 *      Psychiatric Disorders  
 *     Suicidal ideation, Suicidal behavior 
   *      Ophthalmic disorders  
   *     Acute angle closure glaucomaIncreased intraocular pressure 
      Phentermine  
 

 *      Allergic adverse reactions  
 *     Urticaria 
 *      Cardiovascular adverse reactions  
 *     Elevation of blood pressure, Ischemic events 
 *      Central nervous system adverse reactions  
 *     Euphoria, Psychosis, Tremor 
 *      Reproductive adverse reactions  
 *     Changes in libido, Impotence 
      Topiramate  
 

 *      Dermatologic disorders  
 *     Bullous skin reactions (including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis), Pemphigus 
 *      Gastrointestinal disorders  
 *     Pancreatitis 
 *      Hepatic disorders  
 *     Hepatic failure (including fatalities), Hepatitis 
 *      Metabolic disorders  
 *     Hyperammonemia 
 *     Hypothermia 
 *      Ophthalmic disorders  
 *     Maculopathy 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  Qsymia is a federally controlled substance (CIV) because it contains phentermine and can be abused or lead to drug dependence. Keep Qsymia in a safe place, to protect it from theft. Never give your Qsymia to anyone else, because it may cause death or harm them. Selling or giving away this medicine is against the law. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Fetal Toxicity: Females of reproductive potential: Obtain negative pregnancy test before treatment and monthly thereafter; use effective contraception. Qsymia is available through a limited program under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) (  5.1  ). 
 *  Increase in Heart Rate: Monitor heart rate in all patients, especially those with cardiac or cerebrovascular disease (  5.2  ). 
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for depression or suicidal thoughts. Discontinue Qsymia if symptoms develop (  5.3  ). 
 *  Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle Closure Glaucoma: Discontinue Qsymia (  5.4  ). 
 *  Mood and Sleep Disorders: Consider dose reduction or withdrawal for clinically significant or persistent symptoms (  5.5  ). 
 *  Cognitive Impairment: May cause disturbances in attention or memory. Caution patients about operating automobiles or hazardous machinery when starting treatment (  5.6  ). 
 *  Metabolic Acidosis: Measure electrolytes before/during treatment (  5.7  ). 
 *  Elevated Creatinine: Measure creatinine before/during treatment (  5.8  ). 
 *  Use of Antidiabetic Medications: Weight loss may cause hypoglycemia. Measure serum glucose before/during treatment (  5.9  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Fetal Toxicity



  Qsymia can cause fetal harm. Data from pregnancy registries and epidemiology studies indicate that a fetus exposed to topiramate, a component of Qsymia, in the first trimester of pregnancy has an increased risk of oral clefts (cleft lip with or without cleft palate). If Qsymia is used during pregnancy or if a patient becomes pregnant while taking Qsymia, treatment should be discontinued immediately, and the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus. Females of reproductive potential should have a negative pregnancy test before starting Qsymia and monthly thereafter during Qsymia therapy. Females of reproductive potential should use effective contraception during Qsymia therapy [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  and  (8.6)  ]  .



    Qsymia Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS)  



 Because of the teratogenic risk associated with Qsymia therapy, Qsymia is available through a limited program under the REMS. Under the Qsymia REMS, only certified pharmacies may distribute Qsymia. Further information, is available at www.QsymiaREMS.com or by telephone at 1-888-998-4887.



    5.2 Increase in Heart Rate



  Qsymia can cause an increase in resting heart rate.



 A higher percentage of Qsymia-treated overweight and obese adults experienced heart rate increases from baseline of more than 5, 10, 15, and 20 beats per minute (bpm) compared to placebo-treated overweight and obese adults. Table 2 provides the numbers and percentages of patients with elevations in heart rate in clinical studies of up to one year.



 Table 2. Number and Percentage of Patients with an Increase in Heart Rate at a Single Time Point from Baseline 
                        PlaceboN=1561n (%)  Qsymia3.75 mg/23 mgN=240n (%)  Qsymia7.5 mg/46 mgN=498n (%)  Qsymia15 mg/92 mgN=1580n (%)   
  
 Greater than 5 bpm       1021 (65.4)          168 (70.0)             372 (74.7)             1228 (77.7)        
 Greater than 10 bpm       657 (42.1)          120 (50.0)             251 (50.4)             887 (56.1)         
 Greater than 15 bpm       410 (26.3)           79 (32.9)             165 (33.1)             590 (37.3)         
 Greater than 20 bpm       186 (11.9)           36 (15.0)              67 (13.5)             309 (19.6)         
           The clinical significance of a heart rate elevation with Qsymia treatment is unclear, especially for patients with cardiac and cerebrovascular disease (such as patients with a history of myocardial infarction or stroke in the previous 6 months, life-threatening arrhythmias, or congestive heart failure).
 

 Regular measurement of resting heart rate is recommended for all patients taking Qsymia, especially patients with cardiac or cerebrovascular disease or when initiating or increasing the dose of Qsymia. Qsymia has not been studied in patients with recent or unstable cardiac or cerebrovascular disease and therefore use is not recommended.



 Patients should inform healthcare providers of palpitations or feelings of a racing heartbeat while at rest during Qsymia treatment. For patients who experience a sustained increase in resting heart rate while taking Qsymia, the dose should be reduced or Qsymia discontinued.



    5.3 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including topiramate, a component of Qsymia, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with Qsymia should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior. Discontinue Qsymia in patients who experience suicidal thoughts or behaviors.



 Avoid Qsymia in patients with a history of suicidal attempts or active suicidal ideation.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical studies (monotherapy and adjunctive therapy, median treatment duration 12 weeks) of 11 different AEDs across several indications showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% Confidence Interval [CI] 1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. The estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in AED-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about AED effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as 1 week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5 to 100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.



    5.4 Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle Closure Glaucoma



  A syndrome consisting of acute myopia associated with secondary angle closure glaucoma has been reported in patients treated with topiramate, a component of Qsymia. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity and/or ocular pain. Ophthalmologic findings can include myopia, anterior chamber shallowing, ocular hyperemia (redness), and increased intraocular pressure. Mydriasis may or may not be present. This syndrome may be associated with supraciliary effusion resulting in anterior displacement of the lens and iris, with secondary angle closure glaucoma. Symptoms typically occur within 1 month of initiating treatment with topiramate but may occur at any time during therapy. The primary treatment to reverse symptoms is immediate discontinuation of Qsymia. Elevated intraocular pressure of any etiology, if left untreated, can lead to serious adverse events including permanent loss of vision.



    5.5 Mood and Sleep Disorders



  Qsymia can cause mood disorders, including depression, and anxiety, as well as insomnia. Patients with a history of depression may be at increased risk of recurrent depression or other mood disorders while taking Qsymia. The majority of these mood and sleep disorders resolved spontaneously, or resolved upon discontinuation of dosing [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



 For clinically significant or persistent symptoms consider dose reduction or withdrawal of Qsymia. If patients have symptoms of suicidal ideation or behavior, discontinue Qsymia.



    5.6 Cognitive Impairment



  Qsymia can cause cognitive dysfunction (e.g., impairment of concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, and speech or language problems, particularly word-finding difficulties). Rapid titration or high initial doses of Qsymia may be associated with higher rates of cognitive events such as attention, memory, and language/word-finding difficulties [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Since Qsymia has the potential to impair cognitive function, patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain Qsymia therapy does not affect them adversely. If cognitive dysfunction persists consider dose reduction or withdrawal of Qsymia for symptoms that are moderate to severe, bothersome, or those which fail to resolve with dose reduction.



    5.7 Metabolic Acidosis



  Hyperchloremic, non-anion gap, metabolic acidosis (decreased serum bicarbonate below the normal reference range in the absence of chronic respiratory alkalosis) has been reported in patients treated with Qsymia [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



 Conditions or therapies that predispose to acidosis (i.e., renal disease, severe respiratory disorders, status epilepticus, diarrhea, surgery or ketogenic diet) may be additive to the bicarbonate lowering effects of topiramate. Concomitant use of Qsymia and a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide, or dichlorphenamide) may increase the severity of metabolic acidosis and may also increase the risk of kidney stone formation. Therefore, if Qsymia is given concomitantly with another carbonic anhydrase inhibitor to a patient with a predisposing condition for metabolic acidosis the patient should be monitored for the appearance or worsening of metabolic acidosis.



 Some manifestations of acute or chronic metabolic acidosis may include hyperventilation, nonspecific symptoms such as fatigue and anorexia, or more severe sequelae including cardiac arrhythmias or stupor. Chronic, untreated metabolic acidosis may increase the risk for nephrolithiasis or nephrocalcinosis, and may also result in osteomalacia (referred to as rickets in pediatric patients) and/or osteoporosis with an increased risk for fractures. The effect of Qsymia on growth and bone-related sequelae has not been systematically investigated in long-term, placebo-controlled trials.



 Measurement of electrolytes including serum bicarbonate prior to starting Qsymia and during Qsymia treatment is recommended. In Qsymia clinical trials, the peak reduction in serum bicarbonate occurred by week 4, and in most subjects there was a correction of bicarbonate by week 56, without any change to study drug. However, if persistent metabolic acidosis develops while taking Qsymia, reduce the dose or discontinue Qsymia.



    5.8 Elevation in Creatinine



  Qsymia can cause an increase in serum creatinine. Peak increases in serum creatinine were observed after 4 to 8 weeks of treatment. On average, serum creatinine gradually declined but remained elevated over baseline creatinine values. Elevations in serum creatinine often signify a decrease in renal function, but the cause for Qsymia-associated changes in serum creatinine has not been definitively established. Therefore, measurement of serum creatinine prior to starting Qsymia and during Qsymia treatment is recommended. If persistent elevations in creatinine occur while taking Qsymia, reduce the dose or discontinue Qsymia [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.9 Potential Risk of Hypoglycemia in Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus on Anti-Diabetic Therapy



  Weight loss may increase the risk of hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated with insulin and/or insulin secretagogues (e.g., sulfonylureas). Qsymia has not been studied in combination with insulin. Measurement of blood glucose levels prior to starting Qsymia and during Qsymia treatment is recommended in patients with type 2 diabetes. Decreases in medication doses for antidiabetic medications which are non-glucose-dependent should be considered to mitigate the risk of hypoglycemia. If a patient develops hypoglycemia after starting Qsymia, appropriate changes should be made to the antidiabetic drug regimen.



    5.10 Potential Risk of Hypotension in Patients Treated with Antihypertensive Medications



  In hypertensive patients being treated with antihypertensive medications, weight loss may increase the risk of hypotension, and associated symptoms including dizziness, lightheadedness, and syncope. Measurement of blood pressure prior to starting Qsymia and during Qsymia treatment is recommended in patients being treated for hypertension. If a patient develops symptoms associated with low blood pressure after starting Qsymia, appropriate changes should be made to the antihypertensive drug regimen.



    5.11 CNS Depression with Concomitant CNS Depressants Including Alcohol



  The concomitant use of alcohol or central nervous system (CNS) depressant drugs (e.g., barbiturates, benzodiazepines, and sleep medications) with phentermine or topiramate may potentiate CNS depression or other centrally mediated effects of these agents, such as dizziness, cognitive adverse reactions, drowsiness, light-headedness, impaired coordination and somnolence. Therefore, avoid concomitant use of alcohol with Qsymia.



    5.12 Potential Seizures with Abrupt Withdrawal of Qsymia



  Abrupt withdrawal of topiramate, a component of Qsymia, has been associated with seizures in individuals without a history of seizures or epilepsy. In situations where immediate termination of Qsymia is medically required, appropriate monitoring is recommended. Patients discontinuing Qsymia 15 mg/92 mg should be gradually tapered as recommended to reduce the possibility of precipitating a seizure [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ]  .



    5.13 Patients with Renal Impairment



  Phentermine and topiramate, the components of Qsymia, are cleared by renal excretion. Therefore, exposure to phentermine and topiramate is higher in patients with moderate (creatinine clearance [CrCl] greater than or equal to 30 and less than 50 mL/min) or severe (CrCl less than 30 mL/min) renal impairment. Adjust dose of Qsymia for both patient populations.



 Qsymia has not been studied in patients with end-stage renal disease on dialysis. Avoid use of Qsymia in this patient population [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.14 Patients with Hepatic Impairment



  In patients with mild (Child-Pugh score 5 - 6) or moderate (Child-Pugh score 7 - 9) hepatic impairment, exposure to phentermine was higher compared to healthy volunteers. Adjust dose of Qsymia for patients with moderate hepatic impairment.



 Qsymia has not been studied in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh score 10 - 15). Avoid use of Qsymia in this patient population [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.15 Kidney Stones



  Use of Qsymia has been associated with kidney stone formation. Topiramate, a component of Qsymia, inhibits carbonic anhydrase activity and promotes kidney stone formation by reducing urinary citrate excretion and increasing urine pH.



 Avoid the use of Qsymia with other drugs that inhibit carbonic anhydrase (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide, or methazolamide).



 Use of topiramate by patients on a ketogenic diet may also result in a physiological environment that increases the likelihood of kidney stone formation.



 Increase fluid intake to increase urinary output which can decrease the concentration of substances involved in kidney stone formation [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.16 Oligohidrosis and Hyperthermia



  Oligohidrosis (decreased sweating), infrequently resulting in hospitalization, has been reported in association with the use of topiramate, a component of Qsymia. Decreased sweating and an elevation in body temperature above normal characterized these cases. Some of the cases have been reported with topiramate after exposure to elevated environmental temperatures.



 Patients treated with Qsymia should be advised to monitor for decreased sweating and increased body temperature during physical activity, especially in hot weather. Caution should be used when Qsymia is prescribed with other drugs that predispose patients to heat-related disorders; these drugs include, but are not limited to, other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors and drugs with anticholinergic activity.



    5.17 Hypokalemia



  Qsymia can increase the risk of hypokalemia through its inhibition of carbonic anhydrase activity. In addition, when Qsymia is used in conjunction with non-potassium sparing diuretics such as furosemide (loop diuretic) or hydrochlorothiazide (thiazide-like diuretic) this may further potentiate potassium-wasting. When prescribing Qsymia, patients should be monitored for hypokalemia [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.18 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  Qsymia was associated with changes in several clinical laboratory analytes in randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies.



 Obtain a blood chemistry profile that includes bicarbonate, creatinine, potassium, and glucose at baseline and periodically during treatment [s ee  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ,  (5.8)  ,  (5.9)  , and  (5.17)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
