<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="quadramet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE EVENTS

  Adverse events were evaluated in a total of 580 patients who received QUADRAMET  (r)  in clinical trials. Of the 580 patients, there were 472 men and 108 women with a mean age of 66 (range 20 to 87).



 Of these patients, 472 (81%) had at least one adverse event. In a subgroup of 399 patients who received QUADRAMET  (r)  1.0 mCi/kg, there were 23 deaths and 46 serious adverse events. The deaths occurred an average of 67 days (9 to 130) after QUADRAMET  (r)  . Serious events occurred an average of 46 days (1 - 118) after QUADRAMET  (r)  . Although most of the patient deaths and serious adverse events appear to be related to the underlying disease, the relationship of end stage disease, marrow invasion by cancer cells, previous myelotoxic treatment and QUADRAMET  (r)  toxicity can not be easily distinguished. In clinical studies, two patients with rapidly progressive prostate cancer developed thrombocytopenia and died 4 weeks after receiving QUADRAMET  (r)  . One of the patients showed evidence of disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC); the other patient experienced a fatal cerebrovascular accident, with a suspicion of DIC. The relationship of the DIC to the bone marrow suppressive effect of Samarium is not known. Marrow toxicity occurred in 277 (48%) patients (See   Warnings  section).



 In controlled studies, 7% of patients receiving 1.0 mCi/kg QUADRAMET  (r)  (as compared to 6% of patients receiving placebo) reported a transient increase in bone pain shortly after injection (flare reaction). This was usually mild, self-limiting, and responded to analgesics.



 The most common adverse events observed in controlled clinical studies of QUADRAMET  (r)  , are given in Table 6.    



 TABLE 6 SELECTED ADVERSE EVENTS REPORTED IN &gt;= 1.0 % OF PEOPLE WHO RECEIVED QUADRAMET(r) OR PLACEBO IN CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS 
     ADVERSE EVENT                          Placebo    N = 90                  QUADRAMET(r)    1.0 mCi/kg    N = 199    
     # Patients with Any Adverse Event           72 (80%)                           169 (85%)                   
     Body As A Whole                        56 (62%)                           100 (50%)                   
     Pain Flare Reaction                    5 (5.6%)                           14 (7.0%)                   
     Cardiovascular                         19 (21%)                           32 (16%)                    
     Arrhythmias                            2 (2.2%)                           10 (5.0%)                   
     Chest Pain                             4 (4.4%)                           8 (4.0%)                    
     Hypertension                           0                                  6 (3.0%)                    
     Hypotension                            2 (2.2%)                           4 (2.0%)                    
     Digestive                              44 (49%)                           82 (41%)                    
     Abdominal Pain                         7 (7.8%)                           12 (6.0%)                   
     Diarrhea                               3 (3.3%)                           12 (6.0%)                   
     Nausea &amp;/or Vomiting                   37 (41.1%)                         65 (32.7%)                  
     Hematologic &amp; Lymphatic                12 (13%)                           54 (27%)                    
     Coagulation Disorder                   0                                  3 (1.5%)                    
     Hemoglobin Decreased                   21 (23.3%)                         81 (40.7%)                  
     Leukopenia                             6 (6.7%)                           118(59.3%)                  
     Lymphadenopathy                        0                                  4 (2.0%)                    
     Thrombocytopenia                       8 (8.9%)                           138(69.3%)                  
     Any Bleeding Manifestations*           8 (8.9%)                           32 (16.1%)                  
     Ecchymosis                             1 (1.1%)                           3 (3.0%)                    
     Epistaxis                              1 (1.1%)                           4 (2.0%)                    
     Hematuria                              3 (3.3%)                           10 (5%)                     
     Infection                              10 (11.1%)                         34 (17.1%)                  
     Fever and/or Chills                    10 (11.1%)                         17 (8.5%)                   
     Infection, Not Specified               4 (4.4%)                           14 (7.0%)                   
     Oral Moniliasis                        1 (1.1%)                           4 (2.0%)                    
     Pneumonia                              1 (1.1%)                           3 (1.5%)                    
     Musculoskeletal                        28 (31%)                           55 (27%)                    
     Myasthenia                             8 (8.9%)                           13 (6.5%)                   
     Pathologic Fracture                    2 (2.2%)                           5 (2.5%)                    
     Nervous                                39 (43%)                           59 (30%)                    
     Dizziness                              1 (1.1%)                           8 (4.0%)                    
     Paresthesia                            7 (7.8%)                           4 (2.0%)                    
     Spinal Cord Compression                5 (5.5%)                           13 (6.5%)                   
     Cerebrovascular Accident/Stroke           0                                  2 (1.0%)                    
     Respiratory                            24 (27%)                           35 (18%)                    
     Bronchitis/Cough Increased             2 (2.2%)                           8 (4.0%)                    
     Special Senses                         11 (12%)                           11 (6%)                     
     Skin &amp; Appendages                      17 (19%)                           13 (7%)                     
     Purpura                                0                                  2 (1%)                      
     Rash                                   2 (2.2%)                           2 (1%)                      
        *    *Includes hemorrhage (gastrointestinal, ocular) reported in &lt;1%. 
    In an additional 200 patients who received QUADRAMET  (r)  in uncontrolled clinical trials, adverse events that were reported at a rate of &gt;= 1.0% were similar except for 9 (4.5%) patients who had agranulocytosis. Other selected adverse events that were reported in &lt;1% of the patients who received QUADRAMET  (r)  1.0 mCi/kg in any clinical trial include: alopecia, angina, congestive heart failure, sinus bradycardia, and vasodilation.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
