<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="quartette" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions with the use of COCs are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *     *    Serious cardiovascular events and stroke   [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]    
 *    Vascular events   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]    
 *    Liver disease   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]    
    
    Adverse reactions commonly reported by COC users are:
 

 *     *    Irregular uterine bleeding 
 *    Nausea 
 *    Breast tenderness 
 *    Headache 
    
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) in clinical trials for Quartette were headaches, heavy/irregular vaginal bleeding, nausea/vomiting, acne, dysmenorrhea, weight increased, mood changes, anxiety/panic attack, breast pain and migraines (  6  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Teva Pharmaceuticals at 1-866-832-8537 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety data described below are from a 12-month, US, open-label study, which enrolled women aged 18-40, of whom 3,597 took at least one dose of Quartette (2,661 woman-years of exposure)    [see Clinical Studies (14)]    .



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Study Discontinuation  : 13.3% of the women discontinued from the clinical trial due to an adverse reaction; the most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 1% of women) leading to discontinuation were heavy/irregular bleeding (5.0%), mood swings/alteration/affect lability (1.4%), headaches/migraines (1.3%), weight increased (1.3%) and acne (1.0%).



   Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 2% of women)  : headaches (12.2%), heavy/irregular vaginal bleeding (9.7%), nausea/vomiting (8.8%), acne (5.4%), dysmenorrhea (5.4%), weight increased (4.6%), mood changes (depression, depressed mood, crying, major depression, affective disorder, depression suicidal, dysthymic disorder) (2.9%), anxiety/panic attack (2.4%), breast tenderness/pain/discomfort (2.2%), migraine (2.0%).



   Serious Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 2 women):  Abortion Spontaneous, Suicide Attempt, Cholecystitis/ Cholelithiasis, Deep Vein Thrombosis, Ectopic Pregnancy.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of other extended-cycle COCs containing levonorgestrel and ethinyl estradiol. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal distension, vomiting



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  chest pain, fatigue, malaise, edema peripheral, pain



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity reaction



   Investigations:  blood pressure increased



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  muscle spasms, pain in extremity



   Nervous system disorders:  dizziness, loss of consciousness



   Psychiatric disorders:  insomnia



   Reproductive and breast disorders:  dysmenorrhea



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  pulmonary embolism, pulmonary thrombosis



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  alopecia



   Vascular disorders:  thrombosis
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS

  WARNING:  CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS

    Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptives (COC) use.  This risk increases with age, particularly in women over 35 years of age, and with the number of cigarettes smoked.  For this reason, COCs should not be used by women who are over 35 years of age and smoke.     [See Contraindications (4)]      



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Women over 35 years old who smoke should not use Quartette. (4) 
 *  Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive (COC) use. (4) 
    
 







    BOXED WARNING: FDA-Approved Patient Labeling

  FDA-Approved Patient Labeling

    Guide for Using Quartette (levonorgestrel/ethinyl estradiol and ethinyl estradiol)  



   

    WARNING TO WOMEN WHO SMOKE  



   Do not use Quartette if you smoke cigarettes and are over 35 years old.  Smoking increases your risk of serious cardiovascular side effects from birth control pills, including death from heart attack, blood clots or stroke.  This risk increases with age and the number of cigarettes you smoke.  



   Birth control pills help to lower the chances of becoming pregnant.  They do not protect against HIV infection (AIDS) and other sexually transmitted infections.



   What Is Quartette?   



 Quartette is a birth control pill.  It contains two female hormones, an estrogen called ethinyl estradiol, and a progestin called levonorgestrel.



   How Well Does Quartette Work?  



 Your chance of getting pregnant depends on how well you follow the directions for taking your birth control pills.  The more carefully you follow the directions, the less chance you have of getting pregnant.



 Based on the results of a single clinical study lasting 12 months, 2 to 4 women out of 100 women may get pregnant during the first year they use Quartette.  



 The following chart shows the chance of getting pregnant for women who use different methods of birth control.  Each box on the chart contains a list of birth control methods that are similar in effectiveness.  The most effective methods are at the top of the chart.  The box on the bottom of the chart shows the chance of getting pregnant for women who do not use birth control and are trying to get pregnant.



   How Do I Take Quartette?  



 1. Take one pill every day at the same time.  Take pills in the order directed on the Extended-Cycle Tablet Dispenser.  



 Do not skip pills or delay taking your pills.  If you miss pills (including starting the pack late), you could get pregnant.  The more pills you miss, the more likely you are to get pregnant.



 2. You may have spotting or light bleeding, or feel sick to your stomach during the first few months of taking Quartette.  If you feel sick to your stomach, do not stop taking the pill.  The problem will usually go away.  If it doesn't go away, check with your healthcare provider.



 If you vomit or have diarrhea within 4 hours after taking your pill, follow the instructions in "  What To Do If You Miss Pills."  



 3. Missing pills can also cause spotting or light bleeding, even when you take the missed pills later.  On the days you take 2 pills to make up for missed pills, you could also feel a little sick to your stomach. 



 4. If you have trouble remembering to take Quartette, talk to your healthcare provider about how to make pill-taking easier or about using another method of birth control. 



     Before   you start taking Quartette  



 1. Decide what time of day you want to take your pill.  It is important to take it at about the same time every day. 



 2. Look at your Extended-Cycle Tablet Dispenser.  Your Extended-Cycle Tablet Dispenser consists of 3 trays with cards that hold 91 individually sealed pills (a 13-week or 91-day cycle).  The 91 pills consist of 42 light pink tablets, each containing 0.15 mg of levonorgestrel and 0.02 mg ethinyl estradiol, 21 pink tablets containing 0.15 mg of levonorgestrel and 0.025 mg ethinyl estradiol, 21 purple tablets containing 0.15 mg of levonorgestrel and 0.03 mg ethinyl estradiol, and 7 yellow tablets containing 0.01 mg of ethinyl estradiol. 



 Tray 1 contains 4 rows of 7 light pink pills.



 Tray 2 contains 2 rows of 7 light pink pills (a total of 14 light pink pills) followed by 2 rows of 7 pink pills (a total of 14 pink pills).



 Tray 3 contains 1 row of 7 pink pills, followed by three rows of 7 purple pills (a total of 21 purple pills), followed by the last row, which contains 7 yellow pills.



 3. Also find:



 *   Where on the first tray in the pack to start taking pills (upper left corner at the start arrow) and In what order to take the pills (follow the weeks and arrow). 
    4. Be sure you have another kind of birth control (such as condoms and spermicides) ready at all times, to use as a back-up in case you miss pills. 
 

   When to Start Quartette  



 1. Take the first light pink pill on the Sunday after your period starts, even if you are still bleeding.  If your period begins on Sunday, start the first light pink pill that same day.   



 2. Use another method of birth control (such as condoms and spermicides) as a back-up method if you have sex anytime from the Sunday you start your first light pink pill until the next Sunday (first 7 days).  If you have been using a different hormonal method of birth control (such as a different pill, the "patch," or the "vaginal ring"), you need to use another method of birth control (such as condoms and spermicides) each time you have sex after stopping your old method of birth control until you have taken Quartette for 7 days. 



 3. If you have recently given birth and have not yet had a period, use another method of birth control if you have sex (such as condoms and spermicides) as a back-up method until you have taken Quartette for 7 days.



   How to Take Quartette  



 1. Take one pill at the same time every day until you have taken the last pill in the Extended-Cycle Tablet Dispenser. 



 *   Do not skip pills even if you are experiencing spotting or bleeding or feel sick to your stomach (nausea).Do not skip pills even if you do not have sex very often.Do not skip the yellow pills because they are not placebo pills ("sugar pills"). They contain ethinyl estradiol. 
    2. When you finish a tablet dispenser
 

 *   After taking the last yellow pill, start taking the first light pink pill from a new Extended-Cycle Tablet Dispenser the very next day (this should be on a Sunday) regardless of when your period started. 
    3. If you miss your scheduled period when you are taking the yellow pills, contact your healthcare provider because you may be pregnant.  If you are pregnant, you should stop taking Quartette.
 

   What To Do If You Miss Pills  



 If you   MISS 1   light pink, pink or purple pill: 



 1. Take it as soon as you remember.  Take the next pill at your regular time.  This means you may take 2 pills in 1 day. 



 2. You do not need to use a back-up birth control method if you have sex. 



 If you   MISS 2   light pink, pink or purple pills in a row: 



 1. Take 2 pills on the day you remember, and 2 pills the next day. 



 2. Then take 1 pill a day until you finish the pack. 



 3. You could become pregnant if you have sex in the 7 days after you miss two pills.  You MUST use another birth control method (such as condoms and spermicide) as a back-up for the 7 days after you restart your pills.



 If you   MISS 3 OR MORE   light pink, pink or purple pills in a row:



 1. Do not take the missed pills.  Keep taking 1 pill every day as indicated on the pack until you have completed all of the remaining pills in the pack.  For example: If you resume taking the pill on Thursday, take the pill under "Thursday" and do not take the missed pills.  You may experience bleeding during the week following the missed pills. 



 2. You could become pregnant if you have sex during the days of missed pills or during the first 7 days after restarting your pills.



 3. You MUST use a non-hormonal birth control method (such as condoms and spermicide) as a back-up when you miss pills and for the first 7 days after you restart your pills.  If you do not have your period when you are taking the yellow pills, call your healthcare provider because you may be pregnant.



 If you   MISS ANY   of the 7 yellow pills:



 1. Take the next scheduled pill at the scheduled time.



 2. You do not need a back-up method of birth control.



   Finally, if you are still not sure what to do about the pills you have missed  



 1. Use a back-up method anytime you have sex. 



 2. Keep taking one pill each day until you contact your healthcare provider. 



   Who Should Not Take Quartette?  



 Your healthcare provider will not give you Quartette if you have:



 *   Ever had breast cancer or any cancer that is sensitive to female hormonesLiver disease, including liver tumorsEver had blood clots in your arms, legs, eyes, or lungs Ever had a strokeEver had a heart attack Certain heart valve problems or heart rhythm abnormalities that can cause blood clots to form in the heartAn inherited problem with your blood that makes it clot more than normalHigh blood pressure that medicine can't controlDiabetes with kidney, eye, nerve or blood vessel damageEver had certain kinds of severe migraine headaches with aura, numbness, weakness or changes in vision, or have any migraine headaches if you are over 35 
    Also, do not take birth control pills if you:
 

 *   Smoke and are over 35 years oldAre pregnantHave any unexplained bleeding from the vagina 
    Birth control pills may not be a good choice for you if you have ever had jaundice (yellowing of the skin or eyes) caused by pregnancy.
 

 Tell your healthcare provider if you have ever had any of the above conditions (your healthcare provider may recommend another method of birth control.)



   What Else Should I Know About Taking Quartette?  



 Birth control pills do     not     protect you against any sexually transmitted infection, including HIV, the virus that causes AIDS.



 Do not skip any pills, even if you do not have sex often.



 Birth control pills should not be taken during pregnancy.  However, birth control pills taken by accident during pregnancy are not known to cause birth defects.  



 You should stop Quartette at least four weeks before you have major surgery and not restart it for at least two weeks after the surgery, due to an increased risk of blood clots.



 If you are breastfeeding, consider another birth control method until you are ready to stop breastfeeding.  Birth control pills that contain estrogen, like Quartette, may decrease the amount of milk you make.  A small amount of the pill's hormones pass into breast milk. 



 Tell your healthcare provider about all medicines and herbal products that you take.  Some medicines and herbal products may make birth control pills less effective, including:  



 *   barbiturates bosentan carbamazepine felbamate griseofulvinoxcarbazepine phenytoinrifampin St. John's worttopiramate 
    Use a back-up or alternative birth control method when you take medicines that may make birth control pills less effective.
 

 If you have vomiting or diarrhea, your birth control pills may not work as well.  Use another birth control method, like condoms and spermicide, until you check with your healthcare provider.



 Birth control pills may interact with lamotrigine, an anticonvulsant used for epilepsy.  This may increase the risk of seizures, so your healthcare provider may need to adjust the dose of lamotrigine.



 Women on thyroid hormone replacement therapy may need increased doses of thyroid hormone.



   What Are The Most Serious Risks Of Taking Birth Control Pills?  



 Like pregnancy, birth control pills increase the risk of serious blood clots, especially in women who have other risk factors, such as smoking, obesity, or age greater than 35. This increased risk is highest when you first start taking birth control pills and when you restart the same or different birth control pills after not using them for a month or more. 



 It is possible to die from a problem caused by a blood clot, such as a heart attack or a stroke.  Some examples of serious blood clots are blood clots in the: 



 *   Legs (deep vein thrombosis)Lungs (pulmonary embolus) Eyes (loss of eyesight)Heart (heart attack)Brain (stroke) 
    Women who take birth control pills may get:
 

 *   High blood pressureGallbladder problemsRare cancerous or noncancerous liver tumors 
    All of these events are uncommon in healthy women.
 

 Call your healthcare provider right away if you have: 



 *   Persistent leg pain Sudden shortness of breath Sudden blindness, partial or complete Severe pain or pressure in your chestSudden, severe headache unlike your usual headachesWeakness or numbness in an arm or leg, or trouble speakingYellowing of the skin or eyeballs 
      What Are Common Side Effects Of Birth Control Pills?  
 

 The most common side effects of birth control pills are:



 *   Spotting or bleeding between menstrual periodsNausea Breast tendernessHeadache 
    These side effects are usually mild and usually disappear with time.
 

 Less common side effects are:



 *   AcneLess sexual desireBloating or fluid retention Blotchy darkening of the skin, especially on the face High blood sugar, especially in women who already have diabetesHigh fat (cholesterol, triglyceride) levels in the bloodDepression, especially if you have had depression in the past. Call your healthcare provider immediately if you have any thoughts of harming yourself.Problems tolerating contact lensesWeight gain 
    This is not a complete list of possible side effects.  Talk to your healthcare provider if you develop any side effects that concern you. You may report side effects to the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.
 

 No serious problems have been reported from a birth control pill overdose, even when accidentally taken by children.



   Do Birth Control Pills Cause Cancer?  



 Birth control pills do not appear to cause breast cancer.  However, if you have breast cancer now, or have had it in the past, do not use birth control pills because some breast cancers are sensitive to hormones. 



 Women who use birth control pills may have a slightly higher chance of getting cervical cancer. However, this may be due to other reasons such as having more sexual partners.



   What Should I Know About My Period When Taking Quartette?  



 When you take Quartette, which has a 91-day extended dosing cycle, you should expect to have 4 scheduled periods per year (bleeding when you are taking the 7 yellow pills).  Each period is likely to last about 3-4 days.  However, you will probably have more bleeding or spotting between your scheduled periods than if you were using a birth control pill with a 28-day dosing cycle.  This bleeding or spotting tends to decrease with each additional cycle.  Do not stop taking Quartette because of this bleeding or spotting.  If the spotting continues for more than 7 consecutive days or if the bleeding is heavy, call your healthcare provider.



   What If I Miss My Scheduled Period When Taking Quartette?  



 You should consider the possibility that you are pregnant if you miss your scheduled period (no bleeding on the days that you are taking yellow pills).  Because scheduled periods are less frequent when you are taking Quartette, notify your healthcare provider that you have missed your period and that you are taking Quartette.  Also notify your healthcare provider if you have symptoms of pregnancy such as morning sickness or unusual breast tenderness.  It is important that your healthcare provider evaluates you to determine if you are pregnant.  Stop taking Quartette if it is determined that you are pregnant.



   What If I Want To Become Pregnant?  



 You may stop taking the pill whenever you wish.  Consider a visit with your healthcare provider for a pre-pregnancy checkup before you stop taking the pill.  



   General Advice About Quartette  



 Your healthcare provider prescribed Quartette for you. Do not share Quartette with anyone else. Keep Quartette out of the reach of children.



 If you have concerns or questions, ask your healthcare provider. You may also ask your healthcare provider for a more detailed label written for medical professionals.



 Manufactured by:



 Teva Women's Health, Inc.



 Subsidiary of TEVA PHARMACEUTICALS USA, Inc.



 North Wales, PA 19454



 Iss. May 2014



  chart of effectiveness  Tray 1  Tray 2  Tray 3 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Vascular risks: Stop Quartette if a thrombotic event occurs. Stop Quartette at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery. Start Quartette no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Liver disease: Discontinue Quartette if jaundice occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *    High blood pressure: Do not prescribe Quartette for women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Carbohydrate and lipid metabolic effects: Monitor prediabetic and diabetic women taking Quartette. Consider an alternate contraceptive method for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemias. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Headache: Evaluate significant change in headaches and discontinue Quartette if indicated. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Uterine bleeding: Evaluate irregular bleeding or amenorrhea. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thromboembolic Disorders and Other Vascular Problems



  Stop Quartette if an arterial or deep venous thrombotic event (VTE) occurs. Stop Quartette if there is unexplained loss of vision, proptosis, diplopia, papilledema, or retinal vascular lesions. Evaluate for retinal vein thrombosis immediately.



 If feasible, stop Quartette at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery or other surgeries known to have an elevated risk of VTE.



 Start Quartette no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. The risk of postpartum VTE decreases after the third postpartum week, whereas the risk of ovulation increases after the third postpartum week.



 The use of COCs increases the risk of VTE. However, pregnancy increases the risk of VTE as much or more than the use of COCs. The risk of VTE in women using COCs is 3 to 9 per 10,000 woman-years. The risk of VTE is highest during the first year of use of a COC. Data from a large, prospective cohort safety study of various COCs suggest that this increased risk, as compared to that in non-COC users, is greatest during the first 6 months of COC use. Data from this safety study indicate that the greatest risk of VTE is present after initially starting a COC or restarting (following a 4-week or greater pill-free interval) the same or a different COC. The risk of thromboembolic disease due to COCs gradually disappears after COC use is discontinued.



 Use of Quartette provides women with more hormonal exposure on a yearly basis than conventional monthly oral contraceptives containing the same strength synthetic estrogens and progestins (an additional 9 and 13 weeks of exposure to progestin and estrogen, respectively, per year). In the clinical trial, three cases of deep vein thrombosis were reported.



 Use of COCs also increases the risk of arterial thromboses such as strokes and myocardial infarctions, especially in women with other risk factors for these events. COCs have been shown to increase both the relative and attributable risks of cerebrovascular events (thrombotic and hemorrhagic strokes), although, in general, the risk is greatest among older (&gt;35 years of age), and hypertensive women who also smoke. COCs also increase the risk for stroke in women with other underlying risk factors.



 Use COCs with caution in women with cardiovascular disease risk factors.



    5.2 Liver Disease



    Impaired Liver Function    



 Do not use Quartette in women with acute viral hepatitis or severe (decompensated) cirrhosis of the liver [see Contraindications (4)]  . Acute disturbances of liver function may necessitate the discontinuation of COC use until markers of liver function return to normal and COC causation has been excluded. Discontinue Quartette if jaundice develops.



   Liver Tumors    



 Quartette is contraindicated in women with benign and malignant liver tumors [see Contraindications (4)].  Hepatic adenomas are associated with COC use. An estimate of the attributable risk is 3.3 cases/100,000 COC users. Rupture of hepatic adenomas may cause death through intra-abdominal hemorrhage.



 Studies have shown an increased risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in long-term (&gt; 8 years) COC users. However, the attributable risk of liver cancers in COC users is less than one case per million users.



    5.3 High Blood Pressure



  Quartette is contraindicated in women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease [see Contraindications (4)]  . For women with well-controlled hypertension, monitor blood pressure and stop Quartette if blood pressure rises significantly.



 An increase in blood pressure has been reported in women taking COCs, and this increase is more likely in older women and with extended duration of use. The incidence of hypertension increases with increasing concentration of progestin.



    5.4 Gallbladder Disease



  Studies suggest a small increased relative risk of developing gallbladder disease among COC users. Use of COCs may also worsen existing gallbladder disease.



 A past history of COC-related cholestasis predicts an increased risk with subsequent COC use. Women with a history of pregnancy-related cholestasis may be at an increased risk for COC-related cholestasis.



    5.5 Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects



  Carefully monitor prediabetic and diabetic women who are taking Quartette. COCs may decrease glucose tolerance in a dose-related fashion.



 Consider alternative contraception for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemias. A small proportion of women will have adverse lipid changes while on COCs.



 Women with hypertriglyceridemia, or a family history thereof, may be at an increased risk of pancreatitis when using COCs.



    5.6 Headache



  If a woman taking Quartette develops new headaches that are recurrent, persistent, or severe, evaluate the cause and discontinue Quartette if indicated.



 Consider discontinuation of Quartette in the case of increased frequency or severity of migraine during COC use (which may be prodromal of a cerebrovascular event)   [see Contraindications (4)]    .



    5.7 Bleeding Irregularities



  Bleeding and/or spotting that occurs at any time while taking the first 84 tablets (light pink, pink and purple) of each extended-cycle regimen is considered "unscheduled" bleeding/spotting. Bleeding that occurs during the time a woman takes the seven tablets (yellow) containing 10 mcg of ethinyl estradiol is considered "scheduled" bleeding.



   Unscheduled and Scheduled Bleeding and Spotting    



 Unscheduled (breakthrough) bleeding and spotting sometimes occur in patients on COCs, especially during the first 3 months of use. If unscheduled bleeding persists or occurs after previously regular cycles on Quartette, check for causes such as pregnancy or malignancy. If pathology and pregnancy are excluded, bleeding irregularities may resolve over time or with a change to a different COC.



 Before prescribing Quartette, consider the occurrence of fewer scheduled menses (4 per year instead of 13 per year) against the occurrence of increased unscheduled bleeding and/or spotting. A 12-month open-label study of the efficacy of Quartette in preventing pregnancy assessed scheduled and unscheduled bleeding [see Clinical Studies (14)]  in 3,597 women who completed 34,087 28-day cycles of exposure. A total of 178 (4.9%) of the women discontinued Quartette, at least in part, due to bleeding or spotting.



 Scheduled (withdrawal) bleeding and/or spotting remained fairly stable over time, with an average of 3 to 4 days of bleeding and/or spotting per each 91-day cycle.



 Unscheduled bleeding and unscheduled spotting decreased over successive 91-day cycles. Table 1 below presents the number of days with unscheduled bleeding, spotting, and unscheduled bleeding and/or spotting in Treatment Cycles 1 to 4.



 Table 1: Number of Unscheduled Bleeding, Spotting and Bleeding and/or Spotting Days per 91-day Cycle 
  Cycle  (N)    Days of Unscheduled Bleeding per 84-Day Interval    Median Days PerSubject-Month    
  Mean          Q1                   Median         Q3                        
  1 (3330)      7.2                  0              4                         10             1.0                  
  2 (2820)      3.3                  0              0                         4              0.0                  
  3 (2433)      2.5                  0              0                         3              0.0                  
  4 (2213)      2.2                  0              0                         2              0.0                  
  Cycle  (N)    Days of Unscheduled Spotting per 84-Day Interval    Median Days PerSubject-Month    
  Mean          Q1                   Median         Q3                        
  1 (3330)      10.7                 2              7                         15             1.8                  
  2 (2820)      6.7                  0              3                         9              0.8                  
  3 (2433)      5.2                  0              2                         6              0.5                  
  4 (2213)      4.4                  0              1                         5              0.3                  
  Cycle (N)     Days of Unscheduled Bleeding and/or Spotting per 84-Day Interval    Median Days PerSubject-Month    
  Mean          Q1                   Median         Q3                        
  1 (3330)      17.9                 5              14                        27             3.5                  
  2 (2820)      10.0                 1              5                         14             1.3                  
  3 (2433)      7.7                  0              3                         10             0.8                  
  4 (2213)      6.6                  0              3                         8              0.8                  
            Q1=Quartile 1: 25% of women had &lt;= this number of days of unscheduled bleeding/spotting
 

 Median: 50% of women had &lt;= this number of days of unscheduled bleeding/spotting



 Q3=Quartile 3: 75% of women had &lt;= this number of days of unscheduled bleeding/spotting



 Figure 1 shows the percent of Quartette subjects in the primary clinical trial with &gt;= 7 days or &gt;= 20 days of unscheduled bleeding and/or spotting, or just unscheduled bleeding, during each 91-day treatment cycle.



  Figure 1: Percent of Women Taking Quartette Who Reported Unscheduled Bleeding and/or Spotting  



   Amenorrhea and Oligomenorrhea    



 Women who are not pregnant and use Quartette may experience amenorrhea. Based on data from the clinical trial, amenorrhea occurred in approximately 1.9% of women during Cycle 1, 7.7% during Cycle 2, 10.7% during Cycle 3, and 10.1% during Cycle 4 using Quartette. Rule out pregnancy in the event of amenorrhea. Some women may experience amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea after stopping COCs, especially when such a condition was pre-existent.



  Figure 1    5.8 COC Use Before or During Early Pregnancy



  Extensive epidemiological studies have revealed no increased risk of birth defects in women who have used oral contraceptives prior to pregnancy. Studies also do not suggest a teratogenic effect, particularly in so far as cardiac anomalies and limb-reduction defects are concerned, when taken inadvertently during early pregnancy. Discontinue Quartette if pregnancy is confirmed.



 The administration of oral contraceptives to induce withdrawal bleeding should not be used as a test for pregnancy   [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]    .



    5.9 Depression



  Carefully observe women with a history of depression and discontinue Quartette if depression recurs to a serious degree. Six cases of suicidality (suicide attempts and suicidal behavior) were reported in the clinical trial; several of these cases occurred in women with a psychiatric history.



    5.10 Carcinoma of the Breast and Cervix



  Quartette is contraindicated in women who currently have or have had breast cancer because breast cancer may be hormonally sensitive [see Contraindications (4)]  .



 There is substantial evidence that COCs do not increase the incidence of breast cancer. Although some past studies have suggested that COCs might increase the incidence of breast cancer, more recent studies have not confirmed such findings.



 Some studies suggest that COCs are associated with an increase in the risk of cervical cancer or intraepithelial neoplasia. However, there is controversy about the extent to which these findings are due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors.



    5.11 Effect on Binding Globulins



  The estrogen component of COCs may raise the serum concentrations of thyroxine-binding globulin, sex hormone-binding globulin and cortisol-binding globulin. The dose of replacement thyroid hormone or cortisol therapy may need to be increased.



    5.12 Monitoring



  A woman who is taking COCs should have a yearly visit with her healthcare provider for a blood pressure check and for other indicated health care.



    5.13 Hereditary Angioedema



  In women with hereditary angioedema, exogenous estrogens may induce or exacerbate symptoms of angioedema.



    5.14 Chloasma



  Chloasma may occur with COC use, especially in women with a history of chloasma gravidarum. Advise women who tend to develop chloasma to avoid exposure to the sun or ultraviolet radiation while taking Quartette.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
