<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="quazepam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *  CNS-depressant effects and next-day impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Benzodiazepine withdrawal syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Abnormal thinking and behavior changes, and complex behaviors [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Worsening of depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;1%): drowsiness, headache, fatigue, dizziness, dry mouth, dyspepsia (6.1)
 

     



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Questcor Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-465-9217 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or        www.fda.gov/medwatch          .    



 



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The table shows adverse reactions occurring at an incidence of 1% or greater in relatively short-duration, placebo-controlled clinical trials of QUAZEPAM. Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in actual practice.



     




                             QUAZEPAM 15 mg             Placebo                    
   Number of Patients        267                        268                        
                             % of Patients Reporting    
  Central Nervous System                                                           
             Daytime Drowsiness    12                         3                          
             Headache        5                          2                          
             Fatigue         2                          0                          
             Dizziness       2                          &lt;1                         
  Autonomic Nervous System                                                          
             Dry Mouth       2                          &lt;1                         
  Gastrointestinal System                                                          
             Dyspepsia       1                          &lt;1                         
          
 

   A double-blind, controlled sleep laboratory study (N=30) in elderly patients compared the effects of quazepam 7.5 mg and 15 mg to that of placebo over a period of 7 days. Both the 7.5 mg and 15 mg doses appeared to be well tolerated. Caution must be used in interpreting this data due to the small size of the study.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  



    EXCERPT:    *  CNS depressant effects: Impaired alertness and motor coordination, including risk of daytime impairment. Caution patients against driving and other activities requiring complete mental alertness (  5.1  ) 
 *  Benzodiazepine withdrawal syndrome: avoid abrupt discontinuation in at-risk patients (  5.2  ) 
 *  The failure of insomnia to remit after 7 to 10 days of treatment may indicate the presence of a primary psychiatric and/or medical illness that should be evaluated. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Severe anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions: Angioedema and anaphylaxis have been reported. Do not rechallenge if such reactions occur. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Sleep driving and other complex behaviors while not fully awake. Risk increases with dose and concomitant CNS depressants and alcohol. Immediately evaluate any new onset behavioral changes (  5.5  ) 
 *  Worsening of depression or suicidal thinking may occur: Prescribe the least number of tablets feasible to avoid intentional overdose (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 CNS-Depressant Effects and Daytime Impairment



  QUAZEPAM is a central nervous system (CNS) depressant and can impair daytime function in some patients even when used as prescribed. Prescribers should monitor for excess depressant effects, but impairment can occur in the absence of subjective symptoms, and may not be reliably detected by ordinary clinical exam (i.e. less than formal psychomotor testing). While pharmacodynamic tolerance or adaptation to some adverse depressant effects of QUAZEPAM may develop, patients using QUAZEPAM should be cautioned against driving or engaging in other hazardous activities or activities requiring complete mental alertness.



 Additive effects occur with concomitant use of other CNS depressants (e.g., other benzodiazepines, opioids, tricyclic antidepressants, alcohol), including daytime use. Downward dose adjustment of QUAZEPAM and concomitant CNS depressants should be considered. The potential for adverse drug interactions continues for several days following discontinuation of QUAZEPAM, until serum levels of both active parent drug and psychoactive metabolites decline.



 Use of QUAZEPAM with other sedative-hypnotics is not recommended. Alcohol generally should not be used during treatment with QUAZEPAM. The risk of next-day psychomotor impairment is increased if QUAZEPAM is taken with less than a full night of sleep remaining (7- to 8 hours); if higher than the recommended dose is taken; if co-administered with other CNS depressants [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  .



    5.2 Benzodiazepine Withdrawal Syndrome



  A withdrawal syndrome similar to that from alcohol (e.g., convulsions, tremor, abdominal and muscle cramps, vomiting, and sweating) can occur following abrupt discontinuation of QUAZEPAM. The more severe withdrawal effects are usually limited to patients taking higher than recommended doses over an extended time. Abrupt discontinuation should be avoided in such patients, and the dose gradually tapered. Prescribers should monitor patients for tolerance, abuse, and dependence.



 Milder withdrawal symptoms (e.g., dysphoria and insomnia) can occur following abrupt discontinuation of benzodiazepines taken at therapeutic levels for short periods [See Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  .



    5.3 Need to Evaluate for Co-morbid Disorders 



  Because sleep disturbances may be the presenting manifestation of a physical and/or psychiatric disorder, symptomatic treatment of insomnia should be initiated only after a careful evaluation of the patient. The failure of insomnia to remit after 7 to 10 days of treatment may indicate the presence of a primary psychiatric and/or medical illness that should be evaluated. Worsening of insomnia or the emergence of new thinking or behavior abnormalities may be the consequence of an unrecognized psychiatric or physical disorder. Such findings have emerged during the course of treatment with sedative-hypnotic drugs.



    5.4 Severe Anaphylactic or Anaphylactoid Reactions



  Rare cases of angioedema involving the tongue, glottis or larynx have been reported in patients after taking the first or subsequent doses of sedative-hypnotics, including QUAZEPAM. Some patients have had additional symptoms such as dyspnea, throat closing, or nausea and vomiting that suggest anaphylaxis.



 Some patients have required medical therapy in the emergency department. If angioedema involves the tongue, glottis or larynx, airway obstruction may occur and be fatal. Patients who develop angioedema after treatment with QUAZEPAM should not be rechallenged with the drug.



    5.5 Abnormal Thinking and Behavior Changes



  Abnormal thinking and behavior changes have been reported in patients treated with sedative-hypnotics including QUAZEPAM. Some of these changes include decreased inhibition (e.g., aggressiveness and extroversion that seemed out of character), bizarre behavior, and depersonalization. Visual and auditory hallucinations have also been reported. Amnesia, and other neuro-psychiatric symptoms may occur.



  Paradoxical reactions such as stimulation, agitation, increased muscle spasticity, and sleep disturbances may occur unpredictably.  



    Complex behaviors such as "sleep-driving" (i.e., driving while not fully awake, with amnesia for the event) have been reported with use of sedative-hypnotics. These behaviors can occur with initial treatment or in patients previously tolerant of QUAZEPAM or other sedative-hypnotics. Although these behaviors can occur with use at therapeutic doses, risk is increased by higher doses or concomitant use of alcohol or other CNS depressants. Due to risk to the patient and community, QUAZEPAM should be discontinued if "sleep-driving" occurs.



  Other complex behaviors (e.g., preparing and eating food, making phone calls, or having sex) have been reported in patients who are not fully awake after taking a sedative-hypnotic. As with sleep-driving, patients usually do not remember these events.  



    5.6 Worsening of Depression



  Benzodiazepines may worsen depression. Consequently, appropriate precautions (e.g., limiting the total prescription size and increased monitoring for suicidal ideation) should be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
