<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="qudexy" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle Closure Glaucoma [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Visual Field Defects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Oligohydrosis and Hyperthermia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Metabolic Acidosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Cognitive/Neuropsychiatric Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Fetal Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Hyperammonemia and Encephalopathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Kidney Stones [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Hypothermia with Concomitant Valproic Acid Use [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Paresthesia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common (&gt;= 10% more frequent than placebo or low-dose topiramate in monotherapy) adverse reactions in adult and pediatric controlled, clinical trials of immediate release topiramate were paresthesia, anorexia, weight decrease, speech disorders and related speech problems, fatigue, dizziness, somnolence, nervousness, psychomotor slowing, abnormal vision, and fever (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Upsher-Smith Laboratories, Inc. at 1-855-899-9180 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience with Immediate-Release Topiramate

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Increased Risk for Bleeding  



 Topiramate treatment is associated with an increased risk for bleeding. In a pooled analysis of placebo-controlled studies of approved and unapproved indications, bleeding was more frequently reported as an adverse event for topiramate than for placebo (4.5% versus 3.0% in adult patients, and 4.4% versus 2.3% in pediatric patients). In this analysis, the incidence of serious bleeding events for topiramate and placebo was 0.3% versus 0.2% for adult patients, and 0.4% versus 0% for pediatric patients.



 Adverse bleeding reactions reported with topiramate ranged from mild epistaxis, ecchymosis, and increased menstrual bleeding to life-threatening hemorrhages. In patients with serious bleeding events, conditions that increased the risk for bleeding were often present, or patients were often taking drugs that cause thrombocytopenia (other antiepileptic drugs) or affect platelet function or coagulation (e.g., aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, or warfarin or other anticoagulants).



     Adverse Reactions Observed in Monotherapy Trial  



     Patients 16 Years and Older  



 The adverse reactions in the monotherapy controlled trial (Study 1) that occurred most commonly in adults in the 400 mg per day topiramate group and at an incidence &gt;= 5% higher than the 50 mg per day group were paresthesia, weight decrease, somnolence, anorexia, and difficulty with memory (see  Table 4  ).



 Approximately 21% of the 159 adult patients in the 400 mg per day group who received topiramate as monotherapy in Study 1 discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions. The most common (&gt;= 2% more frequent than for topiramate 50 mg per day) adverse reactions causing discontinuation in this trial were difficulty with memory, fatigue, asthenia, insomnia, somnolence and paresthesia.



     Pediatric Patients 6 to less than 16 Years of Age  



 The adverse reactions in Study 1 that occurred most commonly in pediatric patients in the 400 mg per day topiramate group and at an incidence &gt;= 5% higher than in the 50 mg per day group were fever, weight decrease, mood problems, cognitive problems, infection, flushing, and paresthesia (see  Table 4  ).



 Approximately 14% of the 77 pediatric patients in the 400 mg per day group who received topiramate as monotherapy in Study 1 discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions. The most common (&gt;= 2% more frequent than for topiramate 50 mg per day) adverse reactions resulting in discontinuation in this trial were difficulty with concentration/attention, fever, flushing, and confusion.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions in the Immediate-Release Topiramate Monotherapy Trial with incidence &gt;= 2% in any topiramate group and incidence in the 400 mg per day group greater than in the 50 mg per day group 
                                                      Age Group     
                                                     Pediatric(6 to &lt;16 Years)                Adult(Age &gt;=16 Years)   
                                                     Immediate-release Topiramate Daily Dosage Group (mg per day)   
                                                          50           400                50           400        
 Body System/  Adverse Reaction                        (N=74)%       (N=77)%           (N=160)%      (N=159)%     
  
   Body as a Whole-General Disorders                  
   Asthenia                                               0             3                 4             6         
   Chest pain                                                                             1             2         
   Fever                                                  1             12                                        
   Leg pain                                                                               2             3         
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders      
   Ataxia                                                                                 3             4         
   Dizziness                                                                              13            14        
   Hypertonia                                                                             0             3         
   Hypoesthesia                                                                           4             5         
   Muscle contractions involuntary                        0             3                                         
   Paresthesia                                            3             12                21            40        
   Vertigo                                                0             3                                         
   Gastro-intestinal System Disorders                 
   Constipation                                                                           1             4         
   Diarrhea                                               8             9                                         
   Gastritis                                                                              0             3         
   Gastroesophageal reflux                                                                1             2         
   Dry mouth                                                                              1             3         
   Liver and Biliary System Disorders                 
   Gamma-GT increased                                                                     1             3         
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                
   Weight Decrease                                        7             17                6             17        
   Platelet, Bleeding &amp; Clotting Disorders            
   Epistaxis                                              0             4                                         
   Psychiatric Disorders                              
   Anorexia                                                                               4             14        
   Anxiety                                                                                4             6         
   Cognitive problems                                     1             6                 1             4         
   Confusion                                              0             3                                         
   Depression                                             0             3                 7             9         
   Difficulty with concentration/attention                7             10                7             8         
   Difficulty with memory                                 1             3                 6             11        
   Insomnia                                                                               8             9         
   Libido decreased                                                                       0             3         
   Mood problems                                          1             8                 2             5         
   Personality disorder (behavior problems)               0             3                                         
   Psychomotor slowing                                                                    3             5         
   Somnolence                                                                             10            15        
   Red Blood Cell Disorders                           
   Anemia                                                 1             3                                         
   Reproductive Disorders, Female                     
   Intermenstrual bleeding                                0             3                                         
   Vaginal hemorrhage                                                                     0             3         
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders                     
   Infection                                              3             8                 2             3         
   Infection viral                                        3             6                 6             8         
   Respiratory System Disorders                       
   Bronchitis                                             1             5                 3             4         
   Dyspnea                                                                                1             2         
   Rhinitis                                               5             6                 2             4         
   Sinusitis                                              1             4                                         
   Upper respiratory tract infection                      16            18                                        
   Skin and Appendages Disorders                      
   Acne                                                                                   2             3         
   Alopecia                                               1             4                 3             4         
   Pruritus                                                                               1             4         
   Rash                                                   3             4                 1             4         
   Special Senses Other, Disorders                    
   Taste perversion                                                                       3             5         
   Urinary System Disorders                           
   Cystitis                                                                               1             3         
   Dysuria                                                                                0             2         
   Micturition frequency                                  0             3                 0             2         
   Renal calculus                                                                         0             3         
   Urinary incontinence                                   1             3                                         
   Urinary tract infection                                                                1             2         
   Vascular (Extracardiac) Disorders                  
   Flushing                                               0             5                                         
                Adverse Reactions Observed in Adjunctive Therapy Epilepsy Trials  
 

 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of topiramate at dosages of 200 to 400 mg per day (recommended dose range) in controlled trials in adults with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, that were seen at an incidence of higher (&gt;=5%) than in the placebo group were: somnolence, weight decrease, anorexia, dizziness, ataxia, speech disorders and related speech problems, language problems, psychomotor slowing, confusion, abnormal vision, difficulty with memory, paresthesia, diplopia, nervousness, and asthenia (see  Table 5  ). Dose-related adverse reactions at dosages of 200 mg to 1,000 mg per day are shown in Table 7).



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of topiramate at dosages of 5 mg/kg/day to 9 mg/kg/day in controlled trials in pediatric patients with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, that were seen at an incidence higher (&gt;=5%) than in the placebo group were: fatigue, somnolence, anorexia, nervousness, difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, aggressive reaction, and weight decrease (see  Table 8  ). Table 8 also presents the incidence of adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of pediatric patients treated with topiramate and occurring with greater incidence than placebo.



 In controlled clinical trials in adults, 11% of patients receiving topiramate 200 to 400 mg per day as adjunctive therapy discontinued due to adverse reactions. This rate appeared to increase at dosages above 400 mg per day. Adverse events associated with discontinuing therapy included somnolence, dizziness, anxiety, difficulty with concentration or attention, fatigue, and paresthesia and increased at dosages above 400 mg per day. None of the pediatric patients who received topiramate adjunctive therapy at 5 mg/kg/day to 9 mg/kg/day in controlled clinical trials discontinued due to adverse reactions.



 Approximately 28% of the 1757 adults with epilepsy who received topiramate at dosages of 200 mg to 1,600 mg per day in clinical studies discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions; an individual patient could have reported more than one adverse reaction. These adverse reactions were: psychomotor slowing (4.0%), difficulty with memory (3.2%), fatigue (3.2%), confusion (3.1%), somnolence (3.2%), difficulty with concentration/attention (2.9%), anorexia (2.7%), depression (2.6%), dizziness (2.5%), weight decrease (2.5%), nervousness (2.3%), ataxia (2.1%), and paresthesia (2.0%). Approximately 11% of the 310 pediatric patients who received topiramate at dosages up to 30 mg/kg/day discontinued due to adverse reactions. Adverse reactions associated with discontinuing therapy included aggravated convulsions (2.3%), difficulty with concentration/attention (1.6%), language problems (1.3%), personality disorder (1.3%), and somnolence (1.3%).



     Incidence in Epilepsy Controlled Clinical Trials - Adjunctive Therapy - Partial Onset Seizures, Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures, and Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome  



 Table 5 lists the incidence of adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of adults treated with 200 to 400 mg per day topiramate (and also higher daily dosing of 600 mg to 1,000 mg) in controlled trials that was numerically greater with topiramate than with placebo. In general, most patients who experienced adverse reactions during the first eight weeks of these trials no longer experienced them by their last visit. Table 8 lists the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of pediatric patients treated with 5 to 9 mg/kg topiramate in controlled trials and that was numerically greater than the incidence in patients treated with placebo.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Double-Blind Epilepsy Adjunctive Therapy Trials  



 Other adverse reactions that occurred in more than 1% of adults treated with 200 mg to 400 mg of topiramate in placebo-controlled epilepsy trials but with equal or greater frequency in the placebo group were headache, injury, anxiety, rash, pain, convulsions aggravated, coughing, fever, diarrhea, vomiting, muscle weakness, insomnia, personality disorder, dysmenorrhea, upper respiratory tract infection, and eye pain.



 Table 5: Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled, Adjunctive Epilepsy Trials in AdultsPatients in these adjunctive trials were receiving 1 to 2 concomitant antiepileptic drugs in addition to topiramate or placebo,Values represent the percentage of patients reporting a given reaction. Patient may have reported more than one adverse reaction during the study and can be included in more than one adverse reaction category.,Adverse reactions reported by at least 1% of patients in the topiramate 200 mg to 400 mg per day group and more common than in the placebo group 
                                                                       Topiramate Dosage(mg per day)   
 Body System/  Adverse Reaction                       Placebo(N=291)   200 to 400(N=183)  600 to 1,000(N=414)   
  
   Body as a Whole-General Disorders                                                                          
   Fatigue                                                  13                15                 30           
   Asthenia                                                 1                  6                  3           
   Back pain                                                4                  5                  3           
   Chest pain                                               3                  4                  2           
   Influenza-like symptoms                                  2                  3                  4           
   Leg pain                                                 2                  2                  4           
   Hot flushes                                              1                  2                  1           
   Allergy                                                  1                  2                  3           
   Edema                                                    1                  2                  1           
   Body odor                                                0                  1                  0           
   Rigors                                                   0                  1                 &lt;1           
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders                                                              
   Dizziness                                                15                25                 32           
   Ataxia                                                   7                 16                 14           
   Speech disorders/Related speech problems                 2                 13                 11           
   Paresthesia                                              4                 11                 19           
   Nystagmus                                                7                 10                 11           
   Tremor                                                   6                  9                  9           
   Language problems                                        1                  6                 10           
   Coordination abnormal                                    2                  4                  4           
   Hypoesthesia                                             1                  2                  1           
   Gait abnormal                                            1                  3                  2           
   Muscle contractions involuntary                          1                  2                  2           
   Stupor                                                   0                  2                  1           
   Vertigo                                                  1                  1                  2           
   Gastro-intestinal System Disorders                                                                         
   Nausea                                                   8                 10                 12           
   Dyspepsia                                                6                  7                  6           
   Abdominal pain                                           4                  6                  7           
   Constipation                                             2                  4                  3           
   Gastroenteritis                                          1                  2                  1           
   Dry mouth                                                1                  2                  4           
   Gingivitis                                               &lt;1                 1                  1           
   GI disorder                                              &lt;1                 1                  0           
   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders                                                                           
   Hearing decreased                                        1                  2                  1           
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                        
   Weight decrease                                          3                  9                 13           
   Musculo-Skeletal System Disorders                                                                          
   Myalgia                                                  1                  2                  2           
   Skeletal pain                                            0                  1                  0           
   Platelet, Bleeding &amp; Clotting Disorders                                                                    
   Epistaxis                                                1                  2                  1           
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                      
   Somnolence                                               12                29                 28           
   Nervousness                                              6                 16                 19           
   Psychomotor slowing                                      2                 13                 21           
   Difficulty with memory                                   3                 12                 14           
   Anorexia                                                 4                 10                 12           
   Confusion                                                5                 11                 14           
   Depression                                               5                  5                 13           
   Difficulty with concentration/attention                  2                  6                 14           
   Mood problems                                            2                  4                  9           
   Agitation                                                2                  3                  3           
   Aggressive reaction                                      2                  3                  3           
   Emotional lability                                       1                  3                  3           
   Cognitive problems                                       1                  3                  3           
   Libido decreased                                         1                  2                 &lt;1           
   Apathy                                                   1                  1                  3           
   Depersonalization                                        1                  1                  2           
   Reproductive Disorders, Female                                                                             
   Breast pain                                              2                  4                  0           
   Amenorrhea                                               1                  2                  2           
   Menorrhagia                                              0                  2                  1           
   Menstrual disorder                                       1                  2                  1           
   Reproductive Disorders, Male                                                                               
   Prostatic disorder                                       &lt;1                 2                  0           
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders                                                                             
   Infection                                                1                  2                  1           
   Infection viral                                          1                  2                 &lt;1           
   Moniliasis                                               &lt;1                 1                  0           
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                               
   Pharyngitis                                              2                  6                  3           
   Rhinitis                                                 6                  7                  6           
   Sinusitis                                                4                  5                  6           
   Dyspnea                                                  1                  1                  2           
   Skin and Appendages Disorders                                                                              
   Skin disorder                                            &lt;1                 2                  1           
   Sweating increased                                       &lt;1                 1                 &lt;1           
   Rash, erythematous                                       &lt;1                 1                 &lt;1           
   Special Senses Other, Disorders                                                                            
   Taste perversion                                         0                  2                  4           
   Urinary System Disorders                                                                                   
   Hematuria                                                1                  2                 &lt;1           
   Urinary tract infection                                  1                  2                  3           
   Micturition frequency                                    1                  1                  2           
   Urinary incontinence                                     &lt;1                 2                  1           
   Urine abnormal                                           0                  1                 &lt;1           
   Vision Disorders                                                                                           
   Vision abnormal                                          2                 13                 10           
   Diplopia                                                 5                 10                 10           
   White Cell and RES Disorders                                                                               
   Leukopenia                                               1                  2                  1           
              Adverse Reactions Observed in Adjunctive Therapy Trial in Adults with Partial Onset Seizures (Study 7)  
 

 Study 7 was a randomized, double-blind, adjunctive, placebo-controlled, parallel group study with 3 treatment arms: 1) placebo; 2) topiramate 200 mg per day with a 25 mg per day starting dose, increased by 25 mg per day each week for 8 weeks until the 200 mg per day maintenance dose was reached; and 3) topiramate 200 mg per day with a 50 mg per day starting dose, increased by 50 mg per day each week for 4 weeks until the 200 mg per day maintenance dose was reached. All patients were maintained on concomitant carbamazepine with or without another concomitant antiepileptic drug.



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of topiramate that were seen at an incidence higher (&gt;=5%) than in the placebo group were: paresthesia, nervousness, somnolence, difficulty with concentration/attention, and fatigue (Table 6). Because these topiramate treatment difference incidence (topiramate % - placebo %) of many adverse reactions reported in this study were markedly lower than those reported in the previous epilepsy studies, they cannot be directly compared with data obtained in other studies.



 Table 6: Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Study 7Patients in these adjunctive trials were receiving 1 to 2 concomitant antiepileptic drugs in addition to topiramate or placebo,Values represent the percentage of patients reporting a given adverse reaction. Patients may have reported more than one adverse reaction during the study and can be included in more than one adverse reaction category,Adverse reactions reported by at least 2% of patients in the topiramate 200 mg per day group and more common than in the placebo group 
                                                                                Topiramate Dosage(mg per day)   
 Body System/  Adverse Reaction                              Placebo(N=92)             200(N=171)           
  
   Body as a Whole-General Disorders                                                                        
   Fatigue                                                         4                        9               
   Chest pain                                                      1                        2               
   Cardiovascular Disorders, General                                                                        
   Hypertension                                                    0                        2               
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders                                                            
   Paresthesia                                                     2                        9               
   Dizziness                                                       4                        7               
   Tremor                                                          2                        3               
   Hypoesthesia                                                    0                        2               
   Leg cramps                                                      0                        2               
   Language problems                                               0                        2               
   Gastro-intestinal System Disorders                                                                       
   Abdominal pain                                                  3                        5               
   Constipation                                                    0                        4               
   Diarrhea                                                        1                        2               
   Dyspepsia                                                       0                        2               
   Dry mouth                                                       0                        2               
   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders                                                                         
   Tinnitus                                                        0                        2               
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                      
   Weight decrease                                                 4                        8               
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Somnolence                                                      9                       15               
   Anorexia                                                        7                        9               
   Nervousness                                                     2                        9               
   Difficulty with concentration/attention                         0                        5               
   Insomnia                                                        3                        4               
   Difficulty with memory                                          1                        2               
   Aggressive reaction                                             0                        2               
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                             
   Rhinitis                                                        0                        4               
   Urinary System Disorders                                                                                 
   Cystitis                                                        0                        2               
   Vision Disorders                                                                                         
   Diplopia                                                        0                        2               
   Vision abnormal                                                 0                        2               
        Table 7: Incidence (%) of Dose-Related Adverse Reactions From Placebo-Controlled, Adjunctive Trials in Adults With Partial Onset Seizures (Studies 2 through 7)Dose-response studies were not conducted for other adult indications or for pediatric indications 
                                                            Topiramate Dosage (mg per day)   
 Adverse Reaction                          Placebo(N=216)      200(N=45)        400(N=68)     600 to 1,000(N=414)   
  
 Fatigue                                         13               11               12               30          
 Nervousness                                      7               13               18               19          
 Difficulty with concentration/attention          1                7                9               14          
 Confusion                                        4                9               10               14          
 Depression                                       6                9                7               13          
 Anorexia                                         4                4                6               12          
 Language Problems                               &lt;1                2                9               10          
 Anxiety                                          6                2                3               10          
 Mood Problems                                    2                0                6                9          
 Weight Decrease                                  3                4                9               13          
          Table 8: Incidence (%) of Adverse Reaction in Placebo-Controlled, Adjunctive Epilepsy Trial in Pediatric Patients (Ages 2 Years to 16 Years)Patients in these adjunctive trials were receiving 1 to 2 concomitant antiepileptic drugs in addition to topiramate or placebo,Values represent the percentage of patients reporting a given adverse reaction. Patients may have reported more than one adverse reaction during the study and can be included in more than one adverse reaction category,Reactions that Occurred in at Least 1% of Topiramate-Treated Patients and Occurred More Frequently in Topiramate-Treated Than Placebo-Treated Patients (Study 8) 
 Body System/  Adverse Reaction                                   Placebo(N=101)       Topiramate(N=98)     
  
   Body as a Whole-General Disorders                                                                        
   Fatigue                                                              5                     16            
   Injury                                                               13                    14            
   Allergic reaction                                                    1                     2             
   Back pain                                                            0                     1             
   Pallor                                                               0                     1             
   Cardiovascular Disorders, General                                                                        
   Hypertension                                                         0                     1             
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders                                                            
   Gait abnormal                                                        5                     8             
   Ataxia                                                               2                     6             
   Hyperkinesia                                                         4                     5             
   Dizziness                                                            2                     4             
   Speech disorders/Related speech problems                             2                     4             
   Hyporeflexia                                                         0                     2             
   Convulsions grand mal                                                0                     1             
   Fecal incontinence                                                   0                     1             
   Paresthesia                                                          0                     1             
   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders                                                                       
   Nausea                                                               5                     6             
   Saliva increased                                                     4                     6             
   Constipation                                                         4                     5             
   Gastroenteritis                                                      2                     3             
   Dysphasia                                                            0                     1             
   Flatulence                                                           0                     1             
   Gastroesophageal reflux                                              0                     1             
   Glossitis                                                            0                     1             
   Gum hyperplasia                                                      0                     1             
   Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders                                                                          
   Bradycardia                                                          0                     1             
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                      
   Weight decrease                                                      1                     9             
   Thirst                                                               1                     2             
   Hypoglycemia                                                         0                     1             
   Weight increase                                                      0                     1             
   Platelet, Bleeding &amp; Clotting Disorders                                                                  
   Purpura                                                              4                     8             
   Epistaxis                                                            1                     4             
   Hematoma                                                             0                     1             
   Prothrombin increased                                                0                     1             
   Thrombocytopenia                                                     0                     1             
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Somnolence                                                           16                    26            
   Anorexia                                                             15                    24            
   Nervousness                                                          7                     14            
   Personality disorder (Behavior Problems)                             9                     11            
   Difficulty with concentration/attention                              2                     10            
   Aggressive reaction                                                  4                     9             
   Insomnia                                                             7                     8             
   Difficulty with memory                                               0                     5             
   Confusion                                                            3                     4             
   Psychomotor slowing                                                  2                     3             
   Appetite increased                                                   0                     1             
   Neurosis                                                             0                     1             
   Reproductive Disorders, Female                                                                           
   Leukorrhea                                                           0                     2             
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders                                                                           
   Infection viral                                                      3                     7             
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                             
   Pneumonia                                                            1                     5             
   Respiratory disorder                                                 0                     1             
   Skin and Appendages Disorders                                                                            
   Skin Disorder                                                        2                     3             
   Alopecia                                                             1                     2             
   Dermatitis                                                           0                     2             
   Hypertrichosis                                                       1                     2             
   Rash erythematous                                                    0                     2             
   Eczema                                                               0                     1             
   Seborrhea                                                            0                     1             
   Skin discoloration                                                   0                     1             
   Urinary System Disorders                                                                                 
   Urinary incontinence                                                 2                     4             
   Nocturia                                                             0                     1             
   Vision Disorders                                                                                         
   Eye abnormality                                                      1                     2             
   Vision abnormal                                                      1                     2             
   Diplopia                                                             0                     1             
   Lacrimation abnormal                                                 0                     1             
   Myopia                                                               0                     1             
   White Cell and RES Disorders                                                                             
   Leukopenia                                                           0                     2             
             Laboratory Abnormalities  
 

 Topiramate decreases serum bicarbonate  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  .



 Immediate-release topiramate treatment was associated with changes in several clinical laboratory analytes in randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies. Similar effects should be anticipated with use of QUDEXY XR.



 Controlled trials of adjunctive topiramate treatment of adults for partial onset seizures showed an increased incidence of markedly decreased serum phosphorus (6% topiramate, 2% placebo), markedly increased serum alkaline phosphatase (3% topiramate, 1% placebo), and decreased serum potassium (0.4 % topiramate, 0.1 % placebo).



 Changes in several clinical laboratory analytes (i.e., increased creatinine, BUN, alkaline phosphatase, total protein, total eosinophil count and decreased potassium) have been observed in a clinical investigational program in very young (2 years and younger) pediatric patients who were treated with adjunctive topiramate for partial onset seizures  [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



 Topiramate treatment produced a dose-related increased shift in serum creatinine from normal at baseline to an increased value at the end of 4 months treatment in adolescent patients (ages 12 years to 16 years) in a double-blind, placebo-controlled study. The incidence of these abnormal shifts was 4% for placebo, 4% for 50 mg, and 18% for 100 mg.



 Topiramate treatment with or without concomitant valproic acid (VPA) can cause hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  .



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience with QUDEXY XR

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. In the QUDEXY XR study, a dose of 200 mg per day was administered to a limited number of patients; therefore, these results cannot be directly compared to immediate-release topiramate experience.



 The safety data presented below are from 249 patients with partial epilepsy on concomitant AEDs who participated in the QUDEXY XR study  [see  Clinical Studies (14.6)  ]  .



 Table 9 displays the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 2% of patients and numerically greater than placebo.



 Table 9: Incidence (&gt;=2%) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Adjunctive Therapy Clinical Trial in Patients With Partial Onset Seizures 
 Body System/  Adverse Reaction                           Placebo(N=125)        QUDEXY XR (200 mg)(N=124)   
  
   General Disorders                                                                                        
   Fatigue                                                       5                          6               
   Asthenia                                                      1                          2               
   Irritability                                                  1                          2               
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
   Somnolence                                                    2                         12               
   Dizziness                                                     6                          7               
   Paresthesia                                                   2                          7               
   Aphasia                                                       0                          2               
   Dysarthria                                                    1                          2               
   Memory impairment                                             1                          2               
   Psychiatric Disorder                                                                                     
   Psychomotor retardation                                       0                          2               
   Cardiovascular Disorders, General                                                                        
   Hypertension                                                  1                          3               
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                      
   Weight decrease                                               0                          7               
   Decreased appetite                                            2                          4               
   Anorexia                                                      1                          2               
         In the controlled clinical study using QUDEXY XR, 8.9% of patients who received QUDEXY XR and 4.0% who received placebo discontinued as a result of treatment-emergent adverse reactions.
 

   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of topiramate. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The listing is alphabetized: bullous skin reactions (including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis), hepatic failure (including fatalities), hepatitis, maculopathy, pancreatitis, and pemphigus.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute myopia and secondary angle closure glaucoma: Untreated elevated intraocular pressure can lead to permanent visual loss. Discontinue QUDEXY XR if it occurs (  5.1  ) 
 *  Visual field defects: These have been reported independent of elevated intraocular pressure. Consider discontinuation of QUDEXY XR (  5.2  ) 
 *  Oligohydrosis and hyperthermia: Monitor decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in pediatric patients (  5.3  ) 
 *  Metabolic acidosis: Measure baseline and periodic measurement of serum bicarbonate. Consider dose reduction or discontinuation of QUDEXY XR if clinically appropriate (  5.4  ) 
 *  Suicidal behavior and ideation: Antiepileptic drugs increase the risk of suicidal behavior or ideation (  5.5  ) 
 *  Cognitive/neuropsychiatric: QUDEXY XR may cause cognitive dysfunction. Use caution when operating machinery including automobiles. Depression and mood problems may occur (  5.6  ) 
 *  Fetal toxicity: Topiramate use during pregnancy can cause cleft lip and/or palate (  5.7  ) 
 *  Withdrawal of AEDs: Withdrawal of QUDEXY XR should be done gradually (  5.8  ) 
 *  Hyperammonemia and encephalopathy: Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced mitochondrial activity may have an increased risk of hyperammonemia. Measure ammonia if encephalopathic symptoms occur (  5.9  ) 
 *  Kidney stones: Avoid use with other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, other drugs causing metabolic acidosis, or in patients on a ketogenic diet (  5.10  ) 
 *  Hypothermia: Reported with concomitant valproic acid use (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle Closure Glaucoma



  A syndrome consisting of acute myopia associated with secondary angle closure glaucoma has been reported in patients receiving topiramate. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity and/or ocular pain. Ophthalmologic findings can include myopia, anterior chamber shallowing, ocular hyperemia (redness) and increased intraocular pressure. Mydriasis may or may not be present. This syndrome may be associated with supraciliary effusion resulting in anterior displacement of the lens and iris, with secondary angle closure glaucoma. Symptoms typically occur within 1 month of initiating topiramate therapy. In contrast to primary narrow angle glaucoma, which is rare under 40 years of age, secondary angle closure glaucoma associated with topiramate has been reported in pediatric patients as well as adults. The primary treatment to reverse symptoms is discontinuation of QUDEXY XR as rapidly as possible, according to the judgment of the treating physician. Other measures, in conjunction with discontinuation of QUDEXY XR, may be helpful.



 Elevated intraocular pressure of any etiology, if left untreated, can lead to serious sequelae including permanent vision loss.



    5.2 Visual Field Defects



  Visual field defects have been reported in patients receiving topiramate independent of elevated intraocular pressure. In clinical trials, most of these events were reversible after topiramate discontinuation. If visual problems occur at any time during topiramate treatment, consideration should be given to discontinuing the drug.



    5.3 Oligohydrosis and Hyperthermia



  Oligohydrosis (decreased sweating), resulting in hospitalization in some cases, has been reported in association with topiramate use. Decreased sweating and an elevation in body temperature above normal characterized these cases. Some of the cases were reported after exposure to elevated environmental temperatures.



 The majority of the reports have been in pediatric patients. Patients, especially pediatric patients, treated with QUDEXY XR should be monitored closely for evidence of decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in hot weather. Caution should be used when QUDEXY XR is prescribed with other drugs that predispose patients to heat-related disorders; these drugs include, but are not limited to, other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors and drugs with anticholinergic activity.



    5.4 Metabolic Acidosis



  Hyperchloremic, non-anion gap, metabolic acidosis (i.e., decreased serum bicarbonate below the normal reference range in the absence of chronic respiratory alkalosis) is associated with topiramate treatment. This metabolic acidosis is caused by renal bicarbonate loss due to the inhibitory effect of topiramate on carbonic anhydrase. Such electrolyte imbalance has been observed with the use of topiramate in placebo-controlled clinical trials and in the post-marketing period. Generally, topiramate-induced metabolic acidosis occurs early in treatment although cases can occur at any time during treatment. Bicarbonate decrements are usually mild-moderate (average decrease of 4 mEq/L at daily doses of 400 mg in adults and at approximately 6 mg/kg/day in pediatric patients); rarely, patients can experience severe decrements to values below 10 mEq/L. Conditions or therapies that predispose patients to acidosis (such as renal disease, severe respiratory disorders, status epilepticus, diarrhea, ketogenic diet or specific drugs) may be additive to the bicarbonate lowering effects of topiramate.



    Adult Patients  



  In adults, the incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate (levels of less than 20 mEq/L at two consecutive visits or at the final visit) in controlled clinical trials for adjunctive treatment of epilepsy was 32% for 400 mg per day, and 1% for placebo. Metabolic acidosis has been observed at doses as low as 50 mg per day. The incidence of a markedly abnormal low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in the adjunctive therapy trials was 3% for 400 mg per day and 0% for placebo. The incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate in adult patients (&gt;=16 years of age) in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy was 14% for 50 mg per day and 25% for 400 mg per day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial for adults was 1% for 50 mg per day and 6% for 400 mg per day. Serum bicarbonate levels have not been systematically evaluated at daily doses greater than 400 mg per day.  



    Pediatric Patients (2 years to 16 years of age)  



 The incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate in placebo-controlled trials for adjunctive treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome or refractory partial onset seizures in patients age 2 years to 16 years was 67% for topiramate (at approximately 6 mg/kg/day), and 10% for placebo. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in these trials was 11% for topiramate and 0% for placebo. Cases of moderately severe metabolic acidosis have been reported in patients as young as 5 months old, especially at daily doses above 5 mg/kg/day.



 In pediatric patients (6 years to 15 years of age), the incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy performed with topiramate was 9% for 50 mg per day and 25% for 400 mg per day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value less than 17 mEq/L and greater than 5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial was 1% for 50 mg per day and 6% for 400 mg per day.



    Pediatric Patients (under 2 years of age)  



 Although QUDEXY XR is not approved for use in patients less than 2 years of age with partial onset seizures, a study of topiramate as adjunctive use in patients under 2 years of age revealed that topiramate produced a metabolic acidosis that is notably greater in magnitude than that observed in controlled trials in older children and adults. The mean treatment difference (25 mg/kg/day topiramate-placebo) was -5.9 mEq/L for bicarbonate. The incidence of metabolic acidosis (defined by a serum bicarbonate less than 20 mEq/L) was 0% for placebo, 30% for 5 mg/kg/day, 50% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 45% for 25 mg/kg/day [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



     Manifestations of Metabolic Acidosis    



 Some manifestations of acute or chronic metabolic acidosis may include hyperventilation, nonspecific symptoms such as fatigue and anorexia, or more severe sequelae including cardiac arrhythmias or stupor. Chronic, untreated metabolic acidosis may increase the risk for nephrolithiasis or nephrocalcinosis, and may also result in osteomalacia (referred to as rickets in pediatric patients) and/or osteoporosis with an increased risk for fractures. Chronic metabolic acidosis in pediatric patients may also reduce growth rates. A reduction in growth rate may eventually decrease the maximal height achieved. The effect of topiramate on growth and bone-related sequelae has not been systematically investigated in long-term, placebo-controlled trials. Long-term, open-label treatment of infants/toddlers, with intractable partial epilepsy, for up to 1 year, showed reductions from baseline in Z SCORES for length, weight, and head circumference compared to age and sex-matched normative data, although these patients are likely to have different growth rates than normal infants. Reductions in Z SCORES for length and weight were correlated to the degree of acidosis [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  . Topiramate treatment that causes metabolic acidosis during pregnancy can possibly produce adverse effects on the fetus and might also cause metabolic acidosis in the neonate from possible transfer of topiramate to the fetus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



    Measurement of Serum Bicarbonate in Epilepsy Patients  



 Measurement of baseline and periodic serum bicarbonate during topiramate treatment is recommended. If metabolic acidosis develops and persists, consideration should be given to reducing the dose or discontinuing topiramate (using dose tapering). If the decision is made to continue patients on topiramate in the face of persistent acidosis, alkali treatment should be considered.



    5.5 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs) increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED, including QUDEXY XR, for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5 to 100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.



 Table 3 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 3: Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis 
 Indication            Placebo Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients  Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients  Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/ Incidence in Placebo Patients  Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events per 1,000 Patients   
  
 Epilepsy                      1.0                   3.4                   3.5                   2.4            
 Psychiatric                   5.7                   8.5                   1.5                   2.9            
 Other                         1.0                   1.8                   1.9                   0.9            
 Total                         2.4                   4.3                   1.8                   1.9            
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing QUDEXY XR or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated..



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.6 Cognitive/Neuropsychiatric Adverse Reactions



  Adverse reactions most often associated with the use of topiramate, and therefore expected to be associated with the use of QUDEXY XR were related to the central nervous system and were observed in the epilepsy population. In adults, the most frequent of these can be classified into three general categories: 1) Cognitive-related dysfunction (e.g. confusion, psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, speech or language problems, particularly word-finding difficulties), 2) Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (e.g. depression or mood problems), and 3) Somnolence or fatigue.



    Adult Patients  



    Cognitive Related Dysfunction  



 The majority of cognitive-related adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity, and they frequently occurred in isolation. Rapid titration rate and higher initial dose were associated with higher incidences of these reactions. Many of these reactions contributed to withdrawal from treatment [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 In the adjunctive epilepsy controlled trials conducted with topiramate (using rapid titration such as 100 mg per day to 200 mg per day weekly increments), the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 42% for 200 mg per day, 41% for 400 mg per day, 52% for 600 mg per day, 56% for 800 and 1,000 mg per day, and 14% for placebo. These dose-related adverse reactions began with a similar frequency in the titration or in the maintenance phase, although in some patients the events began during titration and persisted into the maintenance phase. Some patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions in the titration phase had a dose-related recurrence of these reactions in the maintenance phase.



 In the monotherapy epilepsy controlled trial conducted with topiramate, the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 19% for topiramate 50 mg per day and 26% for 400 mg per day.



    Psychiatric/Behavioral Disturbances  



 Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (depression or mood) were dose-related for the epilepsy population treated with topiramate [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    Somnolence/Fatigue  



 Somnolence and fatigue were the adverse reactions most frequently reported during clinical trials of topiramate for adjunctive epilepsy. For the adjunctive epilepsy population, the incidence of somnolence did not differ substantially between 200 mg per day and 1,000 mg per day, but the incidence of fatigue was dose-related and increased at dosages above 400 mg per day. For the monotherapy epilepsy population in the 50 mg per day and 400 mg per day groups, the incidence of somnolence was dose-related (9% for the 50 mg per day group and 15% for the 400 mg per day group) and the incidence of fatigue was comparable in both treatment groups (14% each). For other uses not approved for QUDEXY XR, somnolence and fatigue were more common in the titration phase.



 Additional nonspecific CNS events commonly observed with topiramate in the adjunctive epilepsy population include dizziness or ataxia.



    Pediatric Patients  



 In double-blind adjunctive therapy and monotherapy epilepsy clinical studies conducted with topiramate, the incidences of cognitive/neuropsychiatric adverse reactions in pediatric patients were generally lower than observed in adults. These reactions included psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, speech disorders/related speech problems and language problems. The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients during adjunctive therapy double-blind studies were somnolence and fatigue. The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients in the 50 mg per day and 400 mg per day groups during the monotherapy double-blind study were headache, dizziness, anorexia, and somnolence.



 No patients discontinued treatment due to any adverse events in the adjunctive epilepsy double-blind trials. In the monotherapy epilepsy double-blind trial conducted with immediate-release topiramate product, 1 pediatric patient (2%) in the 50 mg per day group and 7 pediatric patients (12%) in the 400 mg per day group discontinued treatment due to any adverse events. The most common adverse reaction associated with discontinuation of therapy was difficulty with concentration/attention; all occurred in the 400 mg per day group.



    5.7 Fetal Toxicity



  Topiramate can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Data from pregnancy registries indicate that infants exposed to topiramate in utero  have an increased risk for cleft lip and/or cleft palate (oral clefts). When multiple species of pregnant animals received topiramate at clinically relevant doses, structural malformations, including craniofacial defects, and reduced fetal weights occurred in offspring [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



 Consider the benefits and risks of topiramate when administering the drug in women of childbearing potential, particularly when topiramate is considered for a condition not usually associated with permanent injury or death [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.9)  ]  . Topiramate should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit outweighs the potential risk. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be informed of the potential hazard to a fetus [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  and  8.9)  ]  .



    5.8 Withdrawal of Antiepileptic Drugs



  In patients with or without a history of seizures or epilepsy, antiepileptic drugs including QUDEXY XR, should be gradually withdrawn to minimize the potential for seizures or increased seizure frequency [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . In situations where rapid withdrawal of QUDEXY XR is medically required, appropriate monitoring is recommended.



    5.9 Hyperammonemia and Encephalopathy



   Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy Without Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA)  



 Topiramate treatment has produced hyperammonemia (in some instances dose-related) in clinical investigational programs in very young pediatric patients (1 month to 24 months) who were treated with adjunctive topiramate for partial onset epilepsy (8% for placebo, 10% for 5 mg/kg/day, 0% for 15 mg/kg/day, 9% for 25 mg/kg/day). QUDEXY XR is not approved as adjunctive treatment of partial onset seizures in pediatric patients less than 2 years old. In some patients, ammonia was markedly increased (greater than 50% above upper limit of normal). The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment occurred with and without encephalopathy in placebo-controlled trials, and in an open-label, extension trial. Dose-related hyperammonemia was also observed in the extension trial in pediatric patients up to 2 years old. Clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting.



 Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients who were taking topiramate without concomitant valproic acid (VPA).



    Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy With Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA)  



 Concomitant administration of topiramate and valproic acid (VPA) has been associated with hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy in patients who have tolerated either drug alone based upon post-marketing reports. Although hyperammonemia may be asymptomatic, clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting. In most cases, symptoms and signs abated with discontinuation of either drug. This adverse reaction is not due to a pharmacokinetic interaction.



 Although QUDEXY XR is not indicated for use in infants/toddlers (1 month to 24 months), topiramate with concomitant VPA clearly produced a dose-related increase in the incidence of treatment-emergent hyperammonemia (above the upper limit of normal, 0% for placebo, 12% for 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, 17% for 25 mg/kg/day) in an investigational program using topiramate. Markedly increased, dose-related hyperammonemia (0% for placebo and 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 8% for 25 mg/kg/day) also occurred in these infants/toddlers. Dose-related hyperammonemia was similarly observed in a long-term, extension trial utilizing topiramate in these very young, pediatric patients [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



 Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients taking topiramate with valproic acid (VPA).



 The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment appears to be more common when used concomitantly with VPA.



    Monitoring for Hyperammonemia  



 Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced hepatic mitochondrial activity may be at an increased risk for hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy. Although not studied, topiramate or QUDEXY XR treatment or an interaction of concomitant topiramate-based product and valproic acid treatment may exacerbate existing defects or unmask deficiencies in susceptible persons.



 In patients who develop unexplained lethargy, vomiting, or changes in mental status associated with any topiramate treatment, hyperammonemic encephalopathy should be considered and an ammonia level should be measured.



    5.10 Kidney Stones



  A total of 32/2086 (1.5%) of adults exposed to topiramate during its adjunctive epilepsy therapy development reported the occurrence of kidney stones, an incidence about 2 to 4 times greater than expected in a similar, untreated population. In the double-blind monotherapy epilepsy study, a total of 4/319 (1.3%) of adults exposed to topiramate reported the occurrence of kidney stones. As in the general population, the incidence of stone formation among topiramate-treated patients was higher in men. Kidney stones have also been reported in pediatric patients taking topiramate for epilepsy.



 During long-term (up to 1 year) topiramate treatment in an open-label extension study of 284 pediatric patients 1 month to 24 months old with epilepsy, 7% developed kidney or bladder stones that were diagnosed clinically or by sonogram. QUDEXY XR is not approved for pediatric patients less than 2 years old [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



 QUDEXY XR would be expected to have the same effect as topiramate on the formation of kidney stones. An explanation for the association of topiramate and kidney stones may lay in the fact that topiramate is a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor. Carbonic anhydrase inhibitors (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide or dichlorphenamide) can promote stone formation by reducing urinary citrate excretion and by increasing urinary pH [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ,  Drug Interactions (7.4)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . The concomitant use of QUDEXY XR with any other drug producing metabolic acidosis, or potentially in patients on a ketogenic diet may create a physiological environment that increases the risk of kidney stone formation, and should therefore be avoided.



 Increased fluid intake increases the urinary output, lowering the concentration of substances involved in stone formation. Hydration is recommended to reduce new stone formation.



    5.11 Hypothermia with Concomitant Valproic Acid Use



  Hypothermia, defined as an unintentional drop in body core temperature to less than 35oC (95oF) has been reported in association with topiramate use with concomitant valproic acid (VPA) both in the presence and in the absence of hyperammonemia. This adverse reaction in patients using concomitant topiramate and valproate can occur after starting topiramate treatment or after increasing the daily dose of topiramate [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . Consideration should be given to stopping topiramate or valproate in patients who develop hypothermia, which may be manifested by a variety of clinical abnormalities including lethargy, confusion, coma, and significant alterations in other major organ systems such as the cardiovascular and respiratory systems. Clinical management and assessment should include examination of blood ammonia levels.



    5.12 Paresthesia



  Paresthesia (usually tingling of the extremities), an effect associated with the use of other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, appears to be a common effect of topiramate in adult and pediatric patients. Paresthesia was more frequently reported in the monotherapy epilepsy trials conducted with immediate-release topiramate than in the adjunctive therapy epilepsy trials conducted with the same product. In the majority of instances, paresthesia did not lead to treatment discontinuation [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.13 Interaction with Other CNS Depressants



  Topiramate is a CNS depressant. Concomitant administration of topiramate with other CNS depressant drugs or alcohol can result in significant CNS depression. Patients should be watched carefully when QUDEXY XR is co-administered with other CNS depressant drugs [see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
