<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="quillivant" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Based on accumulated data from other methylphenidate products, the most common (&gt;=5% and twice the rate of placebo) adverse reactions are appetite decreased, insomnia, nausea, vomiting, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, weight decreased, anxiety, dizziness, irritability, affect lability, tachycardia, and blood pressure increased. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer, Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Clinical Trials Experience with Other Methylphenidate Products in Children, Adolescents, and Adults with ADHD  



 Commonly reported (&gt;=2% of the methylphenidate group and at least twice the rate of the placebo group) adverse reactions from placebo-controlled trials of methylphenidate products include: appetite decreased, weight decreased, nausea, abdominal pain, dyspepsia, dry mouth, vomiting, insomnia, anxiety, nervousness, restlessness, affect lability, agitation, irritability, dizziness, vertigo, tremor, blurred vision, blood pressure increased, heart rate increased, tachycardia, palpitations, hyperhidrosis, and pyrexia.



     Clinical Trials Experience with QUILLIVANT XR in Children and Adolescents with ADHD  



 There is limited experience with QUILLIVANT XR in controlled trials. Based on this limited experience, the adverse reaction profile of QUILLIVANT XR appears similar to other methylphenidate extended-release products. The most common (&gt;=2% in the QUILLIVANT XR group and greater than placebo) adverse reactions reported in the Phase 3 controlled study conducted in 45 ADHD patients (ages 6-12 years) were affect lability, excoriation, initial insomnia, tic, decreased appetite, vomiting, motion sickness, eye pain, and rash.



 Table 2. Common Adverse Reactions occurring in &gt;=2% of subjects on QUILLIVANT XR and greater than placebo during the controlled cross-over phase 
 Adverse reaction                           QUILLIVANT XRN= 45                    PlaceboN= 45              
  
 Affect lability                                    9%                                 2%                   
 Excoriation                                        4%                                  0                   
 Initial Insomnia                                   2%                                  0                   
 Tic                                                2%                                  0                   
 Decreased appetite                                 2%                                  0                   
 Vomiting                                           2%                                  0                   
 Motion sickness                                    2%                                  0                   
 Eye pain                                           2%                                  0                   
 Rash                                               2%                                  0                   
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of methylphenidate products. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These adverse reactions are as follows:



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  : Pancytopenia, Thrombocytopenia, Thrombocytopenic purpura



   Cardiac Disorders  : Angina pectoris, Bradycardia, Extrasystole, Supraventricular tachycardia, Ventricular extrasystole



   Eye Disorders  : Diplopia, Mydriasis, Visual impairment



   General Disorders  : Chest pain, Chest discomfort, Hyperpyrexia



   Immune System Disorders  : Hypersensitivity reactions such as Angioedema, Anaphylactic reactions, Auricular swelling, Bullous conditions, Exfoliative conditions, Urticarias, Pruritus NEC, Rashes, Eruptions, and Exanthemas NEC



   Investigations  : Alkaline phosphatase increased, Bilirubin increased, Hepatic enzyme increased, Platelet count decreased, White blood cell count abnormal



   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders  : Arthralgia, Myalgia, Muscle twitching, Rhabdomyolysis



   Nervous System Disorders  : Convulsion, Grand mal convulsion, Dyskinesia



   Psychiatric Disorders  : Disorientation, Hallucination, Hallucination auditory, Hallucination visual, Libido changes, Mania



   Urogenital System  : Priapism



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  : Alopecia, Erythema



   Vascular Disorders  : Raynaud's phenomenon
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE

    WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE  

    CNS stimulants, including QUILLIVANT XR, other methylphenidate-containing products, and amphetamines, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy     [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ,   Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2  ,   9.3)  ].  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  CNS stimulants, including QUILLIVANT XR, have a high potential for abuse and dependence (5.1, 9.2, 9.3) 
 *  Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy (5.1, 9.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Serious Cardiovascular Reactions : Sudden death has been reported in association with CNS stimulants at recommended doses in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities or other serious heart problems. In adults, sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction have been reported. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmias, or coronary artery disease (  5.2  ) 
 *   Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases : Monitor blood pressure and pulse. Consider the benefits and risks in patients for whom an increase in blood pressure or heart rate would be problematic.(  5.3  ) 
 *   Psychiatric Adverse Reactions : Use of CNS stimulants may cause psychotic or manic symptoms in patients with no prior history, or exacerbation of symptoms in patients with pre-existing psychiatric illness. Evaluate for bipolar disorder prior to QUILLIVANT XR use. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Priapism : Cases of painful and prolonged penile erections and priapism have been reported with methylphenidate products. Immediate medical attention should be sought if signs or symptoms of prolonged penile erections or priapism are observed (  5.5  ) 
 *   Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon : CNS stimulants used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants (  5.6  ) 
 *   Long-Term Suppression of Growth : Monitor height and weight at appropriate intervals in pediatric patients. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Potential for Abuse and Dependence



  CNS stimulants, including QUILLIVANT XR, other methylphenidate-containing products, and amphetamines, have a high potential for abuse and dependence .  Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy [ see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2  ,  9.3)  ].  



    5.2 Serious Cardiovascular Reactions



  Stroke and myocardial infarction have occurred in adults treated with CNS stimulants at recommended doses. Sudden death has occurred in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities and other serious cardiac problems, and in adults taking CNS stimulants at recommended doses for ADHD. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious cardiac arrhythmias, coronary artery disease, or other serious cardiac problems. Further evaluate patients who develop exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or arrhythmias during treatment with QUILLIVANT XR.



    5.3 Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases



  CNS stimulants cause an increase in blood pressure (mean increase approximately 2 to 4 mmHg) and heart rate (mean increase approximately 3 to 6 bpm). Individuals may have larger increases. Monitor all patients for hypertension and tachycardia



    5.4 Psychiatric Adverse Reactions



   Exacerbation of Pre-Existing Psychosis  



 CNS stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with a pre-existing psychotic disorder.



    Induction of a Manic Episode in Patients with Bipolar Disorder  



 CNS stimulants may induce a manic or mixed episode in patients. Prior to initiating treatment, screen patients for risk factors for developing a manic episode (e.g., comorbid or history of depressive symptoms or a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, or depression).



    New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms  



 CNS stimulants, at recommended doses, may cause psychotic or manic symptoms (e.g., hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania) in patients without a prior history of psychotic illness or mania. If such symptoms occur, consider discontinuing QUILLIVANT XR. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies of CNS stimulants, psychotic or manic symptoms occurred in approximately 0.1% of CNS stimulant-treated patients, compared to 0 in placebo-treated patients.



    5.5 Priapism



  Prolonged and painful erections, sometimes requiring surgical intervention, have been reported with methylphenidate products in both pediatric and adult patients. Priapism was not reported with drug initiation but developed after some time on the drug, often subsequent to an increase in dose. Priapism has also appeared during a period of drug withdrawal (drug holidays or during discontinuation). Patients who develop abnormally sustained or frequent and painful erections should seek immediate medical attention.



    5.6 Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon



  CNS stimulants, including QUILLIVANT XR, used to treat ADHD are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Signs and symptoms are usually intermittent and mild; however, very rare sequelae include digital ulceration and/or soft tissue breakdown. Effects of peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon, were observed in post-marketing reports at different times and at therapeutic doses in all age groups throughout the course of treatment. Signs and symptoms generally improve after reduction in dose or discontinuation of drug. Careful observation of digital changes is necessary during treatment with ADHD stimulants. Further clinical evaluation (e.g., rheumatology referral) may be appropriate for certain patients.



    5.7 Long-Term Suppression of Growth



  CNS stimulants have been associated with weight loss and slowing of growth rate in pediatric patients. Closely monitor growth (weight and height) in pediatric patients treated with CNS stimulants, including QUILLIVANT XR. Careful follow-up of weight and height in children ages 7 to 10 years who were randomized to either methylphenidate or nonmedication treatment groups over 14 months, as well as in naturalistic subgroups of newly methylphenidate-treated and nonmedication-treated children over 36 months (to the ages of 10 to 13 years), suggests that consistently medicated children (i.e., treatment for 7 days per week throughout the year) have a temporary slowing in growth rate (on average, a total of about 2 cm less growth in height and 2.7 kg less growth in weight over 3 years), without evidence of growth rebound during this period of development..



 Published data are inadequate to determine whether chronic use of amphetamines may cause a similar suppression of growth; however, it is anticipated that they likely have this effect as well. Therefore, growth should be monitored during treatment with CNS stimulants, and patients who are not growing or gaining height or weight as expected may need to have their treatment interrupted.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
