<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="quinine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are a cluster of symptoms called "cinchonism", which occurs to some degree in almost all patients taking quinine: headache, vasodilation and sweating, nausea, tinnitus, hearing impairment, vertigo or dizziness, blurred vision, disturbance in color perception, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain, deafness, blindness, and disturbances in cardiac rhythm or conduction (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sun Pharmaceutical Industries, Inc. at 1-800-818-4555 or drugsafety@sunpharma.com or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Overall

  Quinine can adversely affect almost every body system. The most common adverse events associated with quinine use are a cluster of symptoms called "cinchonism", which occurs to some degree in almost all patients taking quinine. Symptoms of mild cinchonism include headache, vasodilation and sweating, nausea, tinnitus, hearing impairment, vertigo or dizziness, blurred vision, and disturbance in color perception. More severe symptoms of cinchonism are vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain, deafness, blindness, and disturbances in cardiac rhythm or conduction. Most symptoms of cinchonism are reversible and resolve with discontinuation of quinine.



 The following ADVERSE REACTIONS have been reported with quinine sulfate. Because these reactions have been reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   General:  fever, chills, sweating, flushing, asthenia, lupus-like syndrome, and hypersensitivity reactions.



   Hematologic:  agranulocytosis, hypoprothrombinemia, thrombocytopenia, disseminated intravascular coagulation, hemolytic anemia; hemolytic uremic syndrome, thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, petechiae, ecchymosis, hemorrhage, coagulopathy, blackwater fever, leukopenia, neutropenia, pancytopenia, aplastic anemia, and lupus anticoagulant.



   Neuropsychiatric:  headache, diplopia, confusion, altered mental status, seizures, coma, disorientation, tremors, restlessness, ataxia, acute dystonic reaction, aphasia, and suicide.



   Dermatologic:  cutaneous rashes, including urticarial, papular, or scarlatinal rashes, pruritus, bullous dermatitis, exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, fixed drug eruption, photosensitivity reactions, allergic contact dermatitis, acral necrosis, and cutaneous vasculitis.



   Respiratory:  asthma, dyspnea, pulmonary edema.



   Cardiovascular:  chest pain, vasodilatation, hypotension, postural hypotension, tachycardia, bradycardia, palpitations, syncope, atrioventricular block, atrial fibrillation, irregular rhythm, unifocal premature ventricular contractions, nodal escape beats, U waves, QT prolongation, ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia, torsades de pointes, and cardiac arrest.



   Gastrointestinal:  nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain, gastric irritation, and esophagitis.



   Hepatobiliary:  granulomatous hepatitis, hepatitis, jaundice, and abnormal liver function tests.



   Metabolic:  hypoglycemia and anorexia.



   Musculoskeletal:  myalgias and muscle weakness.



   Renal:  hemoglobinuria, renal failure, renal impairment, and acute interstitial nephritis.



   Special Senses:  visual disturbances, including blurred vision with scotomata, sudden loss of vision, photophobia, diplopia, night blindness, diminished visual fields, fixed pupillary dilatation, disturbed color vision, optic neuritis, blindness, vertigo, tinnitus, hearing impairment, and deafness.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: HEMATOLOGIC REACTIONS

    WARNING: HEMATOLOGIC REACTIONS  

    Quinine sulfate capsules, USP use for the treatment or prevention of nocturnal leg cramps may result in serious and life-threatening hematologic reactions, including thrombocytopenia and hemolytic uremic syndrome/thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (HUS/TTP). Chronic renal impairment associated with the development of TTP has been reported. The risk associated with quinine sulfate capsules, USP use in the absence of evidence of its effectiveness in the treatment or prevention of nocturnal leg cramps outweighs any potential benefit [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: HEMATOLOGIC REACTIONS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   Quinine sulfate capsules, USP use for the treatment or prevention of nocturnal leg cramps may result in serious and life-threatening hematologic reactions, including thrombocytopenia and hemolytic uremic syndrome/thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (HUS/TTP). Chronic renal impairment associated with the development of TTP has been reported. The risk associated with quinine sulfate capsules, USP use in the absence of evidence of its effectiveness in the treatment or prevention of nocturnal leg cramps outweighs any potential benefit (  5.1  ).  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Not indicated for the prevention or treatment of nocturnal leg cramps. Risk of serious and life-threatening adverse reactions (  1  ,  5.1  ). 
 *  Thrombocytopenia, including ITP and HUS/TTP, has been reported. Discontinue drug (  5.2  ). 
 *  QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmias. Avoid concomitant use with drugs known to prolong QT interval (  5.3  ). 
 *  Avoid concomitant use with rifampin. Quinine sulfate capsules, USP treatment failures have been reported (  5.4  ). 
 *  Avoid concomitant use with neuromuscular blocking agents. Quinine sulfate capsules, USP may potentiate neuromuscular blockade and cause respiratory depression (  5.5  ). 
 *  Serious and life threatening hypersensitivity reactions. Discontinue drug (  4  ,  5.6  ). 
 *  Atrial fibrillation and flutter. Paradoxical increase in ventricular rate may occur. Closely monitor digoxin levels if used concomitantly (  5.7  ). 
 *  Hypoglycemia. Monitor for signs and symptoms (  5.8  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Use of Quinine Sulfate Capsules, USP for Treatment or Prevention of Nocturnal Leg Cramps



  Quinine sulfate capsules, USP may cause unpredictable serious and life-threatening hematologic reactions including thrombocytopenia and hemolytic-uremic syndrome/thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (HUS/TTP) in addition to hypersensitivity reactions, QT prolongation, serious cardiac arrhythmias including torsades de pointes, and other serious adverse events requiring medical intervention and hospitalization. Chronic renal impairment associated with the development of TTP, and fatalities have also been reported. The risk associated with the use of quinine sulfate capsules, USP in the absence of evidence of its effectiveness for treatment or prevention of nocturnal leg cramps, outweighs any potential benefit in treating and/or preventing this benign, self-limiting condition [s ee  Boxed Warning    and   Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.2 Thrombocytopenia



  Quinine-induced thrombocytopenia is an immune-mediated disorder. Severe cases of thrombocytopenia that are fatal or life threatening have been reported, including cases of HUS/TTP. Chronic renal impairment associated with the development of TTP has also been reported. Thrombocytopenia usually resolves within a week upon discontinuation of quinine. If quinine is not stopped, a patient is at risk for fatal hemorrhage. Upon re-exposure to quinine from any source, a patient with quinine-dependent antibodies could develop thrombocytopenia that is more rapid in onset and more severe than the original episode.



    5.3 QT Prolongation and Ventricular Arrhythmias



  QT interval prolongation has been a consistent finding in studies which evaluated electrocardiographic changes with oral or parenteral quinine administration, regardless of age, clinical status, or severity of disease. The maximum increase in QT interval has been shown to correspond with peak quinine plasma concentration [ see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ]. Quinine sulfate has been rarely associated with potentially fatal cardiac arrhythmias, including torsades de pointes, and ventricular fibrillation.



 Quinine sulfate capsules, USP have been shown to cause concentration-dependent prolongation of the PR and QRS interval. At particular risk are patients with underlying structural heart disease and preexisting conduction system abnormalities, elderly patients with sick sinus syndrome, patients with atrial fibrillation with slow ventricular response, patients with myocardial ischemia or patients receiving drugs known to prolong the PR interval (e.g. verapamil) or QRS interval (e.g. flecainide or quinidine) [ see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ].



 Quinine sulfate capsules, USP are not recommended for use with other drugs known to cause QT prolongation, including Class IA antiarrhythmic agents (e.g., quinidine, procainamide, disopyramide), and Class III antiarrhythmic agents (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol, dofetilide).



 The use of macrolide antibiotics such as erythromycin should be avoided in patients receiving quinine sulfate capsules, USP. Fatal torsades de pointes was reported in an elderly patient who received concomitant quinine, erythromycin, and dopamine. Although a causal relationship between a specific drug and the arrhythmia was not established in this case, erythromycin is a CYP3A4 inhibitor and has been shown to increase quinine plasma levels when used concomitantly. A related macrolide antibiotic, troleandomycin, has also been shown to increase quinine exposure in a pharmacokinetic study [ see  Drug Interactions (7.1)    ].



 Quinine may inhibit the metabolism of certain drugs that are CYP3A4 substrates and are known to cause QT prolongation, e.g., astemizole, cisapride, terfenadine, pimozide, halofantrine and quinidine. Torsades de pointes has been reported in patients who received concomitant quinine and astemizole. Therefore, concurrent use of quinine sulfate capsules, USP with these medications, or drugs with similar properties, should be avoided [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2)    ].



 Concomitant administration of quinine sulfate capsules, USP with the antimalarial drugs, mefloquine or halofantrine, may result in electrocardiographic abnormalities, including QT prolongation, and increase the risk for torsades de pointes or other serious ventricular arrhythmias. Concurrent use of quinine sulfate capsules, USP and mefloquine may also increase the risk of seizures [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2)    ].



 Quinine sulfate capsules, USP should also be avoided in patients with known prolongation of QT interval and in patients with clinical conditions known to prolong the QT interval, such as uncorrected hypokalemia, bradycardia, and certain cardiac conditions [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.4 Concomitant Use of Rifampin



  Treatment failures may result from the concurrent use of rifampin with quinine sulfate capsules, USP, due to decreased plasma concentrations of quinine, and concomitant use of these medications should be avoided [ see  Drug Interactions (7.1)    ].



    5.5 Concomitant Use of Neuromuscular Blocking Agents



  The use of neuromuscular blocking agents should be avoided in patients receiving quinine sulfate capsules, USP. In one patient who received pancuronium during an operative procedure, subsequent administration of quinine resulted in respiratory depression and apnea. Although there are no clinical reports with succinylcholine or tubocurarine, quinine may also potentiate neuromuscular blockade when used with these drugs [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2)    ].



    5.6 Hypersensitivity



  Serious hypersensitivity reactions reported with quinine sulfate include anaphylactic shock, anaphylactoid reactions, urticaria, serious skin rashes, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis, angioedema, facial edema, bronchospasm, and pruritus.



 A number of other serious adverse reactions reported with quinine, including thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP) and hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS), thrombocytopenia, immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP), blackwater fever, disseminated intravascular coagulation, leukopenia, neutropenia, granulomatous hepatitis, and acute interstitial nephritis may also be due to hypersensitivity reactions.



 Quinine sulfate capsules, USP should be discontinued in case of any signs or symptoms of hypersensitivity [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.7 Atrial Fibrillation and Flutter



  Quinine sulfate capsules, USP should be used with caution in patients with atrial fibrillation or atrial flutter. A paradoxical increase in ventricular response rate may occur with quinine, similar to that observed with quinidine. If digoxin is used to prevent a rapid ventricular response, serum digoxin levels should be closely monitored, because digoxin levels may be increased with use of quinine [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2)    ].



    5.8 Hypoglycemia



  Quinine stimulates release of insulin from the pancreas, and patients, especially pregnant women, may experience clinically significant hypoglycemia.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
