<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="quinapril" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Hypertension

  Quinapril hydrochloride tablets have been evaluated for safety in 4960 subjects and patients. Of these, 3203 patients, including 655 elderly patients, participated in controlled clinical trials. Quinapril hydrochloride tablets have been evaluated for long-term safety in over 1400 patients treated for 1 year or more.



 Adverse experiences were usually mild and transient.



 In placebo-controlled trials, discontinuation of therapy because of adverse events was required in 4.7% of patients with hypertension.



 Adverse experiences probably or possibly related to therapy or of unknown relationship to therapy occurring in 1% or more of the 1563 patients in placebo-controlled hypertension trials who were treated with quinapril hydrochloride tablets are shown below.



 Adverse Events in Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                                     Quinapril HCl (N=1563) Incidence (Discontinuance)  Placebo (N=579) Incidence (Discontinuance)   
  
 Headache                                        5.6 (0.7)                         10.9 (0.7)               
 Dizziness                                       3.9 (0.8)                          2.6 (0.2)               
 Fatigue                                         2.6 (0.3)                             1.0                  
 Coughing                                        2.0 (0.5)                             0.0                  
 Nausea and/or Vomiting                          1.4 (0.3)                          1.9 (0.2)               
 Abdominal Pain                                  1.0 (0.2)                             0.7                  
           Heart Failure
   Quinapril hydrochloride tablets have been evaluated for safety in 1222 quinapril hydrochloride treated patients. Of these, 632 patients participated in controlled clinical trials. In placebo-controlled trials, discontinuation of therapy because of adverse events was required in 6.8% of patients with congestive heart failure.



 Adverse experiences probably or possibly related or of unknown relationship to therapy occurring in 1% or more of the 585 patients in placebo-controlled congestive heart failure trials who were treated with quinapril hydrochloride tablets are shown below.




                                     Quinapril HCl (N=585) Incidence (Discontinuance)  Placebo (N=295) Incidence (Discontinuance)   
  
 Dizziness                                       7.7 (0.7)                          5.1 (1.0)               
 Coughing                                        4.3 (0.3)                             1.4                  
 Fatigue                                         2.6 (0.2)                             1.4                  
 Nausea and/or Vomiting                          2.4 (0.2)                             0.7                  
 Chest Pain                                         2.4                                1.0                  
 Hypotension                                     2.9 (0.5)                             1.0                  
 Dyspnea                                         1.9 (0.2)                             2.0                  
 Diarrhea                                           1.7                                1.0                  
 Headache                                           1.7                             1.0 (0.3)               
 Myalgia                                            1.5                                2.0                  
 Rash                                            1.4 (0.2)                             1.0                  
 Back Pain                                          1.2                                0.3                  
         See .  PRECAUTIONS, Cough  
 

   Hypertension and/or Heart Failure

  Clinical adverse experiences probably, possibly, or definitely related, or of uncertain relationship to therapy occurring in 0.5% to 1.0% (except as noted) of the patients with CHF or hypertension treated with quinapril hydrochloride tablets (with or without concomitant diuretic) in controlled or uncontrolled trials (N=4847) and less frequent, clinically significant events seen in clinical trials or post-marketing experience (the rarer events are in italics) include (listed by body system):



 back pain, malaise, viral infections,  General:    anaphylactoid reaction  



 palpitation, vasodilation, tachycardia,  Cardiovascular:    heart failure, hyperkalemia, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular accident, hypertensive crisis, angina pectoris, orthostatic hypotension, cardiac rhythm disturbances, cardiogenic shock  



    Hematology:    hemolytic anemia  



 flatulence, dry mouth or throat, constipation,  Gastrointestinal:    gastrointestinal hemorrhage, pancreatitis, abnormal liver function tests, dyspepsia  



 somnolence, vertigo, syncope, nervousness, depression, insomnia, paresthesia  Nervous/Psychiatric:  



 alopecia, increased sweating, pemphigus, pruritus,  Integumentary:    exfoliative dermatitis, photosensitivity reaction, dermatopolymyositis  



 urinary tract infection, impotence,  Urogenital:    acute renal failure, worsening renal failure  



    Respiratory:    eosinophilic pneumonitis  



 amblyopia, edema, arthralgia, pharyngitis,  Other:    agranulocytosis, hepatitis, thrombocytopenia  



   Angioedema

  Angioedema has been reported in patients receiving quinapril hydrochloride tablets (0.1%). Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema may be fatal. If angioedema of the face, extremities, lips, tongue, glottis, and/or larynx occurs, treatment with quinapril hydrochloride tablets should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted immediately. (see .)  WARNINGS  



   Clinical Laboratory Test Findings

  Hematology

  (see )  WARNINGS  



   Hyperkalemia

  (see )  PRECAUTIONS  



   Creatinine and Blood Urea Nitrogen

  Increases (&gt;1.25 times the upper limit of normal) in serum creatinine and blood urea nitrogen were observed in 2% and 2%, respectively, of all patients treated with quinapril hydrochloride tablets alone. Increases are more likely to occur in patients receiving concomitant diuretic therapy than in those on quinapril hydrochloride tablets alone. These increases often remit on continued therapy. In controlled studies of heart failure, increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine were observed in 11% and 8%, respectively, of patients treated with quinapril hydrochloride tablets; most often these patients were receiving diuretics with or without digitalis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue quinapril hydrochloride tablets as soon as possible. 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. See Warnings: Fetal Toxicity 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
