<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ranexa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt; 4% and more common than with placebo) are dizziness, headache, constipation, nausea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc., at 1-800-GILEAD-5 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 A total of 2018 patients with chronic angina were treated with ranolazine in controlled clinical trials. Of the patients treated with RANEXA, 1026 were enrolled in three double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized studies (CARISA, ERICA, MARISA) of up to 12 weeks' duration. In addition, upon study completion, 1251 patients received treatment with RANEXA in open-label, long-term studies; 1227 patients were exposed to RANEXA for more than 1 year, 613 patients for more than 2 years, 531 patients for more than 3 years, and 326 patients for more than 4 years.



 At recommended doses, about 6% of patients discontinued treatment with RANEXA because of an adverse event in controlled studies in angina patients compared to about 3% on placebo. The most common adverse events that led to discontinuation more frequently on RANEXA than placebo were dizziness (1.3% versus 0.1%), nausea (1% versus 0%), asthenia, constipation, and headache (each about 0.5% versus 0%). Doses above 1000 mg twice daily are poorly tolerated.



 In controlled clinical trials of angina patients, the most frequently reported treatment-emergent adverse reactions (&gt; 4% and more common on RANEXA than on placebo) were dizziness (6.2%), headache (5.5%), constipation (4.5%), and nausea (4.4%). Dizziness may be dose-related. In open-label, long-term treatment studies, a similar adverse reaction profile was observed.



 The following additional adverse reactions occurred at an incidence of 0.5 to 4.0% in patients treated with RANEXA and were more frequent than the incidence observed in placebo-treated patients:



   Cardiac Disorders  - bradycardia, palpitations



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders  - tinnitus, vertigo



   Eye Disorders -  blurred vision



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  - abdominal pain, dry mouth, vomiting, dyspepsia



   General Disorders and Administrative Site Adverse Events  - asthenia, peripheral edema



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders -  anorexia



   Nervous System Disorders -  syncope (vasovagal)



   Psychiatric Disorders -  confusional state



   Renal and Urinary Disorders -  hematuria



   Respiratory  ,  Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders  - dyspnea



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders -  hyperhidrosis



   Vascular Disorders  - hypotension, orthostatic hypotension



 Other (&lt; 0.5%) but potentially medically important adverse reactions observed more frequently with RANEXA than placebo treatment in all controlled studies included: angioedema, renal failure, eosinophilia, chromaturia, blood urea increased, hypoesthesia, paresthesia, tremor, pulmonary fibrosis, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, and pancytopenia.



 A large clinical trial in acute coronary syndrome patients was unsuccessful in demonstrating a benefit for RANEXA, but there was no apparent proarrhythmic effect in these high-risk patients  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



     Laboratory Abnormalities:  



 RANEXA produces elevations of serum creatinine by 0.1 mg/dL, regardless of previous renal function, likely because of inhibition of creatinine's tubular secretion. In general, the elevation has a rapid onset, shows no signs of progression during long-term therapy, is reversible after discontinuation of RANEXA, and is not accompanied by changes in BUN. In healthy volunteers, RANEXA 1000 mg twice daily had no effect upon the glomerular filtration rate. More marked and progressive increases in serum creatinine, associated with increases in BUN or potassium, indicating acute renal failure, have been reported after initiation of RANEXA in patients with severe renal impairment  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  ]  .



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of RANEXA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure:



   Nervous System Disorders  - Tremor, paresthesia, abnormal coordination, and other serious neurologic adverse events have been reported to occur, sometimes concurrently, in patients taking ranolazine. The onset of events was often associated with an increase in ranolazine dose or exposure. Many patients reported symptom resolution following drug discontinuation or dose decrease.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  - Cases of hypoglycemia have been reported in diabetic patients on antidiabetic medication.



   Psychiatric Disorders  - hallucination



   Renal and Urinary Disorders  - dysuria, urinary retention



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  - angioedema, pruritus, rash
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  QT interval prolongation: Can occur with ranolazine. Little data available on high doses, long exposure, use with QT interval-prolonging drugs, potassium channel variants causing prolonged QT interval, in patients with a family history of (or congenital) long QT syndrome, or in patients with known acquired QT interval prolongation. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Renal failure: Monitor renal function after initiation and periodically in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment (CrCL&lt;60 mL/min). If acute renal failure develops, discontinue RANEXA. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 QT Interval Prolongation



  Ranolazine blocks IKrand prolongs the QTc interval in a dose-related manner.



 Clinical experience in an acute coronary syndrome population did not show an increased risk of proarrhythmia or sudden death [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  . However, there is little experience with high doses (&gt; 1000 mg twice daily) or exposure, other QT-prolonging drugs, potassium channel variants resulting in a long QT interval, in patients with a family history of (or congenital) long QT syndrome, or in patients with known acquired QT interval prolongation.



    5.2 Renal Failure



  Acute renal failure has been observed in some patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance [CrCL] &lt; 30 mL/min) while taking RANEXA. If acute renal failure develops (e.g., marked increase in serum creatinine associated with an increase in blood urea nitrogen [BUN]), discontinue RANEXA and treat appropriately [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  ]  .



 Monitor renal function after initiation and periodically in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment (CrCL &lt; 60 mL/min) for increases in serum creatinine accompanied by an increase in BUN.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
