<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rapamune1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The  following  adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label.



 *  Increased susceptibility to infection, lymphoma, and malignancy [see   Boxed Warning   , Warnings and Precautions (    5.1    ) ] 
 *  Excess mortality, graft loss, and hepatic artery thrombosis in liver transplant patients [see   Boxed Warning   , Warnings and Precautions (    5.2    ) ] 
 *  Bronchial anastomotic dehiscence in lung transplant patients [see   Boxed Warning   , Warnings and Precautions (    5.3    ) ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.4    ) ] 
 *  Exfoliative dermatitis [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.4    ) ] 
 *  Angioedema [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.5    ) ] 
 *  Fluid Accumulation and Wound Healing [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.6  ) ] 
 *  Hypertriglyceridemia, hypercholesterolemia [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.7    ) ] 
 *  Decline in renal function in long-term combination of cyclosporine with Rapamune [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.8    ) ] 
 *  Proteinuria [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.9    ) ] 
 *  Interstitial lung disease [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.11    ) ] 
 *  Increased risk of calcineurin inhibitor-induced hemolytic uremic syndrome/thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura/thrombotic microangiopathy (HUS/TTP/TMA) [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.13    ) ]. 
    The most common (&gt;= 30%) adverse reactions observed with Rapamune in clinical studies for organ rejection prophylaxis in recipients of renal transplantation are: peripheral edema, hypertriglyceridemia, hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, creatinine increased, constipation, abdominal pain, diarrhea, headache, fever, urinary tract infection, anemia, nausea, arthralgia, pain, and thrombocytopenia.
 

 The most common (&gt;= 20%) adverse reactions observed with Rapamune in the clinical study for the treatment of LAM are: stomatitis, diarrhea, abdominal pain, nausea, nasopharyngitis, acne, chest pain, peripheral edema, upper respiratory tract infection, headache, dizziness, myalgia, and hypercholesterolemia.



 The following adverse reactions resulted in a rate of discontinuation of &gt; 5% in clinical trials for renal transplant rejection prophylaxis: creatinine increased, hypertriglyceridemia, and thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP). In patients with LAM, 11% of subjects discontinued due to adverse reactions, with no single adverse reaction leading to discontinuation in more than one patient being treated with Rapamune.



   EXCERPT:   Prophylaxis of organ rejection in patients receiving renal transplants: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 30%) are peripheral edema, hypertriglyceridemia, hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, creatinine increased, abdominal pain, diarrhea, headache, fever, urinary tract infection, anemia, nausea, arthralgia, pain, and thrombocytopenia (  6  ).



 Lymphangioleiomyomatosis: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 20%) are stomatitis, diarrhea, abdominal pain, nausea, nasopharyngitis, acne, chest pain, peripheral edema, upper respiratory tract infection, headache, dizziness, myalgia, and hypercholesterolemia.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience in Prophylaxis of Organ Rejection Following Renal Transplantation

  The safety and efficacy of Rapamune Oral Solution for the prevention of organ rejection following renal transplantation were assessed in two randomized, double-blind, multicenter, controlled trials [see  Clinical Studies (      14.1      )  ]. The safety profiles in the two studies were similar.



 The incidence of adverse reactions in the randomized, double-blind, multicenter, placebo-controlled trial (Study 2) in which 219 renal transplant patients received Rapamune Oral Solution 2 mg/day, 208 received Rapamune Oral Solution 5 mg/day, and 124 received placebo is presented in the  table  below. The study population had a mean age of 46 years (range 15 to 71 years), the distribution was 67% male, and the composition by race was: White (78%), Black (11%), Asian (3%), Hispanic (2%), and Other (5%). All patients were treated with cyclosporine and corticosteroids. Data (&gt;= 12 months post-transplant) presented in the following  table  show the adverse reactions that occurred in at least one of the Rapamune treatment groups with an incidence of &gt;= 20%.



 The safety profile of the tablet did not differ from that of the oral solution formulation [see  Clinical Studies (      14.1      )  ].



 In general, adverse reactions related to the administration of Rapamune were dependent on dose/concentration. Although a daily maintenance dose of 5 mg, with a loading dose of 15 mg, was shown to be safe and effective, no efficacy advantage over the 2 mg dose could be established for renal transplant patients. Patients receiving 2 mg of Rapamune Oral Solution per day demonstrated an overall better safety profile than did patients receiving 5 mg of Rapamune Oral Solution per day.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in one clinical trial of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of the same or another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 TABLE 1: ADVERSE REACTIONS OCCURRING AT A FREQUENCY OF &gt;= 20% IN AT LEAST ONE OF THE RAPAMUNE TREATMENT GROUPS IN A STUDY OF PROPHYLAXIS OF ORGAN REJECTION FOLLOWING RENAL TRANSPLANTATION (%) AT &gt;= 12 MONTHS POST-TRANSPLANTATION (STUDY 2)a 
                                                                                                                                                               ---Rapamune Oral Solution---                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 
                                                                                                                                                               2 mg/day                                                                                                                                                      5 mg/day                                                                                                                                                      Placebo                                                                                                                                                        
 Adverse Reaction                                                                                                                                              (n = 218)                                                                                                                                                     (n = 208)                                                                                                                                                     (n = 124)                                                                                                                                                      
  
 a: Patients received cyclosporine and corticosteroids.                                                                                                         
  
 Peripheral edema                                                                                                                                              54                                                                                                                                                            58                                                                                                                                                            48                                                                                                                                                             
 Hypertriglyceridemia                                                                                                                                          45                                                                                                                                                            57                                                                                                                                                            23                                                                                                                                                             
 Hypertension                                                                                                                                                  45                                                                                                                                                            49                                                                                                                                                            48                                                                                                                                                             
 Hypercholesterolemia                                                                                                                                          43                                                                                                                                                            46                                                                                                                                                            23                                                                                                                                                             
 Creatinine increased                                                                                                                                          39                                                                                                                                                            40                                                                                                                                                            38                                                                                                                                                             
 Constipation                                                                                                                                                  36                                                                                                                                                            38                                                                                                                                                            31                                                                                                                                                             
 Abdominal pain                                                                                                                                                29                                                                                                                                                            36                                                                                                                                                            30                                                                                                                                                             
 Diarrhea                                                                                                                                                      25                                                                                                                                                            35                                                                                                                                                            27                                                                                                                                                             
 Headache                                                                                                                                                      34                                                                                                                                                            34                                                                                                                                                            31                                                                                                                                                             
 Fever                                                                                                                                                         23                                                                                                                                                            34                                                                                                                                                            35                                                                                                                                                             
 Urinary tract infection                                                                                                                                       26                                                                                                                                                            33                                                                                                                                                            26                                                                                                                                                             
 Anemia                                                                                                                                                        23                                                                                                                                                            33                                                                                                                                                            21                                                                                                                                                             
 Nausea                                                                                                                                                        25                                                                                                                                                            31                                                                                                                                                            29                                                                                                                                                             
 Arthralgia                                                                                                                                                    25                                                                                                                                                            31                                                                                                                                                            18                                                                                                                                                             
 Thrombocytopenia                                                                                                                                              14                                                                                                                                                            30                                                                                                                                                            9                                                                                                                                                              
 Pain                                                                                                                                                          33                                                                                                                                                            29                                                                                                                                                            25                                                                                                                                                             
 Acne                                                                                                                                                          22                                                                                                                                                            22                                                                                                                                                            19                                                                                                                                                             
 Rash                                                                                                                                                          10                                                                                                                                                            20                                                                                                                                                            6                                                                                                                                                              
 Edema                                                                                                                                                         20                                                                                                                                                            18                                                                                                                                                            15                                                                                                                                                             
      The  following  adverse reactions were reported less frequently (&gt;= 3%, but &lt; 20%)
 

 *    Body as a Whole  - Sepsis, lymphocele, herpes zoster, herpes simplex. 
 *    Cardiovascular  - Venous thromboembolism (including pulmonary embolism, deep venous thrombosis), tachycardia. 
 *    Digestive System  - Stomatitis. 
 *    Hematologic and Lymphatic System  - Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura/hemolytic uremic syndrome (TTP/HUS), leukopenia. 
 *    Metabolic/Nutritional  - Abnormal healing, increased lactic dehydrogenase (LDH), hypokalemia, diabetes mellitus. 
 *    Musculoskeletal System  - Bone necrosis. 
 *    Respiratory System  - Pneumonia, epistaxis. 
 *    Skin  - Melanoma, squamous cell carcinoma, basal cell carcinoma. 
 *    Urogenital System  - Pyelonephritis, decline in renal function (creatinine increased) in long-term combination of cyclosporine with Rapamune [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.8    ) ], ovarian cysts, menstrual disorders (including amenorrhea and menorrhagia). 
    Less frequently (&lt; 3%) occurring adverse reactions included: lymphoma/post-transplant lymphoproliferative disorder, mycobacterial infections (including  M. tuberculosis  ), pancreatitis, cytomegalovirus (CMV), and Epstein-Barr virus.
 

       Increased Serum Cholesterol and Triglycerides    

  The use of Rapamune in renal transplant patients was associated with increased serum cholesterol and triglycerides that may require treatment.



 In Studies 1 and 2, in  de novo  renal transplant patients who began the study with fasting, total serum cholesterol &lt; 200 mg/dL or fasting, total serum triglycerides &lt; 200 mg/dL, there was an increased incidence of hypercholesterolemia (fasting serum cholesterol &gt; 240 mg/dL) or hypertriglyceridemia (fasting serum triglycerides &gt; 500 mg/dL), respectively, in patients receiving both Rapamune 2 mg and Rapamune 5 mg compared with azathioprine and placebo controls.



 Treatment of new-onset hypercholesterolemia with lipid-lowering agents was required in 42-52% of patients enrolled in the Rapamune arms of Studies 1 and 2 compared with 16% of patients in the placebo arm and 22% of patients in the azathioprine arm. In other Rapamune renal transplant studies, up to 90% of patients required treatment for hyperlipidemia and hypercholesterolemia with anti-lipid therapy (e.g., statins, fibrates). Despite anti-lipid management, up to 50% of patients had fasting serum cholesterol levels &gt;240 mg/dL and triglycerides above recommended target levels [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )  ].



       Abnormal Healing    

  Abnormal healing events following transplant surgery include fascial dehiscence, incisional hernia, and anastomosis disruption (e.g., wound, vascular, airway, ureteral, biliary).



       Malignancies    

  The  table  below summarizes the incidence of malignancies in the two controlled trials (Studies 1 and 2) for the prevention of acute rejection [see  Clinical Studies (      14.1      )  ].



 At 24 months (Study 1) and 36 months (Study 2), there were no significant differences among treatment groups.



 TABLE 2: INCIDENCE (%) OF MALIGNANCIES IN STUDY 1 (24 MONTHS) AND STUDY 2 (36 MONTHS) POST-TRANSPLANTa,b 
 a: Patients received cyclosporine and corticosteroids. b: Includes patients who prematurely discontinued treatment.  c: Patients may be counted in more than one category.                                             
  
 Malignancy                                                                                                                                                                                                            RapamuneOral Solution2 mg/day                             RapamuneOral Solution5 mg/day                             Azathioprine2-3mg/kg/day                                  Placebo                                                    
 Study 1(n = 284)                                                                                                                                                                                                      Study 2(n = 227)                                          Study 1(n = 274)                                          Study 2(n = 219)                                          Study 1(n = 161)                                          Study 2(n = 130)                                                                           
   Lymphoma/    lymphoproliferative disease                                                                                                                                                                              0.7                                                       1.8                                                       1.1                                                       3.2                                                       0.6                                                                                       0.    8                                                              
   Skin Carcinoma                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               
      Any Squamous Cell  c                                                                                                                                                                                             0.4                                                       2.7                                                       2.2                                                       0.9                                                       3.8                                                                                       3.0                                                                    
      Any Basal Cell  c                                                                                                                                                                                                0.7                                                       2.2                                                       1.5                                                       1.8                                                       2.5                                                                                       5.3                                                                    
      Melanoma                                                                                                                                                                                                         0.0                                                       0.4                                                       0.0                                                       1.4                                                       0.0                                                                                       0.0                                                                    
      Miscellaneous/Not       Specified                                                                                                                                                                                0.0                                                       0.0                                                       0.0                                                       0.0                                                       0.0                                                                                       0.8                                                                    
   Total                                                                                                                                                                                                                 1.1                                                       4.4                                                       3.3                                                       4.1                                                       4.3                                                                                       7.7                                                                  
   Other Malignancy                                                                                                                                                                                                      1.1                                                       2.2                                                       1.5                                                       1.4                                                       0.6                                                                                       2.3                                                                  
        6.2 Rapamune Following Cyclosporine Withdrawal
   The incidence of adverse reactions was determined through 36 months in a randomized, multicenter, controlled trial (Study 3) in which 215 renal transplant patients received Rapamune as a maintenance regimen following cyclosporine withdrawal, and 215 patients received Rapamune with cyclosporine therapy [see  Clinical Studies (    14.2    )  ]. All patients were treated with corticosteroids. The safety profile prior to randomization (start of cyclosporine withdrawal) was similar to that of the 2 mg Rapamune groups in Studies 1 and 2.



 Following randomization (at 3 months), patients who had cyclosporine eliminated from their therapy experienced higher incidences of the following adverse reactions: abnormal liver function tests (including increased AST/SGOT and increased ALT/SGPT), hypokalemia, thrombocytopenia, and abnormal healing. Conversely, the incidence of the following adverse events was higher in patients who remained on cyclosporine than those who had cyclosporine withdrawn from therapy: hypertension, cyclosporine toxicity, increased creatinine, abnormal kidney function, toxic nephropathy, edema, hyperkalemia, hyperuricemia, and gum hyperplasia. Mean systolic and diastolic blood pressure improved significantly following cyclosporine withdrawal.



       Malignancies    

  The incidence of malignancies in Study 3 [see  Clinical Studies (    14.2    )  ] is presented in the  table  following.



 In Study 3, the incidence of lymphoma/lymphoproliferative disease was similar in all treatment groups. The overall incidence of malignancy was higher in patients receiving Rapamune plus cyclosporine compared with patients who had cyclosporine withdrawn. Conclusions regarding these differences in the incidence of malignancy could not be made because Study 3 was not designed to consider malignancy risk factors or systematically screen subjects for malignancy. In addition, more patients in the Rapamune with cyclosporine group had a pretransplantation history of skin carcinoma.



 TABLE 3: INCIDENCE (%) OF MALIGNANCIES IN STUDY 3 (CYCLOSPORINE WITHDRAWAL STUDY) AT 36 MONTHS POST-TRANSPLANTa,b 
 a: Patients received cyclosporine and corticosteroids. b: Includes patients who prematurely discontinued treatment.  c: Patients may be counted in more than one category.                                             
  
 Malignancy                                                                                                                                                                                                            Nonrandomized(n = 95)                                                                                                                         Rapamunewith CyclosporineTherapy(n = 215)                                                                                             RapamuneFollowing Cyclosporine Withdrawal(n = 215)                                                                                     
   Lymphoma/    lymphoproliferative disease                                                                                                                                                                              1.1                                                                                                                                           1.4                                                                                                                                   0.5                                                                                                                                  
   Skin Carcinoma                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 
      Any Squamous Cell  c                                                                                                                                                                                             3.2                                                                                                                                           3.3                                                                                                                                   2.3                                                                                                                                    
      Any Basal Cell  c                                                                                                                                                                                                3.2                                                                                                                                           6.5                                                                                                                                   2.3                                                                                                                                    
      Melanoma                                                                                                                                                                                                         0.0                                                                                                                                           0.5                                                                                                                                   0.0                                                                                                                                    
      Miscellaneous/Not     Specified                                                                                                                                                                                  1.1                                                                                                                                           0.9                                                                                                                                   0.0                                                                                                                                    
   Total                                                                                                                                                                                                                 4.2                                                                                                                                           7.9                                                                                                                                   3.7                                                                                                                                  
   Other Malignancy                                                                                                                                                                                                      3.2                                                                                                                                           3.3                                                                                                                                   1.9                                                                                                                                  
        6.3 High-Immunologic Risk Renal Transplant Patients
   Safety was assessed in 224 patients who received at least one dose of sirolimus with cyclosporine [see  Clinical Studies (    14.3    )  ]. Overall, the incidence and nature of adverse events was similar to those seen in previous combination studies with Rapamune. The incidence of malignancy was 1.3% at 12 months.



   6.4 Conversion from Calcineurin Inhibitors to Rapamune in Maintenance Renal Transplant Population

  The safety and efficacy of conversion from calcineurin inhibitors to Rapamune in maintenance renal transplant population have not been established [see  Clinical Studies (      14.4      )  ]. In a study evaluating the safety and efficacy of conversion from calcineurin inhibitors to Rapamune (initial target sirolimus concentrations of 12-20 ng/mL, and then 8-20 ng/mL, by chromatographic assay) in maintenance renal transplant patients, enrollment was stopped in the subset of patients (n = 87) with a baseline glomerular filtration rate of less than 40 mL/min. There was a higher rate of serious adverse events, including pneumonia, acute rejection, graft loss and death, in this stratum of the Rapamune treatment arm.



 The subset of patients with a baseline glomerular filtration rate of less than 40 mL/min had 2 years of follow-up after randomization. In this population, the rate of pneumonia was 15/58 vs. 4/29, graft loss (excluding death with functioning graft loss) was 13/58 vs. 9/29, and death was 9/58 vs. 1/29 in the sirolimus conversion group and CNI continuation group, respectively.



 In the subset of patients with a baseline glomerular filtration rate of greater than 40 mL/min, there was no benefit associated with conversion with regard to improvement in renal function and a greater incidence of proteinuria in the Rapamune conversion arm.



 Overall in this study, a 5-fold increase in the reports of tuberculosis among sirolimus (11/551) and comparator (1/273) treatment groups was observed with 2:1 randomization scheme.



   6.5 Pediatric Renal Transplant Patients

  Safety was assessed in a controlled clinical trial in pediatric (&lt; 18 years of age) renal transplant patients considered at high-immunologic risk, defined as a history of one or more acute allograft rejection episodes and/or the presence of chronic allograft nephropathy on a renal biopsy [see  Clinical Studies (      14.6      )  ]. The use of Rapamune in combination with calcineurin inhibitors and corticosteroids was associated with a higher incidence of deterioration of renal function (creatinine increased) compared to calcineurin inhibitor-based therapy, serum lipid abnormalities (including, but not limited to, increased serum triglycerides and cholesterol), and urinary tract infections.



   6.6 Patients with Lymphangioleiomyomatosis

  Safety was assessed in a controlled trial involving 89 patients with lymphangioleiomyomatosis, 46 of whom were treated with Rapamune [  see  Clinical Studies (14.7)    ]. The adverse drug reactions observed in this trial were consistent with the known safety profile for renal transplant patients receiving Rapamune, with the addition of weight decreased which was reported at a greater incidence with Rapamune when compared to placebo. Adverse reactions occurring at a frequency of &gt;= 20% in the Rapamune treatment group and greater than placebo include stomatitis, diarrhea, abdominal pain, nausea, nasopharyngitis, acne, chest pain, peripheral edema, upper respiratory tract infection, headache, dizziness, myalgia, and hypercholesterolemia.



   6.7 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Rapamune in transplant patients. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *    Body as a Whole  - Lymphedema. 
 *    Cardiovascular  - Pericardial effusion (including hemodynamically significant effusions and tamponade requiring intervention in children and adults) and fluid accumulation. 
 *    Digestive System  - Ascites. 
 *    Hematological/Lymphatic  - The concomitant use of Rapamune with a calcineurin inhibitor may increase the risk of calcineurin inhibitor-induced HUS/TTP/TMA [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.13    ) ]; pancytopenia, neutropenia. 
 *    Hepatobiliary Disorders  - Hepatotoxicity, including fatal hepatic necrosis, with elevated sirolimus trough concentrations. 
 *    Immune System  - Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions, angioedema, and hypersensitivity vasculitis [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.4    ) ]. 
 *    Infections  - Tuberculosis. BK virus associated nephropathy has been observed in patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Rapamune. This infection may be associated with serious outcomes, including deteriorating renal function and renal graft loss. Cases of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), sometimes fatal, have been reported in patients treated with immunosuppressants, including Rapamune [see Warnings and Precautions  (  5.10  ) ]. Clostridium difficile enterocolitis. 
 *    Metabolic/Nutritional  - Liver function test abnormal, AST/SGOT increased, ALT/SGPT increased, hypophosphatemia, hyperglycemia, diabetes mellitus. 
 *    Nervous system - Posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome. 
 *    Respiratory  - Cases of interstitial lung disease (including pneumonitis, bronchiolitis obliterans organizing pneumonia [BOOP], and pulmonary fibrosis), some fatal, with no identified infectious etiology have occurred in patients receiving immunosuppressive regimens including Rapamune. In some cases, the interstitial lung disease has resolved upon discontinuation or dose reduction of Rapamune. The risk may be increased as the sirolimus trough concentration increases [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.11    ) ]; pulmonary hemorrhage; pleural effusion; alveolar proteinosis. 
 *    Skin  - Exfoliative dermatitis [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.4    ) ]. 
 *    Urogenital  - Nephrotic syndrome, proteinuria, focal segmental glomerulosclerosis, ovarian cysts, menstrual disorders (including amenorrhea and menorrhagia). Azoospermia has been reported with the use of Rapamune and has been reversible upon discontinuation of Rapamune in most cases. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: BOX WARNING: IMMUNOSUPPRESSION, USE IS NOT RECOMMENDED IN LIVER OR LUNG TRANSPLANT PATIENTS

    BOX WARNING: IMMUNOSUPPRESSION, USE IS NOT RECOMMENDED IN LIVER OR LUNG TRANSPLANT PATIENTS  

    *  Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of lymphoma and other malignancies may result from immunosuppression 
      Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of lymphoma may result from immunosuppression. Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of renal transplant patients should use Rapamune    (r)     for prophylaxis of organ rejection in patients receiving renal transplants. Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physician responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient     [see   Warnings and Precautions (          5.1          )  ]  .
 

 *  The safety and efficacy of Rapamune (sirolimus) as immunosuppressive therapy have not been established in liver or lung transplant patients, and therefore, such use is not recommended [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2, 5.3)]. 
 *  Liver Transplantation - Excess Mortality, Graft Loss, and Hepatic Artery Thrombosis (HAT) 
      The use of Rapamune in combination with tacrolimus was associated with excess mortality and graft loss in a study in   de novo   liver transplant patients. Many of these patients had evidence of infection at or near the time of death.  
 

   In this and another study in   de novo   liver transplant patients, the use of Rapamune in combination with cyclosporine or tacrolimus was associated with an increase in HAT; most cases of HAT occurred within 30 days post-transplantation and most led to graft loss or death [see   Warnings and Precautions (          5.2          )  ].  



 *  Lung Transplantation - Bronchial Anastomotic Dehiscence 
      Cases of bronchial anastomotic dehiscence, most fatal, have been reported in   de novo   lung transplant patients when Rapamune has been used as part of an immunosuppressive regimen [  see Warnings and Precautions (      5.3      )  ]    .  
 

   EXCERPT:     WARNING: IMMUNOSUPPRESSION, USE IS NOT RECOMMENDED IN LIVER OR LUNG TRANSPLANT PATIENTS  



     See Full Prescribing Information for complete Boxed Warning.    



 *  Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of lymphoma and other malignancies may result from immunosuppression (5.1). Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of renal transplant patients should use Rapamune for prophylaxis of organ rejection in patients receiving renal transplants. 
 *  The safety and efficacy of Rapamune as immunosuppressive therapy have not been established in liver or lung transplant patients, and therefore, such use is not recommended (5.2, 5.3).Liver Transplantation - Excess mortality, graft loss, and hepatic artery thrombosis (5.2).Lung Transplantation - Bronchial anastomotic dehiscence (5.3). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity Reactions (  5.4  ) 
 *  Angioedema (  5.5  ) 
 *  Fluid Accumulation and Wound Healing (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hyperlipidemia (  5.7  ) 
 *  Renal Function (  5.8  ) 
 *  Proteinuria (  5.9  ) 
 *  Latent Viral Infections (  5.10  ) 
 *  Interstitial Lung Disease/Non-Infectious Pneumonitis (  5.11  ) 
 *   De Novo Use Without Cyclosporine (  5.12  ) 
 *  Increased Risk of Calcineurin Inhibitor-induced HUS/TTP/TMA (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Susceptibility to Infection and the Possible Development of Lymphoma



  Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of lymphoma and other malignancies, particularly of the skin, may result from immunosuppression. The rates of lymphoma/lymphoproliferative disease observed in Studies 1 and 2 were 0.7-3.2% (for Rapamune-treated patients) versus 0.6-0.8% (azathioprine and placebo control) [see Adverse Reactions (     6.1     )  and (     6.2     )  ]. Oversuppression of the immune system can also increase susceptibility to infection, including opportunistic infections such as tuberculosis, fatal infections, and sepsis. Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should use Rapamune for prophylaxis of organ rejection in patients receiving renal transplants. Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physician responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient.



    5.2 Liver Transplantation - Excess Mortality, Graft Loss, and Hepatic Artery Thrombosis (HAT)



  The safety and efficacy of Rapamune as immunosuppressive therapy have not been established in liver transplant patients; therefore, such use is not recommended. The use of Rapamune has been associated with adverse outcomes in patients following liver transplantation, including excess mortality, graft loss and Hepatic Artery Thrombosis (HAT).



 In a study in de novo  liver transplant patients, the use of Rapamune in combination with tacrolimus was associated with excess mortality and graft loss (22% in combination versus 9% on tacrolimus alone). Many of these patients had evidence of infection at or near the time of death.



 In this and another study in de novo  liver transplant patients, the use of Rapamune in combination with cyclosporine or tacrolimus was associated with an increase in HAT (7% in combination versus 2% in the control arm); most cases of HAT occurred within 30 days post-transplantation, and most led to graft loss or death.



 In a clinical study in stable liver transplant patients 6-144 months post-liver transplantation and receiving a CNI-based regimen, an increased number of deaths was observed in the group converted to a Rapamune-based regimen compared to the group who was continued on a CNI-based regimen, although the difference was not statistically significant (3.8% versus 1.4%) [see Clinical Studies   (   14.5   )  ].



    5.3 Lung Transplantation - Bronchial Anastomotic Dehiscence



  Cases of bronchial anastomotic dehiscence, most fatal, have been reported in de novo  lung transplant patients when Rapamune has been used as part of an immunosuppressive regimen.



 The safety and efficacy of Rapamune as immunosuppressive therapy have not been established in lung transplant patients; therefore, such use is not recommended.



    5.4 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions, angioedema, exfoliative dermatitis and hypersensitivity vasculitis, have been associated with the administration of Rapamune [see Adverse Reactions (     6.7     )  ].



    5.5 Angioedema



  Rapamune has been associated with the development of angioedema. The concomitant use of Rapamune with other drugs known to cause angioedema, such as ACE-inhibitors, may increase the risk of developing angioedema.



    5.6 Fluid Accumulation and Wound Healing



  There have been reports of impaired or delayed wound healing in patients receiving Rapamune, including lymphocele and wound dehiscence [see Adverse Reactions (     6.1     )  ]. mTOR inhibitors such as sirolimus have been shown in vitro  to inhibit production of certain growth factors that may affect angiogenesis, fibroblast proliferation, and vascular permeability. Lymphocele, a known surgical complication of renal transplantation, occurred significantly more often in a dose-related fashion in patients treated with Rapamune [see Adverse Reactions (     6.1     )  ]. Appropriate measures should be considered to minimize such complications. Patients with a body mass index (BMI) greater than 30 kg/m  2  may be at increased risk of abnormal wound healing based on data from the medical literature.



 There have also been reports of fluid accumulation, including peripheral edema, lymphedema, pleural effusion, ascites, and pericardial effusions (including hemodynamically significant effusions and tamponade requiring intervention in children and adults), in patients receiving Rapamune.



    5.7 Hyperlipidemia



  Increased serum cholesterol and triglycerides requiring treatment occurred more frequently in patients treated with Rapamune compared with azathioprine or placebo controls in Studies 1 and 2 [see Adverse Reactions (     6.1     )  ]. There were increased incidences of hypercholesterolemia (43-46%) and/or hypertriglyceridemia (45-57%) in patients receiving Rapamune compared with placebo controls (each 23%). The risk/benefit should be carefully considered in patients with established hyperlipidemia before initiating an immunosuppressive regimen including Rapamune.



 Any patient who is administered Rapamune should be monitored for hyperlipidemia. If detected, interventions such as diet, exercise, and lipid-lowering agents should be initiated as outlined by the National Cholesterol Education Program guidelines.



 In clinical trials of patients receiving Rapamune plus cyclosporine or Rapamune after cyclosporine withdrawal, up to 90% of patients required treatment for hyperlipidemia and hypercholesterolemia with anti-lipid therapy (e.g., statins, fibrates). Despite anti-lipid management, up to 50% of patients had fasting serum cholesterol levels &gt;240 mg/dL and triglycerides above recommended target levels. The concomitant administration of Rapamune and HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors resulted in adverse events such as CPK elevations (3%), myalgia (6.7%) and rhabdomyolysis (&lt;1%). In these trials, the number of patients was too small and duration of follow-up too short to evaluate the long-term impact of Rapamune on cardiovascular mortality.



 During Rapamune therapy with or without cyclosporine, patients should be monitored for elevated lipids, and patients administered an HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor and/or fibrate should be monitored for the possible development of rhabdomyolysis and other adverse effects, as described in the respective labeling for these agents.



    5.8 Renal Function



  Renal function should be closely monitored during the co-administration of Rapamune with cyclosporine, because long-term administration of the combination has been associated with deterioration of renal function. Patients treated with cyclosporine and Rapamune were noted to have higher serum creatinine levels and lower glomerular filtration rates compared with patients treated with cyclosporine and placebo or azathioprine controls (Studies 1 and 2). The rate of decline in renal function in these studies was greater in patients receiving Rapamune and cyclosporine compared with control therapies.



 Appropriate adjustment of the immunosuppressive regimen, including discontinuation of Rapamune and/or cyclosporine, should be considered in patients with elevated or increasing serum creatinine levels. In patients at low- to moderate-immunologic risk, continuation of combination therapy with cyclosporine beyond 4 months following transplantation should only be considered when the benefits outweigh the risks of this combination for the individual patients. Caution should be exercised when using agents (e.g., aminoglycosides and amphotericin B) that are known to have a deleterious effect on renal function.



 In patients with delayed graft function, Rapamune may delay recovery of renal function.



    5.9 Proteinuria



  Periodic quantitative monitoring of urinary protein excretion is recommended. In a study evaluating conversion from calcineurin inhibitors (CNI) to Rapamune in maintenance renal transplant patients 6-120 months post-transplant, increased urinary protein excretion was commonly observed from 6 through 24 months after conversion to Rapamune compared with CNI continuation [see Clinical Studies (     14.4     ), Adverse Reactions (   6.4)  ]. Patients with the greatest amount of urinary protein excretion prior to Rapamune conversion were those whose protein excretion increased the most after conversion. New onset nephrosis (nephrotic syndrome) was also reported as a treatment-emergent adverse event in 2.2% of the Rapamune conversion group patients in comparison to 0.4% in the CNI continuation group of patients. Nephrotic range proteinuria (defined as urinary protein to creatinine ratio &gt; 3.5) was also reported in 9.2% in the Rapamune conversion group of patients in comparison to 3.7% in the CNI continuation group of patients. In some patients, reduction in the degree of urinary protein excretion was observed for individual patients following discontinuation of Rapamune. The safety and efficacy of conversion from calcineurin inhibitors to Rapamune in maintenance renal transplant patients have not been established.



    5.10 Latent Viral Infections



  Immunosuppressed patients are at increased risk for opportunistic infections, including activation of latent viral infections. These include BK virus-associated nephropathy, which has been observed in renal transplant patients receiving immunosuppressants, including Rapamune. This infection may be associated with serious outcomes, including deteriorating renal function and renal graft loss [see Adverse Reactions (     6.7     )  ]. Patient monitoring may help detect patients at risk for BK virus-associated nephropathy. Reduction in immunosuppression should be considered for patients who develop evidence of BK virus-associated nephropathy.



 Cases of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), sometimes fatal have been reported in patients treated with immunosuppressants, including Rapamune. PML commonly presents with hemiparesis, apathy, confusion, cognitive deficiencies and ataxia. Risk factors for PML include treatment with immunosuppressant therapies and impairment of immune function. In immunosuppressed patients, physicians should consider PML in the differential diagnosis in patients reporting neurological symptoms and consultation with a neurologist should be considered as clinically indicated. Consideration should be given to reducing the amount of immunosuppression in patients who develop PML. In transplant patients, physicians should also consider the risk that reduced immunosuppression represents to the graft.



    5.11 Interstitial Lung Disease/Non-Infectious Pneumonitis



  Cases of interstitial lung disease [ILD] (including pneumonitis, bronchiolitis obliterans organizing pneumonia [BOOP], and pulmonary fibrosis), some fatal, with no identified infectious etiology have occurred in patients receiving immunosuppressive regimens including Rapamune. In some cases, the ILD was associated with pulmonary hypertension (including pulmonary arterial hypertension [PAH]). In some cases, the ILD has resolved upon discontinuation or dose reduction of Rapamune. The risk may be increased as the trough sirolimus concentration increases [see Adverse Reactions (     6.7     )  ].



    5.12 De Novo  Use Without Cyclosporine



  The safety and efficacy of de novo  use of Rapamune without cyclosporine is not established in renal transplant patients. In a multicenter clinical study, de novo  renal transplant patients treated with Rapamune, mycophenolate mofetil (MMF), steroids, and an IL-2 receptor antagonist had significantly higher acute rejection rates and numerically higher death rates compared to patients treated with cyclosporine, MMF, steroids, and IL-2 receptor antagonist. A benefit, in terms of better renal function, was not apparent in the treatment arm with de novo  use of Rapamune without cyclosporine. These findings were also observed in a similar treatment group of another clinical trial.



    5.13 Increased Risk of Calcineurin Inhibitor-Induced Hemolytic Uremic Syndrome/Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura/Thrombotic Microangiopathy (HUS/TTP/TMA)



  The concomitant use of Rapamune with a calcineurin inhibitor may increase the risk of calcineurin inhibitor-induced hemolytic uremic syndrome/thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura/thrombotic microangiopathy (HUS/TTP/TMA) [see Adverse Reactions (     6.7     )  ].



    5.14 Antimicrobial Prophylaxis



  Cases of Pneumocystis carinii  pneumonia have been reported in transplant patients not receiving antimicrobial prophylaxis. Therefore, antimicrobial prophylaxis for Pneumocystis carinii  pneumonia should be administered for 1 year following transplantation.



 Cytomegalovirus (CMV) prophylaxis is recommended for 3 months after transplantation, particularly for patients at increased risk for CMV disease.



    5.15 Different Sirolimus Trough Concentration Reported between Chromatographic and Immunoassay Methodologies



  Currently in clinical practice, sirolimus whole blood concentrations are being measured by various chromatographic and immunoassay methodologies. Patient sample concentration values from different assays may not be interchangeable [see Dosage and Administration (     2.5     )  ].



    5.16 Skin Cancer Events



  Patients on immunosuppressive therapy are at increased risk for skin cancer. Exposure to sunlight and ultraviolet (UV) light should be limited by wearing protective clothing and using a sunscreen with a high protection factor.



    5.17 Interaction with Strong Inhibitors and Inducers of CYP3A4 and/or P-gp



  Co-administration of Rapamune with strong inhibitors of CYP3A4 and/or P-gp (such as ketoconazole, voriconazole, itraconazole, erythromycin, telithromycin, or clarithromycin) or strong inducers of CYP3A4 and/or P-gp (such as rifampin or rifabutin) is not recommended [see Drug Interactions (     7     )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
