<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rayaldee" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following important adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *    Hypercalcemia [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *    Adynamic Bone Disease [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3% and more frequent than placebo) were anemia, nasopharyngitis, increased blood creatinine, dyspnea, congestive heart failure and constipation. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact OPKO Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-844-729-2539 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The data in  Table 1  are derived from two pivotal studies described below [  See Clinical Studies (  14  )  ]. These data reflect exposure of 285 subjects to RAYALDEE 30 or 60 mcg daily for up to 6 months (mean 24 weeks, range 1 to 31 weeks). The mean age of the study population was 66 years old (range 25-85 years). Half of the subjects were male, 65% were White, and 32% were African-American or Black. At baseline, subjects had secondary hyperparathyroidism, stage 3 (52%) or 4 (48%) chronic kidney disease without macroalbuminuria and serum total 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels less than 30 ng/mL. The most common causes of chronic kidney disease were diabetes and hypertension and the mean estimated GFR at baseline was 31 mL/min/1.73m  2  . At baseline, mean plasma intact PTH was 148 pg/mL, mean serum calcium was 9.2 mg/dL, mean serum phosphorus was 3.7 mg/dL and mean serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D was 20 ng/mL.



   Table 1  shows common adverse reactions associated with the use of RAYALDEE in the pooled placebo-controlled trials. These adverse reactions were not present at baseline, occurred more commonly on RAYALDEE than on placebo, and occurred in at least 1.4% of patients treated with RAYALDEE.



 Table 1. Common Adverse Reactions in Placebo-controlled Trials Reported in &gt;=1.4% of RAYALDEE-Treated Subjects 
   Adverse Reaction                                     Placebo              N=144      RAYALDEE    N=285     
  
                                                       %                 %                 
  Anemia                                               3.5               4.9               
  Nasopharyngitis                                      2.8               4.9               
  Blood creatinine increased                           1.4               4.9               
  Dyspnea                                              2.8               4.2               
  Cough                                                2.1               3.5               
  Cardiac failure congestive                           0.7               3.5               
  Constipation                                         2.8               3.2               
  Bronchitis                                           0.7               2.8               
  Hyperkalemia                                         0.7               2.5               
  Osteoarthritis                                       0.7               2.1               
  Hyperuricemia                                        0.7               1.8               
  Contusion                                            0.0               1.8               
  Pneumonia                                            0.7               1.4               
  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease                0.0               1.4               
           Increase in Serum Calcium  
 

 Patients randomized to RAYALDEE experienced a greater mean (SE) increase in serum calcium (P&lt;0.001) than patients randomized to placebo [i.e., 0.2 (0.02) mg/dL on RAYALDEE versus 0.1 (0.03) mg/dL on placebo from baseline to trial end]. Six subjects (2%) in the RAYALDEE treatment group and no subjects (0%) in the placebo group required dose reductions for protocol-defined hypercalcemia (two consecutive serum calcium values greater than 10.3 mg/dL). A total of 4.2% of RAYALDEE treated subjects and 2.1% of placebo treated subjects experienced at least 1 elevation in serum calcium above the upper limit of normal (10.5 mg/dL).



   Increase in Serum Phosphorus  



 Patients randomized to RAYALDEE experienced a greater mean (SE) increase in serum phosphorus than patients randomized to placebo [i.e., 0.2 (0.03) mg/dL on RAYALDEE versus 0.1 (0.04) mg/dL on placebo from baseline to trial end]. One subject (0.4%) in the RAYALDEE treatment group met protocol-defined hyperphosphatemia (two consecutive serum phosphorus values &gt;5.5 mg/dL deemed to be study drug related) compared to no subjects in the placebo group. A total of 45% of RAYALDEE treated subjects and 44% of placebo treated subjects experienced at least one elevation in serum phosphorus above the upper limit of normal (4.5 mg/dL).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Hypercalcemia: Excessive administration of vitamin D compounds, including RAYALDEE , can cause hypercalcemia and hypercalciuria. Severe hypercalcemia due to substantial overdosage of vitamin D and its metabolites may require emergency attention. Patients should be informed about the symptoms of elevated calcium. (  5.1  ) 
 *     Digitalis toxicity: Potentiated by hypercalcemia of any cause. Monitor serum calcium and signs and symptoms of digitalis toxicity more frequently when initiating or adjusting the dose of RAYALDEE . (  5.2  ) 
 *     Adynamic Bone Disease: Monitor for abnormally low levels of intact PTH levels when using RAYALDEE , and adjust dose if needed. (  2.2  ,  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypercalcemia



  Hypercalcemia may occur during RAYALDEE treatment [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. Acute hypercalcemia may increase the risk of cardiac arrhythmias and seizures and may potentiate the effect of digitalis on the heart [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ]. Chronic hypercalcemia can lead to generalized vascular calcification and other soft-tissue calcification. Severe hypercalcemia may require emergency attention.



 Hypercalcemia may be exacerbated by concomitant administration of high doses of calcium containing preparations, thiazide diuretics, or other vitamin D compounds. In addition, high intake of calcium and phosphate concomitantly with vitamin D compounds may lead to hypercalciuria and hyperphosphatemia. In these circumstances, frequent serum calcium monitoring and RAYALDEE dose adjustments may be required. Patients with a history of hypercalcemia prior to initiating therapy with RAYALDEE should be monitored more frequently for possible hypercalcemia during therapy.



 Patients should be informed about the symptoms of elevated serum calcium, which include feeling tired, difficulty thinking clearly, loss of appetite, nausea, vomiting, constipation, increased thirst, increased urination, and weight loss.



    5.2 Digitalis Toxicity



  Hypercalcemia of any cause, including RAYALDEE [ See Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ], increases the risk of digitalis toxicity. In patients using RAYALDEE concomitantly with digitalis compounds, monitor both serum calcium and patients for signs and symptoms of digitalis toxicity and increase the frequency of monitoring when initiating or adjusting the dose of RAYALDEE [ see Dosage and Administration (  2  )  ].



    5.3 Adynamic Bone Disease



  Adynamic bone disease with subsequent increased risk of fractures may develop if intact PTH levels are suppressed by RAYALDEE to abnormally low levels. Monitor intact PTH levels and adjust RAYALDEE dose, if needed [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
