<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rebetol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinical trials with REBETOL in combination with PegIntron or INTRON A have been conducted in over 7800 subjects from 3 to 76 years of age.



 The primary toxicity of ribavirin is hemolytic anemia. Reductions in hemoglobin levels occurred within the first 1 to 2 weeks of oral therapy. Cardiac and pulmonary reactions associated with anemia occurred in approximately 10% of patients  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  



 Greater than 96% of all subjects in clinical trials experienced one or more adverse reactions. The most commonly reported adverse reactions in adult subjects receiving PegIntron or INTRON A in combination with REBETOL were injection site inflammation/reaction, fatigue/asthenia, headache, rigors, fevers, nausea, myalgia and anxiety/emotional lability/irritability. The most common adverse reactions in pediatric subjects, ages 3 and older, receiving REBETOL in combination with PegIntron or INTRON A were pyrexia, headache, neutropenia, fatigue, anorexia, injection site erythema, and vomiting.



 The Adverse Reactions section references the following clinical trials:



 *  *  Clinical Study 1 - evaluated PegIntron monotherapy (not further described in this label; see labeling for PegIntron for information about this trial). 
 *  Study 2 - evaluated REBETOL 800 mg/day flat dose in combination with 1.5 mcg/kg/week PegIntron or with INTRON A. 
 *  Study 3 - evaluated PegIntron/weight-based REBETOL in combination with PegIntron/flat dose REBETOL regimen. 
 *  Study 4 - compared two PegIntron (1.5 mcg/kg/week and 1 mcg/kg/week) doses in combination with REBETOL and a third treatment group receiving Pegasys  (r)  (180 mcg/week)/Copegus  (r)  (1000-1200 mg/day). 
 *  Study 5 - evaluated PegIntron (1.5 mcg/kg/week) in combination with weight-based REBETOL in prior treatment failure subjects. 
   REBETOL/PegIntron Combination therapy trials: 
 *  PegIntron/REBETOL Combination Therapy in Pediatric Patients 
 *  REBETOL/INTRON A Combination Therapy trials for adults and pediatrics 
    Serious adverse reactions have occurred in approximately 12% of subjects in clinical trials with PegIntron with or without REBETOL  [see  BOXED WARNING  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5)  ].  The most common serious events occurring in subjects treated with PegIntron and REBETOL were depression and suicidal ideation  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ],  each occurring at a frequency of less than 1%. Suicidal ideation or attempts occurred more frequently among pediatric patients, primarily adolescents, compared to adult patients (2.4% versus 1%) during treatment and off-therapy follow-up  [  see    Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ].  The most common fatal reaction occurring in subjects treated with PegIntron and REBETOL was cardiac arrest, suicide ideation, and suicide attempt  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ],  all occurring in less than 1% of subjects.
 

 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   EXCERPT:   Hemolytic anemia. (  6.1  )



 Most common adverse reactions (approximately 40%) in adult patients receiving REBETOL/PegIntron or INTRON A combination therapy are injection site reaction, fatigue/asthenia, headache, rigors, fevers, nausea, myalgia and anxiety/emotional lability/irritability. (  6.1  ,  6.2  ) Most common adverse reactions (greater than 25%) in pediatric patients receiving REBETOL/PegIntron therapy are: pyrexia, headache, neutropenia, fatigue, anorexia, injection site erythema, and vomiting. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co. Inc. at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience - REBETOL/PegIntron Combination Therapy

    Adult Subjects  



 Adverse reactions that occurred in the clinical trial at greater than 5% incidence are provided by treatment group from the REBETOL/PegIntron Combination Therapy (Study 2) in    Table 5    .



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions Occurring in Greater Than 5% of Adult Subjects 
 Adverse Reactions       Percentage of Subjects Reporting Adverse Reactions    Adverse Reactions    Percentage of Subjects Reporting Adverse Reactions     
 PegIntron1.5 mcg/kg/ REBETOL(N=511)  INTRON A/REBETOL (N=505)  PegIntron1.5 mcg/kg/ REBETOL(N=511)  INTRON A/REBETOL (N=505)   
  
   Application Site                       Musculoskeletal                           
   Injection Site Inflammation        25               18           Myalgia                   56               50          
   Injection Site Reaction        58               36           Arthralgia                34               28          
   Autonomic Nervous System                       Musculoskeletal Pain  21                          19          
   Dry Mouth                 12                8           Psychiatric                           
   Increased Sweating        11                7           Insomnia                  40               41          
   Flushing                   4                3           Depression                31               34          
   Body as a Whole                        Anxiety/Emotional Lability/Irritability  47                          47          
   Fatigue/Asthenia          66               63           Concentration Impaired        17               21          
   Headache                  62               58           Agitation                  8                5          
   Rigors                    48               41           Nervousness                6                6          
   Fever                     46               33           Reproductive, Female                      
   Weight Loss               29               20           Menstrual Disorder         7                6          
   Right Upper Quadrant Pain        12                6           Resistance Mechanism                      
   Chest Pain                 8                7           Viral Infection           12               12          
   Malaise                    4                6           Fungal Infection           6                1          
   Central/Peripheral Nervous System        Respiratory System                      
   Dizziness                 21               17           Dyspnea                   26               24          
   Endocrine                                Coughing     23                          16          
   Hypothyroidism             5                4           Pharyngitis               12               13          
   Gastrointestinal                         Rhinitis     8                            6          
   Nausea                    43               33           Sinusitis                  6                5          
   Anorexia                  32               27           Skin and Appendages                      
   Diarrhea                  22               17           Alopecia                  36               32          
   Vomiting                  14               12           Pruritus                  29               28          
   Abdominal Pain            13               13           Rash                      24               23          
   Dyspepsia                  9                8           Skin Dry                  24               23          
   Constipation               5                5           Special Senses, Other                      
   Hematologic Disorders                       Taste Perversion  9                            4          
   Neutropenia               26               14           Vision Disorders                                       
   Anemia                    12               17           Vision Blurred             5                6          
   Leukopenia                 6                5           Conjunctivitis             4                5          
   Thrombocytopenia           5                2                                
   Liver and Biliary System                      
   Hepatomegaly               4                4          
                Table 6    summarizes the treatment-related adverse reactions in Study 4 that occurred at a greater than or equal to 10% incidence.
 

 Table 6: Treatment-Related Adverse Reactions (Greater Than or Equal to 10% Incidence) By Descending Frequency 
                            Study 4  Percentage of Subjects Reporting Treatment-Related Adverse Reactions     
 Adverse Reactions          PegIntron 1.5 mcg/kg with REBETOL  PegIntron 1 mcg/kg with REBETOL  Pegasys 180 mcg with Copegus   
                                    (N=1019)                   (N=1016)                   (N=1035)            
  
 Fatigue                               67                         68                         64               
 Headache                              50                         47                         41               
 Nausea                                40                         35                         34               
 Chills                                39                         36                         23               
 Insomnia                              38                         37                         41               
 Anemia                                35                         30                         34               
 Pyrexia                               35                         32                         21               
 Injection Site Reactions              34                         35                         23               
 Anorexia                              29                         25                         21               
 Rash                                  29                         25                         34               
 Myalgia                               27                         26                         22               
 Neutropenia                           26                         19                         31               
 Irritability                          25                         25                         25               
 Depression                            25                         19                         20               
 Alopecia                              23                         20                         17               
 Dyspnea                               21                         20                         22               
 Arthralgia                            21                         22                         22               
 Pruritus                              18                         15                         19               
 Influenza-like Illness                16                         15                         15               
 Dizziness                             16                         14                         13               
 Diarrhea                              15                         16                         14               
 Cough                                 15                         16                         17               
 Weight Decreased                      13                         10                         10               
 Vomiting                              12                         10                          9               
 Unspecified Pain                      12                         13                          9               
 Dry Skin                              11                         11                         12               
 Anxiety                               11                         11                         10               
 Abdominal Pain                        10                         10                         10               
 Leukopenia                             9                          7                         10               
          The incidence of serious adverse reactions was comparable in all trials. In Study 3, there was a similar incidence of serious adverse reactions reported for the weight-based REBETOL group (12%) and for the flat-dose REBETOL regimen. In Study 2, the incidence of serious adverse reactions was 17% in the PegIntron/REBETOL groups compared to 14% in the INTRON A/REBETOL group.
 

 In many but not all cases, adverse reactions resolved after dose reduction or discontinuation of therapy. Some subjects experienced ongoing or new serious adverse reactions during the 6-month follow-up period. In Study 2, many subjects continued to experience adverse reactions several months after discontinuation of therapy. By the end of the 6-month follow-up period, the incidence of ongoing adverse reactions by body class in the PegIntron 1.5/REBETOL group was 33% (psychiatric), 20% (musculoskeletal), and 10% (for endocrine and for GI). In approximately 10 to 15% of subjects, weight loss, fatigue, and headache had not resolved.



 There have been 31 subject deaths that occurred during treatment or during follow-up in these clinical trials. In Study 1, there was 1 suicide in a subject receiving PegIntron monotherapy and 2 deaths among subjects receiving INTRON A monotherapy (1 murder/suicide and 1 sudden death). In Study 2, there was 1 suicide in a subject receiving PegIntron/REBETOL combination therapy; and 1 subject death in the INTRON A/REBETOL group (motor vehicle accident). In Study 3, there were 14 deaths, 2 of which were probable suicides and 1 was an unexplained death in a person with a relevant medical history of depression. In Study 4, there were 12 deaths, 6 of which occurred in subjects who received PegIntron/REBETOL combination therapy, 5 in the PegIntron 1.5 mcg/REBETOL arm (N=1019) and 1 in the PegIntron 1 mcg/REBETOL arm (N=1016), and 6 of which occurred in subjects receiving Pegasys/Copegus (N=1035); there were 3 suicides that occurred during the off treatment follow-up period in subjects who received PegIntron (1.5 mcg/kg)/REBETOL combination therapy.



 In Studies 1 and 2, 10 to 14% of subjects receiving PegIntron, alone or in combination with REBETOL, discontinued therapy compared with 6% treated with INTRON A alone and 13% treated with INTRON A in combination with REBETOL. Similarly in Study 3, 15% of subjects receiving PegIntron in combination with weight-based REBETOL and 14% of subjects receiving PegIntron and flat dose REBETOL discontinued therapy due to an adverse reaction. The most common reasons for discontinuation of therapy were related to known interferon effects of psychiatric, systemic (e.g., fatigue, headache), or gastrointestinal adverse reactions. In Study 4, 13% of subjects in the PegIntron 1.5 mcg/REBETOL arm, 10% in the PegIntron 1 mcg/REBETOL arm and 13% in the Pegasys 180 mcg/Copegus arm discontinued due to adverse events.



 In Study 2, dose reductions due to adverse reactions occurred in 42% of subjects receiving PegIntron (1.5 mcg/kg)/REBETOL and in 34% of those receiving INTRON A/REBETOL. The majority of subjects (57%) weighing 60 kg or less receiving PegIntron (1.5 mcg/kg)/REBETOL required dose reduction. Reduction of interferon was dose-related (PegIntron 1.5 mcg/kg greater than PegIntron 0.5 mcg/kg or INTRON A), 40%, 27%, 28%, respectively. Dose reduction for REBETOL was similar across all three groups, 33 to 35%. The most common reasons for dose modifications were neutropenia (18%), or anemia (9%)  (see    Laboratory Values    ).  Other common reasons included depression, fatigue, nausea, and thrombocytopenia. In Study 3, dose modifications due to adverse reactions occurred more frequently with weight-based dosing (WBD) compared to flat dosing (29% and 23%, respectively). In Study 4, 16% of subjects had a dose reduction of PegIntron to 1 mcg/kg in combination with REBETOL, with an additional 4% requiring the second dose reduction of PegIntron to 0.5 mcg/kg due to adverse events compared to 15% of subjects in the Pegasys/Copegus arm, who required a dose reduction to 135 mcg/week with Pegasys, with an additional 7% in the Pegasys/Copegus arm requiring second dose reduction to 90 mcg/week with Pegasys.



 In the PegIntron/REBETOL combination trials the most common adverse reactions were psychiatric, which occurred among 77% of subjects in Study 2 and 68% to 69% of subjects in Study 3. These psychiatric adverse reactions included most commonly depression, irritability, and insomnia, each reported by approximately 30% to 40% of subjects in all treatment groups. Suicidal behavior (ideation, attempts, and suicides) occurred in 2% of all subjects during treatment or during follow-up after treatment cessation  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5)  ]  . In Study 4, psychiatric adverse reactions occurred in 58% of subjects in the PegIntron 1.5 mcg/REBETOL arm, 55% of subjects in the PegIntron 1 mcg/REBETOL arm, and 57% of subjects in the Pegasys 180 mcg/Copegus arm.



 PegIntron induced fatigue or headache in approximately two-thirds of subjects, with fever or rigors in approximately half of the subjects. The severity of some of these systemic symptoms (e.g., fever and headache) tended to decrease as treatment continued. In Studies 1 and 2, application site inflammation and reaction (e.g., bruise, itchiness, and irritation) occurred at approximately twice the incidence with PegIntron therapies (in up to 75% of subjects) compared with INTRON A. However, injection site pain was infrequent (2 to 3%) in all groups. In Study 3, there was a 23% to 24% incidence overall for injection site reactions or inflammation.



 Subjects receiving REBETOL/PegIntron as re-treatment after failing a previous interferon combination regimen reported adverse reactions similar to those previously associated with this regimen during clinical trials of treatment-naive subjects.



     Pediatric Subjects  



 In general, the adverse-reaction profile in the pediatric population was similar to that observed in adults. In the pediatric trial, the most prevalent adverse reactions in all subjects were pyrexia (80%), headache (62%), neutropenia (33%), fatigue (30%), anorexia (29%), injection-site erythema (29%) and vomiting (27%). The majority of adverse reactions reported in the trial were mild or moderate in severity. Severe adverse reactions were reported in 7% (8/107) of all subjects and included injection site pain (1%), pain in extremity (1%), headache (1%), neutropenia (1%), and pyrexia (4%). Important adverse reactions that occurred in this subject population were nervousness (7%; 7/107), aggression (3%; 3/107), anger (2%; 2/107), and depression (1%; 1/107). Five subjects received levothyroxine treatment, three with clinical hypothyroidism and two with asymptomatic TSH elevations. Weight and height gain of pediatric subjects treated with PegIntron plus REBETOL lagged behind that predicted by normative population data for the entire length of treatment. Severely inhibited growth velocity (less than 3rd percentile) was observed in 70% of the subjects while on treatment.



 Dose modifications of PegIntron and/or ribavirin were required in 25% of subjects due to treatment-related adverse reactions, most commonly for anemia, neutropenia and weight loss. Two subjects (2%; 2/107) discontinued therapy as the result of an adverse reaction.



 Adverse reactions that occurred with a greater than or equal to 10% incidence in the pediatric trial subjects are provided in    Table 7    .



 Table 7: Percentage of Pediatric Subjects with Treatment-Related Adverse Reactions (in At Least 10% of All Subjects) 
 System Organ Class  Preferred Term                                 All Subjects(N=107)                   
  
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders               
   Neutropenia                                                              33%                           
   Anemia                                                                   11%                           
   Leukopenia                                                               10%                           
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                         
   Abdominal Pain                                                           21%                           
   Abdominal Pain Upper                                                     12%                           
   Vomiting                                                                 27%                           
   Nausea                                                                   18%                           
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions     
   Pyrexia                                                                  80%                           
   Fatigue                                                                  30%                           
   Injection-site Erythema                                                  29%                           
   Chills                                                                   21%                           
   Asthenia                                                                 15%                           
   Irritability                                                             14%                           
   Investigations                                     
   Weight Loss                                                              19%                           
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                 
   Anorexia                                                                 29%                           
   Decreased Appetite                                                       22%                           
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
   Arthralgia                                                               17%                           
   Myalgia                                                                  17%                           
   Nervous System Disorders                           
   Headache                                                                 62%                           
   Dizziness                                                                14%                           
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders             
   Alopecia                                                                 17%                           
        Ninety-four of 107 subjects enrolled in a 5 year long-term follow-up trial. The long-term effects on growth were less in those subjects treated for 24 weeks than those treated for 48 weeks. Twenty-four percent of subjects (11/46) treated for 24 weeks and 40% of subjects (19/48) treated for 48 weeks had a &gt;15 percentile height-for-age decrease from pre-treatment to the end of 5 year long-term follow-up compared to pre-treatment baseline percentiles. Eleven percent of subjects (5/46) treated for 24 weeks and 13% of subjects (6/48) treated for 48 weeks were observed to have a decrease from pre-treatment baseline of &gt;30 height-for-age percentiles to the end of the 5 year long-term follow-up. While observed across all age groups, the highest risk for reduced height at the end of long-term follow-up appeared to correlate with initiation of combination therapy during the years of expected peak growth velocity.  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  .]  
 

     Laboratory Values  



     Adult and Pediatric Subjects  



 The adverse reaction profile in Study 3, which compared PegIntron/weight-based REBETOL combination to a PegIntron/flat dose REBETOL regimen, revealed an increased rate of anemia with weight-based dosing (29% vs. 19% for weight-based vs. flat dose regimens, respectively). However, the majority of cases of anemia were mild and responded to dose reductions.



 Changes in selected laboratory values during treatment in combination with REBETOL treatment are described below.  Decreases in hemoglobin, leukocytes, neutrophils, and platelets may require dose reduction or permanent discontinuation from therapy    [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  . Changes in selected laboratory values during therapy are described in    Table 8    . Most of the changes in laboratory values in the PegIntron/REBETOL trial with pediatrics were mild or moderate.



 Table 8: Selected Laboratory Abnormalities During Treatment with REBETOL and PegIntron or REBETOL and INTRON A in Previously Untreated Subjects 
 Laboratory Parameters           Percentage of Subjects   
 Adults (Study 2)                     Pediatrics        
 PegIntron/ REBETOL(N=511)       INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=505)  PegIntron/ REBETOL(N=107)   
  
   Hemoglobin (g/dL)              
   9.5 to &lt;11.0                           26                    27                         30                 
   8.0 to &lt;9.5                            3                     3                          2                  
   6.5-7.9                               0.2                   0.2                         -                  
   Leukocytes (* 10  9  /L)       
   2.0-2.9                                46                    41                         39                 
   1.5 to &lt;2.0                            24                    8                          3                  
   1.0-1.4                                5                     1                          -                  
   Neutrophils (* 10  9  /L)      
   1.0-1.5                                33                    37                         35                 
   0.75 to &lt;1.0                           25                    13                         26                 
   0.5 to &lt;0.75                           18                    7                          13                 
   &lt;0.5                                   4                     2                          3                  
   Platelets (* 10  9  /L)        
   70-100                                 15                    5                          1                  
   50 to &lt;70                              3                    0.8                         -                  
   30-49                                 0.2                   0.2                         -                  
   25 to &lt;50                              -                     -                          1                  
   Total Bilirubin                     (mg/dL)              (umole/L)         
   1.5-3.0                                10                    13                         -                  
   1.26-2.59 * ULN                        -                     -                          7                  
   3.1-6.0                               0.6                   0.2                         -                  
   2.6-5 * ULN                            -                     -                          -                  
   6.1-12.0                               0                    0.2                         -                  
   ALT (U/L)                      
   2 * Baseline                          0.6                   0.2                         1                  
   2.1-5 * Baseline                       3                     1                          5                  
   5.1-10 * Baseline                      0                     0                          3                  
              Hemoglobin  . Hemoglobin levels decreased to less than 11 g/dL in about 30% of subjects in Study 2. In Study 3, 47% of subjects receiving WBD REBETOL and 33% on flat-dose REBETOL had decreases in hemoglobin levels less than 11 g/dl. Reductions in hemoglobin to less than 9 g/dL occurred more frequently in subjects receiving WBD compared to flat dosing (4% and 2%, respectively). In Study 2, dose modification was required in 9% and 13% of subjects in the PegIntron/REBETOL and INTRON A/REBETOL groups. In Study 4, subjects receiving PegIntron (1.5 mcg/kg)/REBETOL had decreases in hemoglobin levels to between 8.5 to less than 10 g/dL (28%) and to less than 8.5 g/dL (3%), whereas in patients receiving Pegasys 180 mcg/Copegus these decreases occurred in 26% and 4% of subjects respectively. Hemoglobin levels became stable by treatment Weeks 4-6 on average. The typical pattern observed was a decrease in hemoglobin levels by treatment Week 4 followed by stabilization and a plateau, which was maintained to the end of treatment. In the PegIntron monotherapy trial, hemoglobin decreases were generally mild and dose modifications were rarely necessary  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ].  
 

     Neutrophils  . Decreases in neutrophil counts were observed in a majority of adult subjects treated with combination therapy with REBETOL in Study 2 (85%) and INTRON A/REBETOL (60%). Severe potentially life-threatening neutropenia (less than 0.5 * 10  9  /L) occurred in 2% of subjects treated with INTRON A/REBETOL and in approximately 4% of subjects treated with PegIntron/REBETOL in Study 2. Eighteen percent of subjects receiving PegIntron/REBETOL in Study 2 required modification of interferon dosage. Few subjects (less than 1%) required permanent discontinuation of treatment. Neutrophil counts generally returned to pre-treatment levels 4 weeks after cessation of therapy  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



     Platelets  . Platelet counts decreased to less than 100,000/mm  3  in approximately 20% of subjects treated with PegIntron alone or with REBETOL and in 6% of adult subjects treated with INTRON A/REBETOL. Severe decreases in platelet counts (less than 50,000/mm  3  ) occur in less than 4% of adult subjects. Patients may require discontinuation or dose modification as a result of platelet decreases  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  . In Study 2, 1% or 3% of subjects required dose modification of INTRON A or PegIntron, respectively. Platelet counts generally returned to pretreatment levels 4 weeks after the cessation of therapy.



     Thyroid Function  . Development of TSH abnormalities, with or without clinical manifestations, is associated with interferon therapies. In Study 2, clinically apparent thyroid disorders occurred among subjects treated with either INTRON A or PegIntron (with or without REBETOL) at a similar incidence (5% for hypothyroidism and 3% for hyperthyroidism). Subjects developed new onset TSH abnormalities while on treatment and during the follow-up period. At the end of the follow-up period 7% of subjects still had abnormal TSH values.



     Bilirubin and uric acid  . In Study 2, 10 to 14% of subjects developed hyperbilirubinemia and 33 to 38% developed hyperuricemia in association with hemolysis. Six subjects developed mild to moderate gout.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience - REBETOL/INTRON A Combination Therapy

    Adult Subjects  



 In clinical trials, 19% and 6% of previously untreated and relapse subjects, respectively, discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions in the combination arms compared to 13% and 3% in the interferon arms. Selected treatment-related adverse reactions that occurred in the US trials with greater than or equal to 5% incidence are provided by treatment group (see    Table 9    ). In general, the selected treatment-related adverse reactions were reported with lower incidence in the international trials as compared to the US trials, with the exception of asthenia, influenza-like symptoms, nervousness, and pruritus.



     Pediatric Subjects  



 In clinical trials of 118 pediatric subjects 3 to 16 years of age, 6% discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions. Dose modifications were required in 30% of subjects, most commonly for anemia and neutropenia. In general, the adverse-reaction profile in the pediatric population was similar to that observed in adults. Injection site disorders, fever, anorexia, vomiting, and emotional lability occurred more frequently in pediatric subjects compared to adult subjects. Conversely, pediatric subjects experienced less fatigue, dyspepsia, arthralgia, insomnia, irritability, impaired concentration, dyspnea, and pruritus compared to adult subjects. Selected treatment-related adverse reactions that occurred with greater than or equal to 5% incidence among all pediatric subjects who received the recommended dose of REBETOL/INTRON A combination therapy are provided in    Table 9    .



 Table 9: Selected Treatment-Related Adverse Reactions: Previously Untreated and Relapse Adult Subjects and Previously Untreated Pediatric Subjects 
 Subjects Reporting Adverse Reactions  Percentage of Subjects   
 US Previously Untreated Study  US Relapse Study  Pediatric Subjects   
 24 weeks of treatment  48 weeks of treatment  24 weeks of treatment  48 weeks of treatment   
 INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=228)  INTRON A/ Placebo(N=231)  INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=228)  INTRON A/ Placebo(N=225)  INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=77)  INTRON A/ Placebo(N=76)  INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=118)   
  
   Application Site Disorders     
   Injection Site Inflammation       13            10            12            14            6             8             14        
   Injection Site Reaction       7             9             8             9             5             3             19        
   Body as a Whole - General Disorders     
   Headache             63            63            66            67            66            68            69        
   Fatigue              68            62            70            72            60            53            58        
   Rigors               40            32            42            39            43            37            25        
   Fever                37            35            41            40            32            36            61        
   Influenza-like Symptoms       14            18            18            20            13            13            31        
   Asthenia             9             4             9             9             10            4             5         
   Chest Pain           5             4             9             8             6             7             5         
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders     
   Dizziness            17            15            23            19            26            21            20        
   Gastrointestinal System Disorders     
   Nausea               38            35            46            33            47            33            33        
   Anorexia             27            16            25            19            21            14            51        
   Dyspepsia            14            6             16            9             16            9             &lt;1        
   Vomiting             11            10            9             13            12            8             42        
   Musculoskeletal System Disorders     
   Myalgia              61            57            64            63            61            58            32        
   Arthralgia           30            27            33            36            29            29            15        
   Musculoskeletal Pain       20            26            28            32            22            28            21        
   Psychiatric Disorders     
   Insomnia             39            27            39            30            26            25            14        
   Irritability         23            19            32            27            25            20            10        
   Depression           32            25            36            37            23            14            13        
   Emotional Lability       7             6             11            8             12            8             16        
   Concentration Impaired       11            14            14            14            10            12            5         
   Nervousness          4             2             4             4             5             4             3         
   Respiratory System Disorders     
   Dyspnea              19            9             18            10            17            12            5         
   Sinusitis            9             7             10            14            12            7             &lt;1        
   Skin and Appendages Disorders     
   Alopecia             28            27            32            28            27            26            23        
   Rash                 20            9             28            8             21            5             17        
   Pruritus             21            9             19            8             13            4             12        
   Special Senses, Other Disorders     
   Taste Perversion       7             4             8             4             6             5             &lt;1        
              During a 48-week course of therapy there was a decrease in the rate of linear growth (mean percentile assignment decrease of 7%) and a decrease in the rate of weight gain (mean percentile assignment decrease of 9%). A general reversal of these trends was noted during the 24-week post-treatment period. Long-term data in a limited number of patients, however, suggests that combination therapy may induce a growth inhibition that results in reduced final adult height in some patients  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ].  
 

     Laboratory Values  



 Changes in selected hematologic values (hemoglobin, white blood cells, neutrophils, and platelets) during therapy are described below (see    Table 10  )  .



     Hemoglobin  . Hemoglobin decreases among subjects receiving REBETOL therapy began at Week 1, with stabilization by Week 4. In previously untreated subjects treated for 48 weeks, the mean maximum decrease from baseline was 3.1 g/dL in the US trial and 2.9 g/dL in the international trial. In relapse subjects, the mean maximum decrease from baseline was 2.8 g/dL in the US trial and 2.6 g/dL in the international trial. Hemoglobin values returned to pretreatment levels within 4 to 8 weeks of cessation of therapy in most subjects.



     Bilirubin and Uric Acid  . Increases in both bilirubin and uric acid, associated with hemolysis, were noted in clinical trials. Most were moderate biochemical changes and were reversed within 4 weeks after treatment discontinuation. This observation occurred most frequently in subjects with a previous diagnosis of Gilbert's syndrome. This has not been associated with hepatic dysfunction or clinical morbidity.



 Table 10: Selected Laboratory Abnormalities During Treatment With REBETOL and INTRON A: Previously Untreated and Relapse Adult Subjects and Previously Untreated Pediatric Subjects 
                     Percentage of Subjects   
 US Previously Untreated Study  US Relapse Study  Pediatric Subjects   
 24 weeks of treatment  48 weeks of treatment  24 weeks of treatment  48 weeks of treatment   
 INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=228)  INTRON A/ Placebo(N=231)  INTRON A/REBETOL(N=228)  INTRON A/ Placebo(N=225)  INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=77)  INTRON A/ Placebo(N=76)  INTRON A/ REBETOL(N=118)   
  
   Hemoglobin (g/dL)                   
   9.5 to 10.9            24            1             32            1             21            3           24        
   8.0 to 9.4             5             0             4             0             4             0            3        
   6.5 to 7.9             0             0             0            0.4            0             0            0        
   &lt;6.5                   0             0             0             0             0             0            0        
   Leukocytes (* 10  9  /L)                   
   2.0 to 2.9             40            20            38            23            45           26           35        
   1.5 to 1.9             4             1             9             2             5             3            8        
   1.0 to 1.4            0.9            0             2             0             0             0            0        
   &lt;1.0                   0             0             0             0             0             0            0        
   Neutrophils (* 10  9  /L)                   
   1.0 to 1.49            30            32            31            44            42           34           37        
   0.75 to 0.99           14            15            14            11            16           18           15        
   0.5 to 0.74            9             9             14            7             8             4           16        
   &lt;0.5                   11            8             11            5             5             8            3        
   Platelets (* 10  9  /L)                   
   70 to 99               9             11            11            14            6            12           0.8       
   50 to 69               2             3             2             3             0             5            2        
   30 to 49               0            0.4            0            0.4            0             0            0        
   &lt;30                   0.9            0             1            0.9            0             0            0        
   Total Bilirubin (mg/dL)                   
   1.5 to 3.0             27            13            32            13            21            7            2        
   3.1 to 6.0            0.9           0.4            2             0             3             0            0        
   6.1 to 12.0            0             0            0.4            0             0             0            0        
   &gt;12.0                  0             0             0             0             0             0            0        
                6.3 Postmarketing Experiences
   The following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during post approval use of REBETOL in combination with INTRON A or PegIntron. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System disorders  



 *     Pure red cell aplasia, aplastic anemia 
      Ear and Labyrinth disorders  
 

 *     Hearing disorder, vertigo 
      Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal disorders  
 

 *     Pulmonary hypertension 
      Eye disorders  
 

 *     Serous retinal detachment 
      Endocrine disorders  
 

 *     Diabetes 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS DISORDERS AND RIBAVIRIN-ASSOCIATED EFFECTS

    WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS DISORDERS AND RIBAVIRIN-ASSOCIATED EFFECTS  

    *  REBETOL monotherapy is not effective for the treatment of chronic hepatitis C virus infection and should not be used alone for this indication [see Warnings and Precautions (5.10)]. 
 *  The primary toxicity of ribavirin is hemolytic anemia. The anemia associated with REBETOL therapy may result in worsening of cardiac disease that has led to fatal and nonfatal myocardial infarctions. Patients with a history of significant or unstable cardiac disease should not be treated with REBETOL [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Warnings and Precautions (5.2), and Adverse Reactions (6.1)]. 
 *  Significant teratogenic and embryocidal effects have been demonstrated in all animal species exposed to ribavirin. In addition, ribavirin has a multiple-dose half-life of 12 days, and so it may persist in nonplasma compartments for as long as 6 months. Therefore, REBETOL therapy is contraindicated in women who are pregnant and in the male partners of women who are pregnant. Extreme care must be taken to avoid pregnancy during therapy and for 6 months after completion of treatment in both female patients and in female partners of male patients who are taking REBETOL therapy. At least two reliable forms of effective contraception must be utilized during treatment and during the 6-month post-treatment follow-up period [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.1), Use in Specific Populations (8.1), Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1), and Patient Counseling Information (17.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS DISORDERS AND RIBAVIRIN-ASSOCIATED EFFECTS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  REBETOL monotherapy is not effective for the treatment of chronic hepatitis C (5.10). 
 *  The hemolytic anemia associated with REBETOL therapy may result in worsening of cardiac disease that has led to fatal and nonfatal myocardial infarctions. Patients with a history of significant or unstable cardiac disease should not be treated with REBETOL (2.4, 5.2, 6.1). 
 *  Significant teratogenic and embryocidal effects have been demonstrated in all animal species exposed to ribavirin. Therefore, REBETOL therapy is contraindicated in women who are pregnant and in the male partners of women who are pregnant. Extreme care must be taken to avoid pregnancy during therapy and for 6 months after completion of treatment in both female patients and in female partners of male patients who are taking REBETOL therapy (4, 5.1, 8.1, 13.1, 17.2). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  *  Birth defects and fetal death with ribavirin: Patients must have a negative pregnancy test prior to therapy; use at least 2 forms of contraception and undergo monthly pregnancy tests. 
    Pregnancy Category X (  5.1  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ) 
    Patients exhibiting the following conditions should be closely monitored and may require dose reduction or discontinuation of therapy:
 

 *  Monotherapy with ribavirin is not permitted. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Hemolytic anemia may occur with a significant initial drop in hemoglobin. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Pancreatitis. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Pulmonary infiltrates or pulmonary function impairment. (  5.4  ) 
 *  New or worsening ophthalmologic disorders. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Severe decreases in neutrophil and platelet counts, and hematologic, endocrine (e.g., TSH), and hepatic abnormalities. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Dental/periodontal disorders reported with combination therapy. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Concomitant administration of azathioprine. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Weight loss and growth inhibition reported during combination therapy in pediatric patients. Long-term growth inhibition (height) reported in some patients. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Pregnancy



   REBETOL capsules and oral solution may cause birth defects and death of the unborn child. REBETOL therapy should not be started until a report of a negative pregnancy test has been obtained immediately prior to planned initiation of therapy. Patients should use at least two forms of contraception and have monthly pregnancy tests during treatment and during the 6-month period after treatment has been stopped.  Extreme care must be taken to avoid pregnancy in female patients and in female partners of male patients. REBETOL has demonstrated significant teratogenic and embryocidal effects in all animal species in which adequate studies have been conducted. These effects occurred at doses as low as one twentieth of the recommended human dose of ribavirin. REBETOL therapy should not be started until a report of a negative pregnancy test has been obtained immediately prior to planned initiation of therapy [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Contraindications (4)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  , and  Patient Counseling Information (17.2)  ].  



    5.2 Anemia



  The primary toxicity of ribavirin is hemolytic anemia, which was observed in approximately 10% of REBETOL/INTRON A-treated subjects in clinical trials. The anemia associated with REBETOL capsules occurs within 1 to 2 weeks of initiation of therapy. Because the initial drop in hemoglobin may be significant, it is advised that hemoglobin or hematocrit be obtained before the start of treatment and at Week 2 and Week 4 of therapy, or more frequently if clinically indicated. Patients should then be followed as clinically appropriate [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4  ,  2.5)  ].  



 Fatal and nonfatal myocardial infarctions have been reported in patients with anemia caused by REBETOL. Patients should be assessed for underlying cardiac disease before initiation of ribavirin therapy. Patients with pre-existing cardiac disease should have electrocardiograms administered before treatment, and should be appropriately monitored during therapy. If there is any deterioration of cardiovascular status, therapy should be suspended or discontinued [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4  ,  2.5)  ].  Because cardiac disease may be worsened by drug-induced anemia, patients with a history of significant or unstable cardiac disease should not use REBETOL.



    5.3 Pancreatitis



  REBETOL and INTRON A or PegIntron therapy should be suspended in patients with signs and symptoms of pancreatitis and discontinued in patients with confirmed pancreatitis.



    5.4 Pulmonary Disorders



  Pulmonary symptoms, including dyspnea, pulmonary infiltrates, pneumonitis, pulmonary hypertension, and pneumonia, have been reported during therapy with REBETOL with alpha interferon combination therapy ;  occasional cases of fatal pneumonia have occurred. In addition, sarcoidosis or the exacerbation of sarcoidosis has been reported. If there is evidence of pulmonary infiltrates or pulmonary function impairment, the patient should be closely monitored, and if appropriate, combination therapy should be discontinued.



    5.5 Ophthalmologic Disorders



  Ribavirin is used in combination therapy with alpha interferons. Decrease or loss of vision, retinopathy including macular edema, retinal artery or vein, thrombosis, retinal hemorrhages and cotton wool spots, optic neuritis, papilledema, and serous retinal detachment are induced or aggravated by treatment with alpha interferons. All patients should receive an eye examination at baseline. Patients with pre-existing ophthalmologic disorders (e.g., diabetic or hypertensive retinopathy) should receive periodic ophthalmologic exams during combination therapy with alpha interferon treatment. Any patient who develops ocular symptoms should receive a prompt and complete eye examination. Combination therapy with alpha interferons should be discontinued in patients who develop new or worsening ophthalmologic disorders.



    5.6 Laboratory Tests



  PegIntron in combination with ribavirin may cause severe decreases in neutrophil and platelet counts, and hematologic, endocrine (e.g., TSH), and hepatic abnormalities.



 Patients on PegIntron/REBETOL combination therapy should have hematology and blood chemistry testing before the start of treatment and then periodically thereafter. In the adult clinical trial, complete blood counts (including hemoglobin, neutrophil, and platelet counts) and chemistries (including AST, ALT, bilirubin, and uric acid) were measured during the treatment period at Weeks 2, 4, 8, 12, and then at 6-week intervals, or more frequently if abnormalities developed. In pediatric subjects, the same laboratory parameters were evaluated with additional assessment of hemoglobin at treatment Week 6. TSH levels were measured every 12 weeks during the treatment period. HCV-RNA should be measured periodically during treatment [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ].  



    5.7 Dental and Periodontal Disorders



  Dental and periodontal disorders have been reported in patients receiving ribavirin and interferon or peginterferon combination therapy. In addition, dry mouth could have a damaging effect on teeth and mucous membranes of the mouth during long-term treatment with the combination of REBETOL and pegylated or nonpegylated interferon alfa-2b. Patients should brush their teeth thoroughly twice daily and have regular dental examinations. If vomiting occurs, they should be advised to rinse out their mouth thoroughly afterwards.



    5.8 Concomitant Administration of Azathioprine



  Pancytopenia (marked decreases in red blood cells, neutrophils, and platelets) and bone marrow suppression have been reported in the literature to occur within 3 to 7 weeks after the concomitant administration of pegylated interferon/ribavirin and azathioprine. In this limited number of patients (n=8), myelotoxicity was reversible within 4 to 6 weeks upon withdrawal of both HCV antiviral therapy and concomitant azathioprine and did not recur upon reintroduction of either treatment alone. PegIntron, REBETOL, and azathioprine should be discontinued for pancytopenia, and pegylated interferon/ribavirin should not be reintroduced with concomitant azathioprine [see  Drug Interactions (7.4)  ].  



    5.9 Impact on Growth - Pediatric Use



  Data on the effects of PegIntron and REBETOL on growth come from an open-label study in subjects 3 through 17 years of age, in which weight and height changes are compared to US normative population data. In general, the weight and height gain of pediatric subjects treated with PegIntron and REBETOL lags behind that predicted by normative population data for the entire length of treatment. Severely inhibited growth velocity (less than 3  rd  percentile) was observed in 70% of the subjects while on treatment. Following treatment, rebound growth and weight gain occurred in most subjects. Long-term follow-up data in pediatric subjects, however, indicates that PegIntron in combination therapy with REBETOL may induce a growth inhibition that results in reduced adult height in some patients [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Similarly, an impact on growth was seen in subjects after treatment with REBETOL and INTRON A combination therapy for one year. In a long-term follow-up trial of a limited number of these subjects, combination therapy resulted in reduced final adult height in some subjects [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



    5.10 Usage Safeguards



  Based on results of clinical trials, ribavirin monotherapy is not effective for the treatment of chronic hepatitis C virus infection; therefore, REBETOL capsules or oral solution must not be used alone. The safety and efficacy of REBETOL capsules and oral solution have only been established when used together with INTRON A or PegIntron (not other interferons) as combination therapy.



 The safety and efficacy of REBETOL/INTRON A and PegIntron therapy for the treatment of HIV infection, adenovirus, RSV, parainfluenza, or influenza infections have not been established. REBETOL capsules should not be used for these indications. Ribavirin for inhalation has separate labeling, which should be consulted if ribavirin inhalation therapy is being considered.



  There are significant adverse reactions caused by REBETOL/INTRON A or PegIntron therapy, including severe depression and suicidal or homicidal ideation, hemolytic anemia, suppression of bone marrow function, autoimmune and infectious disorders, pulmonary dysfunction, pancreatitis, and diabetes. Suicidal ideation or attempts occurred more frequently among pediatric patients, primarily adolescents, compared to adult patients (2.4% versus 1%) during treatment and off-therapy follow-up. Labeling for INTRON A and PegIntron should be reviewed in their entirety for additional safety information prior to initiation of combination treatment.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
