<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="reclast" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (greater than 10%) were pyrexia, myalgia, headache, arthralgia, pain in extremity (  6.1  ). Other important adverse reactions were flu-like illness, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea (  6.2  ), and eye inflammation (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1     Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Treatment of Osteoporosis in Postmenopausal Women  



 The safety of Reclast in the treatment of postmenopausal osteoporosis was assessed in Study 1, a large, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multinational study of 7736 postmenopausal women aged 65-89 years with osteoporosis, diagnosed by bone mineral density or the presence of a prevalent vertebral fracture. The duration of the trial was three years with 3862 patients exposed to Reclast and 3852 patients exposed to placebo administered once annually as a single 5 mg dose in 100 mL solution infused over at least 15 minutes, for a total of three doses. All women received 1000 to 1500 mg of elemental calcium plus 400 to 1200 international units of vitamin D supplementation per day. 



 The incidence of all-cause mortality was similar between groups: 3.4% in the Reclast group and 2.9% in the placebo group. The incidence of serious adverse events was 29.2% in the Reclast group and 30.1% in the placebo group. The percentage of patients who withdrew from the study due to adverse events was 5.4% and 4.8% for the Reclast and placebo groups, respectively. 



 The safety of Reclast in the treatment of osteoporosis patients with a recent (within 90 days) low-trauma hip fracture was assessed in Study 2, a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multinational endpoint-driven study of 2127 men and women aged 50-95 years; 1065 patients were randomized to Reclast and 1062 patients were randomized to placebo. Reclast was administered once annually as a single 5 mg dose in 100 mL solution infused over at least 15 minutes. The study continued until at least 211 patients had a confirmed clinical fracture in the study population who were followed for an average of approximately 2 years on study drug. Vitamin D levels were not routinely measured but a loading dose of vitamin D (50,000 to 125,000 international units orally or IM) was given to patients and they were started on 1000 to 1500 mg of elemental calcium plus 800 to 1200 international units of vitamin D supplementation per day for at least 14 days prior to the study drug infusions.



 The incidence of all-cause mortality was 9.6% in the Reclast group and 13.3% in the placebo group. The incidence of serious adverse events was 38.3% in the Reclast group and 41.3% in the placebo group. The percentage of patients who withdrew from the study due to adverse events was 5.3% and 4.7% for the Reclast and placebo groups, respectively.



 Adverse reactions reported in at least 2% of patients with osteoporosis and more frequently in the Reclast-treated patients than placebo-treated patients in either osteoporosis trial are shown below in Table 1.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in greater than or equal to 2.0% of Patients with Osteoporosis and More Frequently than in Placebo-Treated Patients 
                    Study 1          Study 2         
   System Organ Class      5 mg IV    Reclast    once per year    %    (N=3862)      Placebo    once per year    %    (N=3852)      5 mg IV    Reclast    once per year    %    (N=1054)      Placebo    once per year    %    (N=1057)     
   Blood and the Lymphatic System Disorders                                                                         
      Anemia      4.4              3.6              5.3              5.2               
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                         
      Dehydration  0.6              0.6              2.5              2.3               
      Anorexia    2.0              1.1              1.0              1.0               
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                         
      Headache    12.4             8.1              3.9              2.5               
      Dizziness   7.6              6.7              2.0              4.0               
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                                                                         
      Vertigo     4.3              4.0              1.3              1.7               
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                         
      Atrial Fibrillation  2.4              1.9              2.8              2.6               
   Vascular Disorders                                                                         
      Hypertension  12.7             12.4             6.8              5.4               
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                         
      Nausea      8.5              5.2              4.5              4.5               
      Diarrhea    6.0              5.6              5.2              4.7               
      Vomiting    4.6              3.2              3.4              3.4               
      Abdominal Pain Upper  4.6              3.1              0.9              1.5               
      Dyspepsia   4.3              4.0              1.7              1.6               
   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders                                                                         
      Arthralgia  23.8             20.4             17.9             18.3              
      Myalgia     11.7             3.7              4.9              2.7               
      Pain in Extremity  11.3             9.9              5.9              4.8               
      Shoulder Pain  6.9              5.6              0.0              0.0               
      Bone Pain   5.8              2.3              3.2              1.0               
      Neck Pain   4.4              3.8              1.4              1.1               
      Muscle Spasms  3.7              3.4              1.5              1.7               
      Osteoarthritis  9.1              9.7              5.7              4.5               
      Musculoskeletal Pain  0.4              0.3              3.1              1.2               
   General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions                                                                         
      Pyrexia     17.9             4.6              8.7              3.1               
      Influenza-like Illness  8.8              2.7              0.8              0.4               
      Fatigue     5.4              3.5              2.1              1.2               
      Chills      5.4              1.0              1.5              0.5               
      Asthenia    5.3              2.9              3.2              3.0               
      Peripheral Edema  4.6              4.2              5.5              5.3               
      Pain        3.3              1.3              1.5              0.5               
      Malaise     2.0              1.0              1.1              0.5               
      Hyperthermia  0.3              &lt;0.1             2.3              0.3               
      Chest Pain  1.3              1.1              2.4              1.8               
   Investigations                                                                         
      Creatinine Renal Clearance Decreased  2.0              2.4              2.1              1.7               
             Renal Impairment  
 

 Treatment with intravenous bisphosphonates, including zoledronic acid, has been associated with renal impairment manifested as deterioration in renal function (i.e., increased serum creatinine) and in rare cases, acute renal failure. In the clinical trial for postmenopausal osteoporosis, patients with baseline creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min (based on actual body weight), urine dipstick greater than or equal to 2+ protein or increase in serum creatinine of greater than 0.5 mg/dL during the screening visits were excluded. The change in creatinine clearance (measured annually prior to dosing) and the incidence of renal failure and impairment was comparable for both the Reclast and placebo treatment groups over 3 years, including patients with creatinine clearance between 30-60 mL/min at baseline. Overall, there was a transient increase in serum creatinine observed within 10 days of dosing in 1.8% of Reclast-treated patients versus 0.8% of placebo-treated patients which resolved without specific therapy [  s    ee    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].



   Acute Phase Reaction  



 The signs and symptoms of acute phase reaction occurred in Study 1 following Reclast infusion including fever (18%), myalgia (9%), flu-like symptoms (8%), headache (7%), and arthralgia (7%). The majority of these symptoms occurred within the first 3 days following the dose of Reclast and usually resolved within 3 days of onset but resolution could take up to 7-14 days. In Study 2, patients without a contraindication to acetaminophen were provided with a standard oral dose at the time of the IV infusion and instructed to use additional acetaminophen at home for the next 72 hours as needed. Reclast was associated with fewer signs and symptoms of a transient acute phase reaction in this trial: fever (7%) and arthralgia (3%). The incidence of these symptoms decreased with subsequent doses of Reclast.



   Laboratory Findings  



 In Study 1, in women with postmenopausal osteoporosis, approximately 0.2% of patients had notable declines of serum calcium levels (less than 7.5 mg/dL) following Reclast administration. No symptomatic cases of hypocalcemia were observed. In Study 2, following pre-treatment with vitamin D, no patients had treatment emergent serum calcium levels below 7.5 mg/dL.



   Injection Site Reactions  



 In the osteoporosis trials, local reactions at the infusion site such as itching, redness and/or pain have been reported in 0% to 0.7% of patients following the administration of Reclast and 0% to 0.5% of patients following administration of placebo.



   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw  



 In the postmenopausal osteoporosis trial, Study 1, in 7736 patients, after initiation of therapy, symptoms consistent with ONJ occurred in one patient treated with placebo and one patient treated with Reclast. Both cases resolved after appropriate treatment [  s    ee    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]. No reports of osteonecrosis of the jaw were reported in either treatment group in Study 2.



   Atrial Fibrillation  



 In the postmenopausal osteoporosis trial, Study 1, adjudicated serious adverse events of atrial fibrillation in the zoledronic acid treatment group occurred in 1.3% of patients (50 out of 3862) compared to 0.4% (17 out of 3852) in the placebo group. The overall incidence of all atrial fibrillation adverse events in the zoledronic acid treatment group was reported in 2.5% of patients (96 out of 3862) in the Reclast group vs. 1.9% of patients (75 out of 3852) in the placebo group. Over 90% of these events in both treatment groups occurred more than a month after the infusion. In an ECG sub-study, ECG measurements were performed on a subset of 559 patients before and 9 to 11 days after treatment. There was no difference in the incidence of atrial fibrillation between treatment groups suggesting these events were not related to the acute infusions. In Study 2, adjudicated serious adverse events of atrial fibrillation in the zoledronic acid treatment group occurred in 1.0% of patients (11 out of 1054) compared to 1.2% (13 out of 1057) in the placebo group demonstrating no difference between treatment groups.



   Ocular Adverse Events  



 Cases of iritis/uveitis/episcleritis/conjunctivitis have been reported in patients treated with bisphosphonates, including zoledronic acid. In the osteoporosis trials, 1 (less than 0.1%) to 9 (0.2%) patients treated with Reclast and 0 (0%) to 1 (less than 0.1%) patient treated with placebo developed iritis/uveitis/episcleritis.



   Prevention of Osteoporosis in Postmenopausal Women  



 The safety of Reclast in postmenopausal women with osteopenia (low bone mass) was assessed in a 2-year randomized, multi-center, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of 581 postmenopausal women aged greater than or equal to 45 years. Patients were randomized to one of three treatment groups: (1) Reclast given at randomization and Month 12 (n=198); (2) Reclast given at randomization and placebo at Month 12 (n=181); and (3) placebo given at randomization and Month 12 (n=202). Reclast was administered as a single 5 mg dose in 100 mL solution infused over at least 15 minutes. All women received 500 to 1200 mg elemental calcium plus 400 to 800 international units vitamin D supplementation per day.



 The incidence of serious adverse events was similar for subjects given (1) Reclast at randomization and at Month 12 (10.6%), (2) Reclast at randomization and placebo given at Month 12 (9.4%), and (3) placebo at randomization and at Month 12 (11.4%). The percentages of patients who withdrew from the study due to adverse events were 7.1%, 7.2%, and 3.0% in the two Reclast groups and placebo group, respectively. Adverse reactions reported in at least 2% of patients with osteopenia and more frequently in the Reclast-treated patients than placebo-treated patients are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions Occurring in greater than or equal to 2% of Patients with Osteopenia and More Frequently than in Placebo-Treated Patients 
 * Combined abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, and abdominal pain lower as one ADR** Combined musculoskeletal pain and musculoskeletal chest pain as one ADR   
  
   System Organ Class      5 mg IV Reclast    Once Per Year    %    (n    =198)      5 mg IV Reclast    Once    %    (n    =181)      Placebo    once per year    %    (n    =202)     
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                        
      Anorexia    2.0              0.6              0.0               
   Nervous system disorders                                                        
      Headache    14.6             20.4             11.4              
      Dizziness   7.6              6.1              3.5               
      Hypoesthesia  5.6              2.2              2.0               
   Ear and labyrinth disorders                                                        
      Vertigo     2.0              1.7              1.0               
   Vascular disorders                                                        
      Hypertension  5.1              8.3              6.9               
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                        
      Nausea      17.7             11.6             7.9               
      Diarrhea    8.1              6.6              7.9               
      Vomiting    7.6              5.0              4.5               
      Dyspepsia   7.1              6.6              5.0               
      Abdominal pain*  8.6              6.6              7.9               
      Constipation  6.6              7.2              6.9               
      Abdominal discomfort  2.0              1.1              0.5               
      Abdominal distension  2.0              0.6              0.0               
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                        
      Rash        3.0              2.2              2.5               
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                        
      Arthralgia  27.3             18.8             19.3              
      Myalgia     19.2             22.7             6.9               
      Back pain   18.2             16.6             11.9              
      Pain in extremity  11.1             16.0             9.9               
      Muscle spasms  5.6              2.8              5.0               
      Musculoskeletal pain**  8.1              7.2              7.9               
      Bone pain   5.1              3.3              1.0               
      Neck pain   5.1              6.6              5.0               
      Arthritis   4.0              2.2              1.5               
      Joint stiffness  3.5              1.1              2.0               
      Joint swelling  3.0              0.6              0.0               
      Flank pain  2.0              0.6              0.0               
      Pain in jaw  2.0              3.9              2.5               
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                        
      Pain        24.2             14.9             3.5               
      Pyrexia     21.7             21.0             4.5               
      Chills      18.2             18.2             3.0               
      Fatigue     14.6             9.9              4.0               
      Asthenia    6.1              2.8              1.0               
      Peripheral edema  5.6              3.9              3.5               
      Non-cardiac chest pain  3.5              7.7              3.0               
      Influenza-like illness  1.5              3.3              2.0               
      Malaise     1.0              2.2              0.5               
            Ocular Adverse Events  
 

 Cases of iritis/uveitis/episcleritis/conjunctivitis have been reported in patients treated with bisphosphonates, including zoledronic acid. In the osteoporosis prevention trial, 4 (1.1%) patients treated with Reclast and 0 (0%) patients treated with placebo developed iritis/uveitis.



   Acute Phase Reaction  



 In patients given Reclast at randomization and placebo at Month 12, Reclast was associated with signs and symptoms of an acute phase reaction: myalgia (20.4%), fever (19.3%), chills (18.2%), pain (13.8%), headache (13.3%), fatigue (8.3%), arthralgia (6.1%), pain in extremity (3.9%), influenza-like illness (3.3%), and back pain (1.7%), which occurred within the first 3 days following the dose of Reclast. The majority of these symptoms were mild to moderate and resolved within 3 days of the event onset but resolution could take up to 7-14 days.



   Osteoporosis in Men  



 The safety of Reclast in men with osteoporosis or osteoporosis secondary to hypogonadism was assessed in a two year randomized, multicenter, double-blind, active controlled group study of 302 men aged 25-86 years. One hundred fifty three (153) patients were exposed to Reclast administered once annually with a 5 mg dose in 100 mL infused over 15 minutes for up to a total of two doses, and 148 patients were exposed to a commercially-available oral weekly bisphosphonate (active control) for up to two years. All participants received 1000 mg of elemental calcium plus 800 to 1000 international units of vitamin D supplementation per day.



 The incidence of all-cause mortality (one in each group) and serious adverse events were similar between the Reclast and active control treatment groups. The percentage of patients experiencing at least one adverse event was comparable between the Reclast and active control groups, with the exception of a higher incidence of post-dose symptoms in the Reclast group that occurred within 3 days after infusion. The overall safety and tolerability of Reclast was similar to the active control.



 Adverse reactions reported in at least 2% of men with osteoporosis and more frequently in the Reclast-treated patients than the active control-treated patients and either (1) not reported in the postmenopausal osteoporosis treatment trial or (2) reported more frequently in the trial of osteoporosis in men are presented in Table 3. Therefore, Table 3 should be viewed in conjunction with Table 1.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Occurring in greater than or equal to 2% of Men with Osteoporosis and More Frequently in the Reclast-Treated Patients than the Active Control-Treated Patients and either (1) Not Reported in the Postmenopausal Osteoporosis Treatment Trial or (2) Reported More Frequently in this Trial 
 * Combined abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, and abdominal pain lower as one ADR** Combined musculoskeletal pain and musculoskeletal chest pain as one ADR   
  
   System Organ Class      5 mg IV Reclast    once per year    %    (N=153)      Active Control    once weekly    %    (N=148)     
   Nervous System Disorders                                       
      Headache    15.0             6.1               
      Lethargy    3.3              1.4               
   Eye Disorders                                       
      Eye pain    2.0              0.0               
   Cardiac Disorders                                       
      Atrial fibrillation  3.3              2.0               
      Palpitations  2.6              0.0               
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                       
      Dyspnea     6.5              4.7               
      Abdominal pain*  7.9              4.1               
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                       
      Hyperhidrosis  2.6              2.0               
   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders                                       
      Myalgia     19.6             6.8               
      Musculoskeletal pain**  12.4             10.8              
      Musculoskeletal stiffness  4.6              0.0               
   Renal and Urinary Disorders                                       
      Blood creatinine increased  2.0              0.7               
   General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions                                       
      Fatigue     17.6             6.1               
      Pain        11.8             4.1               
      Chills      9.8              2.7               
      Influenza-like illness  9.2              2.0               
      Malaise     7.2              0.7               
      Acute phase reaction  3.9              0.0               
   Investigations                                       
      C-reactive protein increased  4.6              1.4               
           Renal Impairment       
 

 Creatinine clearance was measured annually prior to dosing and changes in long-term renal function over 24 months were comparable in the Reclast and active control groups [  s    ee Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].



   Acute Phase Reaction  



 Reclast was associated with signs and symptoms of an acute phase reaction: myalgia (17.1%), fever (15.7%), fatigue (12.4%), arthralgia (11.1%), pain (10.5%), chills (9.8%), headache (9.8%), influenza-like illness (8.5%), malaise (5.2%), and back pain (3.3%), which occurred within the first 3 days following the dose of Reclast. The majority of these symptoms were mild to moderate and resolved within 3 days of the event onset but resolution could take up to 7-14 days. The incidence of these symptoms decreased with subsequent doses of Reclast.



   Atrial Fibrillation  



 The incidence of all atrial fibrillation adverse events in the Reclast treatment group was 3.3% (5 out of 153) compared to 2.0% (3 out of 148) in the active control group. However, there were no patients with adjudicated serious adverse events of atrial fibrillation in the Reclast treatment group.



   Laboratory Findings  



 There were no patients who had treatment emergent serum calcium levels below 7.5 mg/dL.



   Injection Site Reactions  



 There were 4 patients (2.6%) on Reclast vs. 2 patients (1.4%) on active control with local site reactions.



   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw  



 In this trial there were no cases of osteonecrosis of the jaw [  s    ee Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].



   Glucocorticoid-Induced Osteoporosis  



 The safety of Reclast in men and women in the treatment and prevention of glucocorticoid-induced osteoporosis was assessed in a randomized, multicenter, double-blind, active controlled, stratified study of 833 men and women aged 18-85 years treated with greater than or equal to 7.5 mg/day oral prednisone (or equivalent). Patients were stratified according to the duration of their pre-study corticosteroid therapy: less than or equal to 3 months prior to randomization (prevention subpopulation), and greater than 3 months prior to randomization (treatment subpopulation).



 The duration of the trial was one year with 416 patients exposed to Reclast administered once as a single 5 mg dose in 100 mL infused over 15 minutes, and 417 patients exposed to a commercially-available oral daily bisphosphonate (active control)     for one year. All participants received 1000 mg of elemental calcium plus 400 to 1000 international units of vitamin D supplementation per day.



 The incidence of all-cause mortality was similar between treatment groups: 0.9% in the Reclast group and 0.7% in the active control group. The incidence of serious adverse events was similar between the Reclast treatment and prevention groups, 18.4% and 18.1%, respectively, and     the active control treatment and prevention groups, 19.8% and 16.0%, respectively. The percentage of subjects who withdrew from the study due to adverse events was 2.2% in the Reclast group vs. 1.4% in the active control group. The overall safety and tolerability were similar between Reclast and active control groups with the exception of a higher incidence of post-dose symptoms in the Reclast group that occurred within 3 days after infusion. The overall safety and tolerability profile of Reclast in glucocorticoid-induced osteoporosis was similar to the adverse events reported in the Reclast postmenopausal osteoporosis clinical trial.



 Adverse reactions reported in at least 2% of patients that were either not reported in the postmenopausal osteoporosis treatment trial or reported more frequently in the treatment and prevention of glucocorticoid-induced osteoporosis trial included the following: abdominal pain (Reclast 7.5%; active control 5.0%), and musculoskeletal pain (Reclast 3.1%; active control 1.7%).     Other musculoskeletal events included back pain (Reclast 4.3%, active control 6.2%), bone pain (Reclast 3.1%, active control 2.2%), and pain in the extremity (Reclast 3.1%, active control 1.2%).     In addition, the following adverse events occurred more frequently than in the postmenopausal osteoporosis trial: nausea (Reclast 9.6%; active control 8.4%), and dyspepsia (Reclast 5.5%; active control 4.3%).



   Renal Impairment  



 Renal function measured prior to dosing and at the end of the 12 month study was comparable in the Reclast and active control groups [  s    ee Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].



   Acute Phase Reaction  



 Reclast was associated with signs and symptoms of a transient acute phase reaction that was similar to that seen in the Reclast postmenopausal osteoporosis clinical trial.



   Atrial Fibrillation       



 The incidence of atrial fibrillation adverse events was 0.7% (3 of 416) in the Reclast group compared to no adverse events in the active control group. All subjects had a prior history of atrial fibrillation and no cases were adjudicated as serious adverse events. One patient had atrial flutter in the active control group.



   Laboratory Findings  



 There were no patients who had treatment emergent serum calcium levels below 7.5 mg/dL.



   Injection Site Reactions       



 There were no local reactions at the infusion site.



   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw  



 In this trial there were no cases of osteonecrosis of the jaw [  s    ee    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].



   Paget's Disease of Bone  



 In the Paget's disease trials, two 6-month, double-blind, comparative, multinational studies of 349 men and women aged greater than 30 years with moderate to severe disease and with confirmed Paget's disease of bone, 177 patients were exposed to Reclast and 172 patients exposed to risedronate. Reclast was administered once as a single 5 mg dose in 100 mL solution infused over at least 15 minutes. Risedronate was given as an oral daily dose of 30 mg for 2 months.



 The incidence of serious adverse events was 5.1% in the Reclast group and 6.4% in the risedronate group. The percentage of patients who withdrew from the study due to adverse events was 1.7% and 1.2% for the Reclast and risedronate groups, respectively.



 Adverse reactions occurring in at least 2% of the Paget's patients receiving Reclast (single 5 mg intravenous infusion) or risedronate (30 mg oral daily dose for 2 months) over a 6-month study period are listed by system organ class in Table 4.



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions Reported in at Least 2% of Paget's Patients Receiving Reclast (Single 5 mg intravenous Infusion) or Risedronate (Oral 30 mg Daily for 2 Months) Over a 6-Month Follow-Up Period 
   System Organ Class      5 mg IV Reclast    %    (N = 177)      30 mg/day x 2 Months risedronate    %    (N = 172)     
   Infections and Infestations                                       
      Influenza   7                5                 
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                       
      Hypocalcemia  3                1                 
      Anorexia    2                2                 
   Nervous System Disorders                                       
      Headache    11               10                
      Dizziness   9                4                 
      Lethargy    5                1                 
      Paresthesia  2                0                 
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                       
      Dyspnea     5                1                 
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                       
      Nausea      9                6                 
      Diarrhea    6                6                 
      Constipation  6                5                 
      Dyspepsia   5                4                 
      Abdominal Distension  2                1                 
      Abdominal Pain  2                2                 
      Vomiting    2                2                 
      Abdominal Pain Upper  1                2                 
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                       
      Rash        3                2                 
   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders                                       
      Arthralgia  9                11                
      Bone Pain   9                5                 
      Myalgia     7                4                 
      Back Pain   4                7                 
      Musculoskeletal Stiffness  2                1                 
   General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions                                       
      Influenza-like Illness  11               6                 
      Pyrexia     9                2                 
      Fatigue     8                4                 
      Rigors      8                1                 
      Pain        5                4                 
      Peripheral Edema  3                1                 
      Asthenia    2                1                 
           Laboratory Findings  
 

 In the Paget's disease trials, early, transient decreases in serum calcium and phosphate levels were observed. Approximately 21% of patients had serum calcium levels less than 8.4 mg/dL 9-11 days following Reclast administration.



   Renal Impairment  



 In clinical trials in Paget's disease there were no cases of renal deterioration following a single 5 mg 15-minute infusion [  s    ee Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].



   Acute Phase Reaction  



 The signs and symptoms of acute phase reaction (influenza-like illness, pyrexia, myalgia, arthralgia, and bone pain) were reported in 25% of patients in the Reclast-treated group compared to 8% in the risedronate-treated group. Symptoms usually occur within the first 3 days following Reclast administration. The majority of these symptoms resolved within 4 days of onset.



   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw  



 Osteonecrosis of the jaw has been reported with zoledronic acid [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ].



   6.2     Post-Marketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Reclast:



   Acute Phase Reactions   



 Fever, headache, flu-like symptoms, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, arthralgia, and myalgia. Symptoms may be significant and lead to dehydration.



   Acute Renal Failure  



 Acute renal failure requiring hospitalization and/or dialysis or with a fatal outcome have been rarely reported. Increased serum creatinine was reported in patients with 1) underlying renal disease, 2) dehydration secondary to fever, sepsis, gastrointestinal losses, or diuretic therapy, or 3) other risk factors such as advanced age, or concomitant nephrotoxic drugs in the post-infusion period. Transient rise in serum creatinine can be correctable with intravenous fluids.



   Allergic Reactions   



 Allergic reactions with intravenous zoledronic acid including anaphylactic reaction/shock, urticaria, angioedema, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and bronchoconstriction have been reported.



   Asthma Exacerbations  



 Asthma exacerbations have been reported.



   Hypocalcemia  



 Hypocalcemia has been reported.



   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw  



 Osteonecrosis of the jaw has been reported.



   Ocular Adverse Events  



 Cases of the following events have been reported: conjunctivitis, iritis, iridocyclitis, uveitis, episcleritis, scleritis and orbital inflammation/edema.



   Other  



 Hypotension in patients with underlying risk factors has been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Products Containing Same Active Ingredient: Patients receiving Zometa should not receive Reclast (  5.1  ) 
 *   Hypocalcemia may worsen during treatment. Patients must be adequately supplemented with calcium and vitamin D (  5.2  ) 
 *   Renal Impairment: A single dose should not exceed 5 mg and the duration of infusion should be no less than 15 minutes. Renal toxicity may be greater in patients with underlying renal impairment or with other risk factors, including advanced age or dehydration. Monitor creatinine clearance before each dose (  2.7  ,  5.3  ) 
 *   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw (ONJ) has been reported. All patients should have a routine oral exam by the prescriber prior to treatment (  5.4  ) 
 *   Atypical Femur Fractures have been reported. Patients with thigh or groin pain should be evaluated to rule out a femoral fracture (  5.5  ) 
 *   Pregnancy: Reclast can cause fetal harm. Women of childbearing potential should be advised (  5.6  ,  8.1  ) 
 *   Severe Bone, Joint, and Muscle Pain may occur. Withhold future doses of Reclast if severe symptoms occur (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Drug Products with Same Active Ingredient



  Reclast contains the same active ingredient found in Zometa, used for oncology indications, and a patient being treated with Zometa should not be treated with Reclast.



    5.2     Hypocalcemia and Mineral Metabolism



  Pre-existing hypocalcemia and disturbances of mineral metabolism (e.g., hypoparathyroidism, thyroid surgery, parathyroid surgery; malabsorption syndromes, excision of small intestine) must be effectively treated before initiating therapy with Reclast. Clinical monitoring of calcium and mineral levels (phosphorus and magnesium) is highly recommended for these patients [ see Contraindications (4)  ].



 Hypocalcemia following Reclast administration is a significant risk in Paget's disease. All patients should be instructed about the symptoms of hypocalcemia and the importance of calcium and vitamin D supplementation in maintaining serum calcium levels [ see Dosage and Administration (2.8), Adverse Reactions (6.1), Information for Patients (17)  ].



 All osteoporosis patients should be instructed on the importance of calcium and vitamin D supplementation in maintaining serum calcium levels [ see Dosage and Administration (2.8), Adverse Reactions (6.1), Information for Patients (17)  ].



    5.3     Renal Impairment



  A single dose of Reclast should not exceed 5 mg and the duration of infusion should be no less than 15 minutes [ see Dosage and Administration (2)  ].



 Reclast is contraindicated in patients with creatinine clearance less than 35 mL/min and in those with evidence of acute renal impairment [ see Contraindications (4)  ]. If history or physical signs suggest dehydration, Reclast therapy should be withheld until normovolemic status has been achieved [ see Post-Marketing Experience (6.2)  ].



 Reclast should be used with caution in patients with chronic renal impairment. Acute renal impairment, including renal failure, has been observed following the administration of zoledronic acid, especially in patients with pre-existing renal compromise, advanced age, concomitant nephrotoxic medications, concomitant diuretic therapy, or severe dehydration occurring before or after Reclast administration. Acute renal failure (ARF) has been observed in patients after a single administration. Rare reports of hospitalization and/or dialysis or fatal outcome occurred in patients with underlying moderate to severe renal impairment or with any of the risk factors described in this section [ see Post-Marketing Experience (6.2)  ]. Renal impairment may lead to increased exposure of concomitant medications and/or their metabolites that are primarily renally excreted [ see Drug Interactions (7.4)  ].



 Creatinine clearance should be calculated based on actual body weight using Cockcroft-Gault formula before each Reclast dose. Transient increase in serum creatinine may be greater in patients with impaired renal function; interim monitoring of creatinine clearance should be performed in at-risk patients. Elderly patients and those receiving diuretic therapy are at increased risk of acute renal failure. These patients should have their fluid status assessed and be appropriately hydrated prior to administration of Reclast. Reclast should be used with caution with other nephrotoxic drugs [ see Drug Interactions (7.3)  ]. Consider monitoring creatinine clearance in patients at-risk for ARF who are taking concomitant medications that are primarily excreted by the kidney [ see Drug Interactions (7.4)  ].



    5.4     Osteonecrosis of the Jaw



   Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ) has been reported in patients treated with bisphosphonates, including zoledronic acid. Most cases have been in cancer patients treated with intravenous bisphosphonates undergoing dental procedures. Some cases have occurred in patients with postmenopausal osteoporosis treated with either oral or intravenous bisphosphonates. A routine oral examination should be performed by the prescriber prior to initiation of bisphosphonate treatment. A dental examination with appropriate preventive dentistry should be considered prior to treatment with bisphosphonates in patients with a history of concomitant risk factors (e.g., cancer, chemotherapy, angiogenesis inhibitors, radiotherapy, corticosteroids, poor oral hygiene, pre-existing dental disease or infection, anemia, coagulopathy). The risk of ONJ may increase with duration of exposure to bisphosphonates. Concomitant administration of drugs associated with ONJ may increase the risk of developing ONJ.  



 While on treatment, patients with concomitant risk factors should avoid invasive dental procedures if possible. For patients who develop ONJ while on bisphosphonate therapy, dental surgery may exacerbate the condition. For patients requiring dental procedures, there are no data available to suggest whether discontinuation of bisphosphonate treatment reduces the risk of ONJ. The clinical judgment of the treating physician should guide the management plan of each patient based on individual benefit/risk assessment [ see Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].



    5.5     Atypical Subtrochanteric and Diaphyseal Femoral Fractures



  Atypical, low-energy, or low trauma fractures of the femoral shaft have been reported in bisphosphonate-treated patients. These fractures can occur anywhere in the femoral shaft from just below the lesser trochanter to above the supracondylar flare and are transverse or short oblique in orientation without evidence of comminution. Causality has not been established as these fractures also occur in osteoporotic patients who have not been treated with bisphosphonates.



 Atypical femur fractures most commonly occur with minimal or no trauma to the affected area. They may be bilateral and many patients report prodromal pain in the affected area, usually presenting as dull, aching thigh pain, weeks to months before a complete fracture occurs. A number of reports note that patients were also receiving treatment with glucocorticoids (e.g., prednisone) at the time of fracture.



 Any patient with a history of bisphosphonate exposure who presents with thigh or groin pain should be suspected of having an atypical fracture and should be evaluated to rule out an incomplete femur fracture. Patients presenting with an atypical femur fracture should also be assessed for symptoms and signs of fracture in the contralateral limb. Interruption of bisphosphonate therapy should be considered, pending a risk/benefit assessment, on an individual basis.



    5.6     Pregnancy



   RECLAST SHOULD NOT BE USED DURING PREGNANCY  . Reclast may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. If the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential harm to the fetus. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while on Reclast therapy [ see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].



    5.7     Musculoskeletal Pain



  In post-marketing experience, severe and occasionally incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain have been infrequently reported in patients taking bisphosphonates, including Reclast. The time to onset of symptoms varied from one day to several months after starting the drug. Consider withholding future Reclast treatment if severe symptoms develop. Most patients had relief of symptoms after stopping. A subset had recurrence of symptoms when rechallenged with the same drug or another bisphosphonate [ see Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].



    5.8     Patients with Asthma



  While not observed in clinical trials with Reclast, there have been reports of bronchoconstriction in aspirin-sensitive patients receiving bisphosphonates. Use Reclast with caution in aspirin-sensitive patients.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
