<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="recombivax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In healthy infants and children (up to 10 years of age), the most frequently reported systemic adverse reactions (&gt;1% injections), in decreasing order of frequency, were irritability, fever, diarrhea, fatigue/weakness, diminished appetite, and rhinitis. In healthy adults, injection site reactions and systemic adverse reactions were reported following 17% and 15% of the injections, respectively.



   EXCERPT:   In healthy infants and children (up to 10 years of age), the most frequently reported systemic adverse reactions (&gt;1% injections), in decreasing order of frequency, were irritability, fever, diarrhea, fatigue/weakness, diminished appetite, and rhinitis. (  6.1  )



 In healthy adults, injection site reactions and systemic adverse reactions were reported following 17% and 15% of the injections, respectively. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In three clinical studies, 434 doses of RECOMBIVAX HB, 5 mcg, were administered to 147 healthy infants and children (up to 10 years of age) who were monitored for 5 days after each dose. Injection site reactions and systemic adverse reactions were reported following 0.2% and 10.4% of the injections, respectively. The most frequently reported systemic adverse reactions (&gt;1% injections), in decreasing order of frequency, were irritability, fever (&gt;=101 degrees F oral equivalent), diarrhea, fatigue/weakness, diminished appetite, and rhinitis.



 In a study that compared the three-dose regimen (5 mcg) with the two-dose regimen (10 mcg) of RECOMBIVAX HB in adolescents, the overall frequency of adverse reactions was generally similar.



 In a group of studies, 3258 doses of RECOMBIVAX HB, 10 mcg, were administered to 1252 healthy adults who were monitored for 5 days after each dose. Injection site reactions and systemic adverse reactions were reported following 17% and 15% of the injections, respectively. The following adverse reactions were reported:



     Incidence Equal To or Greater Than 1% of Injections  



 GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS



 Injection site reactions consisting principally of soreness, and including pain, tenderness, pruritus, erythema, ecchymosis, swelling, warmth, nodule formation.



 The most frequent systemic complaints include fatigue/weakness; headache; fever (&gt;=100 degrees F); malaise.



 GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS



 Nausea; diarrhea



 RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS



 Pharyngitis; upper respiratory infection



     Incidence Less Than 1% of Injections  



   GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS  



 Sweating; achiness; sensation of warmth; lightheadedness; chills; flushing



   GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS  



 Vomiting; abdominal pains/cramps; dyspepsia; diminished appetite



   RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS  



 Rhinitis; influenza; cough



   NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS  



 Vertigo/dizziness; paresthesia



   SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS  



 Pruritus; rash (non-specified); angioedema; urticaria



   MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS  



 Arthralgia including monoarticular; myalgia; back pain; neck pain; shoulder pain; neck stiffness



   BLOOD AND LYMPHATIC DISORDERS  



 Lymphadenopathy



   PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS  



 Insomnia/disturbed sleep



   EAR AND LABYRINTH DISORDERS  



 Earache



   RENAL AND URINARY DISORDERS  



 Dysuria



   CARDIAC DISORDERS  



 Hypotension



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been reported with use of the marketed vaccine. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to a vaccine exposure.



   Immune System Disorders  



 Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions, bronchospasm, and urticaria have been reported within the first few hours after vaccination. An apparent hypersensitivity syndrome (serum-sickness-like) of delayed onset has been reported days to weeks after vaccination, including: arthralgia/arthritis (usually transient), fever, and dermatologic reactions such as urticaria, erythema multiforme, ecchymoses and erythema nodosum  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . Autoimmune diseases including systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), lupus-like syndrome, vasculitis, and polyarteritis nodosa have also been reported.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  



 Elevation of liver enzymes; constipation



   Nervous System Disorders  



 Guillain-Barre syndrome; multiple sclerosis; exacerbation of multiple sclerosis; myelitis including transverse myelitis; seizure; febrile seizure; peripheral neuropathy including Bell's Palsy; radiculopathy; herpes zoster; migraine; muscle weakness; hypesthesia; encephalitis



   Skin and Subcutaneous Disorders  



 Stevens-Johnson syndrome; alopecia; petechiae; eczema



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  



 Arthritis



 Pain in extremity



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  



 Increased erythrocyte sedimentation rate; thrombocytopenia



   Psychiatric Disorders  



 Irritability; agitation; somnolence



   Eye Disorders  



 Optic neuritis; tinnitus; conjunctivitis; visual disturbances; uveitis



   Cardiac Disorders  



 Syncope; tachycardia



 The following adverse reaction has been reported with another Hepatitis B Vaccine (Recombinant) but not with RECOMBIVAX HB: keratitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   The vial stopper, the syringe plunger stopper, and tip cap contain dry natural latex rubber which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. (  5.1  )



 Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. Decisions about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including RECOMBIVAX HB, to infants born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination. (  5.2  )



 



   5.1 Hypersensitivity to Latex



  The vial stopper and the syringe plunger stopper and tip cap contain dry natural latex rubber, which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals.



    5.2 Apnea in Premature Infants



  Apnea following intramuscular vaccination has been observed in some infants born prematurely. Decisions about when to administer an intramuscular vaccine, including RECOMBIVAX HB, to infants born prematurely should be based on consideration of the individual infant's medical status and the potential benefits and possible risks of vaccination. For RECOMBIVAX HB, this assessment should include consideration of the mother's hepatitis B antigen status and the high probability of maternal transmission of hepatitis B virus to infants born to mothers who are HBsAg positive if vaccination is delayed.



    5.3 Infants Weighing Less Than 2000 g



  Hepatitis B vaccination should be delayed until 1 month of age or hospital discharge in infants weighing &lt;2000 g if the mother is documented to be HBsAg negative at the time of the infant's birth. Infants weighing &lt;2000 g born to HBsAg positive or HBsAg unknown mothers should receive vaccine and hepatitis B immune globulin (HBIG) in accordance with ACIP recommendations if HBsAg status cannot be determined{3} [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ].  



    5.4 Prevention and Management of Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration [see  Contraindications (4)  ].  



    5.5 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Hepatitis B virus has a long incubation period. RECOMBIVAX HB may not prevent hepatitis B infection in individuals who have an unrecognized hepatitis B infection at the time of vaccination. Additionally, vaccination with RECOMBIVAX HB may not protect all individuals.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
