<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="reglan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In general, the incidence of adverse reactions correlates with the dose and duration of metoclopramide administration. The following reactions have been reported, although in most instances, data do not permit an estimate of frequency:



   CNS Effects  



 Restlessness, drowsiness, fatigue, and lassitude occur in approximately 10% of patients receiving the most commonly prescribed dosage of 10 mg q.i.d. (see    PRECAUTIONS    ). Insomnia, headache, confusion, dizziness, or mental depression with suicidal ideation (see    WARNINGS    ) occur less frequently. The incidence of drowsiness is greater at higher doses. There are isolated reports of convulsive seizures without clearcut relationship to metoclopramide. Rarely, hallucinations have been reported.



   Extrapyramidal Reactions (EPS)  



 Acute dystonic reactions, the most common type of EPS associated with metoclopramide, occur in approximately 0.2% of patients (1 in 500) treated with 30 to 40 mg of metoclopramide per day. Symptoms include involuntary movements of limbs, facial grimacing, torticollis, oculogyric crisis, rhythmic protrusion of tongue, bulbar type of speech, trismus, opisthotonus (tetanus-like reactions), and, rarely, stridor and dyspnea possibly due to laryngospasm; ordinarily these symptoms are readily reversed by diphenhydramine (see    WARNINGS    ).



 Parkinsonian-like symptoms may include bradykinesia, tremor, cogwheel rigidity, mask-like facies (see    WARNINGS    ).



 Tardive dyskinesia most frequently is characterized by involuntary movements of the tongue, face, mouth, or jaw, and sometimes by involuntary movements of the trunk and/or extremities; movements may be choreoathetotic in appearance (see    WARNINGS    ).



 Motor restlessness (akathisia) may consist of feelings of anxiety, agitation, jitteriness, and insomnia, as well as inability to sit still, pacing, foot tapping. These symptoms may disappear spontaneously or respond to a reduction in dosage.



   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome  



 Rare occurrences of neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS) have been reported. This potentially fatal syndrome is comprised of the symptom complex of hyperthermia, altered consciousness, muscular rigidity, and autonomic dysfunction (see    WARNINGS    ).



   Endocrine Disturbances  



 Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, impotence secondary to hyperprolactlnemia (see    PRECAUTIONS    ). Fluid retention secondary to transient elevation of aldosterone (see    CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY    ).



   Cardiovascular  



 Hypotension, hypertension, supraventricular tachycardia, bradycardia, fluid retention, acute congestive heart failure and possible AV block (see    CONTRAINDICATIONS    and    PRECAUTIONS    ).



   Gastrointestinal  



 Nausea and bowel disturbances, primarily diarrhea.



   Hepatic  



 Rarely, cases of hepatotoxicity, characterized by such findings as jaundice and altered liver function tests, when metoclopramide was administered with other drugs with known hepatotoxic potential.



   Renal  



 Urinary frequency and incontinence.



   Hematologic  



 A few cases of neutropenia, leukopenia, or agranulocytosis, generally without clearcut relationship to metoclopramide. Methemoglobinemia, in adults and especially with overdosage in neonates (see    OVERDOSAGE    ). Sulfhemoglobinemia in adults.



   Allergic Reactions  



 A few cases of rash, urticaria, or bronchospasm, especially in patients with a history of asthma. Rarely, angioneurotic edema, including glossal or laryngeal edema.



   Miscellaneous  



 Visual disturbances. Porphyria.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: TARDIVE DYSKINESIA

    WARNING: TARDIVE DYSKINESIA  

    Treatment with metoclopramide can cause tardive dyskinesia, a serious movement disorder that is often irreversible. The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia increases with duration of treatment and total cumulative dose.  



   Metoclopramide therapy should be discontinued in patients who develop signs or symptoms of tardive dyskinesia. There is no known treatment for tardive dyskinesia. In some patients, symptoms may lessen or resolve after metoclopramide treatment is stopped.  



   Treatment with metoclopramide for longer than 12 weeks should be avoided in all but rare cases where therapeutic benefit is thought to outweigh the risk of developing tardive dyskinesia.  



   See   WARNINGS    
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
