<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="remeron" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment

  Approximately 16% of the 453 patients who received REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets in US 6-week controlled clinical trials discontinued treatment due to an adverse experience, compared to 7% of the 361 placebo-treated patients in those studies. The most common events (&gt;=1%) associated with discontinuation and considered to be drug related (i.e., those events associated with dropout at a rate at least twice that of placebo) are included in Table 2.



 Table 2: Common Adverse Events Associated With Discontinuation of Treatment in 6-Week US REMERON Trials 
 Adverse Event         Percentage of Patients Discontinuing With Adverse Event   
 REMERON (n=453)                   Placebo (n=361)                
  
 Somnolence                             10.4%                                      2.2%                     
 Nausea                                  1.5%                                       0%                      
           Commonly Observed Adverse Events in US Controlled Clinical Trials
   The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets (incidence of 5% or greater) and not observed at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients (REMERON incidence at least twice that for placebo) are listed in Table 3.



 Table 3: Common Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Associated With the Use of REMERON in 6-Week US Trials 
 Adverse Event                   Percentage of Patients Reporting Adverse Event   
 REMERON (n=453)                           Placebo (n=361)             
  
 Somnolence                                      54%                                  18%                   
 Increased Appetite                              17%                                  2%                    
 Weight Gain                                     12%                                  2%                    
 Dizziness                                       7%                                   3%                    
           Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among REMERON-Treated Patients
   Table 4 enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 1% or more, and were more frequent than in the placebo group, among REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets-treated patients who participated in short-term US placebo-controlled trials in which patients were dosed in a range of 5 to 60 mg/day. This table shows the percentage of patients in each group who had at least 1 episode of an event at some time during their treatment. Reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based dictionary terminology.



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the side-effect incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 4: Incidence of Adverse Clinical ExperiencesEvents reported by at least 1% of patients treated with REMERON are included, except the following events, which had an incidence on placebo greater than or equal to REMERON: headache, infection, pain, chest pain, palpitation, tachycardia, postural hypotension, nausea, dyspepsia, diarrhea, flatulence, insomnia, nervousness, libido decreased, hypertonia, pharyngitis, rhinitis, sweating, amblyopia, tinnitus, taste perversion. (&gt;=1%) in Short-Term US Controlled Studies 
 Body System  Adverse Clinical  Experience          REMERON(n=453)                  Placebo(n=361)           
  
   Body as a Whole                          
   Asthenia                                              8%                              5%                 
   Flu Syndrome                                          5%                              3%                 
   Back Pain                                             2%                              1%                 
   Digestive System                         
   Dry Mouth                                            25%                             15%                 
   Increased Appetite                                   17%                              2%                 
   Constipation                                         13%                              7%                 
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders      
   Weight Gain                                          12%                              2%                 
   Peripheral Edema                                      2%                              1%                 
   Edema                                                 1%                              0%                 
   Musculoskeletal System                   
   Myalgia                                               2%                              1%                 
   Nervous System                           
   Somnolence                                           54%                             18%                 
   Dizziness                                             7%                              3%                 
   Abnormal Dreams                                       4%                              1%                 
   Thinking Abnormal                                     3%                              1%                 
   Tremor                                                2%                              1%                 
   Confusion                                             2%                              0%                 
   Respiratory System                       
   Dyspnea                                               1%                              0%                 
   Urogenital System                        
   Urinary Frequency                                     2%                              1%                 
           ECG Changes
   The electrocardiograms for 338 patients who received REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets and 261 patients who received placebo in 6-week, placebo-controlled trials were analyzed. Prolongation in QTc &gt;=500 msec was not observed among mirtazapine-treated patients; mean change in QTc was +1.6 msec for mirtazapine and -3.1 msec for placebo. Mirtazapine was associated with a mean increase in heart rate of 3.4 bpm, compared to 0.8 bpm for placebo. The clinical significance of these changes is unknown.



   Other Adverse Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of REMERON

  During its premarketing assessment, multiple doses of REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets were administered to 2796 patients in clinical studies. The conditions and duration of exposure to mirtazapine varied greatly, and included (in overlapping categories) open and double-blind studies, uncontrolled and controlled studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, fixed-dose and titration studies. Untoward events associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized event categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based dictionary terminology. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the 2796 patients exposed to multiple doses of REMERON who experienced an event of the type cited on at least 1 occasion while receiving REMERON. All reported events are included except those already listed in Table 4, those adverse experiences subsumed under COSTART terms that are either overly general or excessively specific so as to be uninformative, and those events for which a drug cause was very remote.



 It is important to emphasize that, although the events reported occurred during treatment with REMERON, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: frequent adverse events are those occurring on 1 or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients. Only those events not already listed in Table 4 appear in this listing. Events of major clinical importance are also described in the WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS sections.



   Body as a Whole  :  frequent:  malaise, abdominal pain, abdominal syndrome acute;  infrequent:  chills, fever, face edema, ulcer, photosensitivity reaction, neck rigidity, neck pain, abdomen enlarged;  rare:  cellulitis, chest pain substernal.



   Cardiovascular System  :  frequent:  hypertension, vasodilatation;  infrequent:  angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, bradycardia, ventricular extrasystoles, syncope, migraine, hypotension;  rare:  atrial arrhythmia, bigeminy, vascular headache, pulmonary embolus, cerebral ischemia, cardiomegaly, phlebitis, left heart failure.



   Digestive System  :  frequent:  vomiting, anorexia;  infrequent:  eructation, glossitis, cholecystitis, nausea and vomiting, gum hemorrhage, stomatitis, colitis, liver function tests abnormal;  rare:  tongue discoloration, ulcerative stomatitis, salivary gland enlargement, increased salivation, intestinal obstruction, pancreatitis, aphthous stomatitis, cirrhosis of liver, gastritis, gastroenteritis, oral moniliasis, tongue edema.



   Endocrine System  :  rare:  goiter, hypothyroidism.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  :  rare:  lymphadenopathy, leukopenia, petechia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, lymphocytosis, pancytopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  :  frequent:  thirst;  infrequent:  dehydration, weight loss;  rare:  gout, SGOT increased, healing abnormal, acid phosphatase increased, SGPT increased, diabetes mellitus, hyponatremia.



   Musculoskeletal System  :  frequent:  myasthenia, arthralgia;  infrequent:  arthritis, tenosynovitis;  rare:  pathologic fracture, osteoporosis fracture, bone pain, myositis, tendon rupture, arthrosis, bursitis.



   Nervous System  :  frequent:  hypesthesia, apathy, depression, hypokinesia, vertigo, twitching, agitation, anxiety, amnesia, hyperkinesia, paresthesia;  infrequent:  ataxia, delirium, delusions, depersonalization, dyskinesia, extrapyramidal syndrome, libido increased, coordination abnormal, dysarthria, hallucinations, manic reaction, neurosis, dystonia, hostility, reflexes increased, emotional lability, euphoria, paranoid reaction;  rare:  aphasia, nystagmus, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), stupor, dementia, diplopia, drug dependence, paralysis, grand mal convulsion, hypotonia, myoclonus, psychotic depression, withdrawal syndrome, serotonin syndrome.



   Respiratory System  :  frequent:  cough increased, sinusitis;  infrequent:  epistaxis, bronchitis, asthma, pneumonia;  rare:  asphyxia, laryngitis, pneumothorax, hiccup.



   Skin and Appendages  :  frequent:  pruritus, rash;  infrequent:  acne, exfoliative dermatitis, dry skin, herpes simplex, alopecia;  rare:  urticaria, herpes zoster, skin hypertrophy, seborrhea, skin ulcer.



   Special Senses  :  infrequent:  eye pain, abnormality of accommodation, conjunctivitis, deafness, keratoconjunctivitis, lacrimation disorder, angle-closure glaucoma, hyperacusis, ear pain;  rare:  blepharitis, partial transitory deafness, otitis media, taste loss, parosmia.



   Urogenital System  :  frequent:  urinary tract infection;  infrequent:  kidney calculus, cystitis, dysuria, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, vaginitis, hematuria, breast pain, amenorrhea, dysmenorrhea, leukorrhea, impotence;  rare:  polyuria, urethritis, metrorrhagia, menorrhagia, abnormal ejaculation, breast engorgement, breast enlargement, urinary urgency.



   Other Adverse Events Observed During Postmarketing Evaluation of REMERON

  Adverse events reported since market introduction, which were temporally (but not necessarily causally) related to mirtazapine therapy, include 4 cases of the ventricular arrhythmia torsades de pointes. In 3 of the 4 cases, however, concomitant drugs were implicated. All patients recovered.



 Cases of severe skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, bullous dermatitis, erythema multiforme and toxic epidermal necrolysis have also been reported.



 Increased creatine kinase blood levels have also been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs  



   Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of REMERON  (r)   (mirtazapine) Tablets or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. REMERON is not approved for use in pediatric patients. (See   WARNINGS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk  ,   PRECAUTIONS: Information for Patients  , and   PRECAUTIONS: Pediatric Use  )  



 





    BOXED WARNING: Medication Guide

  Medication Guide

  REMERON  (r)   (rem' - e - ron)(mirtazapine)Tablets



 Read the Medication Guide that comes with REMERON before you start taking it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or treatment. If you have any questions about REMERON, talk to your healthcare provider.



   What is the most important information I should know about REMERON  (r)  ?  



 REMERON and other antidepressant medicines may cause serious side effects, including:



 *  1.Suicidal thoughts or actions:REMERON and other antidepressant medicines may increase suicidal thoughts or actions in some children, teenagers, or young adults within the first few months of treatment or when the dose is changed.Depression or other serious mental illnesses are the most important causes of suicidal thoughts or actions.Watch for these changes and call your healthcare provider right away if you notice:New or sudden changes in mood, behavior, actions, thoughts, or feelings, especially if severe.Pay particular attention to such changes when REMERON is started or when the dose is changed. 
    Keep all follow-up visits with your healthcare provider and call between visits if you are worried about symptoms.
 

   Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency, especially if they are new, worse, or worry you:  



 *  attempts to commit suicide 
 *  acting on dangerous impulses 
 *  acting aggressive or violent 
 *  thoughts about suicide or dying 
 *  new or worse depression 
 *  new or worse anxiety or panic attacks 
 *  feeling agitated, restless, angry or irritable 
 *  trouble sleeping 
 *  an increase in activity or talking more than what is normal for you 
 *  other unusual changes in behavior or mood 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency. REMERON may be associated with these serious side effects:  
 

 *  2.Manic episodes:greatly increased energysevere trouble sleepingracing thoughtsreckless behaviorunusually grand ideasexcessive happiness or irritabilitytalking more or faster than usual 
 *  3.Decreased White Blood Cells called neutrophils, which are needed to fight infections. Tell your doctor if you have any indication of infection such as fever, chills, sore throat, or mouth or nose sores, especially symptoms which are flu-like. 
 *  4.Serotonin Syndrome. This condition can be life-threatening and may include:agitation, hallucinations, coma or other changes in mental statuscoordination problems or muscle twitching (overactive reflexes)racing heartbeat, high or low blood pressuresweating or fevernausea, vomiting, or diarrheamuscle rigidity 
 *  5.Visual problemseye painchanges in visionswelling or redness in or around the eyeOnly some people are at risk for these problems. You may want to undergo an eye examination to see if you are at risk and receive preventative treatment if you are. 
 *  6.Seizures 
 *  7.Low salt (sodium) levels in the blood. Elderly people may be at greater risk for this. Symptoms may include:headacheweakness or feeling unsteadyconfusion, problems concentrating or thinking or memory problems 
 *  8.Sleepiness. It is best to take REMERON close to bedtime. 
 *  9.Severe skin reactions: Call your doctor right away if you have any or all of the following symptoms:severe rash with skin swelling (including on the palms of the hands and soles of the feet)painful reddening of the skin and/or blisters/ulcers on the body or in the mouth 
 *  10.Severe allergic reactions: trouble breathing, swelling of the face, tongue, eyes or mouthrash, itchy welts (hives) or blisters, alone or with fever or joint pain 
 *  11.Increases in appetite or weight. Children and adolescents should have height and weight monitored during treatment. 
 *  12.Increased cholesterol and triglyceride levels in your blood 
      Do not stop REMERON without first talking to your healthcare provider.   Stopping REMERON too quickly may cause potentially serious symptoms including:
 

 *  dizziness 
 *  abnormal dreams 
 *  agitation 
 *  anxiety 
 *  fatigue 
 *  confusion 
 *  headache 
 *  shaking 
 *  tingling sensation 
 *  nausea, vomiting 
 *  sweating 
      What is REMERON?  
 

 REMERON is a prescription medicine used to treat depression. It is important to talk with your healthcare provider about the risks of treating depression and also the risks of not treating it. You should discuss all treatment choices with your healthcare provider.



 Talk to your healthcare provider if you do not think that your condition is getting better with REMERON treatment.



   Who should not take REMERON?  



 Do not take REMERON:



 *  if you are allergic to mirtazapine or any of the ingredients in REMERON. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in REMERON. 
 *  if you take a monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI). Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure if you take an MAOI, including the antibiotic linezolid. 
 *  Do not take an MAOI within 2 weeks of stopping REMERON unless directed to do so by your physician. 
 *  Do not start REMERON if you stopped taking an MAOI in the last 2 weeks unless directed to do so by your physician. 
      People who take REMERON close in time to an MAOI may have serious or even life-threatening side effects. Get medical help right away if you have any of these symptoms:  
 

 *  high fever 
 *  uncontrolled muscle spasms 
 *  stiff muscles 
 *  rapid changes in heart rate or blood pressure 
 *  confusion 
 *  loss of consciousness (pass out) 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking REMERON?  
 

   Ask if you are not sure.  



 Before starting REMERON, tell your healthcare provider if you:



 *  Are taking certain drugs such as:Triptans used to treat migraine headacheMedicines used to treat mood, anxiety, psychotic or thought disorders, including tricyclics, lithium, SSRIs, SNRIs, or antipsychoticsTramadol used to treat painOver-the-counter supplements such as tryptophan or St. John's wortPhenytoin, carbamazepine, or rifampicin (these drugs can decrease your blood level of REMERON)Cimetidine or ketoconazole (these drugs can increase your blood level of REMERON) 
 *  Have or had:liver problemskidney problemsheart problemsseizures or convulsionsbipolar disorder or maniaa tendency to get dizzy or faint 
 *  are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. It is not known if REMERON will harm your unborn baby. Talk to your healthcare provider about the benefits and risks of treating depression during pregnancy 
 *  are breastfeeding or plan to breastfeed. Some REMERON may pass into your breast milk. Talk to your healthcare provider about the best way to feed your baby while taking REMERON 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines that you take,   including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. REMERON and some medicines may interact with each other, may not work as well, or may cause serious side effects.
 

 Your healthcare provider or pharmacist can tell you if it is safe to take REMERON with your other medicines. Do not start or stop any medicine while taking REMERON without talking to your healthcare provider first.



   If you take REMERON, you should not take any other medicines that contain mirtazapine including REMERONSolTab  (r)  .



     How should I take REMERON?  



 *  Take REMERON exactly as prescribed. Your healthcare provider may need to change the dose of REMERON until it is the right dose for you. 
 *  Take REMERON at the same time each day, preferably in the evening at bedtime. 
 *  Swallow REMERON as directed. 
 *  It is common for antidepressant medicines such as REMERON to take up to a few weeks before you start to feel better. Do not stop taking REMERON if you do not feel results right away. 
 *  Do not stop taking or change the dose of REMERON without first talking to your doctor, even if you feel better. 
 *  REMERON may be taken with or without food. 
 *  If you miss a dose of REMERON, take the missed dose as soon as you remember. If it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and take your next dose at the regular time. Do not take two doses of REMERON at the same time. 
 *  If you take too much REMERON, call your healthcare provider or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What should I avoid while taking REMERON?  
 

 *  REMERON can cause sleepiness or may affect your ability to make decisions, think clearly, or react quickly. You should not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how REMERON affects you. 
 *  Avoid drinking alcohol or taking diazepam (a medicine used for anxiety, insomnia and seizures, for example) or similar medicines while taking REMERON. If you are uncertain about whether certain medication can be taken with REMERON, please discuss with your doctor. 
      What are the possible side effects of REMERON?  
 

 REMERON may cause serious side effects, including all of those described in the section entitled "What is the most important information I should know about REMERON?"



 Common possible side effects in people who take REMERON include:



 *  sleepiness 
 *  increased appetite, weight gain 
 *  dry mouth 
 *  constipation 
 *  dizziness 
 *  abnormal dreams 
    Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away. These are not all the possible side effects of REMERON. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.
 

   CALL YOUR DOCTOR FOR MEDICAL ADVICE ABOUT SIDE EFFECTS. YOU MAY REPORT SIDE EFFECTS TO THE FDA AT 1-800-FDA-1088.  



   How should I store REMERON?  



 *  Store REMERON at room temperature 25 degrees C (77 degrees F). Storage at 15 degrees C-30 degrees C (59 degrees F-86 degrees F) is permitted occasionally. 
 *  Keep REMERON away from light. 
 *  Keep REMERON bottle closed tightly. 
      Keep REMERON and all medicines out of the reach of children.  
 

   General information about REMERON  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use REMERON for a condition for which it was not prescribed. Do not give REMERON to other people, even if they have the same condition. It may harm them.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about REMERON. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You may ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for information about REMERON that is written for healthcare professionals.



 For more information about REMERON call 1-800-526-4099 or go to www.REMERON.com.



   What are the ingredients in REMERON?   



 Active ingredient: mirtazapine



 Inactive ingredients:



 *  15 mg tablets: Starch (corn), hydroxypropyl cellulose, magnesium stearate, colloidal silicon dioxide, lactose, hypromellose, polyethylene glycol 8000, titanium dioxide, ferric oxide (yellow). 
 *  30 mg tablets: Starch (corn), hydroxypropyl cellulose, magnesium stearate, colloidal silicon dioxide, lactose, hypromellose, polyethylene glycol 8000, titanium dioxide, ferric oxide (yellow), ferric oxide (red). 
 *  45 mg tablets: Starch (corn), hydroxypropyl cellulose, magnesium stearate, colloidal silicon dioxide, lactose, hypromellose, polyethylene glycol 8000, titanium dioxide. 
    This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
