<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="remeronsoltab" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment

  Approximately 16% of the 453 patients who received REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets in US 6-week controlled clinical trials discontinued treatment due to an adverse experience, compared to 7% of the 361 placebo-treated patients in those studies. The most common events (&gt;=1%) associated with discontinuation and considered to be drug related (i.e., those events associated with dropout at a rate at least twice that of placebo) are included in Table 2.



 Table 2: Common Adverse Events Associated With Discontinuation of Treatment in 6-Week US REMERON Trials 
                                     Percentage of Patients Discontinuing with Adverse Event   
 Adverse Event                                REMERON(n=453)                     Placebo(n=361)             
  
 Somnolence                                        10.4%                              2.2%                  
 Nausea                                            1.5%                                0%                   
           Commonly Observed Adverse Events in US Controlled Clinical Trials
   The most commonly observed adverse events associated with the use of REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets (incidence of 5% or greater) and not observed at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients (REMERON incidence at least twice that for placebo) are listed in Table 3.



 Table 3: Common Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Associated With the Use of REMERON in 6-Week US Trials 
                                    Percentage of Patients Reporting Adverse Event   
 Adverse Event                                REMERON(n=453)                     Placebo(n=361)             
  
 Somnolence                                        54%                                 18%                  
 Increased Appetite                                17%                                 2%                   
 Weight Gain                                       12%                                 2%                   
 Dizziness                                          7%                                 3%                   
           Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among REMERON-Treated Patients
   Table 4 enumerates adverse events that occurred at an incidence of 1% or more, and were more frequent than in the placebo group, among REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets-treated patients who participated in short-term US placebo-controlled trials in which patients were dosed in a range of 5 to 60 mg/day. This table shows the percentage of patients in each group who had at least 1 episode of an event at some time during their treatment. Reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based dictionary terminology.



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the side-effect incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 4: Incidence of Adverse Clinical ExperiencesEvents reported by at least 1% of patients treated with REMERON are included, except the following events, which had an incidence on placebo greater than or equal to REMERON: headache, infection, pain, chest pain, palpitation, tachycardia, postural hypotension, nausea, dyspepsia, diarrhea, flatulence, insomnia, nervousness, libido decreased, hypertonia, pharyngitis, rhinitis, sweating, amblyopia, tinnitus, taste perversion. (&gt;=1%) in Short-Term US Controlled Studies 
 Body System  Adverse Clinical Experience                 REMERON(n=453)             Placebo(n=361)         
  
   Body as a Whole                                    
   Asthenia                                                     8%                         5%               
   Flu Syndrome                                                 5%                         3%               
   Back Pain                                                    2%                         1%               
   Digestive System                                   
   Dry Mouth                                                    25%                        15%              
   Increased Appetite                                           17%                        2%               
   Constipation                                                 13%                        7%               
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                
   Weight Gain                                                  12%                        2%               
   Peripheral Edema                                             2%                         1%               
   Edema                                                        1%                         0%               
   Musculoskeletal System                             
   Myalgia                                                      2%                         1%               
   Nervous System                                     
   Somnolence                                                   54%                        18%              
   Dizziness                                                    7%                         3%               
   Abnormal Dreams                                              4%                         1%               
   Thinking Abnormal                                            3%                         1%               
   Tremor                                                       2%                         1%               
   Confusion                                                    2%                         0%               
   Respiratory System                                 
   Dyspnea                                                      1%                         0%               
   Urogenital System                                  
   Urinary Frequency                                            2%                         1%               
           ECG Changes
   The electrocardiograms for 338 patients who received REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets and 261 patients who received placebo in 6-week, placebo-controlled trials were analyzed. Prolongation in QTc &gt;=500 msec was not observed among mirtazapine-treated patients; mean change in QTc was +1.6 msec for mirtazapine and -3.1 msec for placebo. Mirtazapine was associated with a mean increase in heart rate of 3.4 bpm, compared to 0.8 bpm for placebo. The clinical significance of these changes is unknown.



   Other Adverse Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of REMERON

  During its premarketing assessment, multiple doses of REMERON (mirtazapine) Tablets were administered to 2796 patients in clinical studies. The conditions and duration of exposure to mirtazapine varied greatly, and included (in overlapping categories) open and double-blind studies, uncontrolled and controlled studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, fixed-dose and titration studies. Untoward events associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized event categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based dictionary terminology. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the 2796 patients exposed to multiple doses of REMERON who experienced an event of the type cited on at least 1 occasion while receiving REMERON. All reported events are included except those already listed in Table 4, those adverse experiences subsumed under COSTART terms that are either overly general or excessively specific so as to be uninformative, and those events for which a drug cause was very remote.



 It is important to emphasize that, although the events reported occurred during treatment with REMERON, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: frequent adverse events are those occurring on 1 or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients. Only those events not already listed in Table 4 appear in this listing. Events of major clinical importance are also described in the WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS sections.



   Body as a Whole  :  frequent:  malaise, abdominal pain, abdominal syndrome acute;  infrequent:  chills, fever, face edema, ulcer, photosensitivity reaction, neck rigidity, neck pain, abdomen enlarged;  rare:  cellulitis, chest pain substernal.



   Cardiovascular System  :  frequent:  hypertension, vasodilatation;  infrequent:  angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, bradycardia, ventricular extrasystoles, syncope, migraine, hypotension;  rare:  atrial arrhythmia, bigeminy, vascular headache, pulmonary embolus, cerebral ischemia, cardiomegaly, phlebitis, left heart failure.



   Digestive System  :  frequent:  vomiting, anorexia;  infrequent:  eructation, glossitis, cholecystitis, nausea and vomiting, gum hemorrhage, stomatitis, colitis, liver function tests abnormal;  rare:  tongue discoloration, ulcerative stomatitis, salivary gland enlargement, increased salivation, intestinal obstruction, pancreatitis, aphthous stomatitis, cirrhosis of liver, gastritis, gastroenteritis, oral moniliasis, tongue edema.



   Endocrine System  :  rare:  goiter, hypothyroidism.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  :  rare:  lymphadenopathy, leukopenia, petechia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, lymphocytosis, pancytopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders  :  frequent:  thirst;  infrequent:  dehydration, weight loss;  rare:  gout, SGOT increased, healing abnormal, acid phosphatase increased, SGPT increased, diabetes mellitus, hyponatremia.



   Musculoskeletal System  :  frequent:  myasthenia, arthralgia;  infrequent:  arthritis, tenosynovitis;  rare:  pathologic fracture, osteoporosis fracture, bone pain, myositis, tendon rupture, arthrosis, bursitis.



   Nervous System  :  frequent:  hypesthesia, apathy, depression, hypokinesia, vertigo, twitching, agitation, anxiety, amnesia, hyperkinesia, paresthesia;  infrequent:  ataxia, delirium, delusions, depersonalization, dyskinesia, extrapyramidal syndrome, libido increased, coordination abnormal, dysarthria, hallucinations, manic reaction, neurosis, dystonia, hostility, reflexes increased, emotional lability, euphoria, paranoid reaction;  rare:  aphasia, nystagmus, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), stupor, dementia, diplopia, drug dependence, paralysis, grand mal convulsion, hypotonia, myoclonus, psychotic depression, withdrawal syndrome, serotonin syndrome.



   Respiratory System  :  frequent:  cough increased, sinusitis;  infrequent:  epistaxis, bronchitis, asthma, pneumonia;  rare:  asphyxia, laryngitis, pneumothorax, hiccup.



   Skin and Appendages  :  frequent:  pruritus, rash;  infrequent:  acne, exfoliative dermatitis, dry skin, herpes simplex, alopecia;  rare:  urticaria, herpes zoster, skin hypertrophy, seborrhea, skin ulcer.



   Special Senses  :  infrequent:  eye pain, abnormality of accommodation, conjunctivitis, deafness, keratoconjunctivitis, lacrimation disorder, angle-closure glaucoma, hyperacusis, ear pain;  rare:  blepharitis, partial transitory deafness, otitis media, taste loss, parosmia.



   Urogenital System  :  frequent:  urinary tract infection;  infrequent:  kidney calculus, cystitis, dysuria, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, vaginitis, hematuria, breast pain, amenorrhea, dysmenorrhea, leukorrhea, impotence;  rare:  polyuria, urethritis, metrorrhagia, menorrhagia, abnormal ejaculation, breast engorgement, breast enlargement, urinary urgency.



   Other Adverse Events Observed During Postmarketing Evaluation of REMERON

  Adverse events reported since market introduction, which were temporally (but not necessarily causally) related to mirtazapine therapy, include 4 cases of the ventricular arrhythmia torsades de pointes. In 3 of the 4 cases, however, concomitant drugs were implicated. All patients recovered.



 Cases of severe skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, bullous dermatitis, erythema multiforme and toxic epidermal necrolysis have also been reported.



 Increased creatine kinase blood levels have also been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

  Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of REMERONSolTab  (r)   (mirtazapine) Orally Disintegrating Tablets or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. REMERONSolTab is not approved for use in pediatric patients. (See   WARNINGS: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk  ,   PRECAUTIONS: Information for Patients  , and   PRECAUTIONS: Pediatric Use  .)  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
