<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="remodulin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in labeling: Infections associated with intravenous administration  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;3%) reported in clinical studies with Remodulin: subcutaneous infusion site pain and reaction, headache, diarrhea, nausea, jaw pain, vasodilatation, edema, and hypotension. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact United Therapeutics Corp. at 1-866-458-6479 or contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adverse Events with Subcutaneously Administered Remodulin  



 Patients receiving Remodulin as a subcutaneous infusion reported a wide range of adverse events, many potentially related to the underlying disease (dyspnea, fatigue, chest pain, right ventricular heart failure, and pallor). During clinical trials with subcutaneous infusion of Remodulin, infusion site pain and reaction were the most common adverse events among those treated with Remodulin. Infusion site reaction was defined as any local adverse event other than pain or bleeding/bruising at the infusion site and included symptoms such as erythema, induration or rash. Infusion site reactions were sometimes severe and could lead to discontinuation of treatment.



 Table 3: Percentages of subjects reporting subcutaneous infusion site adverse events 
                                    Reaction              Pain           
 Placebo                            Remodulin           Placebo            Remodulin      
  
 Severe                                 1                  38                  2                  39            
 Requiring narcotics                   NA                  NA                  1                  32            
 Leading to discontinuation             0                  3                   0                  7             
           Other adverse events included diarrhea, jaw pain, edema, vasodilatation and nausea, and these are generally considered to be related to the pharmacologic effects of Remodulin, whether administered subcutaneously or intravenously.
 

     Adverse Reactions during Chronic Dosing  



 Table 4 lists adverse reactions defined by a rate of at least 3% more frequent in patients treated with subcutaneous Remodulin than with placebo in controlled trials in PAH.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions in Controlled 12-Week Studies of Subcutaneous Remodulin and at least 3% more frequent than on Placebo. 
 Adverse Reaction                          Remodulin(N=236)Percent of Patients  Placebo(N=233)Percent of Patients   
  
 Infusion Site Pain                                      85                              27                 
 Infusion Site Reaction                                  83                              27                 
 Headache                                                27                              23                 
 Diarrhea                                                25                              16                 
 Nausea                                                  22                              18                 
 Rash                                                    14                              11                 
 Jaw Pain                                                13                              5                  
 Vasodilatation                                          11                              5                  
 Edema                                                   9                               3                  
         Reported adverse reactions (at least 3% more frequent on drug than on placebo) are included except those too general to be informative, and those not plausibly attributable to the use of the drug, because they were associated with the condition being treated or are very common in the treated population.
 

 While hypotension occurred in both groups, the event was experienced twice as frequently in the Remodulin group as compared to the placebo group (4% in Remodulin treatment group verses 2% in placebo-controlled group). As a potent vasodilator, hypotension is possible with the administration of Remodulin.



 The safety of Remodulin was also studied in a long-term, open-label extension study in which 860 patients were dosed for a mean duration of 1.6 years, with a maximum exposure of 4.6 years. Twenty-nine (29%) percent achieved a dose of at least 40 ng/kg/min (max: 290 ng/kg/min). The safety profile during this chronic dosing study was similar to that observed in the 12-week placebo controlled study except for the following suspected adverse drug reactions (occurring in at least 3% of patients): anorexia, vomiting, infusion site infection, asthenia, and abdominal pain.



     Adverse Events Attributable to the Drug Delivery System  



 In controlled studies of Remodulin administered subcutaneously, there were no reports of infection related to the drug delivery system. There were 187 infusion system complications reported in 28% of patients (23% Remodulin, 33% placebo); 173 (93%) were pump related and 14 (7%) related to the infusion set. Eight of these patients (4 Remodulin, 4 Placebo) reported non-serious adverse events resulting from infusion system complications. Adverse events resulting from problems with the delivery systems were typically related to either symptoms of excess Remodulin (e.g., nausea) or return of PAH symptoms (e.g., dyspnea). These events were generally resolved by correcting the delivery system pump or infusion set problem such as replacing the syringe or battery, reprogramming the pump, or straightening a crimped infusion line  .  Adverse events resulting from problems with the delivery system did not lead to clinical instability or rapid deterioration. In addition to these adverse events due to the drug delivery system during subcutaneous administration, the following adverse events may be attributable to the IV mode of infusion including arm swelling, paresthesias, hematoma and pain  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following events have been identified during post-approval use of Remodulin. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. The following events have been chosen for inclusion because of a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, and potential connection to Remodulin. These events are thrombophlebitis associated with peripheral intravenous infusion, thrombocytopenia bone pain, pruritus and dizziness. In addition, generalized rashes, sometimes macular or papular in nature, and cellulitis have been infrequently reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  For intravenous infusion use an indwelling central venous catheter. This route is associated with the risk of blood stream infections (BSIs) and sepsis, which may be fatal. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Do not abruptly lower the dose or withdraw dosing. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Catheter-Related Bloodstream Infection



  Chronic intravenous infusions of Remodulin are delivered using an indwelling central venous catheter. This route is associated with the risk of blood stream infections (BSIs) and sepsis, which may be fatal. Therefore, continuous subcutaneous infusion (undiluted) is the preferred mode of administration.



 In an open-label study of IV treprostinil (n=47), there were seven catheter-related line infections during approximately 35 patient years, or about 1 BSI event per 5 years of use. A CDC survey of seven sites that used IV treprostinil for the treatment of PAH found approximately 1 BSI (defined as any positive blood culture) event per 3 years of use. Administration of IV Remodulin with a high pH glycine diluent has been associated with a lower incidence of BSIs when compared to neutral diluents (sterile water, 0.9% sodium chloride) when used along with catheter care guidelines.



    5.2 Worsening PAH upon Abrupt Withdrawal or Sudden Large Dose Reduction



  Avoid abrupt withdrawal or sudden large reductions in dosage of Remodulin, which may result in worsening of PAH symptoms.



    5.3 Patients with Hepatic or Renal Insufficiency



  Titrate slowly in patients with hepatic or renal insufficiency, because such patients will likely be exposed to greater systemic concentrations relative to patients with normal hepatic or renal function [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4  ,  2.5)  ,  Use In Specific Populations (8.6  ,  8.7)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



    5.4 Effect of Other Drugs on Treprostinil



  Co-administration of a cytochrome P450 (CYP) 2C8 enzyme inhibitor (e.g., gemfibrozil) increases exposure (both Cmaxand AUC) to treprostinil. Co-administration of a CYP2C8 enzyme inducer (e.g., rifampin) decreases exposure to treprostinil [see  Drug Interactions (7.5)    and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
