<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="renvela1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Most of the safety experience is with sevelamer tablets. The most frequently occurring adverse reactions in a short term study with sevelamer carbonate tablets (8-week cross-over) study were: nausea (3%) and vomiting (3%). In a short term study of sevelamer carbonate powder, adverse events were similar to those reported for sevelamer carbonate tablets. In long-term studies with sevelamer hydrochloride, which contains the same active moiety as sevelamer carbonate, the most common adverse events included: vomiting (22%), nausea (20%), diarrhea (19%), dyspepsia (16%), abdominal pain (9%), flatulence (8%) and constipation (8%). (  6.1  ) 
 *  Cases of fecal impaction and, less commonly, ileus, bowel obstruction and bowel perforation have been reported. (  6.2  ) 
        To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genzyme Corporation at 1-800-847-0069 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug can not be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 There are limited data on the safety of Renvela. However, based on the fact that it contains the same active ingredient as the hydrochloride salt, the adverse event profiles of the two salts should be similar. In a cross-over study in hemodialysis patients with treatment durations of eight weeks each and no washout, the adverse reactions on sevelamer carbonate tablets were similar to those reported for sevelamer hydrochloride. In another cross-over study in hemodialysis patients, with treatment durations of four weeks each and no washout between treatment periods, the adverse reactions on sevelamer carbonate powder were similar to those reported for sevelamer hydrochloride.



 In a parallel design study of sevelamer hydrochloride with treatment duration of 52 weeks, adverse reactions reported for sevelamer hydrochloride (n=99) were similar to those reported for the active-comparator group (n=101). Overall adverse reactions among those treated with sevelamer hydrochloride occurring in &gt; 5% of patients included: vomiting (22%), nausea (20%), diarrhea (19%), dyspepsia (16%), abdominal pain (9%), flatulence (8%) and constipation (8%). A total of 27 patients treated with sevelamer and 10 patients treated with comparator withdrew from the study due to adverse reactions.



 Based on studies of 8-52 weeks, the most common reason for withdrawal from sevelamer hydrochloride was gastrointestinal adverse reactions (3-16%).



 In one hundred and forty-three peritoneal dialysis patients studied for 12 weeks using sevelamer hydrochloride, most adverse reactions were similar to adverse reactions observed in hemodialysis patients. The most frequently occurring treatment emergent serious adverse reaction was peritonitis (8 reactions in 8 patients [8%] in the sevelamer group and 2 reactions in 2 patients [4%] on active-control). Thirteen patients (14%) in the sevelamer group and 9 patients (20%) in the active-control group discontinued, mostly for gastrointestinal adverse reactions. Patients on peritoneal dialysis should be closely monitored to ensure the reliable use of appropriate aseptic technique with the prompt recognition and management of any signs and symptoms associated with peritonitis.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of sevelamer hydrochloride, which has the same active moiety as sevelamer carbonate: pruritus, rash, abdominal pain, fecal impaction, and uncommon cases of ileus, intestinal obstruction, and intestinal perforation    .    Appropriate medical management should be given to patients who develop constipation or have worsening of existing constipation to avoid severe complications.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious cases of dysphagia, bowel obstruction, and perforation have been associated with sevelamer use, some requiring hospitalization and surgery. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Gastrointestinal Adverse Events



   Cases of dysphagia and esophageal tablet retention have been reported in association with use of the tablet formulation of sevelamer, some requiring hospitalization and intervention. Consider using sevelamer suspension in patients with a history of swallowing disorders.  Cases of bowel obstruction and perforation have also been reported with sevelamer use.Patients with dysphagia, swallowing disorders, severe gastrointestinal (GI) motility disorders including severe constipation, or major GI tract surgery were not included in the Renvela clinical studies.
 

    5.2 Monitor Serum Chemistries



  Bicarbonate and chloride levels should be monitored.



    5.3 Monitor for Reduced Vitamins D, E, K (clotting factors) and Folic Acid Levels



  In preclinical studies in rats and dogs, sevelamer hydrochloride, which contains the same active moiety as sevelamer carbonate, reduced vitamins D, E, and K (coagulation parameters) and folic acid levels at doses of 6-10 times the recommended human dose. In short-term clinical trials, there was no evidence of reduction in serum levels of vitamins. However, in a one-year clinical trial, 25-hydroxyvitamin D (normal range 10 to 55 ng/mL) fell from 39 +/- 22 ng/mL to 34 +/- 22 ng/mL (p&lt;0.01) with sevelamer hydrochloride treatment. Most (approximately 75%) patients in sevelamer hydrochloride clinical trials received vitamin supplements, which is typical of patients on dialysis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
