<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rescula" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Most common adverse reactions (incidence 10-25%) are burning/stinging, burning/stinging upon drug instillation, dry eyes, itching, increased length of eyelashes and injection  (6.1)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sucampo Pharma Americas at 1-855-RESCULA (1-855-737-2852) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

      



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical studies, the most common ocular adverse reactions with use of Rescula were burning/stinging, burning/stinging upon drug instillation, dry eyes, itching, increased length of eyelashes, and injection. These were reported in approximately 10-25% of patients. Approximately 10-14% of patients were observed to have an increase in the length of eyelashes (&gt;= 1 mm) at 12 months, while 7% of patients were observed to have a decrease in the length of eyelashes.



 Ocular adverse reactions occurring in approximately 5-10% of patients were abnormal vision, eyelid disorder, foreign body sensation, and lacrimation disorder.



 Ocular adverse reactions occurring in approximately 1-5% of patients were blepharitis, cataract, conjunctivitis, corneal lesion, discharge from the eye, eye hemorrhage, eye pain, keratitis, irritation, photophobia, and vitreous disorder.



 Other ocular adverse reactions reported in less than 1% of patients were acute elevated intraocular pressure, color blindness, corneal deposits, corneal edema, corneal opacity, diplopia, hyperpigmentation of the eyelid, increased number of eyelashes, iris hyperpigmentation, iritis, optic atrophy, ptosis, retinal hemorrhage, and visual field defect.



 The most frequently reported nonocular adverse reaction associated with the use of Rescula in the clinical trials was flu-like syndrome that was observed in approximately 6% of patients. Nonocular adverse reactions reported in the 1-5% of patients were accidental injury, allergic reaction, back pain, bronchitis, increased cough, diabetes mellitus, dizziness, headache, hypertension, insomnia, pharyngitis, pain, rhinitis, and sinusitis.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Rescula. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Voluntary reports of adverse reactions occurring with the use of Rescula include corneal erosion.



 There have been rare spontaneous reports with a different formulation of unoprostone isopropyl (0.12%) of chemosis, dry mouth, nausea, vomiting and palpitations.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Rescula has been reported to increase pigmentation of the iris  (5.1)   
 *  Rescula has been reported to increase pigmentation of the periorbital tissues and eyelashes  (5.2)   
 *  Rescula should be used with caution in patients with active intraocular inflammation because the inflammation may be exacerbated  (5.3)   
    
 

   5.1 Iris Pigmentation



  Unoprostone isopropyl ophthalmic solution may gradually increase the pigmentation of the iris. The pigmentation change is believed to be due to increased melanin content in the melanocytes rather than to an increase in the number of melanocytes. The long term effects of increased pigmentation are not known. Iris color changes seen with administration of unoprostone isopropyl ophthalmic solution may not be noticeable for several months to years. Typically, the brown pigmentation around the pupil spreads concentrically towards the periphery of the iris and the entire iris or parts of the iris become more brownish. Neither nevi nor freckles of the iris appear to be affected by treatment. Treatment with Rescula solution can be continued in patients who develop noticeably increased iris pigmentation.



 Patients who receive treatment with Rescula should be informed of the possibility of increased pigmentation [see Patient Counseling Information  (17.2)  ]  .



    5.2 Lid Pigmentation



  Unoprostone isopropyl has been reported to cause pigment changes (darkening) to periorbital pigmented tissues and eyelashes. The pigmentation is expected to increase as long as unoprostone isopropyl is administered, but has been reported to be reversible upon discontinuation of unoprostone isopropyl ophthalmic solution in most patients.



    5.3 Intraocular Inflammation



  Rescula should be used with caution in patients with active intraocular inflammation (e.g., uveitis) because the inflammation may be exacerbated.



    5.4 Macular Edema



  Macular edema, including cystoid macular edema, has been reported. Rescula should be used with caution in aphakic patients, in pseudophakic patients with a torn posterior lens capsule, or in patients with known risk factors for macular edema.



    5.5 Contamination of Tip and Solution



  To minimize contaminating the dropper tip and solution, care should be taken not to touch the eyelids or surrounding areas with the dropper tip of the bottle. Keep bottle tightly closed when not in use. There have been reports of bacterial keratitis associated with the use of multiple-dose containers of topical ophthalmic products [see Patient Counseling Information  (17.1)  ].  



    5.6 Use with Contact Lenses



  Rescula contains benzalkonium chloride, which may be absorbed by soft contact lenses. Contact lenses should be removed prior to application of solution and may be reinserted 15 minutes following its administration [see Patient Counseling Information  (17.4)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
