<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="retisert" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *    Ocular adverse events included procedural complications, and eye pain (&gt; 50%). Thirty-five to forty percent of patients reported ocular/conjunctival hyperemia, reduced visual acuity, and conjunctival hemorrhage.  (6.1)   
 *    The most common non-ocular event reported was headache (&gt; 33%).  (6.2)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bausch &amp; Lomb at 1-800-323-0000 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience - Ocular Events

  The available safety data includes exposure to RETISERT in patients with chronic non-infectious uveitis affecting the posterior segment in two multicenter controlled clinical trials. Patients were randomized to dosage regimens of 0.59 mg or 2.1 mg implants.



 The most frequently reported ocular adverse events were cataract, increased intraocular pressure, procedural complication, and eye pain. These events occurred in approximately 50 - 90% of patients. Cataract includes aggravated cataract, and posterior capsular opacification. Procedural complications includes post-op complication, post-op wound complication, post-op wound site erythema, and wound dehiscense.



 Based on clinical trials with RETISERT, during the 3-year post-implantation period, nearly all phakic eyes are expected to develop cataracts and require cataract surgery. IOP lowering medications to lower intraocular pressure were required in approximately 77% of patients; filtering surgeries were required to control intraocular pressure in 37% of patients.



 Ocular adverse events occurring in approximately 10 - 40% of patients in decreasing order of incidence were ocular/conjunctival hyperemia, reduced visual acuity, glaucoma, conjunctival hemorrhage, blurred vision, abnormal sensation in the eye, eye irritation, maculopathy, vitreous floaters, hypotony, pruritus, ptosis, increased tearing, vitreous hemorrhage, dry eye, eyelid edema, macula edema and visual disturbance.



 Ocular adverse events occurring in approximately 5 - 9% of patients in decreasing order of incidence were eye discharge, photophobia, blepharitis, corneal edema, iris adhesions, choroidal detachment, diplopia, eye swelling, retinal detachment, photopsia, retinal hemorrhage and hyphema.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience - Non-Ocular Events

  The most frequently reported non-ocular adverse event was headache (33%). Other non-ocular adverse events occurring in approximately 5-20% of patients in decreasing order of incidence were nasopharyngitis, arthralgia, sinusitis, dizziness, pyrexia, upper respiratory tract infection, influenza, vomiting, nausea, cough, back pain, limb pain, and rash.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Cataract formation: Nearly all phakic patients are expected to develop cataracts and require cataract surgery.  (5.1)   
 *    Endophthalmitis: Late onset endophthalmitis has been observed.  (5.2)   
 *    Increase in intraocular pressure: Use of corticosteroids may result in elevated IOP and/or glaucoma.  (5.3)  IOP lowering medications were required in &gt; 75% of patients; filtering surgeries were required in &gt; 35% of patients.  (6.1)   
 *    Separation of implant components: Physicians should periodically monitor the integrity of the implant by visual inspection.  (5.4)   
    
 

   5.1 Cataract Formation



  Use of corticosteroids may result in posterior subcapsular cataract formation.



 Based on clinical trials with RETISERT, during the 3-year post implantation period, nearly all phakic eyes are expected to develop cataracts and require cataract surgery.



    5.2 Endophthalmitis and Surgical Complications



  Late onset endophthalmitis has been observed. These events are often related to the integrity of the surgical wound site. Careful attention to assure tight closure of the scleral wound and the integrity of the overlying conjunctiva at the wound site is important. 



 Potential complications accompanying intraocular surgery to place RETISERT into the vitreous cavity may include, but are not limited to, the following: cataract formation, choroidal detachment, endophthalmitis, hypotony, increased intraocular pressure, exacerbation of intraocular inflammation, retinal detachment, vitreous hemorrhage, vitreous loss, and wound dehiscence.



 Following implantation of RETISERT, nearly all patients will experience an immediate and temporary decrease in visual acuity in the implanted eye which lasts for approximately one to four weeks post-operatively.



    5.3 Increase in Intraocular Pressure



  Prolonged use of corticosteroids may result in elevated IOP and/or glaucoma with damage to the optic nerve, defects in visual acuity and fields of vision. Steroids should be used with caution in the presence of glaucoma. Patients must be monitored for elevated IOP. 



 Based on clinical trials with RETISERT, within 3-years post implantation, approximately 77% of patients will require IOP lowering medications to control intraocular pressure and 37% of patients will require filtering procedures to control intraocular pressure. (see  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience - Ocular Events  section).



    5.4 Separation of Implant Components



   In vitro  stability studies show that the strength of the adhesive bond between the silicone cup reservoir and the suture tab is reduced with prolonged hydration, indicating a potential for the separation of these components. The suture tab composition is a silicone elastomer reinforced with a polyester mesh. Physicians should periodically monitor the integrity of the implant by visual inspection. 



    5.5 Other Corticosteroid Induced Adverse Reactions



  RETISERT should be used with caution in patients with a history of a viral, bacterial, mycobacterial or fungal infection of the cornea and conjunctiva including epithelial herpes simplex keratitis (dendritic keratitis), vaccinia and varicella.



 Use of ocular steroids may prolong the course and may exacerbate the severity of many viral infections of the eye (including herpes simplex). Employment of a corticosteroid medication in the treatment of patients with a history of herpes simplex requires great caution.



 Prolonged use of corticosteroids may suppress the host response and thus increase the hazard of secondary ocular infections (bacterial, fungal, and viral). In acute purulent conditions of the eye, steroids may mask infection or enhance existing infection. Fungal and viral infections of the cornea are particularly prone to develop coincidentally with long-term application of steroids. The possibility of fungal invasion should be considered in any persistent corneal ulceration where steroid treatment has been used. 



 Since resistance to infections is known to be reduced by corticosteroids, simultaneous bilateral implantation should not be carried out, in order to limit the potential for bilateral post-operative infection. 



 Ocular administration of corticosteroids has also been associated with delayed wound healing and perforation of the globe where there is thinning of the sclera. 



 The use of steroids after cataract surgery may delay healing and increase the incidence of bleb formation.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
