<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="retrovir" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Hematologic toxicity, including neutropenia and anemia [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].  
 *    Symptomatic myopathy [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.3)].  
 *    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.4)].  
 *    Hepatic decompensation in patients co-infected with HIV-1 and hepatitis C [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)].  
   *     Most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 15%) in adult HIV-1 clinical trials were headache, malaise, nausea, anorexia, and vomiting. (   6.1   )  
 *     Most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 15%) in pediatric HIV-1 clinical trials were fever and cough. (   6.1   )  
 *     Most commonly reported adverse reactions in neonates (incidence greater than or equal to 15%) in the prevention of maternal-fetal transmission of HIV-1 clinical trial were anemia and neutropenia. (   6.1   )  
 *      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ViiV Healthcare at 1-877-844-8872 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
      EXCERPT:   
   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adults  



 The frequency and severity of adverse reactions associated with the use of RETROVIR are greater in patients with more advanced infection at the time of initiation of therapy.



 Table 3 summarizes adverse reactions reported at a statistically significant greater incidence for subjects receiving oral RETROVIR in a monotherapy trial.



 Table 3. Percentage (%) of Subjects with Adverse Reactions (Greater than or Equal to 5% Frequency) in Asymptomatic HIV-1 Infection (ACTG 019) 
  Adverse Reaction                    RETROVIR 500 mg/day  (n = 453)                  Placebo  (n = 428)    
  Body as a whole                                                                                          
     Asthenia                         9%a                                             6%                   
     Headache                         63%                                             53%                  
     Malaise                          53%                                             45%                  
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
     Anorexia                         20%                                             11%                  
     Constipation                     6%a                                             4%                   
     Nausea                           51%                                             30%                  
     Vomiting                         17%                                             10%                  
           a  Not statistically significant versus placebo.
 

 In addition to the adverse reactions listed in Table 3, adverse reactions observed at an incidence of greater than or equal to 5% in any treatment arm in clinical trials (NUCA3001, NUCA3002, NUCB3001, and NUCB3002) were abdominal cramps, abdominal pain, arthralgia, chills, dyspepsia, fatigue, insomnia, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia, and neuropathy. Additionally, in these trials hyperbilirubinemia was reported at an incidence of less than or equal to 0.8%.



 Selected laboratory abnormalities observed during a clinical trial of monotherapy with oral RETROVIR are shown in Table 4.



 Table 4. Frequencies of Selected (Grade 3/4) Laboratory Abnormalities in Subjects with Asymptomatic HIV-1 Infection (ACTG 019) 
  Test  (Abnormal Level)                                 RETROVIR 500 mg/day  (n = 453)     Placebo  (n = 428)    
  Anemia (Hgb&lt;8 g/dL)                                    1%                                 &lt;1%             
  Granulocytopenia (&lt;750 cells/mm3)                      2%                                 2%              
  Thrombocytopenia (platelets&lt;50,000/mm3)                0%                                 &lt;1%             
  ALT (&gt;5 x ULN)                                         3%                                 3%              
  AST (&gt;5 x ULN)                                         1%                                 2%              
         ULN = Upper limit of normal.
 

 The adverse reactions reported during IV administration of RETROVIR injection are similar to those reported with oral administration; neutropenia and anemia were reported most frequently. Long term IV administration beyond 2 to 4 weeks has not been studied in adults and may enhance hematologic adverse reactions. Local reaction, pain, and slight irritation during IV administration occur infrequently.



   Pediatrics  



 The clinical adverse reactions reported among adult recipients of RETROVIR may also occur in pediatric patients.



   Trial ACTG 300:  Selected clinical adverse reactions and physical findings with a greater than or equal to 5% frequency during therapy with EPIVIR  (r)  (lamivudine) oral suspension 4 mg per kg twice daily plus RETROVIR 160 mg per m  2  3 times daily compared with didanosine in therapy-naive (less than or equal to 56 days of antiretroviral therapy) pediatric subjects are listed in Table 5.



 Table 5. Selected Clinical Adverse Reactions and Physical Findings (Greater than or Equal to 5% Frequency) in Pediatric Subjects in Trial ACTG 300 
  Adverse Reaction                                 EPIVIR plus RETROVIR  (n = 236)       Didanosine  (n = 235)    
  Body as a whole                                                                                           
     Fever                                         25%                                   32%                
  Digestive                                                                                                 
     Hepatomegaly                                  11%                                   11%                
     Nausea &amp; vomiting                             8%                                    7%                 
     Diarrhea                                      8%                                    6%                 
     Stomatitis                                    6%                                    12%                
     Splenomegaly                                  5%                                    8%                 
  Respiratory                                                                                               
     Cough                                         15%                                   18%                
     Abnormal breath sounds/wheezing               7%                                    9%                 
  Ear, Nose, and Throat                                                                                     
     Signs or symptoms of earsa                    7%                                    6%                 
     Nasal discharge or congestion                 8%                                    11%                
  Other                                                                                                     
     Skin rashes                                   12%                                   14%                
     Lymphadenopathy                               9%                                    11%                
           a  Includes pain, discharge, erythema, or swelling of an ear.
 

 Selected laboratory abnormalities experienced by therapy-naive (less than or equal to 56 days of antiretroviral therapy) pediatric subjects are listed in Table 6.



 Table 6. Frequencies of Selected (Grade 3/4) Laboratory Abnormalities in Pediatric Subjects in Trial ACTG 300 
  Test  (Abnormal Level)                               EPIVIR plus RETROVIR                Didanosine        
  Neutropenia (ANC&lt;400 cells/mm3)                      8%                                  3%                
  Anemia (Hgb&lt;7.0 g/dL)                                4%                                  2%                
  Thrombocytopenia (platelets&lt;50,000/mm3)              1%                                  3%                
  ALT (&gt;10 x ULN)                                      1%                                  3%                
  AST (&gt;10 x ULN)                                      2%                                  4%                
  Lipase (&gt;2.5 x ULN)                                  3%                                  3%                
  Total amylase (&gt;2.5 x ULN)                           3%                                  3%                
         ULN = Upper limit of normal.
 

 ANC = Absolute neutrophil count.



 Macrocytosis was reported in the majority of pediatric subjects receiving RETROVIR 180 mg per m  2  every 6 hours in open-label trials. Additionally, adverse reactions reported at an incidence of less than 6% in these trials were congestive heart failure, decreased reflexes, ECG abnormality, edema, hematuria, left ventricular dilation, nervousness/irritability, and weight loss.



   Use for the Prevention of Maternal-Fetal Transmission of HIV-1  



 In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in HIV-1-infected women and their neonates conducted to determine the utility of RETROVIR for the prevention of maternal-fetal HIV-1 transmission, RETROVIR syrup at 2 mg per kg was administered every 6 hours for 6 weeks to neonates beginning within 12 hours following birth. The most commonly reported adverse reactions were anemia (hemoglobin less than 9.0 g per dL) and neutropenia (less than 1,000 cells per mm  3  ). Anemia occurred in 22% of the neonates who received RETROVIR and in 12% of the neonates who received placebo. The mean difference in hemoglobin values was less than 1.0 g per dL for neonates receiving RETROVIR compared with neonates receiving placebo. No neonates with anemia required transfusion and all hemoglobin values spontaneously returned to normal within 6 weeks after completion of therapy with RETROVIR. Neutropenia in neonates was reported with similar frequency in the group that received RETROVIR (21%) and in the group that received placebo (27%). The long-term consequences of in utero and infant exposure to RETROVIR are unknown.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of RETROVIR. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole:  Back pain, chest pain, flu-like syndrome, generalized pain, redistribution/accumulation of body fat  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  .



   Cardiovascular:  Cardiomyopathy, syncope.



   Eye:  Macular edema.



   Gastrointestinal:  Constipation, dysphagia, flatulence, oral mucosa pigmentation, mouth ulcer.



   General:  Sensitization reactions including anaphylaxis and angioedema, vasculitis.



   Hematologic:  Aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia with marrow hypoplasia, pure red cell aplasia.



   Hepatobiliary:  Hepatitis, hepatomegaly with steatosis, jaundice, lactic acidosis, pancreatitis.



   Musculoskeletal:  Increased CPK, increased LDH, muscle spasm, myopathy and myositis with pathological changes (similar to that produced by HIV-1 disease), rhabdomyolysis, tremor.



   Nervous:  Anxiety, confusion, depression, dizziness, loss of mental acuity, mania, paresthesia, seizures, somnolence, vertigo.



   Reproductive System and Breast:  Gynecomastia.



   Respiratory:  Dyspnea, rhinitis, sinusitis.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue:  Changes in skin and nail pigmentation, pruritus, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, sweating, urticaria.



   Special Senses:  Amblyopia, hearing loss, photophobia, taste perversion.



   Renal and Urinary:  Urinary frequency, urinary hesitancy.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF HEMATOLOGICAL TOXICITY, MYOPATHY, LACTIC ACIDOSIS

  WARNING: RISK OF HEMATOLOGICAL TOXICITY, MYOPATHY, LACTIC ACIDOSIS

      Hematologic Toxicity    



   RETROVIR  (r)   (zidovudine) capsules, syrup, and injection have been associated with hematologic toxicity including neutropenia and severe anemia, particularly in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .  



     Myopathy    



   Prolonged use of RETROVIR has been associated with symptomatic myopathy   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  .  



     Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly    



   Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues alone or in combination, including RETROVIR and other antiretrovirals. Suspend treatment if clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity occur   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF HEMATOLOGICAL TOXICITY, MYOPATHY, LACTIC ACIDOSIS



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Hematologic toxicity including neutropenia and severe anemia have been associated with the use of zidovudine. (5.1) 
 *  Symptomatic myopathy associated with prolonged use of zidovudine. (5.3) 
 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues including RETROVIR. Suspend treatment if clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity occur. (5.4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    See boxed warning for information about the following: hematologic toxicity, myopathy, and lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly (  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
 *    The vial stoppers for RETROVIR injection contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Exacerbation of anemia has been reported in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving ribavirin and zidovudine. Coadministration of ribavirin and zidovudine is not advised. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Hepatic decompensation, (some fatal), has occurred in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy and interferon alfa with/without ribavirin. Discontinue zidovudine as medically appropriate and consider dose reduction or discontinuation of interferon alfa, ribavirin, or both. (  5.5  ) 
 *    RETROVIR should not be administered with other zidovudine-containing combination products. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Immune reconstitution syndrome (  5.7  ) and redistribution/accumulation of body fat (  5.8  ) have been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy. 
    
 

   5.1 Hematologic Toxicity/Bone Marrow Suppression



  RETROVIR should be used with caution in patients who have bone marrow compromise evidenced by granulocyte count less than 1,000 cells per mm  3  or hemoglobin less than 9.5 g per dL. Hematologic toxicities appear to be related to pretreatment bone marrow reserve and to dose and duration of therapy. In patients with advanced symptomatic HIV-1 disease, anemia and neutropenia were the most significant adverse events observed. In patients who experience hematologic toxicity, a reduction in hemoglobin may occur as early as 2 to 4 weeks, and neutropenia usually occurs after 6 to 8 weeks. There have been reports of pancytopenia associated with the use of RETROVIR, which was reversible in most instances after discontinuance of the drug. However, significant anemia, in many cases requiring dose adjustment, discontinuation of RETROVIR, and/or blood transfusions, has occurred during treatment with RETROVIR alone or in combination with other antiretrovirals.



 Frequent blood counts are strongly recommended to detect severe anemia or neutropenia in patients with poor bone marrow reserve, particularly in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease who are treated with RETROVIR. For HIV-1-infected individuals and patients with asymptomatic or early HIV-1 disease, periodic blood counts are recommended. If anemia or neutropenia develops, dosage interruption may be needed [see Dosage and Administration (2.4)]  .



    5.2 Latex



  The vial stoppers for RETROVIR injection contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals.



    5.3 Myopathy



  Myopathy and myositis with pathological changes, similar to that produced by HIV-1 disease, have been associated with prolonged use of RETROVIR.



    5.4 Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues alone or in combination, including zidovudine and other antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged exposure to antiretroviral nucleoside analogues may be risk factors. Particular caution should be exercised when administering RETROVIR to any patient with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors. Treatment with RETROVIR should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.5 Use with Interferon- and Ribavirin-based Regimens in HIV-1/HCV Co-infected Patients



  In vitro studies have shown ribavirin can reduce the phosphorylation of pyrimidine nucleoside analogues such as zidovudine. Although no evidence of a pharmacokinetic or pharmacodynamic interaction (e.g., loss of HIV-1/HCV virologic suppression) was seen when ribavirin was coadministered with zidovudine in HIV-1/HCV co-infected subjects [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  , exacerbation of anemia due to ribavirin has been reported when zidovudine is part of the HIV regimen. Coadministration of ribavirin and zidovudine is not advised. Consideration should be given to replacing zidovudine in established combination HIV-1/HCV therapy, especially in patients with a known history of zidovudine-induced anemia.



 Hepatic decompensation (some fatal) has occurred in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy for HIV-1 and interferon alfa with or without ribavirin. Patients receiving interferon alfa with or without ribavirin and zidovudine should be closely monitored for treatment-associated toxicities, especially hepatic decompensation, neutropenia, and anemia.



 Discontinuation of zidovudine should be considered as medically appropriate. Dose reduction or discontinuation of interferon alfa, ribavirin, or both should also be considered if worsening clinical toxicities are observed, including hepatic decompensation (e.g., Child-Pugh greater than 6) (see the complete prescribing information for interferon and ribavirin).



    5.6 Use with Other Zidovudine-containing Products



  RETROVIR should not be administered with combination products that contain zidovudine as one of their components (e.g., COMBIVIR  (r)  [lamivudine and zidovudine] tablets or TRIZIVIR  (r)  [abacavir sulfate, lamivudine, and zidovudine] tablets).



    5.7 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including RETROVIR. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune systems respond may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia [PCP], or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.8 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat, including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance," have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
