<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="reyataz0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    cardiac conduction abnormalities [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]  
 *    rash [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]  
 *    hyperbilirubinemia [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]  
 *    nephrolithiasis and cholelithiasis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) are nausea, jaundice/scleral icterus, rash, headache, abdominal pain, vomiting, insomnia, peripheral neurologic symptoms, dizziness, myalgia, diarrhea, depression, and fever.  (6.1  ,  6.2)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience in Adults

  Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Treatment-Naive Patients

  The safety profile of REYATAZ in treatment-naive adults is based on 1625 HIV-1 infected patients in clinical trials. 536 patients received REYATAZ 300 mg with ritonavir 100 mg and 1089 patients received REYATAZ 400 mg or higher (without ritonavir).



 The most common adverse reactions were nausea, jaundice/scleral icterus, and rash.



 Selected clinical adverse reactions of moderate or severe intensity reported in &gt;=2% of treatment-naive patients receiving combination therapy including REYATAZ 300 mg with ritonavir 100 mg and REYATAZ 400 mg (without ritonavir) are presented in Tables 7 and 8, respectively.



 Table 7: Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactionsa of Moderate or Severe Intensity Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Treatment-Naive Patients,b Study AI424-138 
                                   96 weeks  c                          96 weeks  c                         
                                   REYATAZ 300 mg with ritonavir    100 mg (once daily) and tenofovir    with emtricitabine  d        lopinavir 400 mg with ritonavir    100 mg (twice daily) and tenofovir    with emtricitabine  d       
                                   (n=441)                              (n=437)                             
  
 * None reported in this treatment arm.  a  Includes events of possible, probable, certain, or unknown relationship to treatment regimen.  b  Based on the regimen containing REYATAZ.  c  Median time on therapy.  d  As a fixed-dose combination: 300 mg tenofovir, 200 mg emtricitabine once daily.   
  
  Digestive System                                                                                          
     Nausea                       4%                                   8%                                   
     Jaundice/scleral icterus     5%                                   *                                    
     Diarrhea                     2%                                   12%                                  
  Skin and Appendages                                                                                       
     Rash                         3%                                   2%                                   
        Table 8: Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactionsa of Moderate or Severe Intensity Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Treatment-Naive Patients,b Studies AI424-034, AI424-007, and AI424-008 
                         Study AI424-034       Studies AI424-007, -008     
   64 weeks  c      REYATAZ 400 mg once daily + lamivudine + zidovudine  e        64 weeks  c      efavirenz 600 mg once daily + lamivudine + zidovudine  e        120 weeks  c,d      REYATAZ 400 mg once daily + stavudine + lamivudine or didanosine      73 weeks  c,d      nelfinavir 750 mg TID or 1250 mg BID + stavudine + lamivudine or didanosine     
   (n=404)               (n=401)               (n=279)               (n=191)              
  
 * None reported in this treatment arm.  a   Includes events of possible, probable, certain, or unknown relationship to treatment regimen.  b   Based on regimens containing REYATAZ.  c   Median time on therapy.  d   Includes long-term follow-up.  e   As a fixed-dose combination: 150 mg lamivudine, 300 mg zidovudine twice daily.   
  
  Body as a Whole       
     Headache           6%                    6%                    1%                    2%                    
  Digestive System      
     Nausea             14%                   12%                   6%                    4%                    
     Jaundice/scleral    icterus    7%                    *                     7%                    *                     
     Vomiting           4%                    7%                    3%                    3%                    
     Abdominal pain     4%                    4%                    4%                    2%                    
     Diarrhea           1%                    2%                    3%                    16%                   
  Nervous System        
     Insomnia           3%                    3%                    &lt;1%                   *                     
     Dizziness          2%                    7%                    &lt;1%                   *                     
     Peripheral    neurologic    symptoms    &lt;1%                   1%                    4%                    3%                    
  Skin and Appendages    
     Rash               7%                    10%                   5%                    1%                    
             Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Treatment-Experienced Patients
   The safety profile of REYATAZ in treatment-experienced adults is based on 119 HIV-1 infected patients in clinical trials.



 The most common adverse reactions are jaundice/scleral icterus and myalgia.



 Selected clinical adverse reactions of moderate or severe intensity reported in &gt;=2% of treatment-experienced patients receiving REYATAZ/ritonavir are presented in Table 9.



 Table 9: Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactionsa of Moderate or Severe Intensity Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Treatment-Experienced Patients,b Study AI424-045 
                                      48 weeks  c      REYATAZ/ritonavir 300/100 mg    once daily + tenofovir + NRTI      48 weeks  c      lopinavir/ritonavir 400/100 mg    twice daily  d  + tenofovir + NRTI     
   (n=119)                            (n=118)                           
  
 * None reported in this treatment arm.  a  Includes events of possible, probable, certain, or unknown relationship to treatment regimen.  b  Based on the regimen containing REYATAZ.  c  Median time on therapy.  d  As a fixed-dose combination.   
  
  Body as a Whole                    
     Fever                           2%                                 *                                  
  Digestive System                   
     Jaundice/scleral icterus        9%                                 *                                  
     Diarrhea                        3%                                 11%                                
     Nausea                          3%                                 2%                                 
  Nervous System                     
     Depression                      2%                                 &lt;1%                                
  Musculoskeletal System             
     Myalgia                         4%                                 *                                  
           Laboratory Abnormalities in Treatment-Naive Patients
   The percentages of adult treatment-naive patients treated with combination therapy including REYATAZ 300 mg with ritonavir 100 mg and REYATAZ 400 mg (without ritonavir) with Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities are presented in Tables 10 and 11, respectively.



 Table 10: Grade 3-4 Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Treatment-Naive Patients,a Study AI424-138 
   a  Based on the regimen containing REYATAZ.  b  Median time on therapy.  c  ULN = upper limit of normal.  d  As a fixed-dose combination: 300 mg tenofovir, 200 mg emtricitabine once daily.   
  
  Variable              Limitc                96 weeksb                       96 weeksb                       
  REYATAZ 300 mgwith ritonavir 100 mg(once daily) and tenofovirwith emtricitabined    lopinavir 400 mgwith ritonavir 100 mg(twice daily) and tenofovirwith emtricitabined    
  (n=441)               (n=437)               
  Chemistry             High                                                                                  
     SGOT/AST           &gt;=5.1 * ULN           3%                              1%                              
     SGPT/ALT           &gt;=5.1 * ULN           3%                              2%                              
     Total Bilirubin    &gt;=2.6 * ULN           44%                             &lt;1%                             
     Lipase             &gt;=2.1 * ULN           2%                              2%                              
     Creatine Kinase    &gt;=5.1 * ULN           8%                              7%                              
     Total Cholesterol    &gt;=240 mg/dL           11%                             25%                             
  Hematology            Low                                                                                   
     Neutrophils        &lt;750 cells/mm3        5%                              2%                              
         Table 11: Grade 3-4 Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Treatment-Naive Patients,a Studies AI424-034, AI424-007, and AI424-008 
   Variable             Limit  d         Study AI424-034      Studies AI424-007, -008     
   64 weeks  b          64 weeks  b        120 weeks  b,c        73 weeks  b,c       
   REYATAZ    400 mg    once daily    + lamivudine    + zidovudine  e        efavirenz    600 mg    once daily    + lamivudine    + zidovudine  e        REYATAZ    400 mg    once daily    + stavudine    + lamivudine or    + stavudine    + didanosine      nelfinavir    750 mg TID or    1250 mg BID    + stavudine    + lamivudine or    + stavudine    + didanosine     
   (n=404)              (n=401)          (n=279)          (n=191)          
  
 * None reported in this treatment arm.  a  Based on regimen(s) containing REYATAZ.  b  Median time on therapy.  c  Includes long-term follow-up.  d  ULN = upper limit of normal.  e  As a fixed-dose combination: 150 mg lamivudine, 300 mg zidovudine twice daily.   
  
  Chemistry            High                              
     SGOT/AST          &gt;=5.1 * ULN      2%               2%                7%                5%                  
     SGPT/ALT          &gt;=5.1 * ULN      4%               3%                9%                7%                  
     Total Bilirubin    &gt;=2.6 * ULN      35%              &lt;1%               47%               3%                  
     Amylase           &gt;=2.1 * ULN      *                *                 14%               10%                 
     Lipase            &gt;=2.1 * ULN      &lt;1%              1%                4%                5%                  
     Creatine Kinase    &gt;=5.1 * ULN      6%               6%                11%               9%                  
     Total Cholesterol    &gt;=240 mg/dL      6%               24%               19%               48%                 
     Triglycerides     &gt;=751 mg/dL      &lt;1%              3%                4%                2%                  
  Hematology           Low                               
     Hemoglobin        &lt;8.0 g/dL        5%               3%                &lt;1%               4%                  
     Neutrophils       &lt;750 cells/mm3    7%               9%                3%                7%                  
              Laboratory Abnormalities in Treatment-Experienced Patients
   The percentages of adult treatment-experienced patients treated with combination therapy including REYATAZ/ritonavir with Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities are presented in Table 12.



 Table 12: Grade 3-4 Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=2% of Adult Treatment-Experienced Patients, Study AI424-045a 
   Variable              Limit  c              48 weeks  b                     48 weeks  b                    
   REYATAZ/ritonavir    300/100 mg once daily    + tenofovir + NRTI      lopinavir/ritonavir    400/100 mg twice daily  d      + tenofovir + NRTI     
   (n=119)               (n=118)              
  
   a  Based on regimen(s) containing REYATAZ.  b  Median time on therapy.  c  ULN = upper limit of normal.  d  As a fixed-dose combination.   
  
  Chemistry             High                                                  
     SGOT/AST           &gt;=5.1 * ULN           3%                              3%                              
     SGPT/ALT           &gt;=5.1 * ULN           4%                              3%                              
     Total Bilirubin    &gt;=2.6 * ULN           49%                             &lt;1%                             
     Lipase             &gt;=2.1 * ULN           5%                              6%                              
     Creatine Kinase    &gt;=5.1 * ULN           8%                              8%                              
     Total Cholesterol    &gt;=240 mg/dL           25%                             26%                             
     Triglycerides      &gt;=751 mg/dL           8%                              12%                             
     Glucose            &gt;=251 mg/dL           5%                              &lt;1%                             
  Hematology            Low                                                   
     Platelets          &lt;50,000 cells/mm3     2%                              3%                              
     Neutrophils        &lt;750 cells/mm3        7%                              8%                              
            Lipids, Change from Baseline in Treatment-Naive Patients
   For Study AI424-138 and Study AI424-034, changes from baseline in LDL-cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, total cholesterol, and triglycerides are shown in Tables 13 and 14, respectively.



 Table 13: Lipid Values, Mean Change from Baseline, Study AI424-138 
                 REYATAZ/ritonavir  a,b        lopinavir/ritonavir  b,c       
   Baseline      Week 48      Week 96      Baseline      Week 48      Week 96     
   mg/dL         mg/dL      Change  d        mg/dL      Change  d        mg/dL      mg/dL      Change  d        mg/dL      Change  d       
   (n=428  e  )      (n=372  e  )      (n=372  e  )      (n=342  e  )      (n=342  e  )      (n=424  e  )      (n=335  e  )      (n=335  e  )      (n=291  e  )      (n=291  e  )     
  
   a  REYATAZ 300 mg with ritonavir 100 mg once daily with the fixed-dose combination: 300 mg tenofovir, 200 mg emtricitabine once daily.  b  Values obtained after initiation of serum lipid-reducing agents were not included in these analyses. At baseline, serum lipid-reducing agents were used in 1% in the lopinavir/ritonavir treatment arm and 1% in the REYATAZ/ritonavir arm. Through Week 48, serum lipid-reducing agents were used in 8% in the lopinavir/ritonavir treatment arm and 2% in the REYATAZ/ritonavir arm. Through Week 96, serum lipid-reducing agents were used in 10% in the lopinavir/ritonavir treatment arm and 3% in the REYATAZ/ritonavir arm.  c  Lopinavir 400 mg with ritonavir 100 mg twice daily with the fixed-dose combination 300 mg tenofovir, 200 mg emtricitabine once daily.  d  The change from baseline is the mean of within-patient changes from baseline for patients with both baseline and Week 48 or Week 96 values and is not a simple difference of the baseline and Week 48 or Week 96 mean values, respectively.  e  Number of patients with LDL-cholesterol measured.  f  Fasting.   
  
  LDL-Cholesterolf    92         105        +14%       105        +14%       93         111        +19%       110        +17%       
  HDL-Cholesterolf    37         46         +29%       44         +21%       36         48         +37%       46         +29%       
  Total Cholesterolf    149        169        +13%       169        +13%       150        187        +25%       186        +25%       
  Triglyceridesf    126        145        +15%       140        +13%       129        194        +52%       184        +50%       
                Table 14: Lipid Values, Mean Change from Baseline, Study AI424-034 
                           REYATAZ  a,b        efavirenz  b,c       
   Baseline                Week 48        Week 48        Baseline       Week 48        Week 48       
   mg/dL                   mg/dL          Change  d        mg/dL          mg/dL          Change  d       
   (n=383  e  )            (n=283  e  )      (n=272  e  )      (n=378  e  )      (n=264  e  )      (n=253  e  )     
  
   a  REYATAZ 400 mg once daily with the fixed-dose combination: 150 mg lamivudine, 300 mg zidovudine twice daily.  b  Values obtained after initiation of serum lipid-reducing agents were not included in these analyses. At baseline, serum lipid-reducing agents were used in 0% in the efavirenz treatment arm and &lt;1% in the REYATAZ arm. Through Week 48, serum lipid-reducing agents were used in 3% in the efavirenz treatment arm and 1% in the REYATAZ arm.  c  Efavirenz 600 mg once daily with the fixed-dose combination: 150 mg lamivudine, 300 mg zidovudine twice daily.  d  The change from baseline is the mean of within-patient changes from baseline for patients with both baseline and Week 48 values and is not a simple difference of the baseline and Week 48 mean values.  e  Number of patients with LDL-cholesterol measured.  f  Fasting.   
  
  LDL-Cholesterolf        98             98             +1%            98             114            +18%           
  HDL-Cholesterol         39             43             +13%           38             46             +24%           
  Total Cholesterol       164            168            +2%            162            195            +21%           
  Triglyceridesf          138            124            -9%            129            168            +23%           
               Lipids, Change from Baseline in Treatment-Experienced Patients
   For Study AI424-045, changes from baseline in LDL-cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, total cholesterol, and triglycerides are shown in Table 15. The observed magnitude of dyslipidemia was less with REYATAZ/ritonavir than with lopinavir/ritonavir. However, the clinical impact of such findings has not been demonstrated.



 Table 15: Lipid Values, Mean Change from Baseline, Study AI424-045 
                           REYATAZ/ritonavir  a,b        lopinavir/ritonavir  b,c       
   Baseline                Week 48        Week 48        Baseline       Week 48        Week 48       
   mg/dL                   mg/dL          Change  d        mg/dL          mg/dL          Change  d       
   (n=111  e  )            (n=75  e  )      (n=74  e  )      (n=108  e  )      (n=76  e  )      (n=73  e  )     
  
   a  REYATAZ 300 mg once daily + ritonavir + tenofovir + 1 NRTI.  b  Values obtained after initiation of serum lipid-reducing agents were not included in these analyses. At baseline, serum lipid-reducing agents were used in 4% in the lopinavir/ritonavir treatment arm and 4% in the REYATAZ/ritonavir arm. Through Week 48, serum lipid-reducing agents were used in 19% in the lopinavir/ritonavir treatment arm and 8% in the REYATAZ/ritonavir arm.  c  Lopinavir/ritonavir (400/100 mg) BID + tenofovir + 1 NRTI.  d  The change from baseline is the mean of within-patient changes from baseline for patients with both baseline and Week 48 values and is not a simple difference of the baseline and Week 48 mean values.  e  Number of patients with LDL-cholesterol measured.  f  Fasting.   
  
  LDL-Cholesterolf        108            98             -10%           104            103            +1%            
  HDL-Cholesterol         40             39             -7%            39             41             +2%            
  Total Cholesterol       188            170            -8%            181            187            +6%            
  Triglyceridesf          215            161            -4%            196            224            +30%           
               6.2 Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Patients
   Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients: REYATAZ Capsules

  The safety and tolerability of REYATAZ Capsules with and without ritonavir have been established in pediatric patients at least 6 years of age from the open-label, multicenter clinical trial PACTG 1020A.



 The safety profile of REYATAZ in pediatric patients (6 to less than 18 years of age) taking the capsule formulation was generally similar to that observed in clinical studies of REYATAZ in adults. The most common Grade 2-4 adverse events (&gt;=5%, regardless of causality) reported in pediatric patients were cough (21%), fever (18%), jaundice/scleral icterus (15%), rash (14%), vomiting (12%), diarrhea (9%), headache (8%), peripheral edema (7%), extremity pain (6%), nasal congestion (6%), oropharyngeal pain (6%), wheezing (6%), and rhinorrhea (6%). Asymptomatic second-degree atrioventricular block was reported in &lt;2% of patients. The most common Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities occurring in pediatric patients taking the capsule formulation were elevation of total bilirubin (&gt;=3.2 mg/dL, 58%), neutropenia (9%), and hypoglycemia (4%). All other Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities occurred with a frequency of less than 3%.



   Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients: REYATAZ Oral Powder

  The data described below reflect exposure to REYATAZ oral powder in 89 subjects weighing from 10 kg to less than 25 kg, including 65 patients exposed for 48 weeks. These data are from two pooled open-label, multi-center clinical trials in treatment-naive and treatment-experienced pediatric patients (AI424-397 [PRINCE I] and AI424-451 [PRINCE II]). Age ranged from 15 months to less than 7.5 years of age. In these studies 53% were female and 47% were male. All patients received ritonavir and 2 nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs).



 The safety profile of REYATAZ in pediatric patients taking REYATAZ oral powder was generally similar to that observed in clinical studies of REYATAZ in pediatric patients taking REYATAZ capsules. The most common Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities occurring in pediatric patients weighing 10 kg to less than 25 kg taking REYATAZ oral powder were increased amylase (19%), neutropenia (12%), increased SGPT/ALT (5%), elevation of total bilirubin (&gt;=2.6 times ULN, 12%), increased lipase (5%), and decreased hemoglobin (3%). All other Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities occurred with a frequency of less than 3%.



   6.3 Patients Co-Infected with Hepatitis B and/or Hepatitis C Virus

  In study AI424-138, 60 patients treated with REYATAZ/ritonavir 300 mg/100 mg once daily, and 51 patients treated with lopinavir/ritonavir 400 mg/100 mg twice daily, each with fixed dose tenofovir-emtricitabine, were seropositive for hepatitis B and/or C at study entry. ALT levels &gt;5 times ULN developed in 10% (6/60) of the REYATAZ/ritonavir-treated patients and 8% (4/50) of the lopinavir/ritonavir-treated patients. AST levels &gt;5 times ULN developed in 10% (6/60) of the REYATAZ/ritonavir-treated patients and none (0/50) of the lopinavir/ritonavir-treated patients.



 In study AI424-045, 20 patients treated with REYATAZ/ritonavir 300 mg/100 mg once daily, and 18 patients treated with lopinavir/ritonavir 400 mg/100 mg twice daily, were seropositive for hepatitis B and/or C at study entry. ALT levels &gt;5 times ULN developed in 25% (5/20) of the REYATAZ/ritonavir-treated patients and 6% (1/18) of the lopinavir/ritonavir-treated patients. AST levels &gt;5 times ULN developed in 10% (2/20) of the REYATAZ/ritonavir-treated patients and 6% (1/18) of the lopinavir/ritonavir-treated patients.



 In studies AI424-008 and AI424-034, 74 patients treated with 400 mg of REYATAZ once daily, 58 who received efavirenz, and 12 who received nelfinavir were seropositive for hepatitis B and/or C at study entry. ALT levels &gt;5 times ULN developed in 15% of the REYATAZ-treated patients, 14% of the efavirenz-treated patients, and 17% of the nelfinavir-treated patients. AST levels &gt;5 times ULN developed in 9% of the REYATAZ-treated patients, 5% of the efavirenz-treated patients, and 17% of the nelfinavir-treated patients. Within REYATAZ and control regimens, no difference in frequency of bilirubin elevations was noted between seropositive and seronegative patients.  [See      Warnings and Precautions (5.3)      .]  



   6.4 Postmarketing Experience

  The following events have been identified during postmarketing use of REYATAZ. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole:  edema



   Cardiovascular System:  second-degree AV block, third-degree AV block, left bundle branch block, QTc prolongation  [see      Warnings and Precautions (5.1)      ]  



   Gastrointestinal System:  pancreatitis



   Hepatic System:  hepatic function abnormalities



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  cholelithiasis  [see      Warnings and Precautions (5.5)      ]  , cholecystitis, cholestasis



   Metabolic System and Nutrition Disorders:  diabetes mellitus, hyperglycemia  [see      Warnings and Precautions (5.8)      ]  



   Musculoskeletal System:  arthralgia



   Renal System:  nephrolithiasis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  , interstitial nephritis



   Skin and Appendages:  alopecia, maculopapular rash  [see  Contraindications (4)  and      Warnings and Precautions (5.2)      ]  , pruritus, angioedema
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Cardiac conduction abnormalities: PR interval prolongation may occur in some patients. ECG monitoring should be considered in patients with preexisting conduction system disease or when administered with other drugs that may prolong the PR interval.  (5.1  ,  7.3  ,  12.2  ,  17  ) 
 *     Rash: Discontinue if severe rash develops.  (5.2  ,  17)   
 *     Hyperbilirubinemia: Most patients experience asymptomatic increases in indirect bilirubin, which is reversible upon discontinuation. Do not dose reduce. If a concomitant transaminase increase occurs, evaluate for alternative etiologies.  (5.3)   
 *     Hepatotoxicity: Patients with hepatitis B or C infection are at risk of increased transaminases or hepatic decompensation. Monitor hepatic laboratory tests prior to therapy and during treatment.  (2.5  ,  5.5  ,  8.8)   
 *     Nephrolithiasis and cholelithiasis have been reported. Consider temporary interruption or discontinuation.  (5.6)   
 *    The concomitant use of REYATAZ/ritonavir and certain other medications may result in known or potentially significant drug interactions. Consult the full prescribing information prior to and during treatment for potential drug interactions.  (5.7  ,  7.3)   
 *    Patients receiving REYATAZ may develop new onset or exacerbations of diabetes mellitus/hyperglycemia  (5.8)  , immune reconstitution syndrome  (5.9)  , and redistribution/accumulation of body fat  (5.10)  . 
 *     Hemophilia: Spontaneous bleeding may occur and additional factor VIII may be required.  (5.11)   
 *     Phenylketonuria: REYATAZ oral powder contains phenylalanine which can be harmful to patients with phenylketonuria.  (5.4)   
    
 

   5.1 Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities



  REYATAZ has been shown to prolong the PR interval of the electrocardiogram in some patients. In healthy volunteers and in patients, abnormalities in atrioventricular (AV) conduction were asymptomatic and generally limited to first-degree AV block. There have been reports of second-degree AV block and other conduction abnormalities [see  Adverse Reactions (6.4)  and  Overdosage (10)    ]. In clinical trials that included electrocardiograms, asymptomatic first-degree AV block was observed in 5.9% of atazanavir-treated patients (n=920), 5.2% of lopinavir/ritonavir-treated patients (n=252), 10.4% of nelfinavir-treated patients (n=48), and 3.0% of efavirenz-treated patients (n=329). In Study AI424-045, asymptomatic first-degree AV block was observed in 5% (6/118) of atazanavir/ritonavir-treated patients and 5% (6/116) of lopinavir/ritonavir-treated patients who had on-study electrocardiogram measurements. Because of limited clinical experience in patients with preexisting conduction system disease (eg, marked first-degree AV block or second- or third-degree AV block). ECG monitoring should be considered in these patients. [See  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  .]  



    5.2 Rash



  In controlled clinical trials, rash (all grades, regardless of causality) occurred in approximately 20% of patients treated with REYATAZ. The median time to onset of rash in clinical studies was 7.3 weeks and the median duration of rash was 1.4 weeks. Rashes were generally mild-to-moderate maculopapular skin eruptions. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions of moderate or severe rash (occurring at a rate of &gt;=2%) are presented for the individual clinical studies [see     Adverse Reactions (6.1)     ]  . Dosing with REYATAZ was often continued without interruption in patients who developed rash. The discontinuation rate for rash in clinical trials was &lt;1%. Cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiforme, and toxic skin eruptions, including drug rash, eosinophilia, and systemic symptoms (DRESS) syndrome, have been reported in patients receiving REYATAZ. [See     Contraindications (4)     and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  .]  REYATAZ should be discontinued if severe rash develops.



    5.3 Hyperbilirubinemia



  Most patients taking REYATAZ experience asymptomatic elevations in indirect (unconjugated) bilirubin related to inhibition of UDP-glucuronosyl transferase (UGT). This hyperbilirubinemia is reversible upon discontinuation of REYATAZ. Hepatic transaminase elevations that occur with hyperbilirubinemia should be evaluated for alternative etiologies. No long-term safety data are available for patients experiencing persistent elevations in total bilirubin &gt;5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN). Alternative antiretroviral therapy to REYATAZ may be considered if jaundice or scleral icterus associated with bilirubin elevations presents cosmetic concerns for patients. Dose reduction of atazanavir is not recommended since long-term efficacy of reduced doses has not been established. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.1  ,  6.2)  .]  



     5.4 Patients with Phenylketonuria  



   Phenylalanine can be harmful to patients with phenylketonuria (PKU). REYATAZ oral powder contains phenylalanine (a component of aspartame). Each packet of REYATAZ oral powder contains 35 mg of phenylalanine. REYATAZ capsules do not contain phenylalanine.  



    5.5 Hepatotoxicity



  Patients with underlying hepatitis B or C viral infections or marked elevations in transaminases before treatment may be at increased risk for developing further transaminase elevations or hepatic decompensation. In these patients, hepatic laboratory testing should be conducted prior to initiating therapy with REYATAZ and during treatment. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.8)  .]  



    5.6 Nephrolithiasis and Cholelithiasis



  Cases of nephrolithiasis and/or cholelithiasis have been reported during postmarketing surveillance in HIV-infected patients receiving REYATAZ therapy. Some patients required hospitalization for additional management and some had complications. Because these events were reported voluntarily during clinical practice, estimates of frequency cannot be made. If signs or symptoms of nephrolithiasis and/or cholelithiasis occur, temporary interruption or discontinuation of therapy may be considered. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.4)  .]  



     5.7 Risk of Serious Adverse Reactions Due to Drug Interactions  



   Initiation of REYATAZ with ritonavir, a CYP3A inhibitor, in patients receiving medications metabolized by CYP3A or initiation of medications metabolized by CYP3A in patients already receiving REYATAZ with ritonavir, may increase plasma concentrations of medications metabolized by CYP3A. Initiation of medications that inhibit or induce CYP3A may increase or decrease concentrations of REYATAZ with ritonavir, respectively.   These interactions may lead to:  



 *     clinically significant adverse reactions, potentially leading to severe, life threatening, or fatal events from greater exposures of concomitant medications.  
 *     clinically significant adverse reactions from greater exposures of REYATAZ with ritonavir.  
 *     loss of therapeutic effect of REYATAZ with ritonavir and possible development of resistance.  
     See Table 16 for steps to prevent or manage these possible and known significant drug interactions, including dosing recommendations [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  . Consider the potential for drug interactions prior to and during REYATAZ/ritonavir therapy; review concomitant medications during REYATAZ/ritonavir therapy; and monitor for the adverse reactions associated with the concomitant medications [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .  
 

    5.8 Diabetes Mellitus/Hyperglycemia



  New-onset diabetes mellitus, exacerbation of preexisting diabetes mellitus, and hyperglycemia have been reported during postmarketing surveillance in HIV-infected patients receiving protease inhibitor therapy. Some patients required either initiation or dose adjustments of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents for treatment of these events. In some cases, diabetic ketoacidosis has occurred. In those patients who discontinued protease inhibitor therapy, hyperglycemia persisted in some cases. Because these events have been reported voluntarily during clinical practice, estimates of frequency cannot be made and a causal relationship between protease inhibitor therapy and these events has not been established. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.4)  .]  



    5.9 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including REYATAZ. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jiroveci  pneumonia, or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.10 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.11 Hemophilia



  There have been reports of increased bleeding, including spontaneous skin hematomas and hemarthrosis, in patients with hemophilia type A and B treated with protease inhibitors. In some patients additional factor VIII was given. In more than half of the reported cases, treatment with protease inhibitors was continued or reintroduced. A causal relationship between protease inhibitor therapy and these events has not been established.



    5.12 Resistance/Cross-Resistance



  Various degrees of cross-resistance among protease inhibitors have been observed. Resistance to atazanavir may not preclude the subsequent use of other protease inhibitors. [See  Microbiology (12.4)  .]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
