<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rhogam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse events (AE) after administration of RhoGAM and MICRhoGAM are rare.



 The most frequently reported AEs are anti-D formation and injection site reactions, such as swelling, induration, redness and mild pain or warmth. Possible systemic reactions are skin rash, body aches or a slight elevation in temperature. Severe systemic allergic reactions are extremely rare. Patients should be observed for at least 20 minutes after administration. There have been no reported fatalities due to anaphylaxis or any other cause related to RhoGAM or MICRhoGAM administration.



 As with any Rho(D) Immune Globulin (Human), administration to patients who are Rh-positive or have received Rh-positive red blood cells may result in signs and symptoms of a hemolytic reaction, including fever, back pain, nausea and vomiting, hypo- or hypertension, hemoglobinuria/emia, elevated bilirubin and creatinine and decreased haptoglobin.



 RhoGAM and MICRhoGAM contain a small quantity of IgA (less than 15 mug per dose).  10  Although high doses of intravenous immune globulin containing IgA at levels of 270-720 mug/mL have been given without incident during treatment of patients with high-titered antibodies to IgA,  11  the attending physician must weigh the benefit against the potential risks of hypersensitivity reactions.



   EXCERPT:   Most common are:



 *  Injection site reactions that include swelling, induration, redness and mild pain or warmth. (  6  ) 
 *  Systemic reactions that include skin rash, body aches or a slight elevation in temperature. Patients should be observed for at least 20 minutes after administration. Severe systemic allergic reactions are extremely rare. (  6  ) 
 *  Anti-D formation is rarely reported after proper administration of RhoGAM. (  6  ). 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact:  
 

 *   Ortho-Clinical Diagnostics, Inc. at 1-800-421-3311 in the United States.  
 *   Outside of the United States, the company distributing these products should be contacted.  
 *   Voluntary reporting of adverse reactions may also be made to the FDA through MedWatch at 1-800-FDA-1088 or on the Internet at www.fda.gov/medwatch.   
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
