<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="riomet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt; 5% and that were more common in metformin- than placebo-treated patients) are: diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, flatulence, asthenia, indigestion, abdominal discomfort, and headache.(6)



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ranbaxy Laboratories Inc. at 1-888-RANBAXY (726-2299) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  In a U.S. double-blind clinical study of metformin in patients with type 2 diabetes, a total of 141 patients received metformin therapy (up to 2550 mg per day) and 145 patients received placebo. Adverse reactions reported in greater than 5% of the metformin patients, and that were more common in metformin- than placebo-treated patients, are listed in  Table 1.  



 Table 1. Most Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;5.0 Percent) in a Placebo-Controlled Clinical Study of Metformin Monotherapy* 
  Adverse Reaction                 Metformin Monotherapy(n = 141)                 Placebo(n = 145)          
  % of patients                    
  Diarrhea                         53.2                                           11.7                      
  Nausea/ Vomiting                 25.5                                           8.3                       
  Flatulence                       12.1                                           5.5                       
  Asthenia                         9.2                                            5.5                       
  Indigestion                      7.1                                            4.1                       
  Abdominal Discomfort             6.4                                            4.8                       
  Headache                         5.7                                            4.8                       
         *-Reactions that were more common in metformin-than placebo-treated patients.
 

 Diarrhea led to discontinuation of study medication in 6% of patients treated with metformin. Additionally, the following adverse reactions were reported in &gt;= 1.0 to &lt;= 5.0% of metformin patients and were more commonly reported with metformin than placebo: abnormal stools, hypoglycemia, myalgia, lightheaded, dyspnea, nail disorder, rash, sweating increased, taste disorder, chest discomfort, chills, flu syndrome, flushing, palpitation.



   6.2 Pediatric Patients

  In clinical trials with metformin in pediatric patients with type 2 diabetes, the profile of adverse reactions was similar to that observed in adults.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

  WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    *  Lactic acidosis is a rare but serious complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  The onset is often subtle accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  If acidosis is suspected Riomet should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, renal impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate. (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue Riomet and hospitalize the patient immediately. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Lactic acidosis: Warn against excessive alcohol intake. Riomet is not recommended in hepatic impairment and is contraindicated in renal impairment. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter. (5.1, 5.2, 5.3) 
 *    Temporarily discontinue in patients undergoing radiologic studies with intravascular administration of iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food and fluids. (5.5, 5.8) 
 *    Vitamin B12deficiency: Metformin may lower Vitamin B12levels. Measure hematologic parameters annually. (5.6, 5.14) 
 *    Macrovascular outcomes: No conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with Riomet or any other antidiabetic drug. (5.13) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



  Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with Riomet; when it occurs, it is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate levels (&gt;5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels &gt;5 ug/mL are generally found.



 The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin hydrochloride is very low (approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years, with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years). In more than 20,000 patient-years exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal insufficiency, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, in particular those with unstable or acute congestive heart failure who are at risk of hypoperfusion and hypoxemia, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal dysfunction and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking Riomet and by use of the minimum effective dose of Riomet. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. Riomet treatment should not be initiated in patients &gt;= 80 years of age unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced, as these patients are more susceptible to developing lactic acidosis. In addition, Riomet should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, Riomet should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake, either acute or chronic, when taking Riomet, since alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin hydrochloride on lactate metabolism. In addition, Riomet should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  .



 The onset of lactic acidosis often is subtle, and accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. There may be associated hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias with more marked acidosis. The patient and the patient's physician must be aware of the possible importance of such symptoms and the patient should be instructed to notify the physician immediately if they occur. Riomet should be withdrawn until the situation is clarified. Serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, and, if indicated, blood pH, lactate levels, and even blood metformin levels may be useful. Once a patient is stabilized on any dose level of Riomet, gastrointestinal symptoms, which are common during initiation of therapy, are unlikely to be drug related. Later occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms could be due to lactic acidosis or other serious disease.



 Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking Riomet do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be explainable by other mechanisms, such as poorly controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling.



 Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia).



 Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking Riomet, the drug should be discontinued immediately and general supportive measures promptly instituted. Because metformin hydrochloride is dialyzable (with a clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions), prompt hemodialysis is recommended to correct the acidosis and remove the accumulated metformin. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery [see Contraindications (4)]  .



    5.2 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Since impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis, Riomet should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease.



    5.3 Monitoring of Renal Function



  Metformin is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney, and the risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of impairment of renal function. Thus, patients with serum creatinine levels above the upper limit of normal for their age should not receive Riomet. In patients with advanced age, Riomet should be carefully titrated to establish the minimum dose for adequate glycemic effect, because aging is associated with reduced renal function. In elderly patients, particularly those &gt;=80 years of age, renal function should be monitored regularly and, generally, Riomet should not be titrated to the maximum dose [see Dosage and Administration (2.5)]  .



 Before initiation of Riomet therapy and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified as normal. In patients in whom development of renal dysfunction is anticipated, renal function should be assessed more frequently and Riomet discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present.



    5.4 Use of Concomitant Medications That May Affect Renal Function or Metformin Disposition



  Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or may interfere with the disposition of metformin, such as cationic drugs that are eliminated by renal tubular secretion, should be used with caution [see Drug Interactions (7.4)]  .



    5.5 Radiologic Studies Involving the Use of Intravascular Iodinated Contrast Materials



   Radiologic studies involving the use of intravascular iodinated contrast materials (for example, intravenous urogram, intravenous cholangiography, angiography, and computed tomography (CT) scans with intravascular contrast materials)-  Intravascular contrast studies with iodinated materials can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin [see Contraindications (4)]  . Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, Riomet should be temporarily discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been re-evaluated and found to be normal.



    5.6 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled clinical trials of metformin of 29 weeks duration, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum Vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or Vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on Riomet and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.14)]    .



 Certain individuals (those with inadequate Vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal Vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum Vitamin B12measurements at two- to three-year intervals may be useful.



    5.7 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol is known to potentiate the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients, therefore, should be warned against excessive alcohol intake, acute or chronic, while receiving Riomet [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .



    5.8 Surgical Procedures



  Riomet therapy should be temporarily suspended for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.9 Change in Clinical Status of Patients With Previously Controlled Type 2 Diabetes



  A patient with type 2 diabetes previously well controlled on Riomet who develops laboratory abnormalities or clinical illness (especially vague and poorly defined illness) should be evaluated promptly for evidence of ketoacidosis or lactic acidosis. Evaluation should include serum electrolytes and ketones, blood glucose and, if indicated, blood pH, lactate, pyruvate, and metformin levels. If acidosis of either form occurs, Riomet must be stopped immediately and other appropriate corrective measures initiated [see Contraindications (4)]  .



    5.10 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation, or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as sulfonylureas and insulin) or ethanol.



 Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs.



    5.11 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause, acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients on Riomet therapy, the drug should be promptly discontinued.



    5.12 Loss of Control of Blood Glucose



  When a patient stabilized on any diabetic regimen is exposed to stress such as fever, trauma, infection, or surgery, a temporary loss of glycemic control may occur. At such times, it may be necessary to withhold Riomet and temporarily administer insulin. Riomet may be reinstituted after the acute episode is resolved.



 The effectiveness of oral antidiabetic drugs in lowering blood glucose to a targeted level decreases in many patients over a period of time. This phenomenon, which may be due to progression of the underlying disease or to diminished responsiveness to the drug, is known as secondary failure, to distinguish it from primary failure in which the drug is ineffective during initial therapy. Should secondary failure occur with either Riomet or sulfonylurea monotherapy, combined therapy with Riomet and sulfonylurea may result in a response. Should secondary failure occur with combined Riomet /sulfonylurea therapy, it may be necessary to consider therapeutic alternatives including initiation of insulin therapy.



    5.13 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with Riomet or any other oral anti-diabetic drug.



    5.14 Laboratory Tests



  Response to all diabetic therapies should be monitored by periodic measurements of fasting blood glucose and glycosylated hemoglobin levels, with a goal of decreasing these levels toward the normal range. During initial dose titration, fasting glucose can be used to determine the therapeutic response. Thereafter, both glucose and glycosylated hemoglobin should be monitored. Measurements of glycosylated hemoglobin may be especially useful for evaluating long-term control [see Dosage and Administration (2)]  .



 Initial and periodic monitoring of hematologic parameters (e.g., hemoglobin/hematocrit and red blood cell indices) and renal function (serum creatinine) should be performed, at least on an annual basis. While megaloblastic anemia has rarely been seen with metformin therapy, if this is suspected, Vitamin B12deficiency should be excluded [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
