<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="risperdal0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Increased mortality in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Cerebrovascular adverse events, including stroke, in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Neuroleptic malignant syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Tardive dyskinesia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Metabolic changes [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hyperprolactinemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Orthostatic hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Leukopenia/Neutropenia and Agranulocytosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Potential for cognitive and motor impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Dysphagia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Priapism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
 *  Disruption of body temperature regulation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)  ]  
 *  Avoidance of inadvertent injection into a blood vessel [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ]  
 *  Antiemetic effect [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.16)  ]  
 *  Suicide [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.17)  ]  
 *  Increased sensitivity in patients with Parkinson's disease or those with dementia with Lewy bodies [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.18)  ]  
 *  Diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.18)  ]  
 *  Osteodystrophy and tumors in animals [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.19)  ]  
    The most common adverse reactions in clinical trials in patients with schizophrenia (&gt;=5%) were: headache, parkinsonism, dizziness, akathisia, fatigue, constipation, dyspepsia, sedation, weight increased, pain in extremity, and dry mouth. The most common adverse reactions in the double-blind, placebo-controlled periods of the bipolar disorder trials were weight increased (5% in the monotherapy trial) and tremor and parkinsonism (&gt;=10% in the adjunctive treatment trial).
 

 The most common adverse reactions that were associated with discontinuation from the 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in patients with schizophrenia (causing discontinuation in &gt;= 1% of patients) were agitation, depression, anxiety, and akathisia. Adverse reactions that were associated with discontinuation from the double-blind, placebo-controlled periods of the bipolar disorder trials were hyperglycemia (one patient in the monotherapy trial) and hypokinesia and tardive dyskinesia (one patient each in the adjunctive treatment trial).



 The data described in this section are derived from a clinical trial database consisting of 2392 patients exposed to one or more doses of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  for the treatment of schizophrenia. Of these 2392 patients, 332 were patients who received RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  while participating in a 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Two hundred two (202) of the 332 were schizophrenia patients who received 25 mg or 50 mg RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  . The conditions and duration of treatment with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  in the other clinical trials varied greatly and included (in overlapping categories) double-blind, fixed- and flexible-dose, placebo- or active-controlled studies and open-label phases of studies, inpatients and outpatients, and short-term (up to 12 weeks) and longer-term (up to 4 years) exposures. Safety was assessed by collecting adverse events and performing physical examinations, vital signs, body weights, laboratory analyses, and ECGs.



 In addition to the studies in patients with schizophrenia, safety data are presented from a trial assessing the efficacy and safety of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  when administered as monotherapy for maintenance treatment in patients with bipolar I disorder. The subjects in this multi-center, double-blind, placebo-controlled study were adult patients who met DSM-IV criteria for Bipolar Disorder Type I and who were stable on risperidone (oral or long-acting injection), were stable on other antipsychotics or mood stabilizers, or were experiencing an acute episode. After a 3-week period of treatment with open-label oral risperidone (N=440), subjects who demonstrated an initial response to oral risperidone in this period and those who were stable on risperidone (oral or long-acting injection) at study entry entered into a 26-week stabilization period of open-label RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  (N=501). Subjects who demonstrated a maintained response during this period were then randomized into a 24-month double-blind, placebo-controlled period in which they received RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  (N=154) or placebo (N=149) as monotherapy. Subjects who relapsed or who completed the double-blind period could choose to enter an 8-week open-label RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  extension period (N=160).



 Safety data are also presented from a trial assessing the efficacy and safety of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  when administered as adjunctive maintenance treatment in patients with bipolar disorder. The subjects in this multi-center, double-blind, placebo-controlled study were adult patients who met DSM-IV criteria for Bipolar Disorder Type I or Type II and who experienced at least 4 episodes of mood disorder requiring psychiatric/clinical intervention in the previous 12 months, including at least 2 episodes in the 6 months prior to the start of the study. At the start of this study, all patients (N=275) entered into a 16-week open-label treatment phase in which they received RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  in addition to continuing their treatment as usual, which consisted of various mood stabilizers (primarily lithium and valproate), antidepressants, and/or anxiolytics. Patients who reached remission at the end of this 16-week open-label treatment phase (N=139) were then randomized into a 52-week double-blind, placebo-controlled phase in which they received RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  (N=72) or placebo (n=67) as adjunctive treatment in addition to continuing their treatment as usual. Patients who did not reach remission at the end of the 16-week open-label treatment phase could choose to continue to receive RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  as adjunctive therapy in an open-label manner, in addition to continuing their treatment as usual, for up to an additional 36 weeks as clinically indicated for a total period of up to 52 weeks; these patients (N=70) were also included in the evaluation of safety.



 Adverse events during exposure to study treatment were obtained by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using their own terminology. Consequently, to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events, events were grouped in standardized categories using MedDRA terminology.



 Throughout this section, adverse reactions are reported. Adverse reactions are adverse events that were considered to be reasonably associated with the use of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  (adverse drug reactions) based on the comprehensive assessment of the available adverse event information. A causal association for RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  often cannot be reliably established in individual cases. Further, because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The majority of all adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in clinical trials in patients with schizophrenia (&gt;= 5%) were headache, parkinsonism, dizziness, akathisia, fatigue, constipation, dyspepsia, sedation, weight increased, pain in extremity, and dry mouth. The most common adverse reactions in clinical trials in patients with bipolar disorder were weight increased (5% in monotherapy trial) and tremor and parkinsonism (&gt;=10% in adjunctive therapy trial).  (  6  )  



 The most common adverse reactions that were associated with discontinuation from clinical trials in patients with schizophrenia were agitation, depression, anxiety, and akathisia. Adverse reactions that were associated with discontinuation from bipolar disorder trials were hyperglycemia (one subject monotherapy trial) and hypokinesia and tardive dyskinesia (one subject each in adjunctive therapy trial).  (  6  )  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-JANSSEN (1-800-526-7736) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Commonly-Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials - Schizophrenia

  Table 4 lists the adverse reactions reported in 2% or more of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients with schizophrenia in one 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial.



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 2% of RISPERDAL CONSTA(r)-Treated Patients with Schizophrenia in a 12-Week Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
                                           RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)          Placebo          
 System/Organ Class                               25 mg                 50 mg                                 
   Adverse Reaction                               (N=99)               (N=103)                (N=98)          
  
   Eye disorders                                                                                              
   Vision blurred                                   2                     3                     0             
   Gastrointestinal disorders               
   Constipation                                     5                     7                     1             
   Dry mouth                                        0                     7                     1             
   Dyspepsia                                        6                     6                     0             
   Nausea                                           3                     4                     5             
   Toothache                                        1                     3                     0             
   Salivary hypersecretion                          4                     1                     0             
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
   Fatigue                                          3                     9                     0             
   Edema peripheral                                 2                     3                     1             
   Pain                                             4                     1                     0             
   Pyrexia                                          2                     1                     0             
   Infections and infestations              
   Upper respiratory tract infection                2                     0                     1             
   Investigations                           
   Weight increased                                 5                     4                     2             
   Weight decreased                                 4                     1                     1             
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
   Pain in extremity                                6                     2                     1             
   Nervous system disorders                 
   Headache                                         15                    21                    12            
   Parkinsonism                                     8                     15                    9             
   Dizziness                                        7                     11                    6             
   Akathisia                                        4                     11                    6             
   Sedation                                         5                     6                     3             
   Tremor                                           0                     3                     0             
   Syncope                                          2                     1                     0             
   Hypoesthesia                                     2                     0                     0             
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
   Cough                                            4                     2                     3             
   Sinus congestion                                 2                     0                     0             
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders     
   Acne                                             2                     2                     0             
   Dry skin                                         2                     0                     0             
            6.2 Commonly-Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials - Bipolar Disorder
   Table 5 lists the treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported in 2% or more of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients in the 24-month double-blind, placebo-controlled treatment period of the trial assessing the efficacy and safety of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  when administered as monotherapy for maintenance treatment in patients with Bipolar I Disorder.



 Table 5. Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 2% of Patients with Bipolar I Disorder Treated with RISPERDAL CONSTA(r) as Monotherapy in a 24-Month Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
 System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction      RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  (N=154)          Placebo(N=149)           
  
   Investigations                           
   Weight increased                                      5                               1                  
   Nervous system disorders                 
   Dizziness                                             3                               1                  
   Vascular disorders                       
   Hypertension                                          3                               1                  
         Table 6 lists the treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported in 4% or more of patients in the 52-week double-blind, placebo-controlled treatment phase of a trial assessing the efficacy and safety of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  when administered as adjunctive maintenance treatment in patients with bipolar disorder.
 

 Table 6. Adverse Reactions in &gt;= 4% of Patients with Bipolar Disorder Treated with RISPERDAL CONSTA(r) as Adjunctive Therapy in a 52-Week Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
 System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction      RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  + Treatment as Usual(N=72)  Placebo + Treatment as Usual(N=67)   
  
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
   Gait abnormal                                         4                               0                  
   Infections and infestations              
   Upper respiratory tract infection                     6                               3                  
   Investigations                           
   Weight increased                                      7                               1                  
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders       
   Decreased appetite                                    6                               1                  
   Increased appetite                                    4                               0                  
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
   Arthralgia                                            4                               3                  
   Nervous system disorders                 
   Tremor                                                24                              16                 
   Parkinsonism                                          15                              6                  
   Dyskinesia                                            6                               3                  
   Sedation                                              7                               1                  
   Disturbance in attention                              4                               0                  
   Reproductive system and breast disorders     
   Amenorrhea                                            4                               1                  
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
   Cough                                                 4                               1                  
           6.3 Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Trial Evaluation of Risperidone
   The following additional adverse reactions occurred in &lt;2% of the RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients in the above schizophrenia double-blind, placebo-controlled trial dataset, in &lt;2% of the RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients in the above double-blind, placebo-controlled period of the monotherapy bipolar disorder trial dataset, or in &lt;4% of the RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients in the above double-blind, placebo-controlled period of the adjunctive treatment bipolar disorder trial dataset. The following also includes additional adverse reactions reported at any frequency in RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients who participated in the open-label phases of the above bipolar disorder studies and in other studies, including double-blind, active controlled and open-label studies in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders  : anemia, neutropenia



   Cardiac disorders  : tachycardia, atrioventricular block first degree, palpitations, sinus bradycardia, bundle branch block left, bradycardia, sinus tachycardia, bundle branch block right



   Ear and labyrinth disorders  : ear pain, vertigo



   Endocrine disorders  : hyperprolactinemia



   Eye disorders  : conjunctivitis, visual acuity reduced



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : diarrhea, vomiting, abdominal pain upper, abdominal pain, stomach discomfort, gastritis



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  injection site pain, chest discomfort, chest pain, influenza like illness, sluggishness, malaise, induration, injection site induration, injection site swelling, injection site reaction, face edema



   Immune system disorders  : hypersensitivity



   Infections and infestations  : nasopharyngitis, influenza, bronchitis, urinary tract infection, rhinitis, respiratory tract infection, ear infection, pneumonia, lower respiratory tract infection, pharyngitis, sinusitis, viral infection, infection, localized infection, cystitis, gastroenteritis, subcutaneous abscess



   Injury and poisoning  : fall, procedural pain



   Investigations  : blood prolactin increased, alanine aminotransferase increased, electrocardiogram abnormal, gamma-glutamyl transferase increased, blood glucose increased, hepatic enzyme increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, electrocardiogram QT prolonged, glucose urine present



   Metabolism and nutritional disorders  : anorexia, hyperglycemia



   Musculoskeletal, connective tissue and bone disorders  : posture abnormal, myalgia, back pain, buttock pain, muscular weakness, neck pain, musculoskeletal chest pain



   Nervous system disorders  : coordination abnormal, dystonia, tardive dyskinesia, drooling, paresthesia, dizziness postural, convulsion, akinesia, hypokinesia, dysarthria



   Psychiatric disorders  : insomnia, agitation, anxiety, sleep disorder, depression, initial insomnia, libido decreased, nervousness



   Renal and urinary disorders  : urinary incontinence



   Reproductive system and breast disorders  : galactorrhea, oligomenorrhea, erectile dysfunction, sexual dysfunction, ejaculation disorder, gynecomastia, breast discomfort, menstruation irregular, menstruation delayed, menstrual disorder, ejaculation delayed



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  : nasal congestion, pharyngolaryngeal pain, dyspnea, rhinorrhea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : rash, eczema, pruritus generalized, pruritus



   Vascular disorders  : hypotension, orthostatic hypotension



   Additional Adverse Reactions Reported with Oral RISPERDAL  (r)  



 The following is a list of additional adverse reactions that have been reported during the clinical trial evaluation of oral RISPERDAL  (r)  , regardless of frequency of occurrence:



   Blood and Lymphatic Disorders  : granulocytopenia



   Cardiac Disorders  : atrioventricular block



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders  : tinnitus



   Eye Disorders  : ocular hyperemia, eye discharge, eye rolling, eyelid edema, eye swelling, eyelid margin crusting, dry eye, lacrimation increased, photophobia, glaucoma



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : abdominal pain upper, dysphagia, fecaloma, abdominal discomfort, fecal incontinence, lip swelling, cheilitis, aptyalism



   General Disorders  : thirst, feeling abnormal, gait disturbance, pitting edema, edema, chills, discomfort, generalized edema, drug withdrawal syndrome, peripheral coldness



   Immune System Disorders  : drug hypersensitivity



   Infections and Infestations  : tonsillitis, eye infection, cellulitis, otitis media, onychomycosis, acarodermatitis, bronchopneumonia, respiratory tract infection, tracheobronchitis, otitis media chronic



   Investigations  : body temperature increased, heart rate increased, eosinophil count increased, white blood cell count decreased, hemoglobin decreased, blood creatine phosphokinase increased, hematocrit decreased, body temperature decreased, blood pressure decreased, transaminases increased



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  : polydipsia



   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue, and Bone Disorders  : joint swelling, joint stiffness, rhabdomyolysis, torticollis



   Nervous System Disorders  : hypertonia, balance disorder, dysarthria, unresponsive to stimuli, depressed level of consciousness, movement disorder, hypokinesia, parkinsonian rest tremor, transient ischemic attack, cerebrovascular accident, masked facies, speech disorder, loss of consciousness, muscle contractions involuntary, akinesia, cerebral ischemia, cerebrovascular disorder, neuroleptic malignant syndrome, diabetic coma, head titubation



   Psychiatric Disorders:  blunted affect, confusional state, middle insomnia, listlessness, anorgasmia



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  enuresis, dysuria, pollakiuria



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  vaginal discharge, retrograde ejaculation, ejaculation disorder, ejaculation failure, breast enlargement



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  epistaxis, wheezing, pneumonia aspiration, dysphonia, productive cough, pulmonary congestion, respiratory tract congestion, rales, respiratory disorder, hyperventilation, nasal edema



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  erythema, skin discoloration, skin lesion, skin disorder, rash erythematous, rash papular, hyperkeratosis, dandruff, seborrheic dermatitis, rash generalized, rash maculopapular



   Vascular Disorders:  flushing



   6.4 Discontinuations Due to Adverse Reactions

  Schizophrenia



 Approximately 11% (22/202) of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients in the 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled schizophrenia trial discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, compared with 13% (13/98) who received placebo. The adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in two or more RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients were: agitation (3%), depression (2%), anxiety (1%), and akathisia (1%).



   Bipolar Disorder



 In the 24-month double-blind, placebo-controlled treatment period of the trial assessing the efficacy and safety of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  when administered as monotherapy for maintenance treatment in patients with bipolar I disorder, 1 (0.6%) of 154 RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients discontinued due to an adverse reaction (hyperglycemia).



 In the 52-week double-blind phase of the placebo-controlled trial in which RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  was administered as adjunctive therapy to patients with bipolar disorder in addition to continuing with their treatment as usual, approximately 4% (3/72) of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, compared with 1.5% (1/67) of placebo-treated patients. Adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  -treated patients were: hypokinesia (one patient) and tardive dyskinesia (one patient).



   6.5 Dose Dependency of Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials

  Extrapyramidal Symptoms:



 Two methods were used to measure extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS) in the 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial comparing three doses of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  (25 mg, 50 mg, and 75 mg) with placebo in patients with schizophrenia, including: (1) the incidence of spontaneous reports of EPS symptoms; and (2) the change from baseline to endpoint on the total score (sum of the subscale scores for parkinsonism, dystonia, and dyskinesia) of the Extrapyramidal Symptom Rating Scale (ESRS).



 As shown in Table 1, the overall incidence of EPS-related adverse reactions (akathisia, dystonia, parkinsonism, and tremor) in patients treated with 25 mg RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  was comparable to that of patients treated with placebo; the incidence of EPS related adverse reactions was higher in patients treated with 50 mg RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  .



 The median change from baseline to endpoint in total ESRS score showed no worsening in patients treated with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  compared with patients treated with placebo: 0 (placebo group); -1 (25-mg group, significantly less than the placebo group); and 0 (50-mg group).



   Dystonia



     Class Effect  : Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



   6.6 Changes in ECG

  The electrocardiograms of 202 schizophrenic patients treated with 25 mg or 50 mg RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  and 98 schizophrenic patients treated with placebo in the 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial were evaluated. Compared with placebo, there were no statistically significant differences in QTc intervals (using Fridericia's and linear correction factors) during treatment with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  .



 The electrocardiograms of 227 patients with Bipolar I Disorder were evaluated in the 24-month double-blind, placebo-controlled period. There were no clinically relevant differences in QTc intervals (using Fridericia's and linear correction factors) during treatment with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  compared to placebo.



 The electrocardiograms of 85 patients with bipolar disorder were evaluated in the 52-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. There were no statistically significant differences in QTc intervals (using Fridericia's and linear correction factors) during treatment with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  25 mg, 37.5 mg, or 50 mg when administered as adjunctive treatment in addition to continuing treatment as usual compared to placebo.



   6.7 Pain Assessment and Local Injection Site Reactions

  The mean intensity of injection pain reported by patients with schizophrenia using a visual analog scale (0 = no pain to 100 = unbearably painful) decreased in all treatment groups from the first to the last injection (placebo: 16.7 to 12.6; 25 mg: 12.0 to 9.0; 50 mg: 18.2 to 11.8). After the sixth injection (Week 10), investigator ratings indicated that 1% of patients treated with 25 mg or 50 mg RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  experienced redness, swelling, or induration at the injection site.



 In a separate study to observe local-site tolerability in which RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  was administered into the deltoid muscle every 2 weeks over a period of 8 weeks, no patient discontinued treatment due to local injection site pain or reaction. Clinician ratings indicated that only mild redness, swelling, or induration at the injection site was observed in subjects treated with 37.5 mg or 50 mg RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  at 2 hours after deltoid injection. All ratings returned to baseline at the predose assessment of the next injection 2 weeks later. No moderate or severe reactions were observed in any subject.



   6.8 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of risperidone; because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency: agranulocytosis, alopecia, anaphylactic reaction, angioedema, atrial fibrillation, blood cholesterol increased, blood triglycerides increased, diabetes mellitus, diabetic ketoacidosis in patients with impaired glucose metabolism, drug withdrawal syndrome neonatal, dysgeusia, hypoglycemia, hypothermia, ileus, inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion, intestinal obstruction, jaundice, mania, pancreatitis, priapism, QT prolongation, sleep apnea syndrome, thrombocytopenia, urinary retention, and water intoxication. In addition, the following adverse reactions have been observed during postapproval use of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  : cerebrovascular disorders, including cerebrovascular accidents, and diabetes mellitus aggravated.



 Retinal artery occlusion after injection of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  has been reported during postmarketing surveillance. This has been reported in the presence of abnormal arteriovenous anastomosis.



 Serious injection site reactions including abscess, cellulitis, cyst, hematoma, necrosis, nodule, and ulcer have been reported with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  during postmarketing surveillance. Isolated cases required surgical intervention.



 Very rarely, cases of anaphylactic reaction after injection with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  have been reported during postmarketing experience in patients who have previously tolerated oral risperidone.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  

    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)   (risperidone) is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis.    [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)   is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis.     (  5.1  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Cerebrovascular events, including stroke, in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis (  5.2  )  
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring (  5.3  )  
 *  Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue treatment if clinically appropriate (  5.4  )  
 *  *   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus: Monitor patients for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Monitor glucose regularly in patients with diabetes or at risk for diabetes. (  5.5  )  
 *   Dyslipidemia: Undesirable alterations have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. (  5.5  )  
 *   Weight Gain: Significant weight gain has been reported. Monitor weight gain. (  5.5  )  
   Metabolic Changes: Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/ cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and weight gain. (  5.5  )  
 *  Hyperprolactinemia: Risperidone treatment may elevate prolactin levels. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia, when associated with hypogonadism, can lead to decreased bone density in men and women. (  5.6  )  
 *  Orthostatic hypotension: associated with dizziness, tachycardia, bradycardia, and syncope can occur, especially during initial dose titration with oral risperidone. Use caution in patients with cardiovascular disease, cerebrovascular disease, and conditions that could affect hemodynamic responses. (  5.7  )  
 *  Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis have been reported with antipsychotics, including RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  . Patients with history of a clinically significant low white blood cell count (WBC) or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood cell count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and discontinuation of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  should be considered at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors. (  5.8  )  
 *  Potential for cognitive and motor impairment: has potential to impair judgment, thinking, and motor skills. Use caution when operating machinery, including automobiles. (  5.9  )  
 *  Seizures: Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold. (  5.10  )  
 *  Dysphagia: Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration can occur. Use cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia. (  5.11  )  
 *  Priapism: has been reported. Severe priapism may require surgical intervention. (  5.12  )  
 *  Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP): has been reported. (  5.13  )  
 *  Avoid inadvertent administration into a blood vessel. (  5.15  )  
 *  Suicide: There is increased risk of suicide attempt in patients with schizophrenia or bipolar disorder, and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy. (  5.17  )  
 *  Increased sensitivity in patients with Parkinson's disease or those with dementia with Lewy bodies: has been reported. Manifestations include mental status changes, motor impairment, extrapyramidal symptoms, and features consistent with Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome. (  5.18  )  
 *  Diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses: Use with caution in patients with such medical conditions (e.g., recent myocardial infarction or unstable cardiac disease). (  5.18  )  
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  (risperidone) is not approved for the treatment of dementia-related psychosis (see  Boxed Warning  )    .



    5.2 Cerebrovascular Adverse Events, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Cerebrovascular adverse events (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack), including fatalities, were reported in patients (mean age 85 years; range 73-97) in trials of oral risperidone in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis. In placebo-controlled trials, there was a significantly higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse events in patients treated with oral risperidone compared to patients treated with placebo. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis. [see also  Boxed Warning    and   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with antipsychotic drugs. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to identify cases in which the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: (1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and (3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for uncomplicated NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. The patient should be carefully monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4 Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses.



 There is no known treatment for established cases of tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and thereby may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that: (1) is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs, and (2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient treated with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  , drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.5 Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs have been associated with metabolic changes that may increase cardiovascular/cerebrovascular risk. These metabolic changes include hyperglycemia, dyslipidemia, and body weight gain. While all of the drugs in the class have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus



 Hyperglycemia and diabetes mellitus, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, have been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics including RISPERDAL  (r)  . Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse events is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of treatment-emergent hyperglycemia-related adverse events in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. Precise risk estimates for hyperglycemia-related adverse events in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics are not available.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics, including RISPERDAL  (r)  , should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics, including RISPERDAL  (r)  , should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics, including RISPERDAL  (r)  , should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics, including RISPERDAL  (r)  , should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic, including RISPERDAL  (r)  , was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of RISPERDAL  (r)  .



 Pooled data from 3 double-blind, placebo-controlled studies in subjects with schizophrenia and 4 double-blind, placebo-controlled monotherapy studies in subjects with bipolar mania with oral risperidone are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1. Change in Random Glucose From Seven Placebo-Controlled, 3- to 8-Week, Fixed- or Flexible-Dose Studies in Adult Subjects With Schizophrenia or Bipolar Mania With Oral Risperidone 
                                                                   RISPERDAL  (r)       
                                                 Placebo              1-8 mg/day           &gt;8-16 mg/day       
  
                                            Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
                                                  N=555                 N=748                 N=164           
 Serum Glucose                                     -1.4                  0.8                   0.6            
                                            Proportion of patients with shifts     
 Serum Glucose                                     0.6%                  0.4%                   0%            
 (&lt;140 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)                     (3/525)               (3/702)               (0/158)          
          In longer-term, controlled and uncontrolled studies in adult subjects, RISPERDAL  (r)  was associated with a mean change in glucose of +2.8 mg/dL at Week 24 (N=151) and +4.1 mg/dL at Week 48 (N=50).
 

   Dyslipidemia



 Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics.



 Pooled data from 7 placebo-controlled, 3- to 8- week, fixed- or flexible-dose studies in adult subjects with schizophrenia or bipolar mania are presented in Table 2.



 Table 2. Change in Random Lipids From Seven Placebo-Controlled, 3- to 8-Week, Fixed- or Flexible-Dose Studies in Adult Subjects With Schizophrenia or Bipolar Mania With Oral Risperidone 
                                                                   RISPERDAL  (r)       
                                                 Placebo              1-8 mg/day           &gt;8-16 mg/day       
  
                                            Mean change from baseline (mg/dL)     
  Cholesterol                                     N=559                 N=742                 N=156           
 Change from baseline                              0.6                   6.9                   1.8            
  Triglycerides                                   N=183                 N=307                 N=123           
 Change from baseline                             -17.4                  -4.9                  -8.3           
                                            Proportion of patients With Shifts     
  Cholesterol                                      2.7%                  4.3%                  6.3%           
 (&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)                     (10/368)              (22/516)               (6/96)          
  Triglycerides                                    1.1%                  2.7%                  2.5%           
 (&lt;500 mg/dL to &gt;=500 mg/dL)                     (2/180)               (8/301)               (3/121)          
          In longer-term, controlled and uncontrolled studies, RISPERDAL  (r)  was associated with a mean change in (a) non-fasting cholesterol of +4.4 mg/dL at Week 24 (N=231) and +5.5 mg/dL at Week 48 (N=86); and (b) non-fasting triglycerides of +19.9 mg/dL at Week 24 (N=52).
 

   Weight Gain



 Weight gain has been observed with atypical antipsychotic use. Clinical monitoring of weight is recommended.



 Data from a placebo-controlled, 12-week, fixed-dose study in adult subjects with schizophrenia are presented in Table 3.



 Table 3. Mean Change in Body Weight (kg) and the Proportion of Subjects With &gt;=7% Gain in Body Weight From a Placebo-Controlled, 12-Week, Fixed-Dose Study in Adult Subjects With Schizophrenia 
                                                                 RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)     
                                              Placebo(N=83)          25 mg(N=90)           50 mg(N=87)        
  
  Weight (kg)                                                                                                 
 Change from baseline                              -1.4                  0.5                   1.2            
  Weight Gain                                                                                                 
 &gt;=7% increase from baseline                        6%                   10%                    8%            
          In an uncontrolled, longer-term, open-label study, RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  was associated with a mean change in weight of +2.1 kg at Week 24 (N=268) and +2.8 kg at Week 50 (N=199).
 

    5.6 Hyperprolactinemia



  As with other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2receptors, risperidone elevates prolactin levels and the elevation persists during chronic administration. Risperidone is associated with higher levels of prolactin elevation than other antipsychotic agents.



 Hyperprolactinemia may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotropin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported in patients receiving prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male subjects.



 Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin dependent in vitro  , a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is contemplated in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. An increase in pituitary gland, mammary gland, and pancreatic islet cell neoplasia (mammary adenocarcinomas, pituitary and pancreatic adenomas) was observed in the risperidone carcinogenicity studies conducted in mice and rats [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans; the available evidence is considered too limited to be conclusive at this time.



    5.7 Orthostatic Hypotension



  RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  may induce orthostatic hypotension associated with dizziness, tachycardia, and in some patients, syncope, especially during the initial dose-titration period with oral risperidone, probably reflecting its alpha-adrenergic antagonistic properties. Syncope was reported in 0.8% (12/1499 patients) of patients treated with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  in multiple-dose studies. Patients should be instructed in nonpharmacologic interventions that help to reduce the occurrence of orthostatic hypotension (e.g., sitting on the edge of the bed for several minutes before attempting to stand in the morning and slowly rising from a seated position).



 RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  should be used with particular caution in (1) patients with known cardiovascular disease (history of myocardial infarction or ischemia, heart failure, or conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, and conditions which would predispose patients to hypotension, e.g., dehydration and hypovolemia, and (2) in the elderly and patients with renal or hepatic impairment. Monitoring of orthostatic vital signs should be considered in all such patients, and a dose reduction should be considered if hypotension occurs. Clinically significant hypotension has been observed with concomitant use of oral RISPERDAL  (r)  and antihypertensive medication.



    5.8 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



   Class Effect  : In clinical trial and/or postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia/neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents, including RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  . Agranulocytosis has also been reported.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) and a history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a history of a clinically significant low WBC or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and discontinuation of RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  should be considered at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Patients with clinically significant neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm  3  ) should discontinue RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  and have their WBC followed until recovery.



    5.9 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  Somnolence was reported by 5% of patients treated with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  in multiple-dose trials. Since risperidone has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills, patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that treatment with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  does not affect them adversely.



    5.10 Seizures



  During premarketing testing, seizures occurred in 0.3% (5/1499 patients) of patients treated with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  . Therefore, RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures.



    5.11 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in patients with advanced Alzheimer's dementia. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia. [see also  Boxed Warning    and   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



    5.12 Priapism



  Priapism has been reported during postmarketing surveillance [see  Adverse Reactions (6.8)  ]  . Severe priapism may require surgical intervention.



    5.13 Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP)



  A single case of TTP was reported in a 28 year-old female patient receiving oral RISPERDAL  (r)  in a large, open premarketing experience (approximately 1300 patients). She experienced jaundice, fever, and bruising, but eventually recovered after receiving plasmapheresis. The relationship to RISPERDAL  (r)  therapy is unknown.



    5.14 Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of body temperature regulation has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Both hyperthermia and hypothermia have been reported in association with oral RISPERDAL  (r)  or RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  use. Caution is advised when prescribing RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  for patients who will be exposed to temperature extremes.



    5.15 Administration



  RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  should be injected into the deltoid or gluteal muscle, and care must be taken to avoid inadvertent injection into a blood vessel. [see  Dosage and Administration (2)    and   Adverse Reactions (6.7)  ]  



    5.16 Antiemetic Effect



  Risperidone has an antiemetic effect in animals; this effect may also occur in humans, and may mask signs and symptoms of overdosage with certain drugs or of conditions such as intestinal obstruction, Reye's syndrome, and brain tumor.



    5.17 Suicide



  There is an increased risk of suicide attempt in patients with schizophrenia or bipolar disorder, and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  is to be administered by a health care professional [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  ; therefore, suicide due to an overdose is unlikely.



    5.18 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  in patients with certain concomitant systemic illnesses is limited. Patients with Parkinson's Disease or Dementia with Lewy Bodies who receive antipsychotics, including RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  , are reported to have an increased sensitivity to antipsychotic medications. Manifestations of this increased sensitivity have been reported to include confusion, obtundation, postural instability with frequent falls, extrapyramidal symptoms, and clinical features consistent with the neuroleptic malignant syndrome.



 Caution is advisable when using RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  in patients with diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses. RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarket testing.



 Increased plasma concentrations of risperidone and 9-hydroxyrisperidone occur in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ) treated with oral RISPERDAL  (r)  ; an increase in the free fraction of risperidone is also seen in patients with severe hepatic impairment. Patients with renal or hepatic impairment should be carefully titrated on oral RISPERDAL  (r)  before treatment with RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  is initiated at a dose of 25 mg. A lower initial dose of 12.5 mg may be appropriate when clinical factors warrant dose adjustment, such as in patients with renal or hepatic impairment [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



    5.19 Osteodystrophy and Tumors in Animals



  RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  produced osteodystrophy in male and female rats in a 1-year toxicity study and a 2-year carcinogenicity study at a dose of 40 mg/kg administered IM every 2 weeks.



 RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  produced renal tubular tumors (adenoma, adenocarcinoma) and adrenomedullary pheochromocytomas in male rats in the 2-year carcinogenicity study at 40 mg/kg administered IM every 2 weeks. In addition, RISPERDAL CONSTA  (r)  produced an increase in a marker of cellular proliferation in renal tissue in males in the 1-year toxicity study and in renal tumor-bearing males in the 2-year carcinogenicity study at 40 mg/kg administered IM every 2 weeks. (Cellular proliferation was not measured at the low dose or in females in either study.)



 The effect dose for osteodystrophy and the tumor findings is 8 times the IM maximum recommended human dose (MRHD) (50 mg) on a mg/m  2  basis and is associated with a plasma exposure (AUC) 2 times the expected plasma exposure (AUC) at the IM MRHD. The no-effect dose for these findings was 5 mg/kg (equal to the IM MRHD on a mg/m  2  basis). Plasma exposure (AUC) at the no-effect dose was one third the expected plasma exposure (AUC) at the IM MRHD.



  Neither the renal or adrenal tumors, nor osteodystrophy, were seen in studies of orally administered risperidone.  Osteodystrophy was not observed in dogs at doses up to 14 times (based on AUC) the IM MRHD in a 1-year toxicity study.



 The renal tubular and adrenomedullary tumors in male rats and other tumor findings are described in more detail in Section 13.1 (Carcinogenicity, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility).



 The relevance of these findings to human risk is unknown.



    5.20 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  No specific laboratory tests are recommended.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
