<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="risperdal1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Increased mortality in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Cerebrovascular adverse events, including stroke, in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis [ see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Neuroleptic malignant syndrome [ see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Tardive dyskinesia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Hyperglycemia and diabetes mellitus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hyperprolactinemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Orthostatic hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Leukopenia, neutropenia, and agranulocytosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Potential for cognitive and motor impairment [ see   Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Dysphagia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Priapism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
 *  Disruption of body temperature regulation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)  ]  
 *  Antiemetic effect [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ]  
 *  Suicide [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.16)  ]  
 *  Increased sensitivity in patients with Parkinson's disease or those with dementia with Lewy bodies [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.17)  ]  
 *  Diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.17)  ]  
    The most common adverse reactions in clinical trials (&gt;= 10%) were somnolence, appetite increased, fatigue, rhinitis, upper respiratory tract infection, vomiting, coughing, urinary incontinence, saliva increased, constipation, fever, Parkinsonism, dystonia, abdominal pain, anxiety, nausea, dizziness, dry mouth, tremor, rash, akathisia, and dyspepsia.
 

 The most common adverse reactions that were associated with discontinuation from clinical trials (causing discontinuation in &gt;1% of adults and/or &gt;2% of pediatrics) were somnolence, nausea, abdominal pain, dizziness, vomiting, agitation, and akathisia  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.5)  ]  .



 The data described in this section are derived from a clinical trial database consisting of 9712 adult and pediatric patients exposed to one or more doses of RISPERDAL  (r)  for the treatment of schizophrenia, bipolar mania, autistic disorder, and other psychiatric disorders in pediatrics and elderly patients with dementia. Of these 9712 patients, 2626 were patients who received RISPERDAL  (r)  while participating in double-blind, placebo-controlled trials. The conditions and duration of treatment with RISPERDAL  (r)  varied greatly and included (in overlapping categories) double-blind, fixed- and flexible-dose, placebo- or active-controlled studies and open-label phases of studies, inpatients and outpatients, and short-term (up to 12 weeks) and longer-term (up to 3 years) exposures. Safety was assessed by collecting adverse events and performing physical examinations, vital signs, body weights, laboratory analyses, and ECGs.



 Adverse events during exposure to study treatment were obtained by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using their own terminology. Consequently, to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events, events were grouped in standardized categories using WHOART terminology.



 Throughout this section, adverse reactions are reported. Adverse reactions are adverse events that were considered to be reasonably associated with the use of RISPERDAL  (r)  (adverse drug reactions) based on the comprehensive assessment of the available adverse event information. A causal association for RISPERDAL  (r)  often cannot be reliably established in individual cases. Further, because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The majority of all adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in clinical trials (&gt;=10%) were somnolence, appetite increased, fatigue, rhinitis, upper respiratory tract infection, vomiting, coughing, urinary incontinence, saliva increased, constipation, fever, Parkinsonism, dystonia, abdominal pain, anxiety, nausea, dizziness, dry mouth, tremor, rash, akathisia, and dyspepsia. (  6  )



 The most common adverse reactions that were associated with discontinuation from clinical trials were somnolence, nausea, abdominal pain, dizziness, vomiting, agitation, and akathisia. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen, Division of Ortho-McNeil-Janssen Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-JANSSEN (1-800-526-7736) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Commonly-Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials - Schizophrenia

      Adult Patients with Schizophrenia    



 Table 1 lists the adverse reactions reported in 1% or more of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated adult patients with schizophrenia in three 4- to 8-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions in &gt;=1% of RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Adult Patients with Schizophrenia in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
                                             RISPERDAL  (r)                             
 Body System  Adverse Reaction             2-8 mg per day(N=366)  &gt;8-16 mg per day(N=198)     Placebo(N=225)      
  
   Body as a whole - general disorders                                                                        
   Back pain                                        3                     2                     &lt;1            
   Fatigue                                          3                     1                     0             
   Chest pain                                       3                     1                     2             
   Fever                                            2                     1                     1             
   Asthenia                                         1                     1                     &lt;1            
   Syncope                                          &lt;1                    1                     &lt;1            
   Edema                                            &lt;1                    1                     0             
   Cardiovascular disorders, general                                                                          
   Hypotension postural                             2                     &lt;1                    0             
   Hypotension                                      &lt;1                    1                     0             
   Central and peripheral nervous system disorders                                                                       
   Parkinsonism                                     12                    17                    6             
   Dizziness                                        10                    4                     2             
   Dystonia                                         5                     5                     2             
   Akathisia                                        5                     5                     2             
   Dyskinesia                                       1                     1                     &lt;1            
   Gastrointestinal system disorders                                                                          
   Dyspepsia                                        10                    7                     6             
   Nausea                                           9                     4                     4             
   Constipation                                     8                     9                     7             
   Abdominal pain                                   4                     3                     0             
   Mouth dry                                        4                     &lt;1                    &lt;1            
   Saliva increased                                 3                     1                     &lt;1            
   Diarrhea                                         2                     &lt;1                    1             
   Hearing and vestibular disorders                                                                           
   Earache                                          1                     1                     0             
   Heart rate and rhythm disorders                                                                            
   Tachycardia                                      2                     5                     0             
   Arrhythmia                                       0                     1                     0             
   Metabolic and nutritional disorders                                                                        
   Weight increase                                  1                     &lt;1                    0             
   Creatine phosphokinase increased                 &lt;1                    2                     &lt;1            
   Musculoskeletal system disorders                                                                           
   Arthralgia                                       2                     3                     &lt;1            
   Myalgia                                          1                     0                     0             
   Platelet, bleeding and clotting disorders                                                                       
   Epistaxis                                        &lt;1                    2                     0             
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                      
   Anxiety                                          16                    12                    11            
   Somnolence                                       14                    5                     4             
   Anorexia                                         2                     0                     &lt;1            
   Red blood cell disorders                                                                                   
   Anemia                                           &lt;1                    1                     0             
   Reproductive disorders, male                                                                               
   Ejaculation failure                              &lt;1                    1                     0             
   Respiratory system disorders                                                                               
   Rhinitis                                         7                     11                    6             
   Coughing                                         3                     3                     3             
   Upper respiratory tract infection                2                     3                     &lt;1            
   Dyspnea                                          2                     2                     0             
   Skin and appendages disorders                                                                              
   Rash                                             2                     4                     2             
   Seborrhea                                        &lt;1                    2                     0             
   Urinary system disorders                                                                                   
   Urinary tract infection                          &lt;1                    3                     0             
   Vision disorders                                                                                           
   Vision abnormal                                  3                     1                     &lt;1            
                Pediatric Patients with Schizophrenia    
 

 Table 2 lists the adverse reactions reported in 5% or more of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated pediatric patients with schizophrenia in a 6-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial.



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions in &gt;=5% of RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Pediatric Patients with Schizophrenia in a Double-Blind Trial 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
                                             RISPERDAL  (r)                             
 Body System  Adverse Reaction             1-3 mg per day(N=55)  4-6 mg per day(N=51)     Placebo(N=54)       
  
   Central and peripheral nervous system disorders                                                                       
   Parkinsonism                                     13                    16                    6             
   Tremor                                           11                    10                    6             
   Dystonia                                         9                     18                    7             
   Dizziness                                        7                     14                    2             
   Akathisia                                        7                     10                    6             
   Gastrointestinal system disorders                                                                          
   Saliva increased                                 0                     10                    2             
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                      
   Somnolence                                       24                    12                    4             
   Anxiety                                          7                     6                     0             
            6.2 Commonly-Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials - Bipolar Mania
       Adult Patients with Bipolar Mania    



 Table 3 lists the adverse reactions reported in 1% or more of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated adult patients with bipolar mania in four 3-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled monotherapy trials.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions in &gt;=1% of RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Adult Patients with Bipolar Mania in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Monotherapy Trials 
                                                     Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
 Body System  Adverse Reaction                       RISPERDAL  (r)  1-6 mg per day(N=448)       Placebo(N=424)         
  
   Body as a whole - general disorders                                                                      
   Fatigue                                                       2                         &lt;1               
   Fever                                                         1                         &lt;1               
   Asthenia                                                      1                         &lt;1               
   Edema                                                         1                         &lt;1               
   Central and peripheral nervous system disorders                                                           
   Parkinsonism                                                 20                          6               
   Dystonia                                                     11                          3               
   Akathisia                                                     9                          3               
   Tremor                                                        6                          4               
   Dizziness                                                     5                          5               
   Gastrointestinal system disorders                                                                        
   Nausea                                                        5                          2               
   Dyspepsia                                                     4                          2               
   Saliva increased                                              3                         &lt;1               
   Diarrhea                                                      3                          2               
   Mouth dry                                                     1                          1               
   Heart rate and rhythm disorders                                                                          
   Tachycardia                                                   1                         &lt;1               
   Liver and biliary system disorders                                                                       
   SGOT increased                                                1                         &lt;1               
   Musculoskeletal disorders                                                                                
   Myalgia                                                       2                          2               
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Somnolence                                                   12                          4               
   Anxiety                                                       2                          2               
   Reproductive disorders, female                                                                           
   Lactation nonpuerperal                                        1                          0               
   Respiratory disorders                                                                                    
   Rhinitis                                                      2                          2               
   Skin and appendages disorders                                                                            
   Acne                                                          1                          0               
 Vision disorders                                                                                           
   Vision abnormal                                               2                         &lt;1               
         Table 4 lists the adverse reactions reported in 2% or more of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated adult patients with bipolar mania in two 3-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled adjuvant therapy trials.
 

 Table 4. Adverse Reactions in &gt;=2% of RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Adult Patients with Bipolar Mania in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Adjuvant Therapy Trials 
                                                     Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
 Body System  Adverse Reaction                       RISPERDAL(r) + Mood Stabilizer(N=127)  Placebo + Mood Stabilizer(N=126)   
  
   Body as a whole - general disorders                                                                      
   Chest pain                                                    2                          2               
   Fatigue                                                       2                          2               
   Central and peripheral nervous system disorders                                                           
   Parkinsonism                                                  9                          4               
   Dizziness                                                     8                          2               
   Dystonia                                                      6                          3               
   Akathisia                                                     6                          0               
   Tremor                                                        5                          2               
   Gastrointestinal system disorders                                                                        
   Nausea                                                        6                          5               
   Diarrhea                                                      6                          4               
   Saliva increased                                              4                          0               
   Abdominal pain                                                2                          0               
   Heart rate and rhythm disorders                                                                          
   Palpitation                                                   2                          0               
   Metabolic and nutritional disorders                                                                      
   Weight increase                                               2                          2               
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Somnolence                                                   12                          5               
   Anxiety                                                       4                          2               
   Respiratory disorders                                                                                    
   Pharyngitis                                                   5                          2               
   Coughing                                                      3                          1               
   Skin and appendages disorders                                                                            
   Rash                                                          2                          2               
   Urinary system disorders                                                                                 
   Urinary incontinence                                          2                          1               
   Urinary tract infection                                       2                          1               
               Pediatric Patients with Bipolar Mania    
 

 Table 5 lists the adverse reactions reported in 5% or more of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated pediatric patients with bipolar mania in a 3-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trial.



 Table 5. Adverse Reactions in &gt;=5% of RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Pediatric Patients with Bipolar Mania in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
                                             RISPERDAL  (r)                             
 Body System  Adverse Reaction             0.5-2.5 mg per day(N=50)  3-6 mg per day(N=61)     Placebo(N=58)       
  
   Body as a whole - general disorders                                                                        
   Fatigue                                          18                    30                    3             
   Central and peripheral nervous system disorders                                                                       
   Dizziness                                        16                    13                    5             
   Dystonia                                         8                     13                    2             
   Parkinsonism                                     2                     7                     2             
   Akathisia                                        0                     7                     2             
   Gastrointestinal system disorders                                                                          
   Abdominal pain                                   18                    15                    5             
   Dyspepsia                                        16                    5                     3             
   Nausea                                           16                    13                    7             
   Vomiting                                         12                    10                    7             
   Diarrhea                                         8                     7                     2             
   Heart rate and rhythm disorders                                                                            
   Tachycardia                                      0                     5                     2             
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                      
   Somnolence                                       42                    56                    19            
   Appetite increased                               4                     7                     2             
   Anxiety                                          0                     8                     3             
   Reproductive disorders, female                                                                             
   Lactation nonpuerperal                           2                     5                     0             
   Respiratory system disorders                                                                               
   Rhinitis                                         14                    13                    10            
   Dyspnea                                          2                     5                     0             
   Skin and appendages disorders                                                                              
   Rash                                             0                     7                     2             
   Urinary system disorders                                                                                   
   Urinary incontinence                             0                     5                     0             
   Vision disorders                                                                                           
   Vision abnormal                                  4                     7                     0             
            6.3 Commonly-Observed Adverse Reactions in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials - Autistic Disorder
   Table 6 lists the adverse reactions reported in 5% or more of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated pediatric patients treated for irritability associated with autistic disorder in two 8-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials.



 Table 6. Adverse Reactions in &gt;=5% of RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Pediatric Patients Treated for Irritability Associated with Autistic Disorder in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                                                     Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
 Body System  Adverse Reaction                       RISPERDAL  (r)  0.5-4.0 mg per day(N=76)        Placebo(N=80)         
  
   Body as a whole - general disorders                                                                      
   Fatigue                                                      42                         13               
   Fever                                                        20                         19               
   Central and peripheral nervous system disorders                                                           
   Dystonia                                                     12                          6               
   Tremor                                                       12                          1               
   Dizziness                                                     9                          3               
   Parkinsonism                                                  8                          0               
   Automatism                                                    7                          1               
   Dyskinesia                                                    7                          0               
   Gastrointestinal system disorders                                                                        
   Vomiting                                                     25                         21               
   Saliva increased                                             22                          6               
   Constipation                                                 21                          8               
   Mouth dry                                                    13                          6               
   Nausea                                                        8                          8               
   Heart rate and rhythm disorders                                                                          
   Tachycardia                                                   7                          0               
   Metabolic and nutritional disorders                                                                      
   Weight increase                                               5                          0               
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                    
   Somnolence                                                   67                         23               
   Appetite increased                                           49                         19               
   Anxiety                                                      16                         15               
   Anorexia                                                      8                          8               
   Confusion                                                     5                          0               
   Respiratory system disorders                                                                             
   Rhinitis                                                     36                         23               
     Upper respiratory tract infection                          34                         15               
   Coughing                                                     24                         18               
   Skin and appendages disorders                                                                            
   Rash                                                         11                          8               
   Urinary system disorders                                                                                 
   Urinary incontinence                                         22                         20               
           6.4 Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of RISPERDAL  (r)  
   The following adverse reactions occurred in &lt; 1% of the adult patients and in &lt; 5% of the pediatric patients treated with RISPERDAL  (r)  in the above double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial data sets. In addition, the following also includes adverse reactions reported in RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients who participated in other studies, including double-blind, active-controlled and open-label studies in schizophrenia and bipolar mania studies in pediatric patients with psychiatric disorders other than schizophrenia, bipolar mania, or autistic disorder, and studies in elderly patients with dementia.



 Body as a Whole, General Disorders: edema peripheral, pain, influenza-like symptoms, leg pain, malaise, allergy, crying abnormal, allergic reaction, rigors, allergy aggravated, anaphylactoid reaction, hypothermia



 Central Nervous System Disorders: gait abnormal, speech disorder, coma, ataxia, dysphonia, stupor, cramps legs, vertigo, hypoesthesia, tardive dyskinesia, neuroleptic malignant syndrome



 Endocrine Disorders: hyperprolactinemia, gynecomastia



 Gastrointestinal System Disorders: dysphagia, flatulence



 Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders: AV block, bundle branch block



 Liver and Biliary Disorders: SGPT increased, hepatic enzymes increased



 Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders: thirst, hyperglycemia, xerophthalmia, generalized edema, diabetes mellitus aggravated, diabetic coma



 Musculoskeletal Disorders: muscle weakness, rhabdomyolysis



 Platelet, Bleeding, and Clotting Disorders: purpura



 Psychiatric Disorders: insomnia, agitation, emotional lability, apathy, nervousness, concentration impaired, impotence  ,  decreased libido



 Reproductive Disorders, Female: amenorrhea, menstrual disorder, leukorrhea



 Reproductive Disorders, Male: ejaculation disorder, abnormal sexual function, priapism



 Resistance Mechanism Disorders: otitis media, viral infection



 Respiratory Disorders: respiratory disorder



 Skin and Appendages Disorders: skin ulceration, skin discoloration, rash erythematous, skin exfoliation, rash maculopapular, erythema multiforme



 Urinary Disorders: micturition frequency



 Vascular Disorders: cerebrovascular disorder



 Vision Disorders: conjunctivitis



 White Cell Disorders: leucopenia, granulocytopenia



   6.5 Discontinuations Due to Adverse Reactions

  Schizophrenia - Adults



 Approximately 7% (39/564) of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients in double-blind, placebo-controlled trials discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, compared with 4% (10/225) who were receiving placebo. The adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in 2 or more RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients were:



 Table 7. Adverse Reactions Associated With Discontinuation in 2 or More RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Adult Patients in Schizophrenia Trials 
                                             RISPERDAL  (r)                             
 Adverse Reaction                           2-8 mg/day(N=366)    &gt;8-16 mg/day(N=198)      Placebo(N=225)      
  
 Dizziness                                         1.4%                  1.0%                   0%            
 Nausea                                            1.4%                   0%                    0%            
 Agitation                                         1.1%                  1.0%                   0%            
 Parkinsonism                                      0.8%                   0%                    0%            
 Somnolence                                        0.8%                  0.5%                   0%            
 Dystonia                                          0.5%                   0%                    0%            
 Abdominal pain                                    0.5%                   0%                    0%            
 Hypotension postural                              0.3%                  0.5%                   0%            
 Tachycardia                                       0.3%                  0.5%                   0%            
 Akathisia                                          0%                   1.0%                   0%            
          Discontinuation for extrapyramidal symptoms (including Parkinsonism, akathisia, dystonia, and tardive dyskinesia) was 1% in placebo-treated patients, and 3.4% in active control-treated patients in a double-blind, placebo- and active-controlled trial.
 

   Schizophrenia - Pediatrics



 Approximately 7% (7/106), of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients discontinued treatment due to an adverse event in a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, compared with 4% (2/54) placebo-treated patients. The adverse reactions associated with discontinuation for at least one RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patient were somnolence (2%), dizziness (2%), anorexia (1%), anxiety (1%), ataxia (1%), hypotension (1%), and palpitation (1%).



   Bipolar Mania - Adults



 In double-blind, placebo-controlled trials with RISPERDAL  (r)  as monotherapy, approximately 6% (25/448) of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, compared with approximately 5% (19/424) of placebo-treated patients. The adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients were:



 Table 8. Adverse Reactions Associated With Discontinuation in 2 or More RISPERDAL(r)-Treated Adult Patients in Bipolar Mania Clinical Trials 
 Adverse Reaction                                    RISPERDAL  (r)  1-6 mg/day(N=448)       Placebo(N=424)         
  
 Parkinsonism                                                  0.4%                        0%               
 Somnolence                                                    0.2%                        0%               
 Dizziness                                                     0.2%                        0%               
 Dystonia                                                      0.2%                        0%               
 SGOT increased                                                0.2%                       0.2%              
 SGPT increased                                                0.2%                       0.2%              
           Bipolar Mania - Pediatrics
 

 In a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial 12% (13/111) of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients discontinued due to an adverse event, compared with 7% (4/58) of placebo-treated patients. The adverse reactions associated with discontinuation in more than one RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated pediatric patient were somnolence (5%), nausea (3%), abdominal pain (2%), and vomiting (2%).



   Autistic Disorder - Pediatrics



 In the two 8-week, placebo-controlled trials in pediatric patients treated for irritability associated with autistic disorder (n = 156), one RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patient discontinued due to an adverse reaction (Parkinsonism), and one placebo-treated patient discontinued due to an adverse event.



   6.6 Dose Dependency of Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials

  Extrapyramidal Symptoms



 Data from two fixed-dose trials in adults with schizophrenia provided evidence of dose-relatedness for extrapyramidal symptoms associated with RISPERDAL  (r)  treatment.



 Two methods were used to measure extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS) in an 8-week trial comparing 4 fixed doses of RISPERDAL  (r)  (2, 6, 10, and 16 mg/day), including (1) a Parkinsonism score (mean change from baseline) from the Extrapyramidal Symptom Rating Scale, and (2) incidence of spontaneous complaints of EPS:




 Dose Groups               Placebo       RISPERDAL  (r)  2 mg  RISPERDAL  (r)  6 mg  RISPERDAL  (r)  10 mg  RISPERDAL  (r)  16 mg   
  
 Parkinsonism                1.2               0.9               1.8               2.4               2.6          
 EPS Incidence               11%               15%               16%               20%               31%          
            Similar methods were used to measure extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS) in an 8-week trial comparing 5 fixed doses of RISPERDAL  (r)  (1, 4, 8, 12, and 16 mg/day):
 


 Dose Groups           RISPERDAL  (r)  1 mg  RISPERDAL  (r)  4 mg  RISPERDAL  (r)  8 mg  RISPERDAL  (r)  12 mg  RISPERDAL  (r)  16 mg   
  
 Parkinsonism                0.6               1.7               2.4               2.9               4.1          
 EPS Incidence                7%               11%               17%               18%               20%          
              Dystonia
 

     Class Effect:  Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



   Other Adverse Reactions



 Adverse event data elicited by a checklist for side effects from a large study comparing 5 fixed doses of RISPERDAL  (r)  (1, 4, 8, 12, and 16 mg/day) were explored for dose-relatedness of adverse events. A Cochran-Armitage Test for trend in these data revealed a positive trend (p&lt;0.05) for the following adverse reactions: somnolence, vision abnormal, dizziness, palpitations, weight increase, erectile dysfunction, ejaculation disorder, sexual function abnormal, fatigue, and skin discoloration.



   6.7 Changes in Body Weight

  The proportions of RISPERDAL  (r)  and placebo-treated adult patients with schizophrenia meeting a weight gain criterion of &gt;= 7% of body weight were compared in a pool of 6- to 8-week, placebo-controlled trials, revealing a statistically significantly greater incidence of weight gain for RISPERDAL  (r)  (18%) compared to placebo (9%). In a pool of placebo-controlled 3-week studies in adult patients with acute mania, the incidence of weight increase of &gt;= 7% at endpoint was comparable in the RISPERDAL  (r)  (2.5%) and placebo (2.4%) groups, and was slightly higher in the active-control group (3.5%).



 Changes in body weight were also evaluated in pediatric patients  [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  



   6.8 Changes in ECG

  Between-group comparisons for pooled placebo-controlled trials in adults revealed no statistically significant differences between risperidone and placebo in mean changes from baseline in ECG parameters, including QT, QTc, and PR intervals, and heart rate. When all RISPERDAL  (r)  doses were pooled from randomized controlled trials in several indications, there was a mean increase in heart rate of 1 beat per minute compared to no change for placebo patients. In short-term schizophrenia trials, higher doses of risperidone (8-16 mg/day) were associated with a higher mean increase in heart rate compared to placebo (4-6 beats per minute). In pooled placebo-controlled acute mania trials in adults, there were small decreases in mean heart rate, similar among all treatment groups.



 In the two placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with autistic disorder (aged 5 - 16 years) mean changes in heart rate were an increase of 8.4 beats per minute in the RISPERDAL  (r)  groups and 6.5 beats per minute in the placebo group. There were no other notable ECG changes.



 In a placebo-controlled acute mania trial in children and adolescents (aged 10 - 17 years), there were no significant changes in ECG parameters, other than the effect of RISPERDAL  (r)  to transiently increase pulse rate (&lt; 6 beats per minute). In two controlled schizophrenia trials in adolescents (aged 13 - 17 years), there were no clinically meaningful changes in ECG parameters including corrected QT intervals between treatment groups or within treatment groups over time.



   6.9 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of risperidone; because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency: agranulocytosis, alopecia, anaphylactic reaction, angioedema, atrial fibrillation, diabetes mellitus, diabetic ketoacidosis in patients with impaired glucose metabolism, hypoglycemia, inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion, intestinal obstruction, jaundice, mania, pancreatitis, QT prolongation, sleep apnea, thrombocytopenia, urinary retention, and water intoxication.



 Other adverse events reported since market introduction, which were temporally related to risperidone but not necessarily causally related, include the following: pituitary adenoma, pulmonary embolism, precocious puberty, cardiopulmonary arrest, and sudden death.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of 17 placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. RISPERDAL  (r)   (risperidone) is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis.   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. RISPERDAL  (r)   is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis. (  5.1  )  



 









    BOXED WARNING: 

      DOSAGE:   For information about the use of   RISPERDAL  (r)     (risperidone), please see accompanying   Package Insert  .



   STORAGE:   Store bottle at controlled room temperature (59 degrees -77 degrees F/15 degrees -25 degrees C) away from children; avoid freezing and protect from light.



 Manufactured by:Janssen Pharmaceutica N.V.Beerse, Belgium



 Manufactured for:Janssen, Division of Ortho-McNeil-JanssenPharmaceuticals, Inc.Titusville, NJ, United States 08560
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Cerebrovascular events, including stroke, in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis. RISPERDAL  (r)  is not approved for use in patients with dementia-related psychosis (  5.2  ) 
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (  5.3  ) 
 *  Tardive dyskinesia (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hyperglycemia and diabetes mellitus (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hyperprolactinemia (  5.6  ) 
 *  Orthostatic hypotension (  5.7  ) 
 *  Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis: has been reported with antipsychotics, including risperidone. Patients with a history of a clinically significant low white blood cell count (WBC) or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and discontinuation of RISPERDAL  (r)  should be considered at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Potential for cognitive and motor impairment (  5.9  ) 
 *  Seizures (  5.10  ) 
 *  Dysphagia (  5.11  ) 
 *  Priapism (  5.12  ) 
 *  Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP) (  5.13  ) 
 *  Disruption of body temperature regulation (  5.14  ) 
 *  Antiemetic Effect (  5.15  ) 
 *  Suicide (  5.16  ) 
 *  Increased sensitivity in patients with Parkinson's disease or those with dementia with Lewy bodies (  5.17  ) 
 *  Diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses (  5.17  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



   Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. RISPERDAL  (r)  (risperidone) is not approved for the treatment of dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  ]  .  



    5.2 Cerebrovascular Adverse Events, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Cerebrovascular adverse events (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack), including fatalities, were reported in patients (mean age 85 years; range 73-97) in trials of risperidone in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis. In placebo-controlled trials, there was a significantly higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse events in patients treated with risperidone compared to patients treated with placebo. RISPERDAL  (r)  is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis. [See also  Boxed Warnings  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with antipsychotic drugs. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to identify cases in which the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: (1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and (3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for uncomplicated NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. The patient should be carefully monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4 Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses.



 There is no known treatment for established cases of tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and thereby may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, RISPERDAL  (r)  should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who suffer from a chronic illness that: (1) is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs, and (2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient treated with RISPERDAL  (r)  , drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with RISPERDAL  (r)  despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.5 Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus



  Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics including RISPERDAL  (r)  . Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse events is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of treatment-emergent hyperglycemia-related adverse events in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. Precise risk estimates for hyperglycemia-related adverse events in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics are not available.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (e.g., obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



    5.6 Hyperprolactinemia



  As with other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2receptors, RISPERDAL  (r)  elevates prolactin levels and the elevation persists during chronic administration. RISPERDAL  (r)  is associated with higher levels of prolactin elevation than other antipsychotic agents.



 Hyperprolactinemia may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotropin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported in patients receiving prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male subjects.



 Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin dependent in vitro  , a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is contemplated in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. An increase in pituitary gland, mammary gland, and pancreatic islet cell neoplasia (mammary adenocarcinomas, pituitary and pancreatic adenomas) was observed in the risperidone carcinogenicity studies conducted in mice and rats [see  Non-Clinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans; the available evidence is considered too limited to be conclusive at this time.



    5.7 Orthostatic Hypotension



  RISPERDAL  (r)  may induce orthostatic hypotension associated with dizziness, tachycardia, and in some patients, syncope, especially during the initial dose-titration period, probably reflecting its alpha-adrenergic antagonistic properties. Syncope was reported in 0.2% (6/2607) of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients in Phase 2 and 3 studies in adults with schizophrenia. The risk of orthostatic hypotension and syncope may be minimized by limiting the initial dose to 2 mg total (either once daily or 1 mg twice daily) in normal adults and 0.5 mg twice daily in the elderly and patients with renal or hepatic impairment [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1    ,   2.4)  ]  . Monitoring of orthostatic vital signs should be considered in patients for whom this is of concern. A dose reduction should be considered if hypotension occurs. RISPERDAL  (r)  should be used with particular caution in patients with known cardiovascular disease (history of myocardial infarction or ischemia, heart failure, or conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, and conditions which would predispose patients to hypotension, e.g., dehydration and hypovolemia. Clinically significant hypotension has been observed with concomitant use of RISPERDAL  (r)  and antihypertensive medication.



    5.8 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



    Class Effect:  In clinical trial and/or postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia/neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents, including RISPERDAL  (r)  . Agranulocytosis has also been reported.  



  Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) and history of drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a history of a clinically significant low WBC or a drug-induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and discontinuation of RISPERDAL  (r)  should be considered at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.  



  Patients with clinically significant neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm  3  ) should discontinue RISPERDAL  (r)  and have their WBC followed until recovery.  



    5.9 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  Somnolence was a commonly reported adverse event associated with RISPERDAL  (r)  treatment, especially when ascertained by direct questioning of patients. This adverse event is dose-related, and in a study utilizing a checklist to detect adverse events, 41% of the high-dose patients (RISPERDAL  (r)  16 mg/day) reported somnolence compared to 16% of placebo patients. Direct questioning is more sensitive for detecting adverse events than spontaneous reporting, by which 8% of RISPERDAL  (r)  16 mg/day patients and 1% of placebo patients reported somnolence as an adverse event. Since RISPERDAL  (r)  has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills, patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that RISPERDAL  (r)  therapy does not affect them adversely.



    5.10 Seizures



  During premarketing testing in adult patients with schizophrenia, seizures occurred in 0.3% (9/2607) of RISPERDAL  (r)  -treated patients, two in association with hyponatremia. RISPERDAL  (r)  should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures.



    5.11 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in patients with advanced Alzheimer's dementia. RISPERDAL  (r)  and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia. [See also  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



    5.12 Priapism



  Rare cases of priapism have been reported. While the relationship of the events to RISPERDAL  (r)  use has not been established, other drugs with alpha-adrenergic blocking effects have been reported to induce priapism, and it is possible that RISPERDAL  (r)  may share this capacity. Severe priapism may require surgical intervention.



    5.13 Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP)



  A single case of TTP was reported in a 28 year-old female patient receiving oral RISPERDAL  (r)  in a large, open premarketing experience (approximately 1300 patients). She experienced jaundice, fever, and bruising, but eventually recovered after receiving plasmapheresis. The relationship to RISPERDAL  (r)  therapy is unknown.



    5.14 Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of body temperature regulation has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Both hyperthermia and hypothermia have been reported in association with oral RISPERDAL  (r)  use. Caution is advised when prescribing for patients who will be exposed to temperature extremes.



    5.15 Antiemetic Effect



  Risperidone has an antiemetic effect in animals; this effect may also occur in humans, and may mask signs and symptoms of overdosage with certain drugs or of conditions such as intestinal obstruction, Reye's syndrome, and brain tumor.



    5.16 Suicide



  The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in patients with schizophrenia and bipolar mania, including children and adolescent patients, and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy. Prescriptions for RISPERDAL  (r)  should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets, consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



    5.17 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with RISPERDAL  (r)  in patients with certain concomitant systemic illnesses is limited. Patients with Parkinson's Disease or Dementia with Lewy Bodies who receive antipsychotics, including RISPERDAL  (r)  , are reported to have an increased sensitivity to antipsychotic medications. Manifestations of this increased sensitivity have been reported to include confusion, obtundation, postural instability with frequent falls, extrapyramidal symptoms, and clinical features consistent with the neuroleptic malignant syndrome.



 Caution is advisable in using RISPERDAL  (r)  in patients with diseases or conditions that could affect metabolism or hemodynamic responses. RISPERDAL  (r)  has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarket testing.



 Increased plasma concentrations of risperidone and 9-hydroxyrisperidone occur in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ), and an increase in the free fraction of risperidone is seen in patients with severe hepatic impairment. A lower starting dose should be used in such patients [  see   Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



    5.18 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  No specific laboratory tests are recommended.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
