<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rivastigmine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6         ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following adverse reactions are described elsewhere in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *  Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)] . 
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions of the Skin [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . 
 *  Other Adverse Reactions from Increased Cholinergic Activity [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . 
      EXCERPT:   Most commonly observed adverse reactions (&gt;5% and 2 times greater than placebo): nausea, vomiting, anorexia, dyspepsia, and asthenia. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sandoz Inc at 1-800-525-8747 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1       Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Rivastigmine tartrate has been administered to over 5,297 individuals during clinical trials worldwide. Of these, 4,326 patients have been treated for at least 3 months, 3,407 patients have been treated for at least 6 months, 2,150 patients have been treated for 1 year, 1,250 patients have been treated for 2 years, and 168 patients have been treated for over 3 years. With regard to exposure to the highest dose, 2,809 patients were exposed to doses of 10 mg to 12 mg, 2,615 patients treated for 3 months, 2,328 patients treated for 6 months, 1,378 patients treated for 1 year, 917 patients treated for 2 years, and 129 patients treated for over 3 years.



   Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease  



   Most Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions  



 The most common adverse reactions, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% and twice the placebo rate, are largely predicted by rivastigmine tartrate's cholinergic effects. These include nausea, vomiting, anorexia, dyspepsia, and asthenia.



   Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions  



 rivastigmine tartrate use is associated with significant nausea, vomiting, and weight loss [  see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].



   Discontinuation Rates  



 The rate of discontinuation due to adverse events in controlled clinical trials of rivastigmine tartrate was 15% for patients receiving 6 mg to 12 mg per day compared to 5% for patients on placebo during forced weekly dose titration. While on a maintenance dose, the rates were 6% for patients on rivastigmine tartrate compared to 4% for those on placebo.



 The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation, defined as those occurring in at least 2% of patients and at twice the incidence seen in placebo patients, are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1 Most Frequent Adverse Reactions Leading to Withdrawal from Clinical Trials during Titration and Maintenance in Patients Receiving 6 mg to 12 mg per day Rivastigmine Tartrate Using a Forced-Dose Titration 
   Study Phase      Titration        Maintenance      Overall         
                    Rivastigmine Tartrate    &gt;=6-12 mg/day      Placebo          Rivastigmine Tartrate    &gt;=6-12 mg/day      Placebo          Rivastigmine Tartrate    &gt;=6-12 mg/day      Placebo         
                    (n=1,189)        (n=868)          (n=987)          (n=788)          (n=1,189)        (n=868)         
   Event/%    Discontinuing                                                                                                           
 Nausea           8                &lt;1               1                &lt;1               8                1                 
 Vomiting         4                &lt;1               1                &lt;1               5                &lt;1                
 Anorexia         2                0                1                &lt;1               3                &lt;1                
 Dizziness        2                &lt;1               1                &lt;1               2                &lt;1                
               Adverse Reactions Observed at an Incidence of at Least 2%  
 

 Table 2 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that were reported in at least 2% of patients in placebo-controlled trials and for which the rate of occurrence was greater for patients treated with rivastigmine tartrate doses of 6 mg to 12 mg per day than for those treated with placebo. The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the frequency of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice when patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those prevailing during clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be directly compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, or investigators. An inspection of these frequencies, however, does provide the prescriber with one basis by which to estimate the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the adverse event incidences in the population studied.



 In general, adverse reactions were less frequent later in the course of treatment.



 No systematic effect of race or age could be determined from the incidence of adverse events in the controlled studies. Nausea, vomiting and weight loss were more frequent in women than men.



 Table 2 Proportion of Adverse Reactions Observed with a Frequency of &gt;=2% and at a Rate Greater than Placebo in Clinical Trials 
   Body System/Adverse Reaction      Rivastigmine Tartrate    (6-12 mg/day)    (n=1,189)      Placebo    (n=868)     
   Percent of Patients with any Adverse Event    92               79                
                   
   Autonomic Nervous System     
       Sweating Increased  4                1                 
       Syncope    3                2                 
   Body as a Whole     
       Fatigue    9                5                 
       Asthenia   6                2                 
       Malaise    5                2                 
       Weight Decrease**  3                &lt;1                
   Cardiovascular Disorders, General     
       Hypertension  3                2                 
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System     
       Dizziness  21               11                
       Headache   17               12                
       Somnolence  5                3                 
       Tremor     4                1                 
   Gastrointestinal System     
       Nausea*    47               12                
       Vomiting*  31               6                 
       Diarrhea   19               11                
       Anorexia***  17               3                 
       Abdominal Pain  13               6                 
       Dyspepsia  9                4                 
   Psychiatric Disorders     
       Insomnia   9                7                 
       Confusion  8                7                 
       Depression  6                4                 
       Anxiety    5                3                 
       Hallucination  4                3                 
       Aggressive Reaction  3                2                 
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders     
       Urinary Tract Infection  7                6                 
         *Nausea and Vomiting: In the controlled clinical trials, 47% of the patients treated with a rivastigmine tartrate dose in the therapeutic range of 6 mg to 12 mg per day (n=1189) developed nausea (compared with 12% in placebo). A total of 31% of rivastigmine tartrate-treated patients developed at least 1 episode of vomiting (compared with 6% for placebo). The rate of vomiting was higher during the titration phase (24% versus 3% for placebo) than in the maintenance phase (14% versus 3% for placebo). The rates were higher in women than men. Five percent of patients discontinued for vomiting, compared to less than 1% for patients on placebo. Vomiting was severe in 2% of rivastigmine tartrate-treated patients and was rated as mild or moderate each in 14% of patients. The rate of nausea was higher during the titration phase (43% versus 9% for placebo) than in the maintenance phase (17% versus 4% for placebo).
 

 **Weight Decreased: In the controlled trials, approximately 26% of women on high doses of rivastigmine tartrate (greater than 9 mg per day) had weight loss equal to or greater than 7% of their baseline weight compared to 6% in the placebo-treated patients. About 18% of the males in the high-dose group experienced a similar degree of weight loss compared to 4% in placebo-treated patients. It is not clear how much of the weight loss was associated with anorexia, nausea, vomiting, and the diarrhea associated with the drug.



 ***Anorexia: In the controlled clinical trials, of the patients treated with a rivastigmine tartrate dose of 6 mg to 12 mg per day, 17% developed anorexia compared to 3% of the placebo patients. Neither the time course nor the severity of the anorexia is known.



   Mild to Moderate Parkinson's Disease Dementia  



 Rivastigmine tartrate has been administered to 779 individuals during clinical trials worldwide. Of these, 663 patients have been treated for at least 3 months, 476 patients have been treated for at least 6 months, and 313 patients have been treated for 1 year.



   Most Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions  



 The most common adverse events, defined as those occurring at a frequency of at least 5% and twice the placebo rate, are largely predicted by rivastigmine tartrate's cholinergic effects. These include nausea, vomiting, tremor, anorexia, and dizziness.



   Discontinuation Rates  



 The rate of discontinuation due to adverse events in the single placebo-controlled trial of rivastigmine tartrate was 18.2% for patients receiving 3 mg to 12 mg per day compared to 11.2% for patients on placebo during the 24-week study.



 The most frequent adverse events that led to discontinuation from this study, defined as those occurring in at least 1% of patients receiving rivastigmine tartrate and more frequent than those receiving placebo, were nausea (3.6% rivastigmine tartrate versus 0.6% placebo), vomiting (1.9% rivastigmine tartrate versus 0.6% placebo), and tremor (1.7% rivastigmine tartrate versus 0.0% placebo).



   Adverse Reactions Observed at an Incidence of at Least 2%  



 Table 3 lists treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that were reported in at least 2% of patients in a single placebo-controlled trial and during the first 24 weeks of a 76-week open-label active-controlled trial for which the rate of occurrence was greater for patients treated with rivastigmine tartrate doses of 3 mg to 12 mg per day than for those treated with placebo in the placebo-controlled trial. The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the frequency of adverse events in the course of usual medical practice when patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those prevailing during clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be directly compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, or investigators. An inspection of these frequencies, however, does provide the prescriber with 1 basis by which to estimate the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse event incidences in the population studied.



 In general, adverse reactions were less frequent later in the course of treatment.



 Table 3 Proportion of Adverse Reactions Observed at a Frequency &gt;=2% and Occurring at Rate Greater than Placebo in Clinical Trials 
                    Active-ControlledStudy      Placebo-ControlledStudy     
   Body System/Adverse Reaction      Rivastigmine Tartrate    (3-12 mg/day)    (n=294)      Rivastigmine Tartrate    (3-12 mg/day)    (n=362)      Placebo    (n=179)     
   Percent of Patients with any Adverse Event    88               84               71                
                   
   Gastrointestinal Disorders     
 Nausea           38               29               11                
 Vomiting         13               17               2                 
 Diarrhea         8                7                4                 
 Upper Abdominal Pain  4                4                1                 
 Salivary hypersecretion  2                1                0                 
   General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions     
 Fall             10               6                6                 
 Fatigue          5                4                3                 
 Asthenia         4                2                1                 
   Metabolism and Nutritional Disorders     
 Anorexia         -                6                3                 
 Decreased Appetite  5                8                5                 
 Dehydration      1                2                1                 
   Nervous System Disorders     
 Tremor           23               10               4                 
 Dizziness        8                6                1                 
 Headache         4                4                3                 
 Somnolence       6                4                3                 
 Parkinson's Disease (worsening)  -*               3                1                 
 Bradykinesia     3                3                2                 
 Dyskinesia       3                1                1                 
 Cogwheel rigidity  3                1                0                 
 Hypokinesia      2                1                0                 
 Parkinsonism     -                2                1                 
   Psychiatric Disorders     
 Anxiety          4                4                1                 
 Insomnia         2                3                2                 
 Restlessness     1                3                2                 
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders     
 Sweating increased  2                2                1                 
          *Parkinson's disease (worsening) in the active-controlled study was assessed by reported pre-identified adverse events (tremor, cogwheel rigidity, fall), each of them listed with corresponding frequencies.
 

   Other Adverse Events Observed During Clinical Trials  



   Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease  



 Treatment-emergent signs and symptoms that occurred during 8 controlled clinical trials and 9 open-label trials in North America, Western Europe, Australia, South Africa, and Japan were recorded as adverse events by the clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. To provide an overall estimate of the proportion of individuals having similar types of events, the events were grouped into a smaller number of standardized categories using a modified WHO dictionary, and event frequencies were calculated across all studies. These categories are used in the listing below. The frequencies represent the proportion of 5,297 patients from these trials who experienced that event while receiving rivastigmine tartrate. All adverse events occurring in at least 6 patients (approximately 0.1%) are included, except for those already listed elsewhere in labeling, WHO terms too general to be informative, relatively minor events, or events unlikely to be drug-caused.



 Events are classified by body system and listed using the following definitions: frequent adverse events-those occurring in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events-those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients. These adverse events are not necessarily related to rivastigmine tartrate treatment and in most cases were observed at a similar frequency in placebo-treated patients in the controlled studies.



 Autonomic Nervous System:  Infrequent:  Increased saliva.



 Body as a Whole:  Frequent  : Allergy, hot flushes.



 Cardiovascular System:  Frequent:  Hypotension, postural hypotension.



 Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  Frequent:  Abnormal gait, ataxia, paresthesia, convulsions.  Infrequent:  Dysphonia, hypoesthesia, migraine, nystagmus.



 Gastrointestinal System:  Frequent:  Gastritis, constipation, flatulence.  Infrequent:  Gastric ulcer, gastroesophageal reflux, GI hemorrhage, hernia, melena, rectal hemorrhage, duodenal ulcer, hematemesis, pancreatitis.



 Hearing and Vestibular Disorders:  Frequent:  Tinnitus.



 Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders:  Frequent:  Atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, palpitation.  Infrequent:  AV block, sick sinus syndrome, supraventricular tachycardia, extrasystoles, tachycardia.



 Liver and Biliary System Disorders:  Infrequent:  Abnormal hepatic function tests.



 Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  Frequent:  Dehydration, hypokalemia.  Infrequent:  Hyponatremia.



 Musculoskeletal Disorders:  Infrequent:  Muscle weakness.



 Myo-, Endo-, Pericardial and Valve Disorders:  Frequent:  Angina pectoris, myocardial infarction.



 Psychiatric Disorders:  Frequent:  Confusion.  Infrequent:  Apathy, suicide attempt, increased libido, suicidal ideation.



 Reproductive Disorders (Female and Male):  Infrequent:  Breast pain.



 Resistance Mechanism Disorders:  Infrequent:  Herpes simplex, otitis media.



 Respiratory System:  Infrequent:  Bronchospasm.



 Skin and Appendages:  Frequent:  Rashes of various kinds (maculopapular, eczema, bullous, exfoliative, psoriaform, erythematous).  Infrequent:  Urticaria, contact dermatitis.



 Urinary System Disorders:  Frequent:  Hematuria.  Infrequent:  Acute renal failure, dysuria.



 Vascular (extracardiac) Disorders:  Infrequent:  Peripheral ischemia, intracranial hemorrhage.



 Vision Disorders: Frequent: Cataract.  Infrequent:  Diplopia, glaucoma.



 White Cell and Resistance Disorders:  Infrequent:  Lymphadenopathy.



   Mild to Moderate Parkinson's Disease Dementia  



 Additional treatment-emergent adverse events in patients with Parkinson's disease dementia occurring in at least 1 patient (approximately 0.3%) are listed below, excluding events that are already listed above for the dementia of the Alzheimer's type or elsewhere in labeling, WHO terms too general to be informative, relatively minor events, or events unlikely to be drug-caused. Events are classified by body system and listed using the following definitions: frequent adverse events- those occurring in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events-those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients. These adverse events are not necessarily related to rivastigmine tartrate treatment and in most cases were observed at a similar frequency in placebo-treated patients in the controlled studies.



 Central and Peripheral Nervous System  : Frequent:  Transient ischemic attack.



 Gastrointestinal System:  Frequent:  Dyspepsia.  Infrequent:  Fecaloma, dysphagia.



 General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Frequent:  Chest pain.



 Liver and Biliary System Disorders:  Infrequent:  Elevated gamma-glutamyltransferase level.



 Musculoskeletal Disorders:  Frequent:  Back pain.  Infrequent:  Muscle stiffness.



 Psychiatric Disorders:  Frequent:  Agitation, depression.



 Respiratory System:  Frequent:  Dyspnea.  Infrequent:  Cough.



 Urinary System Disorders:  Infrequent:  Urinary incontinence.



 Vision Disorders:  Infrequent:  Blurred vision.



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed with Rivastigmine Transdermal Patch  



 The following additional adverse reactions have been observed with rivastigmine transdermal patch:



 Cerebrovascular accident, delirium, psychomotor hyperactivity, erythema, blister, dermatitis allergic.



   6.2       Postmarketing Experience

  Voluntary reports of adverse events temporally associated with rivastigmine tartrate that have been received since market introduction that are not listed above, and that may or may not be causally related to the drug include the following:



 Hepatobiliary Disorders: Hepatitis.



 Psychiatric Disorders: Aggression.



   Skin and Appendages:  Stevens-Johnson syndrome, disseminated cutaneous hypersensitivity reactions.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5        WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Gastrointestinal adverse reactions: may include significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss, and may necessitate treatment interruption. Dehydration may result from prolonged vomiting or diarrhea and can be associated with serious outcomes. (  5.1  ). 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions of the skin: Discontinue rivastigmine in case of disseminated hypersensitivity reaction of the skin, which may occur after oral or transdermal administration. (  4  ,  5.2  ) In patients with suspected allergic contact dermatitis after transdermal rivastigmine use, switch to oral rivastigmine only after negative allergy testing. 
    
 

   5.1       Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions



   Rivastigmine tartrate can cause gastrointestinal adverse reactions, including significant nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia/decreased appetite, and weight loss.   Dehydration may result from prolonged vomiting or diarrhea and can be associated with serious outcomes. The incidence and severity of these reactions are dose-related   [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]   . For this reason, patients should always be started at a dose of 1.5 mg   twice a day   and titrated to their maintenance dose.  



  If treatment is interrupted for   longer than 3   days, treatment should be reinitiated with the lowest daily dose   [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]   to reduce the possibility of severe vomiting and its potentially serious sequelae (e.g., there has been one postmarketing report of severe vomiting with esophageal rupture following inappropriate reinitiation of treatment with a 4.5-mg dose after 8 weeks of treatment interruption).  



 Inform caregivers to monitor for gastrointestinal adverse reactions and to inform the physician if they occur.  It is critical to inform caregivers that if therapy has been interrupted for more than 3 days because of intolerance, the next dose should not be administered without contacting the physician regarding proper retitration.



    5.2       Hypersensitivity Reactions of the Skin



   There have been isolated postmarketing reports of patients experiencing disseminated hypersensitivity reactions of the skin when administered rivastigmine irrespective of the route of administration (oral or transdermal). Treatment should be discontinued if disseminated hypersensitivity reaction of the skin occurs [see Contraindications (4)]  . Patients and caregivers should be instructed accordingly [see Patient Counseling Information (17)]  .  



  In patients who develop application site reactions suggestive of allergic contact dermatitis to rivastigmine transdermal patch and who still require rivastigmine, treatment should be switched to oral rivastigmine only after negative allergy testing and under close medical supervision. It is possible that some patients sensitized to rivastigmine by exposure to rivastigmine patch may not be able to take rivastigmine in any form.  



    5.3       Other Adverse Reactions from Increased Cholinergic Activity



   Neurologic Effects  



  Extrapyramidal Symptoms  : Cholinomimetics, including rivastigmine may exacerbate or induce extrapyramidal symptoms. Worsening of parkinsonian symptoms, particularly tremor, has been observed in patients with dementia associated with Parkinson's disease who were treated with rivastigmine tartrate capsules.



  Seizures  : Drugs that increase cholinergic activity are believed to have some potential for causing seizures. However, seizure activity also may be a manifestation of Alzheimer's disease.



  Peptic Ulcers/Gastrointestinal Bleeding  



 Cholinesterase inhibitors, including rivastigmine, may be expected to increase gastric acid secretion due to increased cholinergic activity. Monitor patients using rivastigmine tartrate for symptoms of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, especially those at increased risk for developing ulcers, e.g., those with a history of ulcer disease or those receiving concurrent nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). Clinical studies of rivastigmine have shown no significant increase, relative to placebo, in the incidence of either peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding.



  Use with Anesthesia  



 Rivastigmine, as a cholinesterase inhibitor, is likely to exaggerate succinylcholine-type muscle relaxation during anesthesia.



  Cardiac Conduction Effects  



 Because rivastigmine increases cholinergic activity, use of rivastigmine may have vagotonic effects on heart rate (e.g., bradycardia). The potential for this action may be particularly important in patients with sick sinus syndrome or other supraventricular cardiac conduction conditions. In clinical trials, rivastigmine was not associated with any increased incidence of cardiovascular adverse events, heart rate or blood pressure changes, or ECG abnormalities. Syncopal episodes have been reported in 3% of patients receiving 6 mg to 12 mg per day of rivastigmine tartrate, compared to 2% of placebo patients.



  Genitourinary Effects  



 Although not observed in clinical trials of rivastigmine, drugs that increase cholinergic activity may cause urinary obstruction.



  Pulmonary Effects  



 Drugs that increase cholinergic activity, including rivastigmine, should be used with care in patients with a history of asthma or obstructive pulmonary disease.



    5.4       Impairment in Driving or Use of Machinery



  Dementia may cause gradual impairment of driving performance or compromise the ability to use machinery. The administration of rivastigmine may also result in adverse reactions that are detrimental to these functions. During treatment with rivastigmine tartrate, routinely evaluate the patient's ability to continue driving or operating machinery.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
