<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rotarix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Common (&gt;=5%) solicited adverse events included fussiness/irritability, cough/runny nose, fever, loss of appetite, and vomiting. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. As with any vaccine, there is the possibility that broad use of ROTARIX could reveal adverse reactions not observed in clinical trials.



 Solicited and unsolicited adverse events, serious adverse events and cases of intussusception were collected in 7 clinical studies. Cases of intussusception and serious adverse events were collected in an additional large safety study. These 8 clinical studies evaluated a total of 71,209 infants who received ROTARIX (N = 36,755) or placebo (N = 34,454). The racial distribution for these studies was as follows: Hispanic 73.4%, white 16.2%, black 1.0%, and other 9.4%; 51% were male.



   Solicited Adverse Events:  In 7 clinical studies, detailed safety information was collected by parents/guardians for 8 consecutive days following vaccination with ROTARIX (i.e., day of vaccination and the next 7 days). A diary card was completed to record fussiness/irritability, cough/runny nose, the infant's temperature, loss of appetite, vomiting, or diarrhea on a daily basis during the first week following each dose of ROTARIX or placebo. Adverse events among recipients of ROTARIX and placebo occurred at similar rates (Table 1).



 Table 1. Solicited Adverse Events Within 8 Days Following Doses 1 and 2 of ROTARIX or Placebo (Total Vaccinated Cohort) 
                                   Dose 1              Dose 2            
                                   ROTARIX             Placebo           ROTARIX             Placebo           
                                   N = 3,284           N = 2,013         N = 3,201           N = 1,973         
                                   %                   %                 %                   %                 
  Fussiness/irritabilitya          52                  52                42                  42                
  Cough/runny noseb                28                  30                31                  33                
  Feverc                           25                  33                28                  34                
  Loss of appetited                25                  25                21                  21                
  Vomiting                         13                  11                8                   8                 
  Diarrhea                         4                   3                 3                   3                 
          *     Total vaccinated cohort = all vaccinated infants for whom safety data were available. 
 *     N = number of infants for whom at least one symptom sheet was completed. 
 *       a  Defined as crying more than usual. 
 *       b  Data not collected in 1 of 7 studies; Dose 1: ROTARIX N = 2,583; placebo N = 1,897; Dose 2: ROTARIX N = 2,522; placebo N = 1,863. 
 *       c  Defined as temperature &gt;=100.4 degrees F (&gt;=38.0 degrees C) rectally or &gt;=99.5 degrees F (&gt;=37.5 degrees C) orally. 
 *       d  Defined as eating less than usual. 
      Unsolicited Adverse Events:  Infants were monitored for unsolicited serious and non-serious adverse events that occurred in the 31-day period following vaccination in 7 clinical studies. The following adverse events occurred at a statistically higher incidence (95% Confidence Interval [CI] of Relative Risk excluding 1) among recipients of ROTARIX (N = 5,082) as compared with placebo recipients (N = 2,902): irritability (ROTARIX 11.4%, placebo 8.7%) and flatulence (ROTARIX 2.2%, placebo 1.3%).
 

   Serious Adverse Events (SAEs):  Infants were monitored for serious adverse events that occurred in the 31-day period following vaccination in 8 clinical studies. Serious adverse events occurred in 1.7% of recipients of ROTARIX (N = 36,755) as compared with 1.9% of placebo recipients (N = 34,454). Among placebo recipients, diarrhea (placebo 0.07%, ROTARIX 0.02%), dehydration (placebo 0.06%, ROTARIX 0.02%), and gastroenteritis (placebo 0.3%, ROTARIX 0.2%) occurred at a statistically higher incidence (95% CI of Relative Risk excluding 1) as compared with recipients of ROTARIX.



   Deaths:  During the entire course of 8 clinical studies, there were 68 (0.19%) deaths following administration of ROTARIX (N = 36,755) and 50 (0.15%) deaths following placebo administration (N = 34,454). The most commonly reported cause of death following vaccination was pneumonia, which was observed in 19 (0.05%) recipients of ROTARIX and 10 (0.03%) placebo recipients (Relative Risk: 1.74, 95% CI: 0.76, 4.23).



   Intussusception:  In a controlled safety study conducted in Latin America and Finland, the risk of intussusception was evaluated in 63,225 infants (31,673 received ROTARIX and 31,552 received placebo). Infants were monitored by active surveillance including independent, complementary methods (prospective hospital surveillance and parent reporting at scheduled study visits) to identify potential cases of intussusception within 31 days after vaccination and, in a subset of 20,169 infants (10,159 received ROTARIX and 10,010 received placebo), up to one year after the first dose.



 No increased risk of intussusception following administration of ROTARIX was observed within a 31-day period following any dose, and rates were comparable to the placebo group after a median of 100 days (Table 2). In a subset of 20,169 infants (10,159 received ROTARIX and 10,010 received placebo) followed up to one year after dose 1, there were 4 cases of intussusception with ROTARIX compared with 14 cases of intussusception with placebo [Relative Risk: 0.28 (95% CI: 0.10, 0.81)]. All of the infants who developed intussusception recovered without sequelae.



 Table 2. Intussusception and Relative Risk With ROTARIX Compared With Placebo 
  Confirmed Cases of Intussusception                                  ROTARIX            Placebo            
  N = 31,673                                                          N = 31,552         
  Within 31 days following diagnosis after any dose                   6                  7                  
       Relative Risk (95% CI)                                         0.85 (0.30, 2.42)    
  Within 100 days following dose 1a                                   9                  16                 
       Relative Risk (95% CI)                                         0.56 (0.25, 1.24)    
        *     CI = Confidence Interval. 
 *       a  Median duration after dose 1 (follow-up visit at 30 to 90 days after dose 2). 
    Among vaccine recipients, there were no confirmed cases of intussusception within the 0- to 14-day period after the first dose (Table 3), which was the period of highest risk for the previously licensed oral live rhesus rotavirus-based vaccine.  1  
 

 Table 3. Intussusception Cases by Day Range in Relation to Dose 
  Day Range        Dose 1          Dose 2          Any Dose        
  ROTARIX          Placebo         ROTARIX         Placebo         ROTARIX         Placebo         
  N = 31,673       N = 31,552      N = 29,616      N = 29,465      N = 31,673      N = 31,552      
  0-7              0               0               2               0               2               0               
  8-14             0               0               0               2               0               2               
  15-21            1               1               2               1               3               2               
  22-30            0               1               1               2               1               3               
  Total (0-30)     1               2               5               5               6               7               
               Kawasaki Disease:  Kawasaki disease has been reported in 18 (0.035%) recipients of ROTARIX and 9 (0.021%) placebo recipients from 16 completed or ongoing clinical trials. Of the 27 cases, 5 occurred following ROTARIX in clinical trials that were either not placebo-controlled or 1:1 randomized. In placebo-controlled trials, Kawasaki disease was reported in 17 recipients of ROTARIX and 9 placebo recipients [Relative Risk: 1.71 (95% CI: 0.71, 4.38)]. Three of the 27 cases were reported within 30 days post-vaccination: 2 cases (ROTARIX = 1, placebo = 1) were from placebo-controlled trials [Relative Risk: 1.00 (95% CI: 0.01, 78.35)] and one case following ROTARIX was from a non-placebo-controlled trial. Among recipients of ROTARIX, the time of onset after study dose ranged 3 days to 19 months.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The temporal association between vaccination with ROTARIX and intussusception was evaluated in a hospital-based active surveillance study that identified infants with intussusception at participating hospitals in Mexico. Using a self-controlled case series method,  4  the incidence of intussusception during the first 7 days after receipt of ROTARIX and during the 31-day period after receipt of ROTARIX was compared to a control period. The control period was from birth to one year, excluding the pre-defined risk period (first 7 days or first 31 days post-vaccination, respectively).



 Over a 2-year period, the participating hospitals provided health services to approximately 1 million infants under 1 year of age. Among 750 infants with intussusception, the relative incidence of intussusception in the 31-day period after the first dose of ROTARIX compared to the control period was 1.96 (95.5% CI: 1.46, 2.63)]; the relative incidence of intussusception in the first 7 days after the first dose of ROTARIX compared to the control period was 6.07 (95.5% CI: 4.20, 8.63).



 The Mexico study did not take into account all medical conditions that may predispose infants to intussusception. The results may not be generalizable to US infants who have a lower background rate of intussusception than Mexican infants. However, if a temporal increase in the risk for intussusception following ROTARIX similar in magnitude to that observed in the Mexico study does exist in US infants, it is estimated that approximately 1 to 3 additional cases of intussusception hospitalizations would occur per 100,000 vaccinated infants in the US within 7 days following the first dose of ROTARIX. In the first year of life, the background rate of intussusception hospitalizations in the US has been estimated to be approximately 34 per 100,000 infants.  5  



 Other postmarketing observational studies conducted in Brazil and Australia also suggest an increased risk of intussusception within the first 7 days following the second dose of ROTARIX.  2,3  



 Worldwide passive postmarketing surveillance data suggest that most cases of intussusception reported following ROTARIX occur in the 7-day period after the first dose.



 The following adverse events have been reported since market introduction of ROTARIX. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccination with ROTARIX.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Intussusception (including death), recurrent intussusception (including death), hematochezia, gastroenteritis with vaccine viral shedding in infants with Severe Combined Immunodeficiency Disease (SCID).



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura.



   Vascular Disorders:  Kawasaki disease.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Maladministration.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    The tip caps of the prefilled oral applicators of diluent may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Administration of ROTARIX in infants suffering from acute diarrhea or vomiting should be delayed. Safety and effectiveness of ROTARIX in infants with chronic gastrointestinal disorders have not been evaluated. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Safety and effectiveness of ROTARIX in infants with known primary or secondary immunodeficiencies have not been established. (  5.3  ) 
 *    In a postmarketing study, cases of intussusception were observed in temporal association within 31 days following the first dose of ROTARIX, with a clustering of cases in the first 7 days. (  5.5  ,  6.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Latex



  The tip caps of the prefilled oral applicators of diluent may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals.



    5.2 Gastrointestinal Disorders



  Administration of ROTARIX should be delayed in infants suffering from acute diarrhea or vomiting.



 Safety and effectiveness of ROTARIX in infants with chronic gastrointestinal disorders have not been evaluated. [See Contraindications (4.2).]  



    5.3 Altered Immunocompetence



  Safety and effectiveness of ROTARIX in infants with known primary or secondary immunodeficiencies, including infants with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), infants on immunosuppressive therapy, or infants with malignant neoplasms affecting the bone marrow or lymphatic system have not been established.



    5.4 Shedding and Transmission



  Rotavirus shedding in stool occurs after vaccination with peak excretion occurring around day 7 after dose 1.



 One clinical trial demonstrated that vaccinees transmit vaccine virus to healthy seronegative contacts [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  .



 The potential for transmission of vaccine virus following vaccination should be weighed against the possibility of acquiring and transmitting natural rotavirus. Caution is advised when considering whether to administer ROTARIX to individuals with immunodeficient close contacts, such as individuals with malignancies, primary immunodeficiency or receiving immunosuppressive therapy.



    5.5 Intussusception



  Following administration of a previously licensed oral live rhesus rotavirus-based vaccine, an increased risk of intussusception was observed.  1  The risk of intussusception with ROTARIX was evaluated in a pre-licensure randomized, placebo-controlled safety study (including 63,225 infants) conducted in Latin America and Finland. No increased risk of intussusception was observed in this clinical trial following administration of ROTARIX when compared with placebo. [See Adverse Reactions (6.1).]  



 In a postmarketing, observational study conducted in Mexico, cases of intussusception were observed in temporal association within 31 days following the first dose of ROTARIX, with a clustering of cases in the first 7 days. [See Adverse Reactions (6.2).]  



  Other postmarketing observational studies conducted in Brazil and Australia also suggest an increased risk of intussusception within the first 7 days following the second dose of ROTARIX.  2,3   [See Adverse Reactions (6.2).]    



 In worldwide passive postmarketing surveillance, cases of intussusception have been reported in temporal association with ROTARIX [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .



    5.6 Post-Exposure Prophylaxis



  Safety and effectiveness of ROTARIX when administered after exposure to rotavirus have not been evaluated.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
