<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rotateq" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse events included diarrhea, vomiting, irritability, otitis media, nasopharyngitis, and bronchospasm. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or  www.vaers.hhs.gov  {  4  }.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  71,725 infants were evaluated in 3 placebo-controlled clinical trials including 36,165 infants in the group that received RotaTeq and 35,560 infants in the group that received placebo. Parents/guardians were contacted on days 7, 14, and 42 after each dose regarding intussusception and any other serious adverse events. The racial distribution was as follows: White (69% in both groups); Hispanic-American (14% in both groups); Black (8% in both groups); Multiracial (5% in both groups); Asian (2% in both groups); Native American (RotaTeq 2%, placebo 1%); and Other (&lt;1% in both groups). The gender distribution was 51% male and 49% female in both vaccination groups.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under conditions that may not be typical of those observed in clinical practice, the adverse reaction rates presented below may not be reflective of those observed in clinical practice.



   Serious Adverse Events  



 Serious adverse events occurred in 2.4% of recipients of RotaTeq when compared to 2.6% of placebo recipients within the 42-day period of a dose in the phase 3 clinical studies of RotaTeq. The most frequently reported serious adverse events for RotaTeq compared to placebo were:



 bronchiolitis                   (0.6% RotaTeq vs. 0.7% Placebo),



 gastroenteritis               (0.2% RotaTeq vs. 0.3% Placebo),



 pneumonia                    (0.2% RotaTeq vs. 0.2% Placebo),



 fever                              (0.1% RotaTeq vs. 0.1% Placebo), and



 urinary tract infection    (0.1% RotaTeq vs. 0.1% Placebo).



   Deaths  



 Across the clinical studies, 52 deaths were reported. There were 25 deaths in the RotaTeq recipients compared to 27 deaths in the placebo recipients. The most commonly reported cause of death was sudden infant death syndrome, which was observed in 8 recipients of RotaTeq and 9 placebo recipients.



   Intussusception  



 In REST, 34,837 vaccine recipients and 34,788 placebo recipients were monitored by active surveillance to identify potential cases of intussusception at 7, 14, and 42 days after each dose, and every 6 weeks thereafter for 1 year after the first dose.



 For the primary safety outcome, cases of intussusception occurring within 42 days of any dose, there were 6 cases among RotaTeq recipients and 5 cases among placebo recipients (see  Table 1  ). The data did not suggest an increased risk of intussusception relative to placebo.



 Table 1: Confirmed cases of intussusception in recipients of RotaTeq as compared with placebo recipients during REST 
                                                            RotaTeq (n=34,837)     Placebo (n=34,788)     
 Confirmed intussusception cases within 42 days of any dose  6                      5                      
 Relative risk (95% CI)                                     1.6 (0.4, 6.4)          
 Confirmed intussusception cases within 365 days of dose 1  13                     15                     
 Relative risk (95% CI)                                     0.9 (0.4, 1.9)          
         Among vaccine recipients, there were no confirmed cases of intussusception within the 42-day period after the first dose, which was the period of highest risk for the rhesus rotavirus-based product (see  Table 2  ).
 

 Table 2: Intussusception cases by day range in relation to dose in REST 
                 Dose 1      Dose 2      Dose 3      Any Dose     
 Day Range       RotaTeq     Placebo     RotaTeq     Placebo     RotaTeq     Placebo     RotaTeq     Placebo      
 1-7             0           0           1           0           0           0           1           0            
 1-14            0           0           1           0           0           1           1           1            
 1-21            0           0           3           0           0           1           3           1            
 1-42            0           1           4           1           2           3           6           5            
               All of the children who developed intussusception recovered without sequelae with the exception of a 9-month-old male who developed intussusception 98 days after dose 3 and died of post-operative sepsis. There was a single case of intussusception among 2,470 recipients of RotaTeq in a 7-month-old male in the phase 1 and 2 studies (716 placebo recipients).
 

   Hematochezia  



 Hematochezia reported as an adverse experience occurred in 0.6% (39/6,130) of vaccine and 0.6% (34/5,560) of placebo recipients within 42 days of any dose. Hematochezia reported as a serious adverse experience occurred in &lt;0.1% (4/36,150) of vaccine and &lt;0.1% (7/35,536) of placebo recipients within 42 days of any dose.



   Seizures  



 All seizures reported in the phase 3 trials of RotaTeq (by vaccination group and interval after dose) are shown in  Table 3  .



 Table 3: Seizures reported by day range in relation to any dose in the phase 3 trials of RotaTeq 
 Day range                              1-7                    1-14                   1-42                    
 RotaTeq                                10                     15                     33                      
 Placebo                                5                      8                      24                      
          Seizures reported as serious adverse experiences occurred in &lt;0.1% (27/36,150) of vaccine and &lt;0.1% (18/35,536) of placebo recipients (not significant). Ten febrile seizures were reported as serious adverse experiences, 5 were observed in vaccine recipients and 5 in placebo recipients.
 

   Kawasaki Disease  



 In the phase 3 clinical trials, infants were followed for up to 42 days of vaccine dose. Kawasaki disease was reported in 5 of 36,150 vaccine recipients and in 1 of 35,536 placebo recipients with unadjusted relative risk 4.9 (95% CI 0.6, 239.1).



   Most Common Adverse Events  



   Solicited Adverse Events  



 Detailed safety information was collected from 11,711 infants (6,138 recipients of RotaTeq) which included a subset of subjects in REST and all subjects from Studies 007 and 009 (Detailed Safety Cohort). A Vaccination Report Card was used by parents/guardians to record the child's temperature and any episodes of diarrhea and vomiting on a daily basis during the first week following each vaccination. Table 4 summarizes the frequencies of these adverse events and irritability.



 Table 4: Solicited adverse experiences within the first week after doses 1, 2, and 3 (Detailed Safety Cohort) 
 Adverse experience      Dose 1         Dose 2        Dose 3         
                         RotaTeq        Placebo       RotaTeq       Placebo       RotaTeq       Placebo        
 Elevated temperature    n=5,61617.1%   n=5,07716.2%  n=5,21520.0%  n=4,72519.4%  n=4,86518.2%  n=4,38217.6%   
                         n=6,130        n=5,560       n=5,703       n=5,173       n=5,496       n=4,989        
 Vomiting                6.7%           5.4%          5.0%          4.4%          3.6%          3.2%           
                                                                                                               
 Diarrhea                10.4%          9.1%          8.6%          6.4%          6.1%          5.4%           
                                                                                                               
 Irritability            7.1%           7.1%          6.0%          6.5%          4.3%          4.5%           
               Other Adverse Events  
 

 Parents/guardians of the 11,711 infants were also asked to report the presence of other events on the Vaccination Report Card for 42 days after each dose.



 Fever was observed at similar rates in vaccine (N=6,138) and placebo (N=5,573) recipients (42.6% vs. 42.8%). Adverse events that occurred at a statistically higher incidence (i.e., 2-sided p-value &lt;0.05) within the 42 days of any dose among recipients of RotaTeq as compared with placebo recipients are shown in  Table 5  .



 Table 5: Adverse events that occurred at a statistically higher incidence within 42 days of any dose among recipients of RotaTeq as compared with placebo recipients 
 Adverse event                   RotaTeqN=6,138                       PlaceboN=5,573                       
                                 n (%)                                n (%)                                
 Diarrhea                        1,479 (24.1%)                        1,186 (21.3%)                        
 Vomiting                        929 (15.2%)                          758 (13.6%)                          
 Otitis media                    887 (14.5%)                          724 (13.0%)                          
 Nasopharyngitis                 422 (6.9%)                           325 (5.8%)                           
 Bronchospasm                    66 (1.1%)                            40 (0.7%)                            
           Safety in Pre-Term Infants  
 

 RotaTeq or placebo was administered to 2,070 pre-term infants (25 to 36 weeks gestational age, median 34 weeks) according to their age in weeks since birth in REST. All pre-term infants were followed for serious adverse experiences; a subset of 308 infants was monitored for all adverse experiences. There were 4 deaths throughout the study, 2 among vaccine recipients (1 SIDS and 1 motor vehicle accident) and 2 among placebo recipients (1 SIDS and 1 unknown cause). No cases of intussusception were reported. Serious adverse experiences occurred in 5.5% of vaccine and 5.8% of placebo recipients. The most common serious adverse experience was bronchiolitis, which occurred in 1.4% of vaccine and 2.0% of placebo recipients. Parents/guardians were asked to record the child's temperature and any episodes of vomiting and diarrhea daily for the first week following vaccination. The frequencies of these adverse experiences and irritability within the week after dose 1 are summarized in  Table 6  .



 Table 6: Solicited adverse experiences within the first week of doses 1, 2, and 3 among pre-term infants 
                           Dose 1         Dose 2        Dose 3         
 Adverse event             RotaTeq        Placebo       RotaTeq       Placebo       RotaTeq       Placebo        
                           N=127          N=133         N=124         N=121         N=115         N=108          
 Elevated temperature      18.1%          17.3%         25.0%         28.1%         14.8%         20.4%          
                           N=154          N=154         N=137         N=137         N=135         N=129          
 Vomiting                  5.8%           7.8%          2.9%          2.2%          4.4%          4.7%           
                                                                                                                 
 Diarrhea                  6.5%           5.8%          7.3%          7.3%          3.7%          3.9%           
                                                                                                                 
 Irritability              3.9%           5.2%          2.9%          4.4%          8.1%          5.4%           
               6.2 Post-Marketing Experience
   The following adverse events have been identified during post-approval use of RotaTeq from reports to the Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS).



 Reporting of adverse events following immunization to VAERS is voluntary, and the number of doses of vaccine administered is not known; therefore, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the adverse event frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure using VAERS data.



 In post-marketing experience, the following adverse events have been reported following the use of RotaTeq:



   Immune system disorders:  



    Anaphylactic reaction



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  



    Intussusception (including death)



    Hematochezia



    Gastroenteritis with vaccine viral shedding in infants with Severe Combined Immunodeficiency Disease (SCID)



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  



    Urticaria



    Angioedema



   Infections and infestations:  



    Kawasaki disease



    Transmission of vaccine virus strains from vaccine recipient to non-vaccinated contacts.



   Post-Marketing Observational Safety Surveillance Studies  



 The temporal association between vaccination with RotaTeq and intussusception was evaluated in the Post-licensure Rapid Immunization Safety Monitoring (PRISM) program {  2  }, an electronic active surveillance program comprised of 3 US health insurance plans.



 More than 1.2 million RotaTeq vaccinations (507,000 of which were first doses) administered to infants 5 through 36 weeks of age were evaluated. From 2004 through 2011, potential cases of intussusception in either the inpatient or emergency department setting and vaccine exposures were identified through electronic procedure and diagnosis codes. Medical records were reviewed to confirm intussusception and rotavirus vaccination status.



 The risk of intussusception was assessed using self-controlled risk interval and cohort designs, with adjustment for age. Risk windows of 1-7 and 1-21 days were evaluated. Cases of intussusception were observed in temporal association within 21 days following the first dose of RotaTeq, with a clustering of cases in the first 7 days. Based on the results, approximately 1 to 1.5 excess cases of intussusception occur per 100,000 vaccinated US infants within 21 days following the first dose of RotaTeq. In the first year of life, the background rate of intussusception hospitalizations in the US has been estimated to be approximately 34 per 100,000 infants.{  3  }



 In an earlier prospective post-marketing observational cohort study conducted using a large US medical claims database, the risks of intussusception or Kawasaki disease resulting in emergency department visits or hospitalizations during the 30 days following any dose of vaccine were analyzed among 85,150 infants receiving one or more doses of RotaTeq from February 2006 through March 2009. Medical charts were reviewed to confirm these diagnoses. Evaluation included concurrent (n = 62,617) and historical (n=100,000 from 2001-2005) control groups of infants who received diphtheria, tetanus and acellular pertussis vaccine (DTaP) but not RotaTeq.



 Confirmed intussusception cases in the RotaTeq group were compared with those in the concurrent DTaP control group and in the historical control group. The data were analyzed post-dose 1 and post any dose, in both 7 day and 30 day risk windows. A statistically significant increased risk of intussusception after RotaTeq vaccination was not observed.



 One confirmed case of Kawasaki disease (23 days post-dose 3) was identified among infants vaccinated with RotaTeq and one confirmed case of Kawasaki disease (22 days post-dose 2) was identified among concurrent DTaP controls (relative risk = 0.7; 95% CI: 0.01-55.56).



 In addition, general safety was monitored by electronic search of the automated records database for all emergency department visits and hospitalizations in the 30-day period after each dose of RotaTeq compared with: 1) days 31-60 after each dose of RotaTeq (self-matched controls) and 2) the 30-day period after each dose of DTaP vaccine (historical control subset from 2004-2005, n=40,000). In safety analyses which evaluated multiple follow-up windows after vaccination (days: 0-7, 1-7, 8-14 and 0-30), no safety concerns were identified for infants vaccinated with RotaTeq when compared with self-matched controls and the historical control subset.



   Reporting Adverse Events  



 Parents or guardians should be instructed to report any adverse reactions to their health care provider.



 Health care providers should report all adverse events to the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services' Vaccine Adverse Events Reporting System (VAERS).



 VAERS accepts all reports of suspected adverse events after the administration of any vaccine, including but not limited to the reporting of events required by the National Childhood Vaccine Injury Act of 1986. For information or a copy of the vaccine reporting form, call the VAERS toll-free number at 1-800-822-7967 or report on line to  www.vaers.hhs.gov  .{  4  }
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  No safety or efficacy data are available from clinical trials regarding the administration of RotaTeq to infants who are potentially immunocompromised (e.g., HIV/AIDS). (  5.2  ) 
 *  In a post-marketing study, cases of intussusception were observed in temporal association within 21 days following the first dose of RotaTeq, with a clustering of cases in the first 7 days. (  5.3  ,  6.2  ) 
 *  No safety or efficacy data are available for the administration of RotaTeq to infants with a history of gastrointestinal disorders (e.g., active acute gastrointestinal illness, chronic diarrhea, failure to thrive, history of congenital abdominal disorders, and abdominal surgery). (  5.4  ) 
 *  Vaccine virus transmission from vaccine recipient to non-vaccinated contacts has been reported. Caution is advised when considering whether to administer RotaTeq to individuals with immunodeficient contacts. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Managing Allergic Reactions



  Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine.



    5.2 Immunocompromised Populations



  No safety or efficacy data are available from clinical trials regarding the administration of RotaTeq to infants who are potentially immunocompromised including:



 *  Infants with blood dyscrasias, leukemia, lymphomas of any type, or other malignant neoplasms affecting the bone marrow or lymphatic system. 
 *  Infants on immunosuppressive therapy (including high-dose systemic corticosteroids). RotaTeq may be administered to infants who are being treated with topical corticosteroids or inhaled steroids. 
 *  Infants with primary and acquired immunodeficiency states, including HIV/AIDS or other clinical manifestations of infection with human immunodeficiency viruses; cellular immune deficiencies; and hypogammaglobulinemic and dysgammaglobulinemic states. There are insufficient data from the clinical trials to support administration of RotaTeq to infants with indeterminate HIV status who are born to mothers with HIV/AIDS. 
 *  Infants who have received a blood transfusion or blood products, including immunoglobulins within 42 days. 
    Vaccine virus transmission from vaccine recipient to non-vaccinated contacts has been reported [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].  
 

    5.3 Intussusception



  Following administration of a previously licensed live rhesus rotavirus reassortant vaccine, an increased risk of intussusception was observed.{  1  }



 In a post-marketing observational study in the US cases of intussusception were observed in temporal association within 21 days following the first dose of RotaTeq, with a clustering of cases in the first 7 days. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  .]  



 In worldwide passive post-marketing surveillance, cases of intussusception have been reported in temporal association with RotaTeq. [See  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  .]  



    5.4 Gastrointestinal Illness



  No safety or efficacy data are available for administration of RotaTeq to infants with a history of gastrointestinal disorders including infants with active acute gastrointestinal illness, infants with chronic diarrhea and failure to thrive, and infants with a history of congenital abdominal disorders, and abdominal surgery. Caution is advised when considering administration of RotaTeq to these infants.



    5.5 Shedding and Transmission



  Shedding of vaccine virus was evaluated among a subset of subjects in the Rotavirus Efficacy and Safety Trial (REST) 4 to 6 days after each dose and among all subjects who submitted a stool antigen rotavirus positive sample at any time. RotaTeq was shed in the stools of 32 of 360 [8.9%, 95% CI (6.2%, 12.3%)] vaccine recipients tested after dose 1; 0 of 249 [0.0%, 95% CI (0.0%, 1.5%)] vaccine recipients tested after dose 2; and in 1 of 385 [0.3%, 95% CI (&lt;0.1%, 1.4%)] vaccine recipients after dose 3. In phase 3 studies, shedding was observed as early as 1 day and as late as 15 days after a dose. Transmission of vaccine virus was not evaluated in phase 3 studies.



 Transmission of vaccine virus strains from vaccinees to non-vaccinated contacts has been observed post-marketing.



 The potential risk of transmission of vaccine virus should be weighed against the risk of acquiring and transmitting natural rotavirus.



 Caution is advised when considering whether to administer RotaTeq to individuals with immunodeficient close contacts such as:



 *  Individuals with malignancies or who are otherwise immunocompromised; 
 *  Individuals with primary immunodeficiency; or 
 *  Individuals receiving immunosuppressive therapy. 
       5.6 Febrile Illness
 

  Febrile illness may be reason for delaying use of RotaTeq except when, in the opinion of the physician, withholding the vaccine entails a greater risk. Low-grade fever (&lt;100.5 degrees F [38.1 degrees C]) itself and mild upper respiratory infection do not preclude vaccination with RotaTeq.



    5.7 Incomplete Regimen



  The clinical studies were not designed to assess the level of protection provided by only one or two doses of RotaTeq.



    5.8 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  RotaTeq may not protect all vaccine recipients against rotavirus.



    5.9 Post-Exposure Prophylaxis



  No clinical data are available for RotaTeq when administered after exposure to rotavirus.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
