<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rowasa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Clinical Adverse Experience

  ROWASA(r) (mesalamine) Rectal Suspension Enema is usually well tolerated. Most adverse effects have been mild and transient.



 



 ADVERSE REACTIONS OCCURRING IN MORE THAN 0.1% OF ROWASA(r) (MESALAMINE) RECTAL SUSPENSION ENEMA TREATED PATIENTS (COMPARISON TO PLACEBO) 
   SYMPTOM                    ROWASA(r)N=815N            %                          PLACEBON=128N              %                         
  
 Abdominal Pain/Cramps/Discomfort  66                         8.10                       10                         7.81                        
 Headache                   53                         6.50                       16                         12.50                       
 Gas/Flatulence             50                         6.13                       5                          3.91                        
 Nausea                     47                         5.77                       12                         9.38                        
 Flu                        43                         5.28                       1                          0.78                        
 Tired/Weak/Malaise/Fatigue  28                         3.44                       8                          6.25                        
 Fever                      26                         3.19                       0                          0.00                        
 Rash/Spots                 23                         2.82                       4                          3.12                        
 Cold/Sore Throat           19                         2.33                       9                          7.03                        
 Diarrhea                   17                         2.09                       5                          3.91                        
 Leg/Joint Pain             17                         2.09                       1                          0.78                        
 Dizziness                  15                         1.84                       3                          2.34                        
 Bloating                   12                         1.47                       2                          1.56                        
 Back Pain                  11                         1.35                       1                          0.78                        
 Pain on Insertion of Enema Tip  11                         1.35                       1                          0.78                        
 Hemorrhoids                11                         1.35                       0                          0.00                        
 Itching                    10                         1.23                       1                          0.78                        
 Rectal Pain                10                         1.23                       0                          0.00                        
 Constipation               8                          0.98                       4                          3.12                        
 Hair Loss                  7                          0.86                       0                          0.00                        
 Peripheral Edema           5                          0.61                       11                         8.59                        
 UTI/Urinary Burning        5                          0.61                       4                          3.12                        
 Rectal Pain/Soreness/Burning  5                          0.61                       3                          2.34                        
 Asthenia                   1                          0.12                       4                          3.12                        
 Insomnia                   1                          0.12                       3                          2.34                        
      
 

 In addition, the following adverse events have been identified during post-approval use of products which contain (or are metabolized to) mesalamine in clinical practice: nephrotoxicity, pancreatitis, fibrosing alveolitis and elevated liver enzymes. Cases of pancreatitis and fibrosing alveolitis have been reported as manifestations of inflammatory bowel disease as well. Published case reports and/or spontaneous post marketing surveillance have described rare instances of aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia, eosinophilia, pancytopenia, neutropenia, oligospermia, and infertility in men. Anemia, leukocytosis, and thrombocytosis can be part of the clinical presentation of inflammatory bowel disease.



   Hair Loss

  Mild hair loss characterized by "more hair in the comb" but no withdrawal from clinical trials has been observed in 7 of 815 mesalamine patients but none of the placebo-treated patients. In the literature there are at least six additional patients with mild hair loss who received either mesalamine or sulfasalazine. Retreatment is not always associated with repeated hair loss.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
