<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="roxicodone" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  ROXICODONE  (r)  tablets have been evaluated in open label clinical trials in patients with cancer and nonmalignant pain. ROXICODONE  (r)  tablets are associated with adverse experiences similar to those seen with other opioids.



 Serious adverse reactions that may be associated with ROXICODONE  (r)  therapy in clinical use are those observed with other opioid analgesics and include: respiratory depression, respiratory arrest, circulatory depression, cardiac arrest, hypotension, and/or shock (see      OVERDOSAGE    ,  WARNINGS    ).



 The less severe adverse events seen on initiation of therapy with ROXICODONE  (r)  are also typical opioid side effects. These events are dose dependent, and their frequency depends on the clinical setting, the patient's level of opioid tolerance, and host factors specific to the individual. They should be expected and managed as a part of opioid analgesia. The most frequent of these include nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, and pruritus.



 In many cases the frequency of adverse events during initiation of opioid therapy may be minimized by careful individualization of starting dosage, slow titration and the avoidance of large rapid swings in plasma concentration of the opioid. Many of these adverse events will abate as therapy is continued and some degree of tolerance is developed, but others may be expected to remain throughout therapy.



 In all patients for whom dosing information was available (n=191) from the open-label and double-blind studies involving ROXICODONE  (r)  , the following adverse events were recorded in ROXICODONE  (r)  treated patients with an incidence &gt;= 3%. In descending order of frequency they were: nausea, constipation, vomiting, headache, pruritus, insomnia, dizziness, asthenia, and somnolence.



 The following adverse experiences occurred in less than 3% of patients involved in clinical trials with oxycodone:



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain, accidental injury, allergic reaction, back pain, chills and fever, fever, flu syndrome, infection, neck pain, pain, photosensitivity reaction, and sepsis.



   Cardiovascular:  deep thrombophlebitis, heart failure, hemorrhage, hypotension, migraine, palpitation, and tachycardia.



   Digestive:  anorexia, diarrhea, dyspepsia, dysphagia, gingivitis, glossitis, and nausea and vomiting.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  anemia and leukopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  edema, gout, hyperglycemia, iron deficiency anemia and peripheral edema.



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, arthritis, bone pain, myalgia and pathological fracture.



   Nervous:  agitation, anxiety, confusion, dry mouth, hypertonia, hypesthesia, nervousness, neuralgia, personality disorder, tremor, and vasodilation.



   Respiratory:  bronchitis, cough increased, dyspnea, epistaxis, laryngismus, lung disorder, pharyngitis, rhinitis, and sinusitis.



   Skin and Appendages:  herpes simplex, rash, sweating, and urticaria.



   Special Senses:  amblyopia.



   Urogenital:  urinary tract infection.



   Postmarketing Experience:  Review of postmarketing reports showed the occurrence of the following adverse events:



   Cardiac disorders:  myocardial ischemia and ventricular fibrillation with overdose  General disorders and administrative site disorders:  drug withdrawal syndrome neonatal  Immune system disorders:  anaphylactic reactions  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  pharyngeal edema
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
