<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rozerem" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections:



 *  Severe anaphylactic and anaphylactoid reactions [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]  
 *  Abnormal thinking, behavior changes, and complex behaviors [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]  
 *  CNS effects [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ]  
   *  Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3% and more common than with placebo) are: somnolence, dizziness, fatigue, nausea, and exacerbated insomnia. (   6.1   ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Takeda Pharmaceuticals America, Inc. at 1-877-TAKEDA-7 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

    6.1         Clinical Trials Experience  

      Adverse Reactions Resulting in Discontinuation of Treatment    



 The data described in this section reflect exposure to ROZEREM in 5373 subjects, including 722 exposed for 6 months or longer, and 448 subjects for one year.



 Six percent of the 5373 individual subjects exposed to ROZEREM in clinical studies discontinued treatment owing to an adverse event, compared with 2% of the 2279 subjects receiving placebo. The most frequent adverse events leading to discontinuation in subjects receiving ROZEREM were somnolence, dizziness, nausea, fatigue, headache, and insomnia; all of which occurred in 1% of the patients or less.



     ROZEREM Most Commonly Observed Adverse Events    



 Table 1 displays the incidence of adverse events reported by the 2861 patients with chronic insomnia who participated in placebo-controlled trials of ROZEREM.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of other drugs, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



 Table 1. Incidence (% of subjects) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events 
   MedDRA Preferred Term              Placebo    (n=1456)                Ramelteon 8 mg    (n=1405)        
 Somnolence                         2%                                 3%                                  
 Fatigue                            2%                                 3%                                  
 Dizziness                          3%                                 4%                                  
 Nausea                             2%                                 3%                                  
 Insomnia exacerbated               2%                                 3%                                  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Severe anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions: Angioedema and anaphylaxis have been reported. Do not rechallenge if such reactions occur. (   5.1   ) 
 *  Need to evaluate for co-morbid diagnoses: Reevaluate if insomnia persists after 7 to 10 days of treatment. (   5.2   ) 
 *  Abnormal thinking, behavioral changes, complex behaviors: May include "sleep-driving" and hallucinations. Immediately evaluate any new onset behavioral changes. (   5.3   ) 
 *  Depression: Worsening of depression or suicidal thinking may occur. (   5.3   ) 
 *  CNS effects: Potential impairment of activities requiring complete mental alertness such as operating machinery or driving a motor vehicle, after ingesting the drug. (   5.4   ) 
 *  Reproductive effects: Include decreased testosterone and increased prolactin levels. Effect on reproductive axis in developing humans is unknown. (   5.5   ) 
 *  Patients with severe sleep apnea: Rozerem is not recommended for use in this population. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

    5.1        Severe Anaphylactic and Anaphylactoid Reactions  



   Rare cases of angioedema involving the tongue, glottis or larynx have been reported in patients after taking the first or subsequent doses of ROZEREM. Some patients have had additional symptoms such as dyspnea, throat closing, or nausea and vomiting that suggest anaphylaxis. Some patients have required medical therapy in the emergency department. If angioedema involves the tongue, glottis or larynx, airway obstruction may occur and be fatal. Patients who develop angioedema after treatment with ROZEREM should not be rechallenged with the drug.  



     5.2        Need to Evaluate for Co-morbid Diagnoses  



  Since sleep disturbances may be the presenting manifestation of a physical and/or psychiatric disorder, symptomatic treatment of insomnia should be initiated only after a careful evaluation of the patient. The failure of insomnia to remit after   7 to 10 days   of treatment may indicate the presence of a primary psychiatric and/or medical illness that should be evaluated.  Worsening of insomnia, or the emergence of new cognitive or behavioral abnormalities, may be the result of an unrecognized underlying psychiatric or physical disorder and requires further evaluation of the patient. Exacerbation of insomnia and emergence of cognitive and behavioral abnormalities were seen with ROZEREM during the clinical development program .  



     5.3        Abnormal Thinking and Behavioral Changes  



   A variety of cognitive and behavior changes have been reported to occur in association with the use of hypnotics. In primarily depressed patients, worsening of depression (including suicidal ideation and completed suicides) has been reported in association with the use of hypnotics.  



  Hallucinations, as well as behavioral changes such as bizarre behavior, agitation and mania have been reported with ROZEREM use. Amnesia, anxiety and other neuro-psychiatric symptoms may also occur unpredictably.  



  Complex behaviors such as "sleep-driving" (i.e., driving while not fully awake after ingestion of a hypnotic) and other complex behaviors (e.g., preparing and eating food, making phone calls, or having sex), with amnesia for the event, have been reported in association with hypnotic use. The use of alcohol and other CNS depressants may increase the risk of such behaviors. These events can occur in hypnotic-naive as well as in hypnotic-experienced persons. Complex behaviors have been reported with the use of ROZEREM. Discontinuation of ROZEREM should be strongly considered for patients who report any complex sleep behavior.  



     5.4        CNS Effects  



  Patients should avoid engaging in hazardous activities that require concentration (such as operating a motor vehicle or heavy machinery) after taking ROZEREM.



 After taking ROZEREM, patients should confine their activities to those necessary to prepare for bed. 



  Patients should be advised not to consume alcohol in combination with ROZEREM as alcohol and ROZEREM may have additive effects when used in conjunction.  



     5.5        Reproductive Effects  



    Use in Adolescents and Children    



 ROZEREM has been associated with an effect on reproductive hormones in adults, e.g., decreased testosterone levels and increased prolactin levels. It is not known what effect chronic or even chronic intermittent use of ROZEREM may have on the reproductive axis in developing humans [see     Clinical Trials (14.3)     ].  



     5.6        Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness  



   ROZEREM has not been studied in subjects with severe sleep apnea and is not recommended for use in this population [see     Use in Specific Populations (8.7)     ]  .  



 ROZEREM should not be used by patients with severe hepatic impairment [see     Clinical Pharmacology (12.4)     ]  .



     5.7        Laboratory Tests  



    Monitoring    



 No standard monitoring is required.



 For patients presenting with unexplained amenorrhea, galactorrhea, decreased libido, or problems with fertility, assessment of prolactin levels and testosterone levels should be considered as appropriate.



   Interference with laboratory tests    



 ROZEREM is not known to interfere with commonly used clinical laboratory tests. In addition, in    vitro  data indicate that ramelteon does not cause false-positive results for benzodiazepines, opiates, barbiturates, cocaine, cannabinoids, or amphetamines in two standard urine drug screening methods in    vitro  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
