<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rubraca" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Myelodysplastic Syndrome/Acute Myeloid Leukemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  
   *  Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 20%) were nausea, fatigue (including asthenia), vomiting, anemia, abdominal pain, dysgeusia, constipation, decreased appetite, diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, and dyspnea. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Most common laboratory abnormalities (&gt;= 35%) were increase in creatinine, increase in ALT, increase in AST, decrease in hemoglobin, decrease in lymphocytes, increase in cholesterol, decrease in platelets, and decrease in absolute neutrophil count. (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Clovis Oncology, Inc. at 1-844-258-7662 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Rubraca 600 mg twice daily as monotherapy, has been studied in 377 patients with ovarian cancer treated in two open-label, single arm trials. In these patients, the median age was 62 years (range 31 to 86), 100% had an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1, 38% had  BRCA  -mutated ovarian cancer, 45% had received 3 or more prior lines of chemotherapy, and the median time since ovarian cancer diagnosis was 43 months (range 6 to 197).



 Adverse reactions led to dose reduction or interruption in 62% of patients, most frequently from anemia (27%), and fatigue/asthenia (22%). Adverse reactions led to dose discontinuation in 10% of patients, most frequently from fatigue/asthenia (2%). The median duration of treatment was 5.5 months (range 0.1 to 28.0).



   Table 2  and  Table 3  summarize the common adverse reactions and abnormal laboratory findings, respectively, observed in patients treated with Rubraca.



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 20% of Patients with Ovarian Cancer Treated with Rubraca 600 mg Twice Daily 
  a National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE version 4.03)    
  
   Adverse Reaction                                          All Ovarian Cancer Patients(N = 377)    %     
   Grades      a      1-4                                    Grades 3-4            
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                             
      Nausea                                               77                     5                       
      Vomiting                                             46                     4                       
      Constipation                                         40                     2                       
      Diarrhea                                             34                     2                       
      Abdominal Pain                                       32                     3                       
   General Disorders                                                                                      
      Asthenia/Fatigue                                     77                     11                      
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders                                                                   
      Anemia                                               44                     25                      
      Thrombocytopenia                                     21                     5                       
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                               
      Dysgeusia                                            39                     0.3                     
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                     
      Decreased appetite                                   39                     3                       
   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders                                                       
      Dyspnea                                              21                     0.5                     
         The following adverse reactions have been identified in &lt; 20% of the 377 patients treated with Rubraca 600 mg twice daily: dizziness (17%), neutropenia (15%), rash (includes rash, rash erythematous, rash maculopapular and dermatitis) (13%), pyrexia (11%), photosensitivity reaction (10%), pruritus (includes pruritus and pruritus generalized) (9%), Palmar-plantar erythrodysaesthesia syndrome (2%), and febrile neutropenia (1%).
 

 Table 3. Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;= 35% of Patients with Ovarian Cancer Treated with Rubraca 600 mg Twice Daily 
  a At least one worsening shift in CTCAE grade and by maximum shift from baseline.    
  b Increase in ALT/AST led to treatment discontinuation in 0.3% of patients (1/377).    
  
   Laboratory Parameter                                           All Patients with Ovarian Cancer(N = 377)    %     
   Grade 1-4      a                                               Grade 3-4          
   Clinical Chemistry                                                                                     
 Increase in creatinine                                         92                  1                     
 Increase in ALT  b                                             74                  13                    
 Increase in AST  b                                             73                  5                     
 Increase in cholesterol                                        40                  2                     
   Hematologic                                                                                            
 Decrease in hemoglobin                                         67                  23                    
 Decrease in lymphocytes                                        45                  7                     
 Decrease in platelets                                          39                  6                     
 Decrease in absolute neutrophil count                          35                  10                    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Myelodysplastic Syndrome/Acute Myeloid Leukemia (MDS/AML): MDS/AML occurred in patients exposed to RUBRACA, including one fatal event of AML. Monitor patients for hematological toxicity at baseline and monthly thereafter. Discontinue if MDS/AML is confirmed. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: RUBRACA can cause fetal harm. Advise females of reproductive potential of the potential risk to a fetus and to use effective contraception. (  5.2  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myelodysplastic Syndrome/Acute Myeloid Leukemia



  Myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)/Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) was reported in 2 of 377 (0.5%) patients with ovarian cancer treated with Rubraca. The duration of Rubraca treatment prior to the diagnosis of MDS/AML was 57 days and 539 days. Both patients received prior treatment with platinum and other DNA damaging agents.



 In addition, AML was reported in 2 (&lt; 1%) patients with ovarian cancer enrolled in a blinded, randomized trial evaluating Rubraca versus placebo. One case of AML was fatal. The duration of treatment prior to the diagnosis of AML was 107 days and 427 days. Both patients had received prior treatment with platinum and other DNA damaging agents.



 Monitor complete blood count testing at baseline and monthly thereafter. Do not start Rubraca until patients have recovered from hematological toxicity caused by previous chemotherapy (&lt;= Grade 1). For prolonged hematological toxicities, interrupt Rubraca and monitor blood counts weekly until recovery. If the levels have not recovered to Grade 1 or less after 4 weeks, refer the patient to a hematologist for further investigations, including bone marrow analysis and blood sample for cytogenetics. If MDS/AML is confirmed, discontinue Rubraca.



    5.2 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  Rubraca can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman based on its mechanism of action and findings from animal studies. In an animal reproduction study, administration of rucaparib to pregnant rats during organogenesis resulted in embryo-fetal death at maternal exposure that were 0.04 times the AUC in patients receiving the recommended dose of 600 mg twice daily. Apprise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during treatment and for 6 months following the last dose of Rubraca [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ,  8.3  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.1  )].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
