<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rytary" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Falling asleep during activities of daily living and somnolence [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Withdrawal-emergent hyperpyrexia and confusion [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Cardiovascular ischemic events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hallucinations/psychosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Impulse control/compulsive behaviors [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Dyskinesia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Peptic Ulcer Disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Glaucoma [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Melanoma [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
   *  Early Parkinson's disease: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5 % and greater than placebo) are nausea, dizziness, headache, insomnia, abnormal dreams, dry mouth, dyskinesia, anxiety, constipation, vomiting, and orthostatic hypotension (  6.1  ) 
 *  Advanced Parkinson's disease: Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5 % and greater than oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa) are nausea and headache (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Impax Laboratories at 1-877-99-IMPAX or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety population consisted of a total of 978 Parkinson's disease patients who received at least one dose of RYTARY, and had an average duration of exposure of 40 weeks.



     Adverse Reactions in Early Parkinson's Disease  



 In a placebo-controlled clinical study in patients with early Parkinson's disease (Study 1), the most common adverse reactions with RYTARY (in at least 5% of patients and more frequently than in placebo) were nausea, dizziness, headache, insomnia, abnormal dreams, dry mouth, dyskinesia, anxiety, constipation, vomiting, and orthostatic hypotension.



 Table 2 lists adverse reactions occurring in at least 5% of RYTARY-treated patients and at a higher rate than placebo in Study 1.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions in Study 1 in Patients with Early Stage Parkinson's Disease 
                                Placebo      RYTARY36.25 mg carbidopa145 mg Levodopa TID  RYTARY61.25 mg carbidopa245 mg Levodopa TID  RYTARY97.5 mg carbidopa390 mg Levodopa TID   
                                (N=92)%            (N=87)%               (N=104)%              (N=98)%          
  
 Nausea                            9                  14                    19                    20            
 Dizziness                         5                  9                     19                    12            
 Headache                         11                  7                     13                    17            
 Insomnia                          3                  2                     9                     6             
 Abnormal Dreams                   0                  2                     6                     5             
 Dry Mouth                         1                  3                     2                     7             
 Dyskinesia                        0                  2                     4                     5             
 Anxiety                           0                  2                     3                     5             
 Constipation                      1                  2                     6                     2             
 Vomiting                          3                  2                     2                     5             
 Orthostatic Hypotension           1                  1                     1                     5             
               Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation in Study 1  
 

 In Study 1, 12% of patients discontinued RYTARY early due to adverse reactions; a higher proportion of patients in the 61.25 mg / 245 mg RYTARY-treated group (14%) and in the 97.5 mg / 390 mg RYTARY-treated group (15%) experienced adverse reactions leading to early discontinuation compared to (4%) in the placebo group. The most common adverse reactions resulting in early discontinuation were nausea, dizziness, and vomiting.



     Adverse Reactions in Advanced Parkinson's Disease  



 In an active-controlled clinical study in patients with advanced Parkinson's disease (Study 2), the most common adverse reactions with RYTARY that occurred during dose conversion or maintenance (in at least 5% of patients and more frequently than on oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa) were nausea and headache.



 Table 3 lists adverse reactions occurring in at least 5% of RYTARY-treated patients and at a higher rate than oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa in Study 2.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions in Study 2 in Patients with Advanced Parkinson's Disease 
                          RYTARY(N=201)      Immediate-Release carbidopa-levodopa(N=192)   
 Period                  Dose Conversion%        Maintenance%        Dose Conversion%        Maintenance%       
  
 Nausea                         4                     3                     6                     2             
 Headache                       5                     1                     3                     2             
               Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation in Study 2  
 

 In Study 2, 5% of patients discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions during conversion to RYTARY. The common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation during dose conversion were dyskinesia, anxiety, dizziness, and on and off phenomenon.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  May cause falling asleep during activities of daily living (  5.1  ) 
 *  Avoid sudden discontinuation or rapid dose reduction to reduce the risk of withdrawal-emergent hyperpyrexia and confusion (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cardiovascular Events: Monitor patients with a history of cardiovascular disease (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hallucinations/Psychosis may occur (  5.4  ) 
 *  Impulse Control Disorders: Consider dose reduction or stopping RYTARY if occurs (  5.5  ) 
 *  May cause or exacerbate dyskinesia: Consider dose reduction (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence



  Patients treated with levodopa, a component of RYTARY, have reported falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, which sometimes resulted in accidents. Although many of these patients reported somnolence while on levodopa, some perceived that they had no warning signs (sleep attack), such as excessive drowsiness, and believed that they were alert immediately prior to the event. Some of these events have been reported more than 1 year after initiation of treatment.



 It has been reported that falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living usually occurs in a setting of pre-existing somnolence, although patients may not give such a history. For this reason, prescribers should reassess patients for drowsiness or sleepiness in RYTARY-treated patients, especially since some of the events occur well after the start of treatment. Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge drowsiness or sleepiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities.



 Before initiating treatment with RYTARY, advise patients of the potential to develop drowsiness and specifically ask about factors that may increase the risk for somnolence with RYTARY such as concomitant sedating medications or the presence of a sleep disorder. Consider discontinuing RYTARY in patients who report significant daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require active participation (e.g., conversations, eating, etc.).



 If a decision is made to continue RYTARY, patients should be advised not to drive and to avoid other potentially dangerous activities that might result in harm if the patients become somnolent. There is insufficient information to establish that dose reduction will eliminate episodes of falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living.



    5.2 Withdrawal-Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion



  A symptom complex that resembles neuroleptic malignant syndrome (characterized by elevated temperature, muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, and autonomic instability), with no other obvious etiology, has been reported in association with rapid dose reduction, withdrawal of, or changes in dopaminergic therapy. Avoid sudden discontinuation or rapid dose reduction in patients taking RYTARY. If the decision is made to discontinue RYTARY, the dose should be tapered to reduce the risk of hyperpyrexia and confusion [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  .



    5.3 Cardiovascular Ischemic Events



  Cardiovascular ischemic events have occurred in patients taking RYTARY. In a placebo controlled clinical study in patients with early Parkinson's disease, 7/289 (2.4%) of RYTARY-treated patients experienced cardiovascular ischemic adverse reactions compared to 1/92 (1.1%) of placebo-treated patients. In an active-controlled clinical study in patients with advanced Parkinson's disease, 3/450 (0.7%) of RYTARY-treated patients experienced cardiovascular ischemic adverse reactions compared to 0/471 oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa-treated patients. These patients all had a previous history of ischemic heart disease or risk factors for ischemic heart disease.



 In patients with a history of myocardial infarction who have residual atrial, nodal, or ventricular arrhythmias, cardiac function should be monitored in an intensive cardiac care facility during the period of initial dosage adjustment.



    5.4 Hallucinations/Psychosis



  There is an increased risk for hallucinations and psychosis in patients taking RYTARY. In a controlled clinical trial in patients with advanced Parkinson's disease, 9/201 (4%) of RYTARY-treated patients reported hallucinations or psychosis compared to 2/192 (1%) of oral immediate-release carbidopa-levodopa-treated patients.



 Hallucinations present shortly after the initiation of therapy and may be responsive to dose reduction in levodopa. Hallucinations may be accompanied by confusion, insomnia, and excessive dreaming. Abnormal thinking and behavior may present with one or more symptoms, including paranoid ideation, delusions, hallucinations, confusion, psychotic-like behavior, disorientation, aggressive behavior, agitation, and delirium.



 Because of the risk of exacerbating psychosis, patients with a major psychotic disorder should not be treated with RYTARY. In addition, medications that antagonize the effects of dopamine used to treat psychosis may exacerbate the symptoms of Parkinson's disease and may decrease the effectiveness of RYTARY [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



    5.5 Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors



  Case reports suggest that patients can experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money, binge eating, and/or other intense urges, and the inability to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications, including RYTARY, that increase central dopaminergic tone and that are generally used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease. In some cases, although not all, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose was reduced or the medication was discontinued.



 Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal, it is important for prescribers to specifically ask patients or their caregivers about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending or other urges while being treated with RYTARY. Consider a dose reduction or stopping the medication if a patient develops such urges while taking RYTARY.



    5.6 Dyskinesia



  RYTARY can cause dyskinesias that may require a dosage reduction of RYTARY or other medications used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease.



    5.7 Peptic Ulcer Disease



  Treatment with RYTARY may increase the possibility of upper gastrointestinal hemorrhage in patients with a history of peptic ulcer.



    5.8 Glaucoma



  RYTARY may cause increased intraocular pressure in patients with glaucoma. Monitor intraocular pressure in patients with glaucoma after starting RYTARY.



    5.9 Melanoma



  Epidemiological studies have shown that patients with Parkinson's disease have a higher risk (2- to approximately 6-fold higher) of developing melanoma than the general population. Whether the increased risk observed was due to Parkinson's disease or other factors, such as drugs used to treat Parkinson's disease, is unclear.



 Perform periodic skin examinations to monitor for melanoma in patients receiving RYTARY.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
