<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="rythmol0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse events with propafenone (&gt;5% and greater than placebo) excluding those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug included the following: dizziness, palpitations, chest pain, dyspnea, taste disturbance, nausea, fatigue, anxiety, constipation, upper respiratory tract infection, edema, and influenza. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to RYTHMOL SR 225 mg twice daily in 126 patients, to RYTHMOL SR 325 mg twice daily in 135 patients, to RYTHMOL SR 425 mg twice daily in 136 patients, and to placebo in 126 patients for up to 39 weeks (mean 20 weeks) in a placebo-controlled trial (RAFT) conducted in the US. The most commonly reported adverse events with propafenone (&gt;5% and greater than placebo) excluding those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug or because they were associated with the condition being treated, were dizziness, palpitations, chest pain, dyspnea, taste disturbance, nausea, fatigue, anxiety, constipation, upper respiratory tract infection, edema, and influenza. The frequency of discontinuation due to adverse events was 17%, and the rate was highest during the first 14 days of treatment.



 Cardiac-related adverse events occurring in &gt;= 2% of the patients in any of the RAFT propafenone SR treatment groups and more common with propafenone than with placebo, excluding those that are common in the population and those not plausibly related to drug therapy, included the following: angina pectoris, atrial flutter, AV block first-degree, bradycardia, congestive cardiac failure, cardiac murmur, edema, dyspnea, rales, wheezing, and cardioactive drug level above therapeutic.



 Propafenone prolongs the PR and QRS intervals in patients with atrial and ventricular arrhythmias. Prolongation of the QRS interval makes it difficult to interpret the effect of propafenone on the QT interval  [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  .



 Non-cardiac related adverse events occurring in &gt;=2% of the patients in any of the RAFT propafenone SR treatment groups and more common with propafenone than with placebo, excluding those that are common in the population and those not plausibly related to drug therapy, included the following: blurred vision, constipation, diarrhea, dry mouth, flatulence, nausea, vomiting, fatigue, weakness, upper respiratory tract infection, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, hematuria, muscle weakness, dizziness (excluding vertigo), headache, taste disturbance, tremor, somnolence, anxiety, depression, ecchymosis.



 No clinically important differences in incidence of adverse reactions were noted by age or gender. Too few non-Caucasian patients were enrolled to assess adverse events according to race.



 Adverse events occurring in 2% or more of the patients in any of the ERAFT  [see Clinical Studies (14)]  propafenone SR treatment groups and not listed above include the following: bundle branch block left, bundle branch block right, conduction disorders, sinus bradycardia, and hypotension.



 Other adverse events reported with propafenone clinical trials not already listed elsewhere in the prescribing information include the following adverse events by body system and preferred term.



       Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders    

  Anemia, lymphadenopathy, spleen disorder, thrombocytopenia.



       Cardiac Disorders    

  Unstable angina, atrial hypertrophy, cardiac arrest, coronary artery disease, extrasystoles, myocardial infarction, nodal arrhythmia, palpitations, pericarditis, sinoatrial block, sinus arrest, sinus arrhythmia, supraventricular extrasystoles, ventricular extrasystoles, ventricular hypertrophy.



       Ear and Labyrinth Disorders    

  Hearing impaired, tinnitus, vertigo.



       Eye Disorders    

  Eye hemorrhage, eye inflammation, eyelid ptosis, miosis, retinal disorder, visual acuity reduced.



       Gastrointestinal Disorders    

  Abdominal distension, abdominal pain, duodenitis, dyspepsia, dysphagia, eructation, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux disease, gingival bleeding, glossitis, glossodynia, gum pain, halitosis, intestinal obstruction, melena, mouth ulceration, pancreatitis, peptic ulcer, rectal bleeding, sore throat.



       General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    

  Chest pain, feeling hot, hemorrhage, malaise, pain, pyrexia.



       Hepatobiliary Disorders    

  Hepatomegaly.



       Investigations    

  Abnormal heart sounds, abnormal pulse, carotid bruit, decreased blood chloride, decreased blood pressure, decreased blood sodium, decreased hemoglobin, decreased neutrophil count, decreased platelet count, decreased prothrombin level, decreased red blood cell count, decreased weight, glycosuria present, increased alanine aminotransferase, increased aspartate aminotransferase, increased blood bilirubin, increased blood cholesterol, increased blood creatinine, increased blood glucose, increased blood lactate dehydrogenase, increased blood pressure, increased blood prolactin, increased blood triglycerides, increased blood urea, increased blood uric acid, increased eosinophil count, increased gamma-glutamyltransferase, increased monocyte count, increased prostatic specific antigen, increased prothrombin level, increased weight, increased white blood cell count, ketonuria present, proteinuria present.



       Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders    

  Anorexia, dehydration, diabetes mellitus, gout, hypercholesterolemia, hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia, hypokalemia.



       Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue, and Bone Disorders    

  Arthritis, bursitis, collagen-vascular disease, costochondritis, joint disorder, muscle cramps, muscle spasms, myalgia, neck pain, pain in jaw, sciatica, tendonitis.



       Nervous System Disorders    

  Amnesia, ataxia, balance impaired, brain damage, cerebrovascular accident, dementia, gait abnormal, hypertonia, hypothesia, insomnia, paralysis, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, speech disorder, syncope, tongue hypoesthesia.



       Psychiatric Disorder:    

  Decreased libido, emotional disturbance, mental disorder, neurosis, nightmare, sleep disorder.



       Renal and Urinary Disorders    

  Dysuria, nocturia, oliguria, pyuria, renal failure, urinary casts, urinary frequency, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urine abnormal.



       Reproductive System and Breast Disorders    

  Breast pain, impotence, prostatism.



       Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders    

  Atelectasis, breath sounds decreased, chronic obstructive airways disease, cough, epistaxis, hemoptysis, lung disorder, pleural effusion, pulmonary congestion, rales, respiratory failure, rhinitis, throat tightness.



       Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    

  Alopecia, dermatitis, dry skin, erythema, nail abnormality, petechiae, pruritus, sweating increased, urticaria.



       Vascular Disorders    

  Arterial embolism limb, deep limb venous thrombosis, flushing, hematoma, hypertension, hypertensive crisis, hypotension, labile blood pressure, pallor, peripheral coldness, peripheral vascular disease, thrombosis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: MORTALITY

  WARNING: MORTALITY

    *  In the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute's Cardiac Arrhythmia Suppression Trial (CAST), a long-term, multicenter, randomized, double-blind trial in patients with asymptomatic non-life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias who had a myocardial infarction more than 6 days but less than 2 years previously, an increased rate of death or reversed cardiac arrest rate (7.7%; 56/730) was seen in patients treated with encainide or flecainide (Class IC antiarrhythmics) compared with that seen in patients assigned to placebo (3.0%; 22/725). The average duration of treatment with encainide or flecainide in this trial was 10 months. 
 *  The applicability of the CAST results to other populations (e.g., those without recent myocardial infarction) or other antiarrhythmic drugs is uncertain, but at present, it is prudent to consider any IC antiarrhythmic to have a significant proarrhythmic risk in patients with structural heart disease. Given the lack of any evidence that these drugs improve survival, antiarrhythmic agents should generally be avoided in patients with non-life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias, even if the patients are experiencing unpleasant, but not life-threatening, symptoms or signs. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: MORTALITY
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  An increased rate of death or reversed cardiac arrest rate was seen in patients treated with encainide or flecainide (Class IC antiarrhythmics) compared with that seen in patients assigned to placebo. At present it is prudent to consider any IC antiarrhythmic to have a significant risk of provoking proarrhythmic events in patients with structural heart disease. 
 *  Given the lack of any evidence that these drugs improve survival, antiarrhythmic agents should generally be avoided in patients with non-life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias, even if the patients are experiencing unpleasant, but not life-threatening, symptoms or signs. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    May cause new or worsened arrhythmias. Evaluate patients via ECG prior to and during therapy. (  5.1  ) 
 *    RYTHMOL SR may unmask Brugada or Brugada-like Syndrome. Evaluate patients via ECG after initiation of therapy. (  4  ,  5.2  ) 
 *    Avoid use with other antiarrhythmic agents or drugs that prolong the QT interval. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Avoid simultaneous use of propafenone with both a cytochrome P450 2D6 inhibitor and a 3A4 inhibitor. (  5.4  ) 
 *    May provoke overt heart failure. (  5.5  ) 
 *    May cause dose-related first-degree AV block or other conduction disturbances. Should not be given to patients with conduction defects in absence of a pacemaker. (  5.6  ) 
 *    May affect artificial pacemakers. Pacemakers should be monitored during therapy. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Agranulocytosis: Patients should report signs of infection. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Administer cautiously to patients with impaired hepatic and renal function. (  5.9  ,  5.10  ) 
 *    Exacerbation of myasthenia gravis has been reported. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Proarrhythmic Effects



  Propafenone has caused new or worsened arrhythmias. Such proarrhythmic effects include sudden death and life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias such as ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia, asystole, and torsade de pointes. It may also worsen premature ventricular contractions or supraventricular arrhythmias, and it may prolong the QT interval. It is therefore essential that each patient given RYTHMOL SR be evaluated electrocardiographically prior to and during therapy to determine whether the response to RYTHMOL SR supports continued treatment. Because propafenone prolongs the QRS interval in the electrocardiogram, changes in the QT interval are difficult to interpret [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)].  



 In the RAFT trial [see Clinical Studies (14)]  , there were too few deaths to assess the long-term risk to patients. There were 5 deaths, 3 in the pooled group for RYTHMOL SR (0.8%) and 2 in the placebo group (1.6%). In the overall database of 8 trials of RYTHMOL SR and immediate-release RYTHMOL, the mortality rate was 2.5% per year on propafenone and 4.0% per year on placebo. Concurrent use of propafenone with other antiarrhythmic agents has not been well studied.



 In a US uncontrolled, open-label, multicenter trial using the immediate-release formulation in patients with symptomatic supraventricular tachycardia (SVT), 1.9% (9/474) of these patients experienced ventricular tachycardia (VT) or ventricular fibrillation (VF) during the trial. However, in 4 of the 9 patients, the ventricular tachycardia was of atrial origin. Six of the 9 patients that developed ventricular arrhythmias did so within 14 days of onset of therapy. About 2.3% (11/474) of all patients had recurrence of SVT during the trial which could have been a change in the patients' arrhythmia behavior or could represent a proarrhythmic event. Case reports in patients treated with propafenone for atrial fibrillation/flutter have included increased premature ventricular contractions (PVCs), VT, VF, torsades de pointes, asystole, and death.



 Overall in clinical trials with RYTHMOL immediate-release (which included patients treated for ventricular arrhythmias, atrial fibrillation/flutter, and PSVT), 4.7% of all patients had new or worsened ventricular arrhythmia possibly representing a proarrhythmic event (0.7% was an increase in PVCs; 4.0% a worsening, or new appearance, of VT or VF). Of the patients who had worsening of VT (4%), 92% had a history of VT and/or VT/VF, 71% had coronary artery disease, and 68% had a prior myocardial infarction. The incidence of proarrhythmia in patients with less serious or benign arrhythmias, which include patients with an increase in frequency of PVCs, was 1.6%. Although most proarrhythmic events occurred during the first week of therapy, late events also were seen and the CAST trial [see Boxed Warning: Mortality]  suggests that an increased risk of proarrythmia is present throughout treatment.



     5.2 Unmasking Brugada Syndrome  



   Brugada Syndrome may be unmasked after exposure to RYTHMOL SR. Perform an ECG after initiation of RYTHMOL SR and discontinue the drug if changes are suggestive of Brugada Syndrome [see Contraindications (4)]  .  



    5.3 Use With Drugs That Prolong the QT Interval and Antiarrhythmic Agents



  The use of RYTHMOL SR in conjunction with other drugs that prolong the QT interval has not been extensively studied. Such drugs may include many antiarrhythmics, some phenothiazines, tricyclic antidepressants, and oral macrolides. Withhold Class IA and III antiarrhythmic agents for at least 5 half-lives prior to dosing with RYTHMOL SR. Avoid the use of propafenone with Class IA and III antiarrhythmic agents (including quinidine and amiodarone). There is only limited experience with the concomitant use of Class IB or IC antiarrhythmics.



    5.4 Drug Interactions: Simultaneous Use With Inhibitors of Cytochrome P450 Isoenzymes 2D6 and 3A4



  Propafenone is metabolized by CYP2D6, CYP3A4, and CYP1A2 isoenzymes. Approximately 6% of Caucasians in the US population are naturally deficient in CYP2D6 activity and to a somewhat lesser extent in other demographic groups. Drugs that inhibit these CYP pathways (such as desipramine, paroxetine, ritonavir, sertraline for CYP2D6; ketoconazole, erythromycin, saquinavir, and grapefruit juice for CYP3A4; and amiodarone and tobacco smoke for CYP1A2) can be expected to cause increased plasma levels of propafenone.



 Increased exposure to propafenone may lead to cardiac arrhythmias and exaggerated beta-adrenergic blocking activity. Because of its metabolism, the combination of CYP3A4 inhibition and either CYP2D6 deficiency or CYP2D6 inhibition in users of propafenone is potentially hazardous. Therefore, avoid simultaneous use of RYTHMOL SR with both a CYP2D6 inhibitor and a CYP3A4 inhibitor.



    5.5 Use in Patients With a History of Heart Failure



  Propafenone exerts a negative inotropic activity on the myocardium as well as beta blockade effects and may provoke overt heart failure. In the US trial (RAFT) in patients with symptomatic AF, heart failure was reported in 4 (1.0%) patients receiving RYTHMOL SR (all doses), compared with 1 (0.8%) patient receiving placebo. Proarrhythmic effects more likely occur when propafenone is administered to patients with heart failure (NYHA III and IV) or severe myocardial ischemia [see Contraindications (4)]  .



 In clinical trial experience with RYTHMOL immediate-release, new or worsened heart failure has been reported in 3.7% of patients with ventricular arrhythmia. These events were more likely in subjects with pre-existing heart failure and coronary artery disease. New onset of heart failure attributable to propafenone developed in &lt;0.2% of patients with ventricular arrhythmia and in 1.9% of patients with paroxysmal AF or PSVT.



    5.6 Conduction Disturbances



  Propafenone slows atrioventricular conduction and may also cause dose-related first-degree AV block. Average PR interval prolongation and increases in QRS duration are also dose-related. Do not give propafenone to patients with atrioventricular and intraventricular conduction defects in the absence of a pacemaker [see Contraindications (4), Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  .



 In a US trial (RAFT) in 523 patients with a history of symptomatic AF treated with RYTHMOL SR, sinus bradycardia (rate &lt;50 beats/min) was reported with the same frequency with RYTHMOL SR and placebo.



    5.7 Effects on Pacemaker Threshold



  Propafenone may alter both pacing and sensing thresholds of implanted pacemakers and defibrillators. During and after therapy, monitor and re-program these devices accordingly.



    5.8 Agranulocytosis



  Agranulocytosis has been reported in patients receiving propafenone. Generally, the agranulocytosis occurred within the first 2 months of propafenone therapy and upon discontinuation of therapy; the white count usually normalized by 14 days. Unexplained fever or decrease in white cell count, particularly during the initial 3 months of therapy, warrant consideration of possible agranulocytosis or granulocytopenia. Instruct patients to report promptly any signs of infection such as fever, sore throat, or chills.



    5.9 Use in Patients With Hepatic Dysfunction



  Propafenone is highly metabolized by the liver. Severe liver dysfunction increases the bioavailability of propafenone to approximately 70% compared with 3% to 40% in patients with normal liver function when given RYTHMOL immediate-release tablets. In 8 patients with moderate to severe liver disease administered RYTHMOL immediate-release tablets, the mean half-life was approximately 9 hours. No trials have compared bioavailability of propafenone from RYTHMOL SR in patients with normal and impaired hepatic function. Increased bioavailability of propafenone in these patients may result in excessive accumulation. Carefully monitor patients with impaired hepatic function for excessive pharmacological effects [see Overdosage (10)]  .



    5.10 Use in Patients With Renal Dysfunction



  Approximately 50% of propafenone metabolites are excreted in the urine following administration of RYTHMOL immediate-release tablets. No trials have been performed to assess the percentage of metabolites eliminated in the urine following the administration of RYTHMOL SR Capsules.



 In patients with impaired renal function monitor for signs of overdosage [see Overdosage (10)]  .



    5.11 Use in Patients With Myasthenia Gravis



  Exacerbation of myasthenia gravis has been reported during propafenone therapy.



    5.12 Elevated ANA Titers



  Positive ANA titers have been reported in patients receiving propafenone. They have been reversible upon cessation of treatment and may disappear even in the face of continued propafenone therapy. These laboratory findings were usually not associated with clinical symptoms, but there is one published case of drug-induced lupus erythematosis (positive rechallenge); it resolved completely upon discontinuation of therapy. Carefully evaluate patients who develop an abnormal ANA test and if persistent or worsening elevation of ANA titers is detected, consider discontinuing therapy.



    5.13 Impaired Spermatogenesis



  Reversible disorders of spermatogenesis have been demonstrated in monkeys, dogs, and rabbits after high-dose intravenous administration of propafenone. Evaluation of the effects of short-term administration of RYTHMOL on spermatogenesis in 11 normal subjects suggested that propafenone produced a reversible, short-term drop (within normal range) in sperm count.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
