<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ryzolt" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">           Adverse Reactions RYZOLTTM    was administered to a total of 2707 subjects (2406 patients and 301 healthy volunteers) during clinical studies, including four randomized double-blind studies (treatment &gt;= 12 weeks) and two open-label long-term studies (treatment up to 12 months) in patients with moderate to severe pain due to osteoarthritis of the knee. A total of 844 patients were exposed to RYZOLTTM    for 12 weeks, 493 patients for 6 months and 243 patients for 12 months. Treatment emergent adverse events increased with dose from 100 mg to 300 mg in the three twelve-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies.



 The majority of patients who experienced the most common adverse events (&gt;=5%) reported mild to moderate symptoms. Less than 3% of adverse events were rated as severe. Overall, onset of these adverse events usually occurred within the first two weeks of treatment.



            Adverse reactions with an incidence of 1.0% to less than 5.0%   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  vertigo



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal pain, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, upper abdominal pain



   General disorders  : fatigue, weakness



   Investigations:  weight decreased



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders  : anorexia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  arthralgia



   Nervous system disorders  : headache, tremor



   Psychiatric disorders  : anxiety, insomnia



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : pruritus, sweating increased



   Vascular disorders:  hot flushes



            Adverse reactions with an incidence of less than 1.0%   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  anemia, thrombocytopenia



   Cardiac disorders  : bradycardia



   Eye disorders:  blurred vision, visual disturbance



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : abdominal discomfort, abdominal distension, abdominal tenderness, change in bowel habit, constipation aggravated, diverticulitis, diverticulum, dyspepsia aggravated, dysphagia, fecal impaction, gastric irritation, gastritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastrointestinal irritation, gastro-esophageal reflux disease, lower abdominal pain, pancreatitis aggravated, rectal hemorrhage, rectal prolapse, retching



   General disorders  : asthenia, malaise



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  biliary tract disorder, cholelithiasis



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity



   Investigations  : alanine aminotransferase decreased, alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase decreased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood amylase increased, blood creatinine increased, blood in stool, blood potassium abnormal, blood pressure increased gamma glutamyltransferase increased



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders  : appetite decreased, dehydration



   Nervous system disorders  : ataxia, disturbance in attention, dysarthria, gait abnormal, headache aggravated, mental impairment, sedation, seizure, sleep apnea syndrome, syncope, tremor



   Psychiatric disorders  : abnormal behavior, agitation, anxiety, confusion, depression, emotional disturbance, euphoric mood, indifference, irritability, libido decreased, nervousness, sleep disorder



   Renal and urinary disorders  : difficulty in micturition, urinary hesitation, urinary retention



   Reproductive system and breast disorders  : erectile dysfunction, sexual dysfunction



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  : dyspnea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : allergic dermatitis, cold sweat, dermatitis, night sweats, pallor, generalized pruritus, urticaria



   Vascular disorders  : flushing, hypertension, hypotension, orthostatic hypotension
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
