<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="saizen" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are injection site reactions (such as pain, numbness, redness, and swelling), fluid retention, peripheral edema, arthralgia, myalgia, paresthesia, and headache. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact EMD Serono at 1-800-283-8088 ext 5563 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed during the clinical trials performed with one somatropin formulation cannot always be directly compared to the rates observed during the clinical trials performed with a second somatropin formulation, and may not reflect the adverse reaction rates observed in practice.



     Growth Hormone Deficient Pediatric Patients  



 In clinical studies in which Saizen  (r)  was administered to growth hormone deficient children, the following reactions were infrequently seen: local reactions at the injection site (such as pain, numbness, redness and swelling), hypothyroidism, hypoglycemia, seizures, exacerbation of preexisting psoriasis and disturbances in fluid balance.



     Growth Hormone Deficient Adult Patients  



 For a description of the clinical trials refer to section 14. During the 6-month placebo-controlled study, adverse reactions were reported in 56 patients (93.3%) in the somatropin-treated group and 42 patients (76.4%) in the placebo-treated group. Adverse reactions with an incidence of &gt;=5% in Saizen  (r)  -treated patients which were more frequent in Saizen  (r)  -treated patients compared with placebo-treated patients are listed in Table 1. Arthralgia, myalgia, peripheral edema, other types of edema, carpal tunnel syndrome, paraesthesia and hypoaesthesia were common in the somatropin-treated patients and reported more frequently than in the placebo group. These types of adverse reactions are thought to be related to the fluid accumulating effects of somatropin. During the placebo-controlled portion of the study, approximately 10% of patients without preexisting diabetes mellitus or impaired glucose tolerance treated with somatropin manifested mild, but persistent, abnormalities of glucose tolerance, compared with none in the placebo group. During the open label phase of the study, approximately 10% of patients treated with somatropin required a small upward adjustment of thyroid hormone replacement therapy for preexisting central hypothyroidism and 1 patient was newly diagnosed with central hypothyroidism. In addition, during the open label phase of the study, when all patients were being treated with somatropin, two patients with preexisting central hypoadrenalism required upward titration of hydrocortisone maintenance therapy which was considered to be suboptimal (unrelated to intercurrent stress, surgery or disease), and 1 patient was diagnosed  de novo  with central adrenal insufficiency after six months of somatropin treatment. Anti-GH antibodies were not detected.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions with &gt;=5% Overall Incidence in Saizen(r)-Treated Patients Which Were More Frequent in Saizen(r)-Treated Patients Compared with Placebo-Treated Patients During a 6 Month Study 
 Adverse Reaction                      Saizen  (r)  -Treated (N=60)              Placebo (N=55)             
  
 N = number of patients              
  
 Arthralgia                                     14(23.3%)                           7(12.7%)                
 Headache                                       11(18.3%)                           8(14.5%)                
 Edema peripheral                                9(15.0%)                            2(3.7%)                
 Myalgia                                         5(8.3%)                             2(3.6%)                
 Paraesthesia                                    4(6.7%)                             1(1.8%)                
 Hypoaesthesia                                   4(6.7%)                                0                   
 Edema dependent                                 3(5.0%)                             2(3.6%)                
 Skeletal Pain                                   3(5.0%)                             1(1.8%)                
 Carpal tunnel syndrome                          3(5.0%)                             1(1.8%)                
 Edema generalized                               3(5.0%)                                0                   
 Chest pain                                      3(5.0%)                                0                   
 Depression                                      3(5.0%)                                0                   
 Hypothyroidism                                  3(5.0%)                                0                   
 Insomnia                                        3(5.0%)                                0                   
         The adverse reaction pattern observed during the open label phase of the study was similar to the one presented above.
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Saizen  (r)  . Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Leukemia has been reported in a small number of growth hormone deficient patients treated with growth hormone. It is uncertain whether this increased risk is related to the pathology of growth hormone deficiency itself, growth hormone therapy, or other associated treatments such as radiation therapy for intracranial tumors. So far, epidemiological data fail to confirm the hypothesis of a relationship between growth hormone therapy and leukemia.



 The following additional adverse reactions have been observed during the appropriate use of somatropin: headaches (children and adults), gynecomastia (children), and pancreatitis (children and adults)  (see  Warnings and Precautions [5.14]  ).  



   6.3 Immunogenicity

  As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to Saizen  (r)  with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading. In the case of growth hormone, antibodies with binding capacities lower than 2 mg/mL have not been associated with growth attenuation. In a very small number of patients treated with somatropin, when binding capacity was greater than 2 mg/mL, interference with the growth response was observed.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute Critical Illness: Potential benefit of treatment continuation should be weighed against the potential risk (  5.1  ) 
 *  Prader-Willi syndrome in Children: Evaluate for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiation of treatment. Discontinue treatment if these signs occur (  5.2  ) 
 *  Neoplasms: Monitor patients with preexisting tumors for progression or recurrence. Increased risk of a second neoplasm in childhood cancer survivors treated with somatropin-in particular meningiomas as in patients treated with radiation to the head for their first neoplasm (  5.3  ) 
 *  Impaired Glucose Tolerance and Diabetes Mellitus: May be unmasked. Periodically monitor glucose levels in all patients Doses of concurrent antihyperglycemic drugs in diabetics may require adjustment (  5.4  ) 
 *  Intracranial Hypertension: Exclude preexisting papilledema. May develop and is usually reversible after discontinuation or dose reduction (  5.5  ) 
 *  Fluid Retention (i.e., edema, arthralgia, carpal tunnel syndrome - especially in adults): May occur frequently. Reduce dose as necessary (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypothyroidism: May first become evident or worsen (  5.7  ) 
 *  Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis: May develop. Evaluate children with the onset of a limp or hip/knee pain (  5.8  ) 
 *  Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis: May develop (  5.9  ) 
 *  Reevaluation of Childhood Onset Adult GHD (  5.10  ) 
 *  Hypopituitarism: Closely monitor other hormone replacement therapies (  5.12  ) 
 *  Pancreatitis: Consider pancreatitis in patients with persistent severe abdominal pain (  5.14  ) 
 *  Benzyl Alcohol (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Critical Illness



  Increased mortality in patients with acute critical illness due to complications following open heart surgery, abdominal surgery or multiple accidental trauma, or those with acute respiratory failure has been reported after treatment with pharmacologic amounts of somatropin [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  . The safety of continuing somatropin treatment in patients receiving replacement doses for approved indications who concurrently develop these illnesses has not been established. Therefore, the potential benefit of treatment continuation with somatropin in patients having acute critical illnesses should be weighed against the potential risk.



    5.2 Prader-Willi Syndrome in Children



  There have been reports of fatalities after initiating therapy with somatropin in pediatric patients with Prader-Willi syndrome who had one or more of the following risk factors: severe obesity, history of upper airway obstruction or sleep apnea, or unidentified respiratory infection. Male patients with one or more of these factors may be at greater risk than females. Patients with Prader-Willi syndrome should be evaluated for signs of upper airway obstruction and sleep apnea before initiation of treatment with somatropin. If, during treatment with somatropin, patients show signs of upper airway obstruction (including onset of or increased snoring) and/or new onset sleep apnea, treatment should be interrupted. All patients with Prader-Willi syndrome treated with somatropin should also have effective weight control and be monitored for signs of respiratory infection, which should be diagnosed as early as possible and treated aggressively [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ].  Saizen  (r)  is not indicated for the long term treatment of pediatric patients who have growth failure due to genetically confirmed Prader-Willi syndrome.



    5.3 Neoplasms



   In childhood cancer survivors who were treated with radiation to the brain/head for their first neoplasm and who developed subsequent GHD and were treated with somatropin, an increased risk of a second neoplasm has been reported. Intracranial tumors, in particular meningiomas, were the most common of these second neoplasms. In adults, it is unknown whether there is any relationship between somatropin replacement therapy and CNS tumor recurrence [see  Contraindications (4.3)  ]  . Monitor all patients with a history of GHD secondary to an intracranial neoplasm routinely while on somatropin therapy for progression or recurrence of the tumor.  



  Because children with certain rare genetic causes of short stature have an increased risk of developing malignancies, practitioners should thoroughly consider the risks and benefits of starting somatropin in these patients. If treatment with somatropin is initiated, these patients should be monitored carefully for development of neoplasms.  



  Monitor patients on somatropin therapy carefully for increased growth, or potential malignant changes of preexisting nevi.  



    5.4 Glucose Intolerance/Diabetes Mellitus



  Treatment with somatropin may decrease insulin sensitivity, particularly at higher doses in susceptible patients. As a result, previously undiagnosed impaired glucose tolerance and overt diabetes mellitus may be unmasked during somatropin treatment and new onset type 2 diabetes mellitus has been reported in patients. Therefore, glucose levels should be monitored periodically in all patients treated with somatropin, especially in those with risk factors for diabetes mellitus, such as obesity, Turner syndrome, or a family history of diabetes mellitus. Patients with preexisting type 1 or type 2 diabetes mellitus or impaired glucose tolerance should be monitored closely during somatropin therapy. The doses of antihyperglycemic drugs (i.e., insulin or oral agents) may require adjustment when somatropin therapy is instituted in these patients.



    5.5 Intracranial Hypertension



  Intracranial hypertension (IH) with papilledema, visual changes, headache, nausea, and/or vomiting has been reported in a small number of patients treated with somatropin products. Symptoms usually occurred within the first eight (8) weeks after the initiation of somatropin therapy. In all reported cases, IH-associated signs and symptoms rapidly resolved after cessation of therapy or a reduction of the somatropin dose. Funduscopic examination should be performed routinely before initiating treatment with somatropin to exclude preexisting papilledema, and periodically during the course of somatropin therapy. If papilledema is observed by funduscopy during somatropin treatment, treatment should be stopped. If somatropin-induced IH is diagnosed, treatment with somatropin can be restarted at a lower dose after IH-associated signs and symptoms have resolved. Patients with Turner syndrome, chronic renal insufficiency, and Prader-Willi syndrome may be at increased risk for the development of IH.



    5.6 Fluid Retention



  Fluid retention during somatropin replacement therapy in adults may occur. Clinical manifestations of fluid retention are usually transient and dose dependent.



    5.7 Hypothyroidism



  Undiagnosed/untreated hypothyroidism may prevent an optimal response to somatropin, in particular, the growth response in children. Patients with Turner syndrome have an inherently increased risk of developing autoimmune thyroid disease and primary hypothyroidism. In patients with growth hormone deficiency, central (secondary) hypothyroidism may first become evident or worsen during somatropin treatment. Therefore, patients treated with somatropin should have periodic thyroid function tests and thyroid hormone replacement therapy should be initiated or appropriately adjusted when indicated.



    5.8 Slipped Capital Femoral Epiphysis in Pediatric Patients



  Slipped capital femoral epiphysis may occur more frequently in patients with endocrine disorders (including pediatric growth hormone deficiency and Turner syndrome) or in patients undergoing rapid growth. Any pediatric patient with the onset of a limp or complaints of hip or knee pain during somatropin therapy should be carefully evaluated.



    5.9 Progression of Preexisting Scoliosis in Pediatric Patients



  Progression of scoliosis can occur in patients who experience rapid growth. Because somatropin increases growth rate, patients with a history of scoliosis who are treated with somatropin should be monitored for progression of scoliosis. However, somatropin has not been shown to increase the occurrence of scoliosis. Skeletal abnormalities including scoliosis are commonly seen in untreated Turner syndrome patients. Scoliosis is also commonly seen in untreated patients with Prader-Willi syndrome. Physicians should be alert to these abnormalities, which may manifest during somatropin therapy.



    5.10 Reevaluation of Childhood Onset Adult GHD



  Patients with epiphyseal closure who were treated with somatropin replacement therapy in childhood should be reevaluated according to the criteria in INDICATIONS AND USAGE before continuation of somatropin therapy at the reduced dose level recommended for growth hormone deficient adults. Experience with prolonged treatment in adults is limited.



    5.11 Local and Systemic Reaction



  When somatropin is administered subcutaneously at the same site over a long period of time, tissue atrophy may result. This can be avoided by rotating the injection site.



 As for any protein, local or systemic allergic reactions may occur. Parents/Patient should be informed that such reactions are possible and that prompt medical attention should be sought if allergic reactions occur.



    5.12 Hypopituitarism



  Patients with hypopituitarism (multiple hormone deficiencies) should have their other hormonal replacement therapy closely monitored during somatropin treatment.



    5.13 Laboratory Tests



  Serum levels of inorganic phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase, parathyroid hormone (PTH), and IGF-1 may increase with somatropin therapy.



    5.14 Pancreatitis



  Cases of pancreatitis have been reported rarely in children and adults receiving somatropin treatment, with some evidence supporting a greater risk in children compared with adults. Published literature indicates that girls who have Turner syndrome may be at greater risk than other somatropin-treated children. Pancreatitis should be considered in any somatropin-treated patient, especially a child, who develops persistent severe abdominal pain.



    5.15 Benzyl Alcohol



  Benzyl alcohol, a component of this product, has been associated with serious adverse events and death, particularly in pediatric patients. The "gasping syndrome," (characterized by central nervous system depression, metabolic acidosis, gasping respirations, and high levels of benzyl alcohol and its metabolites found in the blood and urine) has been associated with benzyl alcohol dosages &gt;99 mg/kg/day in neonates and low-birth weight neonates. Additional symptoms may include gradual neurological deterioration, seizures, intracranial hemorrhage, hematologic abnormalities, skin breakdown, hepatic and renal failure, hypotension, bradycardia, and cardiovascular collapse. Practitioners administering this and other medications containing benzyl alcohol should consider the combined daily metabolic load of benzyl alcohol from all sources.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
