<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sandostatin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Gallbladder Abnormalities  

  Gallbladder abnormalities, especially stones and/or biliary sludge, frequently develop in patients on chronic Sandostatin  (r)  (octreotide acetate) therapy (  see WARNINGS  ).



     Cardiac  

  In acromegalics, sinus bradycardia (&lt;50 bpm) developed in 25%; conduction abnormalities occurred in 10% and arrhythmias developed in 9% of patients during Sandostatin therapy (  see PRECAUTIONS - General)  .



     Gastrointestinal  

  Diarrhea, loose stools, nausea and abdominal discomfort were each seen in 34%-61% of acromegalic patients in U.S. studies although only 2.6% of the patients discontinued therapy due to these symptoms. These symptoms were seen in 5%-10% of patients with other disorders.



 The frequency of these symptoms was not dose-related, but diarrhea and abdominal discomfort generally resolved more quickly in patients treated with 300 mcg/day than in those treated with 750 mcg/day. Vomiting, flatulence, abnormal stools, abdominal distention, and constipation were each seen in less than 10% of patients.



 In rare instances, gastrointestinal side effects may resemble acute intestinal obstruction, with progressive abdominal distension, severe epigastric pain, abdominal tenderness and guarding.



     Hypo/Hyperglycemia  

  Hypoglycemia and hyperglycemia occurred in 3% and 16% of acromegalic patients, respectively, but only in about 1.5% of other patients. Symptoms of hypoglycemia were noted in approximately 2% of patients.



     Hypothyroidism  

  In acromegalics, biochemical hypothyroidism alone occurred in 12% while goiter occurred in 6% during Sandostatin therapy (  see PRECAUTIONS - General)  . In patients without acromegaly, hypothyroidism has only been reported in several isolated patients and goiter has not been reported.



     Other Adverse Events  

  Pain on injection was reported in 7.7%, headache in 6% and dizziness in 5%. Pancreatitis was also observed (  see WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS)  .



     Other Adverse Events 1%    -4%  

  Other events (relationship to drug not established), each observed in 1%-4% of patients, included fatigue, weakness, pruritus, joint pain, backache, urinary tract infection, cold symptoms, flu symptoms, injection site hematoma, bruise, edema, flushing, blurred vision, pollakiuria, fat malabsorption, hair loss, visual disturbance and depression.



     Other Adverse Events &lt;1%  

  Events reported in less than 1% of patients and for which relationship to drug is not established are listed:  Gastrointestinal:  hepatitis, jaundice, increase in liver enzymes, GI bleeding, hemorrhoids, appendicitis, gastric/peptic ulcer, gallbladder polyp;  Integumentary:  rash, cellulitis, petechiae, urticaria, basal cell carcinoma;  Musculoskeletal:  arthritis, joint effusion, muscle pain, Raynaud's phenomenon;  Cardiovascular:  chest pain, shortness of breath, thrombophlebitis, ischemia, congestive heart failure, hypertension, hypertensive reaction, palpitations, orthostatic BP decrease, tachycardia;  CNS:  anxiety, libido decrease, syncope, tremor, seizure, vertigo, Bell's Palsy, paranoia, pituitary apoplexy, increased intraocular pressure, amnesia, hearing loss, neuritis;  Respiratory:  pneumonia, pulmonary nodule, status asthmaticus;  Endocrine:  galactorrhea, hypoadrenalism, diabetes insipidus, gynecomastia, amenorrhea, polymenorrhea, oligomenorrhea, vaginitis;  Urogenital:  nephrolithiasis, hematuria;  Hematologic:  anemia, iron deficiency, epistaxis;  Miscellaneous:  otitis, allergic reaction, increased CK, weight loss.



 Evaluation of 20 patients treated for at least 6 months has failed to demonstrate titers of antibodies exceeding background levels. However, antibody titers to Sandostatin were subsequently reported in three patients and resulted in prolonged duration of drug action in two patients. Anaphylactoid reactions, including anaphylactic shock, have been reported in several patients receiving Sandostatin.



     Postmarketing Experience  

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during the postapproval use of Sandostatin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal:  intestinal obstruction



   Hematologic:  thrombocytopenia
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
