<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sandimmune" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The principal adverse reactions of Sandimmune (cyclosporine) therapy are renal dysfunction, tremor, hirsutism, hypertension, and gum hyperplasia.



 Hypertension



 Hypertension, which is usually mild to moderate, may occur in approximately 50% of patients following renal transplantation and in most cardiac transplant patients.



 Glomerular Capillary Thrombosis



 Glomerular capillary thrombosis has been found in patients treated with cyclosporine and may progress to graft failure. The pathologic changes resemble those seen in the hemolytic-uremic syndrome and include thrombosis of the renal microvasculature, with platelet-fibrin thrombi occluding glomerular capillaries and afferent arterioles, microangiopathic hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, and decreased renal function. Similar findings have been observed when other immunosuppressives have been employed post transplantation.



 Hypomagnesemia



 Hypomagnesemia has been reported in some, but not all, patients exhibiting convulsions while on cyclosporine therapy. Although magnesium-depletion studies in normal subjects suggest that hypomagnesemia is associated with neurologic disorders, multiple factors, including hypertension, high-dose methylprednisolone, hypocholesterolemia, and nephrotoxicity associated with high plasma concentrations of cyclosporine appear to be related to the neurological manifestations of cyclosporine toxicity.



   Clinical Studies  



 The following reactions occurred in 3% or greater of 892 patients involved in clinical trials of kidney, heart, and liver transplants:




                    Randomized     Kidney Patients      All Sandimmune    (cyclosporine)     Patients     
                    Sandimmune       Azathioprine      Kidney           Heart            Liver           
   Body System/      (N=227)          (N=228)          (N=705)          (N=112)          (N=75)          
         Adverse Reactions      %                %                %                %                %               
 Genitourinary                                                                                          
       Renal Dysfunction  32               6                25               38               37                
 Cardiovascular                                                                                         
       Hypertension  26               18               13               53               27                
       Cramps     4                &lt; 1              2                &lt; 1              0                 
 Skin                                                                                                   
       Hirsutism  21               &lt; 1              21               28               45                
       Acne       6                8                2                2                1                 
 Central Nervous System                                                                                        
       Tremor     12               0                21               31               55                
       Convulsions  3                1                1                4                5                 
       Headache   2                &lt; 1              2                15               4                 
 Gastrointestinal                                                                                        
       Gum Hyperplasia  4                0                9                5                16                
       Diarrhea   3                &lt; 1              3                4                8                 
       Nausea/Vomiting  2                &lt; 1              4                10               4                 
       Hepatotoxicity  &lt; 1              &lt; 1              4                7                4                 
       Abdominal Discomfort  &lt; 1              0                &lt; 1              7                0                 
 Autonomic Nervous System                                                                                        
       Paresthesia  3                0                1                2                1                 
       Flushing   &lt; 1              0                4                0                4                 
 Hematopoietic                                                                                          
       Leukopenia  2                19               &lt; 1              6                0                 
       Lymphoma   &lt; 1              0                1                6                1                 
 Respiratory                                                                                            
       Sinusitis  &lt; 1              0                4                3                7                 
 Miscellaneous                                                                                          
       Gynecomastia  &lt; 1              0                &lt; 1              4                3                 
            The following reactions occurred in 2% or less of patients: allergic reactions, anemia, anorexia, confusion, conjunctivitis, edema, fever, brittle fingernails, gastritis, hearing loss, hiccups, hyperglycemia, muscle pain, peptic ulcer, thrombocytopenia, tinnitus.
 

 The following reactions occurred rarely: anxiety, chest pain, constipation, depression, hair breaking, hematuria, joint pain, lethargy, mouth sores, myocardial infarction, night sweats, pancreatitis, pruritus, swallowing difficulty, tingling, upper GI bleeding, visual disturbance, weakness, weight loss.




   Renal Transplant Patients in Whom Therapy Was Discontinued     
                    Randomized Patients      All Sandimmune Patients     
                    Sandimmune       Azathioprine                      
                    (N=227)          (N=228)          (N=705)         
   Reason for Discontinuation      %                %                %               
 Renal Toxicity   5.7              0                5.4               
 Infection        0                0.4              0.9               
 Lack of Efficacy  2.6              0.9              1.4               
 Acute Tubular Necrosis  2.6              0                1.0               
 Lymphoma/Lymphoproliferative Disease  0.4              0                0.3               
 Hypertension     0                0                0.3               
 Hematological Abnormalities  0                0.4              0                 
 Other            0                0                0.7               
 Sandimmune (cyclosporine) was discontinued on a temporary basis and then restarted in 18 additional patients.   
          Patients receiving immunosuppressive therapies, including cyclosporine and cyclosporine -containing regimens, are at increased risk of infections (viral, bacterial, fungal, parasitic). Both generalized and localized infections can occur. Pre-existing infections may also be aggravated. Fatal outcomes have been reported. (See WARNINGS)
 


   Infectious Complications in the Randomized Renal Transplant Patients     
                    Sandimmune Treatment      Standard Treatment*     
                    (N=227)          (N=228)         
   Complication      % of Complications      % of Complications     
 Septicemia       5.3              4.8               
 Abscesses        4.4              5.3               
 Systemic Fungal Infection  2.2              3.9               
 Local Fungal Infection  7.5              9.6               
 Cytomegalovirus  4.8              12.3              
 Other Viral Infections  15.9             18.4              
 Urinary Tract Infections  21.1             20.2              
 Wound and Skin Infections  7.0              10.1              
 Pneumonia        6.2              9.2               
         *Some patients also received ALG.
 

 Cremophor  (r)  EL (polyoxyethylated castor oil) is known to cause hyperlipemia and electrophoretic abnormalities of lipoproteins. These effects are reversible upon discontinuation of treatment but are usually not a reason to stop treatment.



     Postmarketing Experience  

  Hepatotoxicity



 Cases of hepatotoxicity and liver injury including cholestasis, jaundice, hepatitis and liver failure; serious and/or fatal outcomes have been reported. (See WARNINGS, Hepatotoxicity)



 Increased Risk of Infections



 Cases of JC virus-associated progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), sometimes fatal; and polyoma virus-associated nephropathy (PVAN), especially BK virus resulting in graft loss have been reported. (See WARNINGS, Polyoma Virus Infection)



 Headache, including Migraine



 Cases of migraine have been reported. In some cases, patients have been unable to continue cyclosporine, however, the final decision on treatment discontinuation should be made by the treating physician following the careful assessment of benefits versus risks.



 Pain of lower extremities



 Isolated cases of pain of lower extremities have been reported in association with cyclosporine. Pain of lower extremities has also been noted as part of Calcineurin-Inhibitor Induced Pain Syndrome (CIPS) as described in the literature.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

    WARNING  

  Only physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy and management of organ transplant patients should prescribe Sandimmune (cyclosporine). Patients receiving the drug should be managed in facilities equipped and staffed with adequate laboratory and supportive medical resources. The physician responsible for maintenance therapy should have complete information requisite for the follow-up of the patient.



 Sandimmune (cyclosporine) should be administered with adrenal corticosteroids but not with other immunosuppressive agents. Increased susceptibility to infection and the possible development of lymphoma may result from immunosuppression.



 Sandimmune Soft Gelatin Capsules (cyclosporine capsules, USP) and Sandimmune Oral Solution (cyclosporine oral solution, USP) have decreased bioavailability in comparison to Neoral Soft Gelatin Capsules (cyclosporine capsules, USP) MODIFIED and Neoral Oral Solution (cyclosporine oral solution, USP) MODIFIED.



 Sandimmune and Neoral are not bioequivalent and cannot be used interchangeably without physician supervision.



 The absorption of cyclosporine during chronic administration of Sandimmune Soft Gelatin Capsules and Oral Solution was found to be erratic. It is recommended that patients taking the soft gelatin capsules or oral solution over a period of time be monitored at repeated intervals for cyclosporine blood concentrations and subsequent dose adjustments be made in order to avoid toxicity due to high concentrations and possible organ rejection due to low absorption of cyclosporine. This is of special importance in liver transplants. Numerous assays are being developed to measure blood concentrations of cyclosporine. Comparison of concentrations in published literature to patient concentrations using current assays must be done with detailed knowledge of the assay methods employed. (See Blood Concentration Monitoring under DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION)
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
