<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="savella" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most frequently occurring adverse reactions (&gt;= 5% and greater than placebo) were nausea, headache, constipation, dizziness, insomnia, hot flush, hyperhidrosis, vomiting, palpations, heart rate increased, dry mouth, and hypertension (  6.3  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Forest Pharmaceuticals, Inc., at (800) 678-1605 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Data Sources

  Savella was evaluated in three double-blind placebo-controlled trials involving 2209 fibromyalgia patients (1557 patients treated with Savella and 652 patients treated with placebo) for a treatment period up to 29 weeks.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse reaction of the type listed. A reaction was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   6.2 Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation

  In placebo-controlled trials in patients with fibromyalgia, 23% of patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day, 26% of patients treated with Savella 200 mg/day discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions, compared to 12% of patients treated with placebo. The adverse reactions that led to withdrawal in &gt;= 1% of patients in the Savella treatment group and with an incidence rate greater than that in the placebo treatment group were nausea (milnacipran 6%, placebo 1%), palpitations (milnacipran 3%, placebo 1%), headache (milnacipran 2%, placebo 0%), constipation (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), heart rate increased (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), and hyperhidrosis (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), vomiting (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), and dizziness (milnacipran 1% and placebo 0.5%). Discontinuation due to adverse reactions was generally more common among patients treated with Savella 200 mg/day compared to Savella 100 mg/day.



   6.3 Most Common Adverse Reactions

  In the placebo-controlled fibromyalgia patient trials the most frequently occurring adverse reaction in clinical trials was nausea. The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and twice placebo) in patients treated with Savella were constipation, hot flush, hyperhidrosis, vomiting, palpitations, heart rate increased, dry mouth, and hypertension.



   Table 2  lists all adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with Savella at either 100 or 200 mg/day and at an incidence greater than that of placebo.



 Table 2. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence in Placebo Controlled Trials in Fibromyalgia Patients (Events Occurring in at Least 2% of All Savella-Treated Patients and Occurring More Frequently in Either Savella Treatment Group Than in the Placebo Treatment Group) 
   System Organ Class-    Preferred Term      Savella    100 mg/day    (n = 623) %      Savella    200 mg/day    (n = 934) %      All Savella    (n = 1557) %      Placebo    (n = 652) %     
   Cardiac Disorders                                                                                        
  Palpitations                     8                 7                 7                 2                  
  Tachycardia                      3                 2                 2                 1                  
   Eye Disorders                                                                                            
  Vision blurred                   1                 2                 2                 1                  
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
  Nausea                           35                39                37                20                 
  Constipation                     16                15                16                4                  
  Vomiting                         6                 7                 7                 2                  
  Dry mouth                        5                 5                 5                 2                  
  Abdominal pain                   3                 3                 3                 2                  
   General Disorders                                                                                        
  Chest pain                       3                 2                 2                 2                  
  Chills                           1                 2                 2                 0                  
  Chest discomfort                 2                 1                 1                 1                  
   Infections                                                                                               
  Upper respiratory tract infection  7                 6                 6                 6                  
   Investigations                                                                                           
  Heart rate increased             5                 6                 6                 1                  
  Blood pressure increased         3                 3                 3                 1                  
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                             
  Decreased appetite               1                 2                 2                 0                  
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                                 
  Headache                         19                17                18                14                 
  Dizziness                        11                10                10                6                  
  Migraine                         6                 4                 5                 3                  
  Paresthesia                      2                 3                 2                 2                  
  Tremor                           2                 2                 2                 1                  
  Hypoesthesia                     1                 2                 1                 1                  
  Tension headache                 2                 1                 1                 1                  
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
  Insomnia                         12                12                12                10                 
  Anxiety                          5                 3                 4                 4                  
   Respiratory Disorders                                                                                    
 Dyspnea                           2                 2                 2                 1                  
   Skin Disorders                                                                                           
  Hyperhidrosis                    8                 9                 9                 2                  
  Rash                             3                 4                 3                 2                  
  Pruritus                         3                 2                 2                 2                  
   Vascular Disorders                                                                                       
  Hot flush                        11                12                12                2                  
  Hypertension                     7                 4                 5                 2                  
  Flushing                         2                 3                 3                 1                  
             6.4 Weight Changes
   In placebo-controlled fibromyalgia clinical trials, patients treated with Savella for up to 3 months experienced a mean weight loss of approximately 0.8 kg in both the Savella 100 mg/day and the Savella 200 mg/day treatment groups, compared with a mean weight loss of approximately 0.2 kg in placebo-treated patients.



   6.5 Genitourinary Adverse Reactions in Males

  In the placebo-controlled fibromyalgia studies, the following treatment-emergent adverse reactions related to the genitourinary system were observed in at least 2% of male patients treated with Savella, and occurred at a rate greater than in placebo-treated male patients: dysuria, ejaculation disorder, erectile dysfunction, ejaculation failure, libido decreased, prostatitis, scrotal pain, testicular pain, testicular swelling, urinary hesitation, urinary retention, urethral pain, and urine flow decreased.



   6.6 Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Clinical Trials of Savella in Fibromyalgia

  Following is a list of frequent (those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients) treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported from 1824 fibromyalgia patients treated with Savella for periods up to 68 weeks. The listing does not include those events already listed in  Table 1  , those events for which a drug cause was remote, those events which were so general as to be uninformative, and those events reported only once which did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life threatening.



 Adverse reactions are categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency. Adverse reactions of major clinical importance are described in the  Warnings and Precautions  section (  5  ).



 Gastrointestinal Disorders - diarrhea, dyspepsia, gastroesophageal reflux disease, flatulence, abdominal distension



 General Disorders - fatigue, peripheral edema, irritability, pyrexia



 Infections - urinary tract infection, cystitis



 Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications - contusion, fall



 Investigations - weight decreased or increased



 Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders - hypercholesterolemia



 Nervous System Disorders - somnolence, dysgeusia



 Psychiatric Disorders - depression, stress



 Skin Disorders - night sweats



   6.7 Postmarketing Spontaneous Reports

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified from spontaneous reports of Savella received worldwide. These adverse reactions have been chosen for inclusion because of a combination of seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to Savella. However, because these adverse reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events include:



 Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders - leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia



 Cardiac Disorders - supraventricular tachycardia



 Eye Disorders - accommodation disorder



 Endocrine Disorders - hyperprolactinemia



 Hepatobiliary Disorders - hepatitis



 Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders - anorexia, hyponatremia



 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders - rhabdomyolysis



 Nervous System Disorders - convulsions (including grand mal), loss of consciousness, neuroleptic malignant syndrome, Parkinsonism, serotonin syndrome



 Psychiatric Disorders - delirium, hallucination



 Renal and Urinary Disorders - acute renal failure



 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders - galactorrhea



 Skin Disorders - erythema multiforme, Stevens Johnson syndrome



 Vascular Disorders - hypertensive crisis
</Section>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S2">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most frequently occurring adverse reactions (&gt;= 5% and greater than placebo) were nausea, headache, constipation, dizziness, insomnia, hot flush, hyperhidrosis, vomiting, palpitations, heart rate increased, dry mouth, and hypertension (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Forest Laboratories, LLC., at (800) 678-1605 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Patient Exposure  



 Savella was evaluated in three double-blind placebo-controlled trials involving 2209 fibromyalgia patients (1557 patients treated with Savella and 652 patients treated with placebo) for a treatment period up to 29 weeks.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse reaction of the type listed. A reaction was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



     Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation  



 In placebo-controlled trials in patients with fibromyalgia, 23% of patients treated with Savella



 100 mg/day, 26% of patients treated with Savella 200 mg/day discontinued prematurely due to adverse reactions, compared to 12% of patients treated with placebo. The adverse reactions that led to withdrawal in &gt;= 1% of patients in the Savella treatment group and with an incidence rate greater than that in the placebo treatment group were nausea (milnacipran 6%, placebo 1%), palpitations (milnacipran 3%, placebo 1%), headache (milnacipran 2%, placebo 0%), constipation (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), heart rate increased (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), hyperhidrosis (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), vomiting (milnacipran 1%, placebo 0%), and dizziness (milnacipran 1% and placebo 0.5%). Discontinuation due to adverse reactions was generally more common among patients treated with Savella 200 mg/day compared to Savella 100 mg/day.



     Most Common Adverse Reactions in Placebo Controlled Trials  



 In the placebo-controlled fibromyalgia patient trials, the most frequently occurring adverse reaction in clinical trials was nausea. The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and twice placebo) in patients treated with Savella were constipation, hot flush, hyperhidrosis, vomiting, palpitations, heart rate increased, dry mouth, and hypertension.



     Table 4    lists all adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with Savella at either 100 or 200 mg/day and at an incidence greater than that of placebo.



 Table 4: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence in Placebo Controlled Trials in Fibromyalgia Patients (Events Occurring in at Least 2% of All Savella-Treated Patients and Occurring More Frequently in Either Savella Treatment Group Than in the Placebo Treatment Group) 
  System Organ Class-Preferred Term    Savella100 mg/day(n = 623) %    Savella200 mg/day(n = 934) %    All Savella(n = 1557) %    Placebo(n = 652) %    
  Cardiac Disorders                                                                                              
    Palpitations                     8                  7                  7                  2                  
    Tachycardia                      3                  2                  2                  1                  
  Eye Disorders                                                                                                  
    Vision blurred                   1                  2                  2                  1                  
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                     
    Nausea                           35                 39                 37                 20                 
    Constipation                     16                 15                 16                 4                  
    Vomiting                         6                  7                  7                  2                  
    Dry mouth                        5                  5                  5                  2                  
    Abdominal pain                   3                  3                  3                  2                  
  General Disorders                                                                                              
    Chest pain                       3                  2                  2                  2                  
    Chills                           1                  2                  2                  0                  
    Chest discomfort                 2                  1                  1                  1                  
  Infections                                                                                                     
    Upper respiratory tract infection    7                  6                  6                  6                  
  Investigations                                                                                                 
    Heart rate increased             5                  6                  6                  1                  
    Blood pressure increased         3                  3                  3                  1                  
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                                
    Decreased appetite               1                  2                  2                  0                  
  Nervous System Disorders                                                                                       
    Headache                         19                 17                 18                 14                 
    Dizziness                        11                 10                 10                 6                  
    Migraine                         6                  4                  5                  3                  
    Paresthesia                      2                  3                  2                  2                  
    Tremor                           2                  2                  2                  1                  
    Hypoesthesia                     1                  2                  1                  1                  
    Tension headache                 2                  1                  1                  1                  
  Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                          
    Insomnia                         12                 12                 12                 10                 
    Anxiety                          5                  3                  4                  4                  
  Respiratory Disorders                                                                                          
  Dyspnea                            2                  2                  2                  1                  
  Skin Disorders                                                                                                 
    Hyperhidrosis                    8                  9                  9                  2                  
    Rash                             3                  4                  3                  2                  
    Pruritus                         3                  2                  2                  2                  
  Vascular Disorders                                                                                             
    Hot flush                        11                 12                 12                 2                  
    Hypertension                     7                  4                  5                  2                  
    Flushing                         2                  3                  3                  1                  
               Weight Changes  
 

 In placebo-controlled fibromyalgia clinical trials, patients treated with Savella for up to 3 months experienced a mean weight loss of approximately 0.8 kg in both the Savella 100 mg/day and the Savella 200 mg/day treatment groups, compared with a mean weight loss of approximately 0.2 kg in placebo-treated patients.



     Genitourinary Adverse Reactions in Males  



 In the placebo-controlled fibromyalgia studies, the following treatment-emergent adverse reactions related to the genitourinary system were observed in at least 2% of male patients treated with Savella, and occurred at a rate greater than in placebo-treated male patients: dysuria, ejaculation disorder, erectile dysfunction, ejaculation failure, libido decreased, prostatitis, scrotal pain, testicular pain, testicular swelling, urinary hesitation, urinary retention, urethral pain, and urine flow decreased.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Clinical Trials of Savella in Fibromyalgia  



 Following is a list of frequent (those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients) treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported from 1824 fibromyalgia patients treated with Savella for periods up to 68 weeks. The listing does not include those events already listed in    Table 4    , those events for which a drug cause was remote, those events which were so general as to be uninformative, and those events reported only once which did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life threatening.



 Adverse reactions are categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency. Adverse reactions of major clinical importance are described in the  Warnings and Precautions section (  5  )  .



 Gastrointestinal Disorders - diarrhea, dyspepsia, gastroesophageal reflux disease, flatulence, abdominal distension



 General Disorders - fatigue, peripheral edema, irritability, pyrexia



 Infections - urinary tract infection, cystitis



 Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications - contusion, fall



 Investigations - weight decreased or increased



 Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders - hypercholesterolemia



 Nervous System Disorders - somnolence, dysgeusia



 Psychiatric Disorders - depression, stress



 Skin Disorders - night sweats



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified from spontaneous reports of Savella received worldwide. These adverse reactions have been chosen for inclusion because of a combination of seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to Savella. However, because these adverse reactions were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events include:



 Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders - leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia



 Cardiac Disorders - supraventricular tachycardia



 Eye Disorders - accommodation disorder



 Endocrine Disorders - hyperprolactinemia



 Hepatobiliary Disorders - hepatitis



 Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders - anorexia, hyponatremia



 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders - rhabdomyolysis



 Nervous System Disorders - convulsions (including grand mal), loss of consciousness, Parkinsonism



 Psychiatric Disorders - aggression, anger, delirium, hallucination, homicidal ideation



 Renal and Urinary Disorders - acute renal failure



 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders - galactorrhea



 Skin Disorders - erythema multiforme, Stevens Johnson syndrome



 Vascular Disorders - hypertensive crisis
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S3">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS Savella is a selective serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor (SNRI), similar to some drugs used for the treatment of depression and other psychiatric disorders. Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of such drugs in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on Savella should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. Savella is not approved for use in the treatment of major depressive disorder. Savella is not approved for use in pediatric patients [      see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )      ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Increased risk of suicidal ideation, thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Savella is not approved for use in pediatric patients (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S4">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS 

  WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS 

    Savella is a selective serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor (SNRI), similar to some drugs used for the treatment of depression and other psychiatric disorders. Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of such drugs in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on Savella should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. Savella is not approved for use in the treatment of major depressive disorder. Savella is not approved for use in pediatric patients   [see Indications and Usage (  1  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )]    . 



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Increased risk of suicidal ideation, thinking, and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders (5.1). 
 *  Savella is not approved for use in pediatric patients (1, 8.4). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S5">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Suicidality: Monitor for worsening of depressive symptoms and suicide risk (  5.1  ) 
 *  Serotonin Syndrome: Serotonin syndrome has been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs. Concomitant use of serotonergic drugs is not recommended (  5.2  ) 
 *  Elevated blood pressure and heart rate: Cases have been reported with Savella. Monitor blood pressure and heart rate prior to initiating treatment with Savella and periodically throughout treatment (  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
 *  Seizures: Cases have been reported with Savella therapy. Prescribe Savella with care in patients with a history of seizure disorder. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: More patients treated with Savella than with placebo experienced mild elevations of ALT and AST. Rarely, fulminant hepatitis has been reported in patients treated with Savella. Avoid concomitant use of Savella in patients with substantial alcohol use or chronic liver disease (  5.6  ) 
 *  Discontinuation: Withdrawal symptoms have been reported in patients when discontinuing treatment with Savella. A gradual dose reduction is recommended (  5.7  ) 
 *  Abnormal Bleeding: Savella may increase the risk of bleeding events. Caution patients about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of Savella and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Male patients with a history of obstructive uropathies may experience higher rates of genitourinary adverse events (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Suicide Risk



  Savella is a selective serotonin and norepinephrine re-uptake inhibitor (SNRI), similar to some drugs used for the treatment of depression and other psychiatric disorders.



 Patients, both adult and pediatric, with depression or other psychiatric disorders may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking these medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants, including drugs that inhibit the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin, may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment.



 In the placebo-controlled clinical trials of adults with fibromyalgia, among the patients who had a history of depression at treatment initiation, the incidence of suicidal ideation was 0.5% in patients treated with placebo, 0% in patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day, and 1.3% in patients treated with Savella 200 mg/day. No suicides occurred in the short-term or longer-term (up to 1 year) fibromyalgia trials.



 Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of drugs used to treat depression (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with these drugs compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in suicidality risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults age 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 drugs used to treat depression in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk of differences (drug versus placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in  Table 1  .



 Table 1. Risk Differences (Drug - Placebo) in the number of Cases of Suicidality, per 1000 patients treated 
  Age Range         Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated     
 &lt; 18              14 additional cases                                                                   
 18-24             5 additional cases                                                                    
                    Decreases Compared to Placebo                                                        
 25-64             1 fewer case                                                                          
 &gt;= 65             6 fewer cases                                                                         
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with drugs inhibiting the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with drugs inhibiting the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients who may experience worsening depressive symptoms, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe or abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



 If the decision has been made to discontinue treatment due to worsening depressive symptoms or emergent suicidality, medication should be tapered, as rapidly as is feasible, but with recognition that abrupt discontinuation can produce withdrawal symptoms [see Dosage and Administration-Recommended Dosing (  2.1  ), Dosage-Discontinuing Savella (    2.4  ), and Warnings and Precautions-Discontinuation of Treatment with Savella (    5.7   )].  



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with drugs inhibiting the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. Prescriptions for Savella should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.  



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-Like Reactions



     The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome or Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)-like reactions have been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs alone, including Savella, but particularly with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (including triptans), with drugs which impair metabolism of serotonin (including MAOIs) or with antipsychotics or other dopamine antagonists. Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination) and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea) [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  . Serotonin syndrome, in its most severe form can resemble neuroleptic malignant syndrome, which includes hyperthermia, muscle rigidity, autonomic instability with possible rapid fluctuation of vital signs, and mental status changes. Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome or NMS-like signs and symptoms.



    The concomitant use of Savella with MAOIs is contraindicated [see Contraindications (  4.1  )].  



    If concomitant treatment of Savella with a 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor agonist (triptan) is clinically warranted, careful observation of the patient is advised, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases [see Drug Interactions (  7  )].  



    The concomitant use of Savella with serotonin precursors (such as tryptophan) is not recommended [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  . Treatment with Savella and any concomitant serotonergic or antidopaminergic agents, including antipsychotics, should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Effects on Blood Pressure



  Inhibition of the reuptake of norepinephrine (NE) and serotonin (5-HT) can lead to cardiovascular effects. SNRIs, including Savella, have been associated with reports of increase in blood pressure.



 In a double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical pharmacology study in healthy subjects designed to evaluate the effects of milnacipran on various parameters, including blood pressure at supratherapeutic doses, there was evidence of mean increases in supine blood pressure at doses up to 300 mg twice daily (600 mg/day). At the highest 300 mg twice daily dose, the mean increase in systolic blood pressure was up to 8.1 mm Hg for the placebo group and up to 10.0 mm Hg for the Savella treated group over the 12 hour steady state dosing interval. The corresponding mean increase in diastolic blood pressure over this interval was up to 4.6 mm Hg for placebo and up to 11.5 mm Hg for the Savella treated group.



 In the 3-month placebo-controlled fibromyalgia clinical trials, Savella treatment was associated with mean increases of up to 3.1 mm Hg in systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.3  )  ].



 In the placebo-controlled trials, among fibromyalgia patients who were non-hypertensive at baseline, approximately twice as many patients in the Savella treatment arms became hypertensive at the end of the study (SBP &gt;= 140 mmHg or DBP &gt;= 90 mmHg) compared with the placebo patients: 7.2% of patients in the placebo arm versus 19.5% of patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day and 16.6% of patients treated with Savella 200 mg/day. Among patients who met systolic criteria for pre-hypertension at baseline (SBP 120-139 mmHg), more patients became hypertensive at the end of the study in the Savella treatment arms than placebo: 9% of patients in the placebo arm versus 14% in both the Savella 100 mg/day and the Savella 200 mg/day treatment arms.



 Among fibromyalgia patients who were hypertensive at baseline, more patients in the Savella treatment arms had a &gt;15 mmHg increase in SBP than placebo at the end of the study: 1% of patients in the placebo arm versus 7% in the Savella 100 mg/day and 2% in the Savella 200 mg/day treatment arms. Similarly, more patients who were hypertensive at baseline and were treated with Savella had DBP increases &gt; 10 mmHg than placebo at the end of study: 3% of patients in the placebo arm versus 8% in the Savella 100 mg/day and 6% in the Savella 200 mg/day treatment arms.



 Sustained increases in SBP (increase of &gt;= 15 mmHg on three consecutive post-baseline visits) occurred in 2% of placebo patients versus 9% of patients receiving Savella 100 mg/day and 6% of patients receiving Savella 200 mg/day. Sustained increases in DBP (increase of &gt;= 10 mmHg on 3 consecutive post-baseline visits) occurred in 4% of patients receiving placebo versus 13% of patients receiving Savella 100 mg/day and 10% of patients receiving Savella 200 mg/day.



 Sustained increases in blood pressure could have adverse consequences. Cases of elevated blood pressure requiring immediate treatment have been reported.



 Concomitant use of Savella with drugs that increase blood pressure and pulse has not been evaluated and such combinations should be used with caution [see Drug Interactions (  7  )].  



 Effects of Savella on blood pressure in patients with significant hypertension or cardiac disease have not been systematically evaluated. Savella should be used with caution in these patients.



 Blood pressure should be measured prior to initiating treatment and periodically measured throughout Savella treatment. Pre-existing hypertension and other cardiovascular disease should be treated before starting therapy with Savella. For patients who experience a sustained increase in blood pressure while receiving Savella, either dose reduction or discontinuation should be considered.



    5.4 Effects on Heart Rate



  SNRIs have been associated with reports of increase in heart rate.



 In clinical trials, relative to placebo, Savella treatment was associated with mean increases in pulse rate of approximately 7 to 8 beats per minute [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  ,  6.3  )  ].



 Increases in pulse &gt;= 20 bpm occurred more frequently in Savella-treated patients when compared to placebo: 0.3% in the placebo arm versus 8% in the Savella 100 mg/day and 8% in the 200 mg/day treatment arms. The effect of Savella on heart rate did not appear to increase with increasing dose.



 Savella has not been systematically evaluated in patients with a cardiac rhythm disorder.



 Heart rate should be measured prior to initiating treatment and periodically measured throughout Savella treatment. Pre-existing tachyarrhythmias and other cardiac disease should be treated before starting therapy with Savella. For patients who experience a sustained increase in heart rate while receiving Savella, either dose reduction or discontinuation should be considered.



    5.5 Seizures



  Savella has not been systematically evaluated in patients with a seizure disorder. In clinical trials evaluating Savella in patients with fibromyalgia, seizures/convulsions have not been reported. However, seizures have been reported infrequently in patients treated with Savella for disorders other than fibromyalgia. Savella should be prescribed with care in patients with a history of a seizure disorder.



    5.6 Hepatotoxicity



  In the placebo-controlled fibromyalgia trials, increases in the number of patients treated with Savella with mild elevations of ALT or AST (1-3 times the upper limit of normal, ULN) were observed. Increases in ALT were more frequently observed in the patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day (6%) and Savella 200 mg/day (7%), compared to the patients treated with placebo (3%). One patient receiving Savella 100 mg/day (0.2%) had an increase in ALT greater than 5 times the upper limit of normal but did not exceed 10 times the upper limit of normal. Increases in AST were more frequently observed in the patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day (3%) and Savella 200 mg/day (5%) compared to the patients treated with placebo (2%).



 The increases of bilirubin observed in the fibromyalgia clinical trials were not clinically significant.



 No case met the criteria of elevated ALT &gt; 3x ULN and associated with an increase in bilirubin &gt;= 2x ULN.



 There have been cases of increased liver enzymes and reports of severe liver injury, including fulminant hepatitis with milnacipran from foreign postmarketing experience. In the cases of severe liver injury there were significant underlying clinical conditions and/or the use of multiple concomitant medications. Because of underreporting, it is impossible to provide an accurate estimate of the true incidence of these reactions.



 Savella should be discontinued in patients who develop jaundice or other evidence of liver dysfunction. Treatment with Savella should not be resumed unless another cause can be established.



 Savella should ordinarily not be prescribed to patients with substantial alcohol use or evidence of chronic liver disease.



    5.7 Discontinuation of Treatment with Savella



  Withdrawal symptoms have been observed in clinical trials following discontinuation of milnacipran, as with other SNRIs and SSRIs.



 During marketing of milnacipran, and other SNRIs and SSRIs, there have been spontaneous reports of adverse events indicative of withdrawal and physical dependence occurring upon discontinuation of these drugs, particularly when discontinuation is abrupt. The adverse events include the following: dysphoric mood, irritability, agitation, dizziness, sensory disturbances (e.g., paresthesias such as electric shock sensations), anxiety, confusion, headache, lethargy, emotional lability, insomnia, hypomania, tinnitus, and seizures. Although these events are generally self-limiting, some have been reported to be severe.



 Patients should be monitored for these symptoms when discontinuing treatment with Savella. Savella should be tapered and not abruptly discontinued after extended use. If intolerable symptoms occur following a decrease in the dose or upon discontinuation of treatment, then resuming the previously prescribed dose may be considered. Subsequently, the physician may continue decreasing the dose but at a more gradual rate [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .



    5.8 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia may occur as a result of treatment with SSRIs and SNRIs, including Savella. In many cases, this hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with SNRIs, SSRIs, or Savella. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume-depleted may be at greater risk [ see Geriatric Use (  8.5  )  ]. Discontinuation of Savella should be considered in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia.



 Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which may lead to falls. Signs and symptoms associated with more severe and/or acute cases have included hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.9 Abnormal Bleeding



  SSRIs and SNRIs, including Savella, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, warfarin, and other anti-coagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding events related to SSRIs and SNRIs use have ranged from ecchymoses, hematomas, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages.



 Patients should be cautioned about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of Savella and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation.



    5.10 Activation of Mania



  No activation of mania or hypomania was reported in the clinical trials evaluating effects of Savella in patients with fibromyalgia. However those clinical trials excluded patients with current major depressive episode. Activation of mania and hypomania have been reported in patients with mood disorders who were treated with other similar drugs for major depressive disorder. As with these other agents, Savella should be used cautiously in patients with a history of mania.



    5.11 Patients with a History of Dysuria



  Because of their noradrenergic effect, SNRIs including Savella, can affect urethral resistance and micturition. In the controlled fibromyalgia trials, dysuria occurred more frequently in patients treated with Savella (1%) than in placebo-treated patients (0.5%). Caution is advised in use of Savella in patients with a history of dysuria, notably in male patients with prostatic hypertrophy, prostatitis, and other lower urinary tract obstructive disorders. Male patients are more prone to genitourinary adverse effects, such as dysuria or urinary retention, and may experience testicular pain or ejaculation disorders.



    5.12 Controlled Narrow-Angle Glaucoma



  Mydriasis has been reported in association with SNRIs and Savella; therefore, Savella should be used cautiously in patients with controlled narrow-angle glaucoma.



 Do not use Savella in patients with Uncontrolled Narrow-Angle Glaucoma [see Contraindications (  4.2  )].  



    5.13 Concomitant Use with Alcohol



  In clinical trials, more patients treated with Savella developed elevated transaminases than did placebo treated patients [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )  ]. Because it is possible that milnacipran may aggravate pre-existing liver disease, Savella should not be prescribed to patients with substantial alcohol use or evidence of chronic liver disease.



    5.14 Allergy to FD&amp;C Yellow No. 5



  This product contains FD&amp;C Yellow No. 5 (tartrazine) which may cause allergic-type reactions (including bronchial asthma) in susceptible persons. Although the overall incidence of FD&amp;C Yellow No. 5 (tartrazine) sensitivity in the general population is low, it is frequently seen in patients who also have aspirin hypersensitivity.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S6">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Suicidality: Monitor for worsening of depressive symptoms and suicide risk (  5.1  ). 
 *    Serotonin Syndrome: Serotonin syndrome has been reported with SSRIs and SNRIs, including Savella, both when taken alone, but especially when co-administered with other serotonergic agents (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone and St. John's Wort). If such symptoms occur, discontinue Savella and initiate supportive treatment. If concomitant use of Savella with other serotonergic drugs is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment and dose increases (  5.2  ). 
 *    Elevated blood pressure and heart rate: Savella may increase blood pressure and heart rate. In an ambulatory blood pressure monitoring study, a substantially higher proportion of Savella-treated patients experienced clinically significant blood pressure and heart rate elevations as compared with placebo-treated patients. Measure blood pressure and heart rate prior to initiating treatment with Savella and monitor periodically throughout treatment (  5.3  ,  5.4  ). 
 *    Seizures: Cases have been reported with Savella therapy. Prescribe Savella with care in patients with a history of seizure disorder (  5.5  ). 
 *    Hepatotoxicity: More patients treated with Savella than with placebo experienced mild elevations of ALT and AST. Rarely, fulminant hepatitis has been reported in patients treated with Savella. Avoid concomitant use of Savella in patients with substantial alcohol use or chronic liver disease (  5.6  ). 
 *    Discontinuation: Withdrawal symptoms have been reported in patients when discontinuing treatment with Savella. A gradual dose reduction is recommended (  5.7  ). 
 *    Abnormal Bleeding: Savella may increase the risk of bleeding events. Caution patients about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of Savella and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation (  5.9  ). 
 *    Male patients with a history of obstructive uropathies may experience higher rates of genitourinary adverse events (  5.11  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Suicide Risk



  Savella is a selective serotonin and norepinephrine re-uptake inhibitor (SNRI), similar to some drugs used for the treatment of depression and other psychiatric disorders.



 Patients, both adult and pediatric, with depression or other psychiatric disorders may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking these medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants, including drugs that inhibit the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin, may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment.



 In the placebo-controlled clinical trials of adults with fibromyalgia, among the patients who had a history of depression at treatment initiation, the incidence of suicidal ideation was 0.5% in patients treated with placebo, 0% in patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day, and 1.3% in patients treated with Savella 200 mg/day. No suicides occurred in the short-term or longer-term (up to 1 year) fibromyalgia trials.



 Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of drugs used to treat depression (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with these drugs compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in suicidality risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults age 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 drugs used to treat depression in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients.



 There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk of differences (drug versus placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in   Table 1    .



 Table 1: Risk Differences (Drug - Placebo) in the number of Cases of Suicidality, per 1000 patients treated 
  Age Range         Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated    
  &lt; 18              14 additional cases                                                                   
  18-24             5 additional cases                                                                    
                    Decreases Compared to Placebo                                                         
  25-64             1 fewer case                                                                          
  &gt;= 65             6 fewer cases                                                                         
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months.



 However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with drugs inhibiting the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases  .



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with drugs inhibiting the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients who may experience worsening depressive symptoms, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe or abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



 If the decision has been made to discontinue treatment due to worsening depressive symptoms or emergent suicidality, medication should be tapered, as rapidly as is feasible, but with recognition that abrupt discontinuation can produce withdrawal symptoms [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  ,  2.4  ), and Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  .



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with drugs inhibiting the reuptake of norepinephrine and/or serotonin for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. Prescriptions for Savella should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.  



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs, including Savella, alone but particularly with concomitant use of other serotonergic drugs (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort) and with drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (in particular MAOIs, both those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue).



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome.



 The concomitant use of Savella with MAOIs intended to treat psychiatric disorders is contraindicated. Savella should also not be started in a patient who is being treated with MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue. All reports with methylene blue that provided information on the route of administration involved intravenous administration in the dose range of 1 mg/kg to 8 mg/kg. No reports involved the administration of methylene blue by other routes (such as oral tablets or local tissue injection) or at lower doses. There may be circumstances when it is necessary to initiate treatment with an MAOI such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue in a patient taking Savella. Savella should be discontinued before initiating treatment with the MAOI [see Contraindications (  4.1  ), Dosage and Administration (  2.5  ,  2.6  )].  



 If concomitant use of Savella with other serotonergic drugs including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, buspirone, tryptophan and St. John's Wort is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases.



 Treatment with Savella and any concomitant serotonergic agents should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur, and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Elevated Blood Pressure



  A double-blind, placebo-controlled ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM) study was conducted to evaluate the effects of milnacipran (up to 200 mg/day) on blood pressure in 321 fibromyalgia patients. Among fibromyalgia patients who were normotensive at baseline, an analysis of the blood pressure findings demonstrated a substantially higher proportion of Savella-treated patients had a hypertensive blood pressure measurement at the Week 4, 50 mg BID steady state visit (17.7% [n=21/119]) and the Week 7, 100 mg BID steady state visit (14.3% [n=15/105]) as compared to placebo-treated patients (3.7% [n=2/54] and 0% [0/49] at the Week 4 and Week 7 visits, respectively). Hypertension was defined as mean systolic blood pressure (SBP) &gt;=140 mmHg and change from baseline in mean SBP &gt;=10 mmHg or mean diastolic blood pressure (DBP) &gt;=90 mmHg and change from baseline in mean DBP &gt;=5 mmHg for the 12-hour period post AM study drug measurement at that visit. Furthermore, 1.9% (4/210) of Savella-treated and 0.9% (1/111) of placebo patients discontinued treatment for increases in blood pressure.



 The increased risk of blood pressure measurements in the hypertensive range in Savella-treated patients is supported by substantial increases in mean SBP and DBP measurements observed in the ABPM study.   Table 2    shows that, following treatment with Savella 50 mg BID for three weeks in patients who were normotensive at baseline, the mean increase from baseline was 5 mmHg in systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP). After further treatment with Savella 100 mg BID for two weeks, the mean increase from baseline in SBP and DBP was 6 mmHg. Similar elevations occurred in Savella-treated patients who were hypertensive at baseline.



 Table 2: Mean (Standard Error) Change from Baseline in Mean 24-hour Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure (mmHg) of Milnacipran or Placebo following 4 Weeks of Treatment (50mg BID) and a Subsequent 2 Weeks of Treatment (100mg BID) 
           *Blood pressure measurements made after 3 weeks of milnacipran 50mg BID   
           ^Blood pressure measurements made after 2 weeks of milnacipran 100mg BID   
  
                            Normotensive    Hypertensive    
                            n            Systolic       Diastolic      n             Systolic       Diastolic      
  Placebo                   39           0(2)           -1(1)          50            0(2)           0(2)           
  50 mg BID*                92           5(1)           5(1)           84            5(2)           4(1)           
                                                                                                                   
  Placebo                   37           0(2)           -1(1)          47            -1(2)          0(1)           
  100 mg BID^               82           6(1)           6(1)           80            5(2)           4(1)           
             Similar patterns of treatment-emergent blood pressure elevations were observed in Phase 3 and clinical pharmacology studies as manifested by an increased risk of new onset hypertension or substantial increases in end of study blood pressure measurements in patients with hypertension at baseline (   Table 3    ).
 

 Table 3: Blood pressure changes in Phase 3 randomized controlled trials 
                                            Milnacipran50 mg BID    Milnacipran100 mg BID    Placebo               
  FM patients normotensive at baseline who became hypertensive (defined as SBP &gt;= 140 mmHg or DBP &gt;= 90 mmHg on three consecutive post-baseline visits)    20%                   17%                   7%                    
  FM patients with sustained increases in SBP (increase of &gt;= 15 mmHg on three consecutive post-baseline visits)    9%                    6%                    2%                    
  FM patients with sustained increases in DBP (increase of &gt;= 10 mmHg on three consecutive post-baseline visits)    13%                   10 %                  4%                    
                                            
  FM patients hypertensive at baseline who had increases in SBP &gt;= 15 mmHg at end of study    10%                   7%                    4%                    
  FM patients hypertensive at baseline who had increases in DBP &gt;= 10 mmHg at end of study    8%                    6%                    3%                    
          Sustained increases in blood pressure may have adverse consequences. Cases of elevated blood pressure requiring immediate treatment have been reported.
 

 Concomitant use of Savella with drugs that increase blood pressure and heart rate has not been evaluated and such combinations should be used with caution [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  .



 Effects of Savella on blood pressure in patients with significant hypertension or cardiac disease have not been systematically evaluated. Savella should be used with caution in these patients.



 Measure blood pressure prior to initiating treatment and periodically monitor blood pressure throughout Savella treatment. Treat pre-existing hypertension and other cardiovascular disease before starting therapy with Savella. For patients who experience a sustained increase in blood pressure while receiving Savella, either reduce the dose or discontinue treatment with Savella if clinically warranted.



    5.4 Elevated Heart Rate



  A double-blind, placebo-controlled ABPM study was conducted to evaluate the effects of milnacipran (up to 200 mg/day) on blood pressure in 321 fibromyalgia patients [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  . Information on heart rate was also collected. Following treatment with Savella 50mg BID for three weeks in patients who were normotensive at baseline, the mean increase in mean 24-hour heart rate from baseline was 13 beats per minute. After further treatment with Savella 100 mg BID for two weeks, the mean increase from baseline in heart rate was 13 beats per minute.



 Similar trends were observed in the clinical trials where Savella treatment was associated with mean increases in heart rate of approximately 7 to 8 beats per minute [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ]  .



 Increases in heart rate &gt;= 20 beats per minute occurred more frequently in Savella-treated patients when compared to placebo (8% in the Savella 50 mg BID and 100 mg BID treatment arms versus 0.3% in the placebo arm).



 Savella has not been systematically evaluated in patients with a cardiac rhythm disorder.



 Measure heart rate prior to initiating treatment and periodically monitor the heart rate throughout Savella treatment. Treat pre-existing tachyarrhythmias and other cardiac disease before starting therapy with Savella. For patients who experience a sustained increase in heart rate while receiving Savella, either reduce the dose or discontinue treatment with Savella if clinically warranted.



    5.5 Seizures



  Savella has not been systematically evaluated in patients with a seizure disorder. In clinical trials evaluating Savella in patients with fibromyalgia, seizures/convulsions have not been reported. However, seizures have been reported infrequently in patients treated with Savella for disorders other than fibromyalgia. Savella should be prescribed with care in patients with a history of a seizure disorder.



    5.6 Hepatotoxicity



  In the placebo-controlled fibromyalgia trials, increases in the number of patients treated with Savella with mild elevations of ALT or AST (1-3 times the upper limit of normal, ULN) were observed. Increases in ALT were more frequently observed in the patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day (6%) and Savella 200 mg/day (7%), compared to the patients treated with placebo (3%). One patient receiving Savella 100 mg/day (0.2%) had an increase in ALT greater than 5 times the upper limit of normal but did not exceed 10 times the upper limit of normal. Increases in AST were more frequently observed in the patients treated with Savella 100 mg/day (3%) and Savella 200 mg/day (5%) compared to the patients treated with placebo (2%).



 The increases of bilirubin observed in the fibromyalgia clinical trials were not clinically significant.



 No case met the criteria of elevated ALT &gt; 3x ULN and associated with an increase in bilirubin &gt;= 2x ULN.



 There have been cases of increased liver enzymes and reports of severe liver injury, including fulminant hepatitis with milnacipran from foreign postmarketing experience. In the cases of severe liver injury, there were significant underlying clinical conditions and/or the use of multiple concomitant medications. Because of underreporting, it is impossible to provide an accurate estimate of the true incidence of these reactions.



 Savella should be discontinued in patients who develop jaundice or other evidence of liver dysfunction. Treatment with Savella should not be resumed unless another cause can be established.



 Savella should ordinarily not be prescribed to patients with substantial alcohol use or evidence of chronic liver disease.



    5.7 Discontinuation of Treatment with Savella



  Withdrawal symptoms have been observed in clinical trials following discontinuation of milnacipran, as with other SNRIs and SSRIs.



 During marketing of milnacipran, and other SNRIs and SSRIs, there have been spontaneous reports of adverse events indicative of withdrawal and physical dependence occurring upon discontinuation of these drugs, particularly when discontinuation is abrupt. The adverse events include the following: dysphoric mood, irritability, agitation, dizziness, sensory disturbances (e.g., paresthesias such as electric shock sensations), anxiety, confusion, headache, lethargy, emotional lability, insomnia, hypomania, tinnitus, and seizures. Although these events are generally self-limiting, some have been reported to be severe.



 Patients should be monitored for these symptoms when discontinuing treatment with Savella. Savella should be tapered and not abruptly discontinued after extended use. If intolerable symptoms occur following a decrease in the dose or upon discontinuation of treatment, then resuming the previously prescribed dose may be considered. Subsequently, the physician may continue decreasing the dose but at a more gradual rate [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .



    5.8 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia may occur as a result of treatment with SSRIs and SNRIs, including Savella. In many cases, this hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with SNRIs, SSRIs, or Savella. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume-depleted may be at greater risk [see Geriatric Use (  8.5  )]  . Discontinuation of Savella should be considered in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia.



 Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which may lead to falls. Signs and symptoms associated with more severe and/or acute cases have included hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.9 Abnormal Bleeding



  SSRIs and SNRIs, including Savella, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), warfarin, and other anti-coagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding events related to SSRIs and SNRIs use have ranged from ecchymoses, hematomas, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages.



 Patients should be cautioned about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of Savella and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation.



    5.10 Activation of Mania



  No activation of mania or hypomania was reported in the clinical trials evaluating effects of Savella in patients with fibromyalgia. However those clinical trials excluded patients with current major depressive episode. Activation of mania and hypomania have been reported in patients with mood disorders who were treated with other similar drugs for major depressive disorder. As with these other agents, Savella should be used cautiously in patients with a history of mania.



    5.11 Patients with a History of Dysuria



  Because of their noradrenergic effect, SNRIs including Savella, can affect urethral resistance and micturition. In the controlled fibromyalgia trials, dysuria occurred more frequently in patients treated with Savella (1%) than in placebo-treated patients (0.5%). Caution is advised in use of Savella in patients with a history of dysuria, notably in male patients with prostatic hypertrophy, prostatitis, and other lower urinary tract obstructive disorders. Male patients are more prone to genitourinary adverse effects, such as dysuria or urinary retention, and may experience testicular pain or ejaculation disorders.



    5.12 Angle Closure Glaucoma



  The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of SNRI drugs including Savella may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.



    5.13 Concomitant Use with Alcohol



  In clinical trials, more patients treated with Savella developed elevated transaminases than did placebo treated patients [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  . Because it is possible that milnacipran may aggravate pre-existing liver disease, Savella should not be prescribed to patients with substantial alcohol use or evidence of chronic liver disease.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
