<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="selzentry0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 Adverse Reactions

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Hepatotoxicity [ see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Cardiovascular events [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse events in treatment-experienced subjects (&gt;8% incidence) which occurred at a higher frequency compared to placebo are upper respiratory tract infections, cough, pyrexia, rash, and dizziness (  6  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer  at  1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Studies in Treatment-Experienced Subjects  



 The safety profile of SELZENTRY is primarily based on 840 HIV-infected subjects who received at least one dose of SELZENTRY during two Phase 3 trials. A total of 426 of these subjects received the indicated twice daily dosing regimen.



 Assessment of treatment-emergent adverse events is based on the pooled data from two studies in subjects with CCR5-tropic HIV-1 (A4001027 and A4001028). The median duration of maraviroc therapy for subjects in these studies was 48 weeks, with the total exposure on SELZENTRY twice daily at 309 patient-years versus 111 patient-years on placebo + OBT. The population was 89% male and 84% white, with mean age of 46 years (range 17-75 years). Subjects received dose equivalents of 300 mg maraviroc once or twice daily.



 The most common adverse events reported with SELZENTRY twice daily therapy with frequency rates higher than placebo, regardless of causality, were upper respiratory tract infections, cough, pyrexia, rash, and dizziness. Additional adverse events that occurred with once daily dosing at a higher rate than both placebo and twice daily dosing were diarrhea, edema, influenza, esophageal candidiasis, sleep disorders, rhinitis, parasomnias, and urinary abnormalities. In these two studies, the rate of discontinuation due to adverse events was 5% for subjects who received SELZENTRY twice daily + optimized background therapy (OBT) as well as those who received placebo + OBT. Most of the adverse events reported were judged to be mild to moderate in severity. The data described below occurred with SELZENTRY twice daily dosing.



 The total number of subjects reporting infections were 233 (55%) and 84 (40%) in the SELZENTRY twice daily and placebo groups, respectively. Correcting for the longer duration of exposure on SELZENTRY compared to placebo, the exposure-adjusted frequency (rate per 100 subject-years) of these events was 133 for both SELZENTRY twice daily and placebo.



 Dizziness or postural dizziness occurred in 8% of subjects on either SELZENTRY or placebo, with 2 subjects (0.5%) on SELZENTRY permanently discontinuing therapy (1 due to syncope, 1 due to orthostatic hypotension) versus 1 subject on placebo (0.5%) permanently discontinuing therapy due to dizziness.



 Treatment-emergent adverse events, regardless of causality, from A4001027 and A4001028 are summarized in Table 3. Selected events occurring at &gt;=2% of subjects and at a numerically higher rate in subjects treated with SELZENTRY are included; events that occurred at the same or higher rate on placebo are not displayed.



 Table 3 Percentage of Subjects with Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (All Causality) (&gt;=2% on SELZENTRY and at a higher rate compared to placebo) Studies A4001027 and A4001028 (Pooled Analysis, 48 Weeks) 
                                           SELZENTRYTwice Daily  Exposure-adjusted rate(per 100 pt-yrs)PYE=309      Placebo      Exposure-adjusted rate(per 100 pt-yrs)PYE=111   
                                              N=426(%)                          N=209(%)                        
  
                                                                                                                
   EYE DISORDERS                                                                                                
 Conjunctivitis                                   2                3                1                3          
 Ocular infections, inflammations and associated manifestations         2                3                1                2          
                                                                                                                
   GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                                                                                   
 Constipation                                     6                9                3                6          
                                                                                                                
   GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS                                                                         
 Pyrexia                                         13               20                9               17          
 Pain and discomfort                              4                5                3                5          
                                                                                                                
 I  NFECTIONS AND INFESTATIONS                                                                                  
 Upper respiratory tract infection               23               37               13               27          
 Herpes infection                                 8               11                4                8          
 Sinusitis                                        7               10                3                6          
 Bronchitis                                       7                9                5                9          
 Folliculitis                                     4                5                2                4          
 Pneumonia                                        2                3                5               10          
 Anogenital warts                                 2                3                1                3          
 Influenza                                        2                3               0.5               1          
 Otitis media                                     2                3               0.5               1          
                                                                                                                
   METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS                                                                           
 Appetite disorders                               8               11                7               13          
                                                                                                                
   MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS                                                                         
 Joint related signs and symptoms                 7               10                3                5          
 Muscle pains                                     3                4               0.5               1          
                                                                                                                
   NEOPLASMS BENIGN, MALIGNANT AND UNSPECIFIED                                                                         
 Skin neoplasms benign                            3                4                1                3          
                                                                                                                
   NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                                     
 Dizziness/postural dizziness                     9               13                8               17          
 Paresthesias and dysesthesias                    5                7                3                6          
 Sensory abnormalities                            4                6                1                3          
 Disturbances in consciousness                    4                5                3                6          
 Peripheral neuropathies                          4                5                3                6          
                                                                                                                
   PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                                                                                        
 Disturbances in initiating and maintaining sleep         8               11                5               10          
 Depressive disorders                             4                6                3                5          
 Anxiety symptoms                                 4                5                3                7          
                                                                                                                
   RENAL AND URINARY DISORDERS                                                                                  
 Bladder and urethral symptoms                    5                7                1                3          
 Urinary tract signs and symptoms                 3                4                1                3          
                                                                                                                
   RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS                                                                         
 Coughing and associated symptoms                14               21                5               10          
 Upper respiratory tract signs and symptoms         6                9                3                6          
 Nasal congestion and inflammations               4                6                3                5          
 Breathing abnormalities                          4                5                2                5          
 Paranasal sinus disorders                        3                4               0.5               1          
                                                                                                                
   SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS                                                                         
 Rash                                            11               16                5               11          
 Apocrine and eccrine gland disorders             5                7                4               7.5         
 Pruritus                                         4                5                2                4          
 Lipodystrophies                                  3                5               0.5               1          
 Erythemas                                        2                3                1                2          
                                                                                                                
   VASCULAR DISORDERS                                                                                           
 Vascular hypertensive disorders                  3                4                2                4          
               Laboratory Abnormalities  
 

 Table 4 shows the treatment-emergent Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities that occurred in &gt;2% of subjects receiving SELZENTRY.



 Table 4 Maximum Shift in Laboratory Test Values (Without Regard to Baseline) Incidence &gt;=2% of Grade 3-4 Abnormalities (ACTG Criteria) Studies A4001027 and A4001028 (Pooled Analysis, 48 Weeks) 
 Laboratory Parameter Preferred Term            Limit            SELZENTRYTwice daily+ OBT        Placebo + OBT         
                                                                N =421%                    N =207%            
  
 Aspartate aminotransferase          &gt;5.0* ULN                     4.8                        2.9              
 Alanineaminotransferase            &gt;5.0* ULN                     2.6                        3.4              
 Total bilirubin                    &gt;5.0* ULN                     5.5                        5.3              
 Amylase                            &gt;2.0* ULN                     5.7                        5.8              
 Lipase                             &gt;2.0* ULN                     4.9                        6.3              
 Absolute neutrophil count        &lt;750/mm  3                      4.3                        2.4              
              Study in Treatment-Naive Subjects  
 

   Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events  



 Treatment-emergent adverse events, regardless of causality, from Study A4001026, a double-blind comparative controlled study in which 721 treatment-naive subjects received SELZENTRY 300 mg BID (N=360) or efavirenz (N=361) in combination with zidovudine/lamivudine for 96 weeks, are summarized in Table 5. Selected events occurring at &gt;= 2% of subjects and at a numerically higher rate in subjects treated with SELZENTRY are included; events that occurred at the same or higher rate on efavirenz are not displayed.



 Table 5 Percentage of Subjects with Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (All Causality) (&gt;=2% on SELZENTRY and at a higher rate compared to efavirenz) Study A4001026 (96 Weeks) 
                                           SELZENTRY+zidovudine/lamivudine300 mg BIDN = 360(%)  EFAVIRENZ+zidovudine/lamivudine600 mg QDN = 361(%)   
  
                                                                                                            
   BLOOD AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                     
 Anemias NEC                                             8                               5                  
 Neutropenias                                            4                               3                  
                                                                                                            
   EAR AND LABYRINTH DISORDERS                                                                              
 Ear disorders NEC                                       3                               2                  
   GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                                                                               
 Flatulence, bloating and distention                     10                              7                  
 Gastrointestinal atonic and hypomotility disorders NEC                9                               5                  
 Gastrointestinal signs and symptoms NEC                 3                               2                  
                                                                                                            
   GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS                                                                     
 Body Temperature perception                             3                               1                  
                                                                                                            
 I  NFECTIONS AND INFESTATIONS                                                                              
 Bronchitis                                              13                              9                  
 Herpes Infection                                        7                               6                  
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                       32                              30                 
 Bacterial infections NEC                                6                               3                  
 Herpes zoster/varicella                                 5                               4                  
 Lower respiratory tract and lung infections                3                               2                  
 Neisseria infections                                    3                               0                  
 Tinea infections                                        4                               3                  
 Viral infections NEC                                    3                               2                  
                                                                                                            
   MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS                                                                     
 Joint related signs and symptoms                        6                               5                  
                                                                                                            
   NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                                 
 Memory loss (excluding dementia)                        3                               1                  
 Parasthesias and Dyesthesias                            4                               3                  
                                                                                                            
   RENAL AND URINARY DISORDERS                                                                              
 Bladder and urethral symptoms                           4                               3                  
                                                                                                            
   REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM AND BREAST DISORDERS                                                                     
 Erection and ejaculation conditions and disorders                3                               2                  
                                                                                                            
   RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS                                                                     
 Upper respiratory tract signs and symptoms                9                               5                  
                                                                                                            
   SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS                                                                     
 Acnes                                                   3                               2                  
 Alopecias                                               2                               1                  
 Lipodystrophies                                         4                               3                  
 Nail and nail bed conditions (excluding infections and infestations)                6                               2                  
             Laboratory Abnormalities  
 

 Table 6 Maximum Shift in Laboratory Test Values (Without Regard to Baseline) Incidence &gt;=2% of Grade 3-4 Abnormalities (ACTG Criteria) Study A4001026 (96 Weeks) 
 Laboratory Parameter Preferred Term            Limit            SELZENTRY300 Twice daily+zidovudine/lamivudineN =353%  Efavirenz600 mg QD+zidovudine/lamivudineN =350%   
  
 Percentages based on total subjects evaluated for each laboratory parameter. If the same subject in a given treatment group had &gt;1 occurrence of the same abnormality, only the most severe is counted.   
  
 Aspartate aminotransferase          &gt;5.0* ULN                     4.0                        4.0              
 Alanine aminotransferase           &gt;5.0* ULN                     3.9                        4.0              
 Creatine kinase                                                  3.9                        4.8              
 Amylase                            &gt;2.0* ULN                     4.3                        6.0              
 Absolute neutrophil count        &lt;750/mm  3                      5.7                        4.9              
 Hemoglobin                         &lt;7.0 g/dL                     2.9                        2.3              
              Less Common Adverse Events in Clinical Trials  
 

 The following adverse events occurred in &lt;2% of SELZENTRY-treated subjects. These events have been included because of their seriousness and either increased frequency on SELZENTRY or are potential risks due to the mechanism of action. Events attributed to the patient's underlying HIV infection are not listed.



   Blood and Lymphatic System:  marrow depression and hypoplastic anemia



     Cardiac Disorders    : unstable angina, acute cardiac failure, coronary artery disease, coronary artery occlusion, myocardial infarction, myocardial ischemia



     Hepatobiliary Disorders      :  hepatic cirrhosis, hepatic failure, cholestatic jaundice, portal vein thrombosis, hypertransaminasemia, jaundice



     Infections and Infestations      :  endocarditis, infective myositis, viral meningitis, pneumonia, treponema infections, septic shock,  Clostridium  difficile colitis, meningitis



     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders      :  myositis, osteonecrosis, rhabdomyolysis, blood CK increased



     Neoplasms benign, Malignant and Unspecified (including Cysts and Polyps)      :  abdominal neoplasm, anal cancer, basal cell carcinoma, Bowen's disease, cholangiocarcinoma, diffuse large B-cell lymphoma, lymphoma, metastases to liver, esophageal carcinoma, nasopharyngeal carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma of skin, tongue neoplasm (malignant stage unspecified), anaplastic large cell lymphomas T- and null-cell types, bile duct neoplasms malignant, endocrine neoplasms malignant and unspecified



     Nervous System Disorders      :  cerebrovascular accident, convulsions and epilepsy, tremor (excluding congenital), facial palsy, hemianopia, loss of consciousness, visual field defect



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following events have been identified during post-approval use of SELZENTRY. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not possible to estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to SELZENTRY exposure.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  Stevens-Johnson syndrome.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  HEPATOTOXICITY

    WARNING:  HEPATOTOXICITY  

    Hepatotoxicity has been reported with SELZENTRY use. Evidence of a systemic allergic reaction (e.g., pruritic rash, eosinophilia or elevated IgE) prior to the development of hepatotoxicity may occur. Patients with signs or symptoms of hepatitis or allergic reaction following use of SELZENTRY should be evaluated immediately  [  see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]  .    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING:  HEPATOTOXICITY  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



 *  Hepatotoxicity has been reported which may be preceded by evidence of a systemic allergic reaction (e.g., pruritic rash, eosinophilia or elevated IgE). 
 *  Immediately evaluate patients with signs or symptoms of hepatitis or allergic reaction. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Use caution when administering SELZENTRY to patients with pre-existing liver dysfunction or who are co-infected with viral hepatitis B or C (  5.1  ). 
 *  More cardiovascular events including myocardial ischemia and/or infarction were observed in treatment-experienced subjects who received SELZENTRY. Use with caution in patients at increased risk of cardiovascular events (  5.2  ). 
 *  If patients with severe renal impairment or end-stage renal disease (ESRD) receiving SELZENTRY (without concomitant CYP3A inducers or inhibitors) experience postural hypotension the SELZENTRY dose should be reduced from 300 mg twice daily to 150 mg twice daily (  5.2  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatotoxicity



   A case of possible SELZENTRY-induced hepatotoxicity with allergic features has been reported in a study of healthy volunteers. Discontinuation of SELZENTRY should be considered in any patient with signs or symptoms of hepatitis, or with increased liver transaminases combined with rash or other systemic symptoms.  



 The safety and efficacy of SELZENTRY have not been specifically studied in patients with significant underlying liver disorders. In studies of treatment-experienced HIV-infected subjects, approximately 6% of subjects were co-infected with hepatitis B and approximately 6% were co-infected with hepatitis C. Due to the small number of co-infected subjects studied, no conclusions can be drawn regarding whether they are at an increased risk for hepatic adverse events with SELZENTRY administration. However, caution should be used when administering SELZENTRY to patients with pre-existing liver dysfunction or who are co-infected with viral hepatitis B or C.



    5.2 Cardiovascular Events



   Use with caution in patients at increased risk for cardiovascular events. Eleven subjects (1.3%) who received SELZENTRY had cardiovascular events including myocardial ischemia and/or infarction during the Phase 3 studies in treatment-experienced studies [total exposure 609 patient-years (300 on once daily + 309 on twice daily SELZENTRY)], while no subjects who received placebo had such events (total exposure 111 patient-years). These subjects generally had cardiac disease or cardiac risk factors prior to SELZENTRY use, and the relative contribution of SELZENTRY to these events is not known.  



 In the Phase 2b/3 study in treatment-naive subjects, 3 subjects (0.8%) who received SELZENTRY had events related to ischemic heart diseases and 5 subjects (1.4%) who received efavirenz had such events (total exposure 506 and 508 patient-years for SELZENTRY and efavirenz, respectively).



 When SELZENTRY was administered to healthy volunteers at doses higher than the recommended dose, symptomatic postural hypotension was seen at a greater frequency than in placebo. However, when SELZENTRY was given at the recommended dose in HIV subjects in Phase 3 studies, postural hypotension was seen at a rate similar to placebo (approximately 0.5%). Caution should be used when administering SELZENTRY in patients with a history of postural hypotension or on concomitant medication known to lower blood pressure.



    



   Postural Hypotension in Patients with Renal Impairment  



 Patients with impaired renal function may have cardiovascular co-morbidities and could be at increased risk of cardiovascular adverse events triggered by postural hypotension. An increased risk of postural hypotension may occur in patients with severe renal insufficiency or in those with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) due to increased maraviroc exposure in some patients. SELZENTRY should be used in patients with severe renal impairment or ESRD only if they are not receiving a concomitant potent CYP3A inhibitor or inducer. However, the use of SELZENTRY in these patients should only be considered when no alternative treatment options are available. If patients with severe renal impairment or ESRD experience any symptoms of postural hypotension while taking 300 mg twice daily the dose should be reduced to 150 mg twice daily [see   Dosage and Administration (2.2)    ].



    5.3 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including maraviroc. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as infection with Mycobacterium  avium, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis  jirovecii, Mycobacterium  tuberculosis, or reactivation of Herpes  simplex and Herpes  zoster), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



    5.4 Potential Risk of Infection



   SELZENTRY antagonizes the CCR5 co-receptor located on some immune cells, and therefore could potentially increase the risk of developing infections. The overall incidence and severity of infection, as well as AIDS-defining category C infections, was comparable in the treatment groups during the Phase 3 treatment-experienced studies of SELZENTRY. While there was a higher rate of certain upper respiratory tract infections reported in the SELZENTRY arm compared to placebo (23% versus 13%), there was a lower rate of pneumonia (2% vs 5%) reported in subjects receiving SELZENTRY. A higher incidence of Herpes virus infections (11 per 100 patient-years) was also reported in the SELZENTRY arm when adjusted for exposure compared to placebo (8 per 100 patient-years).  



 In the Phase 2b/3 study in treatment-naive subjects, the incidence of AIDS-defining Category C events when adjusted for exposure was 1.8 for SELZENTRY compared to 2.4 for efavirenz per 100 patient-years of exposure.



 Patients should be monitored closely for evidence of infections while receiving SELZENTRY.



    5.5 Potential Risk of Malignancy



   While no increase in malignancy has been observed with SELZENTRY, due to this drug's mechanism of action it could affect immune surveillance and lead to an increased risk of malignancy.  



 The exposure-adjusted rate for malignancies per 100 patient-years of exposure in treatment-experienced studies was 4.6 for SELZENTRY compared to 9.3 on placebo. In treatment-naive subjects, the rates were 1.0 and 2.4 per 100 patient-years of exposure for SELZENTRY and efavirenz, respectively.



 Long-term follow-up is needed to more fully assess this risk.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
