<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sensipar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (i.e.,  &gt;= 25%) associated with Sensipar were nausea and vomiting. (  6.1  ,  6.2  )     



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Amgen Medical Information at 1-800-77-AMGEN (1-800-772-6436) or FDA at    1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .      



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



       Secondary Hyperparathyroidism in Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease on Dialysis    

  In three double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trials, 1126 patients with CKD on dialysis received study drug (656 Sensipar, 470 placebo) for up to 6 months.  The most frequently reported adverse reactions are listed in Table 1.



 Seizures were observed in 1.4% (13/910) of Sensipar-treated patients and 0.7% (5/641) of placebo-treated patients across all completed placebo controlled trials.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions with Frequency &gt;= 5% in Patients on Dialysis in Short-Term Studies for up to 6 Months 
    Placebo   Sensipar    
    (n = 470)    (n = 656)   
  Event:   (%)   (%)   
  Nausea   19   31   
  Vomiting   15   27   
  Diarrhea   20   21   
  Myalgia   14   15   
  Dizziness   8   10   
  Hypertension   5   7   
  Asthenia   4   7   
  Anorexia   4   6   
  Pain Chest, Non-Cardiac   4   6   
  Dialysis Access Site Infection   4   5   
         In a randomized, double-blind placebo controlled study of 3,883 patients with secondary HPT and CKD receiving dialysis in which patients were treated for up to 64 months (mean duration of treatment was 21 months in the Sensipar group), the most frequently reported adverse reactions (incidence of  &gt;=  5% in the Sensipar group and a difference &gt;= 1% compared to placebo) are listed in Table 2.
 

 Table 2. Frequency of Adverse Reactions in Dialysis Patients Treated for up to 64 Months in a Long-Term Study1 
                                     Placebo (N=1923)   Sensipar (N=1938)                
  3699 subject-years                  4044 subject-years    
  
  Percent of subjects reporting Adverse Reactions (%)    90.9             93.2                            
  Nausea                              15.5             29.1                            
  Vomiting                            13.7             25.6                            
  Diarrhea                            18.7             20.5                            
  Dyspnea                             11.5             13.4                            
  Cough                               9.8              11.7                            
  Hypotension                         10.5             11.6                            
  Headache                            9.6              11.5                            
  Hypocalcaemia                       1.4              11.2                            
  Muscle spasms                       9.2              11.1                            
  Abdominal pain                      9.6              10.9                            
  Abdominal pain upper                6.3              8.2                             
  Hyperkalemia                        6.1              8.1                             
  Upper respiratory tract infection    6.3              7.6                             
  Dyspepsia                           4.6              7.4                             
  Dizziness                           4.7              7.3                             
  Decreased appetite                  3.5              5.9                             
  Asthenia                            3.8              5.4                             
  Constipation                        3.8              5.0                             
           1  Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 5% Frequency in the Sensipar group and a difference &gt;= 1% compared to the placebo group (Safety Analysis Set)Crude incidence rate = 100 * Total number of subjects with event/ NN=Number of subjects receiving at least one dose of study drug
 

 Additional adverse reaction rates from the long-term, randomized, double-blind placebo controlled study for Sensipar versus placebo are as follows: seizure (2.5%, 1.6%), rash (2.2%, 1.9%), hypersensitivity reactions (9.4%, 8.3%).



       Parathyroid Carcinoma and Primary Hyperparathyroidism    

  The safety profile of Sensipar in these patient populations is generally consistent with that seen in patients with CKD on dialysis.  Forty six patients were treated with Sensipar in a single arm study, 29 with Parathyroid Carcinoma and 17 with intractable pHPT.  Nine (20%) of the patients withdrew from the study due to adverse events.  The most frequent adverse reactions and the most frequent cause of withdrawal in these patient populations were nausea and vomiting.  Severe or prolonged cases of nausea and vomiting can lead to dehydration and worsening hypercalcemia so careful monitoring of electrolytes is recommended in patients with these symptoms.



 Eight patients died during treatment with Sensipar in this study, 7 with Parathyroid Carcinoma (24%) and 1 (6%) with intractable pHPT.  Causes of death were cardiovascular (5 patients), multi-organ failure (1 patient), gastrointestinal hemorrhage (1 patient) and metastatic carcinoma (1 patient).  Adverse events of hypocalcemia were reported in three patients (7%).



 Seizures were observed in 0.7% (1/140) of cinacalcet-treated patients and 0.0% (0/46) of placebo-treated patients in all clinical studies.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions with Frequency &gt;= 10% in a Single Arm, Open-Label Study in Patients with Primary Hyperparathyroidism or Parathyroid Carcinoma 
  N=Number of subjects receiving at least one dose of study drug. pHPT=primary hyperparathyroidism   
  
        Sensipar           
                                                 
     ParathyroidCarcinoma (N=29)   IntractablepHPT(N=17)     Total(N=46)   
                                                 
     n (%)             n (%)                  n (%)   
  Number of Subjects Reporting Adverse Events   28 (97)            17 (100)              45 (98)   
                                                 
  Nausea   19 (66)            10 (59)               29 (63)   
  Vomiting   15 (52)            6 (35)                21 (46)   
  Paresthesia   4 (14)             5 (29)                9 (20)   
  Fatigue   6 (21)             2 (12)                8 (17)   
  Fracture   6 (21)             2 (12)                8 (17)   
  Hypercalcemia   6 (21)             2 (12)                8 (17)   
  Anorexia   6 (21)             1 (6)                 7 (15)   
  Asthenia   5 (17)             2 (12)                7 (15)   
  Dehydration   7 (24)             0 (0)                 7 (15)   
  Anemia   5 (17)             1 (6)                 6 (13)   
  Arthralgia   5 (17)             1 (6)                 6 (13)   
  Constipation   3 (10)             3 (18)                6 (13)   
  Depression   3 (10)             3 (18)                6 (13)   
  Headache   6 (21)             0 (0)                 6 (13)   
  Infection Upper Respiratory   3 (10)             2 (12)                5 (11)   
  Pain Limb   3 (10)             2 (12)                5 (11)   
          In a randomized double-blind, placebo-controlled study of 67 patients with primary hyperparathyroidism for whom parathyroidectomy would be indicated on the basis of serum calcium levels, but who are unable to undergo surgery, the most common adverse reactions are listed in Table 4.
 

 Table 4. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 10% of Subjects in a Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Study in Patients with Primary Hyperparathyroidism 
  Adverse Reaction                                                                                                                                  Placebo(N = 34)n (%)                                        Cinacalcet(N = 33)n (%)                                              
  Nausea                                                                                                                                            6 (18)                                                      10 (30)                                                              
  Muscle spasms                                                                                                                                     0 (0)                                                       6 (18)                                                               
  Headache                                                                                                                                          2 (6)                                                       4 (12)                                                               
  Back pain                                                                                                                                         2 (6)                                                       4 (12)                                                               
         N=Number of subjects receiving at least one dose of study drug Coded using MedDRA version 16.0
 

       Hypocalcemia    

  In 26-week studies of patients with secondary HPT and CKD on dialysis 66% of patients receiving Sensipar compared with 25% of patients receiving placebo developed at least one serum calcium value less than 8.4 mg/dL, whereas, 29% of patients receiving Sensipar compared with 11% of patients receiving placebo developed at least one serum calcium value less than 7.5 mg/dL.  Less than 1% of patients in each group permanently discontinued study drug due to hypocalcemia.



 In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study in patients with secondary HPT and CKD receiving dialysis in which patients were treated for up to 64 months (mean duration of treatment was 21 months in the cinacalcet group),  75% of patients receiving Sensipar compared with 29% of patients receiving placebo developed at least one serum calcium value less than 8.4 mg/dL and 33% of cinacalcet patients compared with 12% of patients receiving placebo had at least one serum calcium value less than 7.5 mg/dL. Most of the cases of severe hypocalcemia less than 7.5 mg/dL (21/33=64%) occurred during the first 6 months. In this trial, 1.1% of patients receiving Sensipar and 0.1% of patients receiving placebo permanently discontinued study drug due to hypocalcemia.



 During a placebo-controlled part of a 52-week study in patients with primary HPT who met criteria for parathyroidectomy on the basis of corrected total serum calcium (&gt;11.3 mg/dl [2.82 mmol/L] and &lt;=12.5 mg/dl [3.12 mmol/L]), serum calcium less than 8.4 mg/dL was observed in 6.1% (2/33) of Sensipar treated patients and 0% (0/34) of placebo treated patients. 



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience with Sensipar

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of Sensipar. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Rash and hypersensitivity reactions (including angioedema and urticaria), and myalgia have been identified as adverse reactions during post approval use of Sensipar. Isolated, idiosyncratic cases of hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia have been reported in Sensipar-treated patients with impaired cardiac function in postmarketing safety surveillance  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hypocalcemia  : Life threatening events and fatal outcomes were reported. Hypocalcemia can prolong QT interval, lower the threshold for seizures, and cause hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia. Monitor serum calcium carefully for the occurrence of hypocalcemia during treatment (  2.3  ,  5.1  ) 
 *   Adynamic  Bone Disease : May develop if iPTH levels are suppressed below 100 pg/mL. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Hepatic Impairment: Cinacalcet exposure (i.e. area under the plasma concentration time curve) is increased in patients with moderate and severe hepatic impairment. Patients should be closely monitored for serum calcium, serum phosphorus, and iPTH levels throughout treatment. (  5.3  ,  8.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypocalcemia



  Sensipar lowers serum calcium and, therefore, patients should be carefully monitored for the occurrence of hypocalcemia during treatment [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  ,  2.2  ,  2.3  ) and Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Life threatening events and fatal outcomes associated with hypocalcemia have been reported in patients treated with Sensipar, including pediatric patients [see Pediatric Use (  8.4  )].      Potential manifestations of hypocalcemia include paresthesias, myalgias, muscle cramping, tetany, and convulsions.



 Sensipar is not indicated for patients with CKD not on dialysis [see Indications and Usage (  1  )]  .  In patients with secondary HPT and CKD not on dialysis, the long term safety and efficacy of Sensipar have not been established. Clinical studies indicate that Sensipar-treated patients with CKD not on dialysis have an increased risk for hypocalcemia compared with Sensipar-treated patients with CKD on dialysis, which may be due to lower baseline calcium levels. In a phase 3 study of 32 weeks duration and including 404 patients with CKD not on dialysis (302 cinacalcet, 102 placebo), in which the median dose for cinacalcet was 60 mg per day at the completion of the study, 80% of Sensipar-treated patients experienced at least one serum calcium value &lt; 8.4 mg/dL compared with 5% of patients receiving placebo.



   QT Prolongation    



  Decreases in serum calcium can also prolong the QT interval, potentially resulting in ventricular arrhythmia. Cases of QT prolongation and ventricular arrhythmia secondary to hypocalcemia have been reported in patients treated with Sensipar.   



  Seizures  



 In clinical studies, seizures (primarily generalized or tonic-clonic) were observed in 1.4% (43/3049) of Sensipar-treated patients and 0.7% (5/687) of placebo-treated patients.  While the basis for the reported difference in seizure rate is not clear, the threshold for seizures is lowered by significant reductions in serum calcium levels. Therefore, serum calcium levels should be closely monitored in patients receiving Sensipar, particularly in patients with a history of a seizure disorder .  



  Hypotension and/or Worsening Heart Failure  



 In postmarketing safety surveillance, isolated, idiosyncratic cases of hypotension, worsening heart failure, and/or arrhythmia have been reported in patients with impaired cardiac function, in which a causal relationship to Sensipar could not be completely excluded and which may be mediated by reductions in serum calcium levels [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )].    



    5.2 Adynamic Bone Disease



  Adynamic bone disease may develop if iPTH levels are suppressed below 100 pg/mL. One clinical study evaluated bone histomorphometry in patients treated with Sensipar for 1 year. Three patients with mild hyperparathyroid bone disease at the beginning of the study developed adynamic bone disease during treatment with Sensipar. Two of these patients had iPTH levels below 100 pg/mL at multiple time points during the study. In three 6-month, phase 3 studies conducted in patients with CKD on dialysis, 11% of patients treated with Sensipar had mean iPTH values below 100 pg/mL during the efficacy-assessment phase. If iPTH levels decrease below 150 pg/mL in patients treated with Sensipar, the dose of Sensipar and/or vitamin D sterols should be reduced or therapy discontinued.



    5.3 Hepatic Impairment



  Cinacalcet exposure, as defined by the Area Under the Plasma Drug Concentration Time Curve (AUC0-infinite), is increased by 2.4 and 4.2 fold in patients with moderate and severe hepatic impairment, respectively.  These patients should be monitored throughout treatment with Sensipar [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.7  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
