<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="serevent" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    LABA, including salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, increase the risk of asthma-related death. Data from a large 28-week placebo-controlled US trial that compared the safety of salmeterol or placebo added to usual asthma therapy showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol. Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1), Clinical Studies (14.1)]  .  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5%) are:



 *    Asthma: Headache, influenza, nasal/sinus congestion, pharyngitis, rhinitis, tracheitis/bronchitis.  (6.1)   
 *    COPD: Cough, headache, musculoskeletal pain, throat irritation, viral respiratory infection.  (6.2)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience in Asthma

    Adult and Adolescent Subjects Aged 12 Years and Older:  Two multicenter, 12-week, placebo-controlled clinical trials evaluated twice-daily doses of SEREVENT DISKUS in subjects aged 12 years and older with asthma. Table 1 reports the incidence of adverse reactions in these 2 trials.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions with SEREVENT DISKUS with &gt;=3 Incidence and More Common than Placebo in Adult and Adolescent Subjects with Asthma 
  Adverse Event                              Percent of Subjects    
  Placebo  (n = 152)                         SEREVENT DISKUS  50 mcg  Twice Daily  (n = 149)    Albuterol Inhalation Aerosol  180 mcg  4 Times Daily  (n = 150)    
  Ear, nose, and throat                                                                                        
                                            Nasal/sinus congestion, pallor            
                                                                                        6           9                       8                             
                                            Rhinitis                                  
                                                                                        4           5                       4                             
  Neurological                                                                                                 
                                            Headache                                  
                                                                                        9           13                      12                            
  Respiratory                                                                                                  
                                            Asthma                                    
                                                                                        1           3                       &lt;1                            
                                            Tracheitis/bronchitis                     
                                                                                        4           7                       3                             
                                            Influenza                                 
                                                                                        2           5                       5                             
          Table 1 includes all events (whether considered drug-related or nondrug-related by the investigator) that occurred at a rate of &gt;=3% in the group treated with SEREVENT DISKUS and were more common than in the placebo group.
 

 Pharyngitis, sinusitis, upper respiratory tract infection, and cough occurred at &gt;=3% but were more common in the placebo group. However, throat irritation has been described at rates exceeding that of placebo in other controlled clinical trials.



   Additional Adverse Reactions:  Other adverse reactions not previously listed, whether considered drug-related or not by the investigators, that were reported more frequently by subjects with asthma treated with SEREVENT DISKUS compared with subjects treated with placebo include the following: contact dermatitis, eczema, localized aches and pains, nausea, oral mucosal abnormality, pain in joint, paresthesia, pyrexia of unknown origin, sinus headache, and sleep disturbance.



   Pediatric Subjects Aged 4 to 11 Years:  Two multicenter, 12-week, controlled trials have evaluated twice-daily doses of SEREVENT DISKUS in subjects aged 4 to 11 years with asthma. Table 2 includes all events (whether considered drug-related or nondrug-related by the investigator) that occurred at a rate of &gt;=3% in the group receiving SEREVENT DISKUS and were more common than in the placebo group.



 Table 2. Adverse Reaction Incidence in Two 12-Week Pediatric Clinical Trials in Subjects with Asthma 
  Adverse Event                               Percent of Subjects    
  Placebo  (n = 215)                          SEREVENT DISKUS  50 mcg  Twice Daily  (n = 211)    Albuterol  Inhalation Aerosol  200 mcg  4 Times Daily  (n = 115)    
  Ear, nose, and throat                                                                                        
                                             Ear signs and symptoms                     
                                                                                          3             4                          9                       
                                             Pharyngitis                                
                                                                                          3             6                          3                       
  Neurological                                                                                                 
                                             Headache                                   
                                                                                          14            17                         20                      
  Respiratory                                                                                                  
                                             Asthma                                     
                                                                                          2             4                          &lt;1                      
  Skin                                                                                                         
                                             Skin rashes                                
                                                                                          3             4                          2                       
                                             Urticaria                                  
                                                                                          0             3                          2                       
          The following events were reported at an incidence of &gt;1% in the salmeterol group and with a higher incidence than in the albuterol and placebo groups: gastrointestinal signs and symptoms, lower respiratory signs and symptoms, photodermatitis, and arthralgia and articular rheumatism.
 

 In clinical trials evaluating concurrent therapy of salmeterol with inhaled corticosteroids, adverse events were consistent with those previously reported for salmeterol, or with events that would be expected with the use of inhaled corticosteroids.



   Laboratory Test Abnormalities:  Elevation of hepatic enzymes was reported in &gt;=1% of subjects in clinical trials. The elevations were transient and did not lead to discontinuation from the trials. In addition, there were no clinically relevant changes noted in glucose or potassium.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease

  Two multicenter, 24-week, placebo-controlled US trials evaluated twice-daily doses of SEREVENT DISKUS in subjects with COPD. For presentation (Table 3), the placebo data from a third trial, identical in design, subject entrance criteria, and overall conduct but comparing fluticasone propionate with placebo, were integrated with the placebo data from these 2 trials (total N = 341 for salmeterol and 576 for placebo).



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions with SEREVENT DISKUS with &gt;=3% Incidence in US Controlled Clinical Trials in Subjects with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Diseasea 
  Adverse Event                                            Percent of Subjects    
  Placebo  (n = 576)                                       SEREVENT DISKUS  50 mcg Twice Daily  (n = 341)    
  Cardiovascular                                                                                            
                                                          Hypertension                                            
                                                                                                                    2               4                                
  Ear, nose, and throat                                                                                     
                                                          Throat irritation                                       
                                                                                                                    6               7                                
                                                          Nasal congestion/blockage                               
                                                                                                                    3               4                                
                                                          Sinusitis                                               
                                                                                                                    2               4                                
                                                          Ear signs and symptoms                                  
                                                                                                                    1               3                                
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                          
                                                          Nausea and vomiting                                     
                                                                                                                    3               3                                
  Lower respiratory                                                                                         
                                                          Cough                                                   
                                                                                                                    4               5                                
                                                          Rhinitis                                                
                                                                                                                    2               4                                
                                                          Viral respiratory infection                             
                                                                                                                    4               5                                
  Musculoskeletal                                                                                           
                                                          Musculoskeletal pain                                    
                                                                                                                    10              12                               
                                                          Muscle cramps and spasms                                
                                                                                                                    1               3                                
  Neurological                                                                                              
                                                          Headache                                                
                                                                                                                    11              14                               
                                                          Dizziness                                               
                                                                                                                    2               4                                
  Average duration of exposure (days)                      128.9           138.5                            
           a  Table 3 includes all events (whether considered drug-related or nondrug-related by the investigator) that occurred at a rate of &gt;=3% in the group receiving SEREVENT DISKUS and were more common in the group receiving SEREVENT DISKUS than in the placebo group.
 

   Additional Adverse Reactions:  Other adverse reactions occurring in the group receiving SEREVENT DISKUS that occurred at a frequency of &gt;=1% and were more common than in the placebo group were as follows: anxiety; arthralgia and articular rheumatism; bone and skeletal pain; candidiasis mouth/throat; dental discomfort and pain; dyspeptic symptoms; edema and swelling; gastrointestinal infections; hyperglycemia; hyposalivation; keratitis and conjunctivitis; lower respiratory signs and symptoms; migraines; muscle pain; muscle stiffness, tightness, and rigidity; musculoskeletal inflammation; pain; and skin rashes.



 Adverse reactions to salmeterol are similar in nature to those seen with other selective beta2-adrenoceptor agonists, e.g., tachycardia; palpitations; immediate hypersensitivity reactions, including urticaria, angioedema, rash, bronchospasm; headache; tremor; nervousness; and paradoxical bronchospasm.



   Laboratory Abnormalities:  There were no clinically relevant changes in these trials. Specifically, no changes in potassium were noted.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of salmeterol. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to either their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or causal connection to salmeterol or a combination of these factors.



 In extensive US and worldwide postmarketing experience with salmeterol, serious exacerbations of asthma, including some that have been fatal, have been reported. In most cases, these have occurred in patients with severe asthma and/or in some patients in whom asthma has been acutely deteriorating  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  , but they have also occurred in a few patients with less severe asthma. It was not possible from these reports to determine whether salmeterol contributed to these events.



   Cardiovascular:  Arrhythmias (including atrial fibrillation, supraventricular tachycardia, extrasystoles) and anaphylaxis.



   Non-Site Specific:  Very rare anaphylactic reaction in patients with severe milk protein allergy.



   Respiratory:  Reports of upper airway symptoms of laryngeal spasm, irritation, or swelling such as stridor or choking; oropharyngeal irritation.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

    WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH  



   Long-acting beta2-adrenergic agonists (LABA), such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT  (r)   DISKUS  (r)  , increase the risk of asthma-related death. Data from a large placebo-controlled US trial that compared the safety of salmeterol with placebo added to usual asthma therapy showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol (13 deaths out of 13,176 subjects treated for 28 weeks on salmeterol versus 3 deaths out of 13,179 subjects on placebo). Currently available data are inadequate to determine whether concurrent use of inhaled corticosteroids or other long-term asthma control drugs mitigates the increased risk of asthma-related death from LABA.  



   Because of this risk, use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma without a concomitant long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid, is contraindicated. Use SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Once asthma control is achieved and maintained, assess the patient at regular intervals and step down therapy (e.g., discontinue SEREVENT DISKUS) if possible without loss of asthma control and maintain the patient on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose inhaled corticosteroids.  



   Pediatric and Adolescent Patients: Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. For pediatric and adolescent patients with asthma who require addition of a LABA to an inhaled corticosteroid, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an inhaled corticosteroid and a LABA should ordinarily be used to ensure adherence with both drugs. In cases where use of a separate long-term asthma control medication (e.g., inhaled corticosteroid) and a LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components. If adherence cannot be assured, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an inhaled corticosteroid and a LABA is recommended.  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Long-acting beta2-adrenergic agonists (LABA), such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, increase the risk of asthma-related death. A US trial showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol (13 deaths out of 13,176 subjects treated for 28 weeks on salmeterol versus 3 out of 13,179 subjects on placebo). Currently available data are inadequate to determine whether concurrent use of inhaled corticosteroids or other long-term asthma control drugs mitigates the increased risk of asthma-related death from LABA. (5.1) 
 *  Prescribe SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Once asthma control is achieved and maintained, assess the patient at regular intervals and step down therapy (e.g., discontinue SEREVENT DISKUS) if possible without loss of asthma control and maintain the patient on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose inhaled corticosteroids. (1.1, 5.1) 
 *  Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    LABA increase the risk of asthma-related death and asthma-related hospitalizations. Prescribe for asthma only as concomitant therapy with an inhaled corticosteroid.  (5.1)   
 *    Do not initiate in acutely deteriorating asthma or COPD. Do not use to treat acute symptoms.  (5.2)   
 *    Not a substitute for corticosteroids. Patients with asthma must take a concomitant inhaled corticosteroid.  (5.3)   
 *    Do not use in combination with an additional medicine containing a LABA because of risk of overdose.  (5.4)   
 *    If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs, discontinue SEREVENT DISKUS and institute alternative therapy.  (5.5)   
 *    Use with caution in patients with cardiovascular or central nervous system disorders because of beta-adrenergic stimulation.  (5.6)   
 *    Use with caution in patients with convulsive disorders, thyrotoxicosis, diabetes mellitus, and ketoacidosis.  (5.9)   
 *    Be alert to hypokalemia and hyperglycemia.  (5.10)   
    
 

   5.1 Asthma-Related Death



   LABA, such as salmeterol, the active ingredient in SEREVENT DISKUS, increase the risk of asthma-related death. Currently available data are inadequate to determine whether concurrent use of inhaled corticosteroids or other long-term asthma control drugs mitigates the increased risk of asthma-related death from LABA.  



  Because of this risk, use of SEREVENT DISKUS for the treatment of asthma without concomitant use of a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid, is contraindicated. Use SEREVENT DISKUS only as additional therapy for patients with asthma who are currently taking but are inadequately controlled on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Once asthma control is achieved and maintained, assess the patient at regular intervals and step down therapy (e.g., discontinue SEREVENT DISKUS) if possible without loss of asthma control and maintain the patient on a long-term asthma control medication, such as an inhaled corticosteroid. Do not use SEREVENT DISKUS for patients whose asthma is adequately controlled on low- or medium-dose inhaled corticosteroids.  



  Pediatric and Adolescent Patients:   Available data from controlled clinical trials suggest that LABA increase the risk of asthma-related hospitalization in pediatric and adolescent patients. For pediatric and adolescent patients with asthma who require addition of a LABA to an inhaled corticosteroid, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an inhaled corticosteroid and a LABA should ordinarily be used to ensure adherence with both drugs. In cases where use of a separate long-term asthma control medication (e.g., inhaled corticosteroid) and a LABA is clinically indicated, appropriate steps must be taken to ensure adherence with both treatment components. If adherence cannot be assured, a fixed-dose combination product containing both an inhaled corticosteroid and a LABA is recommended.  



 The Salmeterol Multi-center Asthma Research Trial (SMART) was a large 28-week placebo-controlled US trial comparing the safety of salmeterol (SEREVENT  (r)  Inhalation Aerosol) with placebo, each added to usual asthma therapy, that showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in subjects receiving salmeterol [see Clinical Studies (14.1)]  . Given the similar basic mechanisms of action of beta2-agonists, the findings seen in the SMART trial are considered a class effect.



 A 16-week clinical trial performed in the United Kingdom, the Salmeterol Nationwide Surveillance (SNS) trial, showed results similar to the SMART trial. In the SNS trial, the rate of asthma-related death was numerically, though not statistically significantly, greater in subjects with asthma treated with salmeterol (42 mcg twice daily) than those treated with albuterol (180 mcg 4 times daily) added to usual asthma therapy.



  The SNS and SMART trials enrolled subjects with asthma. No trials have been conducted that were primarily designed to determine whether the rate of death in patients with COPD is increased by LABA.  



    5.2 Deterioration of Disease and Acute Episodes



  SEREVENT DISKUS should not be initiated in patients during rapidly deteriorating or potentially life-threatening episodes of asthma or COPD. SEREVENT DISKUS has not been studied in subjects with acutely deteriorating asthma or COPD. The initiation of SEREVENT DISKUS in this setting is not appropriate.



 Serious acute respiratory events, including fatalities, have been reported when salmeterol has been initiated in patients with significantly worsening or acutely deteriorating asthma. In most cases, these have occurred in patients with severe asthma (e.g., patients with a history of corticosteroid dependence, low pulmonary function, intubation, mechanical ventilation, frequent hospitalizations, previous life-threatening acute asthma exacerbations) and in some patients with acutely deteriorating asthma (e.g., patients with significantly increasing symptoms; increasing need for inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonists; decreasing response to usual medications; increasing need for systemic corticosteroids; recent emergency room visits; deteriorating lung function). However, these events have occurred in a few patients with less severe asthma as well. It was not possible from these reports to determine whether salmeterol contributed to these events.



 Increasing use of inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonists is a marker of deteriorating asthma. In this situation, the patient requires immediate reevaluation with reassessment of the treatment regimen, giving special consideration to the possible need for adding additional inhaled corticosteroid or initiating systemic corticosteroids. Patients should not use more than 1 inhalation twice daily of SEREVENT DISKUS.



 SEREVENT DISKUS should not be used for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm. An inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist, not SEREVENT DISKUS, should be used to relieve acute symptoms such as shortness of breath. When prescribing SEREVENT DISKUS, the healthcare provider should also prescribe an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist (e.g., albuterol) for treatment of acute symptoms.



 When beginning treatment with SEREVENT DISKUS, patients who have been taking oral or inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonists on a regular basis (e.g., 4 times a day) should be instructed to discontinue the regular use of these drugs.



    5.3 SEREVENT DISKUS is Not a Substitute for Corticosteroids



  There are no data demonstrating that SEREVENT DISKUS has a clinical anti-inflammatory effect such as that associated with corticosteroids. When initiating and throughout treatment with SEREVENT DISKUS in patients receiving oral or inhaled corticosteroids for treatment of asthma, patients must continue taking a suitable dosage of corticosteroids to maintain clinical stability even if they feel better as a result of initiating SEREVENT DISKUS. Any change in corticosteroid dosage should be made ONLY after clinical evaluation.



    5.4 Excessive Use of SEREVENT DISKUS and Use with Other Long-Acting Beta2-Agonists



  SEREVENT DISKUS should not be used more often than recommended, at higher doses than recommended, or in conjunction with other medicines containing LABA, as an overdose may result. Clinically significant cardiovascular effects and fatalities have been reported in association with excessive use of inhaled sympathomimetic drugs. Patients using SEREVENT DISKUS should not use another medicine containing a LABA (e.g., formoterol fumarate, arformoterol tartrate, indacaterol) for any reason.



    5.5 Paradoxical Bronchospasm and Upper Airway Symptoms



  As with other inhaled medicines, SEREVENT DISKUS can produce paradoxical bronchospasm, which may be life threatening. If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs following dosing with SEREVENT DISKUS, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator. SEREVENT DISKUS should be discontinued immediately, and alternative therapy should be instituted. Upper airway symptoms of laryngeal spasm, irritation, or swelling, such as stridor and choking, have been reported in patients receiving SEREVENT DISKUS.



    5.6 Cardiovascular and Central Nervous System Effects



  Excessive beta-adrenergic stimulation has been associated with seizures, angina, hypertension or hypotension, tachycardia with rates up to 200 beats/min, arrhythmias, nervousness, headache, tremor, palpitation, nausea, dizziness, fatigue, malaise, and insomnia [see Overdosage (10)]  . Therefore, SEREVENT DISKUS, like all products containing sympathomimetic amines, should be used with caution in patients with cardiovascular disorders, especially coronary insufficiency, cardiac arrhythmias, and hypertension.



 Salmeterol can produce a clinically significant cardiovascular effect in some patients as measured by pulse rate, blood pressure, and/or symptoms. Although such effects are uncommon after administration of salmeterol at recommended doses, if they occur, the drug may need to be discontinued. In addition, beta-agonists have been reported to produce electrocardiogram (ECG) changes, such as flattening of the T wave, prolongation of the QTc interval, and ST segment depression. The clinical significance of these findings is unknown. Large doses of inhaled or oral salmeterol (12 to 20 times the recommended dose) have been associated with clinically significant prolongation of the QTc interval, which has the potential for producing ventricular arrhythmias. Fatalities have been reported in association with excessive use of inhaled sympathomimetic drugs.



    5.7 Immediate Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Immediate hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., urticaria, angioedema, rash, bronchospasm, hypotension), including anaphylaxis, may occur after administration of SEREVENT DISKUS. There have been reports of anaphylactic reactions in patients with severe milk protein allergy after inhalation of powder products containing lactose; therefore, patients with severe milk protein allergy should not use SEREVENT DISKUS [see Contraindications (4)]  .



    5.8 Drug Interactions with Strong Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors



  The use of strong cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir, ketoconazole, telithromycin) with SEREVENT DISKUS is not recommended because increased cardiovascular adverse effects may occur [see Drug Interactions (7.1), Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  .



    5.9 Coexisting Conditions



  SEREVENT DISKUS, like all medicines containing sympathomimetic amines, should be used with caution in patients with convulsive disorders or thyrotoxicosis and in those who are unusually responsive to sympathomimetic amines. Doses of the related beta2-adrenoceptor agonist albuterol, when administered intravenously, have been reported to aggravate preexisting diabetes mellitus and ketoacidosis.



    5.10 Hypokalemia and Hyperglycemia



  Beta-adrenergic agonist medicines may produce significant hypokalemia in some patients, possibly through intracellular shunting, which has the potential to produce adverse cardiovascular effects [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  . The decrease in serum potassium is usually transient, not requiring supplementation. Clinically significant and dose-related changes in blood glucose and/or serum potassium were seen infrequently during clinical trials with SEREVENT DISKUS at recommended doses.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
