<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="seroquel0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and twice placebo) in decreasing frequency are: somnolence, dry mouth, constipation, dizziness, increased appetite, dyspepsia, weight gain, fatigue, dysarthria, and nasal congestion. (6.1)



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The information below is derived from a clinical trial database for SEROQUEL XR consisting of approximately 3400 patients exposed to SEROQUEL XR for the treatment of Schizophrenia, Bipolar Disorder, and Major Depressive Disorder in placebo-controlled trials. This experience corresponds to approximately 1020.1 patient-years. Adverse reactions were assessed by collecting adverse reactions, results of physical examinations, vital signs, body weights, laboratory analyses and ECG results.



 Adverse reactions during exposure were obtained by general inquiry and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse reactions without first grouping similar types of reactions into a smaller number of standardized event categories. In the tables and tabulations that follow, standard MedDRA terminology has been used to classify reported adverse reactions.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse reaction of the type listed. An event was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation.



 Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials



   Schizophrenia:  There was no difference in the incidence and type of adverse reactions associated with discontinuation (6.4% (61/951) for SEROQUEL XR vs. 7.5% (24/319) for placebo) in a pool of controlled Schizophrenia trials. There were no adverse reactions leading to discontinuation that occurred at an incidence of &gt;= 2% for SEROQUEL XR in Schizophrenia trials.



   Bipolar Disorder:  



   Mania:  In a single clinical trial in patients with bipolar mania, 4.6% (7/151) of patients on SEROQUEL XR discontinued due to an adverse reaction compared to 8.1% (13/160) on placebo. There were no adverse reactions leading to discontinuation that occurred at an incidence of &gt;= 2% for SEROQUEL XR in the Bipolar Mania trial.



   Depression:  In a single clinical trial in patients with bipolar depression, 14% (19/137) of patients on SEROQUEL XR discontinued due to an adverse reaction compared to 4% (5/140) on placebo. Somnolence  *  was the only adverse reaction leading to discontinuation that occurred at an incidence of &gt;= 2% in SEROQUEL XR in the Bipolar Depression trial.



   *  The adverse reaction term "somnolence" includes both "somnolence" and "sedation."



   MDD, Adjunctive Therapy:  In adjunctive therapy clinical trials in patients with MDD, 12.1% (76/627) of patients on SEROQUEL XR discontinued due to adverse reaction compared to 1.9% (6/309) on placebo. Somnolence  *  was the only adverse reaction leading to discontinuation that occurred at an incidence of &gt;= 2% in SEROQUEL XR in MDD trials.



 Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials:



 In short-term placebo-controlled studies for schizophrenia the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of SEROQUEL XR (incidence of 5% or greater) and observed at a rate on SEROQUEL XR at least twice that of placebo were somnolence (25%), dry mouth (12%), dizziness (10%), and dyspepsia (5%).



 Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More Among SEROQUEL XR Treated Patients in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials



 Table 11 enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred during acute therapy of schizophrenia (up to 6 weeks) in 1% or more in patients treated with SEROQUEL XR (doses ranging from 300 to 800 mg/day) where the incidence in patients treated with SEROQUEL XR was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 Table 11: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence in 6-Week Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials for the Treatment of Schizophrenia 
                                                     
 Body System/Preferred Term  Placebo          SEROQUEL XR       
                  (n=319)          (n=951)           
  
  Cardiac Disorders    
  Tachycardia      1%               3%               
  Eye Disorders    
  Vision blurred    1%               2%               
  Gastrointestinal Disorders    
  Dry Mouth        1%               12%              
  Constipation     5%               6%               
  Dyspepsia        2%               5%               
  Toothache        0%               2%               
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    
  Fatigue          2%               3%               
  Irritability     0%               1%               
  Pyrexia          0%               1%               
  Investigations    
  Heart Rate Increased    1%               4%               
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders    
  Increased Appetite    0%               2%               
  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders    
  Muscle Spasms    1%               2%               
  Nervous System Disorders    
  Somnolence       10%              25%              
  Dizziness        4%               10%              
  Tremor           1%               2%               
  Akathisia        1%               2%               
  Extrapyramidal Symptoms    5%               8%               
  Psychiatric Disorders    
  Anxiety          1%               2%               
  Schizophrenia    1%               2%               
  Restlessness     1%               2%               
  Vascular Disorders    
  Orthostatic Hypotension    5%               7%               
  Hypotension      1%               3%               
      In a 3-week, placebo-controlled study in bipolar mania the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of SEROQUEL XR (incidence of 5% or greater) and observed at a rate on SEROQUEL XR at least twice that of placebo were somnolence (50%), dry mouth (34%), dizziness (10%), constipation (10%), weight gain (7%), dysarthria (5%), and nasal congestion (5%).
 

 Table 12 enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred during acute therapy of bipolar mania (up to 3 weeks) in 1% or more of patients treated with SEROQUEL XR (doses ranging from 400 to 800 mg/day) where the incidence in patients treated with SEROQUEL XR was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 Table 12: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in a 3-Week Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial for the Treatment of Bipolar Mania 
                                                     
 Body System/Preferred Term  PLACEBO          SEROQUEL XR       
                  (n=160)          (n=151)           
  
  Cardiac Disorders    
  Tachycardia      1%               2%               
  Eye Disorders    
  Vision blurred    1%               2%               
  Gastrointestinal Disorders    
  Dry Mouth        7%               34%              
  Constipation     3%               10%              
  Dyspepsia        4%               7%               
  Toothache        1%               3%               
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    
  Fatigue          4%               7%               
  Sluggishness     1%               2%               
  Pain             0%               1%               
  Investigations    
  Weight Gain      1%               7%               
  Heart Rate Increased    0%               3%               
  Injury, Poisoning And Procedural Complications    
  Contusion        0%               1%               
  Metabolism And Nutrition Disorders    
  Increased Appetite    2%               4%               
  Nervous System Disorders    
  Extrapyramidal Symptoms    4%               7%               
  Somnolence       12%              50%              
  Dizziness        4%               10%              
  Dysarthria       0%               5%               
  Lethargy         1%               2%               
  Postural Dizziness    0%               1%               
  Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders    
  Back Pain        2%               3%               
  Arthralgia       0%               1%               
  Psychiatric Disorders    
  Abnormal Dreams    0%               3%               
  Bipolar I Disorder    0%               1%               
  Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders    
  Nasal Congestion    1%               5%               
  Dry Throat       0%               1%               
  Vascular Disorders    
  Orthostatic Hypotension    0%               3%               
      In the 8-week placebo-controlled bipolar depression study, the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of SEROQUEL XR (incidence of 5% or greater) and observed at a rate on SEROQUEL XR at least twice that of placebo were somnolence (52%), dry mouth (37%), increased appetite (12%), weight gain (7%), dyspepsia (7%), and fatigue (6%).
 

 Table 13: enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred during acute therapy of bipolar depression (up to 8 weeks) in 1% or more of patients treated with SEROQUEL XR 300 mg/day where the incidence in patients treated with SEROQUEL XR was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 Table 13: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in an 8-Week Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial for the Treatment of Bipolar Depression 
                                                     
 Body System/Preferred Term  Placebo          SEROQUEL XR       
                  (n=140)          (n=137)           
  
  Ear And Labyrinth Disorders    
  Ear Pain         1%               2%               
  Gastrointestinal Disorders    
  Dry Mouth        7%               37%              
  Constipation     6%               8%               
  Dyspepsia        1%               7%               
  Toothache        0%               3%               
  Abdominal Distension    0%               1%               
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    
  Fatigue          2%               6%               
  Irritability     3%               4%               
  Immune System Disorders                                      
  Seasonal Allergy    1%               2%               
  Infections And Infestations    
  Viral Gastroenteritis    1%               4%               
  Urinary Tract Infection    0%               2%               
  Sinusitis        1%               2%               
  Investigations    
  Weight Gain      1%               7%               
  Heart Rate Increased    0%               2%               
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorder    
  Increased Appetite    6%               12%              
  Decreased Appetite    1%               2%               
  Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders    
  Arthralgia       1%               4%               
  Back Pain        1%               3%               
  Muscle Spasms    1%               3%               
  Myalgia          1%               2%               
  Neck Pain        0%               2%               
  Nervous System Disorders    
  Somnolence       13%              52%              
  Extrapyramidal Symptoms    1%               4%               
  Dizziness        11%              13%              
  Paraesthesia     2%               3%               
  Disturbance in Attention    1%               2%               
  Dysarthria       0%               2%               
  Akathisia        0%               2%               
  Hypersomnia      0%               2%               
  Mental Impairment    0%               2%               
  Migraine         1%               2%               
  Restless Legs Syndrome    1%               2%               
  Sinus Headache    1%               2%               
  Psychiatric Disorders    
  Abnormal Dreams    0%               3%               
  Anxiety          1%               2%               
  Confusional State    0%               2%               
  Disorientation    0%               2%               
  Libido Decreased    1%               2%               
  Renal And Urinary Disorders    
  Pollakiuria      1%               2%               
  Respiratory, Thoracic And Mediastinal Disorders    
  Sinus Congestion    1%               2%               
  Skin And Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders    
  Hyperhidrosis    1%               2%               
  Vascular Disorders    
  Orthostatic Hypotension    1%               2%               
      In the 6-week placebo-controlled fixed dose adjunctive therapy clinical trials, for MDD, the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of SEROQUEL XR (incidence of 5% or greater and observed at a rate on SEROQUEL XR and at least twice that of placebo) were somnolence (150 mg: 37%; 300 mg: 43%), dry mouth (150 mg: 27%; 300 mg: 40%), fatigue (150 mg: 14%; 300 mg: 11%), constipation (300 mg only: 11%) and weight increased (300 mg only: 5%).
 

 Table 14 enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred during short-term adjunctive therapy of MDD (up to 6 weeks) in 1% or more of patients treated with SEROQUEL XR (at doses of either 150 mg or 300 mg/day) where the incidence in patients treated with SEROQUEL XR was greater than the incidence in placebo-treated patients.



 Table 14: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Adjunctive Therapy Clinical Trials for the Treatment of MDD by Fixed Dose 
                                                     
 Body System/Preferred Term  Placebo(n=309)   SEROQUEL XR 150 mg(n=315)   
  
  Ear And Labyrinth Disorders    
  Vertigo          1%               2%               
  Eye Disorders    
  Vision Blurred    1%               2%               
  Gastrointestinal Disorders    
  Dry Mouth        8%               27%              
  Constipation     4%               6%               
  Nausea           7%               7%               
  Dyspepsia        2%               2%               
  Abdominal Distension    0%               0%               
  Vomiting         1%               3%               
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions    
  Fatigue          4%               14%              
  Irritability     3%               4%               
  Chills           0%               1%               
  Infections And Infestations    
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection    2%               3%               
  Influenza        0%               2%               
  Injury, Poisoning And Procedural Complications    
  Fall             1%               2%               
  Investigations    
  Weight Increased    0%               3%               
  Metabolism And Nutrition Disorders    
  Increased Appetite    3%               3%               
  Musculoskeletal And Connective Tissue Disorders    
  Back pain        1%               3%               
  Muscle Spasms    1%               2%               
  Nervous System Disorders    
  Somnolence       9%               37%              
  Dizziness        7%               11%              
  Extrapyramidal Symptoms    4%               4%               
  Hypersomnia      0%               1%               
  Dysarthria       0%               1%               
  Dysgeusia        0%               1%               
  Lethargy         1%               2%               
  Akathisia        1%               2%               
  Psychiatric Disorders    
  Abnormal Dreams    1%               2%               
  Anxiety          1%               2%               
  Restlessness     1%               1%               
  Libido Decreased    0%               0%               
  Depression       1%               2%               
      
 

 Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 5% or More Among SEROQUEL XR Treated Patients in Long-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials



 In a longer-term placebo-controlled trial, adult patients with schizophrenia who remained clinically stable on SEROQUEL XR during open-label treatment for at least 4 months were randomized to placebo (n=103) or to continue on their current SEROQUEL XR (n=94) for up to 12 months of observation for possible relapse, the adverse reactions reported were generally consistent with those reported in the short-term, placebo-controlled trials. Insomnia (8.5%) and headache (7.4%) were the only adverse events reported by 5% or more patients.



 Adverse Reactions that occurred in &lt;5% of patients and were considered drug-related (incidence greater than placebo and consistent with known pharmacology of drug class) in order of decreasing frequency:



 heart rate increased, hypotension, weight increased, tremor, akathisia, increased appetite, blurred vision, postural dizziness, pyrexia, dysarthria, dystonia, drooling, syncope, tardive dyskinesia, dysphagia, leukopenia, and rash.



 Adverse Reactions in clinical trials with quetiapine and not listed elsewhere in the label:



 nightmares, peripheral edema, rhinitis, eosinophilia, hypersensitivity, elevations in gamma-GT levels, and elevations in serum creatine phosphokinase (not associated with NMS).



 Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS):



   Dystonia  



   Class Effect:  Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



 Four methods were used to measure EPS: (1) Simpson-Angus total score (mean change from baseline) which evaluates Parkinsonism and akathisia, (2) Barnes Akathisia Rating Scale (BARS) Global Assessment Score, (3) incidence of spontaneous complaints of EPS (akathisia, akinesia, cogwheel rigidity, extrapyramidal syndrome, hypertonia, hypokinesia, neck rigidity, and tremor), and (4) use of anticholinergic medications to treat emergent EPS.



   Adults:  In placebo-controlled clinical trials with quetiapine, utilizing doses up to 800 mg per day, the incidence of any adverse reactions potentially related to EPS ranged from 8% to 11% for quetiapine and 4% to 11% for placebo.



 In three-arm placebo-controlled clinical trials for the treatment of schizophrenia, utilizing doses between 300 mg and 800 mg of SEROQUEL XR, the incidence of any adverse reactions potentially related to EPS was 8% for SEROQUEL XR and 8% for SEROQUEL (without evidence of being dose related), and 5% in the placebo group. In these studies, the incidence of the individual adverse reactions (akathisia, extrapyramidal disorder, tremor, dyskinesia, dystonia, restlessness, and muscle rigidity) was generally low and did not exceed 3% for any treatment group.



 At the end of treatment, the mean change from baseline in SAS total score and BARS Global Assessment score was similar across the treatment groups. The use of concomitant anticholinergic medications was infrequent and similar across the treatment groups. The incidence of extrapyramidal symptoms was consistent with that seen with the profile of SEROQUEL in schizophrenia patients.



   Table 15: Adverse Experiences Associated with Extrapyramidal Symptoms in Placebo-controlled Clinical Trials for Schizophrenia  




  Preferred term    Placebo  (N=319)    SEROQUEL XR 300 mg/day  (N=91)    SEROQUEL XR 400 mg/day  (N=227)    SEROQUEL XR 600 mg/day  (N=310)    SEROQUEL XR 800 mg/day  (N=323)    All Doses  (N=951)    
                   n                %                n                %                n                %                n                %                n                %                n                %                
  Dystonic event    0                0.0              3                3.3              0                0.0              4                1.3              1                0.3              8                0.8              
  Parkinsonism     4                1.3              1                1.1              3                1.3              11               3.6              7                2.2              22               2.3              
  Akathisia        4                1.3              0                0.0              3                1.3              7                2.3              7                2.2              17               1.8              
  Dyskinetic event    2                0.6              2                2.2              1                0.4              1                0.3              1                0.3              5                0.5              
  Other extrapyramidal event    7                2.2              3                3.3              4                1.8              7                2.3              12               3.7              26               2.7              
      
 

 In a placebo-controlled clinical trial for the treatment of bipolar mania, utilizing the dose range of 400-800 mg/day of SEROQUEL XR, the incidence of any adverse reactions potentially related to EPS was 6.6% for SEROQUEL XR and 3.8% in the placebo group. In this study, the incidence of the individual adverse reactions (akathisia, extrapyramidal disorder, tremor, dystonia, restlessness, and cogwheel rigidity) did not exceed 2.0% for any adverse reaction.



   Table 16: Adverse Experiences Associated with Extrapyramidal Symptoms in a Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial for Bipolar Mania  



  
  Preferred term    Placebo  (N=160)    SEROQUEL XR  (N=151)    
  n                      %                n                %          
  Dystonic event          0               0.0               1               0.7         
  Parkinsonism           3               1.9               4               2.7         
  Akathisia              1               0.6               2               1.3         
  Other extrapyramidal event          2               1.3               3               2.0         
      
 

 In a placebo-controlled clinical trial for the treatment of bipolar depression utilizing 300 mg of SEROQUEL XR, the incidence of any adverse reactions potentially related to EPS was 4.4% for SEROQUEL XR and 0.7% in the placebo group. In this study, the incidence of the individual adverse reactions (akathisia, extrapyramidal disorder, tremor, dystonia, hypertonia) did not exceed 1.5% for any individual adverse reaction.



   Table 17: Adverse Experiences Associated with Extrapyramidal Symptoms in a Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial for Bipolar Depression  



  
  Preferred term    Placebo  (N=140)    SEROQUEL XR  (N=137)    
  n                %                n                %                
  Dystonic event    0                0.0              2                1.5              
  Parkinsonism     1                0.7              1                0.7              
  Akathisia        0                0.0              2                1.5              
  Other extrapyramidal event    0                0.0              1                0.7              
      In two placebo-controlled short-term adjunctive therapy clinical trials for the treatment of MDD utilizing between 150 mg and 300 mg of SEROQUEL XR, the incidence of any adverse reactions potentially related to EPS was 5.1% for SEROQUEL XR and 4.2% for the placebo group.
 

 Table 18 shows the percentage of patients experiencing adverse reactions potentially associated with EPS in adjunct clinical trials for MDD by dose:



   Table 18: Adverse Reactions Potentially Associated with EPS in MDD Trials by Dose, Adjunctive Therapy Clinical Trials (6 weeks duration)  



  
  Preferred term    Placebo  (N=309)    SEROQUEL XR 150 mg/day  (N=315)    SEROQUEL XR 300 mg/day  (N=312)    All Doses  (N=627)    
  n                      %                n                %                n                %                n                %          
  Dystonic event          0               0.0               1               0.3               0               0.0               1               0.2         
  Parkinsonism           5               1.6               3               1.0               4               1.3               7               1.1         
  Akathisia              3               1.0               5               1.6               8               2.6              13               2.1         
  Dyskinetic event          0               0.0               0               0.0               1               0.3               1               0.2         
  Other extrapyramidal event          5               1.6               5               1.6               7               2.2              12               1.9         
      
 

   Children and Adolescents:  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years. In a short-term placebo-controlled monotherapy trial in adolescent patients with schizophrenia (6-week duration), the aggregated incidence of extrapyramidal symptoms was 12.9% for SEROQUEL and 5.3% for placebo, though the incidence of the individual adverse events (eg, akathisia, tremor, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, restlessness, psychomotor hyperactivity, muscle rigidity, dyskinesia) did not exceed 4.1% in any treatment group. In a short-term placebo-controlled monotherapy trial in children and adolescent patients with bipolar mania (3-week duration), the aggregated incidence of extrapyramidal symptoms was 3.6% for SEROQUEL and 1.1% for placebo.



 Table 19 below presents a listing of patients with adverse experiences potentially associated with EPS in the short-term placebo-controlled monotherapy trial in adolescent patients with schizophrenia (6-week duration).



   Table 19 Adverse experiences potentially associated with EPS in the short-term placebo-controlled monotherapy trial in adolescent patients with schizophrenia (6-week duration).  



  
  Preferred term    Placebo  (N=75)    SEROQUEL 400 mg/day  (N=73)    SEROQUEL 800 mg/day  (N=74)    All SEROQUEL  (N=147)    
  n                :%               n                %                n                %                n                %                
  Dystonic event    0                0.0              2                2.7              0                0.0              2                1.4              
  Parkinsonism     2                2.7              4                5.5              4                5.4              8                5.4              
  Akathisia        3                4.0              3                4.1              4                5.4              7                4.8              
  Dyskinetic event    0                0.0              2                2.7              0                0.0              2                1.4              
  Other extrapyramidal event    0                0.0              2                2.7              2                2.7              4                2.7              
      Table 20 below presents a listing of patients with Adverse Experiences potentially associated with EPS in a short-term placebo-controlled monotherapy trial in children and adolescent patients with bipolar mania (3-week duration)
 

 Table 20: Adverse experiences potentially associated with EPS in a short-term placebo-controlled monotherapy trial in children and adolescent patients with bipolar mania (3-week duration) 
  Preferred term    Placebo  (N=90)    SEROQUEL 400 mg/day  (N=95)    SEROQUEL 600 mg/day  (N=98)    All SEROQUEL  (N=193)    
  n                %                n                %                n                %                n                %                
  Parkinsonism     1                1.1              2                2.1              1                1.0              3                1.6              
  Akathisia        0                0.0              1                1.0              1                1.0              2                1.0              
  Other extrapyramidal event    0                0.0              1                1.1              1                1.0              2                1.0              
      
 

   Children and Adolescents:  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years. In acute placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescent patients with schizophrenia (6-week duration) or bipolar mania (3-week duration), the incidence of increased appetite was 7.6% for SEROQUEL compared to 2.4% for placebo. In a 26-week open-label study that enrolled patients from the above two pediatric trials, the incidence of increased appetite was 7% for SEROQUEL.



 



   6.2 Vital Signs and Laboratory Values

  Hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia, weight gain, orthostatic hypotension and changes in thyroid hormone levels have been reported with quetiapine. Increases in blood pressure have also been reported with quetiapine in children and adolescents [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.4, 5.5, 5.6, 5.8, 5.9 and 5.14)].



 Laboratory Changes:



 Neutrophil Counts



 In three-arm SEROQUEL XR placebo-controlled monotherapy clinical trials, among patients with a baseline neutrophil count &gt;= 1.5 x 10  9  /L, the incidence of at least one occurrence of neutrophil count &lt;1.5 x 10  9  /L was 1.5% in patients treated with SEROQUEL XR and 1.5% for SEROQUEL, compared to 0.8% in placebo-treated patients.



 In placebo-controlled monotherapy clinical trials involving 3368 patients on quetiapine fumarate and 1515 on placebo, the incidence of at least one occurrence of neutrophil count &lt;1.0 x 10  9  /L among patients with a normal baseline neutrophil count and at least one available follow up laboratory measurement was 0.3% (10/2967) in patients treated with quetiapine, compared to 0.1% (2/1349) in patients treated with placebo. Patients with a pre-existing low WBC or a history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and should discontinue SEROQUEL XR at the first sign of a decline in WBC in absence of other causative factors [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.10)].



 Decreased Hemoglobin



 In short-term placebo-controlled trials, decreases in hemoglobin to &lt;= 13 g/dL males, &lt;= 12 g/dL females on at least one occasion occurred in 8.3% (594/7155) of quetiapine-treated patients compared to 6.2% (219/3536) of patients treated with placebo. In a database of controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials, decreases in hemoglobin to &lt;= 13 g/dL males, &lt;= 12 g/dL females on at least one occasion occurred in 11% (2277/20729) of quetiapine-treated patients.



 ECG Changes:



 2.5% of SEROQUEL XR patients, and 2.3% of placebo patients, had tachycardia (&gt;120 bpm) at any time during the trials. SEROQUEL XR was associated with a mean increase in heart rate, assessed by ECG, of 6.3 beats per minute compared to a mean increase of 0.4 beats per minute for placebo. This is consistent with the rates for SEROQUEL. The incidence of adverse reactions of tachycardia was 1.9% for SEROQUEL XR compared to 0.5% for placebo. SEROQUEL use was associated with a mean increase in heart rate, assessed by ECG, of 7 beats per minute compared to a mean increase of 1 beat per minute among placebo patients. The slight tendency for tachycardia may be related to quetiapine's potential for inducing orthostatic changes [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)].



   Children and Adolescents:  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients. In the acute (6-week) schizophrenia trial in adolescents, potentially clinically significant increases in heart rate (&gt; 110 bpm) occurred in 5.2% of patients receiving SEROQUEL 400 mg and 8.5% of patients receiving SEROQUEL 800 mg compared to 0% of patients receiving placebo. Mean increases in heart rate were 3.8 bpm and 11.2 bpm for SEROQUEL 400 mg and 800 mg groups, respectively, compared to a decrease of 3.3 bpm in the placebo group [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)].



 In the acute (3-week) bipolar mania trial in children and adolescents, potentially clinically significant increases in heart rate (&gt; 110 bpm) occurred in 1.1% of patients receiving SEROQUEL 400 mg and 2.4% of patients receiving SEROQUEL 600 mg compared to 0% of patients receiving placebo. Mean increases in heart rate were 12.8 bpm and 13.4 bpm for SEROQUEL 400 mg and 600 mg groups, respectively, compared to a decrease of 1.7 bpm in the placebo group [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)].



   6.3 Post Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions were identified during post approval use of SEROQUEL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions reported since market introduction which were temporally related to SEROQUEL therapy include anaphylactic reaction and galactorrhea.



 Other adverse reactions reported since market introduction, which were temporally related to SEROQUEL therapy, but not necessarily causally related, include the following: agranulocytosis, cardiomyopathy, hyponatremia, myocarditis, rhabdomyolysis, syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH), Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS), and decreased platelets.



 In post-marketing clinical trials, elevations in total cholesterol (predominantly LDL cholesterol), dyspnea, palpitations, somnambulism (and other related events) and hypothermia have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

  WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS

    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of seventeen placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks) largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. SEROQUEL XR is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [  see Warnings and Precautions    (5.1)].  



   SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS  



   Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of SEROQUEL XR or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. SEROQUEL XR is not approved for use in pediatric patients [  see Warnings and Precautions    (5.2)].   



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS       See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Antipsychotic drugs are associated with an increased risk of death. (5.1) 
 *  Quetiapine is not approved for elderly patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis. (5.1) 
      WARNING:  SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    
 

 *  Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder and other psychiatric disorders. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *    Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Antipsychotic drugs, including quetiapine, are associated with an increased risk of death; causes of death are variable. (5.1)



 
 *    Suicidality and Antidepressant Drugs: Increased the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder and other psychiatric disorders. (5.2)



 
 *    Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS): Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring. (5.3)



 
 *    Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus (DM): Ketoacidosis, hyperosmolar coma and death have been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics, including quetiapine. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. When starting treatment, patients with diabetes or risk factors for diabetes should undergo blood glucose testing before and during treatment. (5.4)



 
 *    Hyperlipidemia: Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed. Increases in total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol and triglycerides and decreases in HDL-cholesterol have been reported in clinical trials. Appropriate clinical monitoring is recommended, including fasting blood lipid testing at the beginning of, and periodically, during treatment. (5.5)



 
 *    Weight Gain: Patients should receive regular monitoring of weight. (5.6)



 
 *    Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue if clinically appropriate. (5.7)



 
 *    Orthostatic Hypotension: Associated dizziness, tachycardia and syncope may occur especially during the initial dose titration period. Use in caution in patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease. (5.8)



 
 *    Increased Blood Pressure in Children and Adolescents: Blood pressure should be measured at the beginning of, and periodically during treatment in children and adolescents. SEROQUEL XR has not been evaluated in pediatric patients. (5.9)



 
 *    Leukopenia, Neutropenia and Agranulocytosis: have been reported with atypical antipsychotics including SEROQUEL XR. Patients with a pre-existing low white cell count (WBC) or a history of leukopenia/neutropenia should have complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of treatment and should discontinue SEROQUEL XR at the first sign of a decline in WBC in absence of other causative factors. (5.10)



 
 *    Cataracts: Lens changes have been observed in patients during long-term quetiapine treatment. Lens examination is recommended when starting treatment and at 6-month intervals during chronic treatment. (5.11)



 
 *    QT Prolongation: Post-marketing cases show increases in QT interval in patients who overdosed on quetiapine, in patients with concomitant illness, and in patients taking medicines known to cause electrolyte imbalance or increase QT interval. Avoid use with drugs that increase the QT interval and in patients with risk factors for prolonged QT interval. (5.12)



 
 *    Suicide: The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in schizophrenia, bipolar disorder and depression, and close supervision of high risk patients should accompany drug therapy. (5.21)



 
 *   See Full Prescribing Information for additional WARNINGS and PRECAUTIONS. 



 
   Table 1: 
 Age Range        Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated   
  
                   Increases Compared to Placebo    
  &lt;18              14 additional cases    
  18-24            5 additional cases    
                   Decreases Compared to Placebo    
  25-64            1 fewer case     
  &gt;=65             6 fewer cases    
    
 Laboratory Analyte  Category Change (At Least Once) from Baseline  Treatment Arm    N                Patientsn (%)     
  
  Fasting Glucose    Normal to High  (&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;= 126 mg/dL)    Quetiapine       2907             71 (2.4%)        
  Placebo          1346             19 (1.4%)        
  Borderline to High  (&gt;= 100 mg/dL and &lt;126 mg/dL to &gt;= 126 mg/dL)    Quetiapine       572              67 (11.7%)       
  Placebo          279              33 (11.8%)       
    
 Laboratory Analyte  Treatment Arm    N                Patients n (%)    
  
  Blood Glucose &gt;= 126 mg/dL    Placebo          277              17 (6%)          
  SEROQUEL XR 150 mg    280              19 (7%)          
  SEROQUEL XR 300 mg    269              32 (12%)         
    
 Laboratory Analyte  Indication       Treatment Arm    N                Patientsn (%)     
  
  Total Cholesterol &gt;=240 mg/dL    Schizophrenia6 weeks duration    SEROQUEL XR      718              67 (9%)          
  Placebo          232              21 (9%)          
  Bipolar Depression8 weeks duration    SEROQUEL XR      85               6 (7%)           
  Placebo          106              3 (3%)           
    Bipolar Mania3 weeks duration    SEROQUEL XR      128              9 (7%)           
  Placebo          134              5 (4%)           
  Major Depressive Disorder (Adjunct Therapy)6 weeks duration    SEROQUEL XR      420              67 (16%)         
  Placebo          213              15 (7%)          
  Triglycerides &gt;=200 mg/dL    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL XR      659              118 (18%)        
  Placebo          214              11 (5%)          
  Bipolar Depression    SEROQUEL XR      84               7 (8%)           
  Placebo          93               7 (8%)           
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL XR      102              15 (15%)         
  Placebo          125              8 (6%)           
  Major Depressive Disorder (Adjunct Therapy)    SEROQUEL XR      458              75 (16%)         
  Placebo          223              18 (8%)          
  LDL-Cholesterol &gt;= 160 mg/dL    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL XR      691              47 (7%)          
  Placebo          227              17 (8%)          
  Bipolar Depression    SEROQUEL XR      86               3 (4%)           
  Placebo          104              2 (2%)           
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL XR      125              5 (4%)           
  Placebo          135              2 (2%)           
  Major Depressive Disorder (Adjunct Therapy)    SEROQUEL XR      457              51 (11%)         
  Placebo          219              21 (10%)         
  HDL-Cholesterol &lt;= 40 mg/dL    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL XR      600              87 (15%)         
  Placebo          195              23 (12%)         
  Bipolar Depression    SEROQUEL XR      78               7 (9%)           
  Placebo          83               6 (7%)           
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL XR      100              19 (19%)         
  Placebo          115              15 (13%)         
  Major Depressive Disorder (Adjunct Therapy)    SEROQUEL XR      470              34 (7%)          
  Placebo          230              19 (8%)          
    
 Laboratory Analyte  Treatment Arm    N                Patientsn (%)     
  
  Cholesterol &gt;= 240 mg/dL    Placebo          213              15 (7%)          
  SEROQUEL XR 150 mg    223              41 (18%)         
  SEROQUEL XR 300 mg    197              26 (13%)         
  Triglycerides &gt;= 200 mg/dL    Placebo          223              18 (8%)          
  SEROQUEL XR 150 mg    232              36 (16%)         
  SEROQUEL XR 300 mg    226              39 (17%)         
  LDL-Cholesterol &gt;= 160 mg/dL    Placebo          219              21 (10%)         
  SEROQUEL XR 150 mg    242              29 (12%)         
  SEROQUEL XR 300 mg    215              22 (10%)         
  HDL-Cholesterol &lt;= 40 mg/dL    Placebo          230              19 (8%)          
  SEROQUEL XR 150 mg    238              14 (6%)          
  SEROQUEL XR 300 mg    232              20 (9%)          
    
 Laboratory Analyte  Indication       Treatment Arm    N                Patientsn (%)     
  
  Total Cholesterol &gt;= 200 mg/dL    Schizophrenia13- 17 years, 6 weeks duration    SEROQUEL         107              13 (12%)         
  Placebo          56               1 (2%)           
  Bipolar Mania10-17 years, 3 weeks duration    SEROQUEL         159              16 (10%)         
  Placebo          66               2 (3%)           
  Triglycerides &gt;=150 mg/dL    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL         103              17 (17%)         
  Placebo          51               4 (8%)           
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL         149              32 (22%)         
  Placebo          60               8 (13%)          
  LDL-Cholesterol &gt;= 130 mg/dL    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL         112              4 (4%)           
  Placebo          60               1 (2%)           
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL         169              13 (8%)          
  Placebo          74               4 (5%)           
  HDL-Cholesterol &lt;= 40 mg/dL    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL         104              16 (15%)         
  Placebo          54               10 (19%)         
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL         154              16 (10%)         
  Placebo          61               4 (7%)           
    
 Vital sign       Indication       Treatment Arm    N                Patientsn (%)     
  
  Weight Gain &gt;= 7% of Body Weight    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL XR      907              90 (10%)         
  Placebo          299              16 (5%)          
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL XR      138              7 (5%)           
  Placebo          150              0 (0%)           
  Bipolar Depression    SEROQUEL XR      110              9 (8%)           
  Placebo          125              1 (1%)           
  Major Depressive Disorder (Adjunctive Therapy)    SEROQUEL XR      616              32 (5%)          
  Placebo          302              5 (2%)           
    
 Vital sign       Treatment Arm    N                Patientsn (%)     
  
  Weight Gain &gt;=7% of Body weight in MDD Adjunctive Therapy    Placebo          302              5 (2%)           
  SEROQUEL XR 150 mg    309              10 (3%)          
  SEROQUEL XR 300 mg    307              22 (7%)          
    
 Vital Sign       Indication       Treatment Arm    N                Patientsn (%)     
  
  Weight gain &gt;= 7% of Body Weight    Schizophrenia    SEROQUEL         111              23 (21%)         
  Placebo          44               3 (7%)           
  Bipolar Mania    SEROQUEL         157              18 (12%)         
  Placebo          68               0 (0%)           
     Table 10: Incidence of potentially clinically significant shifts in thyroid hormone levels and TSH in short term placebo-controlled clinical trials 
  Total T4         Free T4          Total T3         Free T3          TSH              
  Quetiapine       Placebo          Quetiapine       Placebo          Quetiapine       Placebo          Quetiapine       Placebo          Quetiapine       Placebo          
  3.4 %  (37/1097)    0.6%  (4/651)    0.7%  (52/7218)    0.1%  (4/3668)    0.5%  (2/369)    0.0%  (0/113)    0.2%  (11/5673)    0.0%  (1/2679)    3.2%  (240/7587)    2.7%  (105/3912)    
      



   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death compared to placebo. SEROQUEL XR (quetiapine fumarate) is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see Boxed Warning].



    5.2 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in Table 1.



 No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to healthcare providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers.  Prescriptions for SEROQUEL XR should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



  Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder:  A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described above represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression.



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with administration of antipsychotic drugs, including quetiapine. Rare cases of NMS have been reported with quetiapine. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis) and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to exclude cases where the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (eg, pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever and primary central nervous system (CNS) pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: 1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; 2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and 3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. The patient should be carefully monitored since recurrences of NMS have been reported.



    5.4 Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus



  Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics, including quetiapine. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Given these confounders, the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions is not completely understood. However, epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of treatment-emergent hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. Precise risk estimates for hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics are not available.



 Patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus who are started on atypical antipsychotics should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients with risk factors for diabetes mellitus (eg, obesity, family history of diabetes) who are starting treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug.



  In some patients, a worsening of more than one of the metabolic parameters of weight, blood glucose and lipids was observed in clinical studies. Changes in these parameters should be managed as clinically appropriate.  



  Adults:  



  Table 2: Fasting Glucose-Proportion of Patients Shifting to &gt;= 126 mg/dL in short-term (&lt;= 12 weeks) Placebo-Controlled Studies  



 



 In a 24-week trial (active-controlled, 115 patients treated with SEROQUEL) designed to evaluate glycemic status with oral glucose tolerance testing of all patients, at week 24 the incidence of a treatment-emergent post-glucose challenge glucose level &gt;= 200 mg/dL was 1.7% and the incidence of a fasting treatment-emergent blood glucose level &gt;= 126 mg/dL was 2.6%. The mean change in fasting glucose from baseline was 3.2 mg/dL and mean change in 2 hour glucose from baseline was -1.8 mg/dL for quetiapine.



 In 2 long-term placebo-controlled randomized withdrawal clinical trials for bipolar maintenance, mean exposure of 213 days for SEROQUEL (646 patients) and 152 days for placebo (680 patients), the mean change in glucose from baseline was +5.0 mg/dL for quetiapine and -0.05 mg/dL for placebo. The exposure-adjusted rate of any increased blood glucose level (&gt;= 126 mg/dL) for patients more than 8 hours since a meal (however, some patients may not have been precluded from calorie intake from fluids during fasting period) was 18.0 per 100 patient years for SEROQUEL (10.7% of patients; n=556) and 9.5 for placebo per 100 patient years (4.6% of patients; n=581).



 Table 3 shows the percentage of patients with shifts in blood glucose to &gt;= 126 mg/dL from normal baseline in MDD adjunct therapy trials by dose.



  Table 3: Percentage of Patients with Shifts from Normal Baseline in Blood Glucose to &gt;= 126 mg/dL (assumed fasting) in MDD Adjunct Therapy Trials by Dose  



 



  Children and Adolescents:  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years. In a placebo-controlled SEROQUEL monotherapy study of adolescent patients (13- 17 years of age) with schizophrenia (6 weeks duration), the mean change in fasting glucose levels for SEROQUEL (n=138) compared to placebo (n=67) was -0.75 mg/dL versus -1.70 mg/dL. In a placebo-controlled SEROQUEL monotherapy study of children and adolescent patients (10-17 years of age) with bipolar mania (3 weeks duration), the mean change in fasting glucose level for SEROQUEL (n=170) compared to placebo (n=81) was 3.62 mg/dL versus -1.17 mg/dL. No patient in either study with a baseline normal fasting glucose level (&lt;100 mg/dL) or a baseline borderline fasting glucose level (&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;126 mg/dL) had a treatment-emergent blood glucose level of &gt;=126 mg/dL.



 



    5.5 Hyperlipidemia



  Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed with quetiapine use. Clinical monitoring, including baseline and periodic follow-up lipid evaluations in patients using quetiapine is recommended.



  In some patients, a worsening of more than one of the metabolic parameters of weight, blood glucose and lipids was observed in clinical studies. Changes in these parameters should be managed as clinically appropriate.  



  Adults:  



 Table 4 shows the percentage of patients with changes in cholesterol and triglycerides from baseline by indication in clinical trials with SEROQUEL XR.



  Table 4: Percentage of Adult Patients with Shifts in Total Cholesterol, Triglycerides, LDL-Cholesterol and HDL-Cholesterol from Baseline to Clinically Significant Levels by Indication  



 In SEROQUEL clinical trials for schizophrenia, the percentage of patients with shifts in cholesterol and triglycerides from baseline to clinically significant levels were 18% (placebo: 7%) and 22% (placebo: 16%). HDL-cholesterol and LDL-cholesterol parameters were not measured in these studies. In SEROQUEL clinical trials for bipolar depression, the following percentage of patients had shifts from baseline to clinically significant levels for the four lipid parameters measured: total cholesterol 9% (placebo: 6%); triglycerides 14% (placebo: 9%); LDL-cholesterol 6% (placebo: 5%) and HDL-cholesterol 14% (placebo: 14%). Lipid parameters were not measured in the bipolar mania studies.



 Table 5 shows the percentage of patients in MDD adjunctive therapy trials with clinically significant shifts in total-cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL-cholesterol and HDL-cholesterol from baseline by dose.



  Table 5: Percentage of Patients with Shifts in Total Cholesterol, Triglycerides, LDL-Cholesterol and HDL-Cholesterol from Baseline to Clinically Significant Levels in MDD Adjunctive Therapy Trials by Dose  



 



  Children and Adolescents:  



 Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients, and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years.



 Table 6 shows the percentage of children and adolescents with shifts in total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL-cholesterol and HDL-cholesterol from baseline to clinically significant levels by indication in clinical trials with SEROQUEL.



  Table 6: Percentage of Children and Adolescents with Shifts in Total Cholesterol, Triglycerides LDL-Cholesterol and HDL-Cholesterol from Baseline to Clinically Significant Levels by Indication  



 



 



    5.6 Weight Gain



  Increases in weight have been observed in clinical trials. Patients receiving quetiapine should receive regular monitoring of weight [ see Patient Counseling Information  (17)].



  In some patients, a worsening of more than one of the metabolic parameters of weight, blood glucose and lipids was observed in clinical studies. Changes in these parameters should be managed as clinically appropriate.  



 Adults: Table 7 shows the percentage of adult patients with weight gain of &gt;= 7% of body weight by indication.



  Table 7: Percentage of Patients with Weight Gain &gt;= 7% of Body Weight (Adults) by Indication  



 



 In schizophrenia trials, the proportions of patients meeting a weight gain criterion of &gt;= 7% of body weight were compared in a pool of four 3- to 6-week placebo-controlled clinical trials, revealing a statistically significant greater incidence of weight gain for SEROQUEL (23%) compared to placebo (6%).



 Table 8 shows the percentage of adult patients with weight gain of &gt;= 7% of body weight for MDD by dose.



  Table 8: Percentage of Patients with Weight Gain &gt;= 7% of Body Weight in MDD Adjunctive Therapy Trials by Dose (Adults)  



  Children and Adolescents:  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years. In two clinical trials with SEROQUEL, one in bipolar mania and one in schizophrenia, reported increases in weight are included in table 9 below.



 Table 9 shows the percentage of patients with weight gain &gt;= 7% of body weight in clinical trials with SEROQUEL.



  Table 9: Percentage of Patients with Weight Gain &gt;= 7% of Body Weight (Children and Adolescents)  



 The mean change in body weight in the schizophrenia trial was 2.0 kg in the SEROQUEL group and -0.4 kg in the placebo group and in the bipolar mania trial it was 1.7 kg in the SEROQUEL group and 0.4 kg in the placebo group.



 In an open-label study that enrolled patients from the above two pediatric trials, 63% of patients (241/380) completed 26 weeks of therapy with SEROQUEL. After 26 weeks of treatment, the mean increase in body weight was 4.4 kg. Forty-five percent of the patients gained &gt;= 7% of their body weight, not adjusted for normal growth. In order to adjust for normal growth over 26 weeks, an increase of at least 0.5 standard deviation from baseline in BMI was used as a measure of a clinically significant change; 18.3% of patients on SEROQUEL met this criterion after 26 weeks of treatment.



 When treating pediatric patients with SEROQUEL for any indication, weight gain should be assessed against that expected for normal growth.



 



    5.7 Tardive Dyskinesia



  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs including quetiapine. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses or may even arise after discontinuation of treatment.



 There is no known treatment for established cases of tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and thereby may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, SEROQUEL XR should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients who appear to suffer from a chronic illness that (1) is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs, and (2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient on SEROQUEL XR, drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with quetiapine despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.8 Orthostatic Hypotension



  Quetiapine may induce orthostatic hypotension associated with dizziness, tachycardia and, in some patients, syncope, especially during the initial dose-titration period, probably reflecting its alpha1-adrenergic antagonist properties. Syncope was reported in 0.3% (5/1866) of the patients treated with SEROQUEL XR across all indications, compared with 0.2% (2/928) on placebo. Syncope was reported in 1% (28/3265) of the patients treated with SEROQUEL, compared with 0.2% (2/954) on placebo. Orthostatic hypotension, dizziness, and syncope may lead to falls.



 Quetiapine should be used with particular caution in patients with known cardiovascular disease (history of myocardial infarction or ischemic heart disease, heart failure or conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease or conditions which would predispose patients to hypotension (dehydration, hypovolemia and treatment with antihypertensive medications) [ see Adverse Reactions  (6.2)]. If hypotension occurs during titration to the target dose, a return to the previous dose in the titration schedule is appropriate.



    5.9 Increases in Blood Pressure (Children and Adolescents)



  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years. In placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with schizophrenia (6-week duration) or bipolar mania (3- week duration), the incidence of increases at any time in systolic blood pressure (&gt;= 20 mmHg) was 15.2% (51/335) for SEROQUEL and 5.5% (9/163) for placebo; the incidence of increases at any time in diastolic blood pressure (&gt;= 10 mmHg) was 40.6% (136/335) for SEROQUEL and 24.5% (40/163) for placebo. In the 26-week open-label clinical trial, one child with a reported history of hypertension experienced a hypertensive crisis. Blood pressure in children and adolescents should be measured at the beginning of, and periodically during treatment.



    5.10 Leukopenia, Neutropenia and Agranulocytosis



  In clinical trials and postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia/neutropenia have been reported temporally related to atypical antipsychotic agents, including quetiapine fumarate. Agranulocytosis (including fatal cases) has also been reported.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white cell count (WBC) and history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a pre-existing low WBC or a history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and should discontinue SEROQUEL XR at the first sign of a decline in WBC in absence of other causative factors.



 Patients with neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm  3  ) should discontinue SEROQUEL XR and have their WBC followed until recovery [ see Adverse Reactions  (6.2)].



    5.11 Cataracts



  The development of cataracts was observed in association with quetiapine treatment in chronic dog studies [ see Animal Toxicology  (13.2)]. Lens changes have also been observed in adults, children, and adolescents during long-term quetiapine treatment, but a causal relationship to quetiapine use has not been established. Nevertheless, the possibility of lenticular changes cannot be excluded at this time. Therefore, examination of the lens by methods adequate to detect cataract formation, such as slit lamp exam or other appropriately sensitive methods, is recommended at initiation of treatment or shortly thereafter, and at 6-month intervals during chronic treatment.



    5.12 QT Prolongation



   In clinical trials quetiapine was not associated with a persistent increase in QT intervals. However, the QT effect was not systematically evaluated in a thorough QT study. In post marketing experience there were cases reported of QT prolongation in patients who overdosed on quetiapine [see Overdosage (10.1)], in patients with concomitant illness, and in patients taking medicines known to cause electrolyte imbalance or increase QT interval [see Drug Interactions (7)].  



  The use of quetiapine should be avoided in combination with other drugs that are known to prolong QTc including Class 1A antiarrythmics (e.g., quinidine, procainamide) or Class III antiarrythmics (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol), antipsychotic medications (e.g., ziprasidone, chlorpromazine, thioridazine), antibiotics (e.g., gatifloxacin, moxifloxacin), or any other class of medications known to prolong the QTc interval (e.g., pentamidine, levomethadyl acetate, methadone).  



  Quetiapine should also be avoided in circumstances that may increase the risk of occurrence of torsade de pointes and/or sudden death including (1) a history of cardiac arrhythmias such as bradycardia; (2) hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia; (3) concomitant use of other drugs that prolong the QTc interval; and (4) presence of congenital prolongation of the QT interval.  



  Caution should also be exercised when quetiapine is prescribed in patients with increased risk of QT prolongation (e.g. cardiovascular disease, family history of QT prolongation, the elderly, congestive heart failure and heart hypertrophy).  



    5.13 Seizures



  During short-term clinical trials with SEROQUEL XR, seizures occurred in 0.05% (1/1866) of patients treated with SEROQUEL XR across all indications compared to 0.3% (3/928) on placebo. During clinical trials with SEROQUEL, seizures occurred in 0.5% (20/3490) of patients treated with SEROQUEL compared to 0.2% (2/954) on placebo. As with other antipsychotics, quetiapine fumarate should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold, e.g., Alzheimer's dementia. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in a population of 65 years or older.



    5.14 Hypothyroidism



    Adults:  Clinical trials with quetiapine demonstrated dose-related decreases in thyroid hormone levels. The reduction in total and free thyroxine (T4) of approximately 20% at the higher end of the therapeutic dose range was maximal in the first six weeks of treatment and maintained without adaptation or progression during more chronic therapy. In nearly all cases, cessation of quetiapine treatment was associated with a reversal of the effects on total and free T4, irrespective of the duration of treatment. In SEROQUEL XR clinical trials across all indications 1.8% (24/1336) of patients on SEROQUEL XR vs. 0.6% (3/530) on placebo experienced decreased free thyroxine and 1.6% (21/1346) on SEROQUEL XR vs. 3.4% (18/534) on placebo experienced increased thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH); however, no patients experienced a combination of clinically significant decreased free thyroxine and increased TSH. About 0.7% (26/3489) of SEROQUEL patients did experience TSH increases in monotherapy studies. Some patients with TSH increases needed replacement thyroid treatment.  



  In all quetiapine trials, the incidence of potentially clinically significant shifts in thyroid hormones and TSH were*: decrease in free T4, 2.0% (357/17513); decrease in total T4, 4.0% (75/1861); decrease in free T3, 0.4% (53/13766); decrease in total T3, 2.0% (26/1312), and increase in TSH, 4.9% (956/19412). In eight patients, where TBG was measured, levels of TBG were unchanged.  



  Table 10 shows the incidence of these shifts in short-term placebo-controlled clinical trials.  



  In short-term placebo-controlled monotherapy trials, the incidence of reciprocal, potentially clinically significant shifts in T3and TSH was 0.0 % for both quetiapine (1/4800) and placebo (0/2190) and for T4and TSH the shifts were 0.1% (7/6154) for quetiapine versus 0.0 % (1/3007) for placebo.  



  Generally, these changes in thyroid hormone levels were of no clinical significance.  



  Children and Adolescents:  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years. In acute placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescent patients with schizophrenia (6-week duration) or bipolar mania (3-week duration), the incidence of shifts to potentially clinically important thyroid function values at any time for SEROQUEL treated patients and placebo-treated patients for elevated TSH was 2.9% (8/280) vs. 0.7% (1/138), respectively and for decreased total thyroxine was 2.8% (8/289) vs. 0% (0/145), respectively. Of the SEROQUEL treated patients with elevated TSH levels, 1 had simultaneous low free T4 level at end of treatment.



    5.15 Hyperprolactinemia



   Adults:  During clinical trials with quetiapine across all indications, the incidence of shifts in prolactin levels to a clinically significant value occurred in 3.6% (158/4416) of patients treated with quetiapine compared to 2.6% (51/1968) on placebo.



  Children and Adolescents:  Safety and effectiveness of SEROQUEL XR have not been established in pediatric patients and SEROQUEL XR is not approved for patients under the age of 18 years. In acute placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescent patients with bipolar mania (3-week duration) or schizophrenia (6-week duration), the incidence of shifts in prolactin levels to a clinically significant value (&gt;20 mug/L males; &gt; 26 mug/L females at any time) was 13.4% (18/134) for SEROQUEL compared to 4% (3/75) for placebo in males and 8.7% (9/104) for SEROQUEL compared to 0% (0/39) for placebo in females.



 Like other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2 receptors, SEROQUEL XR elevates prolactin levels in some patients and the elevation may persist during chronic administration. Hyperprolactinemia, regardless of etiology, may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotrophin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported in patients receiving prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male subjects.



 Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin dependent in vitro  , a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is considered in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. As is common with compounds which increase prolactin release, mammary gland, and pancreatic islet cell neoplasia (mammary adenocarcinomas, pituitary and pancreatic adenomas) was observed in carcinogenicity studies conducted in mice and rats. Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans, but the available evidence is too limited to be conclusive [ see Carcinogenesis, Mutagenesis, Impairment of Fertility  (13.1)].



    5.16 Transaminase Elevations



  Asymptomatic, transient and reversible elevations in serum transaminases (primarily ALT) have been reported. The proportions of patients with transaminase elevations of &gt;3 times the upper limits of the normal reference range in a pool of placebo-controlled trials ranged between 1% and 2% for SEROQUEL XR compared to 2% for placebo. In schizophrenia trials in adults, the proportions of patients with transaminase elevations of &gt;3 times the upper limits of the normal reference range in a pool of 3- to 6-week placebo-controlled trials were approximately 6% (29/483) for SEROQUEL compared to 1% (3/194) for placebo. These hepatic enzyme elevations usually occurred within the first 3 weeks of drug treatment and promptly returned to pre-study levels with ongoing treatment with quetiapine.



    5.17 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  Somnolence was a commonly reported adverse event reported in patients treated with quetiapine especially during the 3-day period of initial dose titration. In schizophrenia trials, somnolence was reported in 24.7% (235/951) of patients on SEROQUEL XR compared to 10.3% (33/319) of placebo patients. In a bipolar depression clinical trial, somnolence was reported in 51.8% (71/137) of patients on SEROQUEL XR compared to 12.9% (18/140) of placebo patients. In a clinical trial for bipolar mania, somnolence was reported in 50.3% (76/151) of patients on SEROQUEL XR compared to 11.9% (19/160) of placebo patients. Since quetiapine has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills, patients should be cautioned about performing activities requiring mental alertness, such as operating a motor vehicle (including automobiles) or operating hazardous machinery until they are reasonably certain that quetiapine therapy does not affect them adversely. Somnolence may lead to falls.



 In short-term adjunctive therapy trials for MDD, somnolence was reported in 40% (252/627) of patients on SEROQUEL XR respectively compared to 9% (27/309) of placebo patients. Somnolence was dose-related in these trials (37% (117/315) and 43% (135/312) for the 150 mg and 300 mg groups, respectively).



    5.18 Priapism



  One case of priapism in a patient receiving quetiapine was reported prior to market introduction. While a causal relationship to use of quetiapine has not been established, other drugs with alpha-adrenergic blocking effects have been reported to induce priapism, and it is possible that quetiapine may share this capacity. Severe priapism may require surgical intervention.



    5.19 Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing SEROQUEL XR for patients who will be experiencing conditions which may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, eg, exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration.



    5.20 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in elderly patients, in particular those with advanced Alzheimer's dementia. SEROQUEL XR and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration pneumonia.



    5.21 Suicide



  The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in schizophrenia, bipolar disorder and depression; close supervision of high risk patients should accompany drug therapy. Prescriptions for SEROQUEL XR should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



 In three, 6-week clinical studies in patients with schizophrenia (N=951) the incidence of treatment emergent suicidal ideation or suicide attempt was 0.6% (n=6) in SEROQUEL XR treated patients and 0.9% (n=3) in placebo-treated patients.



 In an 8-week clinical study in patients with bipolar depression (N=137 for SEROQUEL XR and 140 for placebo) the incidence of treatment emergent suicidal ideation or suicide attempt was 0.7% (n=1) for SEROQUEL XR treated patients and 1.4% (n=2) for placebo.



 In a 3-week clinical study in patients with bipolar mania (N=311, 151 for SEROQUEL XR and 160 for placebo) the incidence of treatment emergent suicidal ideation or suicide attempt was 1.3% (n=2) for SEROQUEL XR compared to 3.8% (n=6) for placebo.



 In two, 6-week MDD adjunctive therapy trials (n=936, 627 on SEROQUEL XR and 309 on placebo) the incidence of treatment emergent suicidal ideation or suicide attempt was 0.5% (n=3) in SEROQUEL XR treated patients and 0.6% (n=2) in placebo.



    5.22 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with SEROQUEL XR in patients with certain concomitant systemic illnesses [ see Pharmacokinetics  (12.3)] is limited.



 SEROQUEL XR has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were excluded from premarketing clinical studies. Because of the risk of orthostatic hypotension with SEROQUEL XR, caution should be observed in cardiac patients [ see Warnings and Precautions  (5.8)].



    5.23 Withdrawal



   Acute withdrawal symptoms, such as insomnia, nausea and vomiting have been described after abrupt cessation of atypical antipsychotic drugs, including quetiapine fumarate. In short-term placebo-controlled, monotherapy clinical trials with SEROQUEL XR that included a discontinuation phase which evaluated discontinuation symptoms, the aggregated incidence of patients experiencing one or more discontinuation symptoms after abrupt cessation was 12.1% (241/1993) for SEROQUEL XR and 6.7% (71/1065) for placebo. The incidence of the individual adverse events (i.e., insomnia, nausea, headache, diarrhea, vomiting, dizziness and irritability) did not exceed 5.3% in any treatment group and usually resolved after 1 week post-discontinuation. Gradual withdrawal is advised.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
