<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sertraline0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  During its premarketing assessment, multiple doses of sertraline hydrochloride were administered to over 4000 adult subjects as of February 18, 2000. The conditions and duration of exposure to sertraline hydrochloride varied greatly, and included (in overlapping categories) clinical pharmacology studies, open and double-blind studies, uncontrolled and controlled studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, fixed-dose and titration studies, and studies for multiple indications, including major depressive disorder, OCD, panic disorder, PTSD, PMDD and social anxiety disorder.



 Untoward events associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized event categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, a World Health Organization dictionary of terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the over 4000 adult individuals exposed to multiple doses of sertraline hydrochloride who experienced a treatment-emergent adverse event of the type cited on at least one occasion while receiving sertraline hydrochloride. An event was considered treatment-emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation. It is important to emphasize that events reported during therapy were not necessarily caused by it.



 The prescriber should be aware that the figures in the tables and tabulations cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the side effect incidence rate in the population studied.



   Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Trials

  Table 2 enumerates the most common treatment-emergent adverse events associated with the use of sertraline hydrochloride (incidence of at least 5% for sertraline hydrochloride and at least twice that for placebo within at least one of the indications) for the treatment of adult patients with major depressive disorder/other, OCD, panic disorder, PTSD, PMDD and social anxiety disorder in placebo-controlled clinical trials. Most patients in major depressive disorder/other, OCD, panic disorder, PTSD and social anxiety disorder studies received doses of 50 to 200 mg/day. Patients in the PMDD study with daily dosing throughout the menstrual cycle received doses of 50 to 150 mg/day, and in the PMDD study with dosing during the luteal phase of the menstrual cycle received doses of 50 to 100 mg/day. Table 3 enumerates treatment-emergent adverse events that occurred in 2% or more of adult patients treated with sertraline hydrochloride and with incidence greater than placebo who participated in controlled clinical trials comparing sertraline hydrochloride with placebo in the treatment of major depressive disorder/other, OCD, panic disorder, PTSD, PMDD and social anxiety disorder. Table 3 provides combined data for the pool of studies that are provided separately by indication in Table 2.



 TABLE 2 MOST COMMON TREATMENT-EMERGENT ADVERSE EVENTS: INCIDENCE IN PLACEBO-CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS 
                       Percentage of Patients Reporting Event   
                       Major Depressive Disorder/Other     OCD      Panic Disorder     PTSD      
 Body System/Adverse Event  Sertraline hydrochloride(N=861)  Placebo(N=853)  Sertraline hydrochloride(N=533)  Placebo(N=373)  Sertraline hydrochloride(N=430)  Placebo(N=275)  Sertraline hydrochloride(N=374)  Placebo(N=376)   
  
   Autonomic Nervous System Disorders                                                                                                     
   Ejaculation Failure      7           &lt;1          17          2           19          1           11          1        
   Mouth Dry               16          9           14          9           15          10          11          6        
   Sweating Increased      8           3           6           1           5           1           4           2        
   Center. &amp; Periph. Nerv. System Disorders                                                                                                     
   Somnolence              13          6           15          8           15          9           13          9        
   Tremor                  11          3           8           1           5           1           5           1        
   Dizziness               12          7           17          9           10          10          8           5        
   General                                                                                                              
   Fatigue                 11          8           14          10          11          6           10          5        
   Pain                    1           2           3           1           3           3           4           6        
   Malaise                 &lt;1          1           1           1           7           14          10          10       
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                                     
   Abdominal Pain          2           2           5           5           6           7           6           5        
   Anorexia                3           2           11          2           7           2           8           2        
   Constipation            8           6           6           4           7           3           3           3        
   Diarrhea/Loose Stools      18          9           24          10          20          9           24          15       
   Dyspepsia               6           3           10          4           10          8           6           6        
   Nausea                  26          12          30          11          29          18          21          11       
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                                     
   Agitation               6           4           6           3           6           2           5           5        
   Insomnia                16          9           28          12          25          18          20          11       
   Libido Decreased        1           &lt;1          11          2           7           1           7           2        
                         PMDDDaily Dosing      PMDDLuteal Phase Dosing      Social Anxiety Disorder                 
   Body System/Adverse Event      Sertraline hydrochloride(N=121)      Placebo(N=122)      Sertraline hydrochloride(N=136)      Placebo(N=127)      Sertraline hydrochloride(N=344)      Placebo(N=268)                             
   Autonomic Nervous System Disorders                                                                                                     
   Ejaculation Failure     N/A         N/A         N/A         N/A          14          -                                
   Mouth Dry               6           3           10          3           12          4                                
   Sweating Increased      6           &lt;1          3           0           11          2                                
   Center. &amp; Periph. Nerv. System Disorders                                                                                                     
   Somnolence              7           &lt;1          2           0           9           6                                
   Tremor                  2           0           &lt;1          &lt;1          9           3                                
   Dizziness               6           3           7           5           14          6                                
   General                                                                                                              
   Fatigue                 16          7           10          &lt;1          12          6                                
   Pain                    6           &lt;1          3           2           1           3                                
   Malaise                 9           5           7           5           8           3                                
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                                     
   Abdominal Pain          7           &lt;1          3           3           5           5                                
   Anorexia                3           2           5           0           6           3                                
   Constipation            2           3           1           2           5           3                                
   Diarrhea/Loose Stools      13          3           13          7           21          8                                
   Dyspepsia               7           2           7           3           13          5                                
   Nausea                  23          9           13          3           22          8                                
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                                     
   Agitation               2           &lt;1          1           0           4           2                                
   Insomnia                17          11          12          10          25          10                               
   Libido Decreased        11          2           4           2           9           3                                
              TABLE 3 TREATMENT-EMERGENT ADVERSE EVENTS: INCIDENCE IN PLACEBO-CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS Percentage of Patients Reporting Event Major Depressive Disorder/OtherMajor depressive disorder and other premarketing controlled trials., OCD, Panic Disorder, PTSD, PMDD and Social Anxiety Disorder combined 
 Body System/Adverse Event                           SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE(N=2799)       Placebo(N=2394)        
                                                                                                            
  
   Autonomic Nervous System Disorders                                                                       
   Ejaculation Failure                                          14                          1               
   Mouth Dry                                                    14                          8               
   Sweating Increased                                            7                          2               
   Center. &amp; Periph. Nerv. System Disorders                                                                 
   Somnolence                                                   13                          7               
   Dizziness                                                    12                          7               
   Headache                                                     25                         23               
   Paresthesia                                                   2                          1               
   Tremor                                                        8                          2               
   Disorders of Skin and Appendages                                                                         
   Rash                                                          3                          2               
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
   Anorexia                                                      6                          2               
   Constipation                                                  6                          4               
   Diarrhea/Loose Stools                                        20                         10               
   Dyspepsia                                                     8                          4               
   Nausea                                                       25                         11               
   Vomiting                                                      4                          2               
   General                                                                                                  
   Fatigue                                                      12                          7               
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
   Agitation                                                     5                          3               
   Anxiety                                                       4                          3               
   Insomnia                                                     21                         11               
   Libido Decreased                                              6                          2               
   Nervousness                                                   5                          4               
   Special Senses                                                                                           
   Vision Abnormal                                               3                          2               
           Associated with Discontinuation in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials
   Table 4 lists the adverse events associated with discontinuation of sertraline hydrochloride treatment (incidence at least twice that for placebo and at least 1% for sertraline hydrochloride in clinical trials) in major depressive disorder/other, OCD, panic disorder, PTSD, PMDD and social anxiety disorder.



 TABLE 4 MOST COMMON ADVERSE EVENTS ASSOCIATED WITH DISCONTINUATION IN PLACEBO-CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS 
  Adverse Event   Major Depressive Disorder/Other, OCD, Panic Disorder, PTSD, PMDD and Social Anxiety Disorder combined(N=2799)  Major Depressive Disorder/ Other(N=861)  OCD(N=533)  Panic Disorder(N=430)  PTSD(N=374)  PMDDDaily Dosing(N=121)  PMDDLuteal Phase Dosing(N=136)  Social Anxiety Disorder(N=344)   
  
 Abdominal Pain            -                -           -          -           -          -          -         1%       
    Agitation              -               1%           -          2%          -          -          -          -       
     Anxiety               -                -           -          -           -          -          -         2%       
 Diarrhea/ Loose Stools          2%               2%          2%          1%          -         2%          -          -       
    Dizziness              -                -          1%          -           -          -          -          -       
    Dry Mouth              -               1%           -          -           -          -          -          -       
    Dyspepsia              -                -           -          1%          -          -          -          -       
 Ejaculation Failure          1%               1%          1%          2%          -         N/A        N/A        2%       
     Fatigue               -                -           -          -           -          -          -         2%       
    Headache              1%               2%           -          -          1%          -          -         2%       
   Hot Flushes             -                -           -          -           -          -         1%          -       
    Insomnia              2%               1%          3%          2%          -          -         1%         3%       
     Nausea               3%               4%          3%          3%         2%         2%         1%         2%       
   Nervousness             -                -           -          -           -         2%          -          -       
   Palpitation             -                -           -          -           -          -         1%          -       
   Somnolence             1%               1%          2%          2%          -          -          -          -       
     Tremor                -               2%           -          -           -          -          -          -       
                 Male and Female Sexual Dysfunction with SSRIs
   Although changes in sexual desire, sexual performance and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of a psychiatric disorder, they may also be a consequence of pharmacologic treatment. In particular, some evidence suggests that selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) can cause such untoward sexual experiences. Reliable estimates of the incidence and severity of untoward experiences involving sexual desire, performance and satisfaction are difficult to obtain, however, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling are likely to underestimate their actual incidence.



 Table 5 below displays the incidence of sexual side effects reported by at least 2% of patients taking sertraline hydrochloride in placebo-controlled trials.



 TABLE 5 
                   Adverse Event                     Sertraline hydrochloride            Placebo            
  
 Ejaculation failure(primarily delayed ejaculation)             14%                        1%               
                  Decreased libido                              6%                         1%               
         There are no adequate and well-controlled studies examining sexual dysfunction with sertraline treatment.
 

 Priapism has been reported with all SSRIs.



 While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of SSRIs, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



   Other Adverse Events in Pediatric Patients

  In over 600 pediatric patients treated with sertraline hydrochloride, the overall profile of adverse events was generally similar to that seen in adult studies. However, the following adverse events, from controlled trials, not appearing in Tables 2 and 3, were reported at an incidence of at least 2% and occurred at a rate of at least twice the placebo rate (N=281 patients treated with sertraline hydrochloride ): fever, hyperkinesia, urinary incontinence, aggressive reaction, sinusitis, epistaxis and purpura.



   Other Events Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of sertraline hydrochloride

  Following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse events reported during premarketing assessment of sertraline hydrochloride in clinical trials (over 4000 adult subjects) except those already listed in the previous tables or elsewhere in labeling.



 In the tabulations that follow, a World Health Organization dictionary of terminology has been used to classify reported adverse events. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the over 4000 adult individuals exposed to multiple doses of sertraline hydrochloride who experienced an event of the type cited on at least one occasion while receiving sertraline hydrochloride. All events are included except those already listed in the previous tables or elsewhere in labeling and those reported in terms so general as to be uninformative and those for which a causal relationship to sertraline hydrochloride treatment seemed remote. It is important to emphasize that although the events reported occurred during treatment with sertraline hydrochloride, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: frequent adverse events are those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients. Events of major clinical importance are also described in the  PRECAUTIONS  section.



   Autonomic Nervous System Disorders-    Frequent:  impotence;  Infrequent:  flushing, increased saliva, cold clammy skin, mydriasis;  Rare:  pallor, angle-closure glaucoma, priapism, vasodilation.



   Body as a Whole-General Disorders-    Rare:  allergic reaction, allergy.



   Cardiovascular-    Frequent:  palpitations, chest pain;  Infrequent:  hypertension, tachycardia, postural dizziness, postural hypotension, periorbital edema, peripheral edema, hypotension, peripheral ischemia, syncope, edema, dependent edema;  Rare:  precordial chest pain, substernal chest pain, aggravated hypertension, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular disorder.



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders-    Frequent:  hypertonia, hypoesthesia;  Infrequent:  twitching, confusion, hyperkinesia, vertigo, ataxia, migraine, abnormal coordination, hyperesthesia, leg cramps, abnormal gait, nystagmus, hypokinesia;  Rare:  dysphonia, coma, dyskinesia, hypotonia, ptosis, choreoathetosis, hyporeflexia.



   Disorders of Skin and Appendages-    Infrequent:  pruritus, acne, urticaria, alopecia, dry skin, erythematous rash, photosensitivity reaction, maculopapular rash;  Rare:  follicular rash, eczema, dermatitis, contact dermatitis, bullous eruption, hypertrichosis, skin discoloration, pustular rash.



   Endocrine Disorders-    Rare:  exophthalmos, gynecomastia.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders-    Frequent:  appetite increased;  Infrequent:  dysphagia, tooth caries aggravated, eructation, esophagitis, gastroenteritis;  Rare:  melena, glossitis, gum hyperplasia, hiccup, stomatitis, tenesmus, colitis, diverticulitis, fecal incontinence, gastritis, rectum hemorrhage, hemorrhagic peptic ulcer, proctitis, ulcerative stomatitis, tongue edema, tongue ulceration.



   General-    Frequent:  back pain, asthenia, malaise, weight increase;  Infrequent:  fever, rigors, generalized edema;  Rare:  face edema, aphthous stomatitis.



   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders-    Rare:  hyperacusis, labyrinthine disorder.



   Hematopoietic and Lymphatic-    Rare:  anemia, anterior chamber eye hemorrhage.



   Liver and Biliary System Disorders-    Rare:  abnormal hepatic function.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders-    Infrequent:  thirst;  Rare:  hypoglycemia, hypoglycemia reaction.



   Musculoskeletal System Disorders-    Frequent:  myalgia;  Infrequent:  arthralgia, dystonia, arthrosis, muscle cramps, muscle weakness.



   Psychiatric Disorders-    Frequent:  yawning, other male sexual dysfunction, other female sexual dysfunction;  Infrequent:  depression, amnesia, paroniria, teeth-grinding, emotional lability, apathy, abnormal dreams, euphoria, paranoid reaction, hallucination, aggressive reaction, aggravated depression, delusions;  Rare:  withdrawal syndrome, suicide ideation, libido increased, somnambulism, illusion.



   Reproductive-    Infrequent:  menstrual disorder, dysmenorrhea, intermenstrual bleeding, vaginal hemorrhage, amenorrhea, leukorrhea;  Rare:  female breast pain, menorrhagia, balanoposthitis, breast enlargement, atrophic vaginitis, acute female mastitis.



   Respiratory System Disorders-    Frequent:  rhinitis;  Infrequent:  coughing, dyspnea, upper respiratory tract infection, epistaxis, bronchospasm, sinusitis;  Rare:  hyperventilation, bradypnea, stridor, apnea, bronchitis, hemoptysis, hypoventilation, laryngismus, laryngitis.



   Special Senses-    Frequent:  tinnitus;  Infrequent:  conjunctivitis, earache, eye pain, abnormal accommodation;  Rare:  xerophthalmia, photophobia, diplopia, abnormal lacrimation, scotoma, visual field defect.



   Urinary System Disorders-    Infrequent:  micturition frequency, polyuria, urinary retention, dysuria, nocturia, urinary incontinence;  Rare:  cystitis, oliguria, pyelonephritis, hematuria, renal pain, strangury.



   Laboratory Tests

  In man, asymptomatic elevations in serum transaminases (SGOT [or AST] and SGPT [or ALT]) have been reported infrequently (approximately 0.8%) in association with sertraline hydrochloride administration. These hepatic enzyme elevations usually occurred within the first 1 to 9 weeks of drug treatment and promptly diminished upon drug discontinuation.



 Sertraline hydrochloride therapy was associated with small mean increases in total cholesterol (approximately 3%) and triglycerides (approximately 5%), and a small mean decrease in serum uric acid (approximately 7%) of no apparent clinical importance.



 The safety profile observed with sertraline hydrochloride treatment in patients with major depressive disorder, OCD, panic disorder, PTSD, PMDD and social anxiety disorder is similar.



   Other Events Observed During the Post marketing Evaluation of sertraline hydrochloride

  Reports of adverse events temporally associated with sertraline hydrochloride that have been received since market introduction, that are not listed above and that may have no causal relationship with the drug, include the following: acute renal failure, anaphylactoid reaction, angioedema, blindness, optic neuritis, cataract, increased coagulation times, bradycardia, AV block, atrial arrhythmias, QT-interval prolongation, ventricular tachycardia (including Torsade de Pointes arrhythmias), cerebrovascular spasm (including reversible cerebral vasconstriction syndrome and Call-Fleming syndrome), hypothyroidism, agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia and pancytopenia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, lupus-like syndrome, serum sickness, diabetes mellitus, hyperglycemia, galactorrhea, hyperprolactinemia, extrapyramidal symptoms, oculogyric crisis, serotonin syndrome, psychosis, pulmonary hypertension, severe skin reactions, which potentially can be fatal, such as Stevens-Johnson syndrome, vasculitis, photosensitivity and other severe cutaneous disorders, rare reports of pancreatitis, and liver events-clinical features (which in the majority of cases appeared to be reversible with discontinuation of sertraline hydrochloride) occurring in one or more patients include: elevated enzymes, increased bilirubin, hepatomegaly, hepatitis, jaundice, abdominal pain, vomiting, liver failure and death.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

  Suicidality  and Antidepressant Drugs

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders.  Anyone considering the use of sertraline hydrochloride or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need.  Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior.  Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber.  Sertraline hydrochloride is not approved for use in pediatric patients except for patients with obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD).  (See   Warnings: Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk  ,   Precautions:  Information for Patients  , and   Precautions: Pediatric Use  )  



 





    BOXED WARNING: Medication Guide

  Medication Guide

    SERTRALINE (SER-tra-line) HYDROCHLORIDE(sertraline hydrochloride) (Tablets and Oral Concentrate (solution))  



 Read the Medication Guide that comes with SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE before you start taking it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or treatment. Talk with your healthcare provider if there is something you do not understand or want to learn more about.



   What is the most important information I should know about SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?  



 SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE and other antidepressant medicines may cause serious side effects, including: 



   1. Suicidal thoughts or actions:  



 *  SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE and other antidepressant medicines may increase suicidal thoughts or actions in some children, teenagers, or young adults within the first few months of treatment or when the dose is changed. 
 *  Depression or other serious mental illnesses are the most important causes of suicidal thoughts or actions. 
 *  Watch for these changes and call your healthcare provider right away if you notice:New or sudden changes in mood, behavior, actions, thoughts, or feelings, especially if severe.Pay particular attention to such changes when SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE is started or when the dose is changed.Keep all follow-up visits with your healthcare provider and call between visits if you are worried about symptoms.Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency, especially if they are new, worse, or worry you: 
   *   attempts to commit suicideacting on dangerous impulsesacting aggressive or violentthoughts about suicide or dyingnew or worse depressionnew or worse anxiety or panic attacksfeeling agitated, restless, angry or irritabletrouble sleepingan increase in activity or talking more than what is normal for youother unusual changes in behavior or mood 
      Call your healthcare provider right away if you have any of the following symptoms, or call 911 if an emergency. SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE may be associated with these serious side effects:  
 

   2.  Serotonin SyndromeThis condition can be life-threatening and may include:  



 *   agitation, hallucinations, coma or other changes in mental statuscoordination problems or muscle twitching (overactive reflexes) racing heartbeat, high or low blood pressuresweating or fever nausea, vomiting, or diarrheamuscle rigidity 
      3.  Severe allergic reactions:    
 

 *   trouble breathingswelling of the face, tongue, eyes or mouthrash, itchy welts (hives) or blisters, alone or with fever or joint pain 
      4.  Abnormal bleeding:   SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE and other antidepressant medicines may increase your risk of bleeding or bruising, especially if you take the blood thinner warfarin (Coumadin  (r)  , Jantoven  (r)  ), a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAIDs, like ibuprofen or naproxen), or aspirin. 
 

   5.  Seizures or convulsions   



   6.  Manic episodes:  



 *   greatly increased energysevere trouble sleepingracing thoughtsreckless behaviorunusually grand ideasexcessive happiness or irritabilitytalking more or faster than usual 
      7.  Changes in appetite or weight.    Children and adolescents should have height and weight monitored during treatment.
 

   8.  Low salt (sodium) levels in the blood.   Elderly people may be at greater risk for this. Symptoms may include: 



 *   headacheweakness or feeling unsteadyconfusion, problems concentrating or thinking or memory problems 
      9. Visual problems  
 

 *  eye pain 
 *  changes in vision 
 *  swelling or redness in or around the eye Only some people are at risk for these problems. You may want to undergo an eye examination to see if you are at risk and receive preventative treatment if you are. 
      Do not stop SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE without first talking to your healthcare provider.   Stopping SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE too quickly may cause serious symptoms including: 
 

 *  anxiety, irritability, high or low mood, feeling restless or changes in sleep habits 
 *  headache, sweating, nausea, dizziness 
 *  electric shock-like sensations, shaking, confusion 
      What is SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?  
 

 SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE is a prescription medicine used to treat depression. It is important to talk with your healthcare provider about the risks of treating depression and also the risks of not treating it. You should discuss all treatment choices with your healthcare provider. SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE is   also   used to treat:



 *  Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) 
 *  Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD) 
 *  Panic Disorder 
 *  Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) 
 *  Social Anxiety Disorder 
 *  Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder (PMDD) 
    Talk to your healthcare provider if you do not think that your condition is getting better with SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE treatment.
 

   Who should not take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?  



 Do not take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE if you:



 *  are allergic to sertraline or any of the ingredients in SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE. 
 *  take the antipsychotic medicine pimozide (Orap(r)) because this can cause serious heart problems. 
 *  take Antabuse(r) (disulfiram) (if you are taking the liquid form of SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE) due to the alcohol content. 
 *  take a monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI). Ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist if you are not sure if you take an MAOI, including the antibiotic linezolid.Do not take an MAOI within 2 weeks of stopping SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE unless directed to do so by your physician.Do not start SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE if you stopped taking an MAOI in the last 2 weeks unless directed to do so by your physician.People who take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE close in time to an MAOI may have serious or even life-threatening side effects. Get medical help right away if you have any of these symptoms: high feveruncontrolled muscle spasmsstiff musclesrapid changes in heart rate or blood pressureconfusionloss of consciousness (pass out) 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before taking SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?   Ask if you are not sure.
 

 Before starting SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE, tell your healthcare provider if you:



 *  Are taking certain drugs such as:Medicines used to treat migraine headaches such as:triptansMedicines used to treat mood, anxiety, psychotic or thought disorders, such as:tricyclic antidepressantslithiumdiazepamSSRIsSNRIsantipsychotic drugsvalproateMedicines used to treat seizures such as:phenytoinMedicines used to treat pain such as:tramadolMedicines used to thin your blood such as:warfarinMedicines used to control your heartbeat such as :propafenoneflecainidedigitoxinMedicines used to treat type II diabetes such as:tolbutamideCimetidine used to treat heartburnOver-the-counter medicines or supplements such as:Aspirin or other NSAIDstryptophanSt. John's Wort 
 *  have liver problems 
 *  have kidney problems. 
 *  have heart problems 
 *  have or had seizures or convulsions 
 *  have bipolar disorder or mania 
 *  have low sodium levels in your blood 
 *  have a history of a stroke 
 *  have high blood pressure 
 *  have or had bleeding problems 
 *  are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. It is not known if SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE will harm your unborn baby. Talk to your healthcare provider about the benefits and risks of treating depression during pregnancy. 
 *  are breast-feeding or plan to breast-feed. Some SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE may pass into your breast milk. Talk to your healthcare provider about the best way to feed your baby while taking SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE. 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the   medicines   that you take,   including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE and some medicines may interact with each other, may not work as well, or may cause serious side effects.
 

 Your healthcare provider or pharmacist can tell you if it is safe to take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE with your other medicines. Do not start or stop any medicine while taking SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE without talking to your healthcare provider first.



   If you take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE, you should not take any other medicines that contain sertraline (sertraline HCl, sertraline hydrochloride, etc.).



     How should I take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?  



 *  Take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE exactly as prescribed. Your healthcare provider may need to change the dose of SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE until it is the right dose for you. 
 *  SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE Tablets may be taken with or without food. 
 *  SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE Oral Concentrate must be diluted before use:Follow the instructions carefullyWhen diluting SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE Oral Concentrate, use ONLY water, ginger ale, lemon/lime soda, lemonade, or orange juice.If you are sensitive to latex, be careful when using the dropper to dispense the Oral Concentrate. 
 *  If you miss a dose of SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE, take the missed dose as soon as you remember. If it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and take your next dose at the regular time. Do not take two doses of SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE at the same time. 
 *  If you take too much SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE, call your healthcare provider or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What should I avoid while taking SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?  
 

 SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE can cause sleepiness or may affect your ability to make decisions, think clearly, or react quickly. You should not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE affects you. Do not drink alcohol while using SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE.



   What are the possible side effects of SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?  



 SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE may cause serious side effects, including:



 *  See "What is the most important information I should know about SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?" 
 *  Feeling anxious or trouble sleeping 
    Common possible side effects in people who take SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE include
 

 *  nausea, loss of appetite, diarrhea or indigestion 
 *  change in sleep habits including increased sleepiness or insomnia 
 *  increased sweating 
 *  sexual problems including decreased libido and ejaculation failure 
 *  tremor or shaking 
 *  feeling tired or fatigued 
 *  agitation 
    Other side effects in children and adolescents include:
 

 *  abnormal increase in muscle movement or agitation 
 *  nose bleed 
 *  urinating more often 
 *  urinary incontinence 
 *  aggressive reaction 
 *  heavy menstrual periods 
 *  possible slowed growth rate and weight change. Your child's height and weight should be monitored during treatment with SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE. 
    Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away.  These are not all the possible side effects of SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE.  For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.
 

   CALL YOUR DOCTOR FOR MEDICAL ADVICE ABOUT SIDE EFFECTS. YOU MAY REPORT SIDE EFFECTS TO THE FDA AT   1-800-FDA-1088.



   How should I store SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?   



 *  Store SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE at room temperature, between 59 degrees F and 86 degrees F (15 degrees C to 30 degrees C). 
 *  Keep SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE bottle closed tightly. 
      Keep SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE and all medicines out of the reach of children.  
 

   General information about SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE  



 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide. Do not use SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE for a condition for which it was not prescribed.  Do not give SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE to other people, even if they have the same condition. It may harm them.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider. You may ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist for information about SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE that is written for healthcare professionals. 



 For more information about sertraline hydrochloride call 1 800 438 1985 or go to www.greenstonellc.com



   What are the ingredients in SERTRALINE HYDROCHLORIDE?  



 Active ingredient: sertraline hydrochloride



 Inactive ingredients



 *  Tablets: dibasic calcium phosphate dihydrate, D&amp;C Yellow #10 aluminum lake (in 25 mg tablet), FD&amp;C Blue #1 aluminum lake (in 25 mg tablet), FD&amp;C Red #40 aluminum lake (in 25 mg tablet), FD&amp;C Blue #2 aluminum lake (in 50 mg tablet), hydroxypropyl cellulose, hypromellose, magnesium stearate, microcrystalline cellulose, polyethylene glycol, polysorbate 80, sodium starch glycolate, synthetic yellow iron oxide (in 100 mg tablet), and titanium dioxide 
 *  Oral concentration: glycerin, alcohol (12%), menthol, butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) 
    This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration
 

 



 LAB-0541-6.0



 May 2014
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
