<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="signifor1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinically significant adverse reactions that appear in other sections of the labeling include:



 *  Hyperglycemia and Diabetes [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *  Bradycardia and QT Prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *  Liver Test Elevations [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *  Cholelithiasis [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *  Pituitary Hormone Deficiency(ies) [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse drug reactions associated with SIGNIFOR LAR and occurring in &gt;=20% of patients were diarrhea, cholelithiasis, hyperglycemia and diabetes mellitus. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Drug-Naive Patients with Acromegaly  



 The data described in Table 1 are derived from an active-controlled trial in patients with acromegaly naive to previous drug therapy  [see Clinical Studies (14.1)]  . The data reflect exposure of 178 patients with acromegaly to SIGNIFOR LAR for a mean duration of 43 weeks. In the overall study population, 52% were female and the average age of patients was 45 years. Additional information on design and demographics of this trial are described below  [see Clinical Studies (14.1)]  .



 Table 1 presents common adverse reactions associated with SIGNIFOR LAR. These adverse reactions were not present at baseline or, if present, worsened from baseline and occurred in at least 5% of patients treated with SIGNIFOR LAR.



 Table 1 - Adverse Reactions Occuring in &gt;= 5% of Patients Exposed to SIGNIFOR LAR in Patients with Acromegaly Naive to Drug Therapy 
 * Diabetes mellitus includes the following PTs: Diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus** Sinus bradycardia includes the following PTs: Bradycardia and sinus bradycardia*** Injection site reaction related AEs includes the following PTs: Injection site pain, Injection site reaction, Injection site haematoma, Injection site pruritus, Injection site swelling, Injection site erythema   
  
   Adverse Reaction Type      SIGNIFOR LAR(40-60mg)%N=178      Active Comparator%N=180     
   Hyperglycemia Related Adverse Reactions     
 Hyperglycemia    29               8                 
 Diabetes mellitus*  26               4                 
 Blood glucose increased  8                2                 
 Glycosylated hemoglobin increased  6                2                 
 Hypoglycemia     5                7                 
   Gastrointestinal Related Adverse Reactions     
 Diarrhea         39               45                
 Abdominal pain   18               22                
 Nausea           14               22                
 Abdominal distension  12               12                
 Vomiting         8                7                 
 Abdominal pain upper  6                8                 
   Hepatobiliary Related Adverse Reactions     
 Cholelithiasis   26               36                
   Cardiac Related Adverse Reactions     
 Sinus bradycardia**  10               7                 
 Hypertension     8                7                 
   Nervous System Related Adverse Reactions     
 Headache         19               26                
 Dizziness        10               11                
   Skin Related Adverse Reactions     
 Alopecia         18               19                
   Infections Related Adverse Reactions     
 Nasopharyngitis  16               16                
 Influenza        8                4                 
 Upper respiratory tract infection  7                3                 
 Cough            5                8                 
   Laboratory Related Adverse Reactions     
 Blood creatine phosphokinase increased  13               12                
 Alanine aminotransferase increased  8                4                 
 Aspartate aminotransferase increased  6                4                 
 Weight decreased  5                4                 
   General and Injection Site Related Adverse Reactions     
 Fatigue          10               10                
 Injection site reaction***  7                7                 
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Related Adverse Reactions     
 Arthralgia       10               12                
 Back pain        8                11                
 Pain in extremity  7                4                 
   Blood Related Adverse Reactions     
 Anemia           6                6                 
         Other notable adverse reactions which occurred with a frequency of 5% or less for SIGNIFOR LAR were: adrenal insufficiency (3%); glucose tolerance impaired (1%); QT-prolongation (4%); blood amylase increased (2%).
 

   Patients with Acromegaly Inadequately Controlled on other Somatostatin Analogs at Baseline  



 The data described in Table 2 are derived from an active-controlled study in patients with acromegaly inadequately controlled at baseline on other somatostatin analogs  [see Clinical Studies (14.2)]  . These data reflect exposure of 63 and 62 patients to SIGNIFOR LAR 40 mg and 60 mg, respectively, for a mean duration of 24 weeks.



 In the overall study population, 56% were female and the average age of patients was 45 years. Additional information on design and demographics of this trial are described below  [see Clinical Studies (14.1)]  .



 Table 2 presents common adverse reactions associated with SIGNIFOR LAR. These common adverse reactions were not present at baseline or, if present, worsened from baseline and occurred in at least 5% of patients treated with SIGNIFOR LAR.



 Table 2 - Adverse Reactions Occuring in &gt;= 5% of Patients Exposed to SIGNIFOR LAR in Patients with Acromegaly Previously Treated with Other Somatostatin Analogs 
 * Diabetes mellitus includes the following PTs: diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus   
  
   Adverse Drug Reactions      SIGNIFOR LAR 40 mg%N=63      SIGNIFOR LAR 60 mg%N=62      Active Comparators%N=66     
   Hyperglycemia Related Adverse Reactions     
 Hyperglycemia    33               30               14                
 Diabetes mellitus*  21               31               9                 
 Blood glucose increased  5                7                0                 
 Hypoglycemia     3                7                0                 
   Gastrointestinal Related Adverse Reactions     
 Diarrhea         16               19               5                 
 Abdominal pain   8                8                3                 
 Nausea           3                7                3                 
   Hepatobiliary Related Adverse Reactions     
 Cholelithiasis   10               13               14                
   Cardiac Related Adverse Reactions     
 Atrioventricular block first degree  6                0                0                 
   Nervous System Related Adverse Reactions     
 Headache         14               3                5                 
 Dizziness        8                2                3                 
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Related Adverse Reactions     
 Alopecia         2                7                0                 
   Infections Related Adverse Reactions     
 Nasopharyngitis  6                11               3                 
   Blood Related Adverse Reactions     
 Anemia           6                3                3                 
          Other notable adverse reactions which occurred with a frequency of 5% or less in the SIGNIFOR LAR 40 mg, SIGNIFOR LAR 60 mg arm, respectively, were adrenal insufficiency (2% and 0%) and glucose tolerance impaired (3% and 5%).
 

   Hyperglycemia  



 The average fasting plasma glucose levels in patients with acromegaly naive to drug therapy study  [see Clinical Studies (14.1)]  across visits is shown in Figure 2 below.



 Figure 2. Mean Fasting Plasma Glucose (mg/dL) by Visit in the Study of Patients with Acromegaly Naive to Drug Therapy*   * Numbers of patients with a glucose value at the given timepoint in the Signifor LAR/Active comparator arms are displayed as xxx/xxx on the x axis
 

   Pancreatic Enzyme Elevation and Pancreatitis  



 Asymptomatic, elevations in lipase and alpha amylase were observed in 30% and 20% of patients receiving SIGNIFOR LAR in the drug naive study  [see Clinical Studies (14.1)]  and in 1% and 3% of patients receiving SIGNIFOR LAR in the study of patients previously treated  [see Clinical Studies (14.2)]  . In the drug-naive study, two patients receiving SIGNIFOR LAR developed pancreatitis. Pancreatitis is a potential adverse reaction associated with the use of SIGNIFOR LAR due to the association between cholelithiasis and acute pancreatitis.



  Figure 2. Mean Fasting Plasma Glucose (mg/dL) by Visit in the Study of Patients with Acromegaly Naive to Drug Therapy* 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hyperglycemia and Diabetes: Sometimes severe. Monitor glucose levels periodically during therapy. Monitor glucose levels more frequently in the months that follow initiation or discontinuation of SIGNIFOR LAR therapy and following SIGNIFOR LAR dose adjustment. Use anti-diabetic treatment if indicated per standard of care. (  2.5  ,  5.1  ) 
 *   Bradycardia and QT Prolongation: Use with caution in at-risk patients; Evaluate ECG and electrolytes prior to dosing and periodically while on treatment. (  2.5  ,  5.2  ,  7.1  ) 
 *   Liver Test Elevations: Evaluate liver enzyme tests prior to and during treatment. (  2.5  ,  5.3  ) 
 *   Cholelithiasis: Monitor periodically. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Pituitary Hormone Deficiency(ies): Monitor for occurrence periodically and treat if clinically indicated. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Hyperglycemia and Diabetes



  SIGNIFOR LAR can cause increases in blood glucose levels which are sometimes severe. In the study of patients with acromegaly, five patients naive to drug therapy exposed to SIGNIFOR LAR (two of whom were normoglycemic at baseline) were hospitalized for blood glucose in the range of 359-506 mg/dL and none in the active comparator group. Two additional patients who had received active comparator in the main trial were switched to SIGNIFOR LAR in the extension trial were hospitalized for elevated glucose levels while on SIGNIFOR LAR treatment during the extension; one of those patients developed diabetic ketoacidosis. Patients with poor baseline glycemic control are at higher risk of developing severe hyperglycemia [see Dosage and Administration (2.5)]  .



 In the clinical development program, treatment with SIGNIFOR LAR caused an increase in the incidence of diabetes and pre-diabetes. A majority of patients, including those with normal glucose tolerance, pre-diabetes and diabetes, experienced increased glucose levels within the first 2 to 3 months of treatment with SIGNIFOR LAR [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . In the drug-naive patient trial, the prevalence of diabetes increased from 30% at baseline to 60% at month 12. In the trial evaluating patients previously treated with somatostatin analogs, the prevalence of diabetes increased from 71% at baseline to 87% at month 6 in patients treated with SIGNIFOR LAR 40 mg and from 60% to 84% in patients treated with SIGNIFOR LAR 60 mg.



 Fasting plasma glucose and hemoglobin A1c should be assessed prior to starting treatment with SIGNIFOR LAR. In patients with poorly controlled diabetes mellitus, anti-diabetic treatment should be optimized before SIGNIFOR LAR treatment is started. Blood glucose monitoring should be done weekly for the first three months after initiating SIGNIFOR LAR and the first four to six weeks after dose increases. Periodic monitoring should continue thereafter, as clinically appropriate.



 Patients who develop significant hyperglycemia on SIGNIFOR LAR may require initiation of anti-diabetic therapy(ies) or adjustment in the dose or type of anti-diabetic therapy(ies) per standard of care. The optimal treatment for the management of SIGNIFOR LAR-induced hyperglycemia is not known. If hyperglycemia cannot be controlled despite medical management, the dose of SIGNIFOR LAR should be reduced or SIGNIFOR LAR should be discontinued.



 After treatment discontinuation, fasting plasma glucose and hemoglobin A1c should be assessed if indicated. Patients on anti-diabetic therapy discontinuing SIGNIFOR LAR may require more frequent blood glucose monitoring and anti-diabetic drug therapy dose adjustment to mitigate the risk of hypoglycemia.



    5.2     Bradycardia and QT Prolongation



   Bradycardia  



 Bradycardia has been reported with the use of SIGNIFOR LAR [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Patients with cardiac disease and/or risk factors for bradycardia, such as history of clinically significant bradycardia, high-grade heart block, or concomitant use of drugs associated with bradycardia, should be monitored. Adjustments in the dose of drugs known to slow the heart rate (e.g., beta-blockers, calcium channel blockers) and correction of electrolyte disturbances may be necessary when initiating or during the course of SIGNIFOR LAR treatment.



  QT Prolongation  



 In cardiac electrophysiology studies (i.e., thorough QT studies) with Signifor s.c., QT prolongation occurred at therapeutic and supra-therapeutic doses [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  .



 In the phase 3 trials, a corrected QT interval (i.e., QTcF) of greater than 480 ms was reported in four patients and an increase in the QTcF from baseline of greater than 60 ms was reported for 2 patients in the SIGNIFOR LAR arm. No patient on SIGNIFOR LAR had a QTcF value of greater than 500 ms [see Adverse Reactions (6.1) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  .



 SIGNIFOR LAR should be used with caution in patients who are at significant risk of developing prolongation of the QT interval, such as those listed below:



 *  with congenital long QT prolongation. 
 *  with uncontrolled or significant cardiac disease including recent myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, unstable angina or clinically significant bradycardia. 
 *  on anti-arrhythmic therapy or other substances that are known to lead to QT prolongation. 
 *  with hypokalemia and/or hypomagnesemia. 
    A baseline ECG is recommended prior to initiating therapy with SIGNIFOR LAR. Monitoring for an effect on the QT interval at the time of maximum drug concentration (21 days after injection) should be obtained in patients at risk. Hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia must be corrected prior to initiating SIGNIFOR LAR and should be monitored periodically during therapy.
 

    5.3     Liver Test Elevations



  Increases in liver enzymes have been observed with SIGNIFOR LAR. Overall, in both phase 3 studies and across all doses, ALT or AST elevation greater than three times the upper limit of normal (ULN) were observed in 3% of patients and ALT or AST elevation greater than five times the upper limit of normal (ULN) were observed in 1% of patients treated with SIGNIFOR LAR.



 Assessment of liver function is recommended prior to treatment with SIGNIFOR LAR , and after the first 2 to 3 weeks, then monthly for 3 months. Thereafter, liver function should be monitored as clinically indicated. Patients who develop increased transaminase levels should be monitored until values return to pre-treatment levels. Treatment with SIGNIFOR LAR should be discontinued if signs or symptoms suggestive of clinically significant liver impairment develop. Following discontinuation of treatment with SIGNIFOR LAR, patients should be monitored until resolution. Treatment should not be restarted, if the liver function abnormalities are suspected to be related to SIGNIFOR LAR.



    5.4     Cholelithiasis



  Cholelithiasis was reported in 33% of drug-naive and 10% of inadequately controlled (40 mg dose) acromegaly patients treated with SIGNIFOR LAR in clinical trials [see Adverse Reactions (6)]  . Patients should be monitored periodically.



    5.5     Pituitary Hormone Deficiency(ies)



  Suppression of pituitary hormones other than GH/IGF-1, may occur on SIGNIFOR LAR. Monitoring pituitary function (e.g., thyroid, adrenal, gonadal) prior to initiation of therapy with SIGNIFOR LAR, as well as periodically during treatment, as clinically appropriate, is recommended. Patients should be monitored for and instructed on the signs and symptoms of adrenal insufficiency during therapy. If adrenal insufficiency is suspected it should be confirmed and treated per standard of care with exogenous glucocorticoids at replacement doses.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
