<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sildenafil" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse events are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Mortality with pediatric use [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  
 *  Hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Vision loss [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hearing loss [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Priapism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Vaso-occlusive crisis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions greater than or equal to 3% and more frequent than placebo were epistaxis, headache, dyspepsia, flushing, insomnia, erythema, dyspnea, and rhinitis. (  6.1  ,  6.2  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Greenstone LLC Professional Information Services at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Safety data of sildenafil in adults were obtained from the 12-week, placebo-controlled clinical study (Study 1) and an open-label extension study in 277 sildenafil-treated patients with PAH, WHO Group I  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .



 The overall frequency of discontinuation in sildenafil-treated patients on 20 mg three times a day was 3% and was the same for the placebo group.



 In Study 1, the adverse reactions that were reported by at least 3% of sildenafil-treated patients (20 mg three times a day) and were more frequent in sildenafil-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients, are shown in Table 1. Adverse reactions were generally transient and mild to moderate in nature.



 Table 1. Most Common Adverse Reactions in Patients with PAH in Study 1 (More Frequent in Sildenafil-Treated Patients than Placebo-Treated Patients and Incidence &gt;=3% in Sildenafil-Treated Patients) 
                               Placebo, %(n = 70)      Sildenafil 20 mg three times a day, %(n = 69)    Placebo-Subtracted, %     
  
 Epistaxis                              1                          9                          8               
 Headache                              39                         46                          7               
 Dyspepsia                              7                         13                          6               
 Flushing                               4                         10                          6               
 Insomnia                               1                          7                          6               
 Erythema                               1                          6                          5               
 Dyspnea exacerbated                    3                          7                          4               
 Rhinitis                               0                          4                          4               
 Diarrhea                               6                          9                          3               
 Myalgia                                4                          7                          3               
 Pyrexia                                3                          6                          3               
 Gastritis                              0                          3                          3               
 Sinusitis                              0                          3                          3               
 Paresthesia                            0                          3                          3               
          At doses higher than the recommended 20 mg three times a day, there was a greater incidence of some adverse reactions including flushing, diarrhea, myalgia and visual disturbances. Visual disturbances were identified as mild and transient, and were predominately color-tinge to vision, but also increased sensitivity to light or blurred vision.
 

 The incidence of retinal hemorrhage at the recommended sildenafil 20 mg three times a day was 1.4% versus 0% placebo and for all sildenafil doses studied was 1.9% versus 0% placebo. The incidence of eye hemorrhage at both 20 mg three times a day and at all doses studied was 1.4% for sildenafil versus 1.4% for placebo. The patients experiencing these reactions had risk factors for hemorrhage including concurrent anticoagulant therapy.



 In a placebo-controlled fixed dose titration study (Study 2) of sildenafil (starting with recommended dose of 20 mg and increased to 40 mg and then 80 mg all three times a day) as an adjunct to intravenous epoprostenol in patients with PAH, the adverse reactions that were more frequent in the sildenafil + epoprostenol group than in the epoprostenol group (greater than 6% difference) are shown in Table 2  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions (%) in patients with PAH in Study 2 (incidence in Sildenafil + Epoprostenol group at least 6% greater than Epoprostenol group) 
                     Sildenafil + Epoprostenol(n = 134)  Epoprostenol(n = 131)  (Sildenafil + Epoprostenol) minus Epoprostenol%   
  
 Headache                       57                   34                             23                        
 Edema                          25                   13                             14                        
 Dyspepsia                      16                   2                              14                        
 Pain in extremity              17                   6                              11                        
 Diarrhea                       25                   18                             7                         
 Nausea                         25                   18                             7                         
 Nasal congestion               9                    2                              7                         
            6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of sildenafil (marketed for both PAH and erectile dysfunction). Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Cardiovascular Events  



 In postmarketing experience with sildenafil at doses indicated for erectile dysfunction, serious cardiovascular, cerebrovascular, and vascular events, including myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death, ventricular arrhythmia, cerebrovascular hemorrhage, transient ischemic attack, hypertension, pulmonary hemorrhage, and subarachnoid and intracerebral hemorrhages have been reported in temporal association with the use of the drug. Most, but not all, of these patients had preexisting cardiovascular risk factors. Many of these events were reported to occur during or shortly after sexual activity, and a few were reported to occur shortly after the use of sildenafil without sexual activity. Others were reported to have occurred hours to days after use concurrent with sexual activity. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to sildenafil, to sexual activity, to the patient's underlying cardiovascular disease, or to a combination of these or other factors.



     Nervous system  



 Seizure, seizure recurrence.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Increased mortality with increasing doses in pediatric patients. Not recommended for use in pediatric patients. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Vasodilation effects may be more common in patients with hypotension or on antihypertensive therapy. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Use in pulmonary veno-occlusive disease may cause pulmonary edema and is not recommended. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hearing or visual impairment: Seek medical attention if sudden decrease or loss of vision or hearing occurs. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Pulmonary hypertension secondary to sickle cell disease: sildenafil may cause serious vaso-occlusive crises. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Mortality with Pediatric Use



  In a long-term trial in pediatric patients with PAH, an increase in mortality with increasing sildenafil dose was observed. Deaths were first observed after about 1 year and causes of death were typical of patients with PAH. Use of sildenafil, particularly chronic use, is not recommended in children [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].  



    5.2 Hypotension



  Sildenafil has vasodilatory properties, resulting in mild and transient decreases in blood pressure. Before prescribing sildenafil, carefully consider whether patients with certain underlying conditions could be adversely affected by such vasodilatory effects (e.g., patients on antihypertensive therapy or with resting hypotension [BP less than 90/50], fluid depletion, severe left ventricular outflow obstruction, or autonomic dysfunction). Monitor blood pressure when co-administering blood pressure lowering drugs with sildenafil.



    5.3 Worsening Pulmonary Vascular Occlusive Disease



  Pulmonary vasodilators may significantly worsen the cardiovascular status of patients with pulmonary veno-occlusive disease (PVOD). Since there are no clinical data on administration of sildenafil to patients with veno-occlusive disease, administration of sildenafil to such patients is not recommended. Should signs of pulmonary edema occur when sildenafil is administered, consider the possibility of associated PVOD.



    5.4 Epistaxis



  The incidence of epistaxis was 13% in patients taking sildenafil with PAH secondary to CTD. This effect was not seen in idiopathic PAH (sildenafil 3%, placebo 2%) patients. The incidence of epistaxis was also higher in sildenafil-treated patients with a concomitant oral vitamin K antagonist (9% versus 2% in those not treated with concomitant vitamin K antagonist).



 The safety of sildenafil is unknown in patients with bleeding disorders or active peptic ulceration.



    5.5 Visual Loss



   When used to treat erectile dysfunction, non-arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION), a cause of decreased vision including permanent loss of vision, has been reported postmarketing in temporal association with the use of phosphodiesterase type 5 (PDE-5) inhibitors, including sildenafil. Most, but not all, of these patients had underlying anatomic or vascular risk factors for developing NAION, including but not necessarily limited to: low cup to disc ratio ("crowded disc"), age over 50, diabetes, hypertension, coronary artery disease, hyperlipidemia and smoking. Based on published literature, the annual incidence of NAION is 2.5-11.8 cases per 100,000 males aged &gt;= 50 per year in the general population. An observational study evaluated whether recent, episodic use of PDE5 inhibitors (as a class), typical of erectile dysfunction treatment, was associated with acute onset of NAION. The results suggest an approximately 2-fold increase in the risk of NAION within 5 half-lives of PDE5 inhibitor use. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of PDE-5 inhibitors, to the patient's underlying vascular risk factors or anatomical defects, to a combination of these factors, or to other factors. Advise patients to seek immediate medical attention in the event of a sudden loss of vision in one or both eyes while taking PDE-5 inhibitors, including sildenafil. Physicians should also discuss the increased risk of NAION with patients who have already experienced NAION in one eye, including whether such individuals could be adversely affected by use of vasodilators, such as PDE-5 inhibitors.  



 There are no controlled clinical data on the safety or efficacy of sildenafil in patients with retinitis pigmentosa, a minority whom have genetic disorders of retinal phosphodiesterases. Prescribe sildenafil with caution in these patients.



    5.6 Hearing Loss



  Cases of sudden decrease or loss of hearing, which may be accompanied by tinnitus and dizziness, have been reported in temporal association with the use of PDE-5 inhibitors, including sildenafil. In some of the cases, medical conditions and other factors were reported that may have played a role. In many cases, medical follow-up information was limited. It is not possible to determine whether these reported events are related directly to the use of sildenafil, to the patient's underlying risk factors for hearing loss, a combination of these factors, or to other factors.



 Advise patients to seek prompt medical attention in the event of sudden decrease or loss of hearing while taking PDE-5 inhibitors, including sildenafil.



    5.7 Combination with other PDE-5 inhibitors



  Sildenafil is also marketed as VIAGRA  (r)  . The safety and efficacy of combinations of sildenafil with VIAGRA or other PDE-5 inhibitors have not been studied. Inform patients taking sildenafil not to take VIAGRA or other PDE-5 inhibitors.



    5.8 Priapism



  Use sildenafil with caution in patients with anatomical deformation of the penis (e.g., angulation, cavernosal fibrosis, or Peyronie's disease) or in patients who have conditions, which may predispose them to priapism (e.g., sickle cell anemia, multiple myeloma, or leukemia). In the event of an erection that persists longer than 4 hours, the patient should seek immediate medical assistance. If priapism (painful erection greater than 6 hours in duration) is not treated immediately, penile tissue damage and permanent loss of potency could result.



    5.9 Vaso-occlusive Crisis in Patients with Pulmonary Hypertension Secondary to Sickle Cell Anemia



  In a small, prematurely terminated study of patients with pulmonary hypertension (PH) secondary to sickle cell disease, vaso-occlusive crises requiring hospitalization were more commonly reported by patients who received sildenafil than by those randomized to placebo. The effectiveness and safety of sildenafil in the treatment of PAH secondary to sickle cell anemia has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
