<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="simbrinza" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS SECTION

    EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions occurring in approximately 3 to 5% of patients included blurred vision, eye irritation, dysgeusia (bad taste), dry mouth, eye allergy.   (6.1)    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Alcon Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-757-9195 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to the rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.  SIMBRINZA  In two clinical trials of 3 months duration 435 patients were treated with SIMBRINZA, and 915 were treated with the two individual components. The most frequently reported adverse reactions in patients treated with SIMBRINZA occurring in approximately 3 to 5% of patients in descending order of incidence were blurred vision, eye irritation, dysgeusia (bad taste), dry mouth, and eye allergy. Rates of adverse reactions reported with the individual components were comparable. Treatment discontinuation, mainly due to adverse reactions, was reported in 11% of SIMBRINZA patients.Other adverse reactions that have been reported with the individual components during clinical trials are listed below.       Brinzolamide 1%  In clinical studies of brinzolamide ophthalmic suspension 1%, the most frequently reported adverse reactions reported in 5 to 10% of patients were blurred vision and bitter, sour or unusual taste. Adverse reactions occurring in 1 to 5% of patients were blepharitis, dermatitis, dry eye, foreign body sensation, headache, hyperemia, ocular discharge, ocular discomfort, ocular keratitis, ocular pain, ocular pruritus and rhinitis.The following adverse reactions were reported at an incidence below 1%: allergic reactions, alopecia, chest pain, conjunctivitis, diarrhea, diplopia, dizziness, dry mouth, dyspnea, dyspepsia, eye fatigue, hypertonia, keratoconjunctivitis, keratopathy, kidney pain, lid margin crusting or sticky sensation, nausea, pharyngitis, tearing and urticaria.  Brimonidine Tartrate 0.2%  In clinical studies of brimonidine tartrate 0.2%, adverse reactions occurring in approximately 10 to 30% of the subjects, in descending order of incidence, included oral dryness, ocular hyperemia, burning and stinging, headache, blurring, foreign body sensation, fatigue/drowsiness, conjunctival follicles, ocular allergic reactions, and ocular pruritus. Reactions occurring in approximately 3 to 9% of the subjects, in descending order included corneal staining/erosion, photophobia, eyelid erythema, ocular ache/pain, ocular dryness, tearing, upper respiratory symptoms, eyelid edema, conjunctival edema, dizziness, blepharitis, ocular irritation, gastrointestinal symptoms, asthenia, conjunctival blanching, abnormal vision and muscular pain. The following adverse reactions were reported in less than 3% of the patients: lid crusting, conjunctival hemorrhage, abnormal taste, insomnia, conjunctival discharge, depression, hypertension, anxiety, palpitations/arrhythmias, nasal dryness and syncope.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of brimonidine tartrate ophthalmic solutions in clinical practice. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. The reactions, which have been chosen for inclusion due to either their seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to brimonidine tartrate ophthalmic solutions, or a combination of these factors, include: bradycardia, hypersensitivity, iritis, keratoconjunctivitis sicca, miosis, nausea, skin reactions (including erythema, eyelid pruritus, rash, and vasodilation), and tachycardia.  Apnea, bradycardia, coma, hypotension, hypothermia, hypotonia, lethargy, pallor, respiratory depression, and somnolence have been reported in infants receiving brimonidine tartrate ophthalmic solutions  [see  Contraindications (4.2)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS SECTION



     EXCERPT:    *  Potential for sulfonamide hypersensitivity reactions because of the brinzolamide tartrate component    (5.1)   
 *  Potential for corneal endothelium cell loss  (5.2)   
 *  Severe renal impairment may limit the metabolism of the brinzolamide tartrate component  (5.3)   
    
 

   5.1 Sulfonamide Hypersensitivity Reactions



  SIMBRINZA contains brinzolamide, a sulfonamide and although administered topically is absorbed systemically. Therefore, the same types of adverse reactions that are attributable to sulfonamides may occur with topical administration of SIMBRINZA. Fatalities have occurred due to severe reactions to sulfonamides including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, fulminant hepatic necrosis, agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia, and other blood dyscrasias. Sensitization may recur when a sulfonamide is re-administered irrespective of the route of administration. If signs of serious reactions or hypersensitivity occur, discontinue the use of this preparation. [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .



    5.2 Corneal Endothelium



  Carbonic anhydrase activity has been observed in both the cytoplasm and around the plasma membranes of the corneal endothelium. There is an increased potential for developing corneal edema in patients with low endothelial cell counts. Caution should be used when prescribing SIMBRINZA to this group of patients.



    5.3 Severe Renal Impairment



  SIMBRINZA has not been specifically studied in patients with severe renal impairment (CrCl &lt; 30 mL/min).  Since brinzolamide and its metabolite are excreted predominantly by the kidney, SIMBRINZA is not recommended in such patients.



    5.4 Acute Angle-Closure Glaucoma



  The management of patients with acute angle-closure glaucoma requires therapeutic interventions in addition to ocular hypotensive agents. SIMBRINZA has not been studied in patients with acute angle-closure glaucoma.



    5.5 Contact Lens Wear



  The preservative in SIMBRINZA, benzalkonium chloride, may be absorbed by soft contact lenses. Contact lenses should be removed during instillation of SIMBRINZA but may be reinserted 15 minutes after instillation [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .



    5.6 Severe Cardiovascular Disease



  Brimonidine tartrate, a component of SIMBRINZA, has a less than 5% mean decrease in blood pressure 2 hours after dosing in clinical studies; caution should be exercised in treating patients with severe cardiovascular disease.



    5.7 Severe Hepatic Impairment



  Because brimonidine tartrate, a component of SIMBRINZA, has not been studied in patients with hepatic impairment, caution should be exercised in such patients.



    5.8 Potentiation of Vascular Insufficiency



  Brimonidine tartrate, a component of SIMBRINZA, may potentiate syndromes associated with vascular insufficiency. SIMBRINZA should be used with caution in patients with depression, cerebral or coronary insufficiency, Raynaud's phenomenon, orthostatic hypotension, or thromboangitis obliterans.



    5.9 Contamination of Topical Ophthalmic Products After Use



  There have been reports of bacterial keratitis associated with the use of multiple-dose containers of topical ophthalmic products. These containers have been inadvertently contaminated by patients who, in most cases, had a concurrent corneal disease or a disruption of the ocular epithelial surface [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.4)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
