<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sinemet0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions reported with SINEMET have included dyskinesias, such as choreiform, dystonic, and other involuntary movements, and nausea.



 The following other adverse reactions have been reported with SINEMET:



   Body as a Whole  



 Chest pain, asthenia.



   Cardiovascular  



 Cardiac irregularities, hypotension, orthostatic effects including orthostatic hypotension, hypertension, syncope, phlebitis, palpitation.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Dark saliva, gastrointestinal bleeding, development of duodenal ulcer, anorexia, vomiting, diarrhea, constipation, dyspepsia, dry mouth, taste alterations.



   Hematologic  



 Agranulocytosis, hemolytic and non-hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia.



   Hypersensitivity  



 Angioedema, urticaria, pruritus, Henoch-Schonlein purpura, bullous lesions (including pemphigus-like reactions).



   Musculoskeletal  



 Back pain, shoulder pain, muscle cramps.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric  



 Psychotic episodes including delusions, hallucinations, and paranoid ideation, bradykinetic episodes ("on-off" phenomenon), confusion, agitation, dizziness, somnolence, dream abnormalities including nightmares, insomnia, paresthesia, headache, depression with or without development of suicidal tendencies, dementia, pathological gambling, increased libido including hypersexuality, impulse control symptoms. Convulsions also have occurred; however, a causal relationship with SINEMET has not been established.



   Respiratory  



 Dyspnea, upper respiratory infection.



   Skin  



 Rash, increased sweating, alopecia, dark sweat.



   Urogenital  



 Urinary tract infection, urinary frequency, dark urine.



   Laboratory Tests  



 Decreased hemoglobin and hematocrit; abnormalities in alkaline phosphatase, SGOT (AST), SGPT (ALT), LDH, bilirubin, BUN, Coombs test; elevated serum glucose; white blood cells, bacteria, and blood in the urine.



 Other adverse reactions that have been reported with levodopa alone and with various carbidopa levodopa formulations, and may occur with SINEMET are:



   Body as a Whole  



 Abdominal pain and distress, fatigue.



   Cardiovascular  



 Myocardial infarction.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Gastrointestinal pain, dysphagia, sialorrhea, flatulence, bruxism, burning sensation of the tongue, heartburn, hiccups.



   Metabolic  



 Edema, weight gain, weight loss.



   Musculoskeletal  



 Leg pain.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric  



 Ataxia, extrapyramidal disorder, falling, anxiety, gait abnormalities, nervousness, decreased mental acuity, memory impairment, disorientation, euphoria, blepharospasm (which may be taken as an early sign of excess dosage; consideration of dosage reduction may be made at this time), trismus, increased tremor, numbness, muscle twitching, activation of latent Horner's syndrome, peripheral neuropathy.



   Respiratory  



 Pharyngeal pain, cough.



   Skin  



 Malignant melanoma (see also  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ), flushing.



   Special Senses  



 Oculogyric crises, diplopia, blurred vision, dilated pupils.



   Urogenital  



 Urinary retention, urinary incontinence, priapism.



   Miscellaneous  



 Bizarre breathing patterns, faintness, hoarseness, malaise, hot flashes, sense of stimulation.



   Laboratory Tests  



 Decreased white blood cell count and serum potassium; increased serum creatinine and uric acid; protein and glucose in urine.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
